<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/podcast/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-06-14T21:07:12+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/podcast/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Pubcast on the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Pubcast on the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2019-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy">&lt;p&gt;The second of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Mr Achyut Chandra, an MSME businessman engaged in the field of manufacturing printing and packaging solutions. Mr Chandra is the Chairman of the New Market Development Committee of the Federation of Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of India, an umbrella organisation of box manufacturing organisations in India. He’s also the current Vice-President of the Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of Eastern India and is an active member of the Bharat Chambers of Commerce. The pubcast with Mr Chandra is in two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part I&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;) - an on-ground overview of what is going wrong with the Indian economy, i.e. the current slowdown, and a brief overview of the state of the MSME sector, in particular&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part II&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2246)&quot;&gt;37:26&lt;/a&gt;) - a vision for India’s economy, including a broad roadmap for future prosperity and for unleashing the potential of India’s small businesses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-2&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast2-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-2&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="podcast" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The second of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Mr Achyut Chandra, an MSME businessman engaged in the field of manufacturing printing and packaging solutions. Mr Chandra is the Chairman of the New Market Development Committee of the Federation of Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of India, an umbrella organisation of box manufacturing organisations in India. He’s also the current Vice-President of the Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of Eastern India and is an active member of the Bharat Chambers of Commerce. The pubcast with Mr Chandra is in two parts: Part I (00:00) - an on-ground overview of what is going wrong with the Indian economy, i.e. the current slowdown, and a brief overview of the state of the MSME sector, in particular Part II (37:26) - a vision for India’s economy, including a broad roadmap for future prosperity and for unleashing the potential of India’s small businesses Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age</title>
      <link href="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age" />
      <published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age">&lt;p&gt;The first of The Pangean’s &lt;em&gt;pubcasts&lt;/em&gt; is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirandamowbray/&quot;&gt;Dr Miranda Mowbray&lt;/a&gt;, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/harsh.tiwari/&quot;&gt;Harsh Tiwari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/reuben.pritchard/&quot;&gt;Reuben Pritchard&lt;/a&gt; sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology as a replacement for human interaction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(60)&quot;&gt;01:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology in business and politics&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(1203)&quot;&gt;20:03&lt;/a&gt;), or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The accessibility of technology&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2142)&quot;&gt;35:42&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast1-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-1&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>harsh.tiwari reuben.pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="podcast" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The first of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Dr Miranda Mowbray, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data. In this podcast, Harsh Tiwari and Reuben Pritchard sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest: Introduction (00:00), Technology as a replacement for human interaction (01:00), Technology in business and politics (20:03), or The accessibility of technology (35:42). Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
