<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/rishi.kant/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-14T20:09:55+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/rishi.kant/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Caustic Crass of Casteism</title>
      <link href="/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Caustic Crass of Casteism" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism">&lt;p&gt;Facebook in India is incessantly flooded with memes — pictures or videos of casteist slurs against the marginalised communities, as those who belong to ‘upper caste’ per se, lament against caste-based reservations in public institutes and government jobs. Their rationale, more prominently since the implementation of the Mandal Commission in 1990, has been that it ‘kills’ the merit factor, i.e. meritorious students who belong to the namesake ‘General’ category are deprived of opportunities that marginalised communities get due to reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the mind of every student in this country is filled with this narrative even before they burn the midnight oil to crack the draconian entrance exams. Such a hate-spewing narrative naturally brings a certain anathema towards the ‘reserved’ categories of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hatred is evident from the repetitive use of &lt;em&gt;cham**r&lt;/em&gt;, a word used as a casteist expletive which generalises all the marginalised communities under a derogative umbrella term, by many students studying in various educational institutions, sub-consciously fuming their exasperation against reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of this article, who has been through the rat-race of preparing for the draconian engineering entrance exams, also blindly believed in this narrative. In hindsight, he now sees how it actually culminated with him profiling classmates and batchmates in the coaching classes, based on whether they could reap the benefits of reservation or not. His time also coincided with the ascendancy of Hindu-supremacist BJP at the centre, which also made him look slyly at Dr Ambedkar and the entire anti-caste movement. Of course, he found little sense in those rallying against casteism — for he only saw from a prism which showed them ‘entitled’ to higher-education in prestigious institutes without ‘merit’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This anecdote supports the aforementioned argument of how upper-caste propaganda embarks students on a path of discrimination and hatred — the wrongdoings of which are extremely difficult, if not impossible, to undo. What is even more concerning is that this propaganda under the garb of ‘merit’ and ‘equality’ brings a certain wind of legitimacy, the whiff of which is often hard to resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, ‘merit’ is the key working word in this debate. However, it has been painstakingly dissected and presented in “Does ‘Merit’ have a Caste?” on &lt;em&gt;The Wire&lt;/em&gt; and it would be a great disservice to the author if it is reiterated only for the sake of argumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duopoly of casteism and classism are the biggest yet the most obscure threat to India’s Xanadu, the liveable manifestation of the promulgations of the Indian Constitution. Caste and class inequalities, on the contrary, are being pushed further into obscurity by a rising intolerance towards monotheistic religions, Islam in particular. Hindu vigilantes are often in what could be a self-perceived duel against their Muslim counterparts and vice versa. The macabre riots in Delhi are a testament to this intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any conflict between religious communities obviously takes precedence over atrocities committed in the name of caste. In fact, the growing divide between monotheistic Islam and polytheistic Hinduism has given the latter a very powerful rationale for a ‘war cry’ of sorts, exhorting Hindus to ‘unite’ to ‘protect’ their sacrosanct religion. In reality, such exhortations culminate only with upper-caste Hindus to make a more impregnable clout and thereby, pushing the marginalised communities further away into oblivion. The upper echelons of public life in India are still largely dominated by upper-caste Hindus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, the author also believes that caste-based politicking is another reason for this growing divide. Whilst the government has brought upon the reformist measures to alleviate centuries of oppression, it still isn’t a step towards abolishing caste altogether. Many upper-caste Hindus often accuse political parties of caste-based political skullduggery for the marginalised communities have always been of a ‘vote-bank’, a sizeable population whose vote is crucial to win elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the author himself was led to strongly believe in the upper-caste narrative which denounces the existence of caste-based oppression altogether and accuses the marginalised communities to raise the caste question only to ‘cling’ onto the reservations that they are entitled to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an opinion of caste comes from a selective reading of society. In order to subscribe to this narrative, one must have class privilege, where the society is so-called ‘westernised’ enough to not bother knowing one’s caste as long as everyone belongs to the same economic class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it would be unfair to assume that being on top of the class pyramid saves one from the caste question, such selective perception of caste also comes from denial and ignorance; to put it crudely, one cannot deny the existence of casteism if one has never been subjected to caste-based discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caste dynamics in India are so precariously balanced that leaders such as Mahatma Gandhi are also accused of ensuring that the caste hierarchy remains. Man Booker-prize winning author Arundhati Roy in her essay ‘The Doctor and the Saint’ has opined that Gandhi supported the caste hierarchy only to appease the high-caste Marwari businessmen who, financially or otherwise, supported his &lt;em&gt;satyagraha&lt;/em&gt; (policy of nonviolent resistance) movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If probably the greatest statesman of this country paid his obeisance to casteism, it would be foolish to assume that a Hindu-supremacist government like the BJP would uproot this anachronistic practice. On the contrary, many Dalit activists are wary of the party’s intentions, and accuse it of ethnic profiling and cleansing with their divisive Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA) and the draconian National Register of Citizens (NRC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legacy of Dr B R Ambedkar, who perhaps was the most profound Dalit thinker, is also thrown in the cesspool of profanities and slurs, hurled by the upper-caste, the propaganda of hate deeply entrenched in their minds. The Indian education system, among its many inherent flaws, also fails to elucidate students about Dr Ambedkar as much as it embellishes Gandhi, which again reeks of the politics behind how impressionable minds are moulded to perceive the history and ethos of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Xanadu which was envisaged by those who broke the shackles of an oppressive colonial rule is questioned and dissected now. Despite Dr Ambedkar’s tribulations for a more egalitarian and just society, the existence of marginalised communities is reduced to a transactional relationship where ‘reservation’ is given in exchange for their suffrage. Whether the doors of an independent India were open for Dalits and tribals is a question that remains unanswered even after 73 years.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Facebook in India is incessantly flooded with memes — pictures or videos of casteist slurs against the marginalised communities, as those who belong to ‘upper caste’ per se, lament against caste-based reservations in public institutes and government jobs. Their rationale, more prominently since the implementation of the Mandal Commission in 1990, has been that it ‘kills’ the merit factor, i.e. meritorious students who belong to the namesake ‘General’ category are deprived of opportunities that marginalised communities get due to reservation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Israel-UAE Deal: History Created?</title>
      <link href="/Israel-UAE-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Israel-UAE Deal: History Created?" />
      <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Israel-UAE-Deal</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Israel-UAE-Deal">&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump exemplified his love affair with Twitter as he took to the microblogging platform to break the news of a historic truce between Israel and the United Arab Emirates (UAE). This makes Abu Dhabi the third nation in the Arab world and the first among the Gulf nations to recognise Israel as a nation. The move is touted by many as a game-changer in the geopolitics of the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gulf countries have not, for over a century, officially recognised Israel as a nation because of the ongoing Israel-Palestinian crisis. Trump also brokered an agreement where Israel would suspend its plans to annex the Western Bank — a region of conflict between the Jewish Israelis and the Palestinian Muslims, where the latter has also been subjucted to various atrocities violating human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle East is a precarious region, and its geopolitics is largely influenced by a Cold War-like proxy war between two of its behemoths – Saudi Arabia and Iran. The roots of this complex crosshairs can be traced back to the First World War, which culminated with the fall of the Ottoman Empire. The local Al Saud tribe in the Arabian peninsula fought off everyone who staked a claim in the region, and modern-day Saudi Arabia was officially recognised in 1932. Until 1979, Saudi Arabia was regarded as an undisputed bastion of Muslims across the world, for the progeny of the dynasty were also the custodians of the holy mosques in Mecca and Medina — the two holiest shrines in Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Iranian Revolution in 1979 saw the rise of a theocratic rule stemming from the Shia sect of Islam under Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini. Not only did he envisage Iran as a regional power, but he also challenged a Sunni-dominated Saudi Arabia’s claim to lead the Muslim world. This came as a shock to many for Khomeini’s ascent was first welcomed by then-Saudi ruler King Salman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran, rich in oil reserves, changed its foreign policy to undermine America’s influence in the region. This further fanned its animosity with Saudi, which had been a pro-America state. However, unlike Saudi, Iran wasn’t able to pull in money for its oil reserves and was crippled with the sanctions imposed on it by the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has largely supported rebel groups, some of them are extremists and are categorised as ‘terrorist groups’ in the unrest that has prevailed in the region. Before the US invasion in Iraq, the country served as somewhat of a buffer zone between the two nations. Many diplomatic circles jokingly say that America invaded Iraq only to gift it to Iran, and it is for a good reason that the ISIS occupation in Iraq had been largely supported by the Iraqi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khomeini’s new government also turned hostile towards Israel, it withdrew its decision to recognise Israel as a state and severed all ties with it. Iraq’s policy of supporting rebel groups in conflict-laden areas also meant that it supported opposing extremist groups against Israel — Hezbollah in Lebanon, and Hamas and Palestinian Islamic Jihad in Israel, for it considers the state a Zionist regime. (Zionism was the movement which led to the foundation of Israel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE’s peace agreement (albeit the government in Abu Dhabi calls it a roadmap to a peaceful relationship) has offended the Palestinians, who saw an ally in them. They were also taken by surprise by this announcement since they were not informed about any of this. &lt;em&gt;“May you never be sold out by your ‘friends’”&lt;/em&gt;, Hanan Ashrawi, a senior official, angrily tweeted at the Emirati crown prince.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian Authority has been championing for a separate state, and its President Mahmoud Abbas is disillusioned with the Trump administration for its pro-Israel stance. &lt;em&gt;“The Palestinian leadership rejects and denounces the UAE, Israeli and US trilateral, surprising, announcement”&lt;/em&gt;, said a senior adviser to Abbas and called it a &lt;em&gt;“betrayal of Jerusalem, Al-Aqsa, and the Palestinian cause”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to look at this agreement is a reaffirmation of the fact that UAE doesn’t detest Israel as much as its Arab counterparts do. This is diametrically opposed to the Arab and Muslim viewpoint of the official recognition of Israel in 1948 as a ‘pro-Western’ move, analogous to the erstwhile European colonialism that once existed. Many diplomatic commentators see this as the UAE’s plan for a more liberal and open foreign policy which is evident from the immigrants that throng to the country for work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian cause is, irrefutably, hurt by this agreement. Although the UAE made it clear that the “suspension of plans to annex the Western Bank” was their priority, Palestinians would see it as tokenism if the UAE doesn’t raise the question of Palestinian statehood. There is an opinion that the Emiratis are disenchanted with the Palestinian separatist movement, possibly because they don’t want to see its citizens or its government to be supportive of a separatist movement, especially when dissent is hardly tolerated in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both for US President Donald Trump and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, it is an attempt to save some of the public approval that elected them. The two leaders are receiving flak and opprobrium for their management of the coronavirus pandemic. While Trump is also criticised for his failed diplomatic projects and a US economy that has been bludgeoned by the pandemic, Netanyahu faces a trial of corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the decision in Washington is bipartisan — the Democratic Presidential candidate Joe Biden and presumptive Vice-Presidential candidate Kamala Harris have also welcomed this decision. This also indicates that the government in Abu Dhabi is preparing itself for the fact that Trump might not win a second term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Trump is pinning his hopes on other Arab states to follow suit. However, this agreement also undermines any hopes of a permanent settlement between the Israelis and Palestinians. The further implications of this deal are yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">President Donald Trump exemplified his love affair with Twitter as he took to the microblogging platform to break the news of a historic truce between Israel and the United Arab Emirates (UAE). This makes Abu Dhabi the third nation in the Arab world and the first among the Gulf nations to recognise Israel as a nation. The move is touted by many as a game-changer in the geopolitics of the region.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Accountability: An Illusion in Reality</title>
      <link href="/An-Illusion-in-Reality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accountability: An Illusion in Reality" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Illusion-in-Reality</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Illusion-in-Reality">&lt;p&gt;India is grappling with a spike in COVID-19 cases—even by the current earliest estimates, the peak is anywhere but close. Amidst the escalating tensions with neighbours Nepal and China, it has set the ball rolling for what is the most difficult test of governance for the incumbent Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what still remains obscure amidst this pandemonium is India’s interminable tryst with sustainable development—maintaining an equipoise of biodiversity and urbanisation. As the country went through phases of lockdowns, the Indian Environment Ministry, led by Prakash Javedkar, uploaded the reformed version of the EIA, which was last amended in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new legislation has led to a huge outcry among environmentalists, for it dilutes the ‘green law’­­—which compelled infrastructure projects to clear the scrutiny of its impact on the environment, and also involved the public. This update was approved by Javedkar and his predecessor, Dr Harsh Vardhan, after being drafted and updated within two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister, who spoke parables and platitudes pertaining to self-reliance, exhorted people to support indigenous brands and products. The growing Sinophobia has culminated with multinational brands such as Apple announcing shift of its manufacturing facilities to India, much to the delight of the average Indian, thumping to celebrate it as an embellishment to the nationalistic pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, what most Indians fail to notice, or passively take cognizance of, is the toll such ambitious manufacturing would take on the environment. This sets a dangerous premise, especially when India’s track record in sustainable development has been mediocre, to be modest, it dates back to the Nehru days. Jawaharlal Nehru famously said to the villagers displaced by the Hirakud Dam in 1948, &lt;em&gt;“If you must suffer, you should suffer in the interest of the country”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s obsession with building dams, despite most studies highlighting their futility, continues to haunt the tribal people living in the hinterlands. The Sardar Sarovar Dam is the country’s prime example of the environmental racism that continues to elude the front pages of the newspapers. Harrowing tales narrated by Man Booker Prize-winning author Arundhati Roy exposes the deepest trenches of social and economic oppression that the tribal landowners are subjected to after being deprived of the very land that is paramount to their survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unaware of how money works in urban dwellings, the displaced people are often stuffed into slum-like residences, sardonically quoted as urban ghettos. Not only are the displaced people forced to work as labourers, the conditions in which they live, far away from their homeland, raise concerns, especially with the country neck-deep in the contagion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To salvage themselves from the perils of a recession looming large at the economy, the government also decided to auction off 41 of its coal mines, many of which are located in the Hasdeo Arand region of Chhattisgarh—which is home to many tribal communities, for it is one of the largest contiguous dense forest areas in India. Privatisation would definitely place them under the threat of being displaced as well as the perils of pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arunachal Pradesh, which is one of the most diverse regions in the country with 26 tribal groups and 100 sub-tribal groups, is home to a 3,097-megawatt Etalin Dam. It is expected to submerge over 300,000 trees and affect Idu Mishmi, an indigenous tribe with a population of over 13,000. Additionally, the 2,880-megawatt Dibang Multipurpose Project, one of the largest planned projects in India, is set to displace nearly 2,000 Mishmi people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the dilution of the EIA, new biodiversity hotspots like Arunachal Pradesh would be set up, especially after the aforementioned projects having been approved without a dialogue with the major stakeholders - the displaced tribal groups. With only 3 Members of Parliament from Arunachal Pradesh, this minuscule representation has also been attributed to environmental racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EIA is essential for India, especially when the country has projects operational without proper environmental clearance. It was found out that the LG Polymer Plant in Vishakapatnam, from which styrene gas was leaked on May 7, was functional for over 20 years without any clearance. A similar incident was reported in Assam where the natural gas of Oil India Limited in the Tinsukia district was incinerated, causing severe damage to local biodiversity. The local environmental authority later released a statement accusing that the plant was running without their approval for the past 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conflagrating a movement for the environment with a law meant for seditious and extremism activities is alarming. A shallow EIA favouring builders with easy environmental clearances can increase incidents in Assam and Andhra Pradesh. It would further push a hitherto obscure yet an important section of the population residing for generations into oblivion. Meanwhile, an EIA report has recently stated that an estimated 33,000 trees would be cut to make way for the proposed Peripheral Ring Road in Bengaluru, from the proposed 200 trees in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unchecked environmental legislation could not only be the final blow to an already bludgeoning biodiversity but can also fan the flames of a humanitarian crisis, for fulfilling the fetishes of the rich.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India is grappling with a spike in COVID-19 cases—even by the current earliest estimates, the peak is anywhere but close. Amidst the escalating tensions with neighbours Nepal and China, it has set the ball rolling for what is the most difficult test of governance for the incumbent Prime Minister.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
