<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/james.eakin/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-18T20:52:05+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/james.eakin/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Examining The Motivations of The Premier Mixed Martial Arts Organisation and Its Charismatic Leader - The UFC and Dana White</title>
      <link href="/UFC-Dana-White" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Examining The Motivations of The Premier Mixed Martial Arts Organisation and Its Charismatic Leader - The UFC and Dana White" />
      <published>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UFC-Dana-White</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-Dana-White">&lt;p&gt;From its realisation in 1993 to where we are now in 2019, the Ultimate Fighting Championship has been a pioneer and market leader in Mixed Martial Arts promotion. Founded by David Isaacs alongside owner Bob Meyrowitz, the UFC was created on the ideals of joining together the top martial artists in a no holds barred tournament to determine which of them possessed the more superior skills in combat. The immediate attraction of the UFC was evident. Marketed as a ‘No Rules’ event, it gave casual combat sports fans a chance to experience a more brutal and raw form of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the apparent barbarism of the sport caused major issues with the governing bodies across America, who threatened to cancel cable coverage of the UFC. It became quickly apparent to Meyrowitz that the company was not sustainable and that drastic action was required in order to save it from going under. This led to Dana White, along with Frank and Lorenzo Fertitta, purchasing the UFC for $2 million in 2001, in a deal that was done more out of passion than logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under their guidance, the UFC has grown into what we know it as now; a multi-billion dollar fight promotion that contains some of the highest level fighters on show in MMA. Thanks to the work of Dana White and the Fertittas, we have witnessed the development of names such as Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Anderson Silva to name but a few. Whilst these names have shaped the modern landscape of mixed martial arts, the line between what is beneficial to the fighters in terms of business and what is good for the promotion has become blurred. Obscurity within the sport has grown increasingly since its conception but recent incidents such as the cutting of top ranked female fighter Cris Cyborg from the organisation have left us to question exactly what image Dana White is attempting to portray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyborg has always been regarded as a pioneer of women’s MMA and, despite her recent brutal loss to Amanda Nunes, she had rejoined championship conversation after her latest victory over Felicia Spencer at UFC 240. What made her exit from the UFC even more confusing was her vocalised desire to have a rematch with Nunes after she was previously criticised by Dana White for being afraid of ‘The Lioness’. While the feud between Cyborg and White has certainly been far from a private matter for some time now, it still seems a strange business move from the President of the company, as a rematch with Nunes would no doubt be a pay-per-view success if their last bout is anything to go by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an interview on his Tuesday Night Contender series, Dana White responded to questions about Cyborg by stating “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mmafighting.com/2019/8/7/20757450/morning-report-dana-white-goes-after-cris-cyborg-dealing-with-her-has-been-a-nightmare&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dealing with her has been a nightmare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” (in regard to her past use of steroids and apparent avoidance of fights). Furthermore, the controversy surrounding Cyborg and White’s relationship was brought to a climax when an edited video released by Cyborg’s team after UFC 240 showed White apparently confessing to Cyborg about lying to the media in relation to her desire to rematch Amanda Nunes. Cyborg has since apologised on behalf of her team. It is clear that the divide between what the fighters deem as good business for them and what the promotion sees as good business has widened exponentially, with more and more fighters it seems disagreeing with their treatment within the company. Notable examples in the past include disagreements between White and Al Iaquinta over the allocation of fighter bonuses. Speaking to Ariel Helwani, Iaquinta criticised White’s comments about the fight card after he claimed that the highlight of his night was his plane ride home. Iaquinta went on a verbal rant stating that White has no idea of the fighter’s struggle when they step into the cage, mentioning injuries and the obvious risk each fighter takes when he or she enters the octagon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has never shied from voicing his opinions, arguing that “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KLNlIWupLlc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;the guys who are complaining about this stuff are the guys that don’t matter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;”. Here we can see an outlying trait of the UFC as a promotion; it’s focus is primarily on the big names, which opens up the argument of fighters being neglected the further down the roster they are placed. If we take a look at the average money made by UFC fighters last year, the median figure excluding bonuses and sponsorships came to $68,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when we consider that these fighters risk their wellbeing every time they step into the cage to fight, it seems surprising that this figure is not higher. It is also vital to consider the recovery time for a fighter after an event as sponsorships can only support so much of a fighters income. For instance, after his all out war with Robbie Lawler at UFC 189, Rory Macdonald was out of competition for almost a year due to injury, and received a payout of $139,000 ($59,000 to show, $50,000 performance of the night bonus and $30,000 Reebok sponsorship). For a sport that can bring about life changing injuries for fighters, it has to be questioned why pay for the majority is so low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particularly shocking incident of pay disparity occured at UFC 157. The main card featured a bantamweight match-up between Urijah Faber and Ivan Menjivar, in which Faber won the bout via submission in the first round. Faber walked out of the Honda Center that night having pocketed a comfortable $100,000 including a $50,000 submission of the night bonus. His opponent on the other hand earned a meager $17,000 for his time. Such a gap in pay is astonishing considering both fighters put themselves at equal risk every time they fight. Other fighters on the undercard that night earned as little as $8,000, truly highlighting the shocking divide between those at the top of the sport and the lesser known fighters who risk just as much as those making the big bucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cause of controversy in White’s organisation was the sponsorship deal made with Reebok in 2015 in an effort to “structure athletes’” income outside of fights’. The deal meant that fighters who had previously been sponsored by a variety of companies would no longer be able to receive sponsorship income outside of Reebok. The promise of increased income fell short and Vitor Belfort even compared the deal to “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/andrewbrennan/2016/05/16/is-it-the-ufc-or-is-it-reebok-that-is-exploiting-ufc-fighters-and-condoning-pay-gaps/#705809f24a93&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;living in slavery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” in his post-fight interview at UFC 198. During an interview on The Cruz Show, when questioned about the fighters’ discrepancies with the Reebok deal, White accused fighters of being “short-sighted”, arguing there had previously been a lack of professionalism from fighters who frequently appeared at weigh-ins with unsponsored underwear. Considering the vast sums of money fighters have lost as a result of the deal, it is evident that that the promotion’s care does not lie with the livelihoods of its fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that White has an inability to provide a cohesive response for his fighters’ doubts, often falling back on simply criticising the fighters as people, as shown in the aforementioned interview. White blasted ex-fighter Brendan Schaub after he criticised his business management tactics, saying “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportsjoe.ie/mma/dana-white-brendan-schaub-168046?utm_content=bufferb81e1&amp;amp;utm_medium=Social+organic&amp;amp;utm_source=Twitter&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Buffer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What the f&lt;/em&gt;** does this idiot know about the sport or the business*&lt;/a&gt;”, with Schaub immediately pointing out that White himself has never been involved in an MMA bout so by default cannot know what is best for the fighters. Schaub has long stood on the side of wanting to see White gone from the organisation, citing his own experience as a fighter for the UFC on his Below The Belt Podcast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportsjoe.ie/mma/brendan-schaub-dana-white-ufc-168769&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’ve been in that exact same scenario where you’re working your ass off to fight another man in a cage and you’re looking for some sort of approval from the head guy who controls your destiny who controls what match-ups you get, who controls how much publicity you get, who controls now what sponsors you get, who controls how much success you’re going to have&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a promoter it is White’s job to be capable of building up his fighters confidence alongside being able to sell the fights. If White continues to talk down to his fighters the way he currently does, then it is likely we will see fighters seek opportunities in other promotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an aggressive backlash from an ex-fighter would be a clear indicator that White’s leadership isn’t supported wholeheartedly. However, unfortunately, without Dana White, the UFC would not be the powerhouse promotion it is today and it does not look likely that White will be going anywhere anytime soon. It is evident that the key motivation for the organisation is financial and global growth, championed by the mindset of Dana White. In future we can hope to see a more equal pay bracket for those who risk their wellbeing by fighting in the octagon. However, due to the current atmosphere of the promotion and the longevity of Dana White’s career as president, whether or not this revised pay bracket will come to fruition is too difficult to predict unless some form of fighters union were to be formed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">From its realisation in 1993 to where we are now in 2019, the Ultimate Fighting Championship has been a pioneer and market leader in Mixed Martial Arts promotion. Founded by David Isaacs alongside owner Bob Meyrowitz, the UFC was created on the ideals of joining together the top martial artists in a no holds barred tournament to determine which of them possessed the more superior skills in combat. The immediate attraction of the UFC was evident. Marketed as a ‘No Rules’ event, it gave casual combat sports fans a chance to experience a more brutal and raw form of action.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Legitimate a Contender is Ben Askren and What Does the Future Hold for the Former Champion?</title>
      <link href="/Ben-Askren" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Legitimate a Contender is Ben Askren and What Does the Future Hold for the Former Champion?" />
      <published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ben-Askren</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ben-Askren">&lt;p&gt;For many, the news of a deal between One Championship and the UFC to bring one of the hottest welterweight names in MMA in the form of Ben Askren to Dana White’s organisation set pulses racing. The previously undefeated Askren had become widely regarded as one of the welterweight GOATs, amassing an undefeated 18-0 record during his time in both Bellator and One Championship before his move to the UFC. Whilst throughout his career Askren’s stand-up game had been called into question, his incessant grappling and collegiate wrestling background allowed him to dominate almost all of his opponents including big names such as Douglas Lima and Shinya Aoki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, recently the tune has changed for Askren. His unconvincing victory over Robbie Lawler in his UFC debut at UFC 235 drew more questions about the legitimacy of Askren’s talents, after having almost been knocked out in the opening minute of the bout. After he engaged the clinch immediately versus Lawler, Askren was brutally sent into the canvas by a piledriver, from where on Askren absorbed heavy ground and pound from the ex-champion. Once Askren successfully regained the clinch, he was able to take Lawler down and secure a bulldog choke. Referee Herb Dean stepped in to ensure Lawler was still conscious after his arm appeared to go limp. After shaking his arm, Herb Dean assumed Lawler was out, not seeing the thumbs up from Lawler indicating that he was still conscious. Dean promptly ended the bout, which incurred strong protest from Lawler who had clearly been conscious the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his post-fight interview Askren made it clear that he would not entertain the idea of a rematch between himself and Lawler, creating yet more controversy around the manner of his victory, leading many to question whether or not Askren was out of his depth. It appeared as if Askren was simply afraid of losing his undefeated record, which had been extended to 19-0, hence his reluctance to book another fight with Lawler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it can be argued that Askren’s objection to rematching Lawler is because he does not have youth on his side. A title shot did not seem far off for Askren upon his arrival and it would appear a necessity for Askren to get his shot quickly in order to defend and secure his legacy, rather than risk his undefeated record in a rematch that may not better his chances of a title shot. Furthermore, given that Askren talks such a strong game, to almost be denied victory in such an ignominious fashion would potentially spell trouble for Askren, as to falter in such a talent stacked division can severely inhibit a fighter of Askren’s age’s chances of getting back to the top of the division. However, given that Askren is considered a big draw for any fighter at welterweight and the promotion as a whole, it was inevitable he would be given multiple opportunities to prove himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his victory over Lawler, Askren expressed his interest in the winner of Jorge Masvidal and Darren Till at UFC Fight Night London. Till had long made his desire to fight Askren clear, with the two going back and forth on social media. However, the upset of Masvidal viciously knocking Till out cold paved the way for one of, if not the greatest knockout in UFC history at UFC 239 in Las Vegas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an interview on The Joe Rogan Experience Podcast, Masvidal made it evident that his dislike of Askren was personal, detailing how he wanted to ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GQ5075ZFilo&quot;&gt;break his face&lt;/a&gt;’ due to the corny and irritating style in which Askren promotes his fights. When we consider the legitimacy of these threats from Masvidal, it would be easy to see this as just business promotion. In addition, it appeared as if Askren had successfully got under Masvidal’s skin and was apparently living inside his head free of rent. I initially thought Masvidal’s anger would get the better of him in the fight but how wrong I proved to be. Masvidal got his start as a street fighter during the Kimbo Slice days and rapidly shot to notoriety. The ferocity of this form of MMA would force Masvidal to channel his anger into his performances, keeping his composure in the build-up but having the ability to become one of the most formidable fighters to enter the octagon in modern times. During the build-up to the fight Askren appeared relaxed, cracking jokes and frequently questioning Masvidal’s anger, to which I thought Masvidal had no response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masvidal shocked the world on July 6th by knocking Askren out in 5 seconds via a flying knee, silencing his doubters and leaving viewers speechless. To knock out the undefeated Askren in such spectacular fashion makes Masvidal the hottest item in the welterweight division right now, with the hype building around him attracting more and more fans to his camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where does Askren go from here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a 19-0 former champion, to the victim of the fastest KO in history with a 1-1 record in the UFC (with a highly controversial victory), his career has really begun to be questioned by critics and fans alike. Whilst the loss to Masvidal has derailed his title hopes for now, it has also called into question the legitimacy of his fighting abilities, which appear to have been overstated by MMA fans due to his undefeated record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it should not be forgotten that Askren was undefeated for a reason; he still remains a highly regarded fighter and to re-enter the octagon in the premier promotion after a year out of the sport takes a lot of bravery, so hats off to Askren. Fans far and wide believe that this loss will serve as a learning curve for Askren which he will certainly benefit from. Despite this, Askren will still run his mouth as much as he did in the build-up to UFC 239, as he is a smart fighter who understands the necessity of self-promotion, similar to the style of promotion from the likes of Chael Sonnen and Conor McGregor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it is clear that Askren himself believes he can bounce back from this, it is difficult to predict what will happen in such a stacked weight class that contains some of the deadliest strikers in the entire organisation. It is clear that Askren needs a bounce back victory, and with rumours of a fight with Darren Till circulating, I am beginning to question the motivations of the UFC as an organisation, however this is a discussion for another time. Although Till has legitimate one punch knockout power which he has shown in his fights with the likes of Cowboy Cerrone, he has shown a deficiency on the ground which will play into Askren’s hands. Till’s shortcomings on the ground were particularly visible when he fought Tyron Woodley and was submitted via a D’arce choke. As Askren and Woodley are training partners it will be advantageous to Askren to learn from Woodley’s fight with Till and discover the flaws in the British fighter’s game in order to better his chances of a victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst this represents an opportunity for Askren to finally showcase his abilities, it does hold a greater risk than, for example, a match up with a journeyman such as Neil Magny or another lower ranked opponent. News has surfaced over the past couple of days of a match-up between Askren and veteran grappler Demian Maia. Maia has long been regarded as one of the most dangerous grapplers and submission experts in the organisation, so this is a highly desirable match-up. Not only does it allow Askren to prove himself against a highly regarded opponent and put his name back into contention, but it also has the potential to showcase Askren being outclassed at his preferred fighting style. It would certainly be intriguing to see Askren take on another high-level grappler in what is a make-or-break fight for the welterweight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the adversity he has faced, Ben Askren does have a future in the UFC. Whilst it would not be strange for a hype train as large as Askren’s to be derailed, due to the calibre of the competition at welterweight, it would be a shame considering the talent Askren showed in other organisations. Whilst Askren is at risk of fading into the periphery, he remains a big draw for a lot of fighters, so we can only hope that his UFC career picks up from here and he has the chance to showcase his abilities as he has done in One Championship and Bellator.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For many, the news of a deal between One Championship and the UFC to bring one of the hottest welterweight names in MMA in the form of Ben Askren to Dana White’s organisation set pulses racing. The previously undefeated Askren had become widely regarded as one of the welterweight GOATs, amassing an undefeated 18-0 record during his time in both Bellator and One Championship before his move to the UFC. Whilst throughout his career Askren’s stand-up game had been called into question, his incessant grappling and collegiate wrestling background allowed him to dominate almost all of his opponents including big names such as Douglas Lima and Shinya Aoki.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up</title>
      <link href="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up" />
      <published>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up">&lt;p&gt;Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 237&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated UFC 237 saw a Brazilian takeover in the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, with the Fight of the Night being awarded to the epic war between then Strawweight Champion Rose Namajunas and ‘Bate Estaca’ (Pile Driver) Jessica Andrade, who demonstrated her superb strength with a vicious slam knockout to claim the Strawweight belt much to the delight of the Brazilian fans, who all together had enjoyed a torrid evening full of disappointment, with Andrade being one of only four Brazilians to taste victory on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil has always been notorious for showcasing undoubtedly the most hostile fans in MMA. Their unwelcoming spirit to any competitor from outside Brazil was exemplified best in Jared Cannonier’s victory over Anderson Silva in the frustrating co-main event. A leg kick from Cannonier to the knee of Silva ended the fight in unfortunate fashion in the first round, much to the displeasure of the Brazilian fans, who proceeded to boo Cannonier throughout his post-fight interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the match-up between Australia’s Alexander ‘The Great’ Volkanovski and the hometown hero José Aldo did not disappoint. With the crowd expecting the -145 betting favourite José Aldo to pull off a victory that would put him back in title contention, Volkanovski came into the cage relaxed and confident. ‘The Great’ Volkanovski quickly demonstrated why he is considered the Number 1 contender, dominating Aldo for all three rounds with leg kicks and strikes, earning himself a unanimous decision victory, extending his fight win streak to sixteen, and his record in MMA to 19-1-0. This leaves Volkanovski waiting to face the winner of Max Holloway versus Frankie Edgar at UFC 240, whilst José Aldo drops down the rankings to Number 3 in the division, potentially opening up a window for a fight with Number 2 ranked Brian Ortega.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event of UFC 237 saw ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas take on Jessica ‘Bate Estaca’ Andrade in a title showdown for the Women’s Strawweight Title. With Namajunas returning to the Octagon for the first time in over a year after recovering from neck surgery, many expected her not to perform to the same level as her incredible two previous victories over former Strawweight champion Joanna Jedrzejczyk. However, it appeared that Rose was as sharp as ever in the first round, completely out-striking and dominating Andrade for the first five minutes. An attempted but unsuccessful arm-bar submission from Namajunas exemplified the narrative of the first round, with the victory appearing to be merely a formality and an inevitability for the American. Nevertheless, with the backing of her hometown fans, Andrade showed her endurance and determination coming out in the second round pressing Namajunas up to the fence and working for the clinch in order to utilise her far superior strength. Once Andrade secured the clinch, she was able to perform a High Crotch Slam, living up to her nickname ‘Pile Driver’, dumping Namajunas onto the canvas and gaining the KO victory. Andrade’s knockout of Namajunas was only the fourth ever slam KO performed in a UFC title fight, and the first slam KO since Matt Hughes defeated Carlos Newton at UFC 34 in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fight, Namajunas cast doubt over her future in the organisation, hinting at a potential retirement due to the strain it was placing on her life and relationship with husband and coach Pat Barry. All MMA fans hope that this won’t be the end of ‘Thug’ Rose’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Andrade, she will now wait to see whether a rematch with Namajunas is the next step or whether she will face the likes of undefeated contender Tatiana Suarez, who holds massive potential and has been likened to current Men’s Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov due to her superior wrestling ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 238&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prelims saw wins for rising stars such as Tatiana Suarez, Aljamain Sterling and Calvin Kattar. Sterling, who is currently ranked third in the bantamweight division, defeated Pedro Munhoz via unanimous decision, with Munhoz riding high after his KO win over former champion Cody Garbrandt. Sterling controlled the fight with ease, utilising his striking and unique style to win the fight 30-27 on all score cards. This should set Sterling up for a shot at the title, unless Moraes is granted a rematch with Cejudo, in which case it is likely Sterling will face Number 2 ranked Raphael Assuncao.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calvin Kattar showcased exactly why MMA fans are so excited about him with a beautiful first round knockout of Ricardo Lamas. A clean lead left hook followed by a precise and brutal straight right hand ended the fight and catapulted Kattar within touching distance of the top ten of the division. There is certainly a lot on the horizon for the 31 year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tatiana Suarez displayed her talent despite a late rally from opponent Nina Ansaroff to earn a unanimous decision victory and set herself up for a potential title shot against champion Jessica Andrade. Suarez showed persistence and perseverance to secure a takedown early in the first, and proceeded to demonstrate superb top control during the 15 minutes to secure the victory, despite Ansaroff showing great heart in the third round with a great striking game on the feet, winning her the round albeit in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main card began with a heavyweight slugfest between Australia’s Tai Tuivasa and Bulgaria’s Blagoy Ivanov. Ivanov took the fight via unanimous decision. The Bulgarian dropped ‘Bam Bam’ Tuivasa in the first with a fantastic combination and would have won the fight via guillotine choke in the second had the bell not sounded. Despite huge shots from ‘Bam Bam’ threatening throughout the third round, Ivanov saw off Tuivasa to earn the victory with a confident performance that could see him potentially enter the top ten in the Heavyweight division.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petr Yan continued to show why he should be taken seriously at Bantamweight as he defeated Jimmie Rivera, dropping him twice, once in the first and then again in the second round. Rivera rallied to muster the performance he needed in the third round, however the knockdowns gifted Yan two 10-8 rounds, so only a stoppage would have given Rivera the victory. Despite landing shots on Yan in the final round, it was ineffectual as Yan claimed the unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aptly titled People’s Main Event saw two savages in Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson and Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone go to war at Lightweight. The opening round saw the two men stand and trade shots in the centre of the octagon, with Ferguson edging the round by outlanding Cowboy with significant strikes to the head and body. Ferguson’s endurance and pressure fighting style began to pay dividends in the second round, with Cerrone appearing to be slowly broken down by the accuracy of Ferguson’s punches and kicks. The end of the fight came shortly after the bell to end round 2, after Ferguson landed a late blow on Cowboy. Cerrone’s right eye was swollen shut. In an effort to clear the swelling he blew his nose, however, this only worsened the swelling and caused the doctor to call off the fight, awarding Ferguson the TKO victory. Whilst the fight did not end the way many had wished, it was in my opinion a correct decision for the bout to be ended despite protests from Cerrone. Ferguson was visibly upset by the way the fight ended, evidently disappointed in himself for landing the late strike. However, in his post-fight interview with Joe Rogan, Cerrone insisted that his injury was not a result of the strike. An anticlimactic ending but without a doubt one of the most entertaining fights of the night. ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson proved that he deserves a shot against the Lightweight champion Khabib Nurmagomedov by defeating Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone to confirm his position as the man to take on the winner of Khabib versus Dustin Poirier at UFC 242.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The co-main and main event did not hold such disappointment. Here we saw Valentina ‘Bullet’ Shevchenko cement her status as one of the most terrifying female competitors in MMA after defending her Flyweight title in style. Number 1 contender Jessica ‘Evil’ Eye was Shevchenko’s opponent in the Kyrgyzstani’s first defence of the title. Shevchenko showed exactly why she is one of the most devastating and feared fighters in women’s MMA, finishing the fight with a right head-kick that left Eye unconscious and twitching on the canvas for several minutes. In my opinion, Shevchenko has truly reached her peak, and produced one of the scariest KO’s in all of MMA history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Cejudo has arguably experienced the most meteoric rise in success in recent times. This success was furthered by his performance in the main event of UFC 238 at the United Centre in Chicago against Marlon Moraes. Cejudo looked to make history by becoming the first fighter to win an Olympic gold medal and be a 2 division UFC champion. In his way was Brazilian Marlon Moraes, who had been on a 4 fight win streak, finishing the likes of Jimmie Rivera and Raphael Assuncao prior to his title shot. With the vacant bantamweight title up for grabs, both men were plenty fired up in the build up, trading trash talk since the bout was announced. Having beaten TJ Dillashaw in his last fight, Cejudo leapt at the opportunity to become Champ Champ once Dillashaw vacated the title due to him testing positive for EPO in his fight with Cejudo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round saw Moraes take the early initiative, peppering Cejudo with hard leg kicks and strikes, easily winning the round. Moraes was on track to make the fight a one-sided contest, however Cejudo had other plans. ‘The Messenger’ came out in round 2 throwing hard right hands that effectively halted Moraes’ progress and Cejudo was also able to land some hard knees in the clinch, awarding him the second round. The third round showed just how determined and driven Cejudo was to become a double champion. Gaining top position on the ground, Cejudo landed devastating elbows and hammer fists on the visibly broken Moraes, which led to the referee stepping in and ending the fight as Cejudo became the 4th UFC fighter to hold belts in multiple divisions, following in the footsteps of the likes of Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Amanda Nunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This victory undoubtedly puts Cejudo in the conversation for the pound for pound best fighter at this moment in time. Certainly, the likes of Jon Jones and Khabib Nurmagomedov cannot be discounted due to the number of title defences from Jones and Khabib’s phenomenal 27-0 record. However, as Cejudo is the only athlete to have an Olympic gold medal on his resume, he has to, in my opinion, be included within the top 3 or at least the top 5 pound for pound greats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up on the calendar is perhaps the most anticipated card of the year. On July 6th in Las Vegas, UFC 239 sees Jon Jones look to defend his Light Heavyweight title against Thiago Santos, on a card that contains the likes of Amanda Nunes, Ben Askren, Jorge Masvidal, Luke Rockhold and many more. This card promises to be explosive and I believe it will be one of the best events of 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">UFC 236 Review</title>
      <link href="/UFC-236" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 236 Review" />
      <published>2019-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UFC-236</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-236">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last weekend we saw arguably two of the greatest title fights in the history of the UFC. A pair of five round wars to decide the Interim Middleweight and Lightweight champion respectively were the standout highlights of a card many anticipated to be one of the most exciting this year. The Co-Main Event saw rising star and elite striker Israel ‘The Last Stylebender’ Adesanya take on the equally formidable Kelvin Gastelum, with the winner moving on to face Undisputed Middleweight Champion Robert Whittaker later in the year. Gastelum had previously been booked to face Whittaker a few months prior at UFC 234 in Melbourne, however Whittaker was forced to withdraw from the bout due to a hernia that could have proved fatal had the fight taken place. As the fight was pulled from the card, much to the disappointment of fans who were eager to see Whittaker face this latest test after two wars with Yoel Romero, Israel Adesanya and Anderson Silva stepped up to fill the main event slot. Adesanya won the fight by unanimous decision and this was seen by many as a passing of the torch, due to Adesanya’s similar fighting style to that of Silva’s. This victory prompted the creation of the fight between Adesanya and Gastelum which did not disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the main event of UFC 236, current Featherweight Champion Max ‘Blessed’ Holloway challenged himself by moving up a weight class to face Dustin ‘The Diamond’ Poirier for the Interim Lightweight Title, with the winner moving on to face Undisputed Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov after his suspension for his involvement in the post-fight brawl at UFC 229 in September. Holloway came into fight the -210 favourite, however it was Poirier who stepped up to shock the crowd in Atlanta’s State Farm Arena, walking Holloway down for the duration of the fight and landing the lion’s share of the damage inflicting strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the card saw Khalil Rowntree JR. come back from his devastating KO loss to young star Johnny Walker to convincingly beat Eryk Anders at Light Heavyweight, landing 158 significant strikes over the three five-minute rounds, scoring several knockdowns to earn him a unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Welterweight, Alan Jouban took on Dwight Grant, losing a very close split-decision which enraged Jouban, who in his post-fight interview stated his desire to speak to the judges and ask about their background in Martial Arts so as to better understand their reasoning behind what he saw as a clear win for himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening the main card at Light Heavyweight, Nikita Krylov was able to submit Ovince Saint Preux via a Rear Naked Choke in the second round. Krylov lost their first bout at UFC 171 in 2014 to a submission, so was clearly fired up for their second meeting, despite Saint Preux stating his desire to beat Krylov in a similar or worse way than last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prelims&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UFC 236 Prelims were made special by two fights in particular. Germany’s Khalid Taha proved his potential at Bantamweight by steamrolling his way through Hawaii’s Boston Salmon in just 24 seconds, landing ten strikes to Salmon’s zero, before a perfect left hook folded the Honolulu native, finishing the fight with ground and pound strikes to earn a TKO victory and improve his record to 12-2. The other fight that took centre stage in the prelims ended in similar fashion, with Flyweight’s Wilson Reis and Alexandre Pantoja squaring off. Less than three minutes into the fight, Pantoja was able to land a beautifully timed right hand and finished with ruthless ground and pound to earn his TKO victory. The two other fights in the prelims saw Max Griffin end Zelim Imadaev’s unbeaten run at Welterweight by outworking him to a majority decision victory, and at Lightweight Matt Frevola was able to outpoint Jalin Turner to a unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-Main Event&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To many, Kelvin Gastelum would be the first real test for Israel Adesanya. The number 4 ranked fighter is a formidable opponent, with brutal wins over former Middleweight Champion Michael Bisping (KO), Jacare Souza (Decision) and Vitor Belfort (KO). Gastelum’s boxing skills would prove to be a cause of concern for Adesanya, who was visibly rocked by a strong right-hand in the opening round. However, Adesanya, whose power was questioned by many, proved his doubters wrong, dropping Gastelum in the second round with a looping right-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gastelum’s moment came in the fourth, catching Adesanya with an unexpected head kick which sent Israel stumbling back towards the fence. Had Gastelum continued striking at this point, it looked possible for him to finish the fight, with referee Mark Goddard asking for a response from Adesanya. Instead, Gastelum strangely decided to shoot for a double leg takedown, which was shrugged off by Adesanya, who showed phenomenal takedown defence to stand up and continue to punish Gastelum with accurate and powerful strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it was the accuracy of Adesanya which proved to be the difference, dropping Gastelum twice in the fifth and final round with clean punches, almost finishing the bout in the final seconds. After the final bell, the two warriors showed their appreciation of each other’s efforts, embracing as Jon Anik described the fight as ‘one of the best championship fights you will see’, a statement echoed by UFC owner Dana White in the post-fight press conference, with the fight earning the Fight of the Night bonuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The judges each scored the contest 48-46 in favour of New Zealander Adesanya, who now moves on to face Australian Robert Whittaker for a Middleweight Unification bout for the right to be called the Undisputed Middleweight Champion of The World. Here’s to hoping for another classic match-up and another thrilling Adesanya performance. As for Gastelum, he moves down the Middleweight rankings to number 5, with his next fight potentially taking shape in the form of number 2 ranked Yoel Romero, or rising prospect Paulo Costa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Main Event&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event treated fans at The State Farm Arena to another classic title fight for the Interim Lightweight Title. A lot was laid on the line for this bout; Max Holloway was moving up a division to challenge number 3 ranked Lightweight Dustin Poirier, putting at risk his unbelievable 13 fight win streak at Featherweight, which featured milestone victories against the likes of Jose Aldo and Brian Ortega. For Poirier, this was his chance to prove that he was worthy of a title shot against Khabib Nurmagomedov, after two thrilling victories over Eddie Alvarez and fan-favourite Justin Gaethje.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question going into the fight was whether or not Holloway’s power would be transferred due to the difference in weight. Known typically as a volume striker, it became quickly evident that Holloway’s power was not up to the level of Poirier’s, with The Diamond almost finishing the fight within the opening round, landing huge punches, forcing Holloway to cover up. However, being the champion that he is, Holloway refused to back down, pushing back against Poirier’s advances, challenging his opponent to fight harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third and fourth round saw the peak of the fight for Holloway, as he rocked Poirier with fast, accurate volume strikes, pushing Poirier back up against the fence, landing strikes to the body and head respectively. Poirier was visibly rattled by the exchanges but was able to land a vicious knee to the head of Holloway, opening up a nasty cut on the forehead that proceeded to leak blood into Holloway’s eyes. However, this only motivated the Hawaiian, calling for Poirier to stand and bang with him. Poirier rallied in the fifth round, with both men swinging for the fences in the last ten seconds of a truly unbelievable title fight. The fight was scored 49-46 by all three judges in favour of Poirier, who was visibly fired up at the end of the fight, knowing he had finally captured UFC gold. The bout also won Fight of the Night bonuses and ended a truly historic card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next event sees Alistair Overeem take on Aleksei Oleinik in the main event of Fight Night St Petersburg in what promises to be an exciting bout. The next big event we see will take place on May 12th at the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, where the Brazilian takeover features the likes of Jessica Andrade, Anderson Silva and Jose Aldo to name but a few, with ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas putting her Women’s Strawweight Title on the line. 2019 certainly promises to be one of the most thrilling and monumental years in the history of the UFC.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Event details</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
