<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/ali.abdi/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-06-22T16:35:39+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/ali.abdi/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Final Preview</title>
      <link href="/CL-Final-Preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Final Preview" />
      <published>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-Final-Preview</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-Final-Preview">&lt;p&gt;Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino’s Legacy and Klopp’s Final Troubles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tottenham are undoubtedly the underdogs but the narrative surrounding Mauricio Pochettino ahead of his first major European final is wholly favourable. If Tottenham prevail on Saturday, Pochettino will be lauded for his principal role in masterminding the North London club to the greatest prize in club football. In any case, Pochettino’s immense coaching qualities are unequivocal; it is no wonder that some of the world’s richest and most successful clubs, such as Juventus, Manchester United and Real Madrid have attempted to lure the Argentine away from N17. Spurs are on the brink of an unforgettable achievement and Pochettino will be a Tottenham legend regardless of the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Pochettino has previously faced criticism from fans and pundits for repeatedly asserting that he is not interested in winning the FA or League Cup and for never having won a major trophy in his managerial career, there is no question that the philosophy and attitude he has inculcated at the club has led to the greatest period of sustained success since the 1950s and 60s. Tottenham’s squad is too thin to compete on all four fronts, therefore it is no wonder that Pochettino has focused on the two most significant club competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to Pochettino, Tottenham’s history of having only won two major trophies since 1991 (2 League Cups) underlied the club’s reputation for ‘bottling’ and being a ‘nearly’ team. There is a strong sense in and around the club that Pochettino’s meticulous management, combined with mindful investment from chairman Daniel Levy to introduce dazzling new training facilities and stadium, has led to the instillment of a winning mentality that had been lacking at Tottenham for too long. The 47 year-old Argentine has indicated that a result in Tottenham’s favour could spell the end of his 5 year stay at Tottenham; he recently stated it is unlikely he will be able to repeat a victory of this magnitude for the club and is therefore open to moving on and seeking a new challenge elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry Kane’s role in the game as well as whether Tottenham can handle the big game pressure and the inexperience of winning finals will be crucial. The latest word from the Spurs camp is that Mauricio Pochettino and his staff will delay telling their players the starting line-up until Saturday afternoon in order to give themselves the more time to assess the fitness of the England captain. Surprising though it may seem, some of Spurs’ best performances this season have occurred without their star striker. It has been argued that this could be due to other players in the squad upping their game in order to account for the loss of Kane’s supreme talent. Nevertheless, everyone can agree that having Kane fit for the final gives Spurs a huge boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pochettino’s equivalent on Saturday evening will be none other than Jürgen Klopp. Klopp has already experienced managing a Champions League final in 2013 and 2018; the former saw his Borussia Dortmund side suffer a 2-1 defeat to Bayern Munich after a late Arjen Robben goal eventually penetrated Dortmund, who had been astutely tactically organised until the 80th minute mark when they were caught out of position as they began to take more risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since, Klopp has lost 5 successive cup finals, leading to questions over his big game management. There is a tendency for Klopp’s sides to lose their shape towards the end of games if they are eagerly attempting to score late in the game. If Spurs are to pull off an upset, they must recognise that in the few games Liverpool have lost this season - such as against Manchester City, Barcelona, Chelsea and Napoli - the Reds have typically conceded goals beyond the 80th minute mark. Nonetheless, the context and reality of Klopp guiding his teams to such a large number of cup finals is testament to his eminent coaching abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparisons can be drawn between Liverpool’s and Spurs’ recent histories. Klopp is bidding to win his first trophy as Liverpool manager, and he has ably reintroduced the consistency needed for success at Anfield. Before his arrival, the Scousers were to failing to compete in the major competitions. It is easy to see why Liverpool are favourites among bookmakers to become Champions of Europe for the sixth time in their history; Klopp has turned Liverpool into a leading European powerhouse once again: the upturn in performances over the last two seasons has been astounding, culminating in reaching two successive Champions League finals and finishing second with 97 points and 1 loss (to champions Manchester City) - no mean feats. The German recently described his current team as the best squad he has worked with in his managerial career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New signings Virgil Van Dijk, Fabinho, Alisson and Shaqiri have all played their part in Liverpool’s excellence and they are subsequently a well-rounded elite team wholly capable of competing among the very best. In the same time period that Liverpool made these formidable signings, Tottenham chose not to spend a single penny across 2 transfer windows. Furthermore, although the pressure on Liverpool to win is greater than their adversary, the Reds have shown many times over that they are able to perform masterfully under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May the best team win.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up</title>
      <link href="/CL-QF" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up" />
      <published>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-QF</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-QF">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City were narrowly defeated against a defiant Tottenham side in an enthralling Champions League quarter-final match that will live long in the memory of the competition’s illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first leg finished 1-0 to Spurs after Heung-Min Son’s late strike gave the home side the advantage heading into the second leg at the Etihad stadium; some will argue that the South Korean’s sole goal should have been saved by Ederson as it was close to his body but the sheer power off Son’s left boot managed to dumbfound the Brazilian goalkeeper. Perhaps the biggest turning point of the tie was Lloris’ early penalty save from Aguero, as from then on City’s opportunities were limited by a formidable Spurs defence who were successfully able to deny the Citizens from scoring a vital away goal. The first leg of the tie was a highly entertaining clash between two sides at the peak of their powers, but nobody expected the second leg to be as engrossing as it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Citizens needed to win by more than one goal at their home stadium to ensure going through to the semi-finals and despite the first leg defeat, City were still favourites to proceed to the next round, largely based on their impressive domestic successes and superior squad. Therefore, when Raheem Sterling scored in the 4th minute of the second leg to equal the aggregate score, many thought it would be a routine win for City, but these postulations were withdrawn after Heung-Min Son scored twice in quick succession to give Spurs the advantage. Astonishingly, Bernardo Silva’s deflected shot made it 2-2 within 11 minutes, and City, via Raheem Sterling again, added another before the interval to make it 3-2 on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expectedly, City began the second half putting immense pressure on the away side and their efforts eventually came to fruition after Sergio Aguero’s powerful near-post finish put City 4-2 up on 59 minutes. Spurs replied through Fernando Llorente, who became the unexpected hero after the ball bounced off his body into the net from a corner kick. In the end, the mesmerising game finished 4-3 to the Premier League champions, but it wasn’t enough as Spurs went through on away goals. The final few minutes of the tie saw Raheem Sterling score only for it to be ruled out for offside after VAR was consulted and City celebrations had already taken place in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After losing their talisman, Harry Kane, through a recurrent ankle injury in the first leg, few people expected Tottenham to beat Pep Guardiola’s prestigious team but Heung-Min Son stepped up to the plate in Kane’s absence, as he has numerous times this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result brings into question whether Pochettino is the better overall manager than Pep. Their rivalry stems from their time in Spain, as Espanyol and Barcelona managers respectively. Although Pep’s achievements in the game are unrivalled and has the superior record over the Argentine, Pochettino has had the lesser squad and defeated Pep in a quarter final despite not having made a signing since January 2018 and missing key players such as Harry Kane and Harry Winks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Messi shines again as Barcelona are into the semi-finals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona were 4-0 aggregate winners against a hopeless Manchester United side as the Catalan giants made light work of the Red Devils. After a 1-0 first leg defeat in which the Mancunians failed to provide any serious threat, United were made to pay for costly mistakes in the second leg as Leo Messi capitalised twice to give Barcelona a 3-0 aggregate advantage within 20 minutes of the second leg, all but ending the tie and sending Barcelona through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result marks Manchester United’s largest ever aggregate defeat in a two-legged European tie, while Barcelona will go on to face Liverpool in the last four of the competition, who will surely provide a sterner test than their English counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, it has become clear that Manchester United’s initial upsurge in form after Ole Gunnar Solskjaer’s appointment in December was only a short term reaction to the mood being lifted around the club. Since the unlikely comeback at the Parc des Princes in the competition’s round of sixteen stage, United have lost 6 of their last 8 matches in all competitions. The two games they did win (2-1 victories vs Watford and West Ham respectively) were unmerited by way of being the lesser side on both occasions. It still remains to be seen whether Solskjaer has the tactical know-how to match the enormity of the task being asked of him, which begs the question: why were United so hasty to appoint him as permanent manager, and why did they offer a three year contract, rather than a one-year rolling contract?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astounding Ajax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in Turin, Juventus were humbled by defeat against Dutch champions Ajax in a game in which the Italian heavyweights were strong favourites. Ajax stunned football fans with their accomplished displays against Real Madrid in the last round, and they continued to silence doubters by producing another set of proficient performances against Juventus. Ajax played Juventus off the park in both legs of the tie and if there is a stat that exemplifies the Dutch team’s dominance it is that Ajax scored three goals over the two legs, while Juventus only managed a measly three shots on target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ajax’s 3-2 aggregate win does not begin to tell the story of just how commanding they were over the Italian champions. However, if there can be any criticism pointed towards Ajax, it is that they are often wasteful in front of goal despite creating numerous chances. This may be partly due to not playing a recognised striker, as their front three is a combination of attacking midfielders and wingers, who are typically more involved in the build-up of goals rather than the finishing of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juventus were wholly uninspiring and lacklustre for a team that was tipped as a potential winner of the competition and Max Allegri’s job has now been called into question as reputable Italian newspapers report that his time at the club could be up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liverpool ease past Porto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porto were thumped 6-1 on aggregate by Liverpool as the Scousers comfortably swept aside the Portuguese champions to go on to the semi-finals. In truth, the scoreline does not truly reflect the nature of the game, in which Liverpool were made to defend for large parts to hang onto their lead. However, the result does reassert Liverpool’s defensive solidity and attacking prowess; the team is exceptional at both ends of the pitch. Liverpool defeated Porto by the same margin last season in the 16 round of the competition on their way to reaching the final and they will hope to do the same this year, although their next opponents will be Barcelona in a mouth-watering tie that promises to captivate audiences across the world as two European heavyweights go head-to-head for a place in this year’s final in Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jurgen Klopp has not yet lost a two-legged European tie during his stint at Liverpool and his side are now faced with a tough task of keeping this record intact against a Barcelona side who have only lost three games in all competitions this season. Luis Suarez and Philippé Coutinho will return to meet their former employers for the first time since leaving Anfield, which will host the second leg of the tie on 7th May at 20:00 BST.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
