<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/ali.abdi/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-07-09T21:25:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/ali.abdi/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Premier League’s 2019/20 Rising Stars</title>
      <link href="/PL-Rising-Stars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Premier League’s 2019/20 Rising Stars" />
      <published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/PL-Rising-Stars</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/PL-Rising-Stars">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another example of Brazil’s extraordinary footballing talent, Martinelli was playing in the fourth tier of Brazilian football before moving to north London. He’s as tenacious and fearless as a freeclimber and although he may lack height and stature, his quick feet, range of finishes and mature decision-making are evidence of precocious ability. Still only 18, he’s already scored 3 goals in 5 league starts this season. Clearly, Arsenal have unearthed a gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brandon Williams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The departure and decline of Ashley Young and Luke Shaw respectively has enabled this Manchester United academy graduate to break into the first-team. Rather than looking out of place or short of confidence, which would be typical of a teenager appearing in the most watched league in the world, Williams’ excellent showings have caught the eye. Proficient with both feet, quick, good technically and able to hold his own against the very best, he is the epitome of the modern fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams had no trouble counteracting the threat of Adama Traore, one of the most powerful and skillful wingers in the league, so much so that Adama was forced to switch flanks in the repeat 3rd round FA Cup fixture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emiliano Buendia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Argentine’s stats this season are something to behold. He’s completed the 3rd most take-ons (78) and the 2nd most chances created (68) in the division, with only Kevin De Bruyne having created more goal scoring opportunities. He’s also the only player in the league to have completed 50+ tackles, take-ons and chances created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stats are evidence of his tremendous quality; he works as hard as anyone, while also having the close control and passing ability of an elite playmaker. With Norwich almost certain to go down, the 22-year-old should be at the top of many clubs’ shopping lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Todd Cantwell&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The England U21 international has been another bright spark for a side who’ve been bottom for most of the season, having popped up with 6 goals and 2 assists so far. Born and bred in Norfolk, and a product of the Norwich academy, he’s a talented dribbler with clever passing and movement which makes him a real handful for defenders. He is another Norwich player who’s been linked with a move away pending their imminent relegation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tammy Abraham&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After scoring 25 goals in the Championship with Aston Villa last season, the 22-year-old returned to his parent club this season and has donned the number 9 shirt for Chelsea accordingly. Tall, quick and skillful, his quality is undoubted after scoring 13 goals in 23 appearances so far this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His clever movement in addition to fine link-up play means he will always pose a threat, and his performances this season have deservedly led to an England call-up. With Harry Kane facing a long injury layoff, Abraham will relish the opportunity to lead the line for the Three Lions at the upcoming European Championships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Japhet Tanganga&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanganga had to wait patiently to be given his first league start for Tottenham after impressing in pre-season against the likes of Real Madrid and Juventus. After being thrust in for his Premier League debut against Liverpool earlier this month, the 20-year-old followed it up with another outstanding display against Middlesbrough in the FA Cup in which he was named Man of the Match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily a centre-back, he’s so far been deployed at right-back and left-back in addition to his favoured role, and some have even gone so far to suggest that he could be an option in defensive midfield. His positional sense fused with his astute reading of play makes him a top-class centre back, but his speed and comfort on the ball makes him adept in both fullback positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing the elite Belgian centre-back pairing of Vertonghen and Alderweireld will be no easy task but supporters and staff alike are confident that Tanganga can cement himself in the Spurs backline for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dean Henderson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 22-year-old is a stalwart of Chris Wilder’s Sheffield United team and has been key to their success over the last 2 seasons. With current England ‘keeper Jordan Pickford flattering to deceive, many fans are calling for the in-form Blades goalie to replace Pickford between the sticks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The on-loan Manchester United ‘keeper has conceded just 20 goals in 23 appearances this season, racking up 8 clean sheets. This trumps both Pickford and Nick Pope, who are Henderson’s main rivals for the England number 1 jersey - Pickford has conceded 35 in 24 appearances with 6 clean sheets, while Pope has let in 38 in 23 with 7 clean sheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henderson’s save percentage is superior too. Of the 15 Premier League goalkeepers to have saved 50+ shots this season, Henderson has the highest save percentage (74.68%). Meanwhile, Pickford and Pope’s save percentages are 64% and 60% respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main gripe with Henderson is that his passing stats are not particularly attractive. While Pickford has completed 56.77% of his passes this season, Pope has completed 38.29%, but Henderson’s passing accuracy is just 33.72%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southgate is a keen proponent of playing out from the back and it seems unlikely that he will replace Pickford between the sticks, whom he’s trusted for the last 2 years, but there’s certainly a strong case for Henderson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reece James&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This youngster is a phenomenon; it’s rarely the case that a player is able to combine technical excellence with physical power and strength, but James is a special case. Though he’s just 19, James plays well beyond his years. It is no wonder why he was named Chelsea’s Academy Player of the Year 2017/18, Wigan’s Player of the Month 4 times in the same season, and in the EFL Championship Team of the Season 2018/19. Although his defensive positioning could be improved upon, he’s often the most creative player on the pitch with his magnificent passing and unrivalled crossing ability. He’s always an outlet on the right-hand side with his pace and intelligent forward runs, and in addition to his direct dribbling, he possesses a menacing shot, his strength is devastating and he has no trouble getting stuck in and timing tackles to perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James’ competencies allow him to excel in a variety of positions, from his favoured right-back role to centre-back to central midfield. His talent and versatility is so noteworthy that it led Wigan’s manager, Paul Cook, to proclaim that “Reece James could play in goal, he’s that outstanding!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England have a flurry of top-class right backs at the moment, and Reece James is making a case for himself to be the most complete. Jermaine Jenas on Match Of The Day described him as a hybrid between Trent Alexander-Arnold, Kyle Walker, Kieran Trippier and Aaron Wan-Bissaka because of the way in which James possesses the best qualities of them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jack Grealish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grealish was still a boy with unleashed potential when his side were relegated from the top-flight 4 years ago, however, this time round he is a fully fledged man and has been a shining light for a team who are among the dark depths of possible relegation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to effectively break the lines with marvellous dribbling and an eye for a pass, he also tracks back and works hard defensively, while also being a first-class finisher who’s adept with both feet. The talisman of his boyhood club has been one of the standout players in the league and his presence significantly increases Villa’s chances of staying in the division. It beggars belief as to how he’s not yet been called up for England, with seemingly everyone but Southgate praising his remarkable ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 24, he has all the necessary qualities to succeed wherever he goes, and a big money move is surely on the cards this summer. Tottenham will be rueing the fact that they came close to securing his signature in the summer of 2018 for a fee that would’ve been paltry compared to his value now as he would’ve gone a long way towards replacing Christian Eriksen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.premierleague.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.premierleague.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Gabriel Martinelli</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Ole ‘Goner’ Solskjaer?</title>
      <link href="/Ole-Goner" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ole ‘Goner’ Solskjaer?" />
      <published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ole-Goner</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ole-Goner">&lt;p&gt;Since being appointed as permanent Manchester United manager, Ole Gunnar Solskjær’s win rate in the Premier League is just 32%, a figure meagre enough for any manager to get sacked, let alone one of a club who are so accustomed to glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do the problems begin and end at Manchester United?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to appoint Ole Gunnar Solskjær on a full-time basis in March 2019, after a 3 month period in which he was greatly successful, epitomised the naivety and ineptitude of the United board. For whatever reason, the United board could not wait until the end of the season to take a more balanced, level-headed decision on the managerial appointment. The fans could be forgiven for believing that the initial honeymoon period which saw a huge upturn in results made Ole the right man for the job, but for the board to buy into this delirium exhibits an utter lack of prudence and shrewdness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their haste to appoint the legendary former striker as manager, they took a risk which has backfired and the decision becomes ever more questionable and costly as each day passes by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last season, when Jose Mourinho was relieved of his duties by Ed Woodward, he had accumulated 26 points from 17 games in the league. This campaign, Ole has managed 25 points in the same number of games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester United have seemingly settled for mediocrity under Solskjær. In recent weeks, Arsenal, Tottenham and Everton have all fired their underperforming managers and replaced them. While United have dithered and dallied, Everton have been able to allure one of the most decorated managers in the world in Carlo Ancelotti, a man who surely would have been of interest to United.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If United were to sack Solskjær soon, Max Allegri and Mauricio Pochettino would be among the favourites to succeed the Norwegian. Ed Woodward and co. have long been admirers of former Spurs boss Pochettino, but they will have to act quickly if they wish to acquire his services. The Argentine has become one of the most sought after coaches in world football during the last few years and he will have no shortage of job offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hit and Miss Signings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signings have also been a sticking point of United’s in recent years. The £80m expended to obtain Harry Maguire was exorbitant, excessive and another example of United overpaying for a player. He’s undoubtedly one of the best centre-halves in the league, but his quality still fails to justify such an inflated fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexis Sanchez was another extortionate mistake, and while Fred has improved in recent weeks, the Brazilian is yet another player who has failed to vindicate such a large price tag. Meanwhile, defenders Diogo Dalot and Eric Bailly have failed to flourish and have subsequently fallen out of favour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youngsters Daniel James and Aaron Wan-Bissaka have been better signings, but both are still raw and will take time to develop into the class of player that United were previously famed for. They would also both benefit from competition for their places; ironically, they are more nailed on to start for Manchester United than they were at their respective previous clubs, Swansea City and Crystal Palace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back even further, the acquisitions of Wilfried Zaha and Memphis Depay perhaps came too early in their careers. Both have gone on to forge formidable reputations for themselves and proven that the Red Devils should have remained patient with them when they didn’t immediately thrive at such young ages. The star quality they possess certainly wouldn’t go amiss at United at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lacking a Playmaker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot has been made of the fact that the Red Devils struggle to break down opposition teams who sit deep. United are bereft of ideas when facing low blocks; they are crying out for a playmaker who can control the tempo of games and break teams down with line-breaking passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In games which tend to be more open, typically against higher quality opposition, United have enjoyed more success. They have the benefit of being able to utilise the lightning quick pace of Rashford, Martial and James, enabling them to be menacing on the break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one damning statistic which proves this notion. United currently lie in 6th place, and they have amassed 13 points from the 5 teams that sit above them, but just 12 points from the teams below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With recent victories over Spurs and rivals City, Ole has bought himself more time to prove to the Old Trafford faithful that he’s got what it takes to be successful in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a positive note, Solskjær is bringing the best out of Marcus Rashford this year. The 22-year-old is in sumptuous form, enjoying his best goal scoring season to date. This is perhaps one reason that the United hierarchy have no plans to sack their manager anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason for sticking with the Norweigian is stability. Stability is vital for any football club and group of players, and a club who had the same manager for 26 years prior to 2013 know that better than anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the reasons outlined above, United’s decay is not entirely the fault of the former Molde manager. He is struggling with an incompetent board and an imbalanced squad, but questions remain over whether Ole has the managerial experience and tactical acumen needed to prevail at the biggest club in England. With long-term managerial target Mauricio Pochettino currently out of a job, it would make sense for Ed Woodward to try to entice Pochettino towards Carrington.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since being appointed as permanent Manchester United manager, Ole Gunnar Solskjær’s win rate in the Premier League is just 32%, a figure meagre enough for any manager to get sacked, let alone one of a club who are so accustomed to glory.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Final Preview</title>
      <link href="/CL-Final-Preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Final Preview" />
      <published>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-Final-Preview</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-Final-Preview">&lt;p&gt;Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino’s Legacy and Klopp’s Final Troubles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tottenham are undoubtedly the underdogs but the narrative surrounding Mauricio Pochettino ahead of his first major European final is wholly favourable. If Tottenham prevail on Saturday, Pochettino will be lauded for his principal role in masterminding the North London club to the greatest prize in club football. In any case, Pochettino’s immense coaching qualities are unequivocal; it is no wonder that some of the world’s richest and most successful clubs, such as Juventus, Manchester United and Real Madrid have attempted to lure the Argentine away from N17. Spurs are on the brink of an unforgettable achievement and Pochettino will be a Tottenham legend regardless of the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Pochettino has previously faced criticism from fans and pundits for repeatedly asserting that he is not interested in winning the FA or League Cup and for never having won a major trophy in his managerial career, there is no question that the philosophy and attitude he has inculcated at the club has led to the greatest period of sustained success since the 1950s and 60s. Tottenham’s squad is too thin to compete on all four fronts, therefore it is no wonder that Pochettino has focused on the two most significant club competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to Pochettino, Tottenham’s history of having only won two major trophies since 1991 (2 League Cups) underlied the club’s reputation for ‘bottling’ and being a ‘nearly’ team. There is a strong sense in and around the club that Pochettino’s meticulous management, combined with mindful investment from chairman Daniel Levy to introduce dazzling new training facilities and stadium, has led to the instillment of a winning mentality that had been lacking at Tottenham for too long. The 47 year-old Argentine has indicated that a result in Tottenham’s favour could spell the end of his 5 year stay at Tottenham; he recently stated it is unlikely he will be able to repeat a victory of this magnitude for the club and is therefore open to moving on and seeking a new challenge elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry Kane’s role in the game as well as whether Tottenham can handle the big game pressure and the inexperience of winning finals will be crucial. The latest word from the Spurs camp is that Mauricio Pochettino and his staff will delay telling their players the starting line-up until Saturday afternoon in order to give themselves the more time to assess the fitness of the England captain. Surprising though it may seem, some of Spurs’ best performances this season have occurred without their star striker. It has been argued that this could be due to other players in the squad upping their game in order to account for the loss of Kane’s supreme talent. Nevertheless, everyone can agree that having Kane fit for the final gives Spurs a huge boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pochettino’s equivalent on Saturday evening will be none other than Jürgen Klopp. Klopp has already experienced managing a Champions League final in 2013 and 2018; the former saw his Borussia Dortmund side suffer a 2-1 defeat to Bayern Munich after a late Arjen Robben goal eventually penetrated Dortmund, who had been astutely tactically organised until the 80th minute mark when they were caught out of position as they began to take more risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since, Klopp has lost 5 successive cup finals, leading to questions over his big game management. There is a tendency for Klopp’s sides to lose their shape towards the end of games if they are eagerly attempting to score late in the game. If Spurs are to pull off an upset, they must recognise that in the few games Liverpool have lost this season - such as against Manchester City, Barcelona, Chelsea and Napoli - the Reds have typically conceded goals beyond the 80th minute mark. Nonetheless, the context and reality of Klopp guiding his teams to such a large number of cup finals is testament to his eminent coaching abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparisons can be drawn between Liverpool’s and Spurs’ recent histories. Klopp is bidding to win his first trophy as Liverpool manager, and he has ably reintroduced the consistency needed for success at Anfield. Before his arrival, the Scousers were to failing to compete in the major competitions. It is easy to see why Liverpool are favourites among bookmakers to become Champions of Europe for the sixth time in their history; Klopp has turned Liverpool into a leading European powerhouse once again: the upturn in performances over the last two seasons has been astounding, culminating in reaching two successive Champions League finals and finishing second with 97 points and 1 loss (to champions Manchester City) - no mean feats. The German recently described his current team as the best squad he has worked with in his managerial career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New signings Virgil Van Dijk, Fabinho, Alisson and Shaqiri have all played their part in Liverpool’s excellence and they are subsequently a well-rounded elite team wholly capable of competing among the very best. In the same time period that Liverpool made these formidable signings, Tottenham chose not to spend a single penny across 2 transfer windows. Furthermore, although the pressure on Liverpool to win is greater than their adversary, the Reds have shown many times over that they are able to perform masterfully under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May the best team win.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up</title>
      <link href="/CL-QF" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up" />
      <published>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-QF</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-QF">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City were narrowly defeated against a defiant Tottenham side in an enthralling Champions League quarter-final match that will live long in the memory of the competition’s illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first leg finished 1-0 to Spurs after Heung-Min Son’s late strike gave the home side the advantage heading into the second leg at the Etihad stadium; some will argue that the South Korean’s sole goal should have been saved by Ederson as it was close to his body but the sheer power off Son’s left boot managed to dumbfound the Brazilian goalkeeper. Perhaps the biggest turning point of the tie was Lloris’ early penalty save from Aguero, as from then on City’s opportunities were limited by a formidable Spurs defence who were successfully able to deny the Citizens from scoring a vital away goal. The first leg of the tie was a highly entertaining clash between two sides at the peak of their powers, but nobody expected the second leg to be as engrossing as it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Citizens needed to win by more than one goal at their home stadium to ensure going through to the semi-finals and despite the first leg defeat, City were still favourites to proceed to the next round, largely based on their impressive domestic successes and superior squad. Therefore, when Raheem Sterling scored in the 4th minute of the second leg to equal the aggregate score, many thought it would be a routine win for City, but these postulations were withdrawn after Heung-Min Son scored twice in quick succession to give Spurs the advantage. Astonishingly, Bernardo Silva’s deflected shot made it 2-2 within 11 minutes, and City, via Raheem Sterling again, added another before the interval to make it 3-2 on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expectedly, City began the second half putting immense pressure on the away side and their efforts eventually came to fruition after Sergio Aguero’s powerful near-post finish put City 4-2 up on 59 minutes. Spurs replied through Fernando Llorente, who became the unexpected hero after the ball bounced off his body into the net from a corner kick. In the end, the mesmerising game finished 4-3 to the Premier League champions, but it wasn’t enough as Spurs went through on away goals. The final few minutes of the tie saw Raheem Sterling score only for it to be ruled out for offside after VAR was consulted and City celebrations had already taken place in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After losing their talisman, Harry Kane, through a recurrent ankle injury in the first leg, few people expected Tottenham to beat Pep Guardiola’s prestigious team but Heung-Min Son stepped up to the plate in Kane’s absence, as he has numerous times this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result brings into question whether Pochettino is the better overall manager than Pep. Their rivalry stems from their time in Spain, as Espanyol and Barcelona managers respectively. Although Pep’s achievements in the game are unrivalled and has the superior record over the Argentine, Pochettino has had the lesser squad and defeated Pep in a quarter final despite not having made a signing since January 2018 and missing key players such as Harry Kane and Harry Winks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Messi shines again as Barcelona are into the semi-finals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona were 4-0 aggregate winners against a hopeless Manchester United side as the Catalan giants made light work of the Red Devils. After a 1-0 first leg defeat in which the Mancunians failed to provide any serious threat, United were made to pay for costly mistakes in the second leg as Leo Messi capitalised twice to give Barcelona a 3-0 aggregate advantage within 20 minutes of the second leg, all but ending the tie and sending Barcelona through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result marks Manchester United’s largest ever aggregate defeat in a two-legged European tie, while Barcelona will go on to face Liverpool in the last four of the competition, who will surely provide a sterner test than their English counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, it has become clear that Manchester United’s initial upsurge in form after Ole Gunnar Solskjaer’s appointment in December was only a short term reaction to the mood being lifted around the club. Since the unlikely comeback at the Parc des Princes in the competition’s round of sixteen stage, United have lost 6 of their last 8 matches in all competitions. The two games they did win (2-1 victories vs Watford and West Ham respectively) were unmerited by way of being the lesser side on both occasions. It still remains to be seen whether Solskjaer has the tactical know-how to match the enormity of the task being asked of him, which begs the question: why were United so hasty to appoint him as permanent manager, and why did they offer a three year contract, rather than a one-year rolling contract?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astounding Ajax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in Turin, Juventus were humbled by defeat against Dutch champions Ajax in a game in which the Italian heavyweights were strong favourites. Ajax stunned football fans with their accomplished displays against Real Madrid in the last round, and they continued to silence doubters by producing another set of proficient performances against Juventus. Ajax played Juventus off the park in both legs of the tie and if there is a stat that exemplifies the Dutch team’s dominance it is that Ajax scored three goals over the two legs, while Juventus only managed a measly three shots on target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ajax’s 3-2 aggregate win does not begin to tell the story of just how commanding they were over the Italian champions. However, if there can be any criticism pointed towards Ajax, it is that they are often wasteful in front of goal despite creating numerous chances. This may be partly due to not playing a recognised striker, as their front three is a combination of attacking midfielders and wingers, who are typically more involved in the build-up of goals rather than the finishing of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juventus were wholly uninspiring and lacklustre for a team that was tipped as a potential winner of the competition and Max Allegri’s job has now been called into question as reputable Italian newspapers report that his time at the club could be up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liverpool ease past Porto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porto were thumped 6-1 on aggregate by Liverpool as the Scousers comfortably swept aside the Portuguese champions to go on to the semi-finals. In truth, the scoreline does not truly reflect the nature of the game, in which Liverpool were made to defend for large parts to hang onto their lead. However, the result does reassert Liverpool’s defensive solidity and attacking prowess; the team is exceptional at both ends of the pitch. Liverpool defeated Porto by the same margin last season in the 16 round of the competition on their way to reaching the final and they will hope to do the same this year, although their next opponents will be Barcelona in a mouth-watering tie that promises to captivate audiences across the world as two European heavyweights go head-to-head for a place in this year’s final in Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jurgen Klopp has not yet lost a two-legged European tie during his stint at Liverpool and his side are now faced with a tough task of keeping this record intact against a Barcelona side who have only lost three games in all competitions this season. Luis Suarez and Philippé Coutinho will return to meet their former employers for the first time since leaving Anfield, which will host the second leg of the tie on 7th May at 20:00 BST.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
