<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/amrit.chadha/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-31T13:57:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/amrit.chadha/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Microsoft’s Satya Nadella: A Catalyst</title>
      <link href="/Satya-Nadella" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microsoft’s Satya Nadella: A Catalyst" />
      <published>2020-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Satya-Nadella</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Satya-Nadella">&lt;p&gt;Hailing from the Southern part of India which has given birth to leaders of giant companies around the world, Satya Nadella has made Microsoft the largest company in the world, in terms of market capitalisation since he took over 6 years ago. His leadership style has been completely different from what the company had witnessed under its past leaders. From Steve Ballmer’s flashy and supposedly ‘epic’ speeches, Nadella brought a more calming effect to the table. This has certainly worked for the company. Instead of a sideward movement of the stock prices witnessed under Ballmer’s reign, the share prices have only been going up under Nadella’s leadership. Nadella, a proponent of the growth mindset philosophy, believes in the growth of individuals and the team as a whole. Instead of focussing too much on tradition, he convinced the employees that innovation is the only thing that is respected in their industry. Often under the guidance of Ballmer and Gates, Microsoft had begun living off of its past rather than focussing on providing world-class tech to its users. However, tradition is fleeting and the only constant is change in this ever-changing world. This philosophy has helped Nadella in bringing Microsoft where it is today. When Nadella was given charge of Microsoft’s Cloud services, Ballmer had warned Nadella that he would be fired if he doesn’t make it work, and yet again while taking charge as the CEO, he faced a similar do-or-die situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft, by many accounts, was in dire shape before Nadella took over in 2014. Windows 8 had debuted with poor reception, and it was struggling to navigate the smartphone revolution. Although the Surface tablet is a modest success, Microsoft’s smartphones have flopped despite the firm paying more than €5.4 billion ($6.2bn; £4.7bn) for Nokia’s handset business. Apple’s iPhone, and then Google’s Android left Microsoft in the dust. Additionally, ‘Zune’, the company’s iPod lookalike, was considered one of the worst product flops in tech history. There was no doubt that Microsoft had maintained a longstanding legacy in Silicon Valley, but many agreed that it needed a new strategy to compete against its more nimble counterparts like Apple Inc and Alphabet Inc. The major problem was that Microsoft was not dynamic. It had not been changing with time, and was not adapting to the changes that its competitors were creating in the business environment. Where Bill Gates had taken the wind of personal computing, Steve Ballmer failed to do the same with smartphones. However, Satya had no intention of committing the same mistake. He made a pronouncement on day one, &lt;em&gt;“The world is about cloud-first, mobile-first”&lt;/em&gt;, and made clear the direction in which the company would be going for the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Nadella’s leadership, Microsoft has embarked on a major transition towards becoming a cloud computing giant through its Azure platform. The cloud business, growing at a rate of 47%, continues to be the primary driver of the company’s success in recent years. The company’s current flagship business has a 20% market share in the cloud business. Azure is second only to Amazon’s AWS, with 31%. The coevolution of software and hardware will digitise most of the things that we do and experience in business, life and the world. It will be interesting to see who comes out on the top in the cloud competition in this world that is moving towards more sophisticated tech every day. Microsoft surely seems to be on the right path, being one step ahead of the change and not relying too much on its past successes. Nadella has completely shifted the company’s focus from its core business of Windows in the tenure of his leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has also forayed into the world of cloud gaming with Azure. Cloud gaming is like a subscription for games that you can play on any platform (mobile phone, laptop, gaming consoles, etc.). For Microsoft, getting the first-mover advantage would be key as Google too is planning to capture the market with ‘Stadia’. However, it should be easier for Microsoft to establish a strong foothold in this area as it already has experience with its gaming console business ‘Xbox’. The company has been using gamers’ data and constantly improving itself, to give the customers what they want, according to their preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella opposed the decision to purchase Nokia as he could not see why the world needed a third ecosystem in phones. He focussed on more sensible acquisitions, such as that of the job-search portal, LinkedIn. With this acquisition, Microsoft has become the leader in professional data. The Redmond giant plans to integrate the portal and make it available inside Outlook, Office, Skype, and Windows, thereby creating an ecosystem that is inescapable for the customer. Moreover, plans to integrate Cortana with LinkedIn have also been made. If something like this happens, Cortana would be able to assist the users in a much more complex manner by providing intel on customers’ business relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella has also incorporated lessons from his personal life into his leadership style. Talking about his son’s struggle with cerebral palsy in his book &lt;em&gt;Hit Refresh&lt;/em&gt;, he talks about how that experience instilled in him the feeling of empathy. He believes that it is important for people working in an innovation-centric company to be empathetic. In order to find a solution for a problem that your consumer is facing, you need to first be able to put yourself in his shoes and feel the need for innovation. He has repeatedly pressed on the importance of understanding what others are going through in order for a business to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella’s managing style, say those who know him, is akin to cricket’s long-form (a sport of which the CEO is very fond of): slow, deliberative and patient. He makes no snap decisions. He focuses on a handful of the most important issues facing the company and takes a deep dive into each, encouraging serious input from others. Listening, probing, questioning. When he’s satisfied that he has enough information, he makes his decision — not a minute sooner. Nadella and his team know exactly what Microsoft is and what they want it to be: an innovative technology company that exists to help other businesses thrive. This vision is what has kept them growing, and will continue doing so in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Hailing from the Southern part of India which has given birth to leaders of giant companies around the world, Satya Nadella has made Microsoft the largest company in the world, in terms of market capitalisation since he took over 6 years ago. His leadership style has been completely different from what the company had witnessed under its past leaders. From Steve Ballmer’s flashy and supposedly ‘epic’ speeches, Nadella brought a more calming effect to the table. This has certainly worked for the company. Instead of a sideward movement of the stock prices witnessed under Ballmer’s reign, the share prices have only been going up under Nadella’s leadership. Nadella, a proponent of the growth mindset philosophy, believes in the growth of individuals and the team as a whole. Instead of focussing too much on tradition, he convinced the employees that innovation is the only thing that is respected in their industry. Often under the guidance of Ballmer and Gates, Microsoft had begun living off of its past rather than focussing on providing world-class tech to its users. However, tradition is fleeting and the only constant is change in this ever-changing world. This philosophy has helped Nadella in bringing Microsoft where it is today. When Nadella was given charge of Microsoft’s Cloud services, Ballmer had warned Nadella that he would be fired if he doesn’t make it work, and yet again while taking charge as the CEO, he faced a similar do-or-die situation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Vision 20/20</title>
      <link href="/Vision-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vision 20/20" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Vision-2020</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Vision-2020">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Info Edge, it seems, has mastered the maths of running online classifieds in India. Industry observers attribute this success to the fact that customers don’t pay anything to use these platforms, except for Jeevansathi. From listings of jobs, real estate, and education, the company earns most of its revenue from businesses, advertisements, listing fees, and subscription products. This is in sharp contrast to the likes of OLX and Quikr, where a customer has the option to buy a paid listing, but the vast majority of users don’t pay to have their products listed; consequently, they have also burnt through millions of dollars to acquire new customers. However, Info Edge founders do not believe in this philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country’s largest employment website, Naukri, boasts about 67 million résumés and currently has 500,000 job listings on its platform. More than 60% of its revenue comes from the fees it charges from employers for access to its huge résumé database. 99acres, another successful venture of the Info Edge brand was founded in 2005 and is also a leader in its category. As of December 31, 2019, the site had total listings of 1,004,378 properties. It competes with Magicbricks, Commonfloor, and Housing. However, between 2013 and 2016, VC funding was abundantly available, triggering a mushrooming of players in the real estate sector. Backed by the likes of NewsCorp, SoftBank, and Tiger Global Management, startups such as Proptiger, Commonfloor, Housing, Quikr, OLX, Indiahomes, and Indiaproperty started giving 99Acres a tough fight. However, 99acres has held its ground. Jeevansathi is the third-largest matrimonial site in India, after Bharat Matrimony and Shaadi. Online spending on the business is likely to grow to ₹11-12 billion by 2023-24 from ₹7-8 billion in 2020-21. This is expected to give a huge boost to Info Edge’s matrimonial website. Shiksha, the portal providing information on careers, examinations, colleges, and courses is facing stiff competition as there are a lot many major players in the EdTech sector. With the likes of Byju’s, it has become tough for Shiksha to make a strong presence in the Indian EdTech sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bikhchandani had seen potential in classifieds websites when there were just around 14,000 internet accounts in the country and a few thousand users comparing that to the around 500 million users in India now, second only to China’s more than 800 million. It became the early mover in the internet economy, taking many essentials online as India’s population started discovering the joys of a virtually connected world. But as an early mover, Bikhchandani knows the downside of the treadmill. He is aware of the need to continuously make innovations in the fast-changing technological world. For that, Info Edge will leverage its advantage of two decades’ worth of data, using artificial intelligence, data analytics, and machine learning to drive informed change through improved user experiences and new products. Also, Info Edge will continue its 12-year-long practice of investing in ‘ideas’ with the ₹1 billion ‘Info Edge Venture Fund’, launched in January, to fund early-stage startups across categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the first fund by Info Edge, but the company has already invested ₹1.03 billion in 16 startups, including the likes of Zomato and PolicyBazaar. Overall the company has 21 active investments worth ₹1.108 billion at the end of 2020-21. In fact, one of its most successful bets has been restaurant aggregator and food delivery platform Zomato. Bikhchandani, a foodie, had been using Foodiebay (rebranded as Zomato only in 2010). A subsequent conversation with founder Deepinder Goyal set the tone for a business association, and Bikhchandani made an initial investment of ₹40.5 million. Its investment till date is ₹1.52 billion with about 22.7% stake. Zomato has already successfully acquired Uber’s food delivery business in India, Uber Eats. Moreover, PolicyBazaar is expected to receive investment from Google in its bid to expand its digital presence in India. Additionally, the insurance aggregator is also expected to raise $500 million from its Initial Public Offering (IPO) sometime next year. So the prospects of Info Edge cashing out big are right around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While making investments, Bikhchandani not only focuses on the business model but also takes into consideration the commitment, capability, and integrity of founders, and good governance. The importance of these qualities can be understood when fiascos like WeWork and Wirecard occur. Of course, some of the newer business models ask for cash burn to gain market share which is not how Bikhchandani runs his companies. He has always advised startups to get ‘customer money’ before ‘investor money’. Maybe some of the larger funds can learn from this strategy instead of blindly burning cash.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lost Vision: The Many Failures of Masayoshi Son</title>
      <link href="/Lost-Vision" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost Vision: The Many Failures of Masayoshi Son" />
      <published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lost-Vision</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lost-Vision">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;45 minutes, $45 billion, $1 billion per minute&lt;/em&gt;”, this is how SoftBank’s Chief Executive Officer Masayoshi Son, described his meeting with Saudi Arabia’s Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman. After this meeting, the Public Investment Fund of Saudi Arabia (PIF) became the largest investor in SoftBank’s outrageous $93 billion technology investment fund, the Vision Fund. This fund was unlike any other fund that anyone had ever seen before - &lt;em&gt;bigger, bolder, and better&lt;/em&gt;. The CEO’s exuberance was even highlighted in the size of the fund which was introduced. With this particular fund, Son wanted to make a presence in tech companies working in artificial intelligence, robotics and the Internet of Things. The fund did fulfil its purpose by giving the company a major share in some of the world’s ‘up and coming’ startups like OYO, Paytm, WeWork, Didi, Uber, Ola, Flipkart, along with 83 others. However, at what cost?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masayoshi Son has always been famous for his gut-led investment style, and it seems that he invests in people rather than in companies. One such person in whom Son invested was Alibaba founder, Jack Ma. Son himself said that Ma had no business plan, but he had “strong eyes”. However unconventional that might sound, it did turn out to be the most profitable investment of SoftBank till date. The investment in Alibaba, $20 million in 2000, turned into $60 billion when the company went public in September 2014. Masa expects every person in whom he invests to become the next Jack Ma. This strategy seemed to be working for the company as it reported a 62% return in the mid of 2019, after making 71 investments for a total of $64.2 billion, and the ride was supposed to be smooth from this point. On the flip side, the company has started facing hurdles and the return on the fund is negative 6%, compared with 62% just a year ago. The fund has lost more for the company than it has earned for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Son’s weakness for charismatic and flashy founders led him to invest in WeWork’s Adam Neumann. Through a combination of glamour and millennial charm, Adam was able to sell WeWrok to Son. It wasn’t even a tech company. Although Son was impressed, the company failed to impress financial analysts. People couldn’t understand the business model of WeWork and were reluctant to invest in it. Even after these speculations, the company decided to go public and as a result of this, their valuation came down to $3 billion from $47 billion in just a year. WeWork’s struggling finances, huge losses, hard-partying culture, and the CEO’s antics sank the ship. Eventually, SoftBank had to step in and buy the company. It came up with a $9.5 billion ‘rescue package’ and took over 80% of the shares. This takeover added dead weight to the company’s balance sheet as the onus to make the real estate firm profitable lay on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such investment that might come to haunt SoftBank in the near future would be OYO. Son invested $1.5 billion in the company and asked the 26-year old founder, Ritesh Agarwal, to make it the world’s largest hotel operator by room count. The business model that worked so well in India wasn’t an obvious fit for the US and European markets, which already had well established, quality hotel chains. In a hasty attempt to expand outside India, OYO faced many logistical and technological challenges. These included double booking of rooms, failing to keep track of the keys, and reducing the rent of the landlords to mere pennies and taking days to fix these glitches. All these failures left the consumers as well as the vendors highly unsatisfied. OYO’s figures haven’t been impressive either, the company had revenue of $951 million for the fiscal year ending in March 2019, while losses surged six-fold to $335 million year-on-year. Furthermore, the young founder has further borrowed $2 billion, to buy out some investors. The loan has been personally guaranteed by Son, in a bizarre deal. The cash-pumping strategy has hampered the company’s natural course and put it on a path to become what many experts believe ‘the next WeWork’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ongoing pandemic, tech companies have faced the most brutal brunt of the lockdowns across the globe. These unicorns have had to let go of people, lose consumers and face burgeoning costs. Uber, another major investment of SoftBank, has been one of the hardest hit. It had merely recovered from the saga of its poor-performing IPO that it had to face the impact of the virus. This has further added to the tensions of the Son-led company. The current scenario has dimmed the hopes of the CEO who was hoping for a $108 billion Vision Fund part-two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to tackle the mounting problems, the company has had to sell shares in Alibaba, its most valuable holding, to raise $11.5 billion. SoftBank is also likely to sell stock in its Japanese telecom unit SoftBank Corp and T-Mobile US Inc. Furthermore, the Japanese company also plans to spend up to ¥500 billion to buy back shares through March 2021, on top of an existing repurchase plan of the same size. That has helped to stabilise SoftBank shares giving them a boost of more than 75% from their low in March. The massive buyback remains the only good news for the shares. The company did not announce any dividend for the first time in its history this year and it has no plans to announce one next year as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, SoftBank said Jack Ma will step down as a director. Additionally, three new directors have been nominated. Son’s increasingly risky bets over the past few years coincided with departures from its board of some of its most outspoken members. With no famous outside directors left on SoftBank’s board, it’s not clear who is going to hold Son responsible anymore. It remains to be seen how that bodes for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, the Vision Fund has made massive losses for the company, it can still be argued that Masayoshi Son has faced worse after he made $70 billion in losses after the dot-com bubble burst and bounced back even stronger. However, to ensure that there is a comeback this time as well, the company needs to make some strategic changes. Instead of investing huge sums of money in these startups in their early stages and making them cash-burning machineries, they should let them grow according to their organic speed. The kind of ‘growth at all costs’ that comes with an asterisk with such large investments is what ruins a good company with a good business plan. Moreover, focussing on profitability rather than on growth solely would help in making the situation better for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson to learn here is that money can’t always buy success. The cheques that Son was blindly cutting for the companies were harming them more than they were helping. He was actually creating bigger and bigger bubbles, which came back to burst right in his face. Although, the enthusiastic CEO has reiterated several times during the past few months that he has learnt his lesson. It remains to be seen as to what he actually does to turn the situation around. Maybe, his self-confidence and stubbornness will help the company after all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“45 minutes, $45 billion, $1 billion per minute”, this is how SoftBank’s Chief Executive Officer Masayoshi Son, described his meeting with Saudi Arabia’s Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman. After this meeting, the Public Investment Fund of Saudi Arabia (PIF) became the largest investor in SoftBank’s outrageous $93 billion technology investment fund, the Vision Fund. This fund was unlike any other fund that anyone had ever seen before - bigger, bolder, and better. The CEO’s exuberance was even highlighted in the size of the fund which was introduced. With this particular fund, Son wanted to make a presence in tech companies working in artificial intelligence, robotics and the Internet of Things. The fund did fulfil its purpose by giving the company a major share in some of the world’s ‘up and coming’ startups like OYO, Paytm, WeWork, Didi, Uber, Ola, Flipkart, along with 83 others. However, at what cost?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Quality or Quantity?</title>
      <link href="/Quality-or-Quantity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quality or Quantity?" />
      <published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Quality-or-Quantity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Quality-or-Quantity">&lt;p&gt;Why are so many students convinced that they should get good grades just because they spent so many hours on a particular paper? It is not a belief about the quality of those papers rather it is a belief about the hours and hours spent on writing them. This fundamental misconception about the value of labour lies at the root of Marx’s critique of capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hundreds of years, many economists believed that goods should be valued on the basis of the number of hours the labour spent to produce those goods. It was considered that any two goods that took the same time to be produced had the same value. This was termed as the ‘Labour Value of Theory’. One of the best-known advocates of this theory was Karl Marx. However, this theory has fallen out of favour among economists since the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory did have some superficial plausibility as it does seem that a good which involves a higher number of labour hours should be valued higher. However, the theory got increasingly complicated as it tried to explain some obvious objections. If we go by this theory the value of land should be nil, as there is no amount of labour that goes into ‘producing’ the land. What about the great pieces of art which hold hefty price tags, despite the fact that they do not require intense labour? What about the exorbitant prices paid to Michelin starred chefs? The theory failed to give a logical reason for these exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Marx, the labour value of theory lied at the center of the problems related to capitalism. The argument that capitalism exploited labourers depended crucially on the theory that labour was the source of all value-added, and that capitalists stole the profits from these labourers who deserved it more. According to him, capitalism destroyed our ability to enjoy the work that we do and forced us to work under their tyranny. Without the theory, Marx would have failed to justify the problems associated with capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It became increasingly difficult for the proponents of the theory to come up with logical explanations for the various exceptions to this theory. An individual’s skill set was completely ignored, it failed to account for the difference in the amount of time it takes for different individuals to perform a certain task. Moreover, it is clearly possible to spend a large amount of time on a product that ends up having no value eventually (something like a sandcastle). Additionally, goods that require the same amount of time to be produced should have the same market value, however, this is not always the case. Different goods have varying values in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition to the labour value of theory was proposed by Carl Menger when he stated that the value of goods is ‘subjective’. While the labour theory argued that the price of inputs determines the value of the final good, the subjectivist theory claimed that the value of a good is derived from the human perception of its usefulness. Value is not something that is objective or can be standardised for every person. It is a function of the role that an object plays in the plans of a certain human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, according to the subjectivists, land has value not because of the labour that goes into tilling it but because of the utility that people expect to derive out of it (such as growing crops to eat). People pay a high amount for solid coloured canvases not because of the painter’s efforts, but because of the beauty that they saw in the painting. Michelin starred restaurants are so pricey not because of the hours and hours that the chef spends in preparation of the food, but because of the satisfaction people get from eating that food. Therefore, the theory drew a line between the economic value of a good and the scientific value of the good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjective theory of value gave a new meaning to the value of labour: the value of inputs like labour depended on the value of outputs that they helped to produce. Hence, labour gets rewarded on the basis of producing things that others value. When you consider that combining labour with capital enables that labour to produce goods that others value, Marx’s arguments seem invalid. Capitalism, hence, provides tools to the labourers to produce valuable goods and thereby increases their remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, capitalism is basically a communication process through which humans try to make the best possible use of the limited resources available with them to satisfy their most urgent wants. Many academics are simply unaware of the fact. It depends on an individual what he values more, ‘quality’ or ‘quantity’.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Why are so many students convinced that they should get good grades just because they spent so many hours on a particular paper? It is not a belief about the quality of those papers rather it is a belief about the hours and hours spent on writing them. This fundamental misconception about the value of labour lies at the root of Marx’s critique of capitalism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?</title>
      <link href="/British-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?" />
      <published>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/British-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/British-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recently introduced skills-focused points-based immigration policy by PM Boris Johnson is going to have a huge impact on the economy. More than one-third of doctors, pharmacists, and dentists in the UK are foreign-born, as are more than 20% of nurses. Seven in 10 workers in the meat-processing industry are from the EU. However, next year onwards, the UK’s Byzantine immigration system for non-EU migrants will also apply to those from the EU. While immigration criteria for skilled labour will be loosened, it will be almost impossible for non-skilled labour to obtain a work visa. One of the hardest-hit sectors will be ‘care for’ the elderly. There is already a shortage of workers in this sector. Moreover, ‘care for’ work is the occupation with the most projected employment growth in the coming years. The UK under the guise of treating EU and non-EU migrants equally on the basis of skills is actually turning away industrious and enterprising individuals who help power its economy and provide for the basic needs of its greying population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the recent examples of what the British government is doing wrong. There are certain structural problems as well that need to be addressed. Capital spending as a share of GDP has fallen to around 17% from 20% in 2007. Capital investment is required in order to ensure long-term economic growth by increasing future production capacity. Moreover, the expenditure on R&amp;amp;D remains persistently below 2% of the GDP. In addition to this, the output per person has remained well below than what would have been termed as satisfactory. The unemployment figures have been relatively good recently, however, these have come at the cost of stagnating real wages and lower labour productivity per hour. Moreover, there has been a constant increase in the number of &lt;em&gt;zero-hour&lt;/em&gt; contracts. In such contracts, the workers have no guarantee of how many hours of work they will be getting. This could be one of the major reasons for under-employment in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2019, the manufacturing activity took a turn for the worse with the sharpest deterioration in output in more than seven years. The IHS Markit/CIPS manufacturing Purchasing Managers’ Index sank to 47.5 in December from 48.9 in November, although it was marginally higher than an initial flash estimate of 47.4. The figure marks the eighth consecutive month with a reading below 50, which indicates a majority of businesses reporting deteriorating activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has a large current account deficit as well. It was around 4.6% of the GDP in 2019. This has been majorly due to negative investor sentiments because of all the political instability. Also, the UK economy has been hit badly by the economic slowdown in the major trading partners, namely, China and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another worrying aspect is the monopoly power in public utility services like electricity and gas. A lack of competition keeps prices high and affects the real incomes of millions of consumers. Moreover, economic, social and demographic pressures continue to mount on public services such as the NHS. Some economists argue that the NHS needs a major injection of extra funding over the next 5-10 years; others believe that there are enough savings still to be achieved by addressing inefficiencies in public health care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With economic forecasts suggesting that the UK’s GDP growth won’t exceed 1.5%, the government will have to watch its discretionary spending even if a recession is avoided, because of spending on national services like the NHS. Moreover, there is also an additional threat to the economy posed by coronavirus. Much remains to be seen how the policymakers will tackle this burden and if the economy will be able to overcome this. The current situation doesn’t leave room for high hopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to plunging stock markets worldwide, the Bank of England cut its key rate by half a percentage point to 0.25%.  The Bank of England introduced a new program for cheap credit and reduced a special capital buffer to give banks more room to lend as well. Rishi Sunak, the Chancellor of the Exchequer,  also scrapped business rates for small firms to help them deal with the disruption caused by the outbreak of coronavirus. Business rates are taxes to help pay for UK local services, charged on most commercial properties. Britain’s retail sector has complained for the longest time that the current business rates system was unfair and needed reform. While the retail sector accounts for 5% of the UK economy, it is burdened with 10% of all business taxes, and 25% of business rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chancellor Sunak also scrapped a planned cut in corporation tax, and he is expected to raise around £6 billion from scrapping a planned drop, money he indicated could be spent on hospitals and doctors across the country. He also announced that the government would establish a coronavirus job retention scheme for all employers, large or small, that will cover 80% of wages, up to £2,500 a month. This scheme was introduced for an initial period of three months but can also be extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a month after stepping into the new job, Rishi Sunak has a lot to prove. There are a lot of expectations for the new Chancellor. Additionally, when the UK is facing an increasing threat from the coronavirus, his job becomes all the more important. It remains to be seen whether Rishi Sunak will break free of any puppet strings or be swept aside by a Treasury insider. Brexit coupled with the coronavirus outbreak has left the country on borrowed time to revamp the economy. What happens in the next few weeks could possibly define the future of the country in the coming years. What we need to wait and watch is whether the government and its policies fall into place in order to break free the shackles of a never-ending system of going back and forth.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
