<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/riya.kaul/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-09-05T09:30:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/riya.kaul/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree</title>
      <link href="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree" />
      <published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree">&lt;p&gt;The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some millennials, burdened by low-income jobs and debt obligations, living from paycheck to paycheck, are genuinely unable to finance stock purchases, the statistics tell us how even better-off millennials are straying away from investing and are preferring to save instead. Unfortunately, their risk-averse tendencies are miscalculated and are costing them precious returns, since the S&amp;amp;P 500 (adjusted for inflation and dividends reinvested) averaged a 7.92% return between 2007 to 2017, while the money market bank accounts averaged a 0.3% return during the same period. Nearly 42% of millennials are conservative investors, as opposed to 38% of GenXers and 23% of the Boomers. They are unwilling to fully embrace the financial markets, and when they do, it is only through a safer, less costly mechanism such as that of an Exchange Traded Fund (ETF), which is a type of fund that holds multiple underlying assets rather than a single stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worth noting is that their caution seems selective. Millennials’ risk-aversion appears to be more about scepticism when one realises how they have stayed away only from what they personally saw fail - the stock markets. They are still the ones responsible for inflating the crypto-market, despite its lack of intrinsic value or any ‘faith’ backing. The only argument in defense of their wild investment choice is perhaps the sophisticated distributed ledger technology used in the asset which makes the case for fostering technological innovation in the stock markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the politically correct environment, with encouragement from Hollywood, has put capitalism out of style for many. The ones still willing to invest have raised the bar over mere profitability when making an investment decision. Company ethics and transparency are a primary consideration for millennials when they choose to invest, and these additional filters reduce the overall amount invested. The rate of investment for women is in an even poorer state. The Harris Poll survey revealed that a staggering 79% of women do not invest at all, with 70% of them stating that the process is confusing to them, while 60% of them believing how they felt investing was ‘an old-white man’s game’. Clearly, the Millennials need a better education when it comes to managing their finances and getting over &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture is clear: Millennials are savers and not investors. 71% of Millennial workers are saving for retirement, and begin saving at the median age of 24, which puts the GenX’s median saving age of 30 to shame. And while they rely on the banks for saving, they try to keep away from availing any of the other services. A three year study from Scratch, an in-house unit of Viacom, as a part of the &lt;em&gt;Millennial Disruption Study&lt;/em&gt;, found that not only were banks among the ‘Most Hated’ brands, but a third of this demographic cohort believed that they’d be better off without them. This is a major concern for banks, who are now resorting to appeasement techniques. Providing special discounts on credit card bills and easing out the enrollment mechanism for loans are a few examples. This has also partially fueled the rise of fintech in the formal banking system and is encouraging the development of such technologies. Developing a system with a user-friendly interface and greater transparency by incorporation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning is an obvious solution to this issue. For instance,  a ZeroHedge survey revealed that one in three Millennials would rather invest in Bitcoin than in the stock market, simply because of the unconventional and futuristic technology involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that in traditional economics, the West had never been considered the saver’s economy, and this pattern is shifting for the better. The situation is quite akin to the rise in savings post the hyperinflationary periods in Germany after World War I, which incidentally was also a result of the psychological impact of the crisis. At the macro level, greater savings would imply lesser dependence on foreign investment. Lesser inflow of USD denominated investment in the USA implies lesser demand for the dollar. The consequent decline in appreciation of the USD is great for recovering the Current Account Deficit, which has been a primary long-term concern for the nation. But this advantage is dwarfed when growth concerns step in, as slowdowns are the projected case for the next few years. Additionally, with the rise of protectionist, right-wing governments around the globe, millennials are increasingly inclining towards what they think is socialism, which implies increased disinterest towards the financial markets. And that is a terrible prospect for growth. Hence, even though this demographic cohort has been through quite a lot at an impressionable age, they must put their concerns aside and take up a more rational approach. They have made a wise decision to save, considering the depleting ability of the burgeoning federal balance sheet to finance their post-retirement expenses. But they must learn to be comfortable with the idea of some risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream</title>
      <link href="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream" />
      <published>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream">&lt;p&gt;“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials …
has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion,
technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing
challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an
American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one
accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the
fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have
exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is
reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s
to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just
the generation gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest
hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore
the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then
aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation
in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when
they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny
scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s
common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five
years that follow graduation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even
comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen
not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young
graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits
of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score,
despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder
for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the
foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new
lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the
Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment
requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at
least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a
home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials
would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the
easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on
the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to
the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic
fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a
subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned
risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has
accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to
a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the
‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact,
they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a
result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the
rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their
savings, and further delays homeownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern
housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global
population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be
added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing
prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow
vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities
but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to
build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in
all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against
the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve,
whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because
the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover
costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism
(Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive
developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution,
rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not
only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc.,
but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an
especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a
combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps
people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India,
about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked,
“Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this
city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums.
Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford
monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent
settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they
actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two
flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3,
while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI
is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would
allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area,
and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for
Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city,
next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence
levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of
encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost
towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working
millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only
exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic
amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class
divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B.
Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the &lt;em&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/em&gt;,
had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the
cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every
petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays
them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they
manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they
must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the
sea.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials … has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion, technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.” Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just the generation gap. One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five years that follow graduation.  This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score, despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment requirements.  Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the ‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact, they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their savings, and further delays homeownership. But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve, whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism (Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution, rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties.  The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc., but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India, about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked, “Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums. Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3, while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area, and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city, next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like.  Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B. Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the Economic and Political Weekly, had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the sea.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It</title>
      <link href="/The-Middle-Income-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Middle-Income-Trap</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Middle-Income-Trap">&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Mahatyohar&lt;/em&gt; (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded
with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by
the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were
perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign.
Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of
6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a
decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which
explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as
compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put
more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have
pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations
can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a
part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could
indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the
National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue
of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He
identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what
the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to
lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per
capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has
become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges
from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the
economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good
industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states
that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with
by the government’s &lt;em&gt;PM Awas Yojana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PM Mudra Yojana&lt;/em&gt; schemes respectively,
it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate
the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re
becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital
development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that
we’re heading into. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation
makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but
then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation.
This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101
nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved
high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily
attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital,
lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is
comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been
exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely
crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being
channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar
to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour
is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages
are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the
current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of
Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of
high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s
demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour
supply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related
expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6%
required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its
restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like
&lt;em&gt;Startup India&lt;/em&gt;, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage
investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture
capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty
valuation of the startups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of
2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will
have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic
convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the
developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like
Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and
efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India,
who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour
and must now bear the consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the
early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers.
Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was
absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South
Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The
global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy
perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing
private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was
the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources
from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than
high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other
professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation.
Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human
capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater
urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic
demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because
becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital
account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently
undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the
politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically
left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive
foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment
destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that
before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations,
for capital is faithful to none.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While the Mahatyohar (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign. Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of 6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence. Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with by the government’s PM Awas Yojana and PM Mudra Yojana schemes respectively, it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that we’re heading into.  The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation. This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101 nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital, lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy.  Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour supply.  As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6% required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like Startup India, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty valuation of the startups.  An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of 2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India, who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour and must now bear the consequences.  The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers. Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation. Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater urgency. Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations, for capital is faithful to none.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Tale of Two Brothers</title>
      <link href="/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Brothers" />
      <published>2019-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CHINA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wedged between the Eastern Coast and the mainland of China, lies the ancient province of Zhongyuan. Historically renowned as the birthplace of the Chinese civilisation, it is home to a multitude of heritage sites ranging from the ruins of the Shang dynasty to the Eight Great Ancient Capitals of the nation. Its nearly-bygone eminence, in part, can be attributed to its fertile mainland, to the river Huang-He that runs through its veins, and perhaps, even to some of its women, like Lady Fu Hao who managed to bloom through the misogynistic past of the nation. Skip ahead a thousand years to the current millennium, and we find that much like the Ancient Greece, Zhongyuan is a graveyard of distant and glorious memories. Although it is now a set of vast agricultural lands with a reasonably efficient productivity level, it’s the demographic structure is quite the disaster. The sex ratio of the province, much more skewed than that of the entire nation, is at a startling 118 men for every 100 women. This implies that nearly one-fifth of the men may not find even a match for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ancient Chinese philosophy of contrasting a passive female principle (Yin) to an active male principle (Yang) for creating a complementary match is the base for the patriarchy that has dominated the traditional family structures in China, which must ideally be patrilineal and prescriptively virilocal. Despite the nation being colonised and later having been through a long regime of Communism, these basic traditions never changed for the common people. Mao Zedong’s antipathy to religion reshaped private beliefs but these traditions were so deep-rooted that they remained unscathed. And so, when the ‘One Child Policy’ was introduced in 1979 (or a decade prior for some parts of the nation), a natural preference for boys arose more predominantly in the countryside areas like Zhongyuan. This gave rise to the current situation of numerous Gen-Y ‘Bachelor Towns’ where men struggle to find wives, not only because there simply aren’t enough women but also because they’re being subjected to societal shaming, such as by being called ‘&lt;em&gt;guanggun&lt;/em&gt;’ or dead branches. On the other hand, the women have to both endure increasing sexual crimes, and take advantage of natural selection, which drives them to marry the higher educated men in the cities. The disparity, after two generations ageing without cousins and siblings, is so vast that many economists believe that retracting the policy in 2015 was a little too late to reestablish balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With hopes of a higher income, and a greater chance at finding a match, thousands of men move to the Pearl River Delta each day, which has nearly 60,000 factories employing 3-4 million people and has much role in making China &lt;em&gt;The World’s Factory&lt;/em&gt;. The Pearl Delta is primarily where all the rapid growth of China came from and where all its FDI went. The workforce is gender-neutral, and even though the balance has shifted from 70-30 in favour of women, to nearly 50-50 now, it still leaves sufficient room for couples to make and breakup at the assembly line each morning. The region additionally includes Shenzhen, the tech hub where the nation’s second stock exchange is situated. Shenzhen acts as an outlet for the labour to cater to the foreign investment projects that have recently been undertaken by China, with an increasing frequency, primarily in poor and middle-income nations of Southeast Asia and Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government’s ambitious programme to create the modern maritime silk route under the Belt and Road Initiative has been met by skepticism in the West, who have resorted to calling it ‘chequebook diplomacy’. But for China, these projects have rendered both a macroeconomic dominance and an unconventional solution to the gender problem, since the projects have eased not only China’s international relations, but also the visa requirements for its citizens to travel to these nations. Thus, many men from Zhongyuan, take on the months’ long journey to nations like Myanmar, Philippines, Indonesia and, recently, Pakistan, to set up a deal with local traffickers who can easily arrange for young women―whose parents willingly participate in such international betrothals in exchange for some money―and the hope for a better future for their daughters. An approximate cost of $10,000 is all it takes for these men to conform to the societal script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PAKISTAN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warmed by the wrath of the 1962 Sino-Indian War and the Cold War, the diplomatic relations between China and Pakistan bolstered through the years, and lately they come to be known as the ‘Iron Brothers’. Metaphorically speaking, both the brothers have grown in different directions, but factually, only one has moved for what we could call ‘growth’, while the other, i.e. Pakistan is struggling in a slough of debt. But China, being the generous brother that it is, has interceded to the rescue of Pakistan by making its international commercial initiative more inclusive through the China Pakistan Economic Corridor (CPEC). It is a project whose combined value was recently estimated to be $62 billion, which is greater than the total amount of FDI in Pakistan since 1970. The two-armed project will connect pipelines, roads and bridges via a 2700 km stretch to the deepwater ports at Karachi and Gwadar, where the latter will be redesigned to increase its cargo capacity from 1 million tonnes to 400 million tonnes, making it one of the most sophisticated ports to ever exist. It will additionally simulate much-needed growth in Pakistan. In fact, nearly $30 billion is dedicated to energy projects, which will generate 7000 MW of energy, contributing to 3% of Pakistan’s GDP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China too has much to gain from this brotherly affection, however. The most prominent underlying advantage being that it will be able to systematically bypass the maritime chokepoints of the South China Sea, and gain control of other strategic hotspots. This is why it is willing to risk venturing into the politically unstable regions of Baloch, Sindh and Khyber-Pakhtunkhwa, while the elite of Islamabad want to systematically cut Baloch out of the Gwadar equation. This marginalisation has partially fueled the rise of Balochi separatists, who recently attacked a bus full of Chinese engineers, prompting China to consider deploying its own troops in Pakistan for the protection of its workers. Considering the fragile situation of the Pakistani economy, with their Rupee falling by over 20% last year, paying off the debt has become even harder, while the forex reserves are below the $10 billion mark. An IMF bailout would pose conditions of coming clean with the CPEC books, and would compel Pakistan to expose the chequebook diplomacy, which is quite unlikely. So, in the foreseeable future, this ‘brotherhood’ is bound to strengthen, as more loans are lent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rising influx of Chinese men, who may not necessarily have a job, is owed to the visa-on-arrival policy for the ease of the Chinese people. Last year alone, over 91,000 Chinese people visited the country and 32,000 visas of Chinese nationals were extended. This has threatened the safety of the women in villages. Trafficking is a profitable business and the minorities, like the Christian community, are specifically targeted, since the Pakistani government is visibly unconcerned about them, as is reflected in the escape of Asia Bibi, the Christian woman who fled the nation after fearing death threats from ordinary citizens, even after she had been aquitted of blasphemy charges. The minorities also appeal to the Chinese men due to their ethnocentrist approach to the Muslim community, the proof being their tyrannical crackdowns on the local Uighur Muslim minority of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan’s Federal Investigation Agency (FIA) approximated that nearly 700 Christian and 300 Muslim women, many underage, were at risk of sexual slavery after falling for the pretext of marriage, as of 2018. Recently, Natasha Robin, 22, who was promised a life free of destitution, had agreed to marry a Chinese suitor whom she had met through an unlawful matchmaking agency. After twelve days of being subjected to the mental and physical torment of sex slavery, she managed to escape. Others have not been so lucky. This callousness of Pakistan towards its women may pose demographic threats to its own environment, since female infanticide is already prevalent and trafficking might further aggravate the sex ratio, which is already at a worrying 106 men per 100 women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggressive policy measures, for adherence to economic indicators, have often put the well being of the population at stake, China made this mistake and has ended up destabilising the sex ratio for the sake of ameliorating the demographic pressure. Pakistan is in pursuit of a disaster if doesn’t curb the illegal activities that accompany China’s growth agenda. It must reconsider if this brotherhood is in fact as mutually beneficial as China claims it to be. As for the people of Zhongyuan, who adulate their Supreme Leader Mao, it’s high time they act on one of his rare rational beliefs: ‘&lt;em&gt;Women hold up half the sky&lt;/em&gt;’. The next few months are crucial to see how the situation pans out further, whether in favour of the local population of the remote Pakistani areas, or the elite of Islamabad who concern themselves with fairly active policy measures to rebuild the economy whilst neglecting the ground-level work towards ensuring a safe and secure environment for their own people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">CHINA</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Inflation - Dead Or Dormant?</title>
      <link href="/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inflation - Dead Or Dormant?" />
      <published>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant">&lt;p&gt;The US Federal Reserve, in its recent Open Market Operations Committee Meeting, chose an ambiguous stance by leaving the federal funds rate unchanged at the range of 2.25-2.5%, much to the dismay of the markets and the Government, who long awaited a rate cut. As the growth rates declined across Europe, China and US in Q1 2019, the Fed was expected to finally move away from the rate hikes, which were also offsetting the fiscal concessions provided by the US government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This monetary tightening began in late 2015, as an attempt to counter the inflation that was expected in the aftermath of using heterodox mutations like Quantitative Easing (QE) to recover demand in the largest Post-War Recession of 2008. While the Fiscal Policy has become increasingly pro-cyclical in the recent (Trump) years, the hawkish Monetary Policy attempts to counter the inflation that is already locked far behind its 2% benchmark, which has resulted in the Trump’s disapproval of Jerome Powell (thus, the threats of replacing him with political cronies like Herman Cain). The low expected inflation has not only caused the recessionary air to resurface but has also invited wild justifications for credibility restoration. Fed’s Loretta Mester recently went as far as to claim that the economy has finally reached its equilibrium in her (neo)classic defense of the recent speculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of the justifications explained why inflation is globally stifled for the developed economies despite the rising-but-low rates. The observation remains that the Monetary Policy is losing grip over the rate of inflation. Prices are no longer as sensitive to the interest rates as they used to be, thus, explaining the recent surge in various financial forums pronouncing inflation dead, attributing it mainly to technological advancements. In times of prosperity, inflation is high due to the increased productivity and employment, which gives the workforce the ability to bargain for greater wages, that will push up the costs and then the prices. With improved technology and reduced labour intensity, the ability of the workers to demand greater wages during an upswing has declined. Additionally, the prophecy paradox, that embodies the self-fulfilling nature of expectations in economics, comes to play. The general level of expected inflation in the markets is low which is seen to be taking its effect on the actual figures, and though these expectations are being publicized as a reflective of the credibility of the Fed, they certainly don’t go in tandem with the economic or the fiscal cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the major setback has been taken by the theory of the Phillips curve, which describes the inverse relationship between inflation and unemployment via the cost-wage spiral. This relation was violated once back in the 70s when stagflation hit the American economy. It was chiefly blamed at the rising oil prices, when in fact it was the abolition of Bretton Woods by Nixon that took a toll on the economy. Though its collapse provided the US with a monetary policy that extended beyond the clasp of the Special Drawing Rights, it immediately resulted in inflation which was previously limited to the $35/ounce gold peg. In order to tackle the inflation, the government bought in price controls which reduced the profitability of businesses, and ended up in large scale layoffs. But this direct relation had helped Milton Friedman in developing a long run perspective to the theory, and concluding that in the long run, the Phillips curve is vertical. In the short-run, however, there is sufficient scope for monetary policy to smooth out fluctuations around the independent pathway of potential output by affecting cyclical unemployment and price levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curve has currently flattened, and this relation is no longer as strong for the developed economies as it used to be, considering how unemployment is presently at 3.9% in the USA, below its natural rate that stands at 4%, but inflation has shown no signs of a revival. A similar pattern had been witnessed right before the tech bubble had burst. This flattening of the curve is possibly a structural problem, not amenable to macroeconomic measures and it reduces the capability of the Central Banks to reach their inflation targets. But if the theory still survives, it could only mean that the Fed anticipates a pending risk for the inflation to resurface, for which the rate hikes, under the alias of a ‘friendly normalisation’, are being pursued. Perhaps inflation is not dead, but dormant and potentially on a rise, although it is ‘inflation targeting’ that might be officially dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this inflation-interest rate relation, which is hardly ever questioned, was never a strong one, to begin with. J.Stiglitz asserts &lt;em&gt;“this rudimentary method is based on a weak economic theory and little empirical evidence…and there is no reason to believe that, whatever the source of inflation, the best solution is to raise interest rates.”&lt;/em&gt; The Central Banks have been over-relying on the Monetary Policy for every minor inconvenience as if it is a panacea for the dearth of aggregate demand. And why not? It’s the easiest way out, 2008 stands witness. But that is if we remain unreasonably adamant on the “In the long run, we’re all dead” approach. While the Fiscal Policy, despite its implementation imperfections, attempts to systematically address the economic issues at their core, the monetary policy has been globally reduced to an interest fluctuation switch, whose volatility takes its toll on its own ability. It is an important but overexploited tool that was ideally supposed to address the Dual Mandate on both price stability and employment issues through a suitable policy mix, but there seems to be no coordination among the fiscal and the monetary policy. The past few centuries stand witness to the fact that no monetary system has stood firm for over 50 years, citing the changes that the monetary policy faced in 1913, 1933, 1945 and 1971. And considering its ageing ability to address inflation, people have already started coming up with alternatives to the existing system, the most prominent one being the Modern Monetary Theory (MMT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a fringe economic model, MMT stems out of the monetary theory of Marx, which later seems to have influenced Keynes, and is nowadays gaining mainstream attention, such as being proposed for financing the Green New Deal by Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez. It basically states that a country with its own currency can simply pay off its debt by printing more currency. The idea would seem questionable even to a layman, but this is only true if the debt is denominated in the domestic currency, which though is not the case for most of the nations, it’s certainly applicable for the USA as an advantage of USD being the major global reserve currency. This theory is often criticised for its utter disregard for the size of the deficits and the impact on inflation, but it does address these issues by manipulating the revenue side. Additionally, being a brain-child of the left doesn’t imply that it will not be accepted by the right since it can just as easily help in financing tax cuts. Major investors such as Ray Dalio, who feed off of capitalism, have stated that something like MMT will inevitably be replacing the Central Banks. In fact, MMT appears to be the only way to elude the burgeoning debt and the declining credibility of the Fed. It will help finance the fiscal profligacy every US government has inherited from its fear of lobbyists, be it progressive or conservative. Either way, it might ameliorate the system after the hawks have devoured what’s left of their monetary policy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The US Federal Reserve, in its recent Open Market Operations Committee Meeting, chose an ambiguous stance by leaving the federal funds rate unchanged at the range of 2.25-2.5%, much to the dismay of the markets and the Government, who long awaited a rate cut. As the growth rates declined across Europe, China and US in Q1 2019, the Fed was expected to finally move away from the rate hikes, which were also offsetting the fiscal concessions provided by the US government.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
