<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/riya.kaul/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-15T08:53:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/riya.kaul/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Emmanuel Farhi’s Safety Trap</title>
      <link href="/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emmanuel Farhi’s Safety Trap" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap">&lt;p&gt;Emmanuel Farhi, considered by many to be the brightest economist of his generation, passed away in July 2020, aged only 41. Farhi, a PhD from Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and amongst the youngest to receive tenure as Professor at Harvard University, was known to challenge traditional economic concepts that people would often take as given. Take, for example, one of his most cited works,  &lt;em&gt;The Safe Asset Shortage Conundrum&lt;/em&gt;, written on safe assets and the lack thereof, in 2008 with Ricardo Caballero of MIT and Pierre-Oliver Gourinchas of UC Berkeley. This paper augmented Keynes’ classical theory of the ‘Liquidity Trap’ and developed it to suit the modern connotation of capital markets, and is more relevant now than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world seemed to have reasonably recovered from the short run curable shocks of the Great Financial Crisis of 2008 by 2018-19, when many first-world nations, including the world’s de-facto economic capital, the US, were considered to have achieved ‘full employment’. There was, however, something anomalistic about this status, when despite high productivity, inflation seemed suppressed. This &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant&quot;&gt;dormant status of inflation&lt;/a&gt;, often explained by the unorthodox policy measures taken for recovery, has evidently trickled into the prolonged COVID-19 induced recession. Monetary policy as a tool might appear crippled at this point, with nominal rates reaching their zero levels bound in most first-world economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventional jargon would explain the situation as follows: what has basically happened in this liquidity trap is the flattening of our LM curve (a curve showing the relationship between real output and interest rates in the money market), a consequence of a high ‘h’ (which is the proportion of change in money demand, when the interest rates change by a percent). In classical (Keynesian) economic sense though, the policy decision is to change the money supply first, and the interest rate change is a consequence of that. Once a decision to increase the money supply, in hopes to revive demand, is implemented, it is accompanied by an equal increase in money demand in order for the market to equilibrate. Money demand, without an increase in income levels, can only rise if the interest rate moves down. But in case of a high ‘h’, a negligible downward movement of rates should be able to compensate for the money demand increase. Coming back to the real world, where money demand is adjusted by moving the nominal interest rates, such a scenario would render the monetary policy useless, once the zero levels bound of interest rates is reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conventional solution to this dilemma, as given by Keynes in &lt;em&gt;The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money&lt;/em&gt; was to make gracious use of fiscal policy in a targeted manner. But as concerns of deficit consolidation popped up, economists at the Fed came up with other heterodox mutations of conventional monetary policy to tackle the issue. It wasn’t until Farhi’s paper on ‘Safety Traps’ was published that the policymakers found a more logical chain of response to the problem. A certain category of assets, often considered immune in periods of depressed market spirits, is called ‘Safe Assets’. During recessions, their markets evidently boom leading to price hikes and consequent fall in the yields. But the yields have a lower bound of zero percent, beyond which they cannot fall, and therefore prices cannot rise. This situation of people acting in private interest, leading to a net consequence of a market failure is a classic example of ‘Fallacy of Composition’. This happens since the asset market does not equilibrate in response to the high demand. And due to nominal rigidities, this equilibrium manifests in the form of output reduction. The output during recessionary periods is entirely demand determined, and the 0-yield on the safe assets is not low enough to encourage agents to move towards consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically the solutions offered to do away with this complication include negative interest rates, forward guidance, quantitative easing, etc. However, in his paper, Farhi accounted for the fact that the market rates do not uniformly equilibrate across all assets, and a certain risk premium remains attached to equity assets, while the safe ones get to zero. This tends to dilute the policy impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we want as our end result, is that despite the high ‘Safe Asset’ demand, we generate enough supply to ensure the yields do not get to zero and there is some scope to utilise the monetary policy. This sudden paucity of safe assets is often attributed to a savings glut, accumulation of reserves by the emerging markets, and to the fact that many assets which shaped the housing market bubble were once considered safe, but were not so at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One popular policy response which was an attempt to untie the hands of monetary policy, but failed to an extent was ‘Quantitative Easing’, which allowed the Fed to pump up the market with fresh money supply while purchasing bonds in return. This measure would not revive demand to its potential if safe assets are the ones being purchased in its return. This is because a proportion of the newly printed money will look for more safe assets, which have now shrunk in supply! Instead, soaking up the risky assets in return for the newly printed money, while simultaneously issuing newer safety assets is the proper way to go about quantitative easing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forward guidance, by ensuring to keep the future rates low was also said to work, because, if the Government’s word on the policy is reliable, lower future yields will imply higher future asset prices, creating current demand for the assets. When the self-fulfilling prophecy works out, the wealth effect naturally generates demand. However, Farhi’s paper found out the misconceptions associated with the effectiveness of this policy. If assets are seen in terms of the two designated classes, then it is likely that the risky assets, with a positive risk premium, will dissipate the impact of anticipated lower rates, and the effect will not trickle to revive the output market. However, one measure that is likely to render the monetary policy free is creating a very high inflation target, which would then allow the economy to run on an output-inducing negative real rate while being on the 0-nominal rate. But then again, this has its long-run ramifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of a high-risk premium is concrete evidence for the existence of a ‘safety trap’, rather than a liquidity trap. It is indicative of the fact that people are rushing towards safe assets, while equity returns remain stable and decoupled from the economic situation, as is the current case. A fiscal policy response by issuing sovereign bonds to address the scarcity of safe assets is now being encouraged with the popularisation of the ‘Modern Monetary Theory’, though Farhi considered the US’ role as the world’s banker to be unsustainable due to higher issuance of sovereign bonds leading many to question their debt levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this paper played an instrumental role in forwarding the scope of the monetary policies of the first world countries, Emmanuel Farhi’s other papers are just as revolutionary, if not as cited. In another one of his works, &lt;em&gt;Dealing with the Trilemma: Optimal Capital Controls with Fixed Exchange Rates&lt;/em&gt; he challenged the ‘Impossible Trinity’ by providing partial capital controls as a solution for emerging markets battling the exchange rate volatility. His research is a perfect amalgamation of academia and policy solutions, and he truly believed that research only made sense when it could be put in real service towards progress. Safe to say that the world of academics and research was in for a shock on his passing on the 23rd of July, 2020. Gita Gopinath, a fellow colleague at Harvard, poignantly wrote, &lt;em&gt;“Imagine the loss to economics if Samuelson had died at the age of 41, that is what we have lost with Emmanuel’s passing”&lt;/em&gt;. His best was truly yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Emmanuel Farhi, considered by many to be the brightest economist of his generation, passed away in July 2020, aged only 41. Farhi, a PhD from Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and amongst the youngest to receive tenure as Professor at Harvard University, was known to challenge traditional economic concepts that people would often take as given. Take, for example, one of his most cited works, The Safe Asset Shortage Conundrum, written on safe assets and the lack thereof, in 2008 with Ricardo Caballero of MIT and Pierre-Oliver Gourinchas of UC Berkeley. This paper augmented Keynes’ classical theory of the ‘Liquidity Trap’ and developed it to suit the modern connotation of capital markets, and is more relevant now than ever.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">India-China Feud: To Boycott or Not?</title>
      <link href="/India-China-Feud" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="India-China Feud: To Boycott or Not?" />
      <published>2020-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/India-China-Feud</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/India-China-Feud">&lt;p&gt;As the world battles the wrath and economic standstill that has emanated from the COVID-19 pandemic, geopolitical tensions have soared in East Asia along the non-delineated borders of India and China. The altercations that ensued between the two nations, along the historically peaceful region of the Galwan River Valley, peaked in mid-June when China attempted to unilaterally change the status quo by violating the sovereignty of the Line of Actual Control (LAC). While the LAC, unlike the Line of Control (LoC) between India and Pakistan, remains non-demarcated and hasn’t been internationally agreed upon, it has ironically sustained relative peace. However, the 2020 skirmishes resulted in 20 casualties on the Indian side while China is said to have lost an unconfirmed number, despite the clash being restrained with no use of bullets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China has been globally targeted for its neocolonialist approach over the past decade, be it through cheque-book diplomacy as in the case of Sri Lanka, or through blatant expansionist policies, as in the current scenario. When India refused to participate in the first Belt and Road Initiative summit in May 2017, it practically refused to fall for the former approach and became a hindrance to China’s grand geopolitical strategy, resulting in the orchestrated Doklam standoff that followed a month later, in June 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bears weak resemblance to the current scenario, wherein the export consignment of faulty medical equipment by nationalised Chinese pharmaceutical companies and the possibility of COVID-19 being an engineered bioweapon has turned global sentiments against the Chinese economy in general. As a consequence, global investment portfolio rebalancing is expected. Additionally, many major MNCs realised that they had put too many eggs in one basket, and are looking to move their production units to South Asia, where India stands waiting in anticipation with lucrative policies. This speculation has prevailed since the US-China trade war began but has been concretised over the past quarter, leading many to believe that this was as much of motivation behind the violation of the de-facto border as the local territorial integrity. While peace is the prioritised goal, the primary objective for India remains to restore the status quo ante, leading to prolonged conflict. Since both nuclear powers ascribe to the ‘no first use’ policy, the dispute has permeated into the economic foreground leading to calls for a strategic boycott.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discord comes at an opportune time for China, as India closes to the peak of COVID-19 and faces a fragile and vulnerable state of affairs. The financial markets have rallied temporarily, and have, since February, gone through the Denial-FOMO (fear of missing out) cycle identified by Robert Shiller in the American markets, which can be loosely extrapolated to fit the Indian scenario. Once again, the stock market appears to be considerably decoupled from the state of the economy which is said to be headed towards depression. In such a situation, the escalation of bilateral tensions with a nation that accounts for over 16% of total imports and 9% of total exports of India is seemingly not a viable course of action. Although, as proclaimed by many, the boycott, if successful, will not be entirely harmless, and ironically, this is the best time to put it to action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India majorly imports organic chemicals and electrical machinery from China to be used as raw materials in the Indian industries. Both can be procured from separate sources, at slightly higher prices, which might interfere with pharmaceutical price control regulations in case of organic chemicals. But hiking import duties on non-essentials is definitely a doable move at this juncture when the fall in imports is much larger than the fall in exports due to slowdown in industrial activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as the nation proceeds to unlock and the economic cycle initiates, it is unlikely that businesses will be able to afford the switch and diversify their supply chains. Ideally, the graph of the India-China trade balance mapped as a function of the timeline since the initiation of a (successful) boycott should take a familiar tilted J-shape, with the curve beginning in the negative-Y (deficit for India) threshold. The initial crater of the J-curve is owed to the inelasticity of demand, and the deficits might worsen when the economy reopens and imports rise from their current low levels. Eventually, as the demand revives, and (if and only if) the businesses remain encouraged to diversify their supply chains, the boycott may be considered successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the argument remains that this will be more of a diplomatic win rather than an economic one. In order to play this strategically and move towards what Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calls an &lt;em&gt;‘Atma Nirbhar’&lt;/em&gt; (self-dependent) India, free of import dependence, one must play for the long haul. China became the world’s factory because of its extremely cheap wages, but it managed to remain so despite the 8,500% wage increase since the past 30 years, solely due to its simplified policy framework. Chapter - 6, Volume - 1 of the Indian Economic Survey 2020, elaborates poignantly how China fairs better than India in virtually all the parameters of the Ease of Doing Business Index by the World Bank. The complications involved in acquiring construction permits, licenses, and the magnitude of applicable rules and statutory laws for manufacturing are quite overwhelming for any business to venture into India. Although there have been underrated reforms like the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code of 2016 that have been revolutionary in disciplining the attitude of businesses towards their sources of finance, we still need a major revamping of the legal system of the nation in order to strengthen contract enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another pertinent question that we need to ask ourselves is that even if the global economy permits, are we ready to become net exporters even in the long run? India’s growth story has always been driven by local consumption power, which is also skewed towards import-intensive goods. That leaves little room for domestic savings, leaving us prying for FDI, and that demand is honoured since India is a favourable destination during prosperous periods owing to the lucrative emerging market grade returns. A country can have either a net current account surplus or a capital account surplus, we face the latter case. China faces the former, by its choice. It even resorted to the old currency devaluation tactic back in 2019, when the trade war with the US began to frustrate the officials with threats of taking away the current account surplus. This surplus is precious to China due to the grand strategy of foreign capital investment it has undertaken under its neocolonialist approach. But India cannot steal both the FDI and the exports of China, that would go against macroeconomic fundamentals. This is practically why many have opposed the idea of a boycott and called for more government focus on rearing natural competition while reaping the advantages of smooth FDI. It is eventually up to the government to prioritise and strike an ideal balance between diplomatic and economic victories, which may not go hand in hand in the short run.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the world battles the wrath and economic standstill that has emanated from the COVID-19 pandemic, geopolitical tensions have soared in East Asia along the non-delineated borders of India and China. The altercations that ensued between the two nations, along the historically peaceful region of the Galwan River Valley, peaked in mid-June when China attempted to unilaterally change the status quo by violating the sovereignty of the Line of Actual Control (LAC). While the LAC, unlike the Line of Control (LoC) between India and Pakistan, remains non-demarcated and hasn’t been internationally agreed upon, it has ironically sustained relative peace. However, the 2020 skirmishes resulted in 20 casualties on the Indian side while China is said to have lost an unconfirmed number, despite the clash being restrained with no use of bullets.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Private Data: A Public Good?</title>
      <link href="/Private-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Private Data: A Public Good?" />
      <published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Private-Data</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Private-Data">&lt;p&gt;While global economies have sent their growth-obsessed capitalistic policy approach on a hiatus for the year, with even the disgraced dragon dropping its annual economic growth targets for the first time since the 1990’s, the competitive aspect of the battle against COVID-19 has not left the grounds of policy-making. Taiwan has surfaced as a recent beneficiary of the comparative analysis initiated by global media houses. The nation is being rightfully lauded for managing to contain the current number of active cases under 500, despite its close proximity and intimate relations with China, the epicentre of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides proper screening, increasing testing capacity and mass insurance, the nation implemented a dynamic containment plan that required the government to partner with the local telecom operators in order to ensure that suspects were properly quarantined by tracking their GPS locations. The surveillance is said to be so precise that one asymptomatic carrier claimed via Twitter that the local police arrived at his doors within half an hour when he accidentally switched off his phone in the early morning hours, back in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During ordinary times, even a mild parliamentary discussion on tracking private data by the government would have been globally marketed as a sign of the nation becoming a digital dictatorship. However, the current crisis has demonstrated that perhaps drawing inferences from private data and using them as a public good has benefits that exceed the costs involved, while simultaneously upholding the privacy of individuals. (A public good is a non­-excludable, non-rivalrous good, i.e., individuals may consume without paying for it and one individual’s consumption does not hinder that of the other individuals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to correctly recognise the benefits of private data as a public good, one must acknowledge that the lack of information is a fundamental economic problem, in the non-textbook economic setup. Lack of resources then becomes a secondary issue in policy making, since a data inference needs to be drawn first to decide the direction of redistribution before subjecting it to any resource constraints. Often policymakers resolve the information problem by statistical sampling which is in itself expensive. Data can become quickly outdated which may lead to non-representative samples and other specification errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when digitalisation comes into the picture, it brings in better solutions to the information problem. It assists not only in policymaking but also in enforcing free-market equilibrium in certain markets by increasing the degree of market efficiency and allowing smoother real-time price discovery mechanisms, thus minimising distortions. An example would be E-NAM (Electronic National Agricultural Market), the online trading platform for agricultural goods, launched by the Indian government, which now has a membership of nearly 4.5 million farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other indirect and more relevant advantages of digitalisation include the large scale database of the digital footprints of a population. Presently, smartphones have become a very accessible device in even developing and emerging nations. The data generated by these devices is mainly with the concerned individual’s telecom operator, as well as other private parties that collect data from the users who install their mobile applications, e.g. Google, Facebook, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the private app developers have facilitated the birth of controversial practices like that of surveillance capitalism, by utilising the competitive edge provided in advertising avenues, the data generated can still be deemed an instrumental tool in studying various macro-level indicators about the population. For instance, by studying the pathway of the telecom antennae one’s device was connected to, one can easily track the real-time mobility of a population and generate migration patterns. Upon analysing the frequency and multitude of online transactions made in a certain period, one can even concretise their hypothesis about the direction of the economy in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If governments, like that of Taiwan, consistently manage to extract benefits out of aggregates of anonymised private data, they can manage to do so without violating individual rights as well as without robbing private benefactors off of the competitive edge generated by the data. The Economic Survey 2019, published by the Indian government, rightfully stated that data is of the people, for the people, and by the people. It acknowledged the lack of clarity and sophistication in the law specifying the ownership of data and elaborated upon the need to take advantage of the multitude of data that is generated. Due to data explosion, the marginal costs of data storage have fallen drastically, with one-gigabyte storage requiring a mere ₹3.48 now, as compared to ₹61,000 back in 1981.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even dissemination costs are negligible owing to real-time transfers over the internet. The marginal benefits, which include evidence-based policymaking, targeted implementation of the same and augmentation of accountability, easily outweigh the costs involved. Of course, in order for these benefits to be realised, there needs to be uniformity in the data circulated. Many schemes have already been launched as an initiative to merge data, such as the ‘Samagra Vedika’ initiative by the Telangana State government in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concerns about privacy are certainly valid since once the government gets its hands on the data; it may do with it as it pleases, which is why better laws need to be in place. Private data is very intimate individually, but collectively, it generates great value for the society, and hence, it is important to provide the data in an anonymised and aggregated form to the government. In the light of COVID-19, greater weight is added to the argument of involving public officials in the picture, not simply because we must track the cases and localise the spread, but also because it will help in conducting future studies to deduce patterns and give early warning signs. The debate is ongoing, but it is high time we make use of the data that is at our disposal to its full potential, in a manner that aligns with the population’s core values about the issue.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While global economies have sent their growth-obsessed capitalistic policy approach on a hiatus for the year, with even the disgraced dragon dropping its annual economic growth targets for the first time since the 1990’s, the competitive aspect of the battle against COVID-19 has not left the grounds of policy-making. Taiwan has surfaced as a recent beneficiary of the comparative analysis initiated by global media houses. The nation is being rightfully lauded for managing to contain the current number of active cases under 500, despite its close proximity and intimate relations with China, the epicentre of the crisis.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fiscal Consolidation: The Choice Between Prudence and Progress</title>
      <link href="/Fiscal-Consolidation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fiscal Consolidation: The Choice Between Prudence and Progress" />
      <published>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Fiscal-Consolidation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fiscal-Consolidation">&lt;p&gt;The growth projections for 2020-21 are in, and to hardly anyone’s surprise, it does not look good. It is during times like these, that the age-old ‘Growth vs Welfare’ debates are resurrected. However, as the pandemic curves around the globe get close to flattening themselves, it is only pragmatic to acknowledge that once we pass these anomalistic times, both variables will once again walk hand in hand. The ones monitoring the movements of these variables have assigned a downward revision to the targeted estimates. The recovery speculated to be V-shaped, will lead us through a phase of growth rates as low as -3%, as projected by the IMF, under the assumption that the pandemic fades by the second half of 2020. Governments, too politically motivated, cannot engage in conducting indirect bail-outs just yet, in the increasingly left sympathising world. So, the Central Banks around the globe have stepped in to stretch their balance sheets as usual. Besides the regular rate cuts, nations like the US, where rates have reached the zero base, have resorted to heterodox ways of stimulating the stock markets. The indices, taking mixed signals from the $4 trillion QE influx, and the climbing unemployment rate, close to 8%, have managed to rally against the odds. Other nations follow the lead as they ease out withdrawal norms, EMI payments, etc., attempting to bring a disequilibrium to the trade-off between consumption expenditure and investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India, while still expected to grow at 1.9%, has not attempted to take up any targeted policy measures, save for the Prime Minister Garib Kalyan Scheme, which isn’t an economically motivated initiative. As a result of lack of productivity, the revenue side of the federal budget has nearly entirely collapsed, with states urging the centre to transfer resources sooner as 70% of the revenue via GST streams has ceased. It is evident that the fiscal deficit target of 3% set under the Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management (FRBM) Act (2003) will be violated by a bold margin, giving the markets another reason to panic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need for a consumption-driven nation like India to keep the deficits in check arises from its reliance on foreign investments, due to the dearth of local savings. This stringency gets rationalised by the validation it receives from the economists grumbling at the nation’s twin balance sheet problem, i.e., both fiscal deficit and a trade deficit, which basically arises from running fiscal deficits by cutting taxes. That causes consumption to rise and thus, savings to fall. A reduction in savings prompts the government to borrow funds from abroad to finance their fiscal expenditure. An influx of investment raises the demand for local currency, which in turn results in its appreciation, and that makes domestic commodities relatively expensive to purchase, thus causing a trade deficit, which transforms into a current account deficit. It can be explained mathematically through a simple equation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y = C + I + G + NX can be written as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Y - C - Tax + Transfer) + (Tax - G - Transfer) = I + NX, which signifies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private Savings + Public Saving = Domestic Investment + Net Foreign Investment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine a decline in Public Savings, due to cutting taxes and causing a fiscal deficit. This can be offset by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Rise in Private Savings&lt;/strong&gt;: As per “Ricardian equivalence”, tax cuts prompt people to increase savings, because they expect taxes to rise in the future. This, though economically ideal, is unlikely in the real-life context of the non-rational people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Fall in Domestic Investment&lt;/strong&gt;: The crowding-out effect, it’s never good.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Fall in the Net foreign Investment&lt;/strong&gt;: The Twin Deficits dilemma&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India’s case 2) &amp;amp; 3) have happened more often than any growing economy would be comfortable with. Several economies that are a member of the twin deficits club are the US, UK, Greece, etc. So, it’s safe to say we’re certainly not in great company since the twin deficits in each of these economies have aggravated the impacts of recessions, even cyclical ones. Though as many believe so, we have not managed to escape a crisis while running twin deficits. The 1991 Balance of Payments (BoP) crisis was essentially that of the twin deficits, owed to years of profligacy and the fiscal crisis of the 1980s. Post the FRBM Act, the deficits did come under targets, but the actual figures remained higher as certain bonds were kept off the balance sheets and remained unaccounted for, rendering the actual adjusted figures higher by 0.5% to 1% from what was reported. However, over the decade, with the combination of FRBM guidelines and the Rajan-era monetary policy, we have restrained the fiscal deficit partially and managed to raise enough Forex reserves to keep the Current Account deficits controlled. Additionally, as we move closer to having a higher proportion of capital expenditures, as compared to the previous budgets, we are setting up a base for investment to crowd in rather than crowd out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fiscal consolidation is necessary when the BoP situation is volatile and reliance on international investment is high. However, for an emerging nation like India, it’s irrational to take the 3% target as a divine ordinance. We would only end up creating a psychological benchmark out of it, exacerbating the volatility in exercises over our markets in recessionary periods. Fiscal prudence makes sense in good times to develop a cushion for bad times and allow targeted policies to take over the recovery. Blindly restricting expenditure ends up being counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The growth projections for 2020-21 are in, and to hardly anyone’s surprise, it does not look good. It is during times like these, that the age-old ‘Growth vs Welfare’ debates are resurrected. However, as the pandemic curves around the globe get close to flattening themselves, it is only pragmatic to acknowledge that once we pass these anomalistic times, both variables will once again walk hand in hand. The ones monitoring the movements of these variables have assigned a downward revision to the targeted estimates. The recovery speculated to be V-shaped, will lead us through a phase of growth rates as low as -3%, as projected by the IMF, under the assumption that the pandemic fades by the second half of 2020. Governments, too politically motivated, cannot engage in conducting indirect bail-outs just yet, in the increasingly left sympathising world. So, the Central Banks around the globe have stepped in to stretch their balance sheets as usual. Besides the regular rate cuts, nations like the US, where rates have reached the zero base, have resorted to heterodox ways of stimulating the stock markets. The indices, taking mixed signals from the $4 trillion QE influx, and the climbing unemployment rate, close to 8%, have managed to rally against the odds. Other nations follow the lead as they ease out withdrawal norms, EMI payments, etc., attempting to bring a disequilibrium to the trade-off between consumption expenditure and investing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Art, the Artist and the Investor</title>
      <link href="/Art-Artist-Investor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art, the Artist and the Investor" />
      <published>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Art-Artist-Investor</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Art-Artist-Investor">&lt;p&gt;Creativity has its own timeline, and art can only blossom through experience and patience. It takes its own sweet time getting through to people letting the art ripen naturally, instead of spoon-feeding its patrons, and is usually a mark of the artist’s authenticity. Take Van Gogh or Kafka, for instance, with both dying in ignorance of the ingenuity of their works. Their patience, or rather underconfidence, eventually led to the posthumous recognition, capitalised on by whoever could claim to ignite the inspiration, rendering their lives analogous to a sad art film, that yet still, managed to inspire people further. But not every artist wants to make a sad art film of their lives. It isn’t simply about the lack of patience or existence of confidence to market their work, it is, quite often, about &lt;em&gt;survival&lt;/em&gt;. Putting all stakes in an industry that isn’t entirely welcoming to new works due to their abstract nature is certainly a dicey choice for one’s career. Looking for popular platforms that can get you eyeballs is only natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These platforms are the ones that claim to ‘discover’ the artists, and subsequently, capitalise on the lifetime of earnings through their artwork. Take the music industry, for example. Artists still make their music, but that is not exactly how they make their money. The commercialisation of the records by label companies has been in place for decades now. Singers would only get a proportion of the sales revenue generated when new music would be released, which is only fair. Associating a famous record label’s name with the music of a new artist is a high-risk position to take business-wise, and hence it’s only natural to expect higher returns. Labels own master recordings, the copyrights associated and the back catalogues of artists. These assets are owned to compensate them in exchange for the risks taken by the platform in financing the artists’ careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in the 80’s &amp;amp; 90’s, the transparency of record deals wasn’t exactly crystal clear, both record labels and the singers managed to make good money because their primary source of revenue was the literal sale of the songs via CDs, vinyl records, etc. Currently, the music sales revenue, though growing, in absolute terms, by nearly $1 billion per year, is only about 60% of what it was in 1999. The industry took its major hit post the year 2000 when internet services began illegally offering easy access to the free download of music. The advent of pirated downloading of music drove down the record sales and seemingly marked a Malthusian-style prophecy of the end of the commercialised and profitable era. That was until the streaming platforms stepped in. Although a third of the global music listeners still pirate their music (as per a report by the International Federation of Phonographic Industry), a massive rise in legal streaming platforms like Spotify, Apple Music and Tidal seems to have curbed the illegal consumption of music. And while the revenues and the contract transparency is on the rise, the monetary credit accrued to the actual artists has fallen with the steepening of the industry’s growth trajectory. Private equity (PE) players have stepped in to invest in the record labels, adding complicated layers to the revenue distribution model, and thus, leaving even lower residual amount that goes to the singers. Now, how do these big-money investors in PE corporates that, at the very least, expect consistency in their returns, align themselves with an industry that has its own volatile timeline? They &lt;em&gt;undershare&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The labels now provide to the artists a platform, and that’s nearly all. An estimate suggests that an average artist gets around one-tenth of a cent per play of an associated song on Spotify. The streaming platform generally takes up 15-30% of the revenue generated, and then a major chunk is instantly slashed off in the name of the record label. At this point, less than 40% of the revenue remains before singers, songwriters or publishers. The final average payout is dependent on how much ownership of the master recordings and the compositions the artists can exert. To put it into perspective, a star as big as Beyoncé makes only 10% of her money through music sales. One would think that music tours and concerts ought to make up for the deficiencies, but they’re simply a marketing programme, an attempt to keep the artists relevant, which becomes evident once you realise that rarely do any of the global or national level tour revenues ever break-even. The artists are paid only a proportional royalty of any other public performance not financed by the label, but by talk-shows or award shows. The payment structure often leaves the singers earning off of advertisements and endorsements, robbing them of their ‘authenticity’ tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the highest-paid pop-artist in 2017, Diddy, who made the money from his Cirac vodka deal, hadn’t even released an album in over 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while the streaming platforms aren’t exactly killing the music industry, they’re still skewed in favour of the private equity players, and hence are the primary drivers of the aggregate growth recorded in the revenues, dwarfing the ability of the actual artists to exert any influence. However, some of the bigger names are now coming out against the unregulated PE influence in the industry. Recently Big Machine Records, which owned the rights to the music catalogue of all of Taylor Swift’s past albums, except for &lt;em&gt;Lover&lt;/em&gt;, was sold out for $300-$350 Million, to Scooter Braun’s Ithaca Holdings, disallowing Swift to perform her own songs at the AMAs, and leading to a highly publicised feud between the two. The sale was backed by the renowned Carlyle Group, that was already facing backlash for its indirect stake in defence contractors who had actively supplied weapons to fund the bombings in Yemen by Saudi Arabia, and now came under the heat of the fans as well as Alexandria Ocasio Cortez and Elizabeth Warren. While the matter remains unresolved, it is likely that this time the artist might register a victory, since Swift has threatened to re-record her past albums. The victory would put her in the rare company of the few major-label artists like Metallica, Janet Jackson and Jay-Z to gain control of the assets associated with their music. The outcome of the lawsuit pursued by EDM artist Martin Garrix against the label Spinnin’ Records has also brought some good news, with Garrix being given the rights and masters to some of his biggest hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investors are constantly innovating to capitalise on the gains of the music industry, with some even experimenting with removal of ownership exclusivity and opening song rights for public offerings. An Initial Song Offering (ISO) was made for Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Jodeci Freestyle&lt;/em&gt;, wherein 10% of the copyright stake was available for public purchase to the top 100 subscribers, with Ethereum based payments. While such innovations are in the interest of the public and allow them to channelise their savings towards better investment options, it needs to be realised that the lack of tangibility of both the output and most of the inputs of this industry is an important consideration in the face of the financial innovations that should follow. Therefore, the battle between rights and arts will continue for an indefinite period, as long as we, as a corporate, wouldn’t stop patronising the creative skills of the people involved in this field.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Creativity has its own timeline, and art can only blossom through experience and patience. It takes its own sweet time getting through to people letting the art ripen naturally, instead of spoon-feeding its patrons, and is usually a mark of the artist’s authenticity. Take Van Gogh or Kafka, for instance, with both dying in ignorance of the ingenuity of their works. Their patience, or rather underconfidence, eventually led to the posthumous recognition, capitalised on by whoever could claim to ignite the inspiration, rendering their lives analogous to a sad art film, that yet still, managed to inspire people further. But not every artist wants to make a sad art film of their lives. It isn’t simply about the lack of patience or existence of confidence to market their work, it is, quite often, about survival. Putting all stakes in an industry that isn’t entirely welcoming to new works due to their abstract nature is certainly a dicey choice for one’s career. Looking for popular platforms that can get you eyeballs is only natural.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Corruption - Cynicism or Pragmatism</title>
      <link href="/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corruption - Cynicism or Pragmatism" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years back, post the implementation of certain paramount structural reforms, Nigerian social media platforms were bizarrely flooded with a rather idiosyncratic hashtag ‘BBOC’, or ‘BringBackOurCorruption’. The laws that were partially aimed at enabling transparency, accountability and a greater oversight of government revenue, with penalisation for infringement extended to incarceration, did not sit well with the public. The government had apparently stolen the ‘grease’ to their economic cycle, which eventually showed in the levels of inflation in the Nigerian economy as well as in a plummeting Nigerian Naira in international markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corruption is bad. There is a large consensus that corroborates its corrosive impact on society. Macro level studies, that have used country-level data to explore cross country variations in both governance and economic indicators, have managed to consistently establish a correlation between low-income countries and greater levels of bureaucratic corruption. But if we look beyond conventional wisdom, it doesn’t take a genius to figure out that while the former argument is purely moral in its reasoning, rather than rational, the latter is also weak in its inability to establish a coherent causational relation between the two variables involved. Rose-Ackerman (1996), through their works, further helped carve into stone the idea that corruption is detrimental to the health of an economy, leading to the rise of a school of thought that opposed the idea of corruption as a positive for the economy (something which was extensively worked upon by various scholars in the 1960’s). It was popularly believed that corruption ‘sands’ the wheels of the economy. One might never be able to debunk the moral argument against corruption, but as for the empirical data backing the second argument, one must note that for every poor and corrupt African nation, there is an equally corrupt but rich Asian nation, leading many to believe that corruption has got nothing to do with the level of growth in an economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one had to defend corruption, it would be difficult, nearly impossible, to do so from an ethical perspective. Any possible argument in its defense would be highly situational. But when it comes to the economic perspective, one might become much more tolerant. It is then simply considered a ‘grease’ that ensures smoother functioning of the economy, like a tax you pay to cut through the bureaucratic red tape. Although corruption is popularly believed to be an aspect inherent to socialism, it arises out of a society’s need to come closer to its capitalistic features. In a free-market, demand and supply balance in a manner that ensures that all goods and services eventually reach their intrinsic value in the market, eliminating any arbitrage opportunities for an individual seller, given perfect knowledge. As soon as there is intervention, this cycle breaks down. This is an issue that was highlighted in Ludwig Von Mises’ Socialist Calculation Debate in the 1920’s. Mises argued for the inability of the socialist system to get through one of the fundamental economic problems: what to produce? The state makes that decision and sets the prices, but since there is a lack of market determination of the eventual prices, a seller may not be able to gauge the demand that exists for his product and may end up believing that the prices are not at par with the intrinsic value, that is what he deserves. In order to get closer to that figure, the seller may resort to hoarding a product or charging a little under-the-table fee, and it’s only fair. However the inability to estimate this intrinsic figure is also something that perpetuates corruption. A public servant in India may demand a bribe to get a service done because he feels that his salary is too low to compensate for his efforts. This behavioural aspect may not go away even if his salary is raised, not simply because it becomes habitual but because he tends to measure his reward relatively. Well, also because human wants are never ending (but this has nothing to do with the intrinsic aspect, here he will charge higher for as long as he can). In this example, even if the given behavioural aspect does go away, that is the employee is satisfied with the salary hike, he would be disincentivised from even showing up to work because he is getting a satisfactory remuneration for a job which has no stringent regulatory mechanism and is known to turn people lethargic. This example counter-intuitively explains how a bribe would proves to be much better for the economy than a salary hike for public servants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this perspective offers an analysis based on the degree of intervention, many believe that the existence of corruption is inherent to any developing economy, citing how all the major developed economies of the modern world went through phases of deep corruption and social unrest to get where they are. In fact, Leff, N.H. (1964) found empirical evidence that anti-corruption campaigns in developing nations, like the then-China, depress economic growth by slowing down investment levels. Another argument states that developing nations have a poorly drafted constitutional and policy framework. When they don’t, it is considered overambitious due to their inability to constantly keep up with redesigning policies, resulting in them falling victim to various perverse incentives. This paucity of appropriate laws and policies is an aspect that was hypothesised by Samuel Huntington in the 1960’s. He believed that in such cases the only way to drive growth and revive businesses stuck in legislative red tape is corruption. It becomes a mechanism to circumvent thoughtless regulations in developing nations and provides rationality to the rising income inequality in these economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncanny response of Nigeria, a barely developing nation, to the anti-corruption crackdown was exactly what Huntington attempted to explain. The reforms happening at a stage when a majority of the population is reliant on the informal economy was an evident policy mis-step that exacerbated the economy that was already bearing the wrath of low oil prices. This can perhaps help us generate a sound ethical justification because here, corruption is not an optional add-on to the system, it is the system itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A couple of years back, post the implementation of certain paramount structural reforms, Nigerian social media platforms were bizarrely flooded with a rather idiosyncratic hashtag ‘BBOC’, or ‘BringBackOurCorruption’. The laws that were partially aimed at enabling transparency, accountability and a greater oversight of government revenue, with penalisation for infringement extended to incarceration, did not sit well with the public. The government had apparently stolen the ‘grease’ to their economic cycle, which eventually showed in the levels of inflation in the Nigerian economy as well as in a plummeting Nigerian Naira in international markets.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree</title>
      <link href="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree" />
      <published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree">&lt;p&gt;The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some millennials, burdened by low-income jobs and debt obligations, living from paycheck to paycheck, are genuinely unable to finance stock purchases, the statistics tell us how even better-off millennials are straying away from investing and are preferring to save instead. Unfortunately, their risk-averse tendencies are miscalculated and are costing them precious returns, since the S&amp;amp;P 500 (adjusted for inflation and dividends reinvested) averaged a 7.92% return between 2007 to 2017, while the money market bank accounts averaged a 0.3% return during the same period. Nearly 42% of millennials are conservative investors, as opposed to 38% of GenXers and 23% of the Boomers. They are unwilling to fully embrace the financial markets, and when they do, it is only through a safer, less costly mechanism such as that of an Exchange Traded Fund (ETF), which is a type of fund that holds multiple underlying assets rather than a single stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worth noting is that their caution seems selective. Millennials’ risk-aversion appears to be more about scepticism when one realises how they have stayed away only from what they personally saw fail - the stock markets. They are still the ones responsible for inflating the crypto-market, despite its lack of intrinsic value or any ‘faith’ backing. The only argument in defense of their wild investment choice is perhaps the sophisticated distributed ledger technology used in the asset which makes the case for fostering technological innovation in the stock markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the politically correct environment, with encouragement from Hollywood, has put capitalism out of style for many. The ones still willing to invest have raised the bar over mere profitability when making an investment decision. Company ethics and transparency are a primary consideration for millennials when they choose to invest, and these additional filters reduce the overall amount invested. The rate of investment for women is in an even poorer state. The Harris Poll survey revealed that a staggering 79% of women do not invest at all, with 70% of them stating that the process is confusing to them, while 60% of them believing how they felt investing was ‘an old-white man’s game’. Clearly, the Millennials need a better education when it comes to managing their finances and getting over &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture is clear: Millennials are savers and not investors. 71% of Millennial workers are saving for retirement, and begin saving at the median age of 24, which puts the GenX’s median saving age of 30 to shame. And while they rely on the banks for saving, they try to keep away from availing any of the other services. A three year study from Scratch, an in-house unit of Viacom, as a part of the &lt;em&gt;Millennial Disruption Study&lt;/em&gt;, found that not only were banks among the ‘Most Hated’ brands, but a third of this demographic cohort believed that they’d be better off without them. This is a major concern for banks, who are now resorting to appeasement techniques. Providing special discounts on credit card bills and easing out the enrollment mechanism for loans are a few examples. This has also partially fueled the rise of fintech in the formal banking system and is encouraging the development of such technologies. Developing a system with a user-friendly interface and greater transparency by incorporation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning is an obvious solution to this issue. For instance,  a ZeroHedge survey revealed that one in three Millennials would rather invest in Bitcoin than in the stock market, simply because of the unconventional and futuristic technology involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that in traditional economics, the West had never been considered the saver’s economy, and this pattern is shifting for the better. The situation is quite akin to the rise in savings post the hyperinflationary periods in Germany after World War I, which incidentally was also a result of the psychological impact of the crisis. At the macro level, greater savings would imply lesser dependence on foreign investment. Lesser inflow of USD denominated investment in the USA implies lesser demand for the dollar. The consequent decline in appreciation of the USD is great for recovering the Current Account Deficit, which has been a primary long-term concern for the nation. But this advantage is dwarfed when growth concerns step in, as slowdowns are the projected case for the next few years. Additionally, with the rise of protectionist, right-wing governments around the globe, millennials are increasingly inclining towards what they think is socialism, which implies increased disinterest towards the financial markets. And that is a terrible prospect for growth. Hence, even though this demographic cohort has been through quite a lot at an impressionable age, they must put their concerns aside and take up a more rational approach. They have made a wise decision to save, considering the depleting ability of the burgeoning federal balance sheet to finance their post-retirement expenses. But they must learn to be comfortable with the idea of some risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream</title>
      <link href="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream" />
      <published>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream">&lt;p&gt;“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials …
has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion,
technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing
challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an
American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one
accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the
fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have
exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is
reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s
to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just
the generation gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest
hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore
the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then
aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation
in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when
they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny
scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s
common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five
years that follow graduation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even
comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen
not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young
graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits
of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score,
despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder
for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the
foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new
lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the
Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment
requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at
least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a
home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials
would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the
easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on
the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to
the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic
fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a
subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned
risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has
accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to
a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the
‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact,
they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a
result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the
rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their
savings, and further delays homeownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern
housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global
population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be
added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing
prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow
vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities
but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to
build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in
all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against
the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve,
whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because
the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover
costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism
(Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive
developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution,
rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not
only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc.,
but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an
especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a
combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps
people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India,
about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked,
“Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this
city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums.
Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford
monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent
settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they
actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two
flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3,
while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI
is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would
allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area,
and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for
Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city,
next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence
levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of
encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost
towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working
millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only
exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic
amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class
divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B.
Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the &lt;em&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/em&gt;,
had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the
cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every
petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays
them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they
manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they
must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the
sea.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials … has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion, technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.” Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just the generation gap. One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five years that follow graduation.  This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score, despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment requirements.  Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the ‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact, they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their savings, and further delays homeownership. But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve, whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism (Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution, rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties.  The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc., but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India, about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked, “Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums. Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3, while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area, and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city, next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like.  Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B. Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the Economic and Political Weekly, had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the sea.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It</title>
      <link href="/The-Middle-Income-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Middle-Income-Trap</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Middle-Income-Trap">&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Mahatyohar&lt;/em&gt; (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded
with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by
the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were
perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign.
Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of
6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a
decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which
explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as
compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put
more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have
pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations
can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a
part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could
indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the
National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue
of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He
identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what
the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to
lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per
capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has
become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges
from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the
economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good
industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states
that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with
by the government’s &lt;em&gt;PM Awas Yojana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PM Mudra Yojana&lt;/em&gt; schemes respectively,
it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate
the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re
becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital
development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that
we’re heading into. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation
makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but
then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation.
This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101
nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved
high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily
attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital,
lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is
comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been
exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely
crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being
channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar
to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour
is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages
are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the
current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of
Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of
high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s
demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour
supply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related
expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6%
required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its
restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like
&lt;em&gt;Startup India&lt;/em&gt;, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage
investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture
capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty
valuation of the startups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of
2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will
have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic
convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the
developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like
Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and
efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India,
who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour
and must now bear the consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the
early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers.
Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was
absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South
Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The
global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy
perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing
private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was
the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources
from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than
high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other
professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation.
Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human
capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater
urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic
demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because
becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital
account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently
undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the
politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically
left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive
foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment
destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that
before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations,
for capital is faithful to none.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While the Mahatyohar (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign. Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of 6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence. Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with by the government’s PM Awas Yojana and PM Mudra Yojana schemes respectively, it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that we’re heading into.  The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation. This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101 nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital, lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy.  Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour supply.  As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6% required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like Startup India, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty valuation of the startups.  An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of 2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India, who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour and must now bear the consequences.  The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers. Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation. Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater urgency. Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations, for capital is faithful to none.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Tale of Two Brothers</title>
      <link href="/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Brothers" />
      <published>2019-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CHINA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wedged between the Eastern Coast and the mainland of China, lies the ancient province of Zhongyuan. Historically renowned as the birthplace of the Chinese civilisation, it is home to a multitude of heritage sites ranging from the ruins of the Shang dynasty to the Eight Great Ancient Capitals of the nation. Its nearly-bygone eminence, in part, can be attributed to its fertile mainland, to the river Huang-He that runs through its veins, and perhaps, even to some of its women, like Lady Fu Hao who managed to bloom through the misogynistic past of the nation. Skip ahead a thousand years to the current millennium, and we find that much like the Ancient Greece, Zhongyuan is a graveyard of distant and glorious memories. Although it is now a set of vast agricultural lands with a reasonably efficient productivity level, it’s the demographic structure is quite the disaster. The sex ratio of the province, much more skewed than that of the entire nation, is at a startling 118 men for every 100 women. This implies that nearly one-fifth of the men may not find even a match for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ancient Chinese philosophy of contrasting a passive female principle (Yin) to an active male principle (Yang) for creating a complementary match is the base for the patriarchy that has dominated the traditional family structures in China, which must ideally be patrilineal and prescriptively virilocal. Despite the nation being colonised and later having been through a long regime of Communism, these basic traditions never changed for the common people. Mao Zedong’s antipathy to religion reshaped private beliefs but these traditions were so deep-rooted that they remained unscathed. And so, when the ‘One Child Policy’ was introduced in 1979 (or a decade prior for some parts of the nation), a natural preference for boys arose more predominantly in the countryside areas like Zhongyuan. This gave rise to the current situation of numerous Gen-Y ‘Bachelor Towns’ where men struggle to find wives, not only because there simply aren’t enough women but also because they’re being subjected to societal shaming, such as by being called ‘&lt;em&gt;guanggun&lt;/em&gt;’ or dead branches. On the other hand, the women have to both endure increasing sexual crimes, and take advantage of natural selection, which drives them to marry the higher educated men in the cities. The disparity, after two generations ageing without cousins and siblings, is so vast that many economists believe that retracting the policy in 2015 was a little too late to reestablish balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With hopes of a higher income, and a greater chance at finding a match, thousands of men move to the Pearl River Delta each day, which has nearly 60,000 factories employing 3-4 million people and has much role in making China &lt;em&gt;The World’s Factory&lt;/em&gt;. The Pearl Delta is primarily where all the rapid growth of China came from and where all its FDI went. The workforce is gender-neutral, and even though the balance has shifted from 70-30 in favour of women, to nearly 50-50 now, it still leaves sufficient room for couples to make and breakup at the assembly line each morning. The region additionally includes Shenzhen, the tech hub where the nation’s second stock exchange is situated. Shenzhen acts as an outlet for the labour to cater to the foreign investment projects that have recently been undertaken by China, with an increasing frequency, primarily in poor and middle-income nations of Southeast Asia and Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government’s ambitious programme to create the modern maritime silk route under the Belt and Road Initiative has been met by skepticism in the West, who have resorted to calling it ‘chequebook diplomacy’. But for China, these projects have rendered both a macroeconomic dominance and an unconventional solution to the gender problem, since the projects have eased not only China’s international relations, but also the visa requirements for its citizens to travel to these nations. Thus, many men from Zhongyuan, take on the months’ long journey to nations like Myanmar, Philippines, Indonesia and, recently, Pakistan, to set up a deal with local traffickers who can easily arrange for young women―whose parents willingly participate in such international betrothals in exchange for some money―and the hope for a better future for their daughters. An approximate cost of $10,000 is all it takes for these men to conform to the societal script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PAKISTAN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warmed by the wrath of the 1962 Sino-Indian War and the Cold War, the diplomatic relations between China and Pakistan bolstered through the years, and lately they come to be known as the ‘Iron Brothers’. Metaphorically speaking, both the brothers have grown in different directions, but factually, only one has moved for what we could call ‘growth’, while the other, i.e. Pakistan is struggling in a slough of debt. But China, being the generous brother that it is, has interceded to the rescue of Pakistan by making its international commercial initiative more inclusive through the China Pakistan Economic Corridor (CPEC). It is a project whose combined value was recently estimated to be $62 billion, which is greater than the total amount of FDI in Pakistan since 1970. The two-armed project will connect pipelines, roads and bridges via a 2700 km stretch to the deepwater ports at Karachi and Gwadar, where the latter will be redesigned to increase its cargo capacity from 1 million tonnes to 400 million tonnes, making it one of the most sophisticated ports to ever exist. It will additionally simulate much-needed growth in Pakistan. In fact, nearly $30 billion is dedicated to energy projects, which will generate 7000 MW of energy, contributing to 3% of Pakistan’s GDP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China too has much to gain from this brotherly affection, however. The most prominent underlying advantage being that it will be able to systematically bypass the maritime chokepoints of the South China Sea, and gain control of other strategic hotspots. This is why it is willing to risk venturing into the politically unstable regions of Baloch, Sindh and Khyber-Pakhtunkhwa, while the elite of Islamabad want to systematically cut Baloch out of the Gwadar equation. This marginalisation has partially fueled the rise of Balochi separatists, who recently attacked a bus full of Chinese engineers, prompting China to consider deploying its own troops in Pakistan for the protection of its workers. Considering the fragile situation of the Pakistani economy, with their Rupee falling by over 20% last year, paying off the debt has become even harder, while the forex reserves are below the $10 billion mark. An IMF bailout would pose conditions of coming clean with the CPEC books, and would compel Pakistan to expose the chequebook diplomacy, which is quite unlikely. So, in the foreseeable future, this ‘brotherhood’ is bound to strengthen, as more loans are lent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rising influx of Chinese men, who may not necessarily have a job, is owed to the visa-on-arrival policy for the ease of the Chinese people. Last year alone, over 91,000 Chinese people visited the country and 32,000 visas of Chinese nationals were extended. This has threatened the safety of the women in villages. Trafficking is a profitable business and the minorities, like the Christian community, are specifically targeted, since the Pakistani government is visibly unconcerned about them, as is reflected in the escape of Asia Bibi, the Christian woman who fled the nation after fearing death threats from ordinary citizens, even after she had been aquitted of blasphemy charges. The minorities also appeal to the Chinese men due to their ethnocentrist approach to the Muslim community, the proof being their tyrannical crackdowns on the local Uighur Muslim minority of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan’s Federal Investigation Agency (FIA) approximated that nearly 700 Christian and 300 Muslim women, many underage, were at risk of sexual slavery after falling for the pretext of marriage, as of 2018. Recently, Natasha Robin, 22, who was promised a life free of destitution, had agreed to marry a Chinese suitor whom she had met through an unlawful matchmaking agency. After twelve days of being subjected to the mental and physical torment of sex slavery, she managed to escape. Others have not been so lucky. This callousness of Pakistan towards its women may pose demographic threats to its own environment, since female infanticide is already prevalent and trafficking might further aggravate the sex ratio, which is already at a worrying 106 men per 100 women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggressive policy measures, for adherence to economic indicators, have often put the well being of the population at stake, China made this mistake and has ended up destabilising the sex ratio for the sake of ameliorating the demographic pressure. Pakistan is in pursuit of a disaster if doesn’t curb the illegal activities that accompany China’s growth agenda. It must reconsider if this brotherhood is in fact as mutually beneficial as China claims it to be. As for the people of Zhongyuan, who adulate their Supreme Leader Mao, it’s high time they act on one of his rare rational beliefs: ‘&lt;em&gt;Women hold up half the sky&lt;/em&gt;’. The next few months are crucial to see how the situation pans out further, whether in favour of the local population of the remote Pakistani areas, or the elite of Islamabad who concern themselves with fairly active policy measures to rebuild the economy whilst neglecting the ground-level work towards ensuring a safe and secure environment for their own people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">CHINA</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
