<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/stuti.gupta/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-01-21T14:34:12+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/stuti.gupta/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Millennials, The Gentle Souls</title>
      <link href="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials, The Gentle Souls" />
      <published>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls">&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely
home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and
sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting
truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our
realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media
has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to
a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to
discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our
parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is
not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions.
And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or
informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare
I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility
to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies
this chaos. What’s noble is that we care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about
how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which
tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the
fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for
themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our
fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We
face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other
in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media
activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the
moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own
endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful
is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives
up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care
about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious
millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring
about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is
nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified
moral compass we never inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply
intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the
picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess;
like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a
favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be
like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as
aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to
blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But
here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of
bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess.
We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more
courageously, also with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength,
for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our
generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces
the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of
daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together
stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian
women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot
f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is
to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to
be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you
hints at you being different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles.
We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with
each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures
humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous
selves, but finally talking about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short,
acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal
mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy
to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to
shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and
have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the
complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the
acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema
and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants.
Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of
motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials
will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it.
Let humans be human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving
through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that
solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a
meme rooted in self-deprecation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis. At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions. And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies this chaos. What’s noble is that we care. A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own endeavours. All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious millennials! ‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified moral compass we never inherited. Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation. Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess; like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess. We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more courageously, also with ourselves. The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength, for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud. Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you hints at you being different. But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles. We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous selves, but finally talking about them. The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short, acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed. In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants. Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it. Let humans be human. They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a meme rooted in self-deprecation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On the Curator of Girlhood: An Ode to Olivia Gatwood</title>
      <link href="/On-the-Curator-of-Girlhood" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Curator of Girlhood: An Ode to Olivia Gatwood" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:10:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:10:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-the-Curator-of-Girlhood</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-the-Curator-of-Girlhood">&lt;p&gt;Olivia Gatwood was a name I stumbled upon in a vast sea of slam poetry videos on
YouTube. Out of the hundreds of videos of finger-snapping and rants over love,
loss, oppression, and identity, it was her name that stuck, long after my fiery
infatuation with spoken word poetry had mellowed to a flicker. I always
gravitate back to this opinionated, curly-haired woman who writes about Manic
Pixie Dream Girls, resting b*tch faces, period underwear and stories of girls
putting in tampons for their friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her writing reflects a wave of feminism which has a ferocious insistence on
&lt;em&gt;reclaiming&lt;/em&gt; femininity with unwavering pride. Olivia doesn’t spend time
clarifying that pink isn’t every woman’s favourite colour, she would much rather
illustrate through poetry the beauty and loveliness of pink, and how there
cannot be shame in loving something that is beautiful. The idea behind
reclamation is to tell-off the patriarchy, by stripping away the shame,
weakness, and unimportance that it attaches to womanliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Imagine, the teen girls gone from our world and how quickly we would beg for
their return.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By writing about girlhood, Olivia advocates for the fact that stories of
girlhood are in fact important enough to be given a name, to be archived and
shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had a love affair with Olivia’s poetry and with her determined conviction
to speak to the teenage girl in me or in any woman. And in all their might,
those words have loved me back too, by bringing me tales of valiant and
interesting women in a world that has only ever painted us as meek and doe-eyed,
and by bringing pride to places that had only known shame. Olivia tells me how
uniquely wonderful the friendship between two teen girls is and I recall all of
those moments of unbelievable intimacy that I had taken for granted. She tells
me about the careless trust she places on old period underwear and my mind
wanders back to every red splotch, together with the vicious scrubbing and the
unnecessary hiding. She talks of the profoundness of female rituals and suddenly
nothing about my existence as a teen girl is mundane to me. With her poetry,
every mundane experience of girlhood evolves into a sacrosanct ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;I had never pined, so badly,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;for denim to slip down her lower back,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;upon taking a seat,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;to reveal the fuzz along her spine,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;that which she likely wished to remove,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;begged her mother for hot wax like we all did&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olivia paints a collage of details, she doesn’t &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; you that queerness is a
beautiful thing, instead she makes you feel a thousand flapping butterflies for
a girl’s fuzzy lower back, and by the end of it you have &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; that queerness
is indeed a beautiful thing, you don’t have to be told anymore. It’s not a poem
of some gigantic struggle for LGBTQ emancipation. Instead, it is one that
combines the smallest of elements, eliciting the most primitive, the most human
of responses, and establishing connectedness in the process. The constant
non-linearity in her writing is what sets her apart from the surge of spoken
word poets, whose poems are more declarative in form. Olivia will let her words
find you at a leisurely pace and gradually engulf you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world of excessive interaction with content, it is easy to become
desensitised to words. Words, as they are, fall short in being able to evoke
fury or love or even solidarity. What then, induces one to drop one’s thoughts
and feel something? Olivia speaks to that desensitised reader/listener through
the entangling net of stories that she weaves. She reminds one that poetry isn’t
a dish to be served on a platter but rather a recipe to be navigated through,
half the fun lies in disentangling the net that the author weaves. Quite unlike
the Rupi Kaur brand of poetry. For Kaur gives a perfectly fitting feminist
message, but that’s it. Her poetry exists merely on the surface, there is
nothing to delve into, to be submerged in. This narrative moves forward in a
straight line, such that there is no space left &lt;em&gt;between&lt;/em&gt; the lines, which is
also the space where the magic happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The last time we made love you asked me if I was scared,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I think you wanted me to say yes”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subtlety is also Olivia’s distinguishing quality. Even in poems with darker
undertones, in stories of pain and abuse, she often speaks about the abuse
without ever outrightly addressing it. And strangely enough, the indistinction
encapsulates the very nature of abuse itself, to be so subtle that we wish to
ignore it. How abuse isn’t usually isolated and identifiable, but it’s in words,
actions and behaviours interlaced with all else, how it is indistinguishable to
the extent that it almost resembles normalcy. She brings out the imperceptible
fears that lurk within us. Olivia gets the grey nature of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The boy doesn’t ask if he can choke me, so I pretend to die while he’s doing
it”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is the curator to the museum of all our stories, some lost and some broken,
what’s different is the light that she uses to guide us through them. A light of
pride. She leaves one with not only the feeling that poetry is magical but that
being a girl itself is so so wondrous and sensationally beautiful in nature.
Olivia is about the details, about the fears and insecurities in the experiences
of girlhood, and the understanding that from the smallest instances emerges the
greatest solidarity. Being a girl can be a constant struggle for selfhood.
Everything teenage girls do and are is under constant attack and ridicule. And
that is precisely how patriarchy is structured, that even a single moment of
uninterrupted female existence is unendurable for them. And to that, she says,
f*ck you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When the boy said, he liked my hair the other way, I shaved my head instead of
my p*ssy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Olivia Gatwood was a name I stumbled upon in a vast sea of slam poetry videos on YouTube. Out of the hundreds of videos of finger-snapping and rants over love, loss, oppression, and identity, it was her name that stuck, long after my fiery infatuation with spoken word poetry had mellowed to a flicker. I always gravitate back to this opinionated, curly-haired woman who writes about Manic Pixie Dream Girls, resting b*tch faces, period underwear and stories of girls putting in tampons for their friends. Her writing reflects a wave of feminism which has a ferocious insistence on reclaiming femininity with unwavering pride. Olivia doesn’t spend time clarifying that pink isn’t every woman’s favourite colour, she would much rather illustrate through poetry the beauty and loveliness of pink, and how there cannot be shame in loving something that is beautiful. The idea behind reclamation is to tell-off the patriarchy, by stripping away the shame, weakness, and unimportance that it attaches to womanliness. “Imagine, the teen girls gone from our world and how quickly we would beg for their return.” By writing about girlhood, Olivia advocates for the fact that stories of girlhood are in fact important enough to be given a name, to be archived and shared. I have had a love affair with Olivia’s poetry and with her determined conviction to speak to the teenage girl in me or in any woman. And in all their might, those words have loved me back too, by bringing me tales of valiant and interesting women in a world that has only ever painted us as meek and doe-eyed, and by bringing pride to places that had only known shame. Olivia tells me how uniquely wonderful the friendship between two teen girls is and I recall all of those moments of unbelievable intimacy that I had taken for granted. She tells me about the careless trust she places on old period underwear and my mind wanders back to every red splotch, together with the vicious scrubbing and the unnecessary hiding. She talks of the profoundness of female rituals and suddenly nothing about my existence as a teen girl is mundane to me. With her poetry, every mundane experience of girlhood evolves into a sacrosanct ceremony. “I had never pined, so badly, for denim to slip down her lower back, upon taking a seat, to reveal the fuzz along her spine, that which she likely wished to remove, begged her mother for hot wax like we all did.” Olivia paints a collage of details, she doesn’t tell you that queerness is a beautiful thing, instead she makes you feel a thousand flapping butterflies for a girl’s fuzzy lower back, and by the end of it you have felt that queerness is indeed a beautiful thing, you don’t have to be told anymore. It’s not a poem of some gigantic struggle for LGBTQ emancipation. Instead, it is one that combines the smallest of elements, eliciting the most primitive, the most human of responses, and establishing connectedness in the process. The constant non-linearity in her writing is what sets her apart from the surge of spoken word poets, whose poems are more declarative in form. Olivia will let her words find you at a leisurely pace and gradually engulf you. In a world of excessive interaction with content, it is easy to become desensitised to words. Words, as they are, fall short in being able to evoke fury or love or even solidarity. What then, induces one to drop one’s thoughts and feel something? Olivia speaks to that desensitised reader/listener through the entangling net of stories that she weaves. She reminds one that poetry isn’t a dish to be served on a platter but rather a recipe to be navigated through, half the fun lies in disentangling the net that the author weaves. Quite unlike the Rupi Kaur brand of poetry. For Kaur gives a perfectly fitting feminist message, but that’s it. Her poetry exists merely on the surface, there is nothing to delve into, to be submerged in. This narrative moves forward in a straight line, such that there is no space left between the lines, which is also the space where the magic happens. “The last time we made love you asked me if I was scared, I think you wanted me to say yes” Subtlety is also Olivia’s distinguishing quality. Even in poems with darker undertones, in stories of pain and abuse, she often speaks about the abuse without ever outrightly addressing it. And strangely enough, the indistinction encapsulates the very nature of abuse itself, to be so subtle that we wish to ignore it. How abuse isn’t usually isolated and identifiable, but it’s in words, actions and behaviours interlaced with all else, how it is indistinguishable to the extent that it almost resembles normalcy. She brings out the imperceptible fears that lurk within us. Olivia gets the grey nature of things. “The boy doesn’t ask if he can choke me, so I pretend to die while he’s doing it” She is the curator to the museum of all our stories, some lost and some broken, what’s different is the light that she uses to guide us through them. A light of pride. She leaves one with not only the feeling that poetry is magical but that being a girl itself is so so wondrous and sensationally beautiful in nature. Olivia is about the details, about the fears and insecurities in the experiences of girlhood, and the understanding that from the smallest instances emerges the greatest solidarity. Being a girl can be a constant struggle for selfhood. Everything teenage girls do and are is under constant attack and ridicule. And that is precisely how patriarchy is structured, that even a single moment of uninterrupted female existence is unendurable for them. And to that, she says, f*ck you. “When the boy said, he liked my hair the other way, I shaved my head instead of my p*ssy.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Cl*t Wants What it Wants</title>
      <link href="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cl*t Wants What it Wants" />
      <published>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants">&lt;p&gt;Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared
of every &lt;em&gt;flogging&lt;/em&gt; and every &lt;em&gt;caning&lt;/em&gt; or suddenly having no faith in
technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to
avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that
one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or &lt;em&gt;category&lt;/em&gt; of
porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one
feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in
person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk
to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why
do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;,
we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re
scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that &lt;em&gt;these&lt;/em&gt; are our
innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared
of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a
certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how
we think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest
the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s
offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely
a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like &lt;em&gt;choking&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;slapping&lt;/em&gt; cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why
we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s
the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place
where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if
there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is
wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so
dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those
same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because
it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic,
we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense
of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control
what we do or do not &lt;strong&gt;desire&lt;/strong&gt;. We think we can choose to want or not want
something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the
dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are
borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the
‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or
craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet
pussy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to
further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in
role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex,
and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex
for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man.
The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the
one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; by serving only his
needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the
appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for
betraying the rule (women not desiring sex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to
be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its
proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that
most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex
dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your
hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an
average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a
discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into
account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with
submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’.
Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To
claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone
else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to
restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy
or even if only for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you
can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we
are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to
understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to
remember is: &lt;em&gt;desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of
them.&lt;/em&gt; No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has
been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of
life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that
this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be
built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with
these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely
the manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray
you.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared of every flogging and every caning or suddenly having no faith in technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or category of porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position. The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we want, we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that these are our innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how we think. Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like choking and slapping cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel. It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic, we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control what we do or do not desire. We think we can choose to want or not want something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing. It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the ‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet pussy. It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex, and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man. The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her role by serving only his needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for betraying the rule (women not desiring sex). The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to be? A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’. Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy or even if only for a while. There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to remember is: desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of them. No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely the manifestation. Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray you.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Should Family Come First?</title>
      <link href="/Should-Family-Come-First" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should Family Come First?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T03:46:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T03:46:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Should-Family-Come-First</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Should-Family-Come-First">&lt;p&gt;The institution of family lies at the foundation of every society on Earth. But in India, it is so much more than just a foundation, family is the sustenance and the bane, the crutch and the agony of all festivals and all funerals, all of society and all of culture. But even when it’s a pain, it’s a pain we do not know how to live without. What seems overbearing and out of line in most cultures is the norm in Indian families. Indian families, with their little comprehension of space and boundaries, constantly barge, intrude and critique. From the ‘aunties’ glaring at exposed cleavages to the uncles who are making matches on marital websites, Indian families have never believed in hesitation. No advice is ever unsolicited. But there is something to say of the large joint families with people constantly milling around the house, the warm grandmothers with their secret recipes and the numberless siblings and cousins. There is something to say of the tightly knit structure of Indian households with an abundance of canopies of comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ever-presence and the intrusions are symbols of a certain type of familiarity; a manifestation and reminder of a claim, of a sanction given long ago in the pages of history. Families lay a claim over us, over our mental and spiritual selves, over our sense of being. These claims perhaps go a long way in making us feel loved, because who else would intrude and scold and worry except those who want to keep us safe and invest in us. Even though it might feel like an encroachment upon autonomy, it certainly has a warmth to it, a charm not found in western homes, which let go. India’s collective inability to let go is rooted in our love, our ever-holding-on, unwilling-to-be-apart love; it is rooted in the way we have been brought up: our values of butting in, and pointing out, and determining for others, what’s best for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the present generation and its streak of rebellion against family and tradition, familial bonds continue to be magnificent and powerful, encroaching and unjust, bustling with its magic and unwavering in its unfairness. These bonds become crucial because of increasing isolationism and the interference of ego in relationships, which make “enforcement and encroachment” necessary. Even when the connection is an enforced one, at least there is some degree of retention of connectedness. The presence of any support system, even if it is far from ideal, is better than having nothing but a dreary 1BHK to come back to. The price of complete autonomy is a high one, one that we Indians are yet to pay. Yet, is their romanticism in our narrative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value that comes out of family and the revered Indian lens through which it is viewed should not blind us to the problems that manifest as a result of the “family structure” being placed on a pedestal. The narratives of queer individuals, of women and of children cannot be pushed to the sidelines. It is easy to look at the cheery side of families and ignore the harshness. This attempt at pretence is easy, almost second nature to us. Growing up, we Indians imbibe a lesson from the world around us; that the front we put up for the world to see is far, far more important than what really goes on. India lives in a world in which the publicity of injustice wounds one more than the injustice itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Indian may dismiss abuse and torture of women as isolated incidents, not as crimes committed by depraved people not fit to engage with civilised society. Abuse doesn’t pop out of a void or only lurk in alleys. It stems from the idea of patriarchal entitlement over the bodies and decisions of women. It is in a household that this &lt;em&gt;entitlement&lt;/em&gt; begins and heightens, and manifests in the worst forms. There is a misguided sense of ownership men feel they have over the women in their families, and society just accepts that, which is why violence against women by family members does not scandalise one’s idea of social propriety or elicit the same response that violence by an outsider would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The false idea that familial ties lend some form of ownership over another human’s body is fed and drilled into one ever since childhood. India is a nation that is still far from even frowning upon children being hit by the elders of the family. Beyond the physical and emotional ramifications, hitting children also instills in them the idea that they have only partial autonomy over their bodies. It teaches children the lesson that bodily autonomy, while otherwise a valid concept, loses all ground when inside the house. This leads to toxic ideas of ownership which in turn leads to a path of denying oneself victimhood in the face of abuse, because if it’s family how wrong can it really be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems lie with us as a society when we twist and bend our limits and thresholds for what is right and what is wrong in order to excuse and justify whatever family does. This stems from the family being glorified as sacred and notions of entitlement that equate familial love with ownership. One’s inability to open up about any kind of trauma, pain or even smaller complaints that have to do with family comes from the belief that family always comes first. “Family always comes first” sounds like a noble sentiment but it can be exploited to make individuals feel as though they have to dismiss the wrong done to them by their family members, family being first is extrapolated to make a person feel as if opening up about family problems in front of friends, teachers, or lovers is wrong, or a form of shameful betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this article is not to say that Indian society must abandon the family structure that glues together the fabric of its society, but to examine how we have been systematically taught to worship and &lt;i&gt;pedestalize&lt;/i&gt; this structure, the institution of family and the people who constitute it. All the problematic things with family life become even more problematic because when our assumption that families provide a safe space fails, there is no alternative safe space to fall back on. The friends, peers, and lovers that should act as a safe space do not, because it becomes very difficult for a victim to break that inner wall of shame and talk about family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sad part is that communities are meant to look after the well-being of its members, but we Indians have become obsessed with merely the “illusion of functionality”. We venerate the ‘structure’ so much that we want to protect it even at the cost of real humans and their very real lives. So long as the overhanging structures of marriage, parenthood, and households stay intact we don’t really care what happens to the cogs that make up the wheel. How is it still that we have not redefined our idea of brokenness, how is it that people get abused and children are driven to committing suicide but we still think it’s working?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love and abuse, on the surface, seem to be mutually exclusive. Two concepts, so contrary, so antithetical to each other that they can never be thought of as coexistent. How can one love their abuser? How obvious, right? But the relationship between the abuser and the abused is anything but obvious. The world and this great nation are littered with tales of how the two thrive together, grip and dig into each other. Maybe the nature of love is such that it is with great difficulty that one might stop loving their abuser, but third parties and well-wishers can go a long way in helping one. Talking about experiences surrounding family that are grim will lead to a much-needed counter-narrative that will finally paint abuse as abuse, whether physical or emotional, that will finally show family as human beings, capable of falling, capable of wrong, and not as oracles who can dictate morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the love that comes for parents and siblings is not as organic in nature as one would like to believe. A lot of it also comes from the narrative that is flashed around us, of how much we are &lt;i&gt;supposed&lt;/i&gt; to and are &lt;i&gt;obligated&lt;/i&gt; to love. The love that is regarded with so much veneration, the devotion towards parents that is thought of as moral accomplishment itself is manufactured by society, it does not arise as authentically as one would like to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading all of this one might ask, &lt;i&gt;so what&lt;/i&gt;? So what if the structure is a certain way that has both pros and cons? The answer lies in valuing family but not pedestalizing it. The answer lies in acknowledging how the family has cared for one whilst understanding that families are not incapable of wrongdoing and some families even inflict grave abuse and injustice. Asking a nation which is willed to throw-off all balance, to approach a middle path might seem counterproductive. A nation in which family is all or nothing, asking for a path that both loves and censures family is daunting in itself. But God knows we’ve needed it, we’ve needed the balance.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The institution of family lies at the foundation of every society on Earth. But in India, it is so much more than just a foundation, family is the sustenance and the bane, the crutch and the agony of all festivals and all funerals, all of society and all of culture. But even when it’s a pain, it’s a pain we do not know how to live without. What seems overbearing and out of line in most cultures is the norm in Indian families. Indian families, with their little comprehension of space and boundaries, constantly barge, intrude and critique. From the ‘aunties’ glaring at exposed cleavages to the uncles who are making matches on marital websites, Indian families have never believed in hesitation. No advice is ever unsolicited. But there is something to say of the large joint families with people constantly milling around the house, the warm grandmothers with their secret recipes and the numberless siblings and cousins. There is something to say of the tightly knit structure of Indian households with an abundance of canopies of comfort.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beauty and the Beast</title>
      <link href="/Beauty-and-the-Beast" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty and the Beast" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beauty-and-the-Beast</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-and-the-Beast">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift given randomly, stupidly.”&lt;/em&gt; – K. Hosseini&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stealthily and openly, invisibly and brazenly, beauty snakes through conversations, decisions and opinions. The discussion of beauty is not just the domain of subjects like narcissism or nature’s trickery to perpetuate a species. Beauty is a matter to be discussed sociologically, for beauty is far more than just how we perceive ourselves, it is also how we perceive each other. In a world that paints less with words and more with filters, it becomes important to examine the intrusion of physical appearances into how one thinks, and leads life. No longer just a measure of what one finds visually or aesthetically soothing, beauty has now become a socially approved metric for the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; we place on people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Indian matrimonial advertisements that yearn for ‘fair’ and ‘slim’ brides and show business boosting looks over talent; right from the start it is ingrained and embedded into us that society fosters a reward mechanism that favours the handsome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift but is it really given &lt;em&gt;randomly&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What truly needs to be pondered upon is, how is it that there is a set of bodily and facial attributes that have been magically fixed as attractive and thereby high value? Why is light skin preferred to dark skin in most cultures? Why are perky breasts seen as more attractive as compared to breasts that sag? Why is it easier for one to find a woman with straight blonde hair aesthetically pleasing but not a woman with frizzy black hair?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fraud in beauty is that we have been made to believe that there is something &lt;em&gt;inherently beautiful&lt;/em&gt; about certain attributes, such as having fair skin. We do not find fair skin beautiful because it is embedded into our genetic constitution to find it so, it is not an innate characteristic of our species to find fair skin beautiful. We find it beautiful because society has deemed it to be beautiful. We find it beautiful because society tells us to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“She had perfect features, with her eye, nose, lips, and ears the right size and in right places. That is all it takes to make people beautiful, normal body parts – yet why does nature mess it up so many times?”&lt;/em&gt; – an un-ironic quote from a Chetan Bhagat novel. Society manufactures and dictates the way we feel about beauty while making us believe that those feelings and judgements arise organically from within. Beauty, is a social construct and this construct too rests upon a farce, which revolves around Eurocentricity and gendered expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Yeh chaand sa roshan chehra, zulfon ka rang sunehra, yeh jheel si neeli aakhein, koi raaz hai inmein gehra, tareef karun kya uski, jisne tumhe banaya?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song, from a 1964 film in India, casting Indian actors to be watched largely by people living in India, glorifies white skin, blonde hair and blue eyes and people actually &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;related&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to this song to the extent that today it is considered to be a classic. How does this make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European standards of beauty are living proof that colonialism once prevailed. When European countries colonised African and Asian nations they did not just see the people they subjugated as &lt;em&gt;‘different’&lt;/em&gt; from themselves but also as inferior, as subhuman. Colonialists glorified everything European as a superior, more civilised and refined way of leading life. They attached ‘disgust’ to everything native and indigenous. Idealisation of European beauty was a by-product of colonisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skewed power dynamics of the world allowed white people to narrate the norms for beauty. Colourism today, grips cultures across the world. From black women who look at their skin and wonder how much black is too black, to a nation of brown people being marketed skin lightening creams under the brand of ‘Fair &amp;amp; Lovely’. Colourism grips us both by the bane of society and the bane of our selfhood. And while beauty standards affect everyone, they affect people of colour way more. Because it has made us forget what we actually look like. Through the alchemy of Eurocentric standards of beauty, the untamed wavy black hair on the heads of Indian goddesses look mythical to Indians, yet somehow Cameron Diaz’s blonde hair looks more &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt; and more &lt;em&gt;attainable&lt;/em&gt;. The conventional archetypes of beauty do not even coincide with traditional looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The normativity extends to gendered expectations too, as society and media continue to be obsessed with narrow waisted women and tall, brawny men. Once again, the sham lies in the fact that these expectations are &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;assumed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;intrinsic&lt;/em&gt; to any gender. In a day and age when media is ever present and more dominant than anything else, when one does not see a single woman having body hair on screen, it’s almost as if society wants us to pretend that women do not have body hair. This promotes a form of normativity that borders on delusion! Media latches on a sense of disgust to chest hair, and sells us the lie that it is ‘gross’ and ‘repulsive’ for men to have it. Media strips away what is natural, and in its place synthesises a new ‘normal’. This new ordinary makes the state of nature seem abnormal, if it didn’t it would be easier to picture Chris Evans with chest hair. Ah! Never mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These imposed standards are so deeply entrenched in us that even when one is aware of the sham surrounding beauty, they visit one in private moments. Like the inward rejoice of having hair straightened because it feels as if frizz was something to be corrected, and straight just looks more ‘normal’. Or stopping a porn video midway because the woman having a tuft of pubic hair made it ‘uncomfortable’ to watch, or because watching people of colour have sex ‘feels wrong’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even when faced with these inner hypocrisies, one must remember that these dilemmas too are imposed and injected into the people by a media that rests upon the commoditization of beauty and reinforces the same toxic ideas. But ah! To hell with norms! It is the era for shaking up normativity and outraging beauty ideals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty, in all its failing and its glory, is subjective. “Beauty is subjective” is not a lie meant to console people who do not fall within conventional archetypes of beauty. On the contrary, &lt;em&gt;‘subjective beauty’&lt;/em&gt; is the only truth, for beauty cannot and should not be standardised. Beauty does not conform, why then should its ideals do the same?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift given randomly, stupidly.” – K. Hosseini</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
