<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/himanshi.saini/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-21T14:45:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/himanshi.saini/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">From Grabbing Eyeballs to Sourcing Toxicity: Television News Broadcasting in India</title>
      <link href="/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Grabbing Eyeballs to Sourcing Toxicity: Television News Broadcasting in India" />
      <published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity">&lt;p&gt;Television has been the dominant form of entertainment in India for over thirty years. Around 850 million people have access to a TV set in India and these numbers not only reflect the large influence of TV in the social and political domains on its viewers but also how it has evolved to become the biggest marketing tool in the media sphere. While many sectors became stagnant with the outbreak of coronavirus, the television industry grabbed the attention of the millions that were confined to their homes during the lockdown. A captive audience celebrated the return of old classics like the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; in the quarantine period. However, the unethical growth and rising TRP of various channels also received huge backlash during the same time. This gave a reality check for the kind of information that was being sourced and the influence of the same on the viewers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Death of Rajiv Tyagi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging deeper into the news sector, which is a major contributor to the television domain, we may consider the sudden passing away of the Indian National Congress National spokesperson Rajiv Tyagi on August 12, 2020. He passed away after a heart attack that occurred soon after a heated debate on a Hindi TV channel. This sparked a debate about the toxic debate culture of TV news. Commenting on this tragic incident, Professor Gaurav Vallabh, a Congress spokesperson, explained how titles of the debate show on news channels are divisive. Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) leader Nawab Malik commented on the format of the debates and how the anchor or the host of the show denies equal opportunity to each speaker, which turns the entire debate show into a bullfighting spectacle. A senior journalist, Abhisar Sharma, who has been a major critic of television debate culture, mentioned the influence of these meaningless debates on vulnerable minds, especially on younger viewers. The Rajiv Tyagi incident exposed the transition of these news debates from facts to fiction and from a platform to tackle important issues to an arena of verbal bloodshed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Changing Nature of TV&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-decided agendas of talk shows during prime time news often peddle hatred and biased opinions to the viewers. Vilification of particular communities and trial by media have become the new normal in the newsrooms. Airing these opinions during prime time with its massive reach of the audience and fixed timings gives legitimacy to biased news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people are openly targeted in the name of live reporting. Despite the recognition of toxicity on news channels, there seems to be no end to the shows that provoke such negativity in the country. A major reason for this is the benefit of such reporting in terms of the ratings and revenue of the news channels. Leading news reporters and editors fight for the same sensational viewership each day, which is why TRPs have become the game-changer and facts have taken backstage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While pursuing my Bachelor’s in Journalism, I read about the Propaganda Model of Communication advanced by&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_S._Herman&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edward S Herman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noam_Chomsky&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Noam Chomsky&lt;/a&gt;. This model explains media biases and the working of corporate media outlets. I see the relevance of this in today’s times. It also answers the question about the future of broadcast in our country, relating to the five filters that are mentioned under the model - ownership, advertising, sourcing, flack and fear. Each filter creates an inherent conflict of interest that drives the propaganda of the news channel in the pursuit of quality journalism. Commenting on media's “societal purpose,” Chomsky wrote in his book&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manufacturing_Consent&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;The mass media are interested in attracting audiences with buying power, not audiences per se; it is affluent audiences that spark advertiser interest today, as in the nineteenth century. The idea that the drive for large audiences makes the mass media ‘democratic’ thus suffers from the initial weakness that its political analogue is a voting system weighted by income!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that broadcast is not going to die anytime soon even though it receives massive backlash and hatred especially from independent media organisations and primarily from new media users because it is still the only source of information that people without internet facility have access to. The privilege of access to news sources plays a large role in news consumption in the country. As much as we look forward to the idea of ‘Digital India’,&amp;nbsp; increasing viewership and regional recognition have made television the biggest revenue grabbing medium in the industry, more than the internet. Ideally, the media industry should work upon the regulation of content that it delivers, which has to be more informational than just persuasive. The ethics of journalism need formal regulation because the selective interpretation of this by news channels has majorly contributed to the spread of biased facts. The tragic death of Rajiv Tyagi should be an eye-opener for public discourse compelling the political leaders, anchors, and the creators of the prime time news and TV shows to think of a media strategy that falls within the walls of what journalism truly stands for- objectivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Television has been the dominant form of entertainment in India for over thirty years. Around 850 million people have access to a TV set in India and these numbers not only reflect the large influence of TV in the social and political domains on its viewers but also how it has evolved to become the biggest marketing tool in the media sphere. While many sectors became stagnant with the outbreak of coronavirus, the television industry grabbed the attention of the millions that were confined to their homes during the lockdown. A captive audience celebrated the return of old classics like the Ramayana and Mahabharata in the quarantine period. However, the unethical growth and rising TRP of various channels also received huge backlash during the same time. This gave a reality check for the kind of information that was being sourced and the influence of the same on the viewers.&amp;nbsp; The Death of Rajiv Tyagi Digging deeper into the news sector, which is a major contributor to the television domain, we may consider the sudden passing away of the Indian National Congress National spokesperson Rajiv Tyagi on August 12, 2020. He passed away after a heart attack that occurred soon after a heated debate on a Hindi TV channel. This sparked a debate about the toxic debate culture of TV news. Commenting on this tragic incident, Professor Gaurav Vallabh, a Congress spokesperson, explained how titles of the debate show on news channels are divisive. Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) leader Nawab Malik commented on the format of the debates and how the anchor or the host of the show denies equal opportunity to each speaker, which turns the entire debate show into a bullfighting spectacle. A senior journalist, Abhisar Sharma, who has been a major critic of television debate culture, mentioned the influence of these meaningless debates on vulnerable minds, especially on younger viewers. The Rajiv Tyagi incident exposed the transition of these news debates from facts to fiction and from a platform to tackle important issues to an arena of verbal bloodshed.&amp;nbsp; Changing Nature of TV Pre-decided agendas of talk shows during prime time news often peddle hatred and biased opinions to the viewers. Vilification of particular communities and trial by media have become the new normal in the newsrooms. Airing these opinions during prime time with its massive reach of the audience and fixed timings gives legitimacy to biased news. Some people are openly targeted in the name of live reporting. Despite the recognition of toxicity on news channels, there seems to be no end to the shows that provoke such negativity in the country. A major reason for this is the benefit of such reporting in terms of the ratings and revenue of the news channels. Leading news reporters and editors fight for the same sensational viewership each day, which is why TRPs have become the game-changer and facts have taken backstage.&amp;nbsp; While pursuing my Bachelor’s in Journalism, I read about the Propaganda Model of Communication advanced by&amp;nbsp;Edward S Herman&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Noam Chomsky. This model explains media biases and the working of corporate media outlets. I see the relevance of this in today’s times. It also answers the question about the future of broadcast in our country, relating to the five filters that are mentioned under the model - ownership, advertising, sourcing, flack and fear. Each filter creates an inherent conflict of interest that drives the propaganda of the news channel in the pursuit of quality journalism. Commenting on media's “societal purpose,” Chomsky wrote in his book&amp;nbsp;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media, “The mass media are interested in attracting audiences with buying power, not audiences per se; it is affluent audiences that spark advertiser interest today, as in the nineteenth century. The idea that the drive for large audiences makes the mass media ‘democratic’ thus suffers from the initial weakness that its political analogue is a voting system weighted by income!” I feel that broadcast is not going to die anytime soon even though it receives massive backlash and hatred especially from independent media organisations and primarily from new media users because it is still the only source of information that people without internet facility have access to. The privilege of access to news sources plays a large role in news consumption in the country. As much as we look forward to the idea of ‘Digital India’,&amp;nbsp; increasing viewership and regional recognition have made television the biggest revenue grabbing medium in the industry, more than the internet. Ideally, the media industry should work upon the regulation of content that it delivers, which has to be more informational than just persuasive. The ethics of journalism need formal regulation because the selective interpretation of this by news channels has majorly contributed to the spread of biased facts. The tragic death of Rajiv Tyagi should be an eye-opener for public discourse compelling the political leaders, anchors, and the creators of the prime time news and TV shows to think of a media strategy that falls within the walls of what journalism truly stands for- objectivity.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Do People Still Listen to Radio in 2020?: A Decentralised Understanding of Radio Broadcasting in India</title>
      <link href="/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do People Still Listen to Radio in 2020?: A Decentralised Understanding of Radio Broadcasting in India " />
      <published>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020">&lt;p&gt;Mass media is generally used to disseminate information through various modes of communication. It helps in the exchange of ideas and information to large segments of society. Broadcast is a field of mass communication that transmits information, imparts knowledge and helps in creating a dialogue between the news agency and the audience via mediums like radio and television. The term ‘broadcast’ refers to visual or audio content dispersion to the people through electronic communication in a one-to-many module.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radio as a Mass Medium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Known as the ‘theatre of mind’, radio is the most pervasive, accessible and affordable mass media available in the developing world. It networks developing programmes to diverse populations and connects them all on the national and international levels. It is a cheap alternative to the glamourous mediums that have evolved with technology. The radio still remains a potential driver of information and entertainment to highly targeted audiences such as the rural population. Especially in a developing country, like India, this plays a major role in spreading information because most of the rural population is generally left bereft of the newer mechanisms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evolution of Radio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of the first radio program in India which was transmitted by the Madras Presidency Radio Club (MPRC) and led by C V Krishnaswami Cheti, was to stimulate interest, inform and instruct the public, and to foster the study of radio communications in the presidency. With the approval being given for the privatisation of radio media organisations by the British colonial government, the Indian Broadcasting Company set up radio stations in Calcutta and Bombay. In 1936, this corporation was renamed All India Radio (AIR), and when India became independent in 1947, AIR became a separate department under the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting. Presently, radio broadcasting gets coverage in 24 languages and 146 dialects all across India. 111 million households own a radio set in the country. Regional radio has reached all states individually, catering to its colloquial audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://d2r2ijn7njrktv.cloudfront.net/IL/uploads/2017/02/community-radio.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/community-radio.jpg&quot; /&gt;Community Radio stations are popular among all age groups and used extensively to spread awareness.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Broadcasting: Community Radio&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It refers to a type of radio service that caters to the interests of a particular person in an area. The primary focus is on the local population and issues concerning them. Use of broadcast here acts as a link between the community problems and the authorities who can do something about the resolution of the same. Community radio is a broadcast tool that is of the people, by the people and for the people. It is a decentralised use of the larger medium of communication, that is, the radio. It is important to talk about community radio in today’s times as it provides a platform to the local people to become citizen journalists and educate themselves and their fellow beings. While FM Radio caters to the urban population mostly, community radio’s target audience includes rural, urban, suburban, regional and sectional communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radio Udaan &lt;/strong&gt;is an example of community radio. Launched in 2014, it is an online radio station developed by and for specially-abled people. &amp;nbsp;It is the only type of radio station that is run by visually challenged people and is widely listened to in more than 115 countries. The vision of the radio station is broad and its agendas are diverse, which is- “&lt;em&gt;To entertain, empower and elevate the listeners. Radio Udaan aims to reach out to maximum possible people. It wants to become not only a supplier of entertainment and knowledge to the listeners but also a part of their daily routine, family and lifestyle. The station seeks to shoulder the burdens of its listeners by empowering them and listening to their stories and problems, and eventually catering them solutions&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apno Radio, 90.4 MHz, Rajasthan &lt;/strong&gt;was launched in 2005 and is Rajasthan’s first community radio station. The station’s objective is to promote self-reliance and women's empowerment. It focuses on several social issues ailing the rural communities of the state such as education, health, nutrition, environment, agriculture, depicting folk, art, culture, rural and community development.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is Radio Dying?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the millennials in urban life devote their maximum time to Apple Music and Spotify, this question often pops up with “yes” as an answer to it. However, that is not true. Radio is not dying but rather it is evolving. The term ‘Tradigital’ (traditional plus digital) is assigned to this evolution wherein traditional radio stations are using digital media platforms for two reasons - one, to expand their audience reach and two, to keep up with the technology and not let the broadcasting medium which has a reach of over 100 million people in India die because of the takeover by bigger and international online streaming platforms, television and satellite revolution. The newer versions of mass communications generally caters to a literate population with access to higher-end devices and it must be acknowledged that radio initially started to educate the uneducated and still plays a pivotal role in doing this duty as a medium of communication. Recognition of local broadcasting is crucial to its development and as we talk more about ‘Communication as a Development Source’ in the 21st century, community reach can boost the country’s process to achieve 2030 Sustainable Development Goals by imparting knowledge in a decentralised manner to the regional sections. Moreover, radio acts as a tool for both development and freedom which provides a platform for people to exercise their freedom of speech and expression, uphold the liberty of thought, especially with the growth of community radio.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this better, I would like to connect this with a media theory called the Knowledge Gap Theory of 1970. It is the brainchild of Philip J Tichenor, George A Donohue and Clarice N Olien. They explained the Knowledge Gap theory as “&lt;em&gt;the infusion of mass media information into a social system where higher socioeconomic status segments tend to acquire this information faster than lower socioeconomic status population segments. Hence&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;gap between the two tends to increase rather than decrease.&lt;/em&gt;” In 2020, these faster modes of communication can be through the accessibility of various sources of information. The availability of these mediums come with a price tag and not everyone can afford it. Radio and especially the growing community radio has revolutionised news delivery in various parts of the country that do not get the proper mainstream coverage in the primetime and are highly underrepresented and neglected in the little coverage that they receive. The only way to connect to the grassroots is by reducing this knowledge gap with a tool of communication. This is where the power of radio lies, in the heart of the community people who use this broadcasting medium to connect and embrace positive change in their society. A boost to a media platform which caters to the lower rungs of the socio-economic ladder is necessary in these times when inequality and unemployment are raging and the youth is being fed with narratives filled with hatred and bigotry. This medium can be the harbinger of change in the society for the better, we just have to care enough about the people left behind to dedicate ourselves to such discourse. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Mass media is generally used to disseminate information through various modes of communication. It helps in the exchange of ideas and information to large segments of society. Broadcast is a field of mass communication that transmits information, imparts knowledge and helps in creating a dialogue between the news agency and the audience via mediums like radio and television. The term ‘broadcast’ refers to visual or audio content dispersion to the people through electronic communication in a one-to-many module.&amp;nbsp; Radio as a Mass Medium Known as the ‘theatre of mind’, radio is the most pervasive, accessible and affordable mass media available in the developing world. It networks developing programmes to diverse populations and connects them all on the national and international levels. It is a cheap alternative to the glamourous mediums that have evolved with technology. The radio still remains a potential driver of information and entertainment to highly targeted audiences such as the rural population. Especially in a developing country, like India, this plays a major role in spreading information because most of the rural population is generally left bereft of the newer mechanisms.&amp;nbsp; Evolution of Radio The objective of the first radio program in India which was transmitted by the Madras Presidency Radio Club (MPRC) and led by C V Krishnaswami Cheti, was to stimulate interest, inform and instruct the public, and to foster the study of radio communications in the presidency. With the approval being given for the privatisation of radio media organisations by the British colonial government, the Indian Broadcasting Company set up radio stations in Calcutta and Bombay. In 1936, this corporation was renamed All India Radio (AIR), and when India became independent in 1947, AIR became a separate department under the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting. Presently, radio broadcasting gets coverage in 24 languages and 146 dialects all across India. 111 million households own a radio set in the country. Regional radio has reached all states individually, catering to its colloquial audience. Community Radio stations are popular among all age groups and used extensively to spread awareness. Local Broadcasting: Community Radio&amp;nbsp; It refers to a type of radio service that caters to the interests of a particular person in an area. The primary focus is on the local population and issues concerning them. Use of broadcast here acts as a link between the community problems and the authorities who can do something about the resolution of the same. Community radio is a broadcast tool that is of the people, by the people and for the people. It is a decentralised use of the larger medium of communication, that is, the radio. It is important to talk about community radio in today’s times as it provides a platform to the local people to become citizen journalists and educate themselves and their fellow beings. While FM Radio caters to the urban population mostly, community radio’s target audience includes rural, urban, suburban, regional and sectional communities.&amp;nbsp; Radio Udaan is an example of community radio. Launched in 2014, it is an online radio station developed by and for specially-abled people. &amp;nbsp;It is the only type of radio station that is run by visually challenged people and is widely listened to in more than 115 countries. The vision of the radio station is broad and its agendas are diverse, which is- “To entertain, empower and elevate the listeners. Radio Udaan aims to reach out to maximum possible people. It wants to become not only a supplier of entertainment and knowledge to the listeners but also a part of their daily routine, family and lifestyle. The station seeks to shoulder the burdens of its listeners by empowering them and listening to their stories and problems, and eventually catering them solutions.” Apno Radio, 90.4 MHz, Rajasthan was launched in 2005 and is Rajasthan’s first community radio station. The station’s objective is to promote self-reliance and women's empowerment. It focuses on several social issues ailing the rural communities of the state such as education, health, nutrition, environment, agriculture, depicting folk, art, culture, rural and community development.&amp;nbsp; Is Radio Dying? While the millennials in urban life devote their maximum time to Apple Music and Spotify, this question often pops up with “yes” as an answer to it. However, that is not true. Radio is not dying but rather it is evolving. The term ‘Tradigital’ (traditional plus digital) is assigned to this evolution wherein traditional radio stations are using digital media platforms for two reasons - one, to expand their audience reach and two, to keep up with the technology and not let the broadcasting medium which has a reach of over 100 million people in India die because of the takeover by bigger and international online streaming platforms, television and satellite revolution. The newer versions of mass communications generally caters to a literate population with access to higher-end devices and it must be acknowledged that radio initially started to educate the uneducated and still plays a pivotal role in doing this duty as a medium of communication. Recognition of local broadcasting is crucial to its development and as we talk more about ‘Communication as a Development Source’ in the 21st century, community reach can boost the country’s process to achieve 2030 Sustainable Development Goals by imparting knowledge in a decentralised manner to the regional sections. Moreover, radio acts as a tool for both development and freedom which provides a platform for people to exercise their freedom of speech and expression, uphold the liberty of thought, especially with the growth of community radio.&amp;nbsp; To understand this better, I would like to connect this with a media theory called the Knowledge Gap Theory of 1970. It is the brainchild of Philip J Tichenor, George A Donohue and Clarice N Olien. They explained the Knowledge Gap theory as “the infusion of mass media information into a social system where higher socioeconomic status segments tend to acquire this information faster than lower socioeconomic status population segments. Hence&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;gap between the two tends to increase rather than decrease.” In 2020, these faster modes of communication can be through the accessibility of various sources of information. The availability of these mediums come with a price tag and not everyone can afford it. Radio and especially the growing community radio has revolutionised news delivery in various parts of the country that do not get the proper mainstream coverage in the primetime and are highly underrepresented and neglected in the little coverage that they receive. The only way to connect to the grassroots is by reducing this knowledge gap with a tool of communication. This is where the power of radio lies, in the heart of the community people who use this broadcasting medium to connect and embrace positive change in their society. A boost to a media platform which caters to the lower rungs of the socio-economic ladder is necessary in these times when inequality and unemployment are raging and the youth is being fed with narratives filled with hatred and bigotry. This medium can be the harbinger of change in the society for the better, we just have to care enough about the people left behind to dedicate ourselves to such discourse.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Photograph</title>
      <link href="/The-Photograph" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Photograph" />
      <published>2020-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Photograph</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Photograph">&lt;p&gt;The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photojournalism is a subset of broadcast journalism, referring to the presentation of a news story through photographs. The use of the medium of photography to compliment a news article or fully tell a story on its own has been a major source of authentic information and facts presentation. However, in order to understand the meaning of ‘photojournalism’, it is important to trace the legacy of it and examine the ways in which it was used in the period when we did not have a term to define this type of art. Here is one such early news story that made it to the headlines and grabbed the attention of its target audience by the camera’s capture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/f/fe/W._Eugene_Smith_-_Tomoko_Uemura_in_Her_Bath.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tomokobath.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup of this photograph is a Japanese, black and white image captured in 1971.  American photojournalist W Eugene Smith captured ‘Tomoko Uemura in Her Bath’, a photograph of a mother holding her severely deformed and naked child in a bathroom. The photojournalist wanted to depict the severity of the disease, Minamata, which is caused by mercury poisoning. It was first discovered in Minamata city of Japan, in 1956. Loss of peripheral vision, numbness in body muscles, and damage of speech and hearing are some of the symptoms. In extreme cases, it also affects foetuses in the womb.  This was not the only photograph that Smith picked to depict the trauma and condition of the people affected in Japan. He picked several photos that even made it to some of the publications, but he was searching for one striking photograph to gain the attention of the entire world. Smith had a symbolic vision of this photograph in his mind before he actually captured it and turned it into a reality. He explained his idea to Tomoko Uemura’s parents and when they agreed to get their daughter clicked, Smith began working on the set up of the photograph. Tomoko Uemura wanted the photo to depict the reality and plight of the people affected and dying in Minamata because of the pollution. Ryoko Uemura (mother) wanted a sympathetic portrayal of the photograph of her daughter and helped Smith in developing his ideas for the shots. She herself suggested the bathing chamber as the location of the photograph. The final capture was done on a chilly evening in December 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first publication of the photograph was done in 1972 in the American magazine, &lt;em&gt;Life&lt;/em&gt;, as a centrepiece for a short photo essay on Minamata. Smith developed an entire book featuring all his clicks of the disease. This photo became famous globally and shed light on the victims, raising their concerns of compensation. With this attention came rumours that Ryoko Uemura’s family was financially benefiting from all the interviews as the photograph had brought them into the spotlight. This intensified worries that the rumours might have an impact on Tomoko’s mental health. Tomoko died at the age of 21 in 1977. The photograph was withdrawn from publication in 1997, 20 years after Tomoko’s death, as per the wishes of the family. They refused the copyright on the photograph and interviews as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s father said &lt;em&gt;“I wanted Tomoko to be laid to rest and this feeling was growing steadily”&lt;/em&gt; in a refusal to permit exploitation of his daughter’s photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s capture brings to light a lot of aspects involved in the field of photojournalism, both from the reporter’s side and the victim’s side. There is always a story that is carried by an image on a news media platform and there are hundreds of stories behind that one capture. Only a photojournalist is remotely close to knowing them in detail. Photojournalism is a globally recognised and much-appreciated form of journalism today. It is an artistic presentation based on the recognition of realism in stories that are constantly changing and evolving as the audience awaits new concepts of storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W Eugene Smith’s journey provides us with insights of photojournalism in the western nations, whereas when talking specifically about the Indian context, many consider Kulwant Roy as a pioneer of Indian Photojournalism. He was one of the photographers who captured the birth of independent India and documented the freedom struggle. Digital photography and online editing have been revolutionary evolutions in photography, but realism is what attaches the term journalism and ethics to these captures. This is one of the major reasons why archival photos of Eugene Smith and Kulwant Roy are till date found to be inspirational to many growing photojournalists. It is interesting to see how far the camera’s click can deliver the news to its target audiences and whether or not it will take over the conventional mediums of journalism reporting in the digital era.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Transgender Bill 2019: A Step Taken Backwards?</title>
      <link href="/Transgender-Bill-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgender Bill 2019: A Step Taken Backwards?" />
      <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Transgender-Bill-2019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Transgender-Bill-2019">&lt;p&gt;On November 26, 2019, the Indian Parliament passed the Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill which provides us with the definition of a transgender as ‘someone whose gender does not match the one assigned at birth’. It also allows the self-perception of gender identity and criminalises begging. The entire process, presentation, amendments, drafting, and passing of the bill faced varied opinions from the public sphere as well as the entire community of LGBTQIA in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill prohibits discrimination against transgenders in educational institutions, government establishments, while using public services, etc. It also allows the right to ‘self-perceived’ gender identity. The policymakers argue that the bill leads to the development of the community with the formation of a National Council for Transgender Persons (NCPT) that will help and advise the government on formulation policies for the community, monitor implementation, address grievances, etc. There have been many instances where families disown their children when they come out about their identity at home. The bill will, hence, provide rehabilitation centre placement for transgenders whose family is unable to take care of them. This enforces a minor’s right of residence of compelling any trans person below 18 years to cohabit with their natal family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the communities and the people opposing the bill feel that it is straight-up against the right to dignity and bodily autonomy of transgenders. Grace Banu, a Dalit transgender rights activist, said that the bill was a “murder of gender and justice” and it did not uplift the community. According to gender activist, Harish Iyer, the Bill is regressive in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill was passed without approaching anyone from the community of transgenders. The process to obtain a transgender certificate has many fallouts. Apart from being an expensive procedure, it raises questions of violation of privacy. Also, there is no classification on how District Magistrate will examine the person based on their documents. The bill does not specify the ‘kind’ of surgery it is expecting because there is more than one type. This also contradicts 2014 NALSA (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Legal_Services_Authority_v._Union_of_India&quot;&gt;National Legal Services Authority v. Union of India&lt;/a&gt;) judgment by the Supreme Court that gave the right to self-identify and did not mandate surgery. Reflecting upon the lack of education, the bill conflates transgenders with intersex people. It fails to define what sexual abuse is. Even the punishment is not fully justified. In case of the rape of a woman, jail of 7 years or life sentence is given as punishment to the person who committed the crime, whereas, if the same happens with a transgender, a minimum of 6 months of jail which can be extended to just 2 years has been defined under the bill. There is no mention of marriage rights, property rights, and reservations for those who belong to disadvantaged groups, social security, or pension. This is nothing but deprivation of basic fundamental rights to the community, I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, I would like to address the problem with rehabilitation centre provision in the bill. Domestic violence has prevailed against transgenders and is clearly evident through examples from the past and present. Here’s what will happen now. A person will be forced to come out to their family which will not only violate their right to privacy but will also lead to mental pressure of how things will turn out. The intensity of ‘what ifs’ is something that cannot be measured by someone who is not facing anything close to this and in a country like India, domestic households do not operate with same ideologies and beliefs for immediate acceptance due to many reasons, lack of education being the primary factor in this case. People join LGBTQ groups or NGOs because they find a home away from their own. If a person in today’s situation wants to leave home then they will be placed in a rehabilitation centre without choice. This denies the rights of a person to join the trans community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the bill makes a feeble attempt at understanding the concept and difference between sex and gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entire process of the bill- from its presentation to its implementation- didn’t make to the headlines as it was concealed by other headliners in the news. When the bill was presented in Lok Sabha, it was overshadowed by the revocation of Article 370 and 35A in the Indian Constitution. When Rajya Sabha passed the bill, the political crisis of Uddhav Thackeray being elected as the new Chief Minister of Maharashtra on November 28, 2019, took over the media platforms. By the time the bill came into effect, the novel coronavirus disease took most of the headliners in news. Although through the efforts of independent media organisations, online social media coverage, art and activism, and voices from the trans communities, LGBTQIA groups and NGOs did grab the attention of the public of India. Some of them feel that Transgender Bill 2019 is transphobia in action. It is a direct violation of the Supreme Court judgment that was passed in 2014 (NALSA vs UOI) that acknowledged the fundamental rights of transgender people in India. The bill reduces the people to just their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, the stigma towards transgenders is prevalent in the Indian society, and when an act like this is passed without consultation of the very people it is designed for, the country as a whole takes a step backwards in its development process.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On November 26, 2019, the Indian Parliament passed the Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill which provides us with the definition of a transgender as ‘someone whose gender does not match the one assigned at birth’. It also allows the self-perception of gender identity and criminalises begging. The entire process, presentation, amendments, drafting, and passing of the bill faced varied opinions from the public sphere as well as the entire community of LGBTQIA in India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Vultures’ 2020</title>
      <link href="/Vultures-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Vultures’ 2020" />
      <published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Vultures-2020</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Vultures-2020">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;I’m really, really sorry. The pain of life overrides the joy to the point that joy does not exist. …depressed … without (a) phone … money for rent … money for child support … money for debts … money!!! … I am haunted by the vivid memories of killings &amp;amp; corpses &amp;amp; anger &amp;amp; pain … of starving or wounded children, of trigger-happy madmen, often police, of killer executioners …&lt;/em&gt;” - Kevin Carter (an excerpt from his suicide note)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 28, 2020, during an Indian Supreme Court hearing on the humanitarian crisis faced by the intra-state migrant workers due to the nationwide lockdown, Tushar Mehta, the Solicitor General (SG) of India, referred to the story of Kevin Carter, a South African photojournalist who won the Pulitzer Prize for depicting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1993_Sudan_famine&quot;&gt;1993 famine in Sudan&lt;/a&gt; through a photograph titled “The Vulture and The Little Girl.” Troubled by all that he had seen, Carter committed suicide at the age of 33.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/nostri-imago/5000121934&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//sudan_famine1993.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narrating this from an archival perspective, Tushar Mehta aimed this towards the way the media is reporting the ongoing migrant crisis; by displaying their visuals, using mounting death tolls as headlines. According to Mehta, the ones documenting this are nothing but ‘vultures’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this very documentation led the Supreme Court to issue a notice to all governments, ordering the Indian Central government and the State governments to immediately provide free-of-cost transport, food, and shelter to migrant workers on May 26, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faye D’Souza, a journalist, retweeted the Supreme Court’s entire conversation and raised a very relevant question – “Would he (SG) prefer if these stories were never told?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a journalism student, I have had and have read plenty of comments and opinions towards the media. I have tried to differentiate criticism from mockery and take the constructive part out of the two. However, statements like the one made by the SG make me feel that even the courts in my country aren’t democratic but just political in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine, &lt;em&gt;Caravan&lt;/em&gt;, in an article on May 28, 2020, reflects upon the plight of the journalists reporting during the pandemic. A snippet from the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Every journalist who has been reporting on the pandemic has been traumatised by what they saw or reported. No one has done it for a moral license to feel better about themselves—this work, in fact, has the opposite effect on journalists. Over time, it changes you forever. The activist, filmmaker, and writer Susan Sontag summed up this journalistic dilemma best: “The person who intervenes cannot record; the person who is recording cannot intervene.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SG, however, told &lt;em&gt;The Times of India&lt;/em&gt; that his statement was being misread as he was referring to some of the pseudo-NGO (Non-Governmental Organisation) workers who have just been criticising the government and the Court for doing nothing when they themselves also haven’t contributed enough to make the situation better for the migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, I personally feel that the justification given here is not exactly matching with the description the SG gave about the journalists in the court. The fact that the SG thought that the documentation could have been done in a better way is nothing but a step back towards blurring the lines of reality presentation by the fourth pillar of democracy. Is this not against the ethics of journalism? Has journalism been reduced to comfort news and neglecting the underprivileged? Is journalism NOT about grabbing the attention of the authorities in charge that have turned too blind to see the plight of the very people that made them sit in power today? Is journalism NOT about raising the voices of the voiceless? Yet the journalists who have been doing all this as responsible media personnel, at the expense of their own health during the pandemic, have been termed as ‘vultures’ in the Court? The SG has forgotten that the ones he claims to be vultures also got the country THREE Pulitizer Prizes 2020 for feature photography depicting the plight of Kashmir after the revocation of Article 370 by the Indian government in August 2019. In places like Kashmir, journalists themselves become stories and their work instead of being appreciated is reduced to zero or charged under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA) by its very own government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journalists like Barkha Dutt have been on road since the past 70-80 days covering the pandemic crisis and helping the migrants get adequate attention so that they reach their homes safely. They are out on the field and are away from their quarantined safe places, documenting stories of the ones who want to go to their own homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So probably for the next time, I can only hope there is a decent amount of respect for the ones who are actually contributing to help the fellow members of the society instead of passing a generalised bland statement for all the media because, in that way, you not only disrespect the journalists working on the documentation but also the sufferers who want to be voiced.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I’m really, really sorry. The pain of life overrides the joy to the point that joy does not exist. …depressed … without (a) phone … money for rent … money for child support … money for debts … money!!! … I am haunted by the vivid memories of killings &amp;amp; corpses &amp;amp; anger &amp;amp; pain … of starving or wounded children, of trigger-happy madmen, often police, of killer executioners …” - Kevin Carter (an excerpt from his suicide note)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
