<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/himanshi.saini/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-20T13:11:20+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/himanshi.saini/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Photograph</title>
      <link href="/The-Photograph" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Photograph" />
      <published>2020-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Photograph</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Photograph">&lt;p&gt;The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photojournalism is a subset of broadcast journalism, referring to the presentation of a news story through photographs. The use of the medium of photography to compliment a news article or fully tell a story on its own has been a major source of authentic information and facts presentation. However, in order to understand the meaning of ‘photojournalism’, it is important to trace the legacy of it and examine the ways in which it was used in the period when we did not have a term to define this type of art. Here is one such early news story that made it to the headlines and grabbed the attention of its target audience by the camera’s capture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/f/fe/W._Eugene_Smith_-_Tomoko_Uemura_in_Her_Bath.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tomokobath.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup of this photograph is a Japanese, black and white image captured in 1971.  American photojournalist W Eugene Smith captured ‘Tomoko Uemura in Her Bath’, a photograph of a mother holding her severely deformed and naked child in a bathroom. The photojournalist wanted to depict the severity of the disease, Minamata, which is caused by mercury poisoning. It was first discovered in Minamata city of Japan, in 1956. Loss of peripheral vision, numbness in body muscles, and damage of speech and hearing are some of the symptoms. In extreme cases, it also affects foetuses in the womb.  This was not the only photograph that Smith picked to depict the trauma and condition of the people affected in Japan. He picked several photos that even made it to some of the publications, but he was searching for one striking photograph to gain the attention of the entire world. Smith had a symbolic vision of this photograph in his mind before he actually captured it and turned it into a reality. He explained his idea to Tomoko Uemura’s parents and when they agreed to get their daughter clicked, Smith began working on the set up of the photograph. Tomoko Uemura wanted the photo to depict the reality and plight of the people affected and dying in Minamata because of the pollution. Ryoko Uemura (mother) wanted a sympathetic portrayal of the photograph of her daughter and helped Smith in developing his ideas for the shots. She herself suggested the bathing chamber as the location of the photograph. The final capture was done on a chilly evening in December 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first publication of the photograph was done in 1972 in the American magazine, &lt;em&gt;Life&lt;/em&gt;, as a centrepiece for a short photo essay on Minamata. Smith developed an entire book featuring all his clicks of the disease. This photo became famous globally and shed light on the victims, raising their concerns of compensation. With this attention came rumours that Ryoko Uemura’s family was financially benefiting from all the interviews as the photograph had brought them into the spotlight. This intensified worries that the rumours might have an impact on Tomoko’s mental health. Tomoko died at the age of 21 in 1977. The photograph was withdrawn from publication in 1997, 20 years after Tomoko’s death, as per the wishes of the family. They refused the copyright on the photograph and interviews as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s father said &lt;em&gt;“I wanted Tomoko to be laid to rest and this feeling was growing steadily”&lt;/em&gt; in a refusal to permit exploitation of his daughter’s photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s capture brings to light a lot of aspects involved in the field of photojournalism, both from the reporter’s side and the victim’s side. There is always a story that is carried by an image on a news media platform and there are hundreds of stories behind that one capture. Only a photojournalist is remotely close to knowing them in detail. Photojournalism is a globally recognised and much-appreciated form of journalism today. It is an artistic presentation based on the recognition of realism in stories that are constantly changing and evolving as the audience awaits new concepts of storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W Eugene Smith’s journey provides us with insights of photojournalism in the western nations, whereas when talking specifically about the Indian context, many consider Kulwant Roy as a pioneer of Indian Photojournalism. He was one of the photographers who captured the birth of independent India and documented the freedom struggle. Digital photography and online editing have been revolutionary evolutions in photography, but realism is what attaches the term journalism and ethics to these captures. This is one of the major reasons why archival photos of Eugene Smith and Kulwant Roy are till date found to be inspirational to many growing photojournalists. It is interesting to see how far the camera’s click can deliver the news to its target audiences and whether or not it will take over the conventional mediums of journalism reporting in the digital era.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Transgender Bill 2019: A Step Taken Backwards?</title>
      <link href="/Transgender-Bill-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgender Bill 2019: A Step Taken Backwards?" />
      <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Transgender-Bill-2019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Transgender-Bill-2019">&lt;p&gt;On November 26, 2019, the Indian Parliament passed the Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill which provides us with the definition of a transgender as ‘someone whose gender does not match the one assigned at birth’. It also allows the self-perception of gender identity and criminalises begging. The entire process, presentation, amendments, drafting, and passing of the bill faced varied opinions from the public sphere as well as the entire community of LGBTQIA in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill prohibits discrimination against transgenders in educational institutions, government establishments, while using public services, etc. It also allows the right to ‘self-perceived’ gender identity. The policymakers argue that the bill leads to the development of the community with the formation of a National Council for Transgender Persons (NCPT) that will help and advise the government on formulation policies for the community, monitor implementation, address grievances, etc. There have been many instances where families disown their children when they come out about their identity at home. The bill will, hence, provide rehabilitation centre placement for transgenders whose family is unable to take care of them. This enforces a minor’s right of residence of compelling any trans person below 18 years to cohabit with their natal family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the communities and the people opposing the bill feel that it is straight-up against the right to dignity and bodily autonomy of transgenders. Grace Banu, a Dalit transgender rights activist, said that the bill was a “murder of gender and justice” and it did not uplift the community. According to gender activist, Harish Iyer, the Bill is regressive in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill was passed without approaching anyone from the community of transgenders. The process to obtain a transgender certificate has many fallouts. Apart from being an expensive procedure, it raises questions of violation of privacy. Also, there is no classification on how District Magistrate will examine the person based on their documents. The bill does not specify the ‘kind’ of surgery it is expecting because there is more than one type. This also contradicts 2014 NALSA (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Legal_Services_Authority_v._Union_of_India&quot;&gt;National Legal Services Authority v. Union of India&lt;/a&gt;) judgment by the Supreme Court that gave the right to self-identify and did not mandate surgery. Reflecting upon the lack of education, the bill conflates transgenders with intersex people. It fails to define what sexual abuse is. Even the punishment is not fully justified. In case of the rape of a woman, jail of 7 years or life sentence is given as punishment to the person who committed the crime, whereas, if the same happens with a transgender, a minimum of 6 months of jail which can be extended to just 2 years has been defined under the bill. There is no mention of marriage rights, property rights, and reservations for those who belong to disadvantaged groups, social security, or pension. This is nothing but deprivation of basic fundamental rights to the community, I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, I would like to address the problem with rehabilitation centre provision in the bill. Domestic violence has prevailed against transgenders and is clearly evident through examples from the past and present. Here’s what will happen now. A person will be forced to come out to their family which will not only violate their right to privacy but will also lead to mental pressure of how things will turn out. The intensity of ‘what ifs’ is something that cannot be measured by someone who is not facing anything close to this and in a country like India, domestic households do not operate with same ideologies and beliefs for immediate acceptance due to many reasons, lack of education being the primary factor in this case. People join LGBTQ groups or NGOs because they find a home away from their own. If a person in today’s situation wants to leave home then they will be placed in a rehabilitation centre without choice. This denies the rights of a person to join the trans community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the bill makes a feeble attempt at understanding the concept and difference between sex and gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entire process of the bill- from its presentation to its implementation- didn’t make to the headlines as it was concealed by other headliners in the news. When the bill was presented in Lok Sabha, it was overshadowed by the revocation of Article 370 and 35A in the Indian Constitution. When Rajya Sabha passed the bill, the political crisis of Uddhav Thackeray being elected as the new Chief Minister of Maharashtra on November 28, 2019, took over the media platforms. By the time the bill came into effect, the novel coronavirus disease took most of the headliners in news. Although through the efforts of independent media organisations, online social media coverage, art and activism, and voices from the trans communities, LGBTQIA groups and NGOs did grab the attention of the public of India. Some of them feel that Transgender Bill 2019 is transphobia in action. It is a direct violation of the Supreme Court judgment that was passed in 2014 (NALSA vs UOI) that acknowledged the fundamental rights of transgender people in India. The bill reduces the people to just their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, the stigma towards transgenders is prevalent in the Indian society, and when an act like this is passed without consultation of the very people it is designed for, the country as a whole takes a step backwards in its development process.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On November 26, 2019, the Indian Parliament passed the Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill which provides us with the definition of a transgender as ‘someone whose gender does not match the one assigned at birth’. It also allows the self-perception of gender identity and criminalises begging. The entire process, presentation, amendments, drafting, and passing of the bill faced varied opinions from the public sphere as well as the entire community of LGBTQIA in India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Vultures’ 2020</title>
      <link href="/Vultures-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Vultures’ 2020" />
      <published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Vultures-2020</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Vultures-2020">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;I’m really, really sorry. The pain of life overrides the joy to the point that joy does not exist. …depressed … without (a) phone … money for rent … money for child support … money for debts … money!!! … I am haunted by the vivid memories of killings &amp;amp; corpses &amp;amp; anger &amp;amp; pain … of starving or wounded children, of trigger-happy madmen, often police, of killer executioners …&lt;/em&gt;” - Kevin Carter (an excerpt from his suicide note)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 28, 2020, during an Indian Supreme Court hearing on the humanitarian crisis faced by the intra-state migrant workers due to the nationwide lockdown, Tushar Mehta, the Solicitor General (SG) of India, referred to the story of Kevin Carter, a South African photojournalist who won the Pulitzer Prize for depicting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1993_Sudan_famine&quot;&gt;1993 famine in Sudan&lt;/a&gt; through a photograph titled “The Vulture and The Little Girl.” Troubled by all that he had seen, Carter committed suicide at the age of 33.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/nostri-imago/5000121934&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//sudan_famine1993.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narrating this from an archival perspective, Tushar Mehta aimed this towards the way the media is reporting the ongoing migrant crisis; by displaying their visuals, using mounting death tolls as headlines. According to Mehta, the ones documenting this are nothing but ‘vultures’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this very documentation led the Supreme Court to issue a notice to all governments, ordering the Indian Central government and the State governments to immediately provide free-of-cost transport, food, and shelter to migrant workers on May 26, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faye D’Souza, a journalist, retweeted the Supreme Court’s entire conversation and raised a very relevant question – “Would he (SG) prefer if these stories were never told?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a journalism student, I have had and have read plenty of comments and opinions towards the media. I have tried to differentiate criticism from mockery and take the constructive part out of the two. However, statements like the one made by the SG make me feel that even the courts in my country aren’t democratic but just political in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine, &lt;em&gt;Caravan&lt;/em&gt;, in an article on May 28, 2020, reflects upon the plight of the journalists reporting during the pandemic. A snippet from the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Every journalist who has been reporting on the pandemic has been traumatised by what they saw or reported. No one has done it for a moral license to feel better about themselves—this work, in fact, has the opposite effect on journalists. Over time, it changes you forever. The activist, filmmaker, and writer Susan Sontag summed up this journalistic dilemma best: “The person who intervenes cannot record; the person who is recording cannot intervene.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SG, however, told &lt;em&gt;The Times of India&lt;/em&gt; that his statement was being misread as he was referring to some of the pseudo-NGO (Non-Governmental Organisation) workers who have just been criticising the government and the Court for doing nothing when they themselves also haven’t contributed enough to make the situation better for the migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, I personally feel that the justification given here is not exactly matching with the description the SG gave about the journalists in the court. The fact that the SG thought that the documentation could have been done in a better way is nothing but a step back towards blurring the lines of reality presentation by the fourth pillar of democracy. Is this not against the ethics of journalism? Has journalism been reduced to comfort news and neglecting the underprivileged? Is journalism NOT about grabbing the attention of the authorities in charge that have turned too blind to see the plight of the very people that made them sit in power today? Is journalism NOT about raising the voices of the voiceless? Yet the journalists who have been doing all this as responsible media personnel, at the expense of their own health during the pandemic, have been termed as ‘vultures’ in the Court? The SG has forgotten that the ones he claims to be vultures also got the country THREE Pulitizer Prizes 2020 for feature photography depicting the plight of Kashmir after the revocation of Article 370 by the Indian government in August 2019. In places like Kashmir, journalists themselves become stories and their work instead of being appreciated is reduced to zero or charged under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA) by its very own government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journalists like Barkha Dutt have been on road since the past 70-80 days covering the pandemic crisis and helping the migrants get adequate attention so that they reach their homes safely. They are out on the field and are away from their quarantined safe places, documenting stories of the ones who want to go to their own homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So probably for the next time, I can only hope there is a decent amount of respect for the ones who are actually contributing to help the fellow members of the society instead of passing a generalised bland statement for all the media because, in that way, you not only disrespect the journalists working on the documentation but also the sufferers who want to be voiced.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I’m really, really sorry. The pain of life overrides the joy to the point that joy does not exist. …depressed … without (a) phone … money for rent … money for child support … money for debts … money!!! … I am haunted by the vivid memories of killings &amp;amp; corpses &amp;amp; anger &amp;amp; pain … of starving or wounded children, of trigger-happy madmen, often police, of killer executioners …” - Kevin Carter (an excerpt from his suicide note)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
