<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/namya.tewari/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-03T23:47:34+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/namya.tewari/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Modern Slavery: Inside the Transgender Communities of India and Pakistan</title>
      <link href="/Modern-Slavery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Slavery: Inside the Transgender Communities of India and Pakistan" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Modern-Slavery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Modern-Slavery">&lt;p&gt;Our world is imbued with contradictions and opposing realities which inform our lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in our social setting. While some reap benefits of the rights and privileges bestowed upon them, others remain tangled in the subjugating mesh of society. The trapped transgenders either end up mangled under the massive burden of gender roles or end up conforming to the gender expectations ascribed to the sex in which they were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; born, as a means of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accident of birth has had serious ramifications on many, but none have been affected as gravely as the transgender. Betrayed by their bodies, and disowned by their families and communities, the transgender (including the eunuch and the intersex), popularly termed as &lt;em&gt;hijras&lt;/em&gt; in India and Pakistan, live as social outcasts, misfits for committing the grave crime of expressing their identities. Their existence itself poses a great threat to social conceptions of gender and sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in such countries, especially Pakistan where a manic obsession with gender roles reigns over every soul, certainly isn’t easy. The slightest deviation from societal conventions may result in ostracisation and humiliation; primarily the reason why the community is forced into darkness, into total seclusion. The expression of individuality comes at the great price of losing honour and respect. Having been stripped of all rights and dignity, they are forced into begging, prostitution, dancing as a means to earn their living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of mankind has largely revolved around freedom, power and recognition. It is a human need to be recognised and respected by others. Our identities form the very basis of our personhood. This is primarily why we assert ourselves wherever we go. We want our presence to be felt. But what if somebody just takes it all away from us? It would cause a massive dent on our personhood. This is precisely what the transgender community undergoes. Society robs them of their personhood. Life for them is suffering; it begins with gender dysphoria and their struggle to recognise themselves and ends with society deeming them as weeds unfit to be with others; the &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forced to remain hidden from the public eye, they form secret communities that observe their own mysterious codes and customs. One such custom is the rite of initiation, where every new transgender wishing to join the community must go through the painful procedure of emasculation and then be accepted by a &lt;em&gt;guru&lt;/em&gt;, who assumes a paternalistic role in the life of the newly initiated novice. The guru – novice relationship forms the bedrock of the transgender community. This is where things start turning really dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initiate or the novice, who is purchased in exchange of money, is literally at the mercy of the guru. She is penalised and punished severely if she fails to discharge the duties imposed on her. And if at all she decides to leave, she is shunned from the entire community. After being purchased, the novice is then forced by the guru into performing professions like begging, dancing, etc. to earn money; a major chunk of which goes to the guru. This practice almost seems like a modern form of slavery, but because of how inherent it is to the culture, it goes unquestioned and unopposed. Sadly, the tradition which was created to protect starts fettering them and taking away their freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the tremendous pressure imposed by the gurus, the novices at times may even have to indulge in sex work for money. Since they are denied all respectable jobs, several transgenders have to undergo this torment. They are coerced, tortured, raped- all under the knowledge of their gurus. Unable to complain to the authorities and fearing further harassment, they are forced to remain silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the young transgender, there remains no respite. On one end, they have to deal with repression from society and on the other, the monopoly of the greedy gurus. Another threat looming over their reality is the possibility of acquiring sexually transmitted diseases. Living in denial, they refuse to get themselves medically examined and continue living in unsafe conditions. They, nevertheless, continue existing, because for them nothing can surpass the feeling of power that comes along with expressing oneself and getting acknowledged as the person one wishes to be. The exhibition of identity becomes the sole purpose of their existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the guru-novice relationship, it’s important to understand that no cultural practice is free of fault. As in the case of this relationship, every cultural practice harbours in itself certain forms of darkness, often hidden from the rest of the world. The only way out here, is for change to come from the outside, so that these cultural practices automatically dismantle and disintegrate, without being meddled with. Change is slowly coming about; transgenders in India and Pakistan are being recognised as a third gender. With a state-issued identity of their own, they can now avail opportunities previously known only to the two genders, and therefore, reduce their dependence on the guru-novice practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acceptance in society can only come with greater visibility. For an all-inclusive world, the transgender community, with all its eccentricity and richness, must be integrated into the mainstream of society. There exists a need to create space for identity to breathe, which must then be recognised and respected. Especially in Asian countries where these groups are attached to labels of abnormality, there is a necessity to uproot the social stigma surrounding their existence. This can only happen when we begin to recognise them as humans before ascribing a gender identity to them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our world is imbued with contradictions and opposing realities which inform our lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in our social setting. While some reap benefits of the rights and privileges bestowed upon them, others remain tangled in the subjugating mesh of society. The trapped transgenders either end up mangled under the massive burden of gender roles or end up conforming to the gender expectations ascribed to the sex in which they were not born, as a means of expression.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Stoic’s Path to Happiness</title>
      <link href="/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Stoic’s Path to Happiness" />
      <published>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness">&lt;p&gt;Call it an endless string of experiences or a series of vivid sensations of the world around, we are all suffering from a mysterious condition, called life or existence. Existence is difficult to define in objective terms. One can only derive a vague understanding of existence through the complex fabric of encounters and experiences that shape how we see the world. But does one’s myopic and vague understanding stop one from expressing one’s subjective take on the matter? Certainly not. Discussions on existence have permeated through the history of humankind. Myriad answers have been proposed and rejected over the years but a solitary troubling question has remained unchanged: what is the best way to live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the peculiar existential ‘situatedness’ that is exclusive to every individual, there remains one universal narrative that has seemed to establish its grip on everyone. An idea that has been passionately explored by myriad traditions of the past and the present – life is suffering; a meld of ephemeral pleasures and perpetual despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The murky river of existence, to which we are eternally stuck, is, well, doomed. With every meandering turn it inflicts painful blows, pulverises hopes and leaves us in a state of absolute despondence and melancholia. Sorrow is inextricably linked to existence. Sorrow stems from attachments and poisons our lives; an idea deeply rooted in Buddhist philosophy. This realisation itself is sufficient to make a person depressed for the rest of his life, knowing that whatever he does shall in no way improve his dull existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much deliberation went into the matter, in response to which a Greek man proposed his own tenets to lead a joyful life. This later took the form of a full-fledged school of thought called &lt;em&gt;Stoicism&lt;/em&gt;. Far removed from other philosophies, that expound obscure esoteric questions pertaining to the metaphysics or epistemology of existence, stoicism employs the Socratic approach to discuss practical issues which have a direct bearing on the lives of common people. The idea was to search for the best means to lead a happy life, in the face of the pandemonium that had descended over the political landscape of the Hellenistic period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our tale begins with a sailing merchant by the name of Zeno who, after surviving a major shipwreck, ends up in the city of Athens. During his stay, he visited a bookstore which proved to be the turning point of his life. That was the day he was introduced to the philosophy of Socrates. Fascinated by his findings, Zeno decided to pursue his newly developed interest in philosophy and asked the librarian to suggest a teacher who could guide him. The librarian recommended a man named Crates, who, for the coming years, instructed Zeno on the idea of Cynicism; an outgrowth of Socratic thought. A passionate student, Zeno studied not only Cynicism but also other schools of thought that prevailed during that time. This equipped him with the ability to understand the world through multiple lenses, and much later helped him develop a theory of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Cynicism exposed Zeno to a brand new world of naturalistic existence, one that defied all societal norms, it didn’t quite resonate with his own personal beliefs. After all who would want to lie around, naked in broad daylight, disturbing everybody passing by, like the cynic Diogenes? Dissatisfied with whatever knowledge he had acquired so far, he decided to part ways with the school and set out on a new journey. Zeno took up teaching. He lectured pupils on his own precepts, in the middle of the city, which actually turned out to be quite successful. Several students flocked to the beautiful building of Stoa Poikile, to hear their great teacher speak. It is here that the foundations of Stoicism were finally laid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Zeno remains a major player in our story, he isn’t the only one. Several other intellectuals also subscribed and greatly contributed to the doctrine. These thinkers included greats such as Seneca, Marcus Aurelius and Epictetus. They, together with Zeno, spoke in great detail about the various facets of Stoicism. Here, I’ll be discussing aspects of Stoic ethics that surprisingly enough remain relevant till date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that is studied in Ethics today has a very direct connection with the ideas that were propounded by these thinkers. Stoic ethics mainly investigated happy existence and the conditions required to reach that state. The aim is to end suffering and live in harmony with nature. So, how did they achieve it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core of Stoic ethics lies the idea of &lt;em&gt;Oikeiosis&lt;/em&gt;, loosely translating to orientation. Every living thing in the world has a basic constitution, assigned to it by the natural order. For animals it is self-preservation, but in the case of humans, the oikeiosis is much greater as it involves our extraordinary ability to reason. Thus stoicism takes into account our primitive behaviour along with the potentiality to transcend it, since to be rational one is required to step out of the realm of primitive desires. It ascribes greater importance to the actions that are motivated by reason rather than animalistic desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very simple doctrine of the Stoics, from which one can derive a massive life lesson is that one needs to make a demarcation between things that fall under one’s control and things which don’t. All that is external to us is, quite naturally, in a state of chaos and something that’s independent of us. We can’t impose ourselves on the mechanisms of nature which remain outside the clutches of our will. However, we can change our perspectives and actions towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it. In a brief session of introspection, we can easily discern that our lives are stranded between regrets of the past and fears of the future. All that stoicism asks is - why give a damn? To be Stoic is to remain indifferent to whatever lies beyond you. And it is when you become indifferent that you begin to act out of reason rather than passion. The Stoics may as well be dubbed the Buddhists of the western tradition, in some respects. Their ethics have a striking resemblance to the 2nd noble truth of the Buddha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever something bothers you, stop a second and ask - “Can I change this situation?” If yes, then strive towards that change otherwise be unfazed by it. This might seem difficult at first but if this little ritual of interrupting negativity is followed, life can transform drastically. The key is to halt expectations and to be at peace with oneself. In the words of Marcus Aurelius:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you work at that which is before you, following right reason seriously, vigorously, calmly, without allowing anything else to distract you, but keeping your divine part pure, as if you were bound to give it back immediately; if you hold to this, expecting nothing, but satisfied to live now according to nature, speaking heroic truth in every word that you utter, you will live happy. And there is no man able to prevent this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understand stoicism as a philosophy that prepares you to face the bitter truths of life, without getting affected. It engineers you in a manner such that you can’t help but walk a virtuous path. It imparts the lesson that one must moderate one’s desires and emotions by employing reason, untouched by the highs and lows of life. Stoicism values self-control and an acceptance of whatever comes one’s way. Above all, however, stoicism is about empowering the ‘ruler within you.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that in the 21st century, the age of despair and silenced voices, humans are drawn towards a philosophy which can offer them tranquillity and order. Ours is a generation being pulled by desire with a force we can’t resist. We end up either letting go of the reins of control, becoming slaves to our passions, or fretting over situations which we can’t possibly control. It, therefore, becomes imperative to adopt Stoicism, because honestly, what is a life without happiness? Stoicism is the emancipatory force to guide us towards the path of a more fulfilled and joyful existence.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Call it an endless string of experiences or a series of vivid sensations of the world around, we are all suffering from a mysterious condition, called life or existence. Existence is difficult to define in objective terms. One can only derive a vague understanding of existence through the complex fabric of encounters and experiences that shape how we see the world. But does one’s myopic and vague understanding stop one from expressing one’s subjective take on the matter? Certainly not. Discussions on existence have permeated through the history of humankind. Myriad answers have been proposed and rejected over the years but a solitary troubling question has remained unchanged: what is the best way to live?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Only I Exist</title>
      <link href="/Only-I-Exist" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only I Exist" />
      <published>2019-08-01T11:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-01T11:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-I-Exist</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-I-Exist">&lt;p&gt;Questions have been the very heart and soul of philosophy and, unlike any other
discipline, it has raised more questions than it has answered. The dire
intellectual need to discern the abstract, in the form of reality and truth,
consumes all thinkers alike. They all seek answers that spring from an objective
source to bring an end to the seemingly perpetual quest for knowledge. However,
it is not that simple. Philosophy, over the years, has gotten mired down in
countless irrefutable hypotheses, thriving on the body of possibilities and
reason. This is especially true of metaphysical discussions, which have resulted
in the blossoming of unconventional, at times, bizarre theories to explain
reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;? One way to grasp reality amounts to the way you understand the
world external to you. But what if that understanding is faulty? Take, for
instance, the understanding of the earth as a flat disc. Today we can ‘claim to
know’ that the earth is spherical, yet in those times the supposed axiom of the
earth being flat was the foundational truth on which the early peoples developed
an understanding of other concepts and ideas. This is disconcerting, because
there’s a pretty high possibility of us assuming a false belief as an
irrefutable fact, because although there are proofs to make claims, science per
se isn’t perfect, just workable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now go even further to understand the concept of matter that we &lt;em&gt;assume&lt;/em&gt;
to be real. As Bertrand Russell discussed in his &lt;em&gt;Problems of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;,
whatever we perceive is the mere appearance of an object, as opposed to its
reality. The surface of an apple that is seen with the naked eye is very
different when viewed under the microscope, its colour varies with the changing
source of light too. In short, what your perception leads you into believing is
real is actually nothing but the appearance of the apple, in varying degrees of
magnification. If this is the case, then the existence of the apple becomes
questionable. Does an &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; apple exist at all? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some, it does not. A philosopher named Bishop Berkeley, for instance, argued
in favour of &lt;em&gt;immaterialism&lt;/em&gt; – that rather than being a form of matter, an apple
in actuality is the amalgamation of several qualities which cannot exist
independent of the mind. You can test this, try defining an apple devoid of its
qualities and properties. It is almost impossible to do so. So are the qualities
(of the objects) that we perceive in the universe, are they created by our
imagination or do they exist as a comprehensive whole contained in an underlying
substratum called matter? This is the starting point of the idea of ‘solipsism.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solipsism revolves around the idea that only I exist and weave the fabric of my
reality. The &lt;em&gt;certainty&lt;/em&gt; I can ascribe to my experience is limited to my &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt;
existence and thoughts, everything else in this world, including the existence
of this article, is doubtable. This may seem very absurd to hear, at first, but
it’s a possibility that is hard to deny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The empirical experiences one goes through forms an essential part of their own
subjective reality. One can, in no way validate the experience of anybody else
(egocentric predicament). One’s understanding of the apple is theirs alone and
cannot be grasped by anyone else. The comprehension of all that is external to
their consciousness is beyond their ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, your thoughts and ideas are the only undisputed and obvious entities that
exist. This is to say that all humans have their own psychological conceptions
whose understanding is forbidden to others. And so, we cannot be certain of the
independent existence of other bodies and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of solipsism has subtly remained embedded in other philosophical
ideas. One such idea was propounded by Rene Descartes’ principle of “&lt;em&gt;Cogito,
ergo sum&lt;/em&gt;” (I think, therefore I am). Descartes was convinced that he was being
deceived, by an evil genius, into believing some essentially flawed concepts as
true. Maintaining that every thought is dubitable, he cleansed his mind of all
distortions and came up with the most irrefutable, indubitable truth (as the
basic frame of reference to understand all the other truths)- “I think therefore
I am.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solipsism takes this idea of &lt;em&gt;Cogito&lt;/em&gt; way too seriously. Nothing but the mind is
true for the solipsist. While Descartes did believe in rationality and
mathematics as a means to search for truth, for the solipsist (metaphysically
and epistemologically) such conceptions are your own inventions, something you
make up in your head, bereft of any independent existence (here your
consciousness shall assume the place of Descartes’ demon). One can understand it
as a perpetual state of hallucination, characterised by vivid details. If you
are a solipsist, then whatever you experience, this article, your friends,
family, nature, all the coolest things in the world are actually an invention of
your own! An understanding of the world devoid of the ego is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However fascinating it may sound, solipsism has some dire outcomes, when
accepted as a lifestyle choice. It possesses the potential to throw the world
into utter chaos. Since everything that one sees around them is a creation of
their imagination, they would have all the power of calling the shots and
asserting their dominance over the entire world around them. Morality and ethics
would lose their credibility and an individual’s will would determine the fate
of all that is around them. Or else, it could make a person abnegate everything,
despairing about the loneliness they experience every second of their existence,
since they have no proof of the existence of any other. Either way, solipsism
could inflict more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult to refute, solipsism continues to haunt the imagination of humankind.
However, rejecting the theory altogether wouldn’t be right either, given the
crucial questions it raises on reality and the foundations of epistemological
speculations. The question of solipsism has stirred minds and propelled
philosophy from a state of certainty to that of unpredictability, thereby adding
profundity and beauty to the subject. And as long as such ingenious thoughts
continue to flow in the body of philosophy, the answer to this problem, along
with all problems, I believe, is not too far away.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Questions have been the very heart and soul of philosophy and, unlike any other discipline, it has raised more questions than it has answered. The dire intellectual need to discern the abstract, in the form of reality and truth, consumes all thinkers alike. They all seek answers that spring from an objective source to bring an end to the seemingly perpetual quest for knowledge. However, it is not that simple. Philosophy, over the years, has gotten mired down in countless irrefutable hypotheses, thriving on the body of possibilities and reason. This is especially true of metaphysical discussions, which have resulted in the blossoming of unconventional, at times, bizarre theories to explain reality. What is real? One way to grasp reality amounts to the way you understand the world external to you. But what if that understanding is faulty? Take, for instance, the understanding of the earth as a flat disc. Today we can ‘claim to know’ that the earth is spherical, yet in those times the supposed axiom of the earth being flat was the foundational truth on which the early peoples developed an understanding of other concepts and ideas. This is disconcerting, because there’s a pretty high possibility of us assuming a false belief as an irrefutable fact, because although there are proofs to make claims, science per se isn’t perfect, just workable.  Let us now go even further to understand the concept of matter that we assume to be real. As Bertrand Russell discussed in his Problems of Philosophy, whatever we perceive is the mere appearance of an object, as opposed to its reality. The surface of an apple that is seen with the naked eye is very different when viewed under the microscope, its colour varies with the changing source of light too. In short, what your perception leads you into believing is real is actually nothing but the appearance of the apple, in varying degrees of magnification. If this is the case, then the existence of the apple becomes questionable. Does an actual apple exist at all?  For some, it does not. A philosopher named Bishop Berkeley, for instance, argued in favour of immaterialism – that rather than being a form of matter, an apple in actuality is the amalgamation of several qualities which cannot exist independent of the mind. You can test this, try defining an apple devoid of its qualities and properties. It is almost impossible to do so. So are the qualities (of the objects) that we perceive in the universe, are they created by our imagination or do they exist as a comprehensive whole contained in an underlying substratum called matter? This is the starting point of the idea of ‘solipsism.’ Solipsism revolves around the idea that only I exist and weave the fabric of my reality. The certainty I can ascribe to my experience is limited to my own existence and thoughts, everything else in this world, including the existence of this article, is doubtable. This may seem very absurd to hear, at first, but it’s a possibility that is hard to deny. The empirical experiences one goes through forms an essential part of their own subjective reality. One can, in no way validate the experience of anybody else (egocentric predicament). One’s understanding of the apple is theirs alone and cannot be grasped by anyone else. The comprehension of all that is external to their consciousness is beyond their ability. Thus, your thoughts and ideas are the only undisputed and obvious entities that exist. This is to say that all humans have their own psychological conceptions whose understanding is forbidden to others. And so, we cannot be certain of the independent existence of other bodies and minds. The theory of solipsism has subtly remained embedded in other philosophical ideas. One such idea was propounded by Rene Descartes’ principle of “Cogito, ergo sum” (I think, therefore I am). Descartes was convinced that he was being deceived, by an evil genius, into believing some essentially flawed concepts as true. Maintaining that every thought is dubitable, he cleansed his mind of all distortions and came up with the most irrefutable, indubitable truth (as the basic frame of reference to understand all the other truths)- “I think therefore I am.”  Solipsism takes this idea of Cogito way too seriously. Nothing but the mind is true for the solipsist. While Descartes did believe in rationality and mathematics as a means to search for truth, for the solipsist (metaphysically and epistemologically) such conceptions are your own inventions, something you make up in your head, bereft of any independent existence (here your consciousness shall assume the place of Descartes’ demon). One can understand it as a perpetual state of hallucination, characterised by vivid details. If you are a solipsist, then whatever you experience, this article, your friends, family, nature, all the coolest things in the world are actually an invention of your own! An understanding of the world devoid of the ego is impossible. However fascinating it may sound, solipsism has some dire outcomes, when accepted as a lifestyle choice. It possesses the potential to throw the world into utter chaos. Since everything that one sees around them is a creation of their imagination, they would have all the power of calling the shots and asserting their dominance over the entire world around them. Morality and ethics would lose their credibility and an individual’s will would determine the fate of all that is around them. Or else, it could make a person abnegate everything, despairing about the loneliness they experience every second of their existence, since they have no proof of the existence of any other. Either way, solipsism could inflict more harm than good. Difficult to refute, solipsism continues to haunt the imagination of humankind. However, rejecting the theory altogether wouldn’t be right either, given the crucial questions it raises on reality and the foundations of epistemological speculations. The question of solipsism has stirred minds and propelled philosophy from a state of certainty to that of unpredictability, thereby adding profundity and beauty to the subject. And as long as such ingenious thoughts continue to flow in the body of philosophy, the answer to this problem, along with all problems, I believe, is not too far away.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Celebrating Darkness Through Style: Yami Kawaii</title>
      <link href="/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating Darkness Through Style: Yami Kawaii" />
      <published>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style">&lt;p&gt;The streets of Harajuku have witnessed it all; the shifts, blends and twists that have gone into making Japan’s street fashion what it is today. As part of one of the world’s most exciting fashion capitals, Tokyo, Harajuku’s streets have given birth to diverse fashion trends, which stem from an interplay of western elements and unique individual tastes. With a splendid array of authentic styles, characterised by heavy accessorisation and experimentation, Harajuku has garnered attention from designers worldwide. The youth of Harajuku, in particular, has begun creating a free space of expression for themselves through the clothes they don. Vibrant and quirky, the Harajuku youth culture, both as a trend in fashion and a lifestyle reflects the constant struggle to break free from mainstream culture, which is marked by order and discipline and leaves little space for people to play with their style and fashion choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world’s obsession with &lt;em&gt;kawaii&lt;/em&gt; (meaning cute) is not new and with growing fame, &lt;em&gt;kawaii&lt;/em&gt; has expanded beyond Hello Kitty products and plushies (which as a matter of fact draw their inspiration from fierce beasts!) to enter the world of fashion. As phrases like “&lt;em&gt;that’s so kawaii!&lt;/em&gt;” emerged, adolescents embraced styles that gave them an innocent, childlike air. Against the backdrop of Japan’s mental health crisis and a cultural unwillingness to speak about it, some even went a step ahead to give their own twist to the idea of kawaii. Thus emerged a new look in the streets of Harajuku, called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;yami kawaii&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Literally translating to ‘sick cute’, yami kawaii wasn’t the normal, conventional kawaii. Something dark and profound pervaded it. It dealt with sickness, a sickness that even though plagued the whole of Japan was one that nobody was and is still ready to talk about. It dealt with depression and suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By fusion of the cute and the dark, yami kawaii produced fashion of a freakish nature, involving soft pastels and anime juxtaposed with guns, syringes, bandages. Underneath the facade of kawaii, the tshirts illustrated chilling messages such as ‘Kill You’, ‘I want to die’ and ‘F*ck You’. What makes such fashion intense is not the frightening imagery that it employs but the implication that underlies that imagery; these clothes were a desperate last resort for people to express themselves, an attempt at catharsis of a deep, deep pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Menhera Chan, a manga character, came to be seen as an important figure in the yami kawaii movement. This is primarily because Menhera chan is different from other manga characters. She has a dark cynical vibe to her, her arms are bandaged, she carries a blade with her and harms herself, she is anxious and depressed. Her despair and agony are what make her a strangely relatable figure to countless others, who experience a similar pain but have to shroud it with their silence. They see her as the personification of the feelings and desires buried in the depths of their hearts, a therapeutic mechanism to pour out the pain of hiding the miserable state they’re in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncannily enough, yami kawaii has opened doors for a healthy dialogue in a society where profession and education overwhelmingly dictate every aspect of an individual’s life, where seeking help in order to tackle mental illness is still labelled a weakness. In the difficulty of having to reshape one’s life during the hard times, expression seems the only recourse, something that yami kawaii offers as a style. This, however, is not to be misunderstood as the glorification of suicide or depression. Personally, I find this style to be emboldening, simply because it marks a dissent from the ongoing discourse that reeks of bigotry and seeks to forbid individuals from expressing what they truly feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With negativity looming over the topic of mental health (which again, is partly responsible for the lack of dialogue) one remains fettered to live a life of lies. Constantly in the shackles of keeping up appearances, one has to project oneself as something they’re not. Those unable to take it anymore, seek their emancipation in suicide. Against the stifling expectations of society, where abiding by rules and etiquette are a must, yami kawaii offers a way out to people, in the form of catharsis. Yami kawaii gives a release to the inner turbulence they experience while helping one connect with others who feel the same way. It possesses a healing power of sorts, alleviating all those enduring the pain of masking their true feelings and enabling their style to speak for them. This makes yami kawaii empowering, fostering a new hope in the world for greater acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using fashion as an instrument of their liberation, the youngsters of Harajuku have certainly begun to lay down the foundations of change, to break silence against this raging catastrophe. By providing an outlet to vent complex emotions through style, an embodiment of the self, they seek to urge others who are suffering like them to join this movement towards self-love. Yami kawaii tells one and all that they have nothing to hide and nothing to fear. Bold and beautiful, these youths, go about announcing their identity in the streets of Harajuku.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The streets of Harajuku have witnessed it all; the shifts, blends and twists that have gone into making Japan’s street fashion what it is today. As part of one of the world’s most exciting fashion capitals, Tokyo, Harajuku’s streets have given birth to diverse fashion trends, which stem from an interplay of western elements and unique individual tastes. With a splendid array of authentic styles, characterised by heavy accessorisation and experimentation, Harajuku has garnered attention from designers worldwide. The youth of Harajuku, in particular, has begun creating a free space of expression for themselves through the clothes they don. Vibrant and quirky, the Harajuku youth culture, both as a trend in fashion and a lifestyle reflects the constant struggle to break free from mainstream culture, which is marked by order and discipline and leaves little space for people to play with their style and fashion choices.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Dialectic on Cultural Relativism</title>
      <link href="/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dialectic on Cultural Relativism" />
      <published>2019-03-28T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism">&lt;p&gt;In this kaleidoscopic world, cultural diversity is a phenomenon that is standard
to every institution and organisation. Adorned with a plethora of societies and
people dressed in almost every colour on the palette, communicating in different
languages, and following all sorts of customs and traditions, the world
certainly is a beautiful place to live in. Wherever you go, whatever you do, you
are bound to encounter differences and unfamiliarity in the form of people and
the cultures they manifest. With every nook and corner characterised by its own
uniqueness, diversity has certainly become an undeniable reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are always taught to appreciate and embrace this diversity, we must
also be cautious of its potential to cause morally problematic situations.
Consider for instance, how would you feel if someone sticks out their tongue at
you? I am sure humiliated would be the answer. But, what if I tell you that it’s
the way people greet each other in Tibet. This would certainly change things a
little bit, however, still, the whole idea of sticking out your tongue to greet
others would seem unnatural or rather weird to you, something you’ll never dare
to do to out of fear of embarrassment, unless you’re from Tibet of course! This
becomes very troubling. With divergent practices exclusive to each culture,
often questions pertaining to the “ideal conduct” are raised. One may, in fact,
be inclined to ask “Is there an ideal way at all?” And this is where the theory
of cultural relativism steps in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have always been very intimately linked with the culture they’re brought
up in, to the extent that their choices, tastes and behaviours resonate with the
spirit and essence of their culture. Especially with respect to actions and
demeanours, culture is believed to exercise a profound influence on the lives of
people. Therefore, it is quite natural for them to cling onto their own cultural
standards and view other cultures with suspicion. Activities like the
recreational use of cemeteries in Denmark, or the Greek practice of pretending
to spit on a married couple for good luck, or the exhuming of dead bodies by
Trojan tribes, long-ringed necks in Thailand, foot binding in China, etc. might
seem a little strange to hear at first and even impel us to pass a negative
judgement. But, according to the idea of cultural relativism, such judgements
would be wrong and irrational, as they are evaluated on the basis of our own
cultural sense and sensibilities, which fail to cover the moral codes of other
cultures. According to the theory of cultural relativism, the conception of good
and evil, right and wrong, is relative to cultures and so there can never be any
universal moral code of judgment. In other words, we can’t asses other cultures
by employing our own cultural standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes immensely important, given the phenomenal rise in ethnocentrism and
intolerance. With culture assuming supremacy over our lives in governing our
views and judgements, often acceptance of others becomes a little challenging.
In the face of such strict cultural conditioning, it would seem the theory of
cultural relativism is our only way out to advance towards a world characterised
by harmony and brotherhood. This seems to make cultural relativism an impeccable
theory. But is it so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a world with strict cultural relativism. Here, there shall be no
cross-cultural judgements; humanity would function on the principle of
tolerance, almost to the extent that everything would be approved. All cultures,
with their boons and banes, would be embraced blindly, without any reservation.
As a result, if a culture commands its male members to rape women as a
traditional custom, then cultural relativism would be able to do very little
about it. And this is where the theory takes a problematic turn. Blind
acceptance of practices paves way for certain evil tendencies to proliferate,
and since no culture is immune to defects, the theory would essentially place
the entire humanity under a grave threat. For example, women in parts of Africa
are robbed of sexual pleasure by the age-old barbaric custom of female
circumcision. But, because of cultural relativism, it becomes almost impossible
to eradicate this ill practice. While the theory does leave some scope for
intra-cultural judgements, very seldom are people seen raising voices of dissent
against their own cultures, given it is something that pulsates through their
veins. Like any other theory, cultural relativism is not a viable solution for
all situations. However, before rejecting the theory completely, it’s also
important to appreciate certain aspects of it, so that one can find a more
nuanced version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution here could be perhaps to design a new relativism altogether, one
which is based on respect, not just for the culture as a whole, but also for
individual subjects belonging to the culture. This new relativism can have a
separate mechanism to address the issues of members, who get victimised in the
name of cultural customs. With people’s participation (and not interference) in
a peaceful, rational dialogue, the seeds of change can be sown in any culture to
do away with the inherent ferocity in it. Whatever be the case, it is difficult
to deny that cultural relativism promotes an atmosphere of tolerance and amity.
By eliminating the views of dogmatism surrounding one’s culture, it makes a
person more grounded and open to greater acceptance by others. Further, it
strengthens the intercultural relationships and builds a world based on the
principles of universal brotherhood. With communities being able to understand
and empathise with each other, the world certainly becomes a better place. Of
course, cultural relativism like any theory is harmful at its logical extreme,
but so long as it is caveated with a spirit of earnest dialogue, critique, and
individual respect, it works as a theory that makes a better world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this kaleidoscopic world, cultural diversity is a phenomenon that is standard to every institution and organisation. Adorned with a plethora of societies and people dressed in almost every colour on the palette, communicating in different languages, and following all sorts of customs and traditions, the world certainly is a beautiful place to live in. Wherever you go, whatever you do, you are bound to encounter differences and unfamiliarity in the form of people and the cultures they manifest. With every nook and corner characterised by its own uniqueness, diversity has certainly become an undeniable reality. While we are always taught to appreciate and embrace this diversity, we must also be cautious of its potential to cause morally problematic situations. Consider for instance, how would you feel if someone sticks out their tongue at you? I am sure humiliated would be the answer. But, what if I tell you that it’s the way people greet each other in Tibet. This would certainly change things a little bit, however, still, the whole idea of sticking out your tongue to greet others would seem unnatural or rather weird to you, something you’ll never dare to do to out of fear of embarrassment, unless you’re from Tibet of course! This becomes very troubling. With divergent practices exclusive to each culture, often questions pertaining to the “ideal conduct” are raised. One may, in fact, be inclined to ask “Is there an ideal way at all?” And this is where the theory of cultural relativism steps in. Humans have always been very intimately linked with the culture they’re brought up in, to the extent that their choices, tastes and behaviours resonate with the spirit and essence of their culture. Especially with respect to actions and demeanours, culture is believed to exercise a profound influence on the lives of people. Therefore, it is quite natural for them to cling onto their own cultural standards and view other cultures with suspicion. Activities like the recreational use of cemeteries in Denmark, or the Greek practice of pretending to spit on a married couple for good luck, or the exhuming of dead bodies by Trojan tribes, long-ringed necks in Thailand, foot binding in China, etc. might seem a little strange to hear at first and even impel us to pass a negative judgement. But, according to the idea of cultural relativism, such judgements would be wrong and irrational, as they are evaluated on the basis of our own cultural sense and sensibilities, which fail to cover the moral codes of other cultures. According to the theory of cultural relativism, the conception of good and evil, right and wrong, is relative to cultures and so there can never be any universal moral code of judgment. In other words, we can’t asses other cultures by employing our own cultural standards. This becomes immensely important, given the phenomenal rise in ethnocentrism and intolerance. With culture assuming supremacy over our lives in governing our views and judgements, often acceptance of others becomes a little challenging. In the face of such strict cultural conditioning, it would seem the theory of cultural relativism is our only way out to advance towards a world characterised by harmony and brotherhood. This seems to make cultural relativism an impeccable theory. But is it so? Consider a world with strict cultural relativism. Here, there shall be no cross-cultural judgements; humanity would function on the principle of tolerance, almost to the extent that everything would be approved. All cultures, with their boons and banes, would be embraced blindly, without any reservation. As a result, if a culture commands its male members to rape women as a traditional custom, then cultural relativism would be able to do very little about it. And this is where the theory takes a problematic turn. Blind acceptance of practices paves way for certain evil tendencies to proliferate, and since no culture is immune to defects, the theory would essentially place the entire humanity under a grave threat. For example, women in parts of Africa are robbed of sexual pleasure by the age-old barbaric custom of female circumcision. But, because of cultural relativism, it becomes almost impossible to eradicate this ill practice. While the theory does leave some scope for intra-cultural judgements, very seldom are people seen raising voices of dissent against their own cultures, given it is something that pulsates through their veins. Like any other theory, cultural relativism is not a viable solution for all situations. However, before rejecting the theory completely, it’s also important to appreciate certain aspects of it, so that one can find a more nuanced version. The solution here could be perhaps to design a new relativism altogether, one which is based on respect, not just for the culture as a whole, but also for individual subjects belonging to the culture. This new relativism can have a separate mechanism to address the issues of members, who get victimised in the name of cultural customs. With people’s participation (and not interference) in a peaceful, rational dialogue, the seeds of change can be sown in any culture to do away with the inherent ferocity in it. Whatever be the case, it is difficult to deny that cultural relativism promotes an atmosphere of tolerance and amity. By eliminating the views of dogmatism surrounding one’s culture, it makes a person more grounded and open to greater acceptance by others. Further, it strengthens the intercultural relationships and builds a world based on the principles of universal brotherhood. With communities being able to understand and empathise with each other, the world certainly becomes a better place. Of course, cultural relativism like any theory is harmful at its logical extreme, but so long as it is caveated with a spirit of earnest dialogue, critique, and individual respect, it works as a theory that makes a better world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Jungian Shadow</title>
      <link href="/The-Jungian-Shadow" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Jungian Shadow" />
      <published>2019-02-18T12:46:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-18T12:46:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Jungian-Shadow</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Jungian-Shadow">&lt;p&gt;What if you’ve got it all wrong: the whole idea of who you are, your identity and how you want to be seen. What if there’s more to your personality: another dimension maybe, or even a caliginous shadow, harbouring in it the nasty demonic tendencies of your very being? While this idea may seem bizarre, the truth of it is hard to deny. There lies in all of us a mysterious unconscious realm seated within the deepest recesses of our personality. This is the Shadow archetype, the Id, or the dark side. Devoid of the conscious light, it is in this tenebrous side where thrives the primitive, malicious, even creative aspects of our being that have long been repressed by the Freudian Ego. Engulfed in obscurity, the Shadow largely remains hidden from the understanding of the Self, making us live in pretence and deception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Propounded by the very renowned Swiss psychoanalyst Carl Jung, the concept of the Shadow operates on the Pleasure Principle. Subdued ideas, primitive instincts, desires, drives, abjections, fears, all are encompassed by this concept, which further mirrors the latent, unknown and dark aspects of the psyche that the conscious Ego fails to resonate with. The Shadow is of two types: the personal and the collective. While the personal Shadow pertains to the individual psyche, the collective Shadow emanates from a united unconsciousness of society-members, a projection of which has resulted in the greatest of evils, in the form of prejudice advanced by society against other communities to conceal their own weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lying under unfathomable depths, the Shadow develops alongside the Ego and Persona. As a child gets culturally conditioned to differentiate between good and bad, certain possessed behaviours and qualities are evaluated by them as deplorable and, ultimately, despised and rejected. In the whole process of growing up, humans also tend to masquerade their identity and don on a façade to gain greater acceptance in society. This is known as a Persona. But the Persona only hides the Shadow, it doesn’t eliminate its gestating potency to unleash the worst in human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is essential for one to accept the Shadow rather than seeking validation in the Persona. For a harmonious universe, the intermingling of both the aspects of good – bad, order - chaos, the yin and yang, becomes necessary. Likewise, for a balanced personality, one needs to unearth the dark aspects of one’s soul from the dreary suppressions of the Ego and integrate them with their conscious side. This is extremely important, for the very reason that each time your Ego represses a part of you, your Shadow gets denser, sprouting in it the destructive potential to completely overshadow your conscious light and cast on you a dark cloud of gloom for the rest of your life. A convenient trick is to think like the antagonist or villain in books or movies, learning to work with the people one hates or feels irritated around, and identifying the lies that they can unravel to challenge ‘the good’―both in society and in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of exploring one’s Shadow is not to bring forth some inner Machiavelli. It is about ensuring one truly understands oneself and accepts that there is a very horrible, unspeakable side to one’s own psyche. Without such knowledge and such humility, one is bound to remain a Nietzschean Last Man, afraid of life and it’s problems, driven not by a sense of true purpose but primal instincts. However, by overcoming the Shadow and directing its destructive forces on the right path, one can achieve true inner peace and the ability to fully realise oneself as The Super Man―thereby taming the demon within to achieve inner peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What if you’ve got it all wrong: the whole idea of who you are, your identity and how you want to be seen. What if there’s more to your personality: another dimension maybe, or even a caliginous shadow, harbouring in it the nasty demonic tendencies of your very being? While this idea may seem bizarre, the truth of it is hard to deny. There lies in all of us a mysterious unconscious realm seated within the deepest recesses of our personality. This is the Shadow archetype, the Id, or the dark side. Devoid of the conscious light, it is in this tenebrous side where thrives the primitive, malicious, even creative aspects of our being that have long been repressed by the Freudian Ego. Engulfed in obscurity, the Shadow largely remains hidden from the understanding of the Self, making us live in pretence and deception.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Order in Chaos</title>
      <link href="/The-Order-in-Chaos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Order in Chaos" />
      <published>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Order-in-Chaos</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Order-in-Chaos">&lt;p&gt;What is the most common phenomenon that binds together a seemingly bitter reality that manifests itself in nearly everything present in the universe? The answer, believe it or not, is chaos. Deep down we all know what chaos is, we have all experienced it and that’s why we despise it. From crowded halls to cluttered rooms to the endless traffic on the roads, chaos has been a most fundamental feature deeply woven into the fabric of our lives. It is not just in our day-to-day experiences, where chaos reigns. This miraculous yet notorious concept has also made its way into the most certain discipline of science as the “theory of chaos”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While chaos as a feature of human existence has been a cause of concern since time immemorial, its presence in the sciences as a separate area of study is relatively new. From the outset, the prime objective of science has always been about addressing the questions of uncertainty, and uncovering the underlying pattern in what is seemingly disoriented in nature. It was this pursuit of “pattern recognition” that resulted in the blossoming of Newtonian physics along with the belief that mathematics is the ultimate truth capable of generating precise predictions of the future. The universe was assumed to be a mechanical entity operating in accordance with certain unalterable mathematical principles and norms, making order and harmony almost synonymous with reality and existence. This belief, however, was short-lived. The prescient beauty of Newtonian claims of universal order crumbled into nothingness as Einsteinian theories and New Age Physics shook the scientific world. This advent of the new and the bold provided fertile ground for the recognition of “the chaos” hidden in the complexities of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of chaos was first brought into scientific scrutiny by the French mathematician Henri Poincaré in the 1880’s, during his study of the interaction between the planets, where he noted that even the slightest error or change in the initial conditions can produce enormous consequences in the final phenomenon. Later this took the form of the “butterfly effect” advanced by Edward Lorenz a mathematician and meteorologist in the 1960’s, who in spite of his precise calculations, could not predict the weather accurately. His findings culminated in his famous speech “Does the flutter of a butterfly’s wings in Brazil set up a tornado in Texas?” This speech was a major breakthrough in the history of chaos, establishing uncertainty to be the only certainty in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The butterfly effect is inherently present everywhere, be it in the uncertainty of weather mechanisms or in the most remarkable episodes of human history. After all, it was a rejected application to the Vienna Academy of Fine Art that caused the Holocaust and the Second World War. While this may sound utterly ridiculous, it is true that the Academy of Fine Arts did reject the application letter of the very infamous dictator, Adolf Hitler, which, as his autobiography &lt;i&gt;Mein Kampf&lt;/i&gt; itself tells you, culminated in his anti-Semitic feelings, his enrolment in the German army and much later the Second World War! Imagine how the world would have been had the Academy accepted him. History is replete with examples of how things could have turned out differently if only one tiny event were altered in the slightest way: Had Mughal Emperor Jahangir not been drinking buddies with Sir Thomas Roe―an emissary from England―the East India Company might never really have gained a true foothold in India. The very fact that you are reading this article right now makes the world function in a particular way than it would have otherwise. Who knows! Maybe two minutes of procrastination today may make you question your career choices tomorrow and lead you somewhere you never expected to be in 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is where do we find order? Is it even possible to find order in a world, which is so consumed and immersed in chaos? In a world of chaos, how did we attain our present form endowed with thinking and reasoning abilities, when we are in actuality nothing but a combination of molecules? How do simple cells with no central control system divide and differentiate on their own to form a complex foetus in the womb? This is precisely what the English mathematician Alan Turing discussed in his work, &lt;i&gt;The Chemical Basis of Morphogenesis &lt;/i&gt;, where he underscored the miraculously ingrained patterns of self-organisation observed in living organisms. This spontaneous order stems from the “local interactions” within the disordered system, such as a majestic flock of birds soaring high in the sky, or the schools of fish underwater. While these biological systems may seem chaotic when viewed from the standpoint of an individual constituent within the system (i.e. a bird flying in a flock), they exhibit extraordinary order and exquisite patterns, when analysed as a whole from a third person’s perspective (a human observing the flock of birds). It is self-organisation that leads to grains of sands being unconsciously assembled such that they create magnificent sand dunes. Trees, rivers and blood vessels branching into stunning patterns of self-similarity, all beautifully demonstrate this paradox of order in disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that we, in our petty human lives, fail to understand that chaos is nothing but a masked form of order and the key lies not in evading it but embracing it. While chaos may cause momentary frustration, it enables man to see the greater truth, showing him how his pathetic attempts to control everything around him may verily be the cause of his misery. In the words of the Buddha, “&lt;i&gt;Chaos is inherent in all compounded things. Strive on with diligence&lt;/i&gt;”. The beauty of life lies in the perfect blend of both the systems and not merely escaping from one. Embrace the chaos, rise every morning in the expectation of being surprised and learning something new, let life teach you how to have peace in all this turmoil that you cannot control.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What is the most common phenomenon that binds together a seemingly bitter reality that manifests itself in nearly everything present in the universe? The answer, believe it or not, is chaos. Deep down we all know what chaos is, we have all experienced it and that’s why we despise it. From crowded halls to cluttered rooms to the endless traffic on the roads, chaos has been a most fundamental feature deeply woven into the fabric of our lives. It is not just in our day-to-day experiences, where chaos reigns. This miraculous yet notorious concept has also made its way into the most certain discipline of science as the “theory of chaos”.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding the Absurdity of Life</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Absurdity of Life" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life">&lt;p&gt;What is the meaning of life? This has been perhaps one of the most vexing questions of all time which has transformed several ordinary men into brooding intellectuals. While the world has seen the emergence of diverse theories propounded by the greatest of philosophers, none seem to have completely quenched the ultimate thirst for an objective analysis of life and its meaning. It was in the pursuit of this meaning that philosophers like Sartre, Kierkegaard and Albert Camus sowed the seeds from which eventually sprang a full grown tree of a new philosophical discourse on absurdism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albert Camus, in particular, has spoken at length about absurdity in his manuscript called the “Myth of Sisyphus”. Here, he has endeavoured to explicate the futility of investigating for the absolute meaning of life—which doesn’t really exist. “The absurd” for Camus stems from the discord between “the human need and the unreasonable silence of the universe”. This ultimately culminates into a sense of hopelessness and despair in the human heart. Camus addresses what he considers the most crucial problem of philosophy: suicide, and whether the absurdity of life is a good reason for committing suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men, by their very nature, are seekers of meanings, and in this pursuit, turn to religion and dogmatism to explain a world which in reality is characterised by sheer indifference and ‘irrationality’. An illusionary world embellished with meanings serves as a major source of comfort to humans as it offers false hope and reassurance, but once this world is stripped of all its meanings, man is thrown in an abyss of chaos and upheaval. Men continue to live in their robotic way, pursuing goals and ambitions mindlessly as if they are in a never-ending race. Then comes a day when they suddenly wake up from this deep slumber of ignorance after receiving a huge blow from the absurdity of life. An alien feeling of disharmony dawns upon them, and life, with all its essence and beauty, loses significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to imagine yourself as an invisible person and look at the world around you. It’s nothing but a mechanical interplay of relations with people chasing temporary materialistic pleasures and associating their very being with these short-lived passions. Such an existence is like an exile or punishment, just like the one awarded to the Greek mythological character named Sisyphus who was condemned by the Gods to perform the futile labour of rolling a massive boulder up the hill only to watch it fall down again and again till eternity. It begs Camus’ ever-so-important question: should we live life at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human understanding is only limited to their own standards. Efforts to reduce the enormity of the universe into a set of uniform principles is futile. In an attempt to content himself, man attaches humanistic feelings of love and suffering to the apathetic universe. While a man’s craving for certainty persists, the universe remains still. And, it is from this relationship between the truth-seeking man and an unfeeling universe that the feeling of absurdity emanates. Science, the most authentic form of inquiry is itself based on hypothesis and conjectures. The claims believed to be true centuries ago are being altered and disproved now. In the face of such dynamism, certainty becomes a far-fetched dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is not the individual or the world that is absurd, but the incongruous relation between the two. The absurd originates from comparisons and confrontation. In the case of man and the world, the absurd lies in the clash between the human desire to look for meanings in a meaningless universe. Although a little baffling to comprehend, once man develops faith in the absurd, it plays an active role in guiding his life’s choices. Apart from accepting the absurd, the other option open to men is to either physically end their lives once and for all, or commit a philosophical suicide, where they assume artificial meanings and purpose of life by resorting to theology or religion. While suicide may seem a reasonable option, it simply negates the problem and does not answer it. Camus staunchly denies suicide and refers to it as ‘a repudiation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is to embrace this absurdity and live with it. This produces three consequences - &lt;strong&gt;Revolt, Freedom, and Passion&lt;/strong&gt;. The revolt is identified by the relentless longing for an objective meaning, which is impossible to achieve. Freedom, on the other hand, is characterised by the realisation that an absurd man is free to act and doesn’t have to submit to the restrictions imposed by life. And finally, consequence or passion arises as a result of living life to the fullest by accepting the absurd and caring only about the present rather than the future or past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now go back to our ‘absurd hero’, Sisyphus. His perpetual toil of pushing the boulder up and watching it roll down enables us to acknowledge the melancholic truth of absurdity. And the only way to remove this anguish is by imagining Sisyphus as a happy person, who despite all the struggle, is enjoying the whole process. Likewise, we must also contemplate the absurd and accept the inevitable drudgery of existence, which can only happen when we conquer our fate without expecting anything in return. So, what are you thinking? Go, enjoy your life, so what if you’ve failed a test, missed a deadline or many deadlines. Such occurrences are insignificant in the grand scheme of things. Appreciate and observe the grandeur of the world around you. Feel the sunlight, the delicate touch of petals, the cold droplets of rain and the beauty of nature, and maybe even derive a meaning out of it (bearing in the mind that it’s absurd of course!). Live your life passionately, and above all, cherish every moment. Stay happy because, at the end of the day, that’s what matters the most!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What is the meaning of life? This has been perhaps one of the most vexing questions of all time which has transformed several ordinary men into brooding intellectuals. While the world has seen the emergence of diverse theories propounded by the greatest of philosophers, none seem to have completely quenched the ultimate thirst for an objective analysis of life and its meaning. It was in the pursuit of this meaning that philosophers like Sartre, Kierkegaard and Albert Camus sowed the seeds from which eventually sprang a full grown tree of a new philosophical discourse on absurdism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Siddis: The Black Rulers of India</title>
      <link href="/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Siddis: The Black Rulers of India" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India">&lt;p&gt;Deep in the annals of Indian history, there lies a long-forgotten tale of daring heroes, who, although foreign to the land, quickly got assimilated into her blood and added to her magnificence. This is the story of the first African rulers of India, the Siddis. India has long been acting as a magnet, drawing to her shores communities from lands afar which have flourished and prospered in her. Amongst these communities were the Africans who although arrived as slaves, still emerged as the mightiest of rulers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journeying all the way from Abyssinia, their motherland, through the treacherous waters, the ‘habshis’ (another term used for addressing the Siddis, descendants of the Bantu people) arrived at the Deccan as a part of the ongoing lucrative slave trade by the Arab merchants. The very distinguished Moroccan scholar, Ibn Batutta recounts how the habshis were reputed for being formidable, such that the presence of even a single habshi in a ship would make the pirates turn away from it. While most of the habshis arrived as slaves and soldiers for the armies of the Delhi Sultanate, not all remained so, and some even climbed the social ladder to become dignified nobles. One of such nobles was Jamal-ud-din Yakut, a close confidant of Razia Sultan (the first female monarch to assume the ascendancy over the Delhi Sultanate), who enjoyed a privileged position as the Amir al-Umara (Amir of Amirs), under her patronage. His growing proximity with the Sultana, along with his racial humbleness, earned him great spite from the Turkish clerics, especially Malik Ikhtiar-ud-din Altunia, who led a violent rebellion against the two, ultimately culminating in his tragic end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also other Abyssinian men like the governor general Malik Sarwar who even went to the extent of laying down the foundation of a sovereign state called Jaunpur, which survived for nearly a century as a symbol of cultural amity and unity. Furthermore, some even established themselves in the eastern part of the subcontinent by dethroning the Sultans of Bengal. The very impressive Siddi Sayed mosque in Ahmedabad was also sanctioned for construction by a Habshi in 1572. Other noteworthy cases of Abyssinians entering the political limelight include Suhail Khan, saviour of the beleaguered Queen of Ahmadnagar, Chand Bibi, who was at war with the Mughals, and Yakut Khan, a navy admiral commissioned by the great Mughal emperor, Aurangzeb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these achievements are indeed great, nowhere had the habshis thrived as much as they did in the Deccan region. Many soared up sky-high, attaining extraordinary heights in the administration and military, because of their physical competency and fidelity. They no longer remained subdued, and with social ascendency, came greater power and privilege at their disposal. Such is the story of another Habshi, Malik Ambar, who held the post of the prime minister of the Ahmadnagar Sultanate. Born in the Oromo tribe, he was sold out at a very young age to an Arab merchant and passed through the hands of several owners to ultimately arrive at India and write his own destiny, where he converted to Islam and was renamed Ambar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 1571 that Ambar arrived at the Deccan where he served under a new master, the Peshwa of Ahmadnagar, who was himself a black man. This must have presented to Ambar a tempting prospect of rising above slavery to cease power and wealth. After the death of his master, he established an independent army (with the help of other habshi lords) and provided his valuable services to Adil Shah for which he was even conferred the title of Malik. But his most impressive accomplishment by far was during the invasions of the 1590’s, where he led a pluralistic force of several thousands under his command against the Mughals. His animosity towards the Mughals was especially long drawn, against whom he fought bravely to establish Nizam Shah on the throne of Ahmadnagar as the lawful monarch. Apart from being an able administrator, Malik Ambar is also accredited with engineering the military tactic of guerrilla warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donning Indian clothes and speaking the language of the land, the Siddis over time have coalesced into the culture and tradition of the subcontinent. However, contrary to the honour and fame attained as a part of history, the Siddis of present-day India remain a secluded community. Maintaining their distance from the mainstream culture and society, they live in tiny clusters scattered around the states of Karnataka, Maharashtra, and Gujarat. Having been reduced to mere outsiders in a country of their own, the Siddis have to continuously battle against the evils of racism and poverty. The only positive step taken by the government towards their upliftment was the establishment of the Special Area Games Project, in the hope of nurturing the raw talent for athletics which runs in their blood. This initiative, however, could not sustain for long and the dream of having Indo-African athletes run for the country in the Olympics was lost. Sports being the only way out of their deplorable condition, the Siddi community now dwells in the hope of the revival of SAG project and creation of many such opportunities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With xenophobia and racial attacks on the rise all over the country, there is a dire need to spread greater awareness about this community. The government, especially, needs to shoulder some responsibility and formulate comprehensive policies to harness the enormous potential lying in the Siddi community. This can come in the form of better employment, education, and opportunities in sports, and most importantly, acceptance from the rest of the countrymen. The time has come for us to uproot this deep-seated feeling of prejudice against the Indo-African community and truly embrace them to the core in an attempt to learn from the glorious past and shape a bright future based on mutual recognition and brotherhood.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Deep in the annals of Indian history, there lies a long-forgotten tale of daring heroes, who, although foreign to the land, quickly got assimilated into her blood and added to her magnificence. This is the story of the first African rulers of India, the Siddis. India has long been acting as a magnet, drawing to her shores communities from lands afar which have flourished and prospered in her. Amongst these communities were the Africans who although arrived as slaves, still emerged as the mightiest of rulers.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
