<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/cheshta.sharma/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-02-22T08:29:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/cheshta.sharma/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Code Red for Humanity’ - the IPCC Report on Climate Change</title>
      <link href="/Code-Red-for-Humanity-the-IPCC-Report-on-Climate-Change" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Code Red for Humanity’ - the IPCC Report on Climate Change" />
      <published>2022-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Code-Red-for-Humanity-the-IPCC-Report-on-Climate-Change</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Code-Red-for-Humanity-the-IPCC-Report-on-Climate-Change">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Humans have deferred restraining their fossil fuel emissions for so long that it's nearly impossible to stop global warming from intensifying over the next 30 years. The evidence of human-induced climate change in every region across the globe is irrefutable and some of these changes are already ‘irreversible’ for centuries to millennia, according to the IPCC report.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/about/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change&lt;/a&gt; (IPCC) was set up by the United Nations Environment Programme and the World Meteorological Organisation in 1988. Its main purpose is to provide governments at all levels with scientific information which they can use to develop climate-related policies. The sixth assessment report, compiled by more than 200 scientists over a period of several years and approved by 195 governments is the first in a trio gauging the state of climate change, efforts to alleviate it and to adapt to it. The document, which was described as &lt;em&gt;&quot;a code red for humanity&quot;&lt;/em&gt; by UN Secretary-General António Guterres, arrived less than three months before the major global climate summit in Glasgow, UK, which took place from October 31 to November 12, 2021, and where governments had the opportunity to make pledges to reverse course and reduce emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The report identifies that “&lt;em&gt;anthropogenic activities have caused approximately 1.0°C of global warming above pre-industrial levels and if no action isn’t taken, global warming is likely to reach 1.5°C by 2030”&lt;/em&gt;. This warming is set to persist for generations, even if zero emission pathways are enforced incontinently. The effects of 1°C global warming are already visible in sea level rise, surge in intensity of heat waves, glacier retreat, coral deaths, more frequent and more severe storms, floods and droughts. According to the report, there will be “&lt;em&gt;no region that will be left unscathed by the impacts of climate change”&lt;/em&gt;, with huge human and economic costs that far outweigh the costs of action. Regions like the Mediterranean, Southern Africa, the western United States, the Amazon and Australia will experience increased droughts and fires, which will affect not only the ecosystems but livelihoods, agriculture, and water systems. Infrastructure, transport, energy production and tourism in North America, the Arctic, Europe, the Andes, and more might be hugely impacted by the changes in snow, ice and river flooding. Storms will probably become more severe over most of North America, Europe, and the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The report points out that the Earth's precious carbon sinks, land and oceans, are at immense risk. They presently perform an astounding service in absorbing the bulk of the carbon dioxide the world emits, but as emissions rise, they will become less effective at absorbing CO2. These land sinks will eventually turn into a source, emitting CO2 instead of sucking it in; for example, the southeast Amazon rainforest is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-01871-6&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;no longer a carbon sink&lt;/a&gt; mainly because of deforestation and local warming. This can lead to uncontrolled warming, which will not only affect the world’s climate efforts, but can pose significant food and water security risks to countries in the region, and may lead to irreversible biodiversity loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to Govindasamy Bala, professor of Climate Change, for the first time, the new report clarifies the ‘&lt;em&gt;delicate balance’&lt;/em&gt; between aerosols and GHG emissions and their influence on precipitation by noting that “&lt;em&gt;greenhouse gas warming is partially offset by aerosol cooling&lt;/em&gt;.” Greenhouse gas-induced warming leads to intensification of rainfall, but from the 1950’s to 1980’s, there was a drop in global land monsoon precipitation and it was somewhat attributed to human-caused Northern Hemisphere aerosol ejection, which signifies that the aerosol cooling effect overpowered the greenhouse effect during the 30 year period. We don't see any trend in &lt;a href=&quot;https://india.mongabay.com/2020/11/how-wildlife-outside-protected-areas-responds-to-climate-extremes/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;monsoon&lt;/a&gt; rainfall in the last three decades, mainly because the effects of GHGs and aerosols are almost balanced. In the coming couple of decades this delicate balance may continue but by mid or end of the century the report predicts that we will see a surge in precipitation, Bala explained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to the IPCC, there is a &lt;em&gt;direct link between the surge in global warming and extreme climate changes&lt;/em&gt;. At 2°C of global warming, heat shocks are more likely to reach critical forbearance thresholds for biodiversity, i.e. out of the 105,000 species that were studied, it is predicted that 8% of plants, 9.6% of insects and 4% of vertebrates will lose over half of their geographic range at 1.5°C, compared with 16% of plants, 18% of insects and 8% of vertebrates at 2°C.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Repercussions associated with other biodiversity-related risks, for instance, the spread of non-native species and forest fires, are lower at 1.5°C compared to 2°C of global warming.&amp;nbsp; Extreme sea level events that used to occur once a century previously could happen every year by 2100.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, the report ascertains that there will be major benefits to limiting global warming to 1.5°C above the pre-industrial level, but doing so will need “&lt;em&gt;rapid, far reaching and extraordinary changes in all aspects of society&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pathways to safety&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As reported by the IPCC, around 85% of CO₂ emissions come from burning fossil fuels. It is much easier to stop releasing more CO₂ into the atmosphere than it is to eliminate it, and the more we emit, the further we degrade the ecosystems that naturally soak it up. Therefore, global net CO₂ emissions by humans have to shrink by about 45% by 2030 relative to 2010 levels and reach net zero by 2050. This is actually achievable, contrary to popular belief through mitigation measures in the energy sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;About 70–85% of electricity is expected to be supplied by renewable sources in 2050. Shares of nuclear and fossil energy with Carbon Capture and Sequestration/Storage (CCS) are modelled to increase, allowing the share of carbon emitted in the atmosphere to fall and natural gas to generate about 8% of global electricity in 2050. All these mitigation measures will need an annual average investment in the energy system of around $2.4 trillion (at 2010 prices) between 2016 and 2035, representing about 2.5% of the world GDP;&amp;nbsp;however, the cost of inaction and delay will be many times more.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Following these pathways, the use of coal will be almost negligible by 2050, which might worry Indian policymakers, who are still talking about getting 45% of the country’s electricity from coal around the middle of the century. It's expected that by 2050, about 75–90% of CO₂ emissions from industry will be lower relative to current levels. The IPCC says this can be accomplished through &quot;&lt;em&gt;combinations of new and already existing technologies and practises, including product substitution, electrification, sustainable bio-based feedstock, carbon capture, utilisation, and storage.&lt;/em&gt;&quot; All this will not only help us tackle the climate change situation but also help us achieve Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions are expected to rise. Because economies have been hard hit, every country is desperate for recovery, which can primarily be accomplished with the current brown economy, which includes using coal, gas, and oil to ratchet up growth as quickly as possible. But the good news is that we have technologies that can disrupt the current fossil-fuel-driven industrial system. We cannot wait for disruptive technologies; rather, we must be disruptive in action or it will be too late. As climatologist Xuebin Zhang says, &quot;&lt;em&gt;the evidence is everywhere, if we don’t act now, the situation is going to get really bad&lt;/em&gt;.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cheshta Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Humans have deferred restraining their fossil fuel emissions for so long that it's nearly impossible to stop global warming from intensifying over the next 30 years. The evidence of human-induced climate change in every region across the globe is irrefutable and some of these changes are already ‘irreversible’ for centuries to millennia, according to the IPCC report.&amp;nbsp; The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) was set up by the United Nations Environment Programme and the World Meteorological Organisation in 1988. Its main purpose is to provide governments at all levels with scientific information which they can use to develop climate-related policies. The sixth assessment report, compiled by more than 200 scientists over a period of several years and approved by 195 governments is the first in a trio gauging the state of climate change, efforts to alleviate it and to adapt to it. The document, which was described as &quot;a code red for humanity&quot; by UN Secretary-General António Guterres, arrived less than three months before the major global climate summit in Glasgow, UK, which took place from October 31 to November 12, 2021, and where governments had the opportunity to make pledges to reverse course and reduce emissions. The report identifies that “anthropogenic activities have caused approximately 1.0°C of global warming above pre-industrial levels and if no action isn’t taken, global warming is likely to reach 1.5°C by 2030”. This warming is set to persist for generations, even if zero emission pathways are enforced incontinently. The effects of 1°C global warming are already visible in sea level rise, surge in intensity of heat waves, glacier retreat, coral deaths, more frequent and more severe storms, floods and droughts. According to the report, there will be “no region that will be left unscathed by the impacts of climate change”, with huge human and economic costs that far outweigh the costs of action. Regions like the Mediterranean, Southern Africa, the western United States, the Amazon and Australia will experience increased droughts and fires, which will affect not only the ecosystems but livelihoods, agriculture, and water systems. Infrastructure, transport, energy production and tourism in North America, the Arctic, Europe, the Andes, and more might be hugely impacted by the changes in snow, ice and river flooding. Storms will probably become more severe over most of North America, Europe, and the Mediterranean. The report points out that the Earth's precious carbon sinks, land and oceans, are at immense risk. They presently perform an astounding service in absorbing the bulk of the carbon dioxide the world emits, but as emissions rise, they will become less effective at absorbing CO2. These land sinks will eventually turn into a source, emitting CO2 instead of sucking it in; for example, the southeast Amazon rainforest is no longer a carbon sink mainly because of deforestation and local warming. This can lead to uncontrolled warming, which will not only affect the world’s climate efforts, but can pose significant food and water security risks to countries in the region, and may lead to irreversible biodiversity loss. According to Govindasamy Bala, professor of Climate Change, for the first time, the new report clarifies the ‘delicate balance’ between aerosols and GHG emissions and their influence on precipitation by noting that “greenhouse gas warming is partially offset by aerosol cooling.” Greenhouse gas-induced warming leads to intensification of rainfall, but from the 1950’s to 1980’s, there was a drop in global land monsoon precipitation and it was somewhat attributed to human-caused Northern Hemisphere aerosol ejection, which signifies that the aerosol cooling effect overpowered the greenhouse effect during the 30 year period. We don't see any trend in monsoon rainfall in the last three decades, mainly because the effects of GHGs and aerosols are almost balanced. In the coming couple of decades this delicate balance may continue but by mid or end of the century the report predicts that we will see a surge in precipitation, Bala explained. According to the IPCC, there is a direct link between the surge in global warming and extreme climate changes. At 2°C of global warming, heat shocks are more likely to reach critical forbearance thresholds for biodiversity, i.e. out of the 105,000 species that were studied, it is predicted that 8% of plants, 9.6% of insects and 4% of vertebrates will lose over half of their geographic range at 1.5°C, compared with 16% of plants, 18% of insects and 8% of vertebrates at 2°C.&amp;nbsp; Repercussions associated with other biodiversity-related risks, for instance, the spread of non-native species and forest fires, are lower at 1.5°C compared to 2°C of global warming.&amp;nbsp; Extreme sea level events that used to occur once a century previously could happen every year by 2100.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the report ascertains that there will be major benefits to limiting global warming to 1.5°C above the pre-industrial level, but doing so will need “rapid, far reaching and extraordinary changes in all aspects of society”. Pathways to safety As reported by the IPCC, around 85% of CO₂ emissions come from burning fossil fuels. It is much easier to stop releasing more CO₂ into the atmosphere than it is to eliminate it, and the more we emit, the further we degrade the ecosystems that naturally soak it up. Therefore, global net CO₂ emissions by humans have to shrink by about 45% by 2030 relative to 2010 levels and reach net zero by 2050. This is actually achievable, contrary to popular belief through mitigation measures in the energy sector.&amp;nbsp; About 70–85% of electricity is expected to be supplied by renewable sources in 2050. Shares of nuclear and fossil energy with Carbon Capture and Sequestration/Storage (CCS) are modelled to increase, allowing the share of carbon emitted in the atmosphere to fall and natural gas to generate about 8% of global electricity in 2050. All these mitigation measures will need an annual average investment in the energy system of around $2.4 trillion (at 2010 prices) between 2016 and 2035, representing about 2.5% of the world GDP;&amp;nbsp;however, the cost of inaction and delay will be many times more.&amp;nbsp; Following these pathways, the use of coal will be almost negligible by 2050, which might worry Indian policymakers, who are still talking about getting 45% of the country’s electricity from coal around the middle of the century. It's expected that by 2050, about 75–90% of CO₂ emissions from industry will be lower relative to current levels. The IPCC says this can be accomplished through &quot;combinations of new and already existing technologies and practises, including product substitution, electrification, sustainable bio-based feedstock, carbon capture, utilisation, and storage.&quot; All this will not only help us tackle the climate change situation but also help us achieve Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs). As a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions are expected to rise. Because economies have been hard hit, every country is desperate for recovery, which can primarily be accomplished with the current brown economy, which includes using coal, gas, and oil to ratchet up growth as quickly as possible. But the good news is that we have technologies that can disrupt the current fossil-fuel-driven industrial system. We cannot wait for disruptive technologies; rather, we must be disruptive in action or it will be too late. As climatologist Xuebin Zhang says, &quot;the evidence is everywhere, if we don’t act now, the situation is going to get really bad.&quot;&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Female Labour Force Participation in India: Why Is It So Stunted?</title>
      <link href="/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Female Labour Force Participation in India: Why Is It So Stunted?" />
      <published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Recently, India has found itself in the monetary and segment conditions that would prompt an increased female workforce participation rate. Financial development has been high, averaging at 6-7% during the 1990's and 2000's. On the other hand, fertility has significantly fallen alongside the drastic rise in training of females.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, according to the International Labour Organisation's (ILO) estimates, the female labour force participation rate (FLPR) in India has declined from 30.27% in 1990 to 20.33% in 2020. The average value of the said figure for India during the period between 1990-2020 was 27.38%, with a minimum of 20.33% (in 2020) and maximum of 31.79% (in 2005).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The average for 2020, based on 182 countries, was 51.86%. Rwanda scored the highest rate of 83.95% and Yemen the lowest at 5.69%. The FLPR for China, the country with the largest population, was 64% while for the US, it was 56.3%. Women remained underrepresented in the Indian workforce, a circumstance that has not changed in the last 30 years.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Among its neighbouring countries, India’s FLPR is shockingly the lowest, falling even behind Afghanistan and Pakistan, which had scored half of India’s rates back in 1990. Nepal has a FLPR of 83% which is an all-time high amongst all the South Asian economies, and Pakistan (India’ biggest rival) has secured a higher position by 4 points, sitting at a FLPR of 24.6%. Globally only Yemen, Iraq, Jordan, Syria, Algeria, Iran, the West Bank and Gaza have lower rates than India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Analysis of National Sampling Survey Office (NSSO) data (1970-2018) shows that women have largely been undertaking home-based and labour intensive informal work concentrated in low-productivity sectors. During the period of 1977-2017, the proportion of women working in agriculture fell from 88.1% to 73.2% in the rural areas, while their share in the service sector rose from 35.7% to 60.7% in the urban areas. Females in the tertiary sector concentrated in professions such as teaching and nursing, which provided restricted scope for progression in their careers. However, unlike their male counterparts, females could not increase their presence in the secondary sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What explains low participation in India?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the last decade, fertility has declined rapidly while wages have expanded considerably, and the contribution for this goes to the high speed of development in the country. Furthermore, avenues for job seekers are not rare, except for the educated workforce where there is a distinct relative shortage. So why are more females not entering the workforce?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to a paper published in 2008, much of the discussion on the falling trends in female labour force participation has focused on four key elements:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;1) rising enrolment in secondary schooling;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;2) wage and sex discrimination in the workplace;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;3) increase in household incomes; and&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;4) females engaged in either unpaid family jobs or marginal jobs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There has been an increase in the percentage of women who have completed a minimum of secondary level education or more, particularly in rural India. The NSSO data also confirms younger women have greater aspirations to participate in the labour market than the previous generations, however, due to norms around chastity and early marriage (still heavily prevalent in the country), they are prevented from doing so. The average age of marriage for girls in rural India is around 21.7 years. Additionally, there has been a fall in participation rate of approximately 30% owing to greater demand on their time to pursue education. Post their education, absence of appropriate job availability leads to their lower participation in the workforce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There exists a U-shaped relation between education and paid work participation, yet the rate of return for each year of education is lower for women than men in India. This relation also asserts the fact that illiterate women are forced to rely on the unorganised sector for meeting their basic needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Wage and sex dicrimination within the workplace is an addition amongst the above mentioned factors where females are rewarded with a lower pay and greater discrimination than their male counterparts. This is serious as it not only affects the economic growth of the nation but also speaks volume on the prevalent working conditions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Males are awarded with a pay of more than 19% than their female colleagues. This income disparity has only narrowed by 1% in 2018 from the 20% of the preceding year. The pay inequality can be corresponded to the following factors - discriminaton and occupational decisions by females into lower paying jobs, such as clerical work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another interesting reason for lower female workforce participation can be attributed to the fact that many educated females drop out of the workforce due the family income effect, i.e., with an increase in family earnings, the dependency on females to work fall, thereby shifting their attention towards domestic chores and child care. As a result women hailing from higher economic status are less likely to work than women belonging from lower income strata.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This gap widens when we look at the 2019 report by the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation, wherein it becomes evident that the burden of unpaid labour falls on women significantly in the country. The report states that an average Indian woman spends nearly 84% of her working hours on unpaid work while the men spend 80% of their working hours on paid work.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the government doing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Government has taken several steps to increase the female workforce participation rate in India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Ministry of Skill Development and Entrepreneurship (MSDE) has been set up for improving the involvement rate across sectors and areas. Likewise the government has also initiated the National Career Service (NCS) project which entails a digital portal to link jobseekers and businesses for work and incorporate a repository of enlarged career content.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Other steps include incorporation of the &lt;em&gt;Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act, 2017 &lt;/em&gt;by institutions which focuses on improvement in paid maternity leaves from 12 weeks to 26 weeks, and arrangement for compulsory crèche services in establishments having at least 50 employees; issue of an advisory to the States under the &lt;em&gt;Factories Act, 1948&lt;/em&gt; for allowing women workers of night shifts with sufficient safety measures.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, to improve the employability of female labourers, numerous institutes have been set up to provide them with training ranging from vocational to industrial. Various work laws have been amended to foster a more safe and amicable work environment for women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Laws for a fairer work environment passed by the government include:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Minimum Wage Act 1948&lt;/em&gt;, the wages set by the corresponding government are equally applicable to male and female workers, and therefore, the law doesn't segregate on the premise of sex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Equal Remuneration Act 1976 &lt;/em&gt;provides for equal wages to be paid to employees for similar jobs, with no discrimination based on sex, class, caste or religion followed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Protection of Women against Sexual Harassment at Workplace Act 2013&lt;/em&gt; characterizes lewd behavior or sexual harassment at the workplace, and helps in the redressal of such objections. It provides shields against fake or noxious charges.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, many government policies are targeted towards the organised workforce while the&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;unorganised sector that homes the largest number of females has very little to no penetration of such&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;schemes, thereby making government policies ineffective to some extent. Additionally, in several areas, these policies are only restricted to documentation, thus, never making it to actual implementation. For instance, severe expenditure cuts associated with the centrally sponsored National Crèche Scheme had led to the closure of multiple crèches across the country, thus, de-incentivising female workers who could work earlier only because of the availability of such facilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover the government policies regularly fail to focus on the real audience. In order to avail most of the above listed benefits, there's an enormous process and cumbersome documentation requirement which excludes the illiterate or marginalised women of the country. While issues like corruption conjointly attack the system, and the welfare policies fail to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comprehensive approaches are needed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In India, the gender gap in labour force participation is high and is worsening continually when looked at from a global point of view. The decline in female employment&amp;nbsp; is primarily attributed to the sharp fall in female agricultural employment, which till date employs more than 65% of the total women in the workforce; half of them working as unpaid family workers. This decline in agriculture share is not accompanied by a commensurate increase in non-agricultural activities, except for construction. Employment opportunities are very limited for women, and are solely concentrated in only a few sub-sectors, mainly in low value-added activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Agriculture, which is as yet the biggest employer of female labour, can be used as a wellspring of economic growth and job creation for women, if they are guaranteed possession rights and power over grounds while at the same time, movement of women is required towards the production of high value-added crops. These of course should be supplemented by other strategy measurements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover, promotion of female entrepreneurship can give way to economic elevation of women, and thus, distribution of its benefits more equitably. But lack of credit facilities in the absence of collateral, and complications of the established formalities present a major roadblock to such entrepreneurial ambitions. Self Help Groups (SHGs) can be utilised to improve access to finance, and links with formal financial institutions would enable women (especially from lower economic status) to access the market better.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Women in India face many barriers to enter the workforce, such as pre dominant socio-cultural practices, access to choice of work, poor working conditions, wage disparity, exploitation, balancing domestic and work responsibilities, and more. It is essential that policy makers adopt strategies to improve the labour market for women through gender neutral norms, education, proper infrastructure, and the creation of more opportunities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;At last, the objective isn't simply to increase the female labour force participation rate but to build opportunities for decent work and economic progression which can add to the financial strengthening of women and the economy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cheshta Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Recently, India has found itself in the monetary and segment conditions that would prompt an increased female workforce participation rate. Financial development has been high, averaging at 6-7% during the 1990's and 2000's. On the other hand, fertility has significantly fallen alongside the drastic rise in training of females.&amp;nbsp; However, according to the International Labour Organisation's (ILO) estimates, the female labour force participation rate (FLPR) in India has declined from 30.27% in 1990 to 20.33% in 2020. The average value of the said figure for India during the period between 1990-2020 was 27.38%, with a minimum of 20.33% (in 2020) and maximum of 31.79% (in 2005).&amp;nbsp; The average for 2020, based on 182 countries, was 51.86%. Rwanda scored the highest rate of 83.95% and Yemen the lowest at 5.69%. The FLPR for China, the country with the largest population, was 64% while for the US, it was 56.3%. Women remained underrepresented in the Indian workforce, a circumstance that has not changed in the last 30 years.&amp;nbsp; Among its neighbouring countries, India’s FLPR is shockingly the lowest, falling even behind Afghanistan and Pakistan, which had scored half of India’s rates back in 1990. Nepal has a FLPR of 83% which is an all-time high amongst all the South Asian economies, and Pakistan (India’ biggest rival) has secured a higher position by 4 points, sitting at a FLPR of 24.6%. Globally only Yemen, Iraq, Jordan, Syria, Algeria, Iran, the West Bank and Gaza have lower rates than India.&amp;nbsp; Analysis of National Sampling Survey Office (NSSO) data (1970-2018) shows that women have largely been undertaking home-based and labour intensive informal work concentrated in low-productivity sectors. During the period of 1977-2017, the proportion of women working in agriculture fell from 88.1% to 73.2% in the rural areas, while their share in the service sector rose from 35.7% to 60.7% in the urban areas. Females in the tertiary sector concentrated in professions such as teaching and nursing, which provided restricted scope for progression in their careers. However, unlike their male counterparts, females could not increase their presence in the secondary sector.&amp;nbsp; What explains low participation in India? In the last decade, fertility has declined rapidly while wages have expanded considerably, and the contribution for this goes to the high speed of development in the country. Furthermore, avenues for job seekers are not rare, except for the educated workforce where there is a distinct relative shortage. So why are more females not entering the workforce? According to a paper published in 2008, much of the discussion on the falling trends in female labour force participation has focused on four key elements:&amp;nbsp; 1) rising enrolment in secondary schooling;&amp;nbsp; 2) wage and sex discrimination in the workplace;&amp;nbsp; 3) increase in household incomes; and&amp;nbsp; 4) females engaged in either unpaid family jobs or marginal jobs.&amp;nbsp; There has been an increase in the percentage of women who have completed a minimum of secondary level education or more, particularly in rural India. The NSSO data also confirms younger women have greater aspirations to participate in the labour market than the previous generations, however, due to norms around chastity and early marriage (still heavily prevalent in the country), they are prevented from doing so. The average age of marriage for girls in rural India is around 21.7 years. Additionally, there has been a fall in participation rate of approximately 30% owing to greater demand on their time to pursue education. Post their education, absence of appropriate job availability leads to their lower participation in the workforce.&amp;nbsp; There exists a U-shaped relation between education and paid work participation, yet the rate of return for each year of education is lower for women than men in India. This relation also asserts the fact that illiterate women are forced to rely on the unorganised sector for meeting their basic needs.&amp;nbsp; Wage and sex dicrimination within the workplace is an addition amongst the above mentioned factors where females are rewarded with a lower pay and greater discrimination than their male counterparts. This is serious as it not only affects the economic growth of the nation but also speaks volume on the prevalent working conditions.&amp;nbsp; Males are awarded with a pay of more than 19% than their female colleagues. This income disparity has only narrowed by 1% in 2018 from the 20% of the preceding year. The pay inequality can be corresponded to the following factors - discriminaton and occupational decisions by females into lower paying jobs, such as clerical work. Another interesting reason for lower female workforce participation can be attributed to the fact that many educated females drop out of the workforce due the family income effect, i.e., with an increase in family earnings, the dependency on females to work fall, thereby shifting their attention towards domestic chores and child care. As a result women hailing from higher economic status are less likely to work than women belonging from lower income strata.&amp;nbsp; This gap widens when we look at the 2019 report by the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation, wherein it becomes evident that the burden of unpaid labour falls on women significantly in the country. The report states that an average Indian woman spends nearly 84% of her working hours on unpaid work while the men spend 80% of their working hours on paid work.&amp;nbsp; What is the government doing? The Government has taken several steps to increase the female workforce participation rate in India.&amp;nbsp; The Ministry of Skill Development and Entrepreneurship (MSDE) has been set up for improving the involvement rate across sectors and areas. Likewise the government has also initiated the National Career Service (NCS) project which entails a digital portal to link jobseekers and businesses for work and incorporate a repository of enlarged career content.&amp;nbsp; Other steps include incorporation of the Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act, 2017 by institutions which focuses on improvement in paid maternity leaves from 12 weeks to 26 weeks, and arrangement for compulsory crèche services in establishments having at least 50 employees; issue of an advisory to the States under the Factories Act, 1948 for allowing women workers of night shifts with sufficient safety measures.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, to improve the employability of female labourers, numerous institutes have been set up to provide them with training ranging from vocational to industrial. Various work laws have been amended to foster a more safe and amicable work environment for women.&amp;nbsp; Laws for a fairer work environment passed by the government include:&amp;nbsp; Minimum Wage Act 1948, the wages set by the corresponding government are equally applicable to male and female workers, and therefore, the law doesn't segregate on the premise of sex.&amp;nbsp;The Equal Remuneration Act 1976 provides for equal wages to be paid to employees for similar jobs, with no discrimination based on sex, class, caste or religion followed.&amp;nbsp;The Protection of Women against Sexual Harassment at Workplace Act 2013 characterizes lewd behavior or sexual harassment at the workplace, and helps in the redressal of such objections. It provides shields against fake or noxious charges. However, many government policies are targeted towards the organised workforce while the&amp;nbsp; unorganised sector that homes the largest number of females has very little to no penetration of such schemes, thereby making government policies ineffective to some extent. Additionally, in several areas, these policies are only restricted to documentation, thus, never making it to actual implementation. For instance, severe expenditure cuts associated with the centrally sponsored National Crèche Scheme had led to the closure of multiple crèches across the country, thus, de-incentivising female workers who could work earlier only because of the availability of such facilities.&amp;nbsp; Moreover the government policies regularly fail to focus on the real audience. In order to avail most of the above listed benefits, there's an enormous process and cumbersome documentation requirement which excludes the illiterate or marginalised women of the country. While issues like corruption conjointly attack the system, and the welfare policies fail to deliver. Comprehensive approaches are needed In India, the gender gap in labour force participation is high and is worsening continually when looked at from a global point of view. The decline in female employment&amp;nbsp; is primarily attributed to the sharp fall in female agricultural employment, which till date employs more than 65% of the total women in the workforce; half of them working as unpaid family workers. This decline in agriculture share is not accompanied by a commensurate increase in non-agricultural activities, except for construction. Employment opportunities are very limited for women, and are solely concentrated in only a few sub-sectors, mainly in low value-added activities.&amp;nbsp; Agriculture, which is as yet the biggest employer of female labour, can be used as a wellspring of economic growth and job creation for women, if they are guaranteed possession rights and power over grounds while at the same time, movement of women is required towards the production of high value-added crops. These of course should be supplemented by other strategy measurements.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, promotion of female entrepreneurship can give way to economic elevation of women, and thus, distribution of its benefits more equitably. But lack of credit facilities in the absence of collateral, and complications of the established formalities present a major roadblock to such entrepreneurial ambitions. Self Help Groups (SHGs) can be utilised to improve access to finance, and links with formal financial institutions would enable women (especially from lower economic status) to access the market better.&amp;nbsp; Women in India face many barriers to enter the workforce, such as pre dominant socio-cultural practices, access to choice of work, poor working conditions, wage disparity, exploitation, balancing domestic and work responsibilities, and more. It is essential that policy makers adopt strategies to improve the labour market for women through gender neutral norms, education, proper infrastructure, and the creation of more opportunities.&amp;nbsp; At last, the objective isn't simply to increase the female labour force participation rate but to build opportunities for decent work and economic progression which can add to the financial strengthening of women and the economy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
