<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/ritisha.gupta/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-02T16:51:45+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/ritisha.gupta/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘What are They Really Trying to Prevent?</title>
      <link href="/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'What are They Really Trying to Prevent?" />
      <published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent">&lt;p&gt;Among the things Indians pride themselves on, tall stands the Indian Constitution. A beacon of everything that is right with the country. Not only does it carry the spirit of the nation’s freedom struggle, but it also is an amalgamation of what the founders of independent India thought were the solutions for the worries of a new India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dark and dogmatic flaw in this idealised document materialises in the form of Art. 22, which denies certain fundamental rights to those arrested or detained under laws of preventive detention. The concept of preventive detention is simple - a person is taken into custody if the state machinery sees in them the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; to commit a crime. After stating certain protections from arrest and detention in Article 22(1) and (2), the Constitution further states that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nothing in clauses (1) and (2) shall apply— (a) to any person who for the time being is an enemy alien; or (b) to any person who is arrested or detained under any law providing for preventive detention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preventive detention is one of the many laws that have a deeply-rooted colonial legacy. The laws date back to the early days of the colonial era when the Bengal Regulation III of 1818 was enacted to empower the government to arrest anyone for maintenance of public order without any judicial proceedings. A century later, the British government enacted the Rowlatt Acts of 1919 that allowed confinement of a suspect without trial. Now, the very makers of the Constitution had been repeatedly arrested under these laws. So, the expectation was that such laws would be completely eradicated when independence was attained. But alas! that did not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Constituent Assembly Debates of India have long served as a leading example for dissent, debate and discussion. However, on the matter of preventive detention, all members seemed to have solemnly agreed. Alladi Krishnaswamy Ayyar, a distinguished jurist, had described preventive detention as a “necessary evil” because, in his view, there were people determined to undermine the sanctity of the Constitution, the security of the state and even individual liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the members resorted to incorporating safeguards against its abuse. However, it was left to Parliament to prescribe the period of detention and even that limit was meaningless because a fresh detention order could easily be passed, and advisory boards had no power to evaluate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 1950, one month after the promulgation of India’s first self-governing Constitution, Parliament passed a Preventive Detention Act which provided for the arrest and detention of persons who, in the opinion of the government, “represented a threat to the social stability and economic development of the country”. The Act was piloted by Sardar Patel, who said that he had several “sleepless nights” in the process of introducing the bill. The courts were expressly forbidden to question the necessity for any order issued by the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after in 1950, under this Act, an eminent communist political leader, A K Gopalan, was arrested. Gopalan challenged his detention by stating that his civil liberty was being hampered as he had the right to equality of law. However, the Supreme Court examined that he was detained according to the procedure established by law and rejected his argument. Although this ruling was later repealed by subsequent judgments of the Supreme Court, this initial arrest set the stage for the kind of curbing of dissent that this Act would entail as well as the passivity of the courts on the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most famous case involved Sheikh Abdullah, former Prime Minister of the State of Jammu and Kashmir. Arrested in 1953, he was held in detention until January 1958. The Government of India released Sheikh Abdullah upon good behaviour. However, the experiment did not last long, and he was rearrested on April 30, having amply revealed in a number of public speeches and statements that his opinions about the political future of Jammu and Kashmir had not changed at all. His brief respite from detention had lasted just 96 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Preventive Detention Act, 1950 expired in 1969 and was followed by the Maintenance of Internal Security Act (MISA), 1971. MISA is infamous for the controversial arrests and detentions that it facilitated. The entirety of the period of the Indian Emergency (1975-77) was further darkened by the cloud of MISA hanging over all political opponents of the ruling government. It was repealed once the Janata Party came to power after the Emergency, in 1977. When subsequently Indira Gandhi came back to power, the National Security Act, 1980 was instated. Over the years, many preventive detention laws have similarly risen and been repealed, but many have also remained and left a significant mark on the democratic process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1978, the Jammu and Kashmir Public Safety Act (PSA) was passed, under which a person is taken into custody to prevent them from acting harmfully against “the security of the state or the maintenance of the public order”. Strikingly, it was introduced by the then-&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_chief_ministers_of_Jammu_and_Kashmir&quot;&gt;Chief Minister&lt;/a&gt; of Jammu and Kashmir, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheikh_Abdullah&quot;&gt;Sheikh Abdullah&lt;/a&gt;, in 1978 under the guise of stopping the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timber_mafia&quot;&gt;smuggling of timber&lt;/a&gt;, but subsequently was used to remove political opponents. Since its usage in the late 1970’s, it is still being used today for “the security of the state”. Even after the revocation of Article 370, which ended Jammu and Kashmir’s special status, the PSA was one of the state laws which was retained under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jammu_and_Kashmir_Reorganisation_Act,_2019&quot;&gt;Jammu and Kashmir Reorganization Act of 2019&lt;/a&gt; - another sign of the “normalcy” in the state. Would Sheikh Abdullah have thought that 40 years later his own son Farooq Abdullah would be a victim of that very law?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no official count of the number of people detained in Kashmir after the government imposed a lockdown on August 5, 2019. Not just post August 5, there is no proper record of detentions under the PSA since its inception itself. It is safe to say that no official count will even reflect the true number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent times, the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967 (UAPA), along with its numerous amendments, has been the choice weapon of the state. The insidious intentions and arbitrary nature of the Act can be seen through an example of its implementation - the Bhima-Koregaon violence on January 1, 2018. The backdrop was a conference called the Elgar Parishad. 3 million people had gathered, led by numerous Dalit (Indian ‘untouchables’) organisations in the state of Maharashtra to commemorate the 200th anniversary of the Bhima-Koregaon battle, believed by the Dalits to have been won by their ancestors to end the oppressive regime of Brahmin Peshwas (higher ‘castes’). It gave a call to “Bury the New Peshwai” of the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) seen by the Dalits and minorities as the revival of Brahminic rule. This did not sit right with Hindutva forces, which attacked the congregation at the obelisk at Koregaon. The police refused to act against the named culprits. Instead, they began insinuating that the violence was caused by the inflammatory speeches made in the Elgar Parishad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months following the event, a number of people present at the event were arrested under the UAPA including renowned Dalit scholars and human rights advocates. It was alleged by the Pune Police that the event was organised by members of the banned Communist Party of India (Maoist), hence making these arrests necessary. The 11 accused were Sudhir Dhawale, Shoma Sen, Mahesh Raut, Rona Wilson, Surendra Gadling, P Varavara Rao, Sudha Bharadwaj, Arun Ferreira, Vernon Gonsalves, Anand Teltumbde and Gautam Navlakha. Except Teltumbde and Navlakha, the others were arrested by Pune Police in June and August 2018 in connection with the violence. They were accused of having links with the banned Communist Party of India (Maoist), and are still in prison. Navlakha and Teltumbde were presented in front of a special court in Mumbai on February 28, 2020 and were denied anticipatory bail. They were, however, given four weeks of protection from arrest to file a plea in the Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A barrage of criticism can be found against the UAPA for its provisions as well as its implementation. The definitions in the act are vague, for example, “questioning the territorial integrity of India is an unlawful activity” according to s. 2. Similarly, it is also an unlawful activity to cause “disaffection against India”. All these terms do not find definition in the Act. The state also reserves the power to declare any organisation as a terrorist organisation and just a membership of the same could get you imprisoned. Membership has often been proven using evidence as flimsy as copies of the Communist Manifesto to prove Naxal or Maoist ties. Although the Supreme Court has established that membership does not provide enough ground for arrest, this directive is yet to find hold in ground reality. Additionally, it is near-impossible to get bail once booked under this Act, despite the lack of concrete evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 amendment to UAPA allows the State to now declare individuals as terrorists as well. The judicious use of this provision has been seen during the protests against the Citizenship Amendment Act which began in December 2019. The first arrest under the newly amended act was made in Assam. Akhil Gogoi, an activist and leader of the &lt;em&gt;Krishak Mukti Sangraam Samiti&lt;/em&gt; (Congregation of Farmers’ Freedom Fighters), was booked by the National Investigation Agency under the UAPA for participating in the anti-CAA protests in Assam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voices that stand opposed to the government are a blessing in disguise. They are a rich source- identifying missteps and rectifying them. However, this idealistic relationship between the ruling elite and the opposition has never been realised. What comes next, however, is the relationship between the opposition and the people. Though not perfect, this relationship is in many ways what it truly means to be a part of a democracy. Votes do not always materialise as fulfillment of interests, and that is where the opposition must step in, to further this materialisation, on the behalf of all sections of society. Here opposition does not mean merely the one in Parliament, but voices across society, like those who gathered at Elgar Parishad and those who spoke up against the CAA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy is often tiring. Governments come and go, but the status quo remains. Is there any real way to affect such large processes as a mere individual? Firstly, it would help us to recognise that democracy is not an end, it is a process in its conception. It is meant to be an endless cycle, and all we can do is improve and make the process as effective and inclusive as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition is at the heart of achieving such a democracy. The practice of demonising anyone who is opposed to the ruling elite is not a new one. It began with A K Gopalan and it continues to haunt us. At this crucial moment, it is the people who must reiterate their relationship with the opposition. Not in a partisan sense, but by remaining critical of whoever is in power and by collectively protecting those who actively do so. National security should no longer be able to act as a curtain hiding undemocratic and unconstitutional laws. We should be enraged at the idea of dissent being equated with terrorism. And we should be aware that fascist policies like preventive detention slowly steal our power as the people without us noticing. Let us not wait for the day that our voices are completely silenced.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Among the things Indians pride themselves on, tall stands the Indian Constitution. A beacon of everything that is right with the country. Not only does it carry the spirit of the nation’s freedom struggle, but it also is an amalgamation of what the founders of independent India thought were the solutions for the worries of a new India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Enemies of the People: a Study of the Libyan Conflict</title>
      <link href="/Enemies-of-the-People" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enemies of the People: a Study of the Libyan Conflict" />
      <published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Enemies-of-the-People</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Enemies-of-the-People">&lt;p&gt;Foreign intervention is a domino. Behind which are aligned hundreds of dominos, often not of the development and prosperity they promise, but of more foreign intervention. Libya is a perfect example. The recent Berlin Conference on Libya, which gathered world leaders to ‘decide’ the fate of Libya, is an irony in itself. It is an* intervention to cure an intervention*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand Libya (and arguably to understand anything), there is a need to historicise and contextualise the current situation. The conflict didn’t start in 2011 or 2014 but has much deeper roots in Libya’s history. For this reason, we can study the Libyan conflict in two stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libya before 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For much of its history, Libya was not a single unified land. Its three territories:Tripolitania, Cyrenaica and Fezzan were separated for much longer than they were united. Libya has continuously faced occupation by almost every power in history including the Greeks, the Romans and the Turks. It was only after the Italian occupation in 1911 that the three territories were unified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to their brutal treatment, the colonisers were inevitably faced with the discontent of their subjects. This gave rise to a Sufi movement, known as the Senussi order, which led the resistance. During the Second World War, Italy lost Libya to Britain and France and during this switch of colonisers, the Senussi order gained ground. In 1951, Libya was the first country to be granted independence by the United Nations. King Idris became the first Libyan monarch to rule the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 1959, everything changed. As rich oil reserves were found, Libya witnessed the transformative powers of oil. The West strategically increased its sphere of influence in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a bird’s eye view of this part of the world at the time, Arab countries were experiencing a wave of what came to be known as ‘Nasserism’. The word itself is based on the former Egyptian President Nasser, and represents an anti-imperialist and pan-Arab nationalist movement. Therefore, in the 1960’s, the Arab world was hit by a wave of Nasserist coups aimed at changing regimes that were reactionary and pro-West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libyan students began to agitate against the monarchy and on September 1, 1969, the revolution deposed King Idris. This revolution was led by a man whose name would define Libya for years to come, the 27-year-old General Muammar Gaddafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the coup, 12 Free Officers proclaimed themselves the Revolutionary Command Council, the government of the new republic, and Gaddafi was the de-facto head. Gaddafi was a man of the people, and his regime was extremely popular. He undertook large-scale nationalisation and rested his policy on three pillars, “Freedom, Socialism and Unity”. As a disciple of Nasser, he set out to tackle the unfair legacy of Western economic interference. By dismantling the influence of foreign companies and seizing complete control of the National Oil Corporation in 1970, he made Libya the first developing country to secure a majority share of the revenues from its own oil production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi used the income from oil to fund social welfare. While using the sharia law as a basis for social reform, he worked extensively for women’s empowerment, healthcare, education and house-building programs. He also used the money to fund revolutionary movements against injustice and colonialism all across the world. From helping those fighting apartheid to Marxist Palestinian liberation groups, the Irish Revolutionary Army as well as left-wing groups across Europe and Latin America, Gaddafi extended his hand of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A turning point in his rule came in April, 1973 with his “5 points” at a conference at Zuwarah. He proclaimed the beginning of a ‘Popular Revolution’. People’s committees were set up and he gave up his position only to remain as what he called the ‘Brother Leader’ to guide them through. The bureaucracy was to be removed and all opponents to the revolution were to be removed. This rang similar to the Great Cultural Revolution in China. Libya was renamed the &lt;em&gt;Great Socialist People’s Libyan Arab Jamahiriya,&lt;/em&gt; meaning a “state of the masses”, as conceptualised by Gaddafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to Mao’s &lt;em&gt;Red Book&lt;/em&gt; Gaddafi formulated a Third Universal Theory in his &lt;em&gt;Green Book&lt;/em&gt;. He saw both the USA and USSR as imperialist and set out to create a theory that took an Islamic Socialist standpoint. This revolution quickly became a witch hunt, either you were a revolutionary or a counter-revolutionary. Gaddafi was the centre of everything: all roads of power led to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Egypt’s new President Anwar Sadat began to fall in line with the Western powers in the 1970’s, Gaddafi’s pan-Arab ideal seemed further away. His staunch anti-American stance, as well as his undying support for revolutions against imperialism, labelled him “a supporter of worldwide terror”; Ronald Reagan called him the “Mad Dog of the Middle East”, to which Gaddafi retorted that America was the real terrorist. The USA bombed the Libyan capital in a clear attempt to kill Gaddafi but ended up killing civilians. After all, it was typical of the ‘leader of the free world’ to assassinate someone just because they didn’t like him. Further, severe sanctions were imposed on Libya after Gaddafi was alleged to be involved in an aeroplane crash in Scotland and the Berlin discotheque bombing (despite the lack of conclusive evidence). The Abu Salim prison massacre also drew flak from the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another turning point for Gaddafi came after the US invasion of Iraq and the death of Saddam Hussein. It was allegedly the fear of meeting a similar fate, and fear for the safety of his family, that brought a shift in Gaddafi’s attitudes. Libya began to pander to Western powers, like many nations who were earlier forced to do so. Reform programs were conducted, political prisoners were released and eventually, sanctions were lifted. Libya was officially invited back to the international fold, gaining levels of legitimacy that Gaddafi had never experienced in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, alienated him from the Arab world. Parrying with the powers who were supporting the Arab enemy, Israel, was not acceptable. In this situation, still wanting to be a part of a larger territory-based movement, Gaddafi moved from pan-Arabism to pan-Africanism. He became Chairman of the African Union in 2009. It also began to show that his alliance with the West did not align with his personal beliefs. This was seen clearly in 2009 when Gaddafi went to the UN for the first time and called the UN Security Council a “terror council”. American media said that he had shown his “true colours”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libya after 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Arab Spring uprisings across North African and Central Asian Arab states began to surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi’s stronghold was in the West of Libya and the East always felt wronged by him. The families of those killed in the Abu Salim massacre were planning a ‘day of rage’ on February 17 in Benghazi, a city in the East. However, the leader of the movement was arrested two days before the protests and his supporters clashed with security forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These protests quickly turned into protests against Gaddafi and his repressive regime. It moved on to other cities and attracted a growing number of militias, who were fighting against state power. The protests turned to armed rebellion, but Gaddafi decided not to use force, which is why the revolution grew without restraint and could not be suppressed once he decided to respond. The protests then reached his stronghold in Tripoli, the capital of Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2011, a group of military officials and ministers defected and set up a National Transitional Council (NTC). Working with the Arab League, they urged the UN to intervene in Libya. Many accusations of mass rapes, bombing and extrajudicial killings were put on Gaddafi forces. However, these were never proven. In fact, even many Western human rights NGOs visited Libya and found no proof of these allegations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a push for NATO action, and world leaders saw this as an opportunity for fulfilling personal vendetta. A no-fly zone was established over Libya and NATO declared that they would undertake “all necessary measures to protect civilians”. Under this guideline, NATO countries trained rebels and flooded them with weapons from the West despite the weapons embargo. Rebels divided by region and objectives joined hands against Gaddafi. Posters of freedom fighter Omar Mukhtar and flags of independent Libya flew again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August of 2011, the rebels took Tripoli without the fierce resistance that people had anticipated. The National Transitional Council took over control and Gaddafi went back to his hometown in Sirte. On October 20, with the help of NATO, the rebels found Gaddafi. What ensued was televised torture and murder, with the rebels showing no mercy and videotaping the entire scene. Gaddafi’s last words caught on camera were broken: “What did I do to you?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who fought for Gaddafi were killed or tortured and paraded around Tripoli. Many went missing and remain so till this day. Foreign leaders rejoiced. Hillary Clinton was caught on camera joking about his death, “We came, we saw, he died”. Gulf states were also relieved as Libya’s development threatened to put Central Asia in second place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed, however, was a power vacuum and violent in-fighting between militias as the differences had resurfaced once their common goal to get rid of Gaddafi was met. Although formally under NTC control, Libya was a patchwork of competing militias. In fact, the militia life became attractive to the youth as it paid much more than any other job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2012, parliamentary elections were hurried through, pressured by the international community. The NTC transferred power to the General National Congress (GNC) who were to rule only for 18 months. A series of decisions by them further reinforced the militancy culture. A state salary was given to those who fought in the revolution. Further, GNC gave into federalist demands from the East which set the precedent that force, or threat of force, would lead to concessions. Violence became a political currency. The most outright power grab was the 2013 Political Isolation Act which stated that if you were working under Gaddafi you could no longer hold a government post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GNC extended its term even though it was supposed to end in 2013. Simultaneously, General Khalifa Haftar rose in the East. He was abandoned by Gaddafi in Chad and subsequently rescued by the CIA and given citizenship in the USA. Upon his return in 2011, he formed the Libyan National Army in the East. He launched a ‘dignity war’ against the terrorist militias in Benghazi in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the June 2014 elections, an environment of violence had already been normalised. A party called the House of Representatives, backed by Haftar, won the majority and the government was shifted East to the city of Tobruk. However, the old government refused to give up power and there were two governments in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that during this civil war, the Tripoli controlled National Oil Corporation, as well as the Central Bank, continued to function under international pressure. So, militias were funded by the Central Bank on both sides with no national institutions or public services and oil sales boosted cash further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the UN tried to resolve the conflict by creating the Government of National Accord in Tripoli to act as an interim government of Libya, but they were not recognised by the Haftar-backed House of Representatives. Haftar slowly took control of Eastern oil ports and today controls most of Libya’s territory. Haftar aims to eventually take Tripoli and establish his regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which countries are invested and why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haftar is supported by Gulf countries like United Arab Emirates, Saudi Arabia as well as Egypt simply because they wish to curb the spread of ‘political Islam’, something that they believe the GNA stands for. These countries are largely responsible for the provision of arms, air support and troops to Haftar’s forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Turkey has been a foremost supporter of the GNA. President Erdogan has even promised military help to the GNA against Haftar’s Tripoli campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US, having arguably been the cause of this mess, has chosen to remain silent while officially supporting the UN efforts of a ceasefire. France and Russia, although officially supporting UN efforts, have also shown their vested interests by blocking an EU attempt to stop Haftar’s campaign. In fact, they have both been accused of providing weapons to Haftar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berlin Conference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Berlin conference was a last-minute attempt by Germany to salvage what little political process is left in Libya. Held on January 19, 2020, it was timed to defer Haftar’s ‘final assault’ on Tripoli. Germany, the only country in Europe with enough political clout to summon important players, came to everyone’s rescue - at least for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference ended with a 55-point communique calling for a permanent ceasefire, the implementation of a UN arms embargo, the dismantling of militias, and the resumption of the political process. However, this is impossible to implement and, honestly, a little ironic, considering that many of the conference member states are themselves suppliers of arms that keep the conflict afloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that this account brings is who is safeguarding the interests of the people? Protests from the grassroots have spread like fire in Libya, condemning the violence and the disrupting effects it has on everyday lives. Has international power politics gone so far that domestic populations do not even receive cursory importance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question we can ask is what did the death of Gaddafi really achieve? Many Libyans still mourn his death and hail his regime as a haven with free healthcare and education. Was his policy of using Libya’s oil for the Libyan people too much for the West to handle? One thing is clear - whichever foreign actor supported the revolution by way of arms or by way of silence, they remain enemies of the people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Foreign intervention is a domino. Behind which are aligned hundreds of dominos, often not of the development and prosperity they promise, but of more foreign intervention. Libya is a perfect example. The recent Berlin Conference on Libya, which gathered world leaders to ‘decide’ the fate of Libya, is an irony in itself. It is an* intervention to cure an intervention*.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The End of an Era</title>
      <link href="/End-of-an-Era" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of an Era" />
      <published>2020-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/End-of-an-Era</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/End-of-an-Era">&lt;p&gt;A globalized world means a lot of things, most of which is relegated to the back of our minds in the bustle of day-to-day life. The Brexit enigma too often fails to become imminent to those outside Europe, resting in our peripheral vision. This is partly owed to the large amount of time that has passed since Britain ‘left’ the European Union, without actually having left the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even until the December 12 general elections, with the possibility (not probability) of Labour leader Jeremy Corbyn’s victory, there were speculations regarding the future of the UK vis-a-vis leaving the EU. However, with the re-election of Conservative Party leader Boris Johnson as Prime Minister with an overwhelming majority, UK’s path to Brexit seems strikingly clear. In this environment, there is a need to clearly understand what has led to and what will potentially follow Brexit, hailed as possibly the most important moment in European history since the fall of the Berlin Wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of leaving the European Union has been on Britain’s mind from the moment it joined. Post Second World War tensions were high, and Britain’s economic growth was frightfully low. At the same time, in an attempt to ensure lasting peace, a few European states established the European Economic Community (EEC) hoping that economic interdependence would help avoid conflict. The EEC was a predecessor to the EU and surprisingly their old war ally Britain was not invited to the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in 1963, when the United Kingdom first applied for membership in the EEC, France’s President Charles de Gaulle &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/amp/s/www.bbc.co.uk/news/amp/world-europe-42165383&quot;&gt;vetoed its application&lt;/a&gt;. He claimed that the UK would always be on America’s side, even as a part of the EEC. UK became a member only in 1973 and just two years later a national referendum was held on whether to leave the Common Market. 67% voted to stay. In 1993, under the Maastricht Treaty, the European Union was formed to integrate states economically and politically, and to establish a common citizenship, currency and unified foreign policy. The EU was not bereft of skirmishes. Some of these would quite literally be the epitome of ‘first-world problems’ such as petty trade barriers on commodities ranging from beef to chocolate. Others were more prominent, such as those regarding immigration and sharing the burden of the crisis surrounding the Euro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three overarching reasons that fuelled the ‘eurosceptic’ view and simultaneously drove the ‘Leave campaign’ in Britain were sovereignty, immigration and the Euro. British conservatives loathed the idea that the mighty United Kingdom must take orders from someone else. The growing power of the European Parliament, the ridiculous amount of red tape and the growing lack of autonomy were major causes of resentment against the EU. The economic crisis of 2008 and the subsequent failure to deal with the flaws of the Euro made people not only in the UK but across the continent skeptical about the economic benefits of EU membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, what arguably had the most effect on the voters during the referendum was the free flow of people within the EU. Employment of locals posed one problem and a perceived relationship between immigration and crime posed another. The Migration Advisory Committee, however, in its review of the evidence of the labour market impact of EU migration, found that migrants have had little or no impact on the employment and unemployment outcomes of the UK-born workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should be noted is that EU states have a &lt;em&gt;choice&lt;/em&gt; to restrict free movement. It was a decision made by Tony Blair’s government in 2003 that allowed full free movement, which is what led to an increase in immigration. Nevertheless, in the EU referendum campaign, the Leave campaigners pinned the surge of workers on the EU and not the British government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Prime Minister David Cameron promised a national referendum on European Union membership, convinced that ‘Remain’ camp would win handily. That turned out to be a serious miscalculation. The referendum passed by a slim 51.9% in favour of leaving. However, there were stark differences across the UK. Northern Ireland and London voted to remain in the EU, as did Scotland, leading to renewed calls for another referendum on Scottish independence. The rest of England and Wales, however, voted in favour of Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After three of Theresa May’s Brexit deals were rejected by the UK, she resigned, leaving Brexit to her successor Boris Johnson. As of December 20, 2019, Johnson succeeded in getting his Withdrawal Agreement Bill (WAB) passed in the House of Commons, signaling the end of many years of political infighting regarding the issue. After the WAB becomes law, the withdrawal agreement also needs to be ratified by the European Parliament next month. Then the stage will be set for Brexit on January 31, when the post-Brexit transition period will begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 11 months, the UK will still follow all the EU’s rules and regulations, it will remain in the single market and the Customs Union, and the free movement of people will continue. The government and the EU will work out a Free Trade Agreement (FTA) for a smooth transition. Johnson has made it clear in the WAB that there will be no extension beyond 2020, and if no deal is worked out, then trade will carry on without agreement, meaning that tariffs would be levied on UK goods entering the EU and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WAB implies the following things. Firstly, the UK will have to settle its financial obligations to the EU. Secondly, UK citizens in the EU, and EU citizens in the UK, will retain their residency and social security rights after Brexit. Those residing in an EU country for five years or more can apply for residency in said country. Thirdly, the UK will leave the EU Customs Union, which exempts members from tariffs and levies uniform tariffs on other countries. Leaving the Customs Union means the UK will be able to strike trade deals with other countries in the future—although the exact extent of that freedom will only be revealed in the course of the trade talks with the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there is the matter of how Johnson has dealt with the new ‘Irish question’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Northern Ireland and its land border with the Republic of Ireland has posed a problem for Brexit for many years. Largely due to the ‘backstop’. The backstop was designed to ensure there would be no border posts or barriers between Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland after Brexit. Such posts would rekindle tensions and also serve as targets for potential insurgents groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new deal solves this problem by shifting these posts to the UK-Northern Ireland border instead. The actual checks will be on what is effectively a customs border between Great Britain and the island of Ireland, with goods being checked at ‘points of entry’ into Northern Ireland. Taxes will only have to be paid on goods being moved from Great Britain to Northern Ireland if those products are considered ‘at risk’ of then being transported into the Republic of Ireland. The deal gives the Northern Ireland Assembly a vote on these new arrangements, but only four years after the end of the transition period, in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Unionist Party of Northern Ireland opposes the WAB for leaving Northern Ireland behind and creating a situation where it must comply with EU customs laws even though it will be a part of the UK’s foreign trade deals. They advocate upholding the “economic and constitutional integrity of Northern Ireland within the United Kingdom”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integrity of the Kingdom is further rattled by Scotland, which had expressed a 62% desire to remain with the EU in 2016. Although it does not seem economically viable for Scotland to unilaterally remain with the EU, Brexit gave impetus to the Scottish Nationalist Party, for whom all roads lead to Scottish independence. Even though they had voted ‘yes’ to maintaining union with the UK in 2014, the Scottish public opinion is still sharply divided (50:50). The Scottish government has proposed holding a second referendum on Scottish independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brexit is no longer a lulling stream but a whirlpool that is approaching quickly and with near-complete certainty. Although the UK may achieve external sovereignty, the integrity of its union may be deeply affected. On the other hand, a year does not seem nearly enough to undo 46 years of Common Market. Although Johnson is staunch on wrapping up Brexit in 2020, things are bound to overflow. The ‘remain’ votes in 2016 were dominated by the youth. Which leads us to think that by the time deals are made and debts are paid, those who inherit a ‘free’ and ‘independent’ UK, may not want it at all. However, where there is political will there is a way, as can be seen in Boris Johnson’s dogged eagerness. We really are then, at the end of an era.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A globalized world means a lot of things, most of which is relegated to the back of our minds in the bustle of day-to-day life. The Brexit enigma too often fails to become imminent to those outside Europe, resting in our peripheral vision. This is partly owed to the large amount of time that has passed since Britain ‘left’ the European Union, without actually having left the European Union.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War</title>
      <link href="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War" />
      <published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War">&lt;p&gt;So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit
presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the
region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of
wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question
about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the
perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the
conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict
between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in
constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but
only do so with the use of proxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi
Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered.
Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and
the USA was its ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things
chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was
set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This
scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was
overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the
pliant Shah of Iran. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was
immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in
1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the
Shah and established an Islamic Shia government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia.
It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed
that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly
Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it
is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to
govern most alliances in the region today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a
CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan
to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US
alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries
except Iraq. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In
1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian
Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring
about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the
war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise
of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further
plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for
Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the
government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia,
Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially
quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on
September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed
on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions
have been placed on Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the
race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and
beyond their own boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yemeni Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is
important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict
has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi
armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This
will need some backtracking again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially
called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals
include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to
combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while
seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, however, is against &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; popular movement as it wants to maintain
the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the
Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the
Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of
the Houthi rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war.
Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces
the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving.
Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote
a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council,
a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secession&quot;&gt;secessionist&lt;/a&gt; organisation
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemen&quot;&gt;Yemen&lt;/a&gt;. Before unification in 1990,
Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with
the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of
the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as
extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi
Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a
common enemy in the Houthi rebellion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not
accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed
the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals,
Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many
refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple
conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more
difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Syrian Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East,
but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions
of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the
President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the
disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict
into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join
them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign
states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist
prisoners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called
Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from
Assad’s Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf
states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012,
Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support
Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia
countries were supporting Assad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used
chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike;
however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They
convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of
Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was
its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers
dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and
formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the
formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and
not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also
shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS
poses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training
program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They
struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian
Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish
militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but
Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA.
However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls
with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the
cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image
that barely resembles a state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Israeli-Palestine Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would
be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially
recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more
sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for
the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which
demands Israeli withdrawal from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli-occupied_territories&quot;&gt;occupied
territories&lt;/a&gt; and
full equality for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_citizens_of_Israel&quot;&gt;Arab-Palestinian citizens of
Israel&lt;/a&gt;, among other
things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite
(even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to
the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that
constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees
at their borders (although not always amiably). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of
Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied
land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart
and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of
any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements
violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population
into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is
another stain on its record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian
Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant
organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions,
which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank,
meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks
significantly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge
everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims
would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will
annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of
Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over
peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the
Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless
Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring
and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a
disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the
consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of
external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a
few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by
world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most
negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the
conflicts is bound to fail.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way. When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself.  As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East.  The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but only do so with the use of proxies. To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered. Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and the USA was its ally. Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the pliant Shah of Iran.  The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in 1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the Shah and established an Islamic Shia government.  The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia. It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to govern most alliances in the region today. As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries except Iraq.  Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In 1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire.  In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum. Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia, Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind.  Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions have been placed on Iran. This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and beyond their own boundaries. The Yemeni Civil War The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This will need some backtracking again. Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country.  Saudi Arabia, however, is against any popular movement as it wants to maintain the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of the Houthi rebels.  The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war. Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving. Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen. Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council, a secessionist organisation in Yemen. Before unification in 1990, Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a common enemy in the Houthi rebellion.  UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals, Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’. The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more difficult.  The Syrian Civil War The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East, but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries.  The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist prisoners.  Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from Assad’s Syria. In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012, Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia countries were supporting Assad.  Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike; however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels.  In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS poses. In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad. Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA. However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image that barely resembles a state. Israeli-Palestine Conflict Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which demands Israeli withdrawal from the occupied territories and full equality for Arab-Palestinian citizens of Israel, among other things. Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite (even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees at their borders (although not always amiably).  Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is another stain on its record. Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions, which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank, meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks significantly.  Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books. These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the conflicts is bound to fail.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?</title>
      <link href="/Greener-Pastures" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?" />
      <published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Greener-Pastures</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Greener-Pastures">&lt;p&gt;Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem absurd in general terms, how would you be an asset to a team that has already won? However, in politics, numbers are everything. If you defect to the majority, they increase their percentage points and maintain their majority. Each defector is like an additional layer of bubble wrap to the fragile glass of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a realist perspective, defection makes sense. If politics is all about power, then why would a politician willingly remain without any? At the end of the day, what good is ideological and partisan loyalty if you cannot make a dent in the political arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has a long (and borderline funny history) with defection. The phrase ‘&lt;em&gt;Aaya Ram, Gaya Ram&lt;/em&gt;’ (‘God came, God left’) was coined after an MP from the northern state of Haryana, Gaya Lal changed parties thrice on the same day in 1967. The period of continuous defections in the 1980’s is what led to the institution of the Anti-Defection Law in 1985 during the tenure of Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi’s government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anti-defection Law in India disqualifies members of the legislature under any one of the two conditions. Firstly, if they voluntarily give up membership of the party. And secondly, if they go against the party whip. The party whip is a command that comes from the party organisation, usually regarding which bills to pass and which to vote against. Interestingly enough, the first condition subsumes things other than simple resignation from the party. According to court judgments, the giving up of membership can be inferred from conduct. So, if a legislator was to speak against his party or in favour of the opposition, a case could be made against him against this law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many arguments against this law have been formulated in the past years. A major concern is the curbing of the freedom of expression. The defence to this freedom of expression argument is that differing opinions within parties leads to instability in the body politik. Just as defection makes sense for individual interest, the law makes sense for structural interests. However, at the end of the day, it means that if the legislator’s constituency is negatively affected by a certain policy or decision that his party is promoting, he doesn’t have the right to express dissent. The politician stands separated from his conscience. The second condition goes further to impair the legislator from taking any action or even abstaining to act for his party. Consent is dubious in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue was raised in the Supreme Court in 1992, to which it said, “the anti-defection law seeks to recognize the practical need to place the proprieties of political and personal conduct… above certain theoretical assumptions.” There is no right way of reacting when the apex court in your country calls the freedom of speech a “theoretical assumption”, but a bit of shock is valid. It is true that most cases of defection are about being on the winning team, about seeking out greener pastures. However, in situations such as post-poll alliances with an ideologically opposite party, the legislator must remain completely in favour of party decisions even at the cost of disappointing his constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stance of the court clearly states the assumption that the party is always right. While ideological compatibility is the basis for party formation, it is impossible for an entire party to have the same vision even under the same umbrella ideology. Many identities are embraced in a party and most of the times, these identities determine individual priorities. Denying a voice to any legislator goes directly against the spirit of democracy and multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this note, we can look into some of the structural and implemental loopholes that allow defection to continue despite the 1985 law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an exception that protects legislators from disqualification. If two-thirds of the legislators from a party agree to a “merger” with a different party, then this does not fall under the purview of the Anti-Defection Law. Using this loophole, 12 MLAs from the Congress party “merged” with the Telangana Rashtra Samithi, the ruling party in the southern state of Telangana, in June 2019. When read closely, the law provides this exception only when the original party merges with the party being defected to. Also, following certain court judgments, this decision of merger could only have been made by the All India Congress Committee and not the Telangana Pradesh Congress Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Presiding officer of the presiding party decides the verdict on defection cases. This officer is almost always a part of the ruling party. This means that defections &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party will be blocked but the ones &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party never will. Since the latter is the wave that defectors tend to ride, this provision effectively reduces the chances of defectors being disqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom, defection causes expulsion from the party but the legislator retains her seat. They are also only a result of defying a three-line party whip (the most urgent type of whip issued) as a sign of voluntarily giving up membership of the party. In Australia, some minor penalties such as barring of access to party resources is the punishment for defying party whips. It is the mildest in the USA where parties cannot expel their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark increase in defections paints a grim picture of political ethics in India. The Karnataka debacle, where Congress-JD(S) alliance MLAs defected to the BJP in the southern state after the party’s sweeping success in the national elections also reflects the blurred lines of the federal system of governance. 17 MLAs were disqualified after the incident in July 2019, allegations of bribery were thrown at the ruling party. The Indian Parliament’s upper house proceedings were repeatedly adjourned as Congress MPs demanded that the BJP government resign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only solution that seems to be in tandem with the political values that India’s Constitution embodies is that once there is defection to a new party, elections in that legislator’s constituency should be reheld. Admittedly this is a long and tedious process, but the provision might itself act as a deterrent for defection itself. There is a very small chance of a defector to be reelected by his people who most likely will hold feelings of betrayal and contempt for him. No legislator would want to face his constituency so soon after defecting. On the other hand, people would get a fair chance to elect someone with clear and full information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications relating to corruption have not even been discussed above as dissecting the role of money and muscle deserves a whole another article. However, it must be stated at least once that along with power, almost all defections involve promises of money and positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, welcome to the seven-decades old Indian democracy. Here, parties are oligarchic and legislators are for sale.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
