<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/vanshika.sighroha/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-04T11:00:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/vanshika.sighroha/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lebanon Quagmire Spins Out of Control</title>
      <link href="/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lebanon Quagmire Spins Out of Control " />
      <published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control">&lt;p&gt;On October 17,  2019, the Government of Lebanon, the world’s third most indebted country, decided to impose a tax on WhatsApp messaging application to engulf its amassed fiscal deficit. Unfortunately, nothing changed except the calamity exacerbating with each passing day. As the prices for basic commodities soar high, people find it difficult to feed themselves and have resorted to selling their gold in order to fill their empty stomachs. Adding to the troubles, the pandemic is likely to downgrade the economy, which is already unable to withstand the jolts it has received, by 12-13%. With an urgent requirement of aid to 75% of its population, an instantaneous revival for the economy reminds me of the Gucci shoes in my shopping wishlist for years that have never been able to find their path to ‘add to cart’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese have been known for maintaining a fine standard of living, the bars and restaurants have always stayed open even during the wars. The unhygienic water, heckling power supply, etc. was never a matter of concern for the middle-class until they enjoyed their affordable foreign tours. Despite a kaput monetary system, the luxuries and seamless interaction with the world have been courtesy of the Lebanese currency’s 22-year-old peg to the US currency, but who knew that this could turn into a substantial contributor to the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For several years, the Government has continued to borrow from global as well as domestic lenders to keep up with the pegged US dollars. As the Central Bank liberally hiked the interest rates, Lebanon became a strong magnet for the opulent investors across the globe. The unrealistic peg at 1,507 Lebanese pounds to a dollar and thriving efforts to keep up with it when there was a shortage of dollars in the market led to enormous debts. Further, to escape from the deficit, the Central Bank increased the interest rate to attract more investors. Nearly 50% of the state revenue goes into paying the debt, a major chunk of the remaining portion is put in effect for the government employees’ salaries, leaving very little margin for infrastructure development, capital investment, and expenditure on human resources. Thus, the Lebanese economy closes its boundary for revenue generation as there is no scope from other sectors, all the money is burned for consumption through imports, real estate and to defend the peg. Despite a sluggish economy, the government kept piling on the debts through depraved spendings, majorly on the expanded public sector which was put in effect to brim up their vote banks and divert focus from an ailing power grid. The situation became even more hostile owing to the political instability and the Prime Minister disappearing into Saudi Arabia, this shook the confidence of the Lebanese affluents who then decided to transfer their deposits out of the country. With the fear of depleting the country’s reserves, the banks had to close owing to the shortage of dollars. This has been a major concern for ordinary citizens, who have to stand in long queues to only return with a tiny amount of cash in hand which is insufficient to buy the daily bread, and have to sleep with an empty stomach during this pandemic. Economists view it as a matter of concern as the government continues to prioritise foreign creditors who hold an enormous $12 billion of the Lebanese debt, at the expense of the empty stomachs of its citizens. The banking sector, which has enjoyed mellow relations with the country’s political elite who held shares in some of these banks is a significant culprit. As the ordinary citizens fear a risk to their deposits, the commercial lenders who were always on the receiving end, even after capital controls in action have managed to pave their way for profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an uncertain political atmosphere, inefficient government policies driven with self-interest, faulty monetary system, and much more on the home-front, there are a few external factors that also act as a cherry to this toppling cake. A small country with a population of six million is largely dependent on remittances. 12.7% of the Lebanese GDP constitutes remittances from family members living abroad and majorly from the majestic oil-producers in the Middle-Eastern country, second only to Palestine. As coronavirus grips the world and the global GDP, numerous people have lost their jobs in various parts of the world. Owing to the global crisis, the number of people transferring and depositing money in Lebanon for their families and for tax exemptions abroad has seen a significant drop. In fact, they seek withdrawal from their already deposited funds in the Lebanese banks. The truncated oil prices have aggravated the revenue crisis for Lebanon. Moving closer, the oil-rich nations neighbouring the state of Lebanon that inhabited Lebanese emigrants have already cut down on the remittances they provided at regular intervals. These nations formulated the major chunk of the revenue Lebanon generated from remittances and used it further to fund its additional debt. With a threat of Saudi Arabia likely to expel Lebanese nationals, the inflow of remittance dollars that would support the dysfunctional peg has begun to diminish at a petrifying rate, making the situation even more muddled up for the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese economy finds itself amidst a thick forest, and the process of revival is definitely going to be a prolonged one along with a dire need for sustained efforts. With an urgent need for external liquidity that is possible only with the IMF reform programme which comes with a set of associated reforms that all the nations need to abide by when subscribing to the stimulus package. As the IMF estimates a debt reaching 155% of the Lebanese GDP, the government remains reluctant to adopt the IMF reforms and slashes the reports presented by the organisation. The economic experts and advisors, both within the state and globally, have to ultimately adopt the IMF reforms package to survive and provide daily bread to its citizens and the refugees. This detailed analysis is food for thought for further plan of action and devastating experience to learn from for the other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On October 17, 2019, the Government of Lebanon, the world’s third most indebted country, decided to impose a tax on WhatsApp messaging application to engulf its amassed fiscal deficit. Unfortunately, nothing changed except the calamity exacerbating with each passing day. As the prices for basic commodities soar high, people find it difficult to feed themselves and have resorted to selling their gold in order to fill their empty stomachs. Adding to the troubles, the pandemic is likely to downgrade the economy, which is already unable to withstand the jolts it has received, by 12-13%. With an urgent requirement of aid to 75% of its population, an instantaneous revival for the economy reminds me of the Gucci shoes in my shopping wishlist for years that have never been able to find their path to ‘add to cart’.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Coughing Losses: Indian States Subject to Austerity</title>
      <link href="/Coughing-Losses" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coughing Losses: Indian States Subject to Austerity" />
      <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Coughing-Losses</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Coughing-Losses">&lt;p&gt;As the number of COVID-19 cases continue to burgeon around the globe, most countries are experiencing an unprecedented slowdown with a shrinkage in economic activities. The already prevailing global slowdown in the pre-corona months has fused with the present-day scenario, resulting in an economic jolt. The ‘Great Lockdown’ as the IMF calls it, will give birth to economies with lowered interest rates and public debts reaching record levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India stands as the third worst-hit country globally with a tally nearing 700,000 cases. Looking deeper into the domestic circumstances, it is an unfortunate coincidence that the five gravely affected Indian states: Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu, Delhi, Gujarat and Uttar Pradesh, constitute 42% of India’s GDP. It is estimated that these five will make-up 48% of the total losses all the states will incur in 2020-21. Dried-up cash inflows have disconcerted both the Union and State Governments, however, as the actual battle is being fought by the State Governments and they are incurring the associated expenditure, the hardship is greater for them. With grave fiscal constraints, dealing with the loss of livelihoods has become a matter of concern for most states just as saving lives has. Cash handouts and provisions for subsidised food/ration have been put in place by states as humanitarian expenditure, not to ease the crisis. The return of migrant workers has exacerbated the problem with the disbursement on transport, quarantine facilities and rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite ironically, the ₹20.9 trillion stimulus package, which has been claimed to be 10% of the national GDP by the Union Government, is, in fact, an exiguous 0.8% of the GDP, as authenticated by a DSB Bank report and several other experts. This is one reason why the States have been demanding resources from the Union Government. The prime reason still lies in the fact that all the influential contributors (states) generated 60-70% of revenue from their own sources. These states gave us 75% of the GDP generated and hence, were the driving engines of the national economy—and therefore need and deserve more financial packages. Moreover, due to the already existing economic crunch that had affected the nation even before COVID-19, State Governments have been experiencing serious revenue impediments through the second half of 2019-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value Added Tax (VAT) on petroleum and excise duty on alcohol are the two predominant sources of revenue for states. Alcohol fosters the generation of ₹150 billion for states, on average, every month, along with ₹2 trillion brought in by petroleum products. The lockdown witnessed a plunge in the demand for petroleum and a collapse in the sale of alcohol, drying up the states’ revenues. The states generating a major portion of finances through their own resources are worst affected owing to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as the lockdown begins to ease out, relief is a far away dream for the states, liquor vendors are expecting a 25% fall in sales this year and bars have barely witnessed any footfall. Even though Delhi increased the excise duty on liquor, the gains weren’t fruitful enough to make good the deficit. Although oil prices in the international market stand truncated, the Union Government has continued to keep the prices high along with an escalation in the central excise duty to make good its deficit, so even if states increase VAT on petroleum, they are left with a very cramped taxing area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Goods and Services Tax (GST), which is collected by the Centre and then shared with the states comprises 43-44% of the revenue. Ever since its implementation, states have complained of revenue losses. One principal reason for this is the delayed and uneven release of the GST compensation. Compensation for December 2019 to February 2020 was released only in June, this led to much hue and cry as the states were starved of revenue during the lockdown. The Union Government’s assurance of a 14% annual growth for the next five years in the states’ GST revenue concoct mere dreams as the target is highly unachievable as they are likely to grow at a much lower rate. The only escape is borrowing, either the Centre borrows to issue grants to the states or the GST Council will have to borrow in order to keep pace with the share of compensation due to the states during these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crisis in hand, the Indian states have limited recourse. They can either cut down on their budgeted expenditure or increase tax buoyancy or increase their borrowings. Expenditure taps in the form of salaries, pensions, allowances, interests, etc. have already been turned off by many states as a cut in salaries, freezing of allowances and increments have been ordered by the State Governments. This compression of public expenditure is unlikely to provide the desired results. Borrowing from the market looks like candy to the eye and shall curb the issue of revenue in the short run, but states can’t afford to ignore the hindrances in borrowing, such as an expansion of the fiscal deficit in the long run. The second reason looks more political in nature, the Centre has inflicted four conditions on states – universalisation of ration cards, improvement in ease of doing business, reforms to make state-owned power distribution companies more profitable, and shoring up urban local body revenues. On the one hand, these conditions restrict the borrowing tendency of the states and on the other hand, the Centre has conveniently brimmed-up their coffer from ₹4.2 trillion to ₹12 trillion by inflating borrowings by 54% over the estimated budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation joins hands to fight the contagious virus but it seems that there is a grave disagreement between the States and the Centre when it comes to revenue generation, allotment and financial grants. The Centre curtails the income opportunities of the States through numerous constraints, yet expects States to fight the crisis on their own. The States look for grants in order to release the salaries of their employees and expects the Centre to reveal a package of at least 4-5% of the GDP. Many economists believe that an addition to the 15th Indian Finance Commission report, which allocates financial resources between the Centre and the states, in the form of a COVID-19 grant to states shall be a helping hand. A collaborative effort towards a common strategy aimed at rooting out the pandemic to ‘mask the losses being coughed by the states’ is the actual need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the number of COVID-19 cases continue to burgeon around the globe, most countries are experiencing an unprecedented slowdown with a shrinkage in economic activities. The already prevailing global slowdown in the pre-corona months has fused with the present-day scenario, resulting in an economic jolt. The ‘Great Lockdown’ as the IMF calls it, will give birth to economies with lowered interest rates and public debts reaching record levels.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis</title>
      <link href="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis" />
      <published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 China Financial Stability Report published by the People’s Bank of China officially deems 586 out of 4,379 Chinese lenders to be ‘high-risk’. The figures came into light only after the failure of a third bank within three months as national economic growth manifested a 30-year low. The Hengfeng Bank has become the third bank, after Baoshang Bank and Bank of Jinzhou, to suffer an economic collapse after a $40 trillion debt. But the Chinese government isn’t exceedingly famous for its honesty and transparency, thus the reported figure is likely masking the true extent of the banking quandary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has bailed out many of the high risk lenders. Precarious private shareholders have been effectively replaced by the ones backed by the state, often weaker in terms of their finances. The fact that bailouts are offered only for companies whose bankruptcy has a grave adverse impact on the economy as a whole and not just on a specified sector, cannot be ignored. Moreover, any amount of bailout allocated to this sector will have a domino effect on the Chinese economy which will be several times greater. For instance, the banking system calls for a 5-6% bailout which is equal to 20-24% of the Chinese GDP. A bailout of 20% of the GDP is a non-viable deal for any economy, even if it is China. The numeric is a statement of the fact that any pebble aimed at the banking sector shall bring ripples to the entire economy that in turn will shake China’s status of being a global economic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The People’s Bank of China conducted a stress test in the first half of 2019 on 1,171 commercial banks, 7.7% were stated to be at ‘extreme risk’ and deemed incapable of absorbing even a light shock, 13.6% will probably not be able to endure the financial crisis that shall follow. In November, Yingkou Coastal Bank and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/economy/china-economy/article/3035596/wechat-rumour-sparks-run-rural-chinese-bank-fresh-sign&quot;&gt;Yichuan Rural Commercial Bank&lt;/a&gt; – despite boasting healthy capital adequacy ratios – suffered bank runs as customers rushed to withdraw cash, fearing that the banks would close down, displaying a lack of confidence in banking institutions. The current situation is very similar to the one that cropped up in the late 1990’s. Towards the end of 1997, 20% of the main banks were non-performing, which was equivalent to a value of ¥1.19 trillion on the books of state-owned banks, which was deemed to be equal to 15.6% of the GDP. In order to resolve these crises and recapitalise the banks, ¥270 billion of special government bonds were issued and injected by August 1998. Walking on the same rope, the Chinese government is peddling its way through the crisis by adopting a somewhat similar technique. Today, the interbank market has been injected with around ¥2 trillion by the People’s Bank of China after the Baoshang Bank collapse. Along with this, a helping hand of the sovereign fund, China Investment Corporation, the Central Huijin Investment Company is injecting ¥60 billion into Hengfeng Bank. One of the 12 nationwide joint-stock banks in China, Hengfeng Bank is stacked up with non-performing loans and the situation became grimmer as the bank’s former president was handed out a death sentence for purloining funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, overlooking the different macroeconomic situation shall prove fatal to the Chinese economy in the present scenario. The key antidote for the crisis back then was the spurt of hyper economic growth in the early 2000’s. If China wants to avoid tormenting its economy with the inevitability of bad loans and its weakening banking structure, it will have to aim for a masterful economic growth. However, this stands as a challenge with the outbreak of COVID-19 and its likely aftermath on the global economy. Secondly, continuous evolution over the years has resulted in an entwined and fragile banking structure. The financial system in modern times has given rise to an integrated market that ensures banking transactions are speeded up and are facile in nature. Since the speed of transactions and their impact on the economy is brisk, it also means that any kind of shock in the structure is transmitted faster than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate and interbank customers suffer heavy losses, the volume of negotiable certificates of deposit—which are securities traded between financial institutions for short-term liquidity—has plunged by 90%. The situation threatens to cause the entire banking system to seize up as small and medium-sized banks are heavily dependent on liquidity in the interbank market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crisis should be an eye-opener for the administration as it calls for reforms in the entire financial system which has been overreliant on its banking sector for channeling funds. The fact that the financial structure has changed barely in the last fourteen years is an explanation for the crisis at hand. The world continues to keep a close watch on China, as this crisis is far too big to ignore because any large scale disruption in the driving engine of the global economy will lead the other economies into recession.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
