<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/vanshika.sighroha/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-08-11T10:09:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/vanshika.sighroha/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Kickstarting Revival: The Battered Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/Kickstarting-Revival-The-Battered-Indian-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kickstarting Revival: The Battered Indian Economy" />
      <published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Kickstarting-Revival-The-Battered-Indian-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Kickstarting-Revival-The-Battered-Indian-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Oxygen cylinders, hospital beds, exhausted crematoriums and medicines weren’t the mere struggles that India faced when the second wave of COVID-19, disguised as the tsunami, struck India. What was ravaged too was the Indian economy, which was already struggling to find a grip after it was derailed in the first wave.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There was no national lockdown imposed this time, keeping in mind the ramifications it could have generated on revenue and livelihood. The government was not in a position to politically afford another labour migration like in 2020.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, individual states were forced to impose a lockdown which caused India to lose $8 billion per week in May 2021.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decoding the Slowdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As per S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings, several companies have revised their growth estimate from 11% at the beginning of 2021 to 8%. It is vital to note that the Indian Economy will experience a loss of&amp;nbsp; ₹6-6.7 trillion by this fall of 3% in growth estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The second wave induced shutdown resulted in an unemployment rate of 17.4% and 13.5% in urban and rural areas respectively. As per the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), almost nine million salaried jobs were lost between February, 2021- April, 2021.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In addition to the already alarming situation, 97% of Indian households witnessed a tremendous fall in their incomes. Owing to the tremors felt by the Indian economy in 2020, people have started moving back to agricultural activities and are being forced into disguised unemployment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Lack of demand, the root cause of this economic mire, has continuously missed the eyes of the government. The choked sales of fast-moving consumer goods (FMCG), consumer durable goods, apparel, footwear and car sales that witnessed a dip of 25% have contributed to the degrowth of India’s GDP.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prescription for Revival&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India finds itself in a dual set of challenges. On one hand, it strives to swim its way through the crisis at hand and on the other, it needs to build a stronger exchequer for long term growth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To begin with, providing the jobless with financial assistance should be the stepping stone. The states are struggling to keep up with the inflation rate while they lend a helping hand. The Central government should come forward and pay the due GST compensations that it owes to the states, amounting to ₹ 63,000 crores, as it shall ease the financial strain of states.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The time calls for a sector-specific approach to be adopted by the policymakers in the Central government. Identification of sectors that are struggling to keep their heads above the water should be the first step in this direction. The stressed sectors like automobile, retail, tourism and Micro Small and Medium Enterprises (MSMEs) should receive targeted stimulus.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another crucial step for pushing towards equitable growth is restoring employment by kick-starting the infrastructure projects that have been halted due to the pandemic. Additionally, the multi-billion developmental projects shall help companies generate revenue and in turn enable individuals to pay their bills.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Reserve Bank of India has done its job by managing the liquidity. The ball to support the entrepreneurs is in the Central government’s court now.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Monitoring the price movement of top 10 raw materials being used by MSMEs and reduction of import duties on such materials should be taken into account, to make survival easier for such firms. Furthermore, experts have time and again advised the policymakers to expand the Emergency Credit Linked Guarantee Scheme (ECLGS) from ₹3 trillion to ₹5 trillion.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This might look like a 1991 moment for the Narendra Modi-led government, but the problem at hand is grave and far more complex. In 1991, the Indian economy was already in the growth momentum owing to the aggressive expansionary policy followed in the previous decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, this time, the economy was already experiencing negative growth since 2016, and 2020-21 brought itself not only a GDP contraction of 7-8%&amp;nbsp; but also a humanitarian crisis. Such a scenario cannot possibly be solved by simple policy tools.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the present scenario, the government must adopt a step-by-step approach to reform, especially because of the limited resources available to it. Speeding-up vaccinations should be on the priority list, as this will result in the revival of contact-based services like hospitality and tourism, which contribute a major chunk to India’s GDP.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This must be followed by increased government spending. The National Infrastructure Pipeline released by the government in 2019, which outlined capital expenditure worth ₹120 trillion over a period of five years, needs to be accelerated. This project can be easily accommodated, despite the government running deficits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A fantastic sector, to begin with, is healthcare. This has been the talk for many years and the pandemic has exacerbated the importance of a robust healthcare sector. Initiating development in this sector by building well-equipped hospitals across the 700 districts of the country will boost employment and revenue generation by many folds.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The middle-class of the Indian economy is the driver of consumption-demand. The pandemic has resulted in a lack of money in their hands, thus bringing the demand-driven economy to a screeching halt. The first wave resulted in 32 million Indians being pushed out of the middle class.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Why is this a cause of concern?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A middle-class person in India is defined with an income between ₹724 to ₹1,449 per day, and even this meagre income-earning group has shrunk by one-third. The government needs to provide tax relief to this class which will enable them to re-start their consumption-demand expenditure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There is a dire need of imposing a progressive tax system in the country.&amp;nbsp; Reports suggest that the top 10 rich families of the country were able to expand their wealth during this time, thus widening the already huge gap between the rich and the poor. Many other countries across the globe have begun charging higher taxes from the richest class and have cut down tax rates for the service class.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The continuous boost to exports along with the above-mentioned measures shall help India meet the challenges while it medicates the deep-rooted wounds of the second wave. Well-planned and efficiently executed policies by the government will decide the future of India’s rebound after the second-wave. But the question obviously remains if that will actually happen or not.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Oxygen cylinders, hospital beds, exhausted crematoriums and medicines weren’t the mere struggles that India faced when the second wave of COVID-19, disguised as the tsunami, struck India. What was ravaged too was the Indian economy, which was already struggling to find a grip after it was derailed in the first wave.&amp;nbsp; There was no national lockdown imposed this time, keeping in mind the ramifications it could have generated on revenue and livelihood. The government was not in a position to politically afford another labour migration like in 2020.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; However, individual states were forced to impose a lockdown which caused India to lose $8 billion per week in May 2021.&amp;nbsp; Decoding the Slowdown As per S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings, several companies have revised their growth estimate from 11% at the beginning of 2021 to 8%. It is vital to note that the Indian Economy will experience a loss of&amp;nbsp; ₹6-6.7 trillion by this fall of 3% in growth estimates. The second wave induced shutdown resulted in an unemployment rate of 17.4% and 13.5% in urban and rural areas respectively. As per the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), almost nine million salaried jobs were lost between February, 2021- April, 2021.&amp;nbsp; In addition to the already alarming situation, 97% of Indian households witnessed a tremendous fall in their incomes. Owing to the tremors felt by the Indian economy in 2020, people have started moving back to agricultural activities and are being forced into disguised unemployment.&amp;nbsp; Lack of demand, the root cause of this economic mire, has continuously missed the eyes of the government. The choked sales of fast-moving consumer goods (FMCG), consumer durable goods, apparel, footwear and car sales that witnessed a dip of 25% have contributed to the degrowth of India’s GDP.&amp;nbsp; Prescription for Revival India finds itself in a dual set of challenges. On one hand, it strives to swim its way through the crisis at hand and on the other, it needs to build a stronger exchequer for long term growth.&amp;nbsp; To begin with, providing the jobless with financial assistance should be the stepping stone. The states are struggling to keep up with the inflation rate while they lend a helping hand. The Central government should come forward and pay the due GST compensations that it owes to the states, amounting to ₹ 63,000 crores, as it shall ease the financial strain of states.&amp;nbsp; The time calls for a sector-specific approach to be adopted by the policymakers in the Central government. Identification of sectors that are struggling to keep their heads above the water should be the first step in this direction. The stressed sectors like automobile, retail, tourism and Micro Small and Medium Enterprises (MSMEs) should receive targeted stimulus.&amp;nbsp; Another crucial step for pushing towards equitable growth is restoring employment by kick-starting the infrastructure projects that have been halted due to the pandemic. Additionally, the multi-billion developmental projects shall help companies generate revenue and in turn enable individuals to pay their bills.&amp;nbsp; The Reserve Bank of India has done its job by managing the liquidity. The ball to support the entrepreneurs is in the Central government’s court now.&amp;nbsp; Monitoring the price movement of top 10 raw materials being used by MSMEs and reduction of import duties on such materials should be taken into account, to make survival easier for such firms. Furthermore, experts have time and again advised the policymakers to expand the Emergency Credit Linked Guarantee Scheme (ECLGS) from ₹3 trillion to ₹5 trillion.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; This might look like a 1991 moment for the Narendra Modi-led government, but the problem at hand is grave and far more complex. In 1991, the Indian economy was already in the growth momentum owing to the aggressive expansionary policy followed in the previous decade. However, this time, the economy was already experiencing negative growth since 2016, and 2020-21 brought itself not only a GDP contraction of 7-8%&amp;nbsp; but also a humanitarian crisis. Such a scenario cannot possibly be solved by simple policy tools.&amp;nbsp; In the present scenario, the government must adopt a step-by-step approach to reform, especially because of the limited resources available to it. Speeding-up vaccinations should be on the priority list, as this will result in the revival of contact-based services like hospitality and tourism, which contribute a major chunk to India’s GDP.&amp;nbsp; This must be followed by increased government spending. The National Infrastructure Pipeline released by the government in 2019, which outlined capital expenditure worth ₹120 trillion over a period of five years, needs to be accelerated. This project can be easily accommodated, despite the government running deficits.&amp;nbsp; A fantastic sector, to begin with, is healthcare. This has been the talk for many years and the pandemic has exacerbated the importance of a robust healthcare sector. Initiating development in this sector by building well-equipped hospitals across the 700 districts of the country will boost employment and revenue generation by many folds.&amp;nbsp; The middle-class of the Indian economy is the driver of consumption-demand. The pandemic has resulted in a lack of money in their hands, thus bringing the demand-driven economy to a screeching halt. The first wave resulted in 32 million Indians being pushed out of the middle class.&amp;nbsp; Why is this a cause of concern? A middle-class person in India is defined with an income between ₹724 to ₹1,449 per day, and even this meagre income-earning group has shrunk by one-third. The government needs to provide tax relief to this class which will enable them to re-start their consumption-demand expenditure.&amp;nbsp; There is a dire need of imposing a progressive tax system in the country.&amp;nbsp; Reports suggest that the top 10 rich families of the country were able to expand their wealth during this time, thus widening the already huge gap between the rich and the poor. Many other countries across the globe have begun charging higher taxes from the richest class and have cut down tax rates for the service class.&amp;nbsp; The continuous boost to exports along with the above-mentioned measures shall help India meet the challenges while it medicates the deep-rooted wounds of the second wave. Well-planned and efficiently executed policies by the government will decide the future of India’s rebound after the second-wave. But the question obviously remains if that will actually happen or not.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Wars: The Hole in a Country’s Pocket</title>
      <link href="/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wars: The Hole in a Country’s Pocket" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What gives rise to wars? Well, conflicts are an inevitable part of the survival of the human race; especially when existence is heterogeneous in nature. When conflicts intersect with political ideals and ideologies, land rights, religious dominance, etc they have the potential to churn out a war.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Time and time again, countries around the world have stepped down to avoid war but a few remain unlucky and suffer the aftermath. The cost of war is immeasurable for all the parties involved. No matter who wins the battle, the loss is suffered on all ends; and usually, it is equal in magnitude. Economics is well-stitched into a war, so much so that experts believe every war entails an economic motive irrespective of the reason presented to the public. This is probably why one will never come across two entities fighting for a barren land with no water sources, no mineral wealth and no means of attracting investment in any form. Even if the total area of such land can help the country expand its territorial boundaries, it is not worth a war!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To lay the foundation it is important to understand the ‘war economy’. When a nation is in a state of war, the prioritisation principle witnesses a shift in expenditure. The production of goods and services that support war efforts and strengthen the defence front of the country assume importance. A country at war re-configures its budget and diverts all the taxes towards national security, the nation might also borrow to fund its requirements. One ramification of war is that it encourages innovation. War economies demonstrate more technological, industrial and medical advancements as they are in competition to create cheaper defence products along with the emergency medical units to be well prepared. This is an instance of infrastructural development. However, the focus is not the welfare of its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One might expect wealthy nations to be more violent as they have more to fight over. However, the econometric evidence is divided, most researches show that wealth reduces the probability of a civil war by manifolds. In addition, economic growth acts as a shield against violence, while recession increases the probability. The most common reason for this is that wealthier societies are able to better protect assets, thus making violence less attractive for would-be rebels. Another explanation, given by political scientist Thomas Homer-Dixon argues that poverty causes violence, and points to cases where scarcity leads to migrations that result in conflicts between identity groups over resources. The cost of physical capital destruction and human capital destruction remain inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;Do wars benefit anyone?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It will be paradoxical to state that war will benefit the country. A conflict that results in loss of human lives, destruction of property, trauma, leaving hundreds of people homeless, and the list goes on, cannot do good to anyone. However, economics rises a notch above human sentiments and reflects on the infrastructural developments and a shift in the demand-supply chain. A country that is in a state of war will accommodate its working population in order to work to the brim and achieve the fullest of its capacity, thus aiming at full employment across different sectors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Spike in employment, the surge in working capacity and inclusion of the latest technology to produce efficiently helps in boosting economic growth. The government invests in the latest technology in order to keep pace with the war which in turn boosts innovation in the territory and paves way for research and development (R&amp;amp;D).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another important side effect of war is the change in social outlook and attitudes. History is evidence of the fact that women have stepped out of their houses in order to be a part of the labour force contributing to the battle whenever a war breaks out. Healthcare, a major support system during wars, witnesses women participating in large numbers to save the lives of soldiers. Various industries that work to boost the supplies welcome women in order to elevate the production capacity while the men go out to the battlefield. Women have played an important role in all the wars that humanity has witnessed till now, so much so that they became aware of their rights after World War I and World War II and with a stride of independence they continued to voice their rights and soon the demand for ‘vote’ was raised by women across the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is at stake for Israel-Palestine?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In May 2021, Israel and Pakistan counted 11 days of hostilities that resulted in the loss of life and physical capital on both ends. The housing ministry of Gaza stated that 16,800 housing units have been damaged. The electricity grids across Gaza remain dismantled with barely three-four hours of power supply in a day. The Hamas media office estimated the bombardments had caused $40 million in damage to factories and the strip’s industrial zone and other industrial facilities, in addition to $22 million in damage to the energy sector. In addition, the sanitation facilities have been damaged and the water supply remains disrupted with limited or no access to water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Israeli economy already contracted by 6.5% in the first quarter due to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The Central Bureau of Statistics predicts that the road to revival is likely to stay disrupted owing to the fight between Israel and Palestine. Israel’s manufacturers’ association reported a loss of $166 million as of 13 May 2021 because the south and centre of the country witnessed intense rocket fire from Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The economic relations between Israel and Palestine date back to 1967 when Israel occupied the West Bank and Gaza Strip and integrated their markets with its own. The Israeli economy was about ten times the size of its neighbour’s economy and the manufacturing sector’s GDP share was over four times larger. Thus the difference was between a large, rich and advanced economy and a small, poor and underdeveloped economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Both theoretical analysis and empirical studies suggest that the dynamics of such a relationship always generates two opposing forces that disproportionately affect the smaller economy and shape its development. A favourable repercussion is an increased demand for the products of the small economy, diffusion of technology and knowledge. Unfavourable repercussions arise from the disappearance of many industries in the small economy, its confinement to producing low-skill goods, and the emigration of a sizable segment of its labour force to the neighbouring economy, as well as to other countries. This suppression of a powerful neighbour has resulted in numerous incidents of violence, time and again. The end consequence has been that the region of Palestine has seen practically no development and has remained war torn.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, “who benefits from war?” remains unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What gives rise to wars? Well, conflicts are an inevitable part of the survival of the human race; especially when existence is heterogeneous in nature. When conflicts intersect with political ideals and ideologies, land rights, religious dominance, etc they have the potential to churn out a war.&amp;nbsp; Time and time again, countries around the world have stepped down to avoid war but a few remain unlucky and suffer the aftermath. The cost of war is immeasurable for all the parties involved. No matter who wins the battle, the loss is suffered on all ends; and usually, it is equal in magnitude. Economics is well-stitched into a war, so much so that experts believe every war entails an economic motive irrespective of the reason presented to the public. This is probably why one will never come across two entities fighting for a barren land with no water sources, no mineral wealth and no means of attracting investment in any form. Even if the total area of such land can help the country expand its territorial boundaries, it is not worth a war!&amp;nbsp; To lay the foundation it is important to understand the ‘war economy’. When a nation is in a state of war, the prioritisation principle witnesses a shift in expenditure. The production of goods and services that support war efforts and strengthen the defence front of the country assume importance. A country at war re-configures its budget and diverts all the taxes towards national security, the nation might also borrow to fund its requirements. One ramification of war is that it encourages innovation. War economies demonstrate more technological, industrial and medical advancements as they are in competition to create cheaper defence products along with the emergency medical units to be well prepared. This is an instance of infrastructural development. However, the focus is not the welfare of its citizens. One might expect wealthy nations to be more violent as they have more to fight over. However, the econometric evidence is divided, most researches show that wealth reduces the probability of a civil war by manifolds. In addition, economic growth acts as a shield against violence, while recession increases the probability. The most common reason for this is that wealthier societies are able to better protect assets, thus making violence less attractive for would-be rebels. Another explanation, given by political scientist Thomas Homer-Dixon argues that poverty causes violence, and points to cases where scarcity leads to migrations that result in conflicts between identity groups over resources. The cost of physical capital destruction and human capital destruction remain inevitable. &amp;nbsp;Do wars benefit anyone? It will be paradoxical to state that war will benefit the country. A conflict that results in loss of human lives, destruction of property, trauma, leaving hundreds of people homeless, and the list goes on, cannot do good to anyone. However, economics rises a notch above human sentiments and reflects on the infrastructural developments and a shift in the demand-supply chain. A country that is in a state of war will accommodate its working population in order to work to the brim and achieve the fullest of its capacity, thus aiming at full employment across different sectors.&amp;nbsp; Spike in employment, the surge in working capacity and inclusion of the latest technology to produce efficiently helps in boosting economic growth. The government invests in the latest technology in order to keep pace with the war which in turn boosts innovation in the territory and paves way for research and development (R&amp;amp;D).&amp;nbsp; Another important side effect of war is the change in social outlook and attitudes. History is evidence of the fact that women have stepped out of their houses in order to be a part of the labour force contributing to the battle whenever a war breaks out. Healthcare, a major support system during wars, witnesses women participating in large numbers to save the lives of soldiers. Various industries that work to boost the supplies welcome women in order to elevate the production capacity while the men go out to the battlefield. Women have played an important role in all the wars that humanity has witnessed till now, so much so that they became aware of their rights after World War I and World War II and with a stride of independence they continued to voice their rights and soon the demand for ‘vote’ was raised by women across the world. What is at stake for Israel-Palestine? In May 2021, Israel and Pakistan counted 11 days of hostilities that resulted in the loss of life and physical capital on both ends. The housing ministry of Gaza stated that 16,800 housing units have been damaged. The electricity grids across Gaza remain dismantled with barely three-four hours of power supply in a day. The Hamas media office estimated the bombardments had caused $40 million in damage to factories and the strip’s industrial zone and other industrial facilities, in addition to $22 million in damage to the energy sector. In addition, the sanitation facilities have been damaged and the water supply remains disrupted with limited or no access to water. The Israeli economy already contracted by 6.5% in the first quarter due to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The Central Bureau of Statistics predicts that the road to revival is likely to stay disrupted owing to the fight between Israel and Palestine. Israel’s manufacturers’ association reported a loss of $166 million as of 13 May 2021 because the south and centre of the country witnessed intense rocket fire from Gaza. The economic relations between Israel and Palestine date back to 1967 when Israel occupied the West Bank and Gaza Strip and integrated their markets with its own. The Israeli economy was about ten times the size of its neighbour’s economy and the manufacturing sector’s GDP share was over four times larger. Thus the difference was between a large, rich and advanced economy and a small, poor and underdeveloped economy.&amp;nbsp; Both theoretical analysis and empirical studies suggest that the dynamics of such a relationship always generates two opposing forces that disproportionately affect the smaller economy and shape its development. A favourable repercussion is an increased demand for the products of the small economy, diffusion of technology and knowledge. Unfavourable repercussions arise from the disappearance of many industries in the small economy, its confinement to producing low-skill goods, and the emigration of a sizable segment of its labour force to the neighbouring economy, as well as to other countries. This suppression of a powerful neighbour has resulted in numerous incidents of violence, time and again. The end consequence has been that the region of Palestine has seen practically no development and has remained war torn.&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, “who benefits from war?” remains unanswered.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What seeds medical tourism?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Home Front&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, &lt;em&gt;atithi-devo-bhava &lt;/em&gt;(guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp; Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp; Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility. What seeds medical tourism? Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp; India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp; While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp; The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp; The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes. India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp; Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp; On the Home Front The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp; Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp; The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp; Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, atithi-devo-bhava (guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Contracting India</title>
      <link href="/Contracting-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Contracting India" />
      <published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Contracting-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Contracting-India">&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy contracted by a drastic 23.9% in the April-June quarter of 2020-21 which is being stated as the most drastic fall in the Indian economy. What is more worrisome is the fact that this diminution is the worst amongst the world’s top economies and is an issue of immense concern for a major developing economy like India. The extent of the damage is expected to be manifold with the informal sector being the worst hit and revival looking like a prolonged journey. This can be supported by a statement made by Professor Arun Kumar of &lt;em&gt;New Delhi’s Institute of Social Sciences&lt;/em&gt; wherein he estimates the economic slide to be a negative 40% if the informal sector is taken into account. While the outbreak of COVID-19 is the prime cause of the gloomy economy, the already prevalent global economic slowdown and side-effects of the trade war cannot be overlooked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 25, 2020, India declared a complete national lockdown which was the world’s largest lockdown owing to the widespread pandemic. Apart from the limited movement of essential commodities, all businesses either came to a standstill with bleak immunity to have a revival spurt or they got wiped out. With people losing jobs in various sectors of the economy, the rise in unemployment has only deepened the strain. Experts analyse the figures and the trend as the onset of India’s largest recession since 1996.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For emerging economies, the prospects of a speedy recovery seem to be dim as per the International Monetary Fund (IMF), but the scenario is worst for India as the GDP contracted by a way larger margin than what was actually predicted. Adding to the crisis is the prediction by IMF which forecasted a contraction of 10.3% in the GDP in the fiscal year 2021, against the Central Bank’s prediction of 9.5%. The forecast in itself brings about a cloud of panic as this rate was predicted to be 4.5% in June 2020, the 5.8% leap is a near-indigestible figure for an economy of a great significance like that of India. The global economic significance that the nation has managed to engrave and give a stiff fight to its neighbour finds itself dwindling as China’s road to revival is far stronger than what was anticipated. While households and small businesses stand wrecked as an aftermath of the lockdown, the government has been continuously chalking out strategies to boost demand as a measure to curtail the downfall of one of the world’s major economies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quake in the economy shook all the sectors but the major contributors like construction, manufacturing and transportation were the worst hit. While agriculture did fairly well with an unexpected growth of 3.4%, it wasn’t strong enough to nullify the 39.3% contraction in the manufacturing sector, 23.3% in the mining sector, and 50.3% in the construction sector. Not only this, transportation along with trade, hotels, communication and broadcasting shrank by 47% in the first quarter. The pandemic forced the export shipments to dry out, people were locked at home with no eating out and no tourism. Businessmen had to either shut down their trade or put it to a halt. The prostration of the real-estate sector cannot be overlooked, which is clearly evident from the sharp fall in the rates and lack of demand for property. Along with this, tenants began emptying spaces already rented-out, as many started moving back to native places owing to no job in hand. Hence, the sectors that managed to keep themselves afloat in these troubled times could not stop the others from slipping down a sharp cliff.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the most profound problem that the Indian economy faces is that of its informal sector. While India’s large and a considerable proportion of workforce adjusts itself in the informal sector, fled back to its hometowns with a lesser impetus to come back. With no food to fill their stomachs, this downtrodden section of the society finds itself in a quagmire.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road to revival is definitely a tough one, but the government is gearing up itself in all and every way possible. With a systematic unlocking of the economy, the growth is finding its way back. While the experts call for a need to introduce a fresh stimulus package for the middle class, the government seems to be delaying its actions aimed at fighting the slowdown. But why a stimulus package for the middle class? The answer lies in the urgent need to revive the private consumption, that is to generate demand. The driving factor behind the slowdown remains a slowed consumption and lack of demand from the middle-class which forms an important chunk of the population consuming the most. A stimulus package to this sect of the population would mean kickstarting the revival process, and 85-90% of the population in this section is employed either in the government sector or in Public Sector Units (PSUs). It is evident that the government is functioning to the best of its capacity in these unprecedented times. Nevertheless, it is very important to clear state dues at the earliest in order to ensure revival in each and every part of the country. While the states and the Centre have been in a tussle over pending Goods and Sales Tax (GST) compensations, the Centre clearly stated that it cannot submit these pending compensations to the states owing to the medical and financial emergency and has, in fact, demanded the states to pay their GST dues for the year by borrowing, thus adding to the stress for the State governments who are already struggling to extract revenue. This is in complete contradiction to the ex-RBI Governor, Raghuram Rajan’s, statement who clearly stated in a recent article the dire need to replenish the state’s coffers as a crucial move towards recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With enough food for thought and tremendous scope to plan out recovery models, there is another contradiction this article will close itself with. At the beginning of 2020, while presenting the budget, the Honourable Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman had assumed a GDP growth of 10% for the fiscal year and moving closer to the target of a $5 trillion economy by 2024. On the contrary, the world’s fifth-largest economy in the pre-Covid era is believed to get 10% smaller as per economists across the world. The dire need to act real quick along with substantial stimulus packages is expected out of the government without any further delay, otherwise, the re-examination of the targets and goals stated in the budget for the financial year 2020-21 will be the last resort.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian economy contracted by a drastic 23.9% in the April-June quarter of 2020-21 which is being stated as the most drastic fall in the Indian economy. What is more worrisome is the fact that this diminution is the worst amongst the world’s top economies and is an issue of immense concern for a major developing economy like India. The extent of the damage is expected to be manifold with the informal sector being the worst hit and revival looking like a prolonged journey. This can be supported by a statement made by Professor Arun Kumar of New Delhi’s Institute of Social Sciences wherein he estimates the economic slide to be a negative 40% if the informal sector is taken into account. While the outbreak of COVID-19 is the prime cause of the gloomy economy, the already prevalent global economic slowdown and side-effects of the trade war cannot be overlooked.&amp;nbsp; On March 25, 2020, India declared a complete national lockdown which was the world’s largest lockdown owing to the widespread pandemic. Apart from the limited movement of essential commodities, all businesses either came to a standstill with bleak immunity to have a revival spurt or they got wiped out. With people losing jobs in various sectors of the economy, the rise in unemployment has only deepened the strain. Experts analyse the figures and the trend as the onset of India’s largest recession since 1996.&amp;nbsp; For emerging economies, the prospects of a speedy recovery seem to be dim as per the International Monetary Fund (IMF), but the scenario is worst for India as the GDP contracted by a way larger margin than what was actually predicted. Adding to the crisis is the prediction by IMF which forecasted a contraction of 10.3% in the GDP in the fiscal year 2021, against the Central Bank’s prediction of 9.5%. The forecast in itself brings about a cloud of panic as this rate was predicted to be 4.5% in June 2020, the 5.8% leap is a near-indigestible figure for an economy of a great significance like that of India. The global economic significance that the nation has managed to engrave and give a stiff fight to its neighbour finds itself dwindling as China’s road to revival is far stronger than what was anticipated. While households and small businesses stand wrecked as an aftermath of the lockdown, the government has been continuously chalking out strategies to boost demand as a measure to curtail the downfall of one of the world’s major economies. The quake in the economy shook all the sectors but the major contributors like construction, manufacturing and transportation were the worst hit. While agriculture did fairly well with an unexpected growth of 3.4%, it wasn’t strong enough to nullify the 39.3% contraction in the manufacturing sector, 23.3% in the mining sector, and 50.3% in the construction sector. Not only this, transportation along with trade, hotels, communication and broadcasting shrank by 47% in the first quarter. The pandemic forced the export shipments to dry out, people were locked at home with no eating out and no tourism. Businessmen had to either shut down their trade or put it to a halt. The prostration of the real-estate sector cannot be overlooked, which is clearly evident from the sharp fall in the rates and lack of demand for property. Along with this, tenants began emptying spaces already rented-out, as many started moving back to native places owing to no job in hand. Hence, the sectors that managed to keep themselves afloat in these troubled times could not stop the others from slipping down a sharp cliff.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, the most profound problem that the Indian economy faces is that of its informal sector. While India’s large and a considerable proportion of workforce adjusts itself in the informal sector, fled back to its hometowns with a lesser impetus to come back. With no food to fill their stomachs, this downtrodden section of the society finds itself in a quagmire.&amp;nbsp; The road to revival is definitely a tough one, but the government is gearing up itself in all and every way possible. With a systematic unlocking of the economy, the growth is finding its way back. While the experts call for a need to introduce a fresh stimulus package for the middle class, the government seems to be delaying its actions aimed at fighting the slowdown. But why a stimulus package for the middle class? The answer lies in the urgent need to revive the private consumption, that is to generate demand. The driving factor behind the slowdown remains a slowed consumption and lack of demand from the middle-class which forms an important chunk of the population consuming the most. A stimulus package to this sect of the population would mean kickstarting the revival process, and 85-90% of the population in this section is employed either in the government sector or in Public Sector Units (PSUs). It is evident that the government is functioning to the best of its capacity in these unprecedented times. Nevertheless, it is very important to clear state dues at the earliest in order to ensure revival in each and every part of the country. While the states and the Centre have been in a tussle over pending Goods and Sales Tax (GST) compensations, the Centre clearly stated that it cannot submit these pending compensations to the states owing to the medical and financial emergency and has, in fact, demanded the states to pay their GST dues for the year by borrowing, thus adding to the stress for the State governments who are already struggling to extract revenue. This is in complete contradiction to the ex-RBI Governor, Raghuram Rajan’s, statement who clearly stated in a recent article the dire need to replenish the state’s coffers as a crucial move towards recovery. With enough food for thought and tremendous scope to plan out recovery models, there is another contradiction this article will close itself with. At the beginning of 2020, while presenting the budget, the Honourable Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman had assumed a GDP growth of 10% for the fiscal year and moving closer to the target of a $5 trillion economy by 2024. On the contrary, the world’s fifth-largest economy in the pre-Covid era is believed to get 10% smaller as per economists across the world. The dire need to act real quick along with substantial stimulus packages is expected out of the government without any further delay, otherwise, the re-examination of the targets and goals stated in the budget for the financial year 2020-21 will be the last resort.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Battle of the Superpowers</title>
      <link href="/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Battle of the Superpowers" />
      <published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers">&lt;p&gt;The two driving engines of the global economy have been locked in a trade war since July 6, 2018, with the United States imposing a 25% tariff on $34 billion worth of Chinese imports. While Trump claims tariff policy to be a practice to encourage the consumption of American products by making imported goods and services more expensive, it is, in fact, a tool adopted by the US to force China to make changes to its “unfair trade practices” (as termed by the United States). Economists are viewing this trade war as a by-product of the ongoing battle between the two nations for economic and technological world dominance, along with a wave of nationalism, protectionism, and self-reliance growing almost everywhere including the US. The trade war has adversely affected the economic growth of both China and the United States. With the onset of COVID-19, the grievances have increased and a sharp fall in the GDP has been observed in both the nations. The impact of the trade war is not limited to these two parties, the global economy too has witnessed a slowdown owing to the influence that the US and China possess on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial growth rate has hit its seventeen-year low in China, a clear indication of the heavy brunt being felt by China. The trade war continues to threaten the rising global economic influence of China and exerts downward pressure on Chinese economic growth. Experts on the Chinese economy view this war as fatal for business operations and believe that it is likely to leave a long-lasting adverse impact. They view it as the American leadership’s eloquence disguised for selfish national interests and the desire to maintain American hegemony, which has been at play ever since the States ended its cold war with the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR). The domestic reporting on the trade war is censored in China, the situation on the ground is difficult to comment upon, but Chinese social media has managed to throw some light on the adversities by drawing reference from the Marvel Comics wherein Thanos, the villain wipes out half of all the life in the universe using the infinity gauntlet (a superpower); similarly, Trump is believed to wipe out half of China’s investors and businesses using this superpower of tariff policy. The halt in the manufacturing sector in China can be observed by understanding these events from the Chinese industrial city, Dongguan. This sprawling manufacturing hub Dongguan, nicknamed as the ‘Workshop of the World’, is the hardest hit by the ongoing trade war. The impact isn’t limited to the manufacturing sector alone, food joints and other budgeted sources of entertainment in and around the industrial complexes of Dongguan have been shut down too, the bars that were mostly over-crowded during shift changes in the factories now accommodate empty chairs. Dongguan produces and exports a majority of chunk to the United States, and specialises in shoes and brightly coloured plastic bags (for detergents, candies, apparels, dog poop and other essentials needed by Americans in their daily lives), with a double-digit tariff on these goods, the loud noises of the machines in the factories have been muted. Workers residing nearby have begun to migrate back to their native home-towns as America shifts the hub to Vietnam and Indonesia, dropping China’s exports to the US (the country it exported more to than any other country) by 12%. The Chinese economy finds itself in a swamp due to a number of structural lags like the failing banking system, lack of low-skilled workers in the factories, economic over-reliance on manufacturing, ageing workforce, etc., followed by a trade war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tariff policy has not been a cake-walk for the United States too, with 3 million people losing their jobs, the US economy has come to a standstill. The consumers, businessmen, investors and farmers have expressed their dissent on the tariff policy inflicted by Trump’s administration. Though the effect felt on American exports is comparatively smaller than its Asian rival, a number of businesses and various industrialists in the manufacturing sector have felt the brunt. The lower profit margins have infuriated American companies and the farmers protested against the $24 billion worth market they lost in China as a result of retaliatory actions from the American rival in the Asian continent. While America explores new opportunities outside China to compensate for the goods it imported from the dragon, the prices continue to inflate in the American market. Is the trade war worth the pain it has caused to the American economy, which is in the worst shape since the Great Depression?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various emerging economies have been fortunate enough to draw the attention of the American, European and Japanese investors to import the substitutes from countries like Indonesia, Vietnam, Singapore, India and others. A switch in the wave of the global market shall take time to adjust and establish a smooth-sailing ride for the world, but at present, the European market is being strangled the most because of the uncertainty that prevails in the global market. The United States of America and the European Union have always worked in coordination and agreement in like-minded economic organisations and the US continues to be Europe’s most important trade and investment partner. Thus, America’s inward-looking policies have been a matter of great concern for the European countries as well. With the global wind against China amidst the blame-game for the pandemic and China’s furious economic behaviour in the market, the European continent cannot afford to turn its neck towards the Asian giant. Europe too has expressed its grievances on the unfair trade practices by China and has expressed its concerns over the theft of intellectual property by China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the EU can manage to carve its niche in the global market by accommodating the void the two rivals create in each other’s trade. Similarly, Britain too can utilise this opportunity to establish its financial and tech markets in Washington and profit from the growing dissent between the States and the Dragon. Apart from Europe, India too should utilise this opportunity by making a shift in its manufacturing sector as both the US and China are likely to shift their investment flow towards India. Indian exporters should definitely take the risk to explore the gap that the trade war will generate, as the US imposes higher tariffs on Chinese goods and vice versa, this is the most awaited chance for exporters to fiddle and find a space in both the markets. Xiaomi, known as China’s Apple (iPhone), has the largest market in India outside China, India can and should definitely use this opportunity to establish a strong profit margin for itself. While India gained about $775 million additional exports from the US, Apple is likely to shift its base for manufacturing in India, which would make it the largest assembler of iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade war has definitely teetered the global economy to uncertainties and an unprecedented slowdown, the global pandemic made it more difficult for the economies to survive this wind and stand tall in the global market. Whether America continues to maintain its hegemony or China will take over the global market, will remain an unanswered question for a while until the world revives and breathes into a fresh economic environment post the COVID-19 period.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The two driving engines of the global economy have been locked in a trade war since July 6, 2018, with the United States imposing a 25% tariff on $34 billion worth of Chinese imports. While Trump claims tariff policy to be a practice to encourage the consumption of American products by making imported goods and services more expensive, it is, in fact, a tool adopted by the US to force China to make changes to its “unfair trade practices” (as termed by the United States). Economists are viewing this trade war as a by-product of the ongoing battle between the two nations for economic and technological world dominance, along with a wave of nationalism, protectionism, and self-reliance growing almost everywhere including the US. The trade war has adversely affected the economic growth of both China and the United States. With the onset of COVID-19, the grievances have increased and a sharp fall in the GDP has been observed in both the nations. The impact of the trade war is not limited to these two parties, the global economy too has witnessed a slowdown owing to the influence that the US and China possess on the world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Narrating The Plodding South-African Economy</title>
      <link href="/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Narrating The Plodding South-African Economy" />
      <published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy">&lt;p&gt;The second-largest producer of gold in the world is in dire need of its sluggish economic growth to be narrated and analysed. Along with gold, diamond and platinum are the top three exports of South Africa, it is the largest producer of chrome, manganese, platinum, vanadium, and vermiculite; second largest producer of ilmenite, palladium, rutile and zirconium, and most significantly, it is the world’s third-largest exporter of coal. Despite being a king-pin in precious gemstones and minerals, three in every four South Africans live with a constant threat of poverty taking over their daily lives. The most industrialised country of the African continent has not expanded by more than 2.5% a year since 2013, with nearly 50% of the South African population living in the state of poverty. Astoundingly, the swamp isn’t a decade old but has been impending for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Struggling with a mere growth rate of 1.1% per year, the economy cannot absorb the rapidly growing population, leading to a higher rate of deprivation among the people. The cyclical tools which are veiled in monetary and fiscal policies cannot break down the encumbrances of structural weaknesses in the economy. To begin with, even after showcasing improvement, the household saving rate in South Africa is a meagre 0.2% (as per the fourth quarter of 2017). Why is the saving rate a matter of significance? Well, it is the savings that generate capital for investment spending, with no space for investment, the economy can never accelerate due to the lagging infrastructure that has the potential for future growth and provision of high returns to the Gross Domestic Product (GDP). The present rate of household savings is utterly unfavourable when compared to other emerging market countries which usually maintain a rate above 2% and invest rigorously in infrastructural development along with measures to generate and expand the capacity for new capital, unlike the African country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education, the pavement to advancement, has continued to be an issue of concern for South Africa as it was ranked the 75th nation out of 76 in the ‘Table of Education Systems’ drawn by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). The fourth industrial revolution hovers over the globe and calls for a skilled workforce, which has been a clear lag for the African country, the paucity of a skilled workforce arising out of an underdeveloped education system has been ranked as the third-most problematic factor for doing business in South Africa. Revamping the educational structure and enhancing its delivery should be the top-notch priority while restructuring the government policies in order to escalate economic progress, standard of living, ease of doing business, and to attract global as well as domestic investors. The smooth functioning of small and medium-sized enterprises in a developing nation is as cardinal as education to eradicate unemployment and foster a healthy living index. Government bureaucracy, heavy tax burden, and constrictive labour regulations are few of the many unnecessary curtailments for the small and medium enterprises (SMEs). The state-owned enterprises, deployed to generate utility for the public have been relocated to cushion the coffers of a selected few. The public enterprises have capitulated to inefficiency, mismanagement of revenue, bureaucratic lapses, tender rigging, delay in project delivery. This has resulted in a distorted infrastructure, scanty services, and has robbed the national treasure of billions in terms of opportunity cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How disinteresting has it been for the investors? Well, South Africa was ranked 82 out of 190 countries in the ‘Ease of Doing Business Index’ drawn by the World Bank in 2017. It might seem impressive to find a country with numerous economic and financial blemishes to find a spot in the middle of the Index, but the 32nd rank in 2008 is an epiphany to the swift fall. The plethora of monetary policies that have been put into effect will remain ineffective if the grass-root structure of the economic administration is not revamped and paralleled with the fast-paced world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering its 70th month of a downward cycle, the longest since 1945, the economy is stuck in a mire, with rescue looking like a far-fetched dream. A surfeit of sectors felt the tremors of the contracting economy but manufacturing, mining and trade, catering and accommodation, agriculture, and the power sector have been the worst hit. Experts are of the view that low demand, sharp rising fuel prices, and Eskom’s load shedding are the prime factors contributing to the contraction of the economy. Eskom is amongst the top twenty power utilities worldwide, it generates more than 90% of South Africa’s power and 40% of the electricity in the African continent. The surging salary, fuel, and debt-servicing costs along with mismanagement and corruption scandals have led to Eskom having a $30 billion debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of ambitious economic programmes accompanied by the coronavirus pandemic will deepen the crack in the economy. As the nation is in a state of lockdown, hue and cry amongst the public with a lack of essentials and power cuts have worsened the strain on the government. South Africa was one of the few nations to implement the most draconian containment measures to curb the spread of the virus, with an already dwindling economy, a complete shutdown of all the major industries has piled up the heap of debts for the administration. A failure in the political atmosphere, inefficiency of the government to deliver to the public instead of stocking up their coffers, and inviting projects with vested interests have continued to cause a haemorrhage with no defined antidote to the South African economy. Revival seems like a mere dream when the present trends of a global slowdown are observed, the various developed nations which were key importers of the South African minerals and precious gems have curtailed their imports, leaving South Africa with a depleting repository. Failing to engage investors, the government continues to borrow in order to repay its already mounting debts, the matter of concern still remains a part of the vicious cycle as no monetary policy or financial injections can break down the persisting swamp which has driven half of South Africa into poverty.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The second-largest producer of gold in the world is in dire need of its sluggish economic growth to be narrated and analysed. Along with gold, diamond and platinum are the top three exports of South Africa, it is the largest producer of chrome, manganese, platinum, vanadium, and vermiculite; second largest producer of ilmenite, palladium, rutile and zirconium, and most significantly, it is the world’s third-largest exporter of coal. Despite being a king-pin in precious gemstones and minerals, three in every four South Africans live with a constant threat of poverty taking over their daily lives. The most industrialised country of the African continent has not expanded by more than 2.5% a year since 2013, with nearly 50% of the South African population living in the state of poverty. Astoundingly, the swamp isn’t a decade old but has been impending for decades.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lebanon Quagmire Spins Out of Control</title>
      <link href="/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lebanon Quagmire Spins Out of Control " />
      <published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control">&lt;p&gt;On October 17,  2019, the Government of Lebanon, the world’s third most indebted country, decided to impose a tax on WhatsApp messaging application to engulf its amassed fiscal deficit. Unfortunately, nothing changed except the calamity exacerbating with each passing day. As the prices for basic commodities soar high, people find it difficult to feed themselves and have resorted to selling their gold in order to fill their empty stomachs. Adding to the troubles, the pandemic is likely to downgrade the economy, which is already unable to withstand the jolts it has received, by 12-13%. With an urgent requirement of aid to 75% of its population, an instantaneous revival for the economy reminds me of the Gucci shoes in my shopping wishlist for years that have never been able to find their path to ‘add to cart’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese have been known for maintaining a fine standard of living, the bars and restaurants have always stayed open even during the wars. The unhygienic water, heckling power supply, etc. was never a matter of concern for the middle-class until they enjoyed their affordable foreign tours. Despite a kaput monetary system, the luxuries and seamless interaction with the world have been courtesy of the Lebanese currency’s 22-year-old peg to the US currency, but who knew that this could turn into a substantial contributor to the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For several years, the Government has continued to borrow from global as well as domestic lenders to keep up with the pegged US dollars. As the Central Bank liberally hiked the interest rates, Lebanon became a strong magnet for the opulent investors across the globe. The unrealistic peg at 1,507 Lebanese pounds to a dollar and thriving efforts to keep up with it when there was a shortage of dollars in the market led to enormous debts. Further, to escape from the deficit, the Central Bank increased the interest rate to attract more investors. Nearly 50% of the state revenue goes into paying the debt, a major chunk of the remaining portion is put in effect for the government employees’ salaries, leaving very little margin for infrastructure development, capital investment, and expenditure on human resources. Thus, the Lebanese economy closes its boundary for revenue generation as there is no scope from other sectors, all the money is burned for consumption through imports, real estate and to defend the peg. Despite a sluggish economy, the government kept piling on the debts through depraved spendings, majorly on the expanded public sector which was put in effect to brim up their vote banks and divert focus from an ailing power grid. The situation became even more hostile owing to the political instability and the Prime Minister disappearing into Saudi Arabia, this shook the confidence of the Lebanese affluents who then decided to transfer their deposits out of the country. With the fear of depleting the country’s reserves, the banks had to close owing to the shortage of dollars. This has been a major concern for ordinary citizens, who have to stand in long queues to only return with a tiny amount of cash in hand which is insufficient to buy the daily bread, and have to sleep with an empty stomach during this pandemic. Economists view it as a matter of concern as the government continues to prioritise foreign creditors who hold an enormous $12 billion of the Lebanese debt, at the expense of the empty stomachs of its citizens. The banking sector, which has enjoyed mellow relations with the country’s political elite who held shares in some of these banks is a significant culprit. As the ordinary citizens fear a risk to their deposits, the commercial lenders who were always on the receiving end, even after capital controls in action have managed to pave their way for profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an uncertain political atmosphere, inefficient government policies driven with self-interest, faulty monetary system, and much more on the home-front, there are a few external factors that also act as a cherry to this toppling cake. A small country with a population of six million is largely dependent on remittances. 12.7% of the Lebanese GDP constitutes remittances from family members living abroad and majorly from the majestic oil-producers in the Middle-Eastern country, second only to Palestine. As coronavirus grips the world and the global GDP, numerous people have lost their jobs in various parts of the world. Owing to the global crisis, the number of people transferring and depositing money in Lebanon for their families and for tax exemptions abroad has seen a significant drop. In fact, they seek withdrawal from their already deposited funds in the Lebanese banks. The truncated oil prices have aggravated the revenue crisis for Lebanon. Moving closer, the oil-rich nations neighbouring the state of Lebanon that inhabited Lebanese emigrants have already cut down on the remittances they provided at regular intervals. These nations formulated the major chunk of the revenue Lebanon generated from remittances and used it further to fund its additional debt. With a threat of Saudi Arabia likely to expel Lebanese nationals, the inflow of remittance dollars that would support the dysfunctional peg has begun to diminish at a petrifying rate, making the situation even more muddled up for the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese economy finds itself amidst a thick forest, and the process of revival is definitely going to be a prolonged one along with a dire need for sustained efforts. With an urgent need for external liquidity that is possible only with the IMF reform programme which comes with a set of associated reforms that all the nations need to abide by when subscribing to the stimulus package. As the IMF estimates a debt reaching 155% of the Lebanese GDP, the government remains reluctant to adopt the IMF reforms and slashes the reports presented by the organisation. The economic experts and advisors, both within the state and globally, have to ultimately adopt the IMF reforms package to survive and provide daily bread to its citizens and the refugees. This detailed analysis is food for thought for further plan of action and devastating experience to learn from for the other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On October 17, 2019, the Government of Lebanon, the world’s third most indebted country, decided to impose a tax on WhatsApp messaging application to engulf its amassed fiscal deficit. Unfortunately, nothing changed except the calamity exacerbating with each passing day. As the prices for basic commodities soar high, people find it difficult to feed themselves and have resorted to selling their gold in order to fill their empty stomachs. Adding to the troubles, the pandemic is likely to downgrade the economy, which is already unable to withstand the jolts it has received, by 12-13%. With an urgent requirement of aid to 75% of its population, an instantaneous revival for the economy reminds me of the Gucci shoes in my shopping wishlist for years that have never been able to find their path to ‘add to cart’.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Coughing Losses: Indian States Subject to Austerity</title>
      <link href="/Coughing-Losses" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coughing Losses: Indian States Subject to Austerity" />
      <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Coughing-Losses</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Coughing-Losses">&lt;p&gt;As the number of COVID-19 cases continue to burgeon around the globe, most countries are experiencing an unprecedented slowdown with a shrinkage in economic activities. The already prevailing global slowdown in the pre-corona months has fused with the present-day scenario, resulting in an economic jolt. The ‘Great Lockdown’ as the IMF calls it, will give birth to economies with lowered interest rates and public debts reaching record levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India stands as the third worst-hit country globally with a tally nearing 700,000 cases. Looking deeper into the domestic circumstances, it is an unfortunate coincidence that the five gravely affected Indian states: Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu, Delhi, Gujarat and Uttar Pradesh, constitute 42% of India’s GDP. It is estimated that these five will make-up 48% of the total losses all the states will incur in 2020-21. Dried-up cash inflows have disconcerted both the Union and State Governments, however, as the actual battle is being fought by the State Governments and they are incurring the associated expenditure, the hardship is greater for them. With grave fiscal constraints, dealing with the loss of livelihoods has become a matter of concern for most states just as saving lives has. Cash handouts and provisions for subsidised food/ration have been put in place by states as humanitarian expenditure, not to ease the crisis. The return of migrant workers has exacerbated the problem with the disbursement on transport, quarantine facilities and rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite ironically, the ₹20.9 trillion stimulus package, which has been claimed to be 10% of the national GDP by the Union Government, is, in fact, an exiguous 0.8% of the GDP, as authenticated by a DSB Bank report and several other experts. This is one reason why the States have been demanding resources from the Union Government. The prime reason still lies in the fact that all the influential contributors (states) generated 60-70% of revenue from their own sources. These states gave us 75% of the GDP generated and hence, were the driving engines of the national economy—and therefore need and deserve more financial packages. Moreover, due to the already existing economic crunch that had affected the nation even before COVID-19, State Governments have been experiencing serious revenue impediments through the second half of 2019-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value Added Tax (VAT) on petroleum and excise duty on alcohol are the two predominant sources of revenue for states. Alcohol fosters the generation of ₹150 billion for states, on average, every month, along with ₹2 trillion brought in by petroleum products. The lockdown witnessed a plunge in the demand for petroleum and a collapse in the sale of alcohol, drying up the states’ revenues. The states generating a major portion of finances through their own resources are worst affected owing to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as the lockdown begins to ease out, relief is a far away dream for the states, liquor vendors are expecting a 25% fall in sales this year and bars have barely witnessed any footfall. Even though Delhi increased the excise duty on liquor, the gains weren’t fruitful enough to make good the deficit. Although oil prices in the international market stand truncated, the Union Government has continued to keep the prices high along with an escalation in the central excise duty to make good its deficit, so even if states increase VAT on petroleum, they are left with a very cramped taxing area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Goods and Services Tax (GST), which is collected by the Centre and then shared with the states comprises 43-44% of the revenue. Ever since its implementation, states have complained of revenue losses. One principal reason for this is the delayed and uneven release of the GST compensation. Compensation for December 2019 to February 2020 was released only in June, this led to much hue and cry as the states were starved of revenue during the lockdown. The Union Government’s assurance of a 14% annual growth for the next five years in the states’ GST revenue concoct mere dreams as the target is highly unachievable as they are likely to grow at a much lower rate. The only escape is borrowing, either the Centre borrows to issue grants to the states or the GST Council will have to borrow in order to keep pace with the share of compensation due to the states during these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crisis in hand, the Indian states have limited recourse. They can either cut down on their budgeted expenditure or increase tax buoyancy or increase their borrowings. Expenditure taps in the form of salaries, pensions, allowances, interests, etc. have already been turned off by many states as a cut in salaries, freezing of allowances and increments have been ordered by the State Governments. This compression of public expenditure is unlikely to provide the desired results. Borrowing from the market looks like candy to the eye and shall curb the issue of revenue in the short run, but states can’t afford to ignore the hindrances in borrowing, such as an expansion of the fiscal deficit in the long run. The second reason looks more political in nature, the Centre has inflicted four conditions on states – universalisation of ration cards, improvement in ease of doing business, reforms to make state-owned power distribution companies more profitable, and shoring up urban local body revenues. On the one hand, these conditions restrict the borrowing tendency of the states and on the other hand, the Centre has conveniently brimmed-up their coffer from ₹4.2 trillion to ₹12 trillion by inflating borrowings by 54% over the estimated budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation joins hands to fight the contagious virus but it seems that there is a grave disagreement between the States and the Centre when it comes to revenue generation, allotment and financial grants. The Centre curtails the income opportunities of the States through numerous constraints, yet expects States to fight the crisis on their own. The States look for grants in order to release the salaries of their employees and expects the Centre to reveal a package of at least 4-5% of the GDP. Many economists believe that an addition to the 15th Indian Finance Commission report, which allocates financial resources between the Centre and the states, in the form of a COVID-19 grant to states shall be a helping hand. A collaborative effort towards a common strategy aimed at rooting out the pandemic to ‘mask the losses being coughed by the states’ is the actual need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the number of COVID-19 cases continue to burgeon around the globe, most countries are experiencing an unprecedented slowdown with a shrinkage in economic activities. The already prevailing global slowdown in the pre-corona months has fused with the present-day scenario, resulting in an economic jolt. The ‘Great Lockdown’ as the IMF calls it, will give birth to economies with lowered interest rates and public debts reaching record levels.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis</title>
      <link href="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis" />
      <published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 China Financial Stability Report published by the People’s Bank of China officially deems 586 out of 4,379 Chinese lenders to be ‘high-risk’. The figures came into light only after the failure of a third bank within three months as national economic growth manifested a 30-year low. The Hengfeng Bank has become the third bank, after Baoshang Bank and Bank of Jinzhou, to suffer an economic collapse after a $40 trillion debt. But the Chinese government isn’t exceedingly famous for its honesty and transparency, thus the reported figure is likely masking the true extent of the banking quandary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has bailed out many of the high risk lenders. Precarious private shareholders have been effectively replaced by the ones backed by the state, often weaker in terms of their finances. The fact that bailouts are offered only for companies whose bankruptcy has a grave adverse impact on the economy as a whole and not just on a specified sector, cannot be ignored. Moreover, any amount of bailout allocated to this sector will have a domino effect on the Chinese economy which will be several times greater. For instance, the banking system calls for a 5-6% bailout which is equal to 20-24% of the Chinese GDP. A bailout of 20% of the GDP is a non-viable deal for any economy, even if it is China. The numeric is a statement of the fact that any pebble aimed at the banking sector shall bring ripples to the entire economy that in turn will shake China’s status of being a global economic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The People’s Bank of China conducted a stress test in the first half of 2019 on 1,171 commercial banks, 7.7% were stated to be at ‘extreme risk’ and deemed incapable of absorbing even a light shock, 13.6% will probably not be able to endure the financial crisis that shall follow. In November, Yingkou Coastal Bank and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/economy/china-economy/article/3035596/wechat-rumour-sparks-run-rural-chinese-bank-fresh-sign&quot;&gt;Yichuan Rural Commercial Bank&lt;/a&gt; – despite boasting healthy capital adequacy ratios – suffered bank runs as customers rushed to withdraw cash, fearing that the banks would close down, displaying a lack of confidence in banking institutions. The current situation is very similar to the one that cropped up in the late 1990’s. Towards the end of 1997, 20% of the main banks were non-performing, which was equivalent to a value of ¥1.19 trillion on the books of state-owned banks, which was deemed to be equal to 15.6% of the GDP. In order to resolve these crises and recapitalise the banks, ¥270 billion of special government bonds were issued and injected by August 1998. Walking on the same rope, the Chinese government is peddling its way through the crisis by adopting a somewhat similar technique. Today, the interbank market has been injected with around ¥2 trillion by the People’s Bank of China after the Baoshang Bank collapse. Along with this, a helping hand of the sovereign fund, China Investment Corporation, the Central Huijin Investment Company is injecting ¥60 billion into Hengfeng Bank. One of the 12 nationwide joint-stock banks in China, Hengfeng Bank is stacked up with non-performing loans and the situation became grimmer as the bank’s former president was handed out a death sentence for purloining funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, overlooking the different macroeconomic situation shall prove fatal to the Chinese economy in the present scenario. The key antidote for the crisis back then was the spurt of hyper economic growth in the early 2000’s. If China wants to avoid tormenting its economy with the inevitability of bad loans and its weakening banking structure, it will have to aim for a masterful economic growth. However, this stands as a challenge with the outbreak of COVID-19 and its likely aftermath on the global economy. Secondly, continuous evolution over the years has resulted in an entwined and fragile banking structure. The financial system in modern times has given rise to an integrated market that ensures banking transactions are speeded up and are facile in nature. Since the speed of transactions and their impact on the economy is brisk, it also means that any kind of shock in the structure is transmitted faster than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate and interbank customers suffer heavy losses, the volume of negotiable certificates of deposit—which are securities traded between financial institutions for short-term liquidity—has plunged by 90%. The situation threatens to cause the entire banking system to seize up as small and medium-sized banks are heavily dependent on liquidity in the interbank market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crisis should be an eye-opener for the administration as it calls for reforms in the entire financial system which has been overreliant on its banking sector for channeling funds. The fact that the financial structure has changed barely in the last fourteen years is an explanation for the crisis at hand. The world continues to keep a close watch on China, as this crisis is far too big to ignore because any large scale disruption in the driving engine of the global economy will lead the other economies into recession.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
