<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>Taking a step back</description>
    <link>
    </link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Picture of Dorian Gray</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest
compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as
I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of
St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a
composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could
distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s
&lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of
&lt;em&gt;Die Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Figaro&lt;/em&gt; with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker
dramas, &lt;em&gt;The Turn of the Screw&lt;/em&gt; or perhaps &lt;em&gt;Owen Wingrave&lt;/em&gt;. I was mistaken. It
took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking
some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera
into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many
more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s
effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act
show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its
completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the
public by the wonderful people at &lt;em&gt;LoveOpera&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Counting Down the Biggest Economic Policy Announcements since the 2008 Financial Crash</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In economics, recessions and depressions are supposed to have taught us many valuable lessons (Keynes was one of them). What about the last major recession? It’s been a decade since the Global Markets Crash of ’08. As we enter 2019, let’s see how our governments and institutions have used their financial knowledge over the decade. Many of these announcements are a direct cause of the crisis, while the rest were too important to be left out. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /Counting-down-the-biggest-economic</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
