<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>Taking a step back</description>
    <link>
    </link>
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Corruption and Coercion on the Digital Silk Road</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The squalid conditions of the Xinjiang region of Northwestern China, in which Uighur Muslims, Khazakhs and Uzbeks are forced to surrender DNA and blood samples, remain a stark reminder of the extent to which civil liberties can be assailed in the name of ‘counter-terrorism’. 47-year old Bakitali Nur, a fruit and vegetable exporter from Khargos, &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5735411/china-surveillance-privacy-issues/&quot;&gt;told &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt; magazine&lt;/a&gt; that he and seven other inmates were forced to sit still on plastic stools for seventeen consecutive hours as their movements were monitored by security cameras. In Xinjiang, 2.5 million citizens have their whereabouts tracked by CCTV whilst being subjected to a punitive social credit system that discourages behaviour not approved of by the Chinese State.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /Corruption-and-Coercion</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Corruption-and-Coercion</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Exposing the Irrational Voter, Mathematically!</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The Indian elections are right around the corner and the mood is currently in
full swing. Check the papers and you’ll barely find any real estate left for
anything else (but you can always check back with &lt;a href=&quot;http://thepangean.com&quot;&gt;The
Pangean&lt;/a&gt; for more). The juries are out and so are the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloombergquint.com/bq-blue-exclusive/elections-2019-a-manifesto-for-political-manifestos&quot;&gt;manifestos&lt;/a&gt;.
The line between celebrities and candidates gets blurrier by the day and
election campaigns are &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/kolkata/for-mimi-chakraborty-its-all-work-and-no-sleep-before-poll-drill-starts/articleshow/68434360.cms&quot;&gt;quickly turning into promotional
tours&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to feel sorry for the manifestos, which the &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; of voters will
probably have only a glance of at most. Studies at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002205310800080X?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;frontiers of decision
theory&lt;/a&gt;
have shown that when people do not pay attention to candidate policy choices,
uninformed voters end up making decisions based on personalities. This seems to
explain most of the name-calling and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MkqIEWY2-aY&quot;&gt;on-stage
singing&lt;/a&gt; that candidates have
resorted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of all this, three main talking points have emerged: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiainfoline.com/article/general-blog/rising-unemployment-and-the-future-of-indian-youth-118112200298_1.html&quot;&gt;youth
unemployment&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fairobserver.com/region/central_south_asia/indian-farmer-suicides-india-south-asian-world-news-latest-32349/&quot;&gt;farmer’s
perils&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2018/06/27/india-ranked-worlds-most-dangerous-place-for-women-reigniting-debate-about-womens-safety/?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.933d533d9a10&quot;&gt;safety of
women&lt;/a&gt;.
It is no doubt that these topics will be sticking out as the major drivers of
the 2019 Indian election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at some data that will give us some insight into the State of the
Nation. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=2019-01-08%2009:28:37&amp;amp;msec=666&quot;&gt;Centre for Monitoring Indian
Economy&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=2019-01-08%2009:28:37&amp;amp;msec=666&quot;&gt;CMIE&lt;/a&gt;)
estimated that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/opinion/lead/surveying-indias-unemployment-numbers/article26218615.ece&quot;&gt;11 million
jobs&lt;/a&gt;
were lost in 2018 – pushing the unemployment rate to 7.38%. A leaked NSSO report
pegged the unemployment rate at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/unemployment-rate-at-four-decade-high-nsso-survey-compared-past-figures-119020100042_1.html&quot;&gt;6.1%&lt;/a&gt;,
the highest in over four decades. Things do not look so good for our youth at
work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the farmers, the bedrock of our society? Well, this is where
things go further downhill. According to Wholesale Price Index
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://tradingeconomics.com/india/producer-prices-change&quot;&gt;WPI&lt;/a&gt;) data for the
month of December released by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry, the WPI
sub-component for primary food articles has been negative for six consecutive
months beginning July 2018. This is a direct indication of the sliding prices
that farmers have been facing for their produce, which has led to innumerable
suicides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women’s safety is also experiencing issues that India cannot seem to get away
from that have been lingering for far too long and are only getting worse.
According to a recent poll of 548 experts by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://poll2018.trust.org/country/?id=india&quot;&gt;Thomson Reuters
Foundation&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“India ranked 1st among the world’s most dangerous countries for women.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No progress here, ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is dire and the immediate need for change is crystal clear. It is
also understood that this summer the onus is on the people to effect change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can we &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt; the voters? How rational are they when it comes to making
decisions? How rational are &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where our rant comes to an end and the &lt;em&gt;dissection&lt;/em&gt; begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us play a little game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections are only about promises and promises do not hold up most of the time,
so we reduce them to a matter of &lt;em&gt;probability&lt;/em&gt;. Now, let’s see how you and your
choices fare in our mock election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let there be two political parties, A and B, standing in the elections. Party A
promises to reduce unemployment by 20%, with a 100% chance of fulfilling his
promise. Whereas, Party B promises to reduce unemployment by 35%, with a 15 out
of 16 chance of fulfilling his promise. To put it neatly,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;20% unemployment drop, with certainty (100% Guarantee).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;35% unemployment reduction, with 15/16 chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go on. Take your pick. Is it party A or party B? Who would you bank on for the
country’s sake?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, here’s a second case to choose from.  Party A promises a 20% reduction in
unemployment, only now with a 16% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas,
Party B promises 35% fall, with a 15% chance. Restating it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;20% unemployment drop, with a 16% chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;35% unemployment reduction, with a 15% chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, whom did you pick? If you happened to pick Party A in Case 1, then you are
like the majority, who prefer certainty over chance. For those who chose Party B
in the first case, you were ready to take the risk for the greater reward. But
there is nothing wrong with either choice, the real game starts with Case 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what about Case 2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, here’s the bombshell. Case 2 is equal to Case 1 with a one-sixth chance.
That is, Case 2 is the same situation as Case 1, only with a 16% probability.
The change between the party’s probability of fulfilling promises in both cases
was proportional and thus, renders both cases to be the absolute same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if the problem never changed, did your choice of candidates change? From B to
A, or A to B?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you did not, then congratulations, you have
rational preferences. If you did, then there are more than a few things at work
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us try another problem of this sort. Whether or not the government promised
to deposit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businesstoday.in/current/economy-politics/bjp-never-promised-to-deposit-rs-15-lakh-in-people-bank-accounts-rajnath-singh/story/335629.html&quot;&gt;Rs. 15
Lakh&lt;/a&gt;
in everyone’s accounts, it is always possible another party will make a similar
promise in the run-up to the elections. Farmers are definitely in need of severe
financial help, so take Party A and Party B who make the respective
&lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/economy/agriculture/budget-2019-income-support-for-farmers-a-progressive-step-but-not-enough-to-mitigate-stress/articleshow/67802322.cms&quot;&gt;income-support&lt;/a&gt;
promises:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 11,000 a year, with an 11% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 11,000 a year, &lt;b&gt;guaranteed&lt;/b&gt; (100% chance).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance, and Rs 11,000 a year, with an 89%
chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who gets the vote, in each case, this time around? Did you choose the same party
both times, or different parties? Choosing different parties is a sign of
incoherent decision-making. This is because Case 1 is once again of a similar
form as Case 2. There has been no significant change in the factors that should
influence your decision-making. Yet there will be more than a few instances of
people making unidentical choices for Cases 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to do a bit of explaining. Consider these cases as lotteries. Both Party A
and Party B have an 89% chance of not fulfilling any promise in Case 1. But
wait? Didn’t Party B promise a 10% chance? So it gives us (100% -10%=) 90%
chance of empty-handed farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, there is the existence of a lottery within a lottery; a &lt;strong&gt;compound&lt;/strong&gt;
lottery, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lottery within is actually a 10 out of 11 chance of receiving Rs 15000 and 1
out of 11 chance of getting Rs 0. So when it is nested inside the outer lottery
of Party B, we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 0&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is essentially,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance and Rs 0, with a 90% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, things are getting discombobulated in your head, but stay with me.
Eventually, what we are left with is a much detailed way to re-write and
represent Cases 1 and 2 as &lt;em&gt;nested&lt;/em&gt; probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: 11% x &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt; +   &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;11% x [&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)&lt;/span&gt;]   +  &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: 11% x &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt; +   &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;11% x [&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)&lt;/span&gt;]   + &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parts marked in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Red&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are the actual &lt;em&gt;determinants&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; factors
when it comes to decision-making between the two parties. The segments marked in
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;Blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are offered by &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; parties and thus, should not be a determining
factor in rational choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you ended up choosing A in Case 1 and B in Case 2 (or vice versa), you
have just chosen two different answers for the same problem. Do you see it now?
That is where rational preferences are violated and we can now find our
&lt;em&gt;irrational voter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this, we come to the origins of the problem. The lack of coherence
empirically observed above is called the &lt;strong&gt;Allais Paradox&lt;/strong&gt;, and has been the
talk of game theorists and psychologists for years. First published in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wolfweb.unr.edu/homepage/pingle/Teaching/BADM%20791/Week%206%20Decision%20Making%20Under%20Uncertainty/Allais%20Paradox%201953.pdf&quot;&gt;1953&lt;/a&gt;,
in the &lt;em&gt;Econometrica&lt;/em&gt; journal by French economist Maurice Allais, the Allais
Paradox was observed among subjects who, when presented with choices such as the
ones above, made snap decisions that were proven to be incoherent upon further
study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not everyone got it wrong, a significant number of people made the
error which prompted him to wonder whether there was more than just rationality
behind human choices. So the Allais Paradox started off as more of a standout
against conventional rationality theory, than as the rationality test that it
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/zJZvoiwydJ5zvzTHK/the-allais-paradox&quot;&gt;has evolved to
today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maurice Allais did end up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/1988/summary/&quot;&gt;winning the 1988 Nobel Prize in
Economics&lt;/a&gt;
but it was not until 20 years after it was first published, that the Allais
Paradox was brought back to the mainstream by Daniel Kahneman. In a way, the
Allais Paradox was what got Nobel laureate Daniel Kahneman (2002 Nobel laureate)
into economics. He along with Amos Tversky, were two young psychologists back in
the 1970s who came across this paradox and were so intrigued by the study of
human approach towards uncertainty that they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1207/S15427579JPFM0402_01&quot;&gt;opened up new
dimensions&lt;/a&gt; in
the world of economics and &lt;a href=&quot;http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/economics/laureates/2002/&quot;&gt;decision-making under
uncertainty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maurice Allais had made one of the foremost and yet perplexing dives into human
rationality and for that, today, the world is in a better position to understand
human behaviour and decision-making. And while we are on the topic of making
decisions, we get back to the decision of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This election may be driven by 3 &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; issues: unemployment, farmers and
women’s protection. But at the end of the day, it is the people who &lt;em&gt;drive&lt;/em&gt;
elections. Yet what we often overlook is what drives the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; and their
&lt;em&gt;choices&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we as smart as we think we are? Does being &lt;em&gt;irrational&lt;/em&gt; only mean being
‘unreasonable’ or ‘baseless’ as the Dictionary says? Or is there more to this
than meets the eye &lt;em&gt;or brain&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that note, we ask you to think twice before calling someone else irrational.
Oh, and yes, don’t forget to think twice before voting. Happy elections!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*31st May, 2019 marks the 108th Birth Anniversary of French physicist and
economist Maurice Allais, best known for his contributions to the neoclassical
synthesis and the Allais Paradox.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 01:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Higher Ups: Appointments and Disappointments</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In this article, we take a look at the people in the past decade and more who had exponential burdens placed on their shoulders and examine how they fared. The men and women who moved markets and sentiments; whose names were heard on the internet and in households across the globe, setting examples to follow and learn from, for the generation ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 01:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /The-Higher-Ups</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/The-Higher-Ups</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Counting Down the Biggest Economic Policy Announcements since the 2008 Financial Crash</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In economics, recessions and depressions are supposed to have taught us many valuable lessons (Keynes was one of them). What about the last major recession? It’s been a decade since the Global Markets Crash of ’08. As we enter 2019, let’s see how our governments and institutions have used their financial knowledge over the decade. Many of these announcements are a direct cause of the crisis, while the rest were too important to be left out. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /Counting-down-the-biggest-economic</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
