<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-24T18:33:45+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree</title><link href="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree" /><published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree">&lt;p&gt;The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some millennials, burdened by low-income jobs and debt obligations, living from paycheck to paycheck, are genuinely unable to finance stock purchases, the statistics tell us how even better-off millennials are straying away from investing and are preferring to save instead. Unfortunately, their risk-averse tendencies are miscalculated and are costing them precious returns, since the S&amp;amp;P 500 (adjusted for inflation and dividends reinvested) averaged a 7.92% return between 2007 to 2017, while the money market bank accounts averaged a 0.3% return during the same period. Nearly 42% of millennials are conservative investors, as opposed to 38% of GenXers and 23% of the Boomers. They are unwilling to fully embrace the financial markets, and when they do, it is only through a safer, less costly mechanism such as that of an Exchange Traded Fund (ETF), which is a type of fund that holds multiple underlying assets rather than a single stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worth noting is that their caution seems selective. Millennials’ risk-aversion appears to be more about scepticism when one realises how they have stayed away only from what they personally saw fail - the stock markets. They are still the ones responsible for inflating the crypto-market, despite its lack of intrinsic value or any ‘faith’ backing. The only argument in defense of their wild investment choice is perhaps the sophisticated distributed ledger technology used in the asset which makes the case for fostering technological innovation in the stock markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the politically correct environment, with encouragement from Hollywood, has put capitalism out of style for many. The ones still willing to invest have raised the bar over mere profitability when making an investment decision. Company ethics and transparency are a primary consideration for millennials when they choose to invest, and these additional filters reduce the overall amount invested. The rate of investment for women is in an even poorer state. The Harris Poll survey revealed that a staggering 79% of women do not invest at all, with 70% of them stating that the process is confusing to them, while 60% of them believing how they felt investing was ‘an old-white man’s game’. Clearly, the Millennials need a better education when it comes to managing their finances and getting over &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture is clear: Millennials are savers and not investors. 71% of Millennial workers are saving for retirement, and begin saving at the median age of 24, which puts the GenX’s median saving age of 30 to shame. And while they rely on the banks for saving, they try to keep away from availing any of the other services. A three year study from Scratch, an in-house unit of Viacom, as a part of the &lt;em&gt;Millennial Disruption Study&lt;/em&gt;, found that not only were banks among the ‘Most Hated’ brands, but a third of this demographic cohort believed that they’d be better off without them. This is a major concern for banks, who are now resorting to appeasement techniques. Providing special discounts on credit card bills and easing out the enrollment mechanism for loans are a few examples. This has also partially fueled the rise of fintech in the formal banking system and is encouraging the development of such technologies. Developing a system with a user-friendly interface and greater transparency by incorporation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning is an obvious solution to this issue. For instance,  a ZeroHedge survey revealed that one in three Millennials would rather invest in Bitcoin than in the stock market, simply because of the unconventional and futuristic technology involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that in traditional economics, the West had never been considered the saver’s economy, and this pattern is shifting for the better. The situation is quite akin to the rise in savings post the hyperinflationary periods in Germany after World War I, which incidentally was also a result of the psychological impact of the crisis. At the macro level, greater savings would imply lesser dependence on foreign investment. Lesser inflow of USD denominated investment in the USA implies lesser demand for the dollar. The consequent decline in appreciation of the USD is great for recovering the Current Account Deficit, which has been a primary long-term concern for the nation. But this advantage is dwarfed when growth concerns step in, as slowdowns are the projected case for the next few years. Additionally, with the rise of protectionist, right-wing governments around the globe, millennials are increasingly inclining towards what they think is socialism, which implies increased disinterest towards the financial markets. And that is a terrible prospect for growth. Hence, even though this demographic cohort has been through quite a lot at an impressionable age, they must put their concerns aside and take up a more rational approach. They have made a wise decision to save, considering the depleting ability of the burgeoning federal balance sheet to finance their post-retirement expenses. But they must learn to be comfortable with the idea of some risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><category term="millennial" /><summary type="html">The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Future of Islamic Finance in the Global Economy</title><link href="/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Islamic Finance in the Global Economy" /><published>2019-07-18T00:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-18T00:10:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance">&lt;p&gt;Islamic banks do not have a long history. The first bank started its operations
in 1963 in Egypt. The main centres worldwide are in Iran, Saudi Arabia,
Malaysia, Europe, Great Britain and Switzerland. Islamic banking and religion
are correlated (shock!). However preposterous it may sound, it is a bank that
does not charge you interest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider that you want to start a manufacturing plant. A conventional bank will
provide you with the money and charge interest on it: the concept of
‘multiplying’ money. On the contrary, Islamic banks are forbidden from charging
interest. Instead, they will offer to be partners in your business and share
profits and losses. This strengthens the economy by reducing the burden from the
promoter’s shoulders and sharing it with financial institutions. In fact, their
peculiar business model helped Islamic banks largely avert the adverse impact of
the 2008 crisis. In particular, it was investment portfolios that were smaller
in size, partially deleveraged, and adherence to &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt; principles which
prevented Islamic banks from putting money in the kind of instruments that
affected their conventional competitors and helped limit the impact of the
crisis on them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A characteristic feature of Islamic banking is the role of the bank. The basic
mission is, surprisingly, not to generate profit for the bank or multiply the
income for customers but to support local development and entrepreneurship.
Everything in the Islamic banking system is made according to  &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt; law.
The things which are allowed in Islam are called ‘&lt;em&gt;halal&lt;/em&gt;’ and the things which
are forbidden are ‘&lt;em&gt;haram&lt;/em&gt;’. So, the bank is not able to invest any of their
money in the products or services forbidden in Islam. For example, in production
or trade of alcohol, nicotine, drugs, or in sectors related to pornography, the
defence sector, casino, and nightclubs. So, a customer of the Islamic bank can
be well assured that his money would not be invested in anything inconsistent
with Islam. The rule of ‘&lt;em&gt;Money makes Money&lt;/em&gt;’ does not exist in Islam because
money has no value in itself and cannot be multiplied just by rotating it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two key aspects of Islamic finance. First, it has the advantage of
being asset-backed which makes it inherently less risky than conventional
finance. Second, a prevalent risk-reward sharing arrangement exists. Apart from
this, there are some rules which guide such institutions. For example, retaining
surplus profit is unfair in this system, it is strictly related to usury -
&lt;em&gt;‘Reba’&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Reba&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important rules in the Islamic banking
system. The second rule is &lt;em&gt;gharar&lt;/em&gt;, which is related to risky or hazardous
sales and the fact that gambling is prohibited in the Islamic world. For
instance, you cannot sell the goods or services which are not yet produced. It
can be traded upon only once it comes into existence. Moreover, nothing can be
sold unless you acquire it. This essentially eliminates the risk of not
possessing the goods. All products offered in Islamic banks have to be observed
and accepted by the Council for Islamic Banks (by their lawyers and clergy). The
most popular transaction in Islamic banking is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/murabaha.asp&quot;&gt;‘Murabaha’-&lt;/a&gt; a cost-plus
financing structure where the client and the bank agree on the markup or
“cost-plus” price for the item being sold. In essence, the bank purchases the
item on behalf of the client and retains its ownership rights until the client
pays back the amount (which is the cost-plus profit on the item) to the bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic finance is growing rapidly but remains concentrated on a few
jurisdictions. Its strong growth reflects a tremendous interest on the part of
the Muslim population who have previously been underserved by the banking
industry. For the past two decades, many Islamic banks have witnessed
double-digit growth rates, surpassing their conventional peers. The industry’s
total worth, across its three main sectors (banking, capital markets, and
&lt;em&gt;Takaful&lt;/em&gt;), was estimated to be $2.05 trillion in 2017. At a mere glance, all
seems well for the Islamic banking industry. However, several potential markets
with a considerable quantum of the Muslim population remain largely unbreached,
including India and the Commonwealth of Independent States countries, made up of
the former Soviet republics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic finance holds great promise for promoting macroeconomic and financial
stability but to fulfil these promises three prerequisites really need to be
met: first, a further deepening of the standard and codes for the application of
Islamic finance and their consistent application globally. Secondly, it is
essential for &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt;-compliant money markets to be developed. This will allow
Islamic banks to manage their liquidity in a more effective way and free up
resources for them to invest in growth-enhancing projects. The Islamic financial
market is now facing increased competition due to the establishment of other
Islamic financial institutions and conventional banks who have established
Islamic subsidiaries or windows. Islamic banks also suffer from an overhang of
bad loans, and they lag behind their Western counterparts in technology and
expertise. The religious dimension adds an extra layer of problems with respect
to introducing new products that need to cater to both the Islamic law and the
needs of the general public. Lastly, there is a vital need for institutional
reforms in the areas of tax policy and capital markets development, which will
be needed for Islamic finance to fulfil its promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics consider Islamic banking similar to having a boiled ice cream-cream, it
cannot exist in real life without trickling down our confidence. For instance,
if you need a loan for purchasing a house, Islamic Banks will not charge you
interest on this money. Instead, they will buy the house for you and sell it
back to you at a higher price, demanding this amount from you in, say, 15 years,
of course, interest-free. This is a backdoor policy of interest collection. In
other words, it is interest-collection in all but name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to India, which will soon be the home to most Muslims in the
world, there has been a long-standing debate on Islamic banking. Currently, the
rules don’t allow it. Critics say it’s a bad idea because it goes against
India’s secular fabric. Is India ready for it? Will it open a Pandora’s Box?
Should we look at it through a religious prism? The opinions are sharply
divided. The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and the Banking Regulations Act,
1949 both prohibit the setting up of an Islamic banking system. Only an act of
Parliament can set up one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, growth has sparked optimism about the future of Islamic
finance. However, as competition intensifies, Islamic financial banks are still
left with work to do. Most Islamic banks need to function more efficiently along
the entire value chain, regardless of whether the strategy is aimed at entering
a niche market, at competing with traditional banks or at both. They need to
scrutinise strategic choices and focus on operational basics to grab unused
market opportunities and overcome the changing dynamics of the industry. In all,
Islamic finance is still at a nascent stage which is yet to meet its full
potential.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Islamic banks do not have a long history. The first bank started its operations in 1963 in Egypt. The main centres worldwide are in Iran, Saudi Arabia, Malaysia, Europe, Great Britain and Switzerland. Islamic banking and religion are correlated (shock!). However preposterous it may sound, it is a bank that does not charge you interest.  Consider that you want to start a manufacturing plant. A conventional bank will provide you with the money and charge interest on it: the concept of ‘multiplying’ money. On the contrary, Islamic banks are forbidden from charging interest. Instead, they will offer to be partners in your business and share profits and losses. This strengthens the economy by reducing the burden from the promoter’s shoulders and sharing it with financial institutions. In fact, their peculiar business model helped Islamic banks largely avert the adverse impact of the 2008 crisis. In particular, it was investment portfolios that were smaller in size, partially deleveraged, and adherence to Shariah principles which prevented Islamic banks from putting money in the kind of instruments that affected their conventional competitors and helped limit the impact of the crisis on them.  A characteristic feature of Islamic banking is the role of the bank. The basic mission is, surprisingly, not to generate profit for the bank or multiply the income for customers but to support local development and entrepreneurship. Everything in the Islamic banking system is made according to  Shariah law. The things which are allowed in Islam are called ‘halal’ and the things which are forbidden are ‘haram’. So, the bank is not able to invest any of their money in the products or services forbidden in Islam. For example, in production or trade of alcohol, nicotine, drugs, or in sectors related to pornography, the defence sector, casino, and nightclubs. So, a customer of the Islamic bank can be well assured that his money would not be invested in anything inconsistent with Islam. The rule of ‘Money makes Money’ does not exist in Islam because money has no value in itself and cannot be multiplied just by rotating it.  There are two key aspects of Islamic finance. First, it has the advantage of being asset-backed which makes it inherently less risky than conventional finance. Second, a prevalent risk-reward sharing arrangement exists. Apart from this, there are some rules which guide such institutions. For example, retaining surplus profit is unfair in this system, it is strictly related to usury - ‘Reba’. Reba is one of the most important rules in the Islamic banking system. The second rule is gharar, which is related to risky or hazardous sales and the fact that gambling is prohibited in the Islamic world. For instance, you cannot sell the goods or services which are not yet produced. It can be traded upon only once it comes into existence. Moreover, nothing can be sold unless you acquire it. This essentially eliminates the risk of not possessing the goods. All products offered in Islamic banks have to be observed and accepted by the Council for Islamic Banks (by their lawyers and clergy). The most popular transaction in Islamic banking is ‘Murabaha’- a cost-plus financing structure where the client and the bank agree on the markup or “cost-plus” price for the item being sold. In essence, the bank purchases the item on behalf of the client and retains its ownership rights until the client pays back the amount (which is the cost-plus profit on the item) to the bank.  Islamic finance is growing rapidly but remains concentrated on a few jurisdictions. Its strong growth reflects a tremendous interest on the part of the Muslim population who have previously been underserved by the banking industry. For the past two decades, many Islamic banks have witnessed double-digit growth rates, surpassing their conventional peers. The industry’s total worth, across its three main sectors (banking, capital markets, and Takaful), was estimated to be $2.05 trillion in 2017. At a mere glance, all seems well for the Islamic banking industry. However, several potential markets with a considerable quantum of the Muslim population remain largely unbreached, including India and the Commonwealth of Independent States countries, made up of the former Soviet republics. Islamic finance holds great promise for promoting macroeconomic and financial stability but to fulfil these promises three prerequisites really need to be met: first, a further deepening of the standard and codes for the application of Islamic finance and their consistent application globally. Secondly, it is essential for Shariah-compliant money markets to be developed. This will allow Islamic banks to manage their liquidity in a more effective way and free up resources for them to invest in growth-enhancing projects. The Islamic financial market is now facing increased competition due to the establishment of other Islamic financial institutions and conventional banks who have established Islamic subsidiaries or windows. Islamic banks also suffer from an overhang of bad loans, and they lag behind their Western counterparts in technology and expertise. The religious dimension adds an extra layer of problems with respect to introducing new products that need to cater to both the Islamic law and the needs of the general public. Lastly, there is a vital need for institutional reforms in the areas of tax policy and capital markets development, which will be needed for Islamic finance to fulfil its promise. Critics consider Islamic banking similar to having a boiled ice cream-cream, it cannot exist in real life without trickling down our confidence. For instance, if you need a loan for purchasing a house, Islamic Banks will not charge you interest on this money. Instead, they will buy the house for you and sell it back to you at a higher price, demanding this amount from you in, say, 15 years, of course, interest-free. This is a backdoor policy of interest collection. In other words, it is interest-collection in all but name. When it comes to India, which will soon be the home to most Muslims in the world, there has been a long-standing debate on Islamic banking. Currently, the rules don’t allow it. Critics say it’s a bad idea because it goes against India’s secular fabric. Is India ready for it? Will it open a Pandora’s Box? Should we look at it through a religious prism? The opinions are sharply divided. The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and the Banking Regulations Act, 1949 both prohibit the setting up of an Islamic banking system. Only an act of Parliament can set up one. In recent years, growth has sparked optimism about the future of Islamic finance. However, as competition intensifies, Islamic financial banks are still left with work to do. Most Islamic banks need to function more efficiently along the entire value chain, regardless of whether the strategy is aimed at entering a niche market, at competing with traditional banks or at both. They need to scrutinise strategic choices and focus on operational basics to grab unused market opportunities and overcome the changing dynamics of the industry. In all, Islamic finance is still at a nascent stage which is yet to meet its full potential.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Millennials, The Gentle Souls</title><link href="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials, The Gentle Souls" /><published>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls">&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely
home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and
sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting
truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our
realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media
has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to
a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to
discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our
parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is
not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions.
And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or
informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare
I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility
to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies
this chaos. What’s noble is that we care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about
how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which
tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the
fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for
themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our
fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We
face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other
in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media
activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the
moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own
endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful
is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives
up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care
about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious
millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring
about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is
nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified
moral compass we never inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply
intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the
picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess;
like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a
favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be
like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as
aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to
blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But
here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of
bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess.
We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more
courageously, also with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength,
for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our
generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces
the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of
daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together
stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian
women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot
f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is
to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to
be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you
hints at you being different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles.
We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with
each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures
humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous
selves, but finally talking about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short,
acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal
mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy
to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to
shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and
have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the
complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the
acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema
and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants.
Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of
motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials
will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it.
Let humans be human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving
through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that
solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a
meme rooted in self-deprecation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stuti Gupta</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis. At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions. And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies this chaos. What’s noble is that we care. A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own endeavours. All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious millennials! ‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified moral compass we never inherited. Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation. Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess; like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess. We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more courageously, also with ourselves. The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength, for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud. Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you hints at you being different. But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles. We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous selves, but finally talking about them. The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short, acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed. In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants. Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it. Let humans be human. They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a meme rooted in self-deprecation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game</title><link href="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game" /><published>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</updated><id>/On-Codes-and-Ciphers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers">&lt;p&gt;“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will
miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and
you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are
and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen.
You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a1/Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer
scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War
II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The
Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the
Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the
Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s
original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German
movements during the War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/_dchris/19612913884&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//enigma-machine.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was
broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system
has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists
like Shamir and Bonhe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the
history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous
cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to
communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the
authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is
replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a
similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets
replaced by H and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://s4scoding.com/images/caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of
steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of
cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information,
using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the
very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of
people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone
to crack it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher.
A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages
or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication
even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time, 
being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the
throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code.
The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code,
is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you
guessed it, Samuel Morse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b5/International_Morse_Code.svg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//International_Morse_Code.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic
messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the
letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and
it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has
been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps;
tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed
it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if
masked properly that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements
in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most
talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have
talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that
age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the
Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher
replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous author David Kahn notes in his book &lt;em&gt;The Codebreakers&lt;/em&gt; that history
has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many
mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher
used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no
dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher
system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to
replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher)
to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without
the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human
comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no
matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused
to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an
inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to
Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule
the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest
concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex
and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract
concepts on the quantum nature of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting
up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we
are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build
and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only
for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is
truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be
brought down, thanks to humans themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of
the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into
effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen. You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - The Imitation Game, 2014. Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German movements during the War. The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists like Shamir and Bonhe. The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets replaced by H and so on. One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information, using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone to crack it. Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher. A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time,  being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code. The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code, is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you guessed it, Samuel Morse. For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps; tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if masked properly that is. Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text. The famous author David Kahn notes in his book The Codebreakers that history has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher) to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without the key. However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract concepts on the quantum nature of information. Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be brought down, thanks to humans themselves. Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into effect.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Wandering Wonder</title><link href="/The-Wandering-Wondar" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wandering Wonder" /><published>2019-07-12T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Wandering-Wondar</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Wandering-Wondar">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wandered off while sitting down―all in your head, all out of
wonder? Ever imagined multiple lives for yourself? Ever wondered how there are a
gazillion lives that are all affected by the interconnectedness of everything?
Has there been a time when you have wanted to exchange places, or be at multiple
places, living multiple lives at the same time? If you have, my friend, we are
aboard the same boat and I hope your frustration wards off just as soon as I
wish for mine to leave. Or maybe, just maybe, better yet, this wonder is what
keeps us afloat, keeps us from dreading the worst. We know there’s a lot that
exists, we know we may never know about it all, and maybe it’s this wonder that
keeps us excited to be alive. I may be rationalising here and I promise to get
rid of this defence mechanism as soon as I find a better one. But language is
funny in more ways than not. We feel liberated using it, and at the same time,
there is also a strange kind of entrapment. We cannot communicate without words,
and yet are words sufficient to voice everything we feel?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I did not know that the frustration of being limited to one
experience was a common dilemma, I had no idea there was even a name for it,
albeit none that one can use in their English essay. Onism, and we shall all
thank John Koenig for the same, is a word that tries to explain the frustration
of being stuck in just one body, that inhabits only one place at a time. It is
understood to be like standing in front of the departures screen at an airport,
flickering over with strange place names like other people’s passwords, each
representing one more thing you will never get to see before you die―and all
because, as the arrow on the map helpfully points out, you are here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can imagine how much more rich and satisfying it would be to have multiple
bodies, not just one―so one could escape themselves for a while and live on the
other side of the planet. Or take a step back and see themselves from someone
else’s point of view, in full context with the rest of the world, with their
face the right way around, their eyes un-flattened, just as vivid as one appears
to other people. It would be like knowing yourself like others do, judging our
own quirks but with much less self-loathing, just seeing them as unique factions
of our being. However absurd the idea may seem; it would bring so much more
clarity and joy. Of course, this may be coming from a place of bias, with myself
being someone who has felt this for a long time and only just recently found out
about the word that expresses it so well on an unanticipated night. A friend
introduced me to &lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt; and that’s when I met with
the genius work of John Koenig. This man is on a mission to fill the gaps
incurred in the English language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His dictionary includes words that describe emotions that one may feel but can’t
put into motion through speech or writing, it includes questioning the
limitations that language puts on us. One has to acknowledge that our bodies and
minds are bombarded with so many complex sensations throughout the day that it
would be impossible to assign a name to each. Feelings are a product of any
stimulation one can procure―the lack of it―a phenomenon in itself. Even though
&lt;em&gt;Merriam&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oxford&lt;/em&gt; haven’t made it yet, Koenig with his popular Tumblr Blog
and subsequent YouTube Channel and website is paving the way. &lt;em&gt;TDOBS&lt;/em&gt; is
intriguing because it presents a word that is obscure or completely invented and
then connects it to a stylised video to further enhance the definition of that
word. As Koenig indicates on his website, “Each original definition aims to fill
a hole in the language—to give a name to emotions we all might experience but
don’t yet have a word for.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koenig has said multiple times that the blog began with his desire to write
poems. He made up words to help frame the poems better. He insists that the
inception began at a dark time in his life. In his Ted Talk, Koenig recollects
the time when his own melancholy triggered him to compose the dictionary, and
how people later came up to him to thank him for his work. The graphic
designer/editor/voice performer speaks of how his sombreness gave him a penchant
for words. One should be aware of the fact that he makes sure that all his words
have etymological significance. That they all have sense and reason behind them.
&lt;em&gt;TDOBS&lt;/em&gt; gained popularity with the wilfulness of Twitter, someone tweeted out 23
of the words and then, boom! The crowd came rushing, in shared understanding of
the un-worded emotions. Words such as ‘sonder’ have made it to the bigwigs, with
companies using them to name products. A very prominent bar in New York has
named its drinks after the 23 popularised words; artists too have now started
naming their paintings with the help of these words, so as to express themselves
better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why out of every interesting word this man has invented, I
longed to make this word the winter sun―Onism. Onism is a portmanteau of monism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;onanism. In philosophy, monism is the view that a variety of things can be
explained in terms of a single reality or substance, or a distinct source. Onism
can be seen as a kind of monism, because one’s life is indeed limited to a
single reality, by virtue of being restricted to a single body, but something is
clearly missing. Meanwhile, onanism is another word for masturbation or
self-pleasure, transfixed inside our own menagerie of fantasies like going on a
sightseeing tour of our own apartment—frustrating in its closed-off familiarity.
Again, something is missing. What makes it even more special is that Onism was
born while Koenig was travelling in an airplane, across 6 countries, in the
process of moving places and struggling with the idea of a new life. To me, this
brings in the idea more so than anything else. It makes me think of Remedial
Chaos Theory: there are lots of me in other timelines who - collectively - have
done everything I have not. It is the awareness of everything you are giving up,
to be where you are right now. It is questioning the excuses we have invented to
explain why so much of our life belongs in the background. Koenig very well
expresses this in how he words his video transcripts- “We sketch monsters on the
map because we find their presence comforting. They guard the edges of the
abyss, and force us to look away; so, we can live comfortably in the Known
World, at least for a little while.” An analogy I came across may help you
visualise it better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we enter primary school, we have heard all about the planets in our
Solar System. As we grow older, we learn that the Solar System is just a speck
in the Milky Way Galaxy, and that there are thousands of galaxies out there,
peppering our universe with their glow and might. The celestial mysteries that
beckon to us are countless, but we resign ourselves to the fact that they are
limited to computer screens and observatories. We accept the fact that the stars
are too far away to take seriously, that Jupiter has a turbulent red spot over
twice the size of our planet, that the moon will always be a distant relative.
So instead, we look around at how far the horizon is and how hauntingly it
encircles us. That scircle is just a fleck of life, dotted on the surface of the
earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may think about the number of adventures we could be having, the divergent
memories we could be creating, the new people we could be meeting—within the
ring that encircles us. We have only one body, although our minds would surely
wish we had ten. The world becomes even more intriguing once we extricate
ourselves from that ring- there are mountains and slopes waiting to be climbed,
fields of snow waiting to be shaped into spheres and thrown, peaks that are
craving to be mounted, oceans with shadowy depths, beautiful creatures, and fish
that we still do not know exist. There are villages waiting to be visited, whose
culture is unlike anything we have ever witnessed. There are waterfalls,
rainforests, and glaciers still unknown to the human mind, foreign sunshine that
is waiting to infuse itself into our bloodstreams, caves that scream adrenaline
and excitement. There are airplanes, trains, cars, bicycles, and our own two
feet. But something stops us, limitations confine us. The lack of time, money,
and flexibility in our schedules. The fact that the seconds keep ticking by,
that so much of our time goes in useless endeavours we will never remember. And
the reality that we cannot be in two places at once. The fact that our two feet
are rooted in the same place, that there are millions of places we could be in
right now—but we are always forced to choose one. That when we are at the
airport, we have only one destination to go to—while the other cities flicker
like candlelight on a windy afternoon. When we drive a car, there are thousands
of alternate routes we could take. And yet, we do not—because we believe that we
are not meant to deviate from our predetermined route. In other words, we are
unknowingly ensnared. Onism is the frustration of knowing how little of the
universe we will be able to appreciate; the impatience of seeing the stars
twinkling at night, as if mocking our inability to escape the ground. But
somehow, it only makes us dream more. Our inability to traverse the Solar System
makes us imagine; it makes us envisage a universe that is probably more
beautiful and romantic than what it really is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may construe Onism as something that resembles sadness or sorrow, or one may
call it the Chi Force and what keeps us alive, but whatever it may be thought of
as- we are all affected by it, however it may come. I’d really encourage people
to go about looking for &lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt; and open their minds
to new words that express age-old emotions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the chance, I’d definitely like to end with a line from Koenig’s script- &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But if someone were to ask you on your Deathbed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it was like to live here on Earth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the only honest answer would be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know, I passed through it once, but I’ve never really been there.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Have you ever wandered off while sitting down―all in your head, all out of wonder? Ever imagined multiple lives for yourself? Ever wondered how there are a gazillion lives that are all affected by the interconnectedness of everything? Has there been a time when you have wanted to exchange places, or be at multiple places, living multiple lives at the same time? If you have, my friend, we are aboard the same boat and I hope your frustration wards off just as soon as I wish for mine to leave. Or maybe, just maybe, better yet, this wonder is what keeps us afloat, keeps us from dreading the worst. We know there’s a lot that exists, we know we may never know about it all, and maybe it’s this wonder that keeps us excited to be alive. I may be rationalising here and I promise to get rid of this defence mechanism as soon as I find a better one. But language is funny in more ways than not. We feel liberated using it, and at the same time, there is also a strange kind of entrapment. We cannot communicate without words, and yet are words sufficient to voice everything we feel? Personally, I did not know that the frustration of being limited to one experience was a common dilemma, I had no idea there was even a name for it, albeit none that one can use in their English essay. Onism, and we shall all thank John Koenig for the same, is a word that tries to explain the frustration of being stuck in just one body, that inhabits only one place at a time. It is understood to be like standing in front of the departures screen at an airport, flickering over with strange place names like other people’s passwords, each representing one more thing you will never get to see before you die―and all because, as the arrow on the map helpfully points out, you are here. One can imagine how much more rich and satisfying it would be to have multiple bodies, not just one―so one could escape themselves for a while and live on the other side of the planet. Or take a step back and see themselves from someone else’s point of view, in full context with the rest of the world, with their face the right way around, their eyes un-flattened, just as vivid as one appears to other people. It would be like knowing yourself like others do, judging our own quirks but with much less self-loathing, just seeing them as unique factions of our being. However absurd the idea may seem; it would bring so much more clarity and joy. Of course, this may be coming from a place of bias, with myself being someone who has felt this for a long time and only just recently found out about the word that expresses it so well on an unanticipated night. A friend introduced me to The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows and that’s when I met with the genius work of John Koenig. This man is on a mission to fill the gaps incurred in the English language. His dictionary includes words that describe emotions that one may feel but can’t put into motion through speech or writing, it includes questioning the limitations that language puts on us. One has to acknowledge that our bodies and minds are bombarded with so many complex sensations throughout the day that it would be impossible to assign a name to each. Feelings are a product of any stimulation one can procure―the lack of it―a phenomenon in itself. Even though Merriam and Oxford haven’t made it yet, Koenig with his popular Tumblr Blog and subsequent YouTube Channel and website is paving the way. TDOBS is intriguing because it presents a word that is obscure or completely invented and then connects it to a stylised video to further enhance the definition of that word. As Koenig indicates on his website, “Each original definition aims to fill a hole in the language—to give a name to emotions we all might experience but don’t yet have a word for.” Koenig has said multiple times that the blog began with his desire to write poems. He made up words to help frame the poems better. He insists that the inception began at a dark time in his life. In his Ted Talk, Koenig recollects the time when his own melancholy triggered him to compose the dictionary, and how people later came up to him to thank him for his work. The graphic designer/editor/voice performer speaks of how his sombreness gave him a penchant for words. One should be aware of the fact that he makes sure that all his words have etymological significance. That they all have sense and reason behind them. TDOBS gained popularity with the wilfulness of Twitter, someone tweeted out 23 of the words and then, boom! The crowd came rushing, in shared understanding of the un-worded emotions. Words such as ‘sonder’ have made it to the bigwigs, with companies using them to name products. A very prominent bar in New York has named its drinks after the 23 popularised words; artists too have now started naming their paintings with the help of these words, so as to express themselves better. One might wonder why out of every interesting word this man has invented, I longed to make this word the winter sun―Onism. Onism is a portmanteau of monism onanism. In philosophy, monism is the view that a variety of things can be explained in terms of a single reality or substance, or a distinct source. Onism can be seen as a kind of monism, because one’s life is indeed limited to a single reality, by virtue of being restricted to a single body, but something is clearly missing. Meanwhile, onanism is another word for masturbation or self-pleasure, transfixed inside our own menagerie of fantasies like going on a sightseeing tour of our own apartment—frustrating in its closed-off familiarity. Again, something is missing. What makes it even more special is that Onism was born while Koenig was travelling in an airplane, across 6 countries, in the process of moving places and struggling with the idea of a new life. To me, this brings in the idea more so than anything else. It makes me think of Remedial Chaos Theory: there are lots of me in other timelines who - collectively - have done everything I have not. It is the awareness of everything you are giving up, to be where you are right now. It is questioning the excuses we have invented to explain why so much of our life belongs in the background. Koenig very well expresses this in how he words his video transcripts- “We sketch monsters on the map because we find their presence comforting. They guard the edges of the abyss, and force us to look away; so, we can live comfortably in the Known World, at least for a little while.” An analogy I came across may help you visualise it better. By the time we enter primary school, we have heard all about the planets in our Solar System. As we grow older, we learn that the Solar System is just a speck in the Milky Way Galaxy, and that there are thousands of galaxies out there, peppering our universe with their glow and might. The celestial mysteries that beckon to us are countless, but we resign ourselves to the fact that they are limited to computer screens and observatories. We accept the fact that the stars are too far away to take seriously, that Jupiter has a turbulent red spot over twice the size of our planet, that the moon will always be a distant relative. So instead, we look around at how far the horizon is and how hauntingly it encircles us. That scircle is just a fleck of life, dotted on the surface of the earth. We may think about the number of adventures we could be having, the divergent memories we could be creating, the new people we could be meeting—within the ring that encircles us. We have only one body, although our minds would surely wish we had ten. The world becomes even more intriguing once we extricate ourselves from that ring- there are mountains and slopes waiting to be climbed, fields of snow waiting to be shaped into spheres and thrown, peaks that are craving to be mounted, oceans with shadowy depths, beautiful creatures, and fish that we still do not know exist. There are villages waiting to be visited, whose culture is unlike anything we have ever witnessed. There are waterfalls, rainforests, and glaciers still unknown to the human mind, foreign sunshine that is waiting to infuse itself into our bloodstreams, caves that scream adrenaline and excitement. There are airplanes, trains, cars, bicycles, and our own two feet. But something stops us, limitations confine us. The lack of time, money, and flexibility in our schedules. The fact that the seconds keep ticking by, that so much of our time goes in useless endeavours we will never remember. And the reality that we cannot be in two places at once. The fact that our two feet are rooted in the same place, that there are millions of places we could be in right now—but we are always forced to choose one. That when we are at the airport, we have only one destination to go to—while the other cities flicker like candlelight on a windy afternoon. When we drive a car, there are thousands of alternate routes we could take. And yet, we do not—because we believe that we are not meant to deviate from our predetermined route. In other words, we are unknowingly ensnared. Onism is the frustration of knowing how little of the universe we will be able to appreciate; the impatience of seeing the stars twinkling at night, as if mocking our inability to escape the ground. But somehow, it only makes us dream more. Our inability to traverse the Solar System makes us imagine; it makes us envisage a universe that is probably more beautiful and romantic than what it really is.  One may construe Onism as something that resembles sadness or sorrow, or one may call it the Chi Force and what keeps us alive, but whatever it may be thought of as- we are all affected by it, however it may come. I’d really encourage people to go about looking for The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows and open their minds to new words that express age-old emotions.  Given the chance, I’d definitely like to end with a line from Koenig’s script-  “But if someone were to ask you on your Deathbed What it was like to live here on Earth Perhaps the only honest answer would be, I don’t know, I passed through it once, but I’ve never really been there.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fleabag: A Tale of Clumsy Womanhood</title><link href="/Fleabag" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fleabag: A Tale of Clumsy Womanhood" /><published>2019-07-12T16:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T16:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/Fleabag</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Fleabag">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt;, a dark comedy, is a television show for every chaotic feminist out
there. It is a brutally honest account of a dysfunctional yet nonchalant woman,
who is clearly failing at life with her passive-aggressive family, dead business
and meaningless sexual relationships. The show, set in contemporary London,
speaks the mind of a modern woman through a feminist lens. Phoebe Waller-Bridge,
the writer of the show, also stars as the protagonist and plays her unnamed
character with utter brilliance, whom we call Fleabag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viewers take a ride through Fleabag’s mind, quite literally, when she talks
to them by breaking the fourth wall. She, conceitedly, predicts the actions of
the people she meets and talks to her audience about it. In the very first
scene, she presumes exactly what is going to happen after she has sex with an
immensely attractive man, and does so throughout the series. She seems to
understand the routine behaviour of the men who she sleeps with, and is seldom
fascinated by them. As viewers, we do not see Fleabag’s story, we see Fleabag.
She is present in every scene of every episode and is almost constantly talking.
The audience is not provided with other characters’ stories, and Fleabag’s
encounters and perceptions form the plot of the entire series. In fact, a few
interesting events in the characters’ lives build up to form the narrative of a
rather bigger story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first episode, Fleabag and her sister, Claire, attend a feminist lecture,
the tickets of which were given to them by their father. Fleabag called this
“[her] dad’s way of coping with two motherless daughters”, who is now in a
relationship with their godmother and has minimised contact with them. The
lecturer asks the audience to “raise [their] hands if you would trade five years
of your life for the so-called perfect body”, to which the sisters promptly
raise their hands, followed by Fleabag calling themselves ‘bad feminists.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a lot of instances in the show, we come to understand how Fleabag uses
sex to validate her own body and desirability, once even explicitly saying, “I
know that my body is the only thing I have left, and when that gets old and
unfuckable, I may as well kill it.” We later see how the complexities of
Fleabag’s anguish over the death of her mother and her best friend are
intertwined with her sexual encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Season 1 is an entry into the mayhem of Fleabag’s life, whereas season 2 is what
she calls her love story. Andrew Scott enters season 2 as &lt;em&gt;Sexy Priest&lt;/em&gt; and one
cannot take eyes off him. As Fleabag says ‘his arm’, ‘his beautiful neck’, ‘I
found myself pining &lt;em&gt;YES, YES, YES!&lt;/em&gt;’ But glass shatters, it’s not as much a
love story between Fleabag and ‘Sexy Priest’, as it is Fleabag’s
self-introspection and overcoming her disruptive behaviour. She learns to love
and to let go. Her cafe business thrives, and so does her relationship with
Claire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A magnificent scene in season 2, with guest star Kristin Scott Thomas, playing
the role of Belinda who wins an award for women in business, might just be the
monologue of the year, and will absolutely pierce through your heart. Belinda
says, “I was in an aeroplane the other day, and I realised – I’ve been longing
to say this out loud – women are born with pain built-in. It’s our physical
destiny. Period pain, sore boobs, childbirth, you know. We carry it within
ourselves throughout our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Men don’t. They have to seek it out. They invent all these Gods and demons and
things just so they can feel guilty about things, which is something we do very
well on our own. Then they create wars so they can feel things and touch each
other, and when there aren’t any wars they can play rugby.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And we have it all going on in here, inside. We have pain on a cycle for years
and years and years. And then, just as you feel you’re making peace with it all,
what happens? The menopause comes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men capitalise to feel alive, but women bring things to life. She protected even
when she suffered, while he created violence to be able to restore peace. Women
built walls to nurture, not to divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview with &lt;em&gt;The Hollywood Reporter&lt;/em&gt;, Phoebe Waller-Bridge confirmed
that &lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt; is not autobiographical. “A lot of the time when I was being
asked about the show, it was through the prism of feminism which was an
important part of the show for me…I just started feeling like I was suddenly
being moved into a different position that it wasn’t so much that I was a
writer, it was that I was a feminist writer, which of course I am, but that
becomes a category of writing”, added Phoebe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I would say, watch this for the love of clumsy womanhood, for learning to be
strong in this modern feminist world even when your entire life is crumbling
down. &lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt; taught me that feminism is hope, even if its standards you
cannot seem to reach, and women (dead or alive) will be your strength.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hrishita Sharma</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Fleabag, a dark comedy, is a television show for every chaotic feminist out there. It is a brutally honest account of a dysfunctional yet nonchalant woman, who is clearly failing at life with her passive-aggressive family, dead business and meaningless sexual relationships. The show, set in contemporary London, speaks the mind of a modern woman through a feminist lens. Phoebe Waller-Bridge, the writer of the show, also stars as the protagonist and plays her unnamed character with utter brilliance, whom we call Fleabag. The viewers take a ride through Fleabag’s mind, quite literally, when she talks to them by breaking the fourth wall. She, conceitedly, predicts the actions of the people she meets and talks to her audience about it. In the very first scene, she presumes exactly what is going to happen after she has sex with an immensely attractive man, and does so throughout the series. She seems to understand the routine behaviour of the men who she sleeps with, and is seldom fascinated by them. As viewers, we do not see Fleabag’s story, we see Fleabag. She is present in every scene of every episode and is almost constantly talking. The audience is not provided with other characters’ stories, and Fleabag’s encounters and perceptions form the plot of the entire series. In fact, a few interesting events in the characters’ lives build up to form the narrative of a rather bigger story. In the first episode, Fleabag and her sister, Claire, attend a feminist lecture, the tickets of which were given to them by their father. Fleabag called this “[her] dad’s way of coping with two motherless daughters”, who is now in a relationship with their godmother and has minimised contact with them. The lecturer asks the audience to “raise [their] hands if you would trade five years of your life for the so-called perfect body”, to which the sisters promptly raise their hands, followed by Fleabag calling themselves ‘bad feminists.’ Through a lot of instances in the show, we come to understand how Fleabag uses sex to validate her own body and desirability, once even explicitly saying, “I know that my body is the only thing I have left, and when that gets old and unfuckable, I may as well kill it.” We later see how the complexities of Fleabag’s anguish over the death of her mother and her best friend are intertwined with her sexual encounters. Season 1 is an entry into the mayhem of Fleabag’s life, whereas season 2 is what she calls her love story. Andrew Scott enters season 2 as Sexy Priest and one cannot take eyes off him. As Fleabag says ‘his arm’, ‘his beautiful neck’, ‘I found myself pining YES, YES, YES!’ But glass shatters, it’s not as much a love story between Fleabag and ‘Sexy Priest’, as it is Fleabag’s self-introspection and overcoming her disruptive behaviour. She learns to love and to let go. Her cafe business thrives, and so does her relationship with Claire. A magnificent scene in season 2, with guest star Kristin Scott Thomas, playing the role of Belinda who wins an award for women in business, might just be the monologue of the year, and will absolutely pierce through your heart. Belinda says, “I was in an aeroplane the other day, and I realised – I’ve been longing to say this out loud – women are born with pain built-in. It’s our physical destiny. Period pain, sore boobs, childbirth, you know. We carry it within ourselves throughout our lives.” “Men don’t. They have to seek it out. They invent all these Gods and demons and things just so they can feel guilty about things, which is something we do very well on our own. Then they create wars so they can feel things and touch each other, and when there aren’t any wars they can play rugby.” “And we have it all going on in here, inside. We have pain on a cycle for years and years and years. And then, just as you feel you’re making peace with it all, what happens? The menopause comes.” Men capitalise to feel alive, but women bring things to life. She protected even when she suffered, while he created violence to be able to restore peace. Women built walls to nurture, not to divide. In an interview with The Hollywood Reporter, Phoebe Waller-Bridge confirmed that Fleabag is not autobiographical. “A lot of the time when I was being asked about the show, it was through the prism of feminism which was an important part of the show for me…I just started feeling like I was suddenly being moved into a different position that it wasn’t so much that I was a writer, it was that I was a feminist writer, which of course I am, but that becomes a category of writing”, added Phoebe. So, I would say, watch this for the love of clumsy womanhood, for learning to be strong in this modern feminist world even when your entire life is crumbling down. Fleabag taught me that feminism is hope, even if its standards you cannot seem to reach, and women (dead or alive) will be your strength.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream</title><link href="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream" /><published>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream">&lt;p&gt;“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials …
has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion,
technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing
challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an
American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one
accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the
fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have
exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is
reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s
to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just
the generation gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest
hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore
the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then
aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation
in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when
they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny
scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s
common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five
years that follow graduation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even
comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen
not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young
graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits
of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score,
despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder
for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the
foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new
lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the
Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment
requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at
least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a
home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials
would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the
easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on
the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to
the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic
fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a
subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned
risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has
accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to
a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the
‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact,
they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a
result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the
rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their
savings, and further delays homeownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern
housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global
population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be
added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing
prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow
vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities
but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to
build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in
all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against
the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve,
whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because
the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover
costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism
(Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive
developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution,
rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not
only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc.,
but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an
especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a
combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps
people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India,
about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked,
“Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this
city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums.
Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford
monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent
settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they
actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two
flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3,
while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI
is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would
allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area,
and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for
Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city,
next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence
levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of
encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost
towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working
millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only
exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic
amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class
divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B.
Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the &lt;em&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/em&gt;,
had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the
cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every
petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays
them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they
manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they
must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the
sea.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials … has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion, technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.” Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just the generation gap. One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five years that follow graduation.  This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score, despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment requirements.  Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the ‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact, they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their savings, and further delays homeownership. But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve, whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism (Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution, rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties.  The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc., but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India, about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked, “Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums. Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3, while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area, and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city, next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like.  Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B. Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the Economic and Political Weekly, had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the sea.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Educating the Millennials: Whose Responsibility?</title><link href="/Educating-the-Millennials" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Educating the Millennials: Whose Responsibility?" /><published>2019-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Educating-the-Millennials</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Educating-the-Millennials">&lt;p&gt;“Education is the most powerful weapon which you can use to change the world.” These words of Nelson Mandela capture the importance of obtaining an education for every individual across any generation. Millennials, too, recognise the importance of getting educated. In fact, according to the Pew Research Center, they are the most educated generation yet. However, the major impediment that comes in their way of entering the formal schooling system and, later, higher education is limited availability of finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education funding is the most important means to strengthen education systems in the world. This has evolved over the years. In mid-19th century, governments across the world did most of the funding using revenue from taxes levied at the local level. Around the 20th century, the growth of the education sector became a global phenomenon. Other sources of education financing such as external grants or loans provided by foreign government, private organisations such as NGOs, and local administrations were being increasingly tapped. The amount spent by developing countries on improving the condition was close enough to the average spent in developed countries. A historical decline in education inequalities was observed during this time. UNGC’s Millennium Development Goals were signed in 2000, in which the second goal was to achieve universal primary education. The first decade of the 21st century saw increased international financial flows for development assistance. Post-2010, there was a notable reduction in the amount of public funds being used to finance education. Secondary and tertiary levels of education receive more funding than the primary level. Notable examples in this regard would be Europe and Sub-Saharan Africa where less development assistance is provided for primary education. The UNICEF report, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unicef.org/publications/files/Investment_Case_for_Education_and_Equity_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Investment Case for Education and Equity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;2015&lt;/em&gt;, shows that in low-income countries, on average 46% of public resources for education are allocated to the 10% of students who are most educated – while this figure goes down to 26% and 13% in lower-middle and upper-middle income countries respectively. Larger allocation to higher education is important to ensure better national competitiveness through innovation, and to enhance the skills of millennials. Moreover, there is cross-country heterogeneity with respect to the importance of the education sector vis-à-vis other sectors. For example, American Samoa and Kiribati spend more than 12% of their national income on education while countries such as Bangladesh and Bermuda spend only about 1% for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting to note is even when more public funds are allocated and private funding is also playing its part towards higher education financing, they are not enough. The demand for higher education among millennials is constantly growing and this is inevitably transforming this sector from an elite to a mass system across different parts of the world. The traditional revenue-driven model was based on public funding, student tuition fees and other charges collected from them, along with endowments. A major component of the revenue so collected goes into paying salaries to the faculty. It is necessary because of the increased opportunity cost of employment avenues. Besides dwindling public funding, the rate of increase in the cost of higher education exceeds the inflation rate in most countries. As a result, the cost of higher education is escalating at an alarming rate. Even in a country like India, where higher education has traditionally been highly subsidised, the government is pulling its purse strings. Across the world, public funding is moving from committal funds to assessment-based funding. Now even the youngest millennial is an adult and is ready for higher education. It is the responsibility of all stakeholders to ensure that education is within the means of each interested millennial. Christensen and Eyring in 2011 introduced the concept of ‘disruptive innovation’ in their book &lt;em&gt;The Innovative University&lt;/em&gt;. This idea was used to implement information and communication technology in education, which was done by the introduction of online courses. Virtual education not only reduced the cost of education for millennials but also helped improve the quality of teaching. Many universities have ‘Work-Study Programs’ and offer an opportunity to study and work part-time simultaneously under such initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries are designing different models for sustainable funding of education. In some countries, like Germany, need-based student aid is provided for students, while in the UK, financial institutions are generally tapped to raise capital. New Zealand follows a Performance-Linked Funding Policy wherein students over the 50th percentile receive 100% government funding, while the remaining students receive 95%. To keep a check on the exorbitant tuition fees, a Tuition Grant Scheme (TGS) is in place in Singapore where students enjoy a substantially subsidised tuition. A new system of philanthro-capitalism has been introduced in India where capitalistic style objectives direct the entry of philanthropic enterprises in the education sector. Compared to the slow growth rate in higher education enrolment in North America and Europe, India enjoys the advantage of a large youth population so higher education sees enrolment in huge numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are doing their bit to reduce strain on resources. Some students enter the workforce while being enrolled in higher education to either financially support themselves or to gain practical experience. Many start-up stories unfold in universities. Many millennials believe in the ‘earn while you learn’ concept. Education loans are becoming increasingly popular as a means to finance education in developed as well as developing countries. According to an estimate by CNBC, student debt stands at nearly $1.5 trillion and, roughly, one in four American adults is paying off student loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financing of higher education institutions assumes great significance in today’s extremely competitive world. Higher education makes an immense contribution towards building the social capital of a nation. The government should have a futuristic outlook and increase spending on education with a focus on the quality. This is important because millennials see education as a means not only to acquire a degree but an avenue to enhance their knowledge and employability. While need-based grants and scholarships are available to some students, there are many who are denied these. Industry can provide lucrative internship opportunities to students, which help them finance their education. Policymakers should assess the impact of student loans as a source of financing education. Loan servicing results in reduced disposable income, which may impact the economic growth of a country adversely. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalreserve.gov/econresdata/feds/2016/files/2016010pap.pdf&quot;&gt;Federal Reserve Board of Washington,&lt;/a&gt; DC concluded in a study that increasing student debt in the US has resulted in reduced homeownership. The growth of the housing sector is important for the economic revival of any country because of backward and forward linkages. High student debt will have implications for workforce composition as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/blog/investing/millennial-grad-retirement-age-is-75/&quot;&gt;A study&lt;/a&gt; from NerdWallet predicts that students who graduated from US colleges in 2015 will have to delay retirement until the age of 75, in part because of the increasing burden of student debt. It is, thus, imperative for policymakers across the world to brainstorm and find ways to finance education in a manner that it becomes a win-win situation for millennials and their successors – Generation Z.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manya Manushi</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“Education is the most powerful weapon which you can use to change the world.” These words of Nelson Mandela capture the importance of obtaining an education for every individual across any generation. Millennials, too, recognise the importance of getting educated. In fact, according to the Pew Research Center, they are the most educated generation yet. However, the major impediment that comes in their way of entering the formal schooling system and, later, higher education is limited availability of finance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Portuguese Drug Decriminalisation – Has it Worked?</title><link href="/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portuguese Drug Decriminalisation – Has it Worked?" /><published>2019-07-10T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-10T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation">&lt;p&gt;In 2001, Portugal became a global leader in the war against drugs when it
decriminalised the possession and consumption of all illegal substances. When
this topic comes up in conversation, most people (especially those from the UK
and the US) are rather shocked when they find out. Two obvious questions then
arise. Firstly, how and why could a traditionally conservative country, tucked
away at the edge of Europe, just decriminalise all drugs? The second question
is, of course, did it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background to this article&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is inspired by a university project that I completed whilst
spending 5 months in Lisbon. The interviews referenced are personal interviews
that I completed in April, 2019. Some have been translated from Portuguese to
English. The three interviews I will reference are of the following people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;João Santa Maria&lt;/em&gt; – Peer mediator in the NGO IN-Mouraria – a harm reduction
centre for drug users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes&lt;/em&gt; – Principal Scientist and expert in Drug Legislation at the
European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;João Goulão&lt;/em&gt; – Director of SICAD, the government department for Intervention
on Addictive Behaviours and Dependencies, and the architect for Portugal’s drug
policy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portugal’s decision to decriminalise drugs cannot be understood without first
looking at the recent history of the country. From 1933 to 1974, Portugal was
under the rule of the Estado Novo regime, a right-wing, Catholic, authoritarian
government led by Antonio Salazar. If this name sounds familiar, it’s because it
was the inspiration behind Salazar Slytherin, as J.K. Rowling used to live and
teach in Porto. Portugal was shut off from the outside world, with its only
neighbouring country Spain under a similarly restrictive right-wing
dictatorship, so Portugal “missed out on the experimentation and mind-expanding
culture of the 1960s.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the colonial troops came back from Africa, they brought cannabis with them;
soon after, heroin entered the country. As João Santa Maria explains, “freedom
gave us the right to do whatever we wanted.” However, there would be
consequences to this liberty. By the end of the 90s, heroin addiction, HIV and
Hepatitis C had ravaged the country. In truth, nobody quite knows how many
people were addicted, but it’s estimated that 1 in 10 people were using heroin,
1 in 100 were battling heroin addiction, and HIV rates reached a high of 104.2
new cases per million in 2000. To put that into context, the current HIV rate is
4.2 per million. One of the most important things to understand is that heroin
use was not limited to a certain class of people. Bankers, lawyers, doctors,
teachers; João Goulão remembers how everybody seemed to know a heroin addict. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, implementing wide-scale change and challenging the social norms of a drug
policy was a far more realistic and achievable task in Portugal than it would be
in the UK or the US today. Furthermore, the policy was not a result of left-wing
liberalisation, as some people might assume. The motivation, as explained, was a
response to a health crisis, not an ideological movement. In 2001, the new
decriminalisation law was implemented and although there have been some small
alterations, it essentially remains the same to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it is important to address exactly what decriminalisation
actually means. Brendan Hughes has made a very useful video
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc&quot;&gt;www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc&lt;/a&gt;)
which I highly recommend watching. To explain it briefly, decriminalisation is
&lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; the same as legalisation. In the diagram below, taken from Hughes’
video, the red dots indicated illegal activity, and the green dots, legal
activity. Decriminalisation, or a non-criminal offence, does not pass the line
from criminal to legal. It simply becomes an administrative offence, rather than
a criminal one. For example, bad parking is not a criminal offence, but may
still be fined and punished. The same can be said for the possession and
consumption of illegal substances in Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//drug-decriminalisation.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Image result for drug decriminalisation explained&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main issues with decriminalisation in Portugal, and across the world,
is that the general public does not seem to understand what it entails. In
Lisbon, this is not helped by the fact that tourist areas are filled with ‘drug
dealers’, who offer unsuspecting tourists cannabis, hashish and cocaine. The
drugs are almost always fake (which is why the police do not intervene), but
this gives visitors the impression that drugs are legal in Portugal which
definitely muddies the water. Another issue is that the concept of
decriminalisation has become incredibly and dangerously politicised. Here is an
extract from my interview with Brendan, wherein he concisely details the issues
with decriminalisation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “From what I see, a chunk of it is to with this horrible word
decriminalisation, which evokes so many feelings in different people, despite
the fact that most of them don’t actually know what it is or what it means. They
imagine it to mean something, and therefore either they are greatly in favour of
what they think it means, or they are greatly against. So, they are in favour
because it means people don’t get criminal records, or people get treated and
treated as humans, and they have dignity, and you take the drug users away from
contact with the police or the criminal justice system. And people are against
it because they think that it takes away the threat, and it suggests somehow
society considers that this offence isn’t particularly that bad after all and
therefore it will encourage a bunch of other people to do it - those are the
main arguments. And because neither of them are fully correct - but again,
people don’t really seem to talk so much about the facts.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me: “And, you know, that decriminalisation doesn’t lead to increased use.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “It doesn’t. We don’t know! It doesn’t lead to anything
predictable.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me: “It’s not about liberalisation. And I guess I think some people think that
it’s a left-wing policy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “And that’s what I say. People think it’s a badge, and it’s
either a badge of achievement to say that you’ve done it, or it’s a badge of
achievement to say that you’ve resisted it, when neither side really sees the
full picture.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Extract from my interview with Brendan Hughes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the politics, what have been the quantifiable outcomes of the policy?
Well, it is not a simple answer. Statistically speaking, Portugal has
dramatically improved. HIV rates have plummeted, overall drug use is down,
though Hepatitis C and problem drug use are still an issue. If you are caught
with an illegal substance, you are either fined, given a warning, or sent to a
commission. These commissions have the mantra of ‘treatment before punishment’,
and the vast majority of cases are dismissed. If you are a drug addict, then
there is no possibility of a fine, only treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of policing, the local authorities rarely bother anybody on the street,
and it is extremely common to smell cannabis at any time of the day. The
attitude towards drug addicts has also improved, and heroin-assisted treatment
centres, in Lisbon, are finally about to open, having been promised for over two
years. The improvements listed above definitely qualify as drastic progress, in
comparison to where Portugal was in the 80s and the 90s, yet it would be an
oversimplification to credit all of this to decriminalisation. João Goulão has
detailed how they could have done the whole policy without decriminalisation,
and still put in place the social services and commissions that exist today. In
fact, there is definitely a symbolic element to Portuguese decriminalisation;
allowing the Portuguese population the freedoms that they had so badly missed
for the majority of the 20th century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, upon speaking to various street teams involved with drug use, homelessness
and other issues, I discovered that there is definitely the feeling that the
policy did not go far enough; some believe that legalisation and regulation are
the only solutions. Financing, from the state and local governments, has
dwindled, and drug users still feel punished purely for being drug users. Though
people are more accepting, Santa Maria notes that, “although they support our
work, they don’t want to deal with it on their own doorstep”. When I asked João
Goulão about these complaints, he responded in an empathetic but pragmatic way.
It is clear that he cares about how his policy is perceived by those it affects,
but being an activist and being a politician are two separate things; in charge
of a delicate political balancing act, it is a tricky task to please
politicians, the public and drug users all at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global trend towards cannabis legalisation is also causing problems. Part of
the basis for the entire Portuguese policy is that there is no such thing as
‘hard’ drugs and ‘soft’ drugs; all of them are treated as equal. However, with
other countries starting to legalise cannabis, this creates a sticky situation
for the Portuguese. It would be very difficult, if not impossible, to justify
the legalisation of cannabis; if all drugs are equally ‘good’ or ‘bad’, then if
you legalise one, you must legalise them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking ahead - Is Portugal an example to follow?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I stated earlier, it is hard to label the policy in a binary sense of ‘it
works’ or ‘it does not work’. That said, I find it difficult not to see the
Portuguese policy as progress in the right direction. There are clearly some
issues, but these generally take the form of improvements that need to be made,
rather than fundamental problems of the policy itself. As more and more
countries start to think about and implement similar policies, the Portuguese
2001 legislation is still relevant nearly twenty years later. Whether or not it
serves as an example or model for other countries is debatable. Drug policy is
very nuanced, and each individual country has its own idiosyncrasies and culture
that would affect whether decriminalisation would work. To try and imitate the
Portuguese success by replicating them would not work; the policy was reacting
to a specific situation at a specific time. However, using the Portuguese as an
inspiration of alternative policymaking, and thus reviewing our own beliefs
about drug and drug policy could be a way forward. Too often, we follow the
dogma that we have been taught by friends, family, politicians, looking for an
easy, ‘one size fits all’ answer to the very difficult question of drug policy.
The Portuguese have shown us that there is another way, and maybe we should take
note.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Daniel Harris</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 2001, Portugal became a global leader in the war against drugs when it decriminalised the possession and consumption of all illegal substances. When this topic comes up in conversation, most people (especially those from the UK and the US) are rather shocked when they find out. Two obvious questions then arise. Firstly, how and why could a traditionally conservative country, tucked away at the edge of Europe, just decriminalise all drugs? The second question is, of course, did it work? Background to this article This article is inspired by a university project that I completed whilst spending 5 months in Lisbon. The interviews referenced are personal interviews that I completed in April, 2019. Some have been translated from Portuguese to English. The three interviews I will reference are of the following people: João Santa Maria – Peer mediator in the NGO IN-Mouraria – a harm reduction centre for drug users. Brendan Hughes – Principal Scientist and expert in Drug Legislation at the European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction. João Goulão – Director of SICAD, the government department for Intervention on Addictive Behaviours and Dependencies, and the architect for Portugal’s drug policy.  The History Portugal’s decision to decriminalise drugs cannot be understood without first looking at the recent history of the country. From 1933 to 1974, Portugal was under the rule of the Estado Novo regime, a right-wing, Catholic, authoritarian government led by Antonio Salazar. If this name sounds familiar, it’s because it was the inspiration behind Salazar Slytherin, as J.K. Rowling used to live and teach in Porto. Portugal was shut off from the outside world, with its only neighbouring country Spain under a similarly restrictive right-wing dictatorship, so Portugal “missed out on the experimentation and mind-expanding culture of the 1960s.”  When the colonial troops came back from Africa, they brought cannabis with them; soon after, heroin entered the country. As João Santa Maria explains, “freedom gave us the right to do whatever we wanted.” However, there would be consequences to this liberty. By the end of the 90s, heroin addiction, HIV and Hepatitis C had ravaged the country. In truth, nobody quite knows how many people were addicted, but it’s estimated that 1 in 10 people were using heroin, 1 in 100 were battling heroin addiction, and HIV rates reached a high of 104.2 new cases per million in 2000. To put that into context, the current HIV rate is 4.2 per million. One of the most important things to understand is that heroin use was not limited to a certain class of people. Bankers, lawyers, doctors, teachers; João Goulão remembers how everybody seemed to know a heroin addict.  Thus, implementing wide-scale change and challenging the social norms of a drug policy was a far more realistic and achievable task in Portugal than it would be in the UK or the US today. Furthermore, the policy was not a result of left-wing liberalisation, as some people might assume. The motivation, as explained, was a response to a health crisis, not an ideological movement. In 2001, the new decriminalisation law was implemented and although there have been some small alterations, it essentially remains the same to this day. At this point, it is important to address exactly what decriminalisation actually means. Brendan Hughes has made a very useful video (www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc) which I highly recommend watching. To explain it briefly, decriminalisation is not the same as legalisation. In the diagram below, taken from Hughes’ video, the red dots indicated illegal activity, and the green dots, legal activity. Decriminalisation, or a non-criminal offence, does not pass the line from criminal to legal. It simply becomes an administrative offence, rather than a criminal one. For example, bad parking is not a criminal offence, but may still be fined and punished. The same can be said for the possession and consumption of illegal substances in Portugal. Image result for drug decriminalisation explained One of the main issues with decriminalisation in Portugal, and across the world, is that the general public does not seem to understand what it entails. In Lisbon, this is not helped by the fact that tourist areas are filled with ‘drug dealers’, who offer unsuspecting tourists cannabis, hashish and cocaine. The drugs are almost always fake (which is why the police do not intervene), but this gives visitors the impression that drugs are legal in Portugal which definitely muddies the water. Another issue is that the concept of decriminalisation has become incredibly and dangerously politicised. Here is an extract from my interview with Brendan, wherein he concisely details the issues with decriminalisation: Brendan Hughes: “From what I see, a chunk of it is to with this horrible word decriminalisation, which evokes so many feelings in different people, despite the fact that most of them don’t actually know what it is or what it means. They imagine it to mean something, and therefore either they are greatly in favour of what they think it means, or they are greatly against. So, they are in favour because it means people don’t get criminal records, or people get treated and treated as humans, and they have dignity, and you take the drug users away from contact with the police or the criminal justice system. And people are against it because they think that it takes away the threat, and it suggests somehow society considers that this offence isn’t particularly that bad after all and therefore it will encourage a bunch of other people to do it - those are the main arguments. And because neither of them are fully correct - but again, people don’t really seem to talk so much about the facts.” Me: “And, you know, that decriminalisation doesn’t lead to increased use.” Brendan Hughes: “It doesn’t. We don’t know! It doesn’t lead to anything predictable.” Me: “It’s not about liberalisation. And I guess I think some people think that it’s a left-wing policy.” Brendan Hughes: “And that’s what I say. People think it’s a badge, and it’s either a badge of achievement to say that you’ve done it, or it’s a badge of achievement to say that you’ve resisted it, when neither side really sees the full picture.” (Extract from my interview with Brendan Hughes). The Results Beyond the politics, what have been the quantifiable outcomes of the policy? Well, it is not a simple answer. Statistically speaking, Portugal has dramatically improved. HIV rates have plummeted, overall drug use is down, though Hepatitis C and problem drug use are still an issue. If you are caught with an illegal substance, you are either fined, given a warning, or sent to a commission. These commissions have the mantra of ‘treatment before punishment’, and the vast majority of cases are dismissed. If you are a drug addict, then there is no possibility of a fine, only treatment. In terms of policing, the local authorities rarely bother anybody on the street, and it is extremely common to smell cannabis at any time of the day. The attitude towards drug addicts has also improved, and heroin-assisted treatment centres, in Lisbon, are finally about to open, having been promised for over two years. The improvements listed above definitely qualify as drastic progress, in comparison to where Portugal was in the 80s and the 90s, yet it would be an oversimplification to credit all of this to decriminalisation. João Goulão has detailed how they could have done the whole policy without decriminalisation, and still put in place the social services and commissions that exist today. In fact, there is definitely a symbolic element to Portuguese decriminalisation; allowing the Portuguese population the freedoms that they had so badly missed for the majority of the 20th century.  Yet, upon speaking to various street teams involved with drug use, homelessness and other issues, I discovered that there is definitely the feeling that the policy did not go far enough; some believe that legalisation and regulation are the only solutions. Financing, from the state and local governments, has dwindled, and drug users still feel punished purely for being drug users. Though people are more accepting, Santa Maria notes that, “although they support our work, they don’t want to deal with it on their own doorstep”. When I asked João Goulão about these complaints, he responded in an empathetic but pragmatic way. It is clear that he cares about how his policy is perceived by those it affects, but being an activist and being a politician are two separate things; in charge of a delicate political balancing act, it is a tricky task to please politicians, the public and drug users all at the same time. The global trend towards cannabis legalisation is also causing problems. Part of the basis for the entire Portuguese policy is that there is no such thing as ‘hard’ drugs and ‘soft’ drugs; all of them are treated as equal. However, with other countries starting to legalise cannabis, this creates a sticky situation for the Portuguese. It would be very difficult, if not impossible, to justify the legalisation of cannabis; if all drugs are equally ‘good’ or ‘bad’, then if you legalise one, you must legalise them all. Looking ahead - Is Portugal an example to follow? As I stated earlier, it is hard to label the policy in a binary sense of ‘it works’ or ‘it does not work’. That said, I find it difficult not to see the Portuguese policy as progress in the right direction. There are clearly some issues, but these generally take the form of improvements that need to be made, rather than fundamental problems of the policy itself. As more and more countries start to think about and implement similar policies, the Portuguese 2001 legislation is still relevant nearly twenty years later. Whether or not it serves as an example or model for other countries is debatable. Drug policy is very nuanced, and each individual country has its own idiosyncrasies and culture that would affect whether decriminalisation would work. To try and imitate the Portuguese success by replicating them would not work; the policy was reacting to a specific situation at a specific time. However, using the Portuguese as an inspiration of alternative policymaking, and thus reviewing our own beliefs about drug and drug policy could be a way forward. Too often, we follow the dogma that we have been taught by friends, family, politicians, looking for an easy, ‘one size fits all’ answer to the very difficult question of drug policy. The Portuguese have shown us that there is another way, and maybe we should take note.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review: ‘The Book of Ram’ by Devdutt Pattanaik</title><link href="/The-Book-of-Ram" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review: 'The Book of Ram' by Devdutt Pattanaik" /><published>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Book-of-Ram</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Book-of-Ram">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Ram&lt;/em&gt; is the outcome of Pattanaik’s endeavour to weave magic into the timeless Indian epic tale of the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;. As the title suggests, the book brings to light, the story of &lt;em&gt;Maryada Purushottam&lt;/em&gt; Ram, the seventh ‘avatar’ of Lord Vishnu (the one who nurtures and maintains balance in the worldly life), the scion of the Raghu clan, the worthy heir, the jewel of the Solar dynasty, the Prince and the Supreme Upholder of social norms and values, the warrior and the ideal king. The author admits that he felt compelled to write the book when he realised that the epic in question was being used as a tool to fuel anger, animosity, hatred, and violence. Pattanaik’s &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; is as informative as it is gripping and riveting. Pattanaik’s simple yet exceedingly well-written book explores the relevance of Shri Ram, the only Hindu deity to be worshipped as The King in the contemporary world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book very rightly portrays Lord Ram as ‘&lt;em&gt;Eka-Vachani&lt;/em&gt;’: A king who is always true to his words; ‘&lt;em&gt;Ek-bani&lt;/em&gt;’: a supreme archer who strikes his target with the first arrow, and ‘&lt;em&gt;Ek-Patni&lt;/em&gt;’: A man who is eternally devoted to one woman. Censured by feminists and appropriated by innumerable politicians, Ram still remains pious and serene in his majesty. Hindus firmly believe that in times of turmoil, by chanting Lord Ram’s name and his tales, one can achieve peace, stability, hope, and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik’s story is through the eyes of Sita, Ram’s wife and the avatar of Vishnu’s consort Lakshmi. The book glimpses through all the different versions of the revered epic starting from before the 1st century CE to the 19th century, including the versions popular in South East Asian cultures. The author meticulously shows the contrast between different mini &lt;em&gt;Ramayanas&lt;/em&gt;, ranging from Kamban’s &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; to Valmiki’s, from Maya Sita to Devi Sita. All these versions speak a different tale but eventually converge into a singular point that reflects the grandeur of the creator(s) and an ancient faith. It also becomes crucial to note that &lt;em&gt;Sanatan Dharma&lt;/em&gt; (Eternal Order, as so many Hindus refer to Hinduism) does not subscribe to the idea of differentiating between the male and the female along a strict line. Pattanaik makes the use of symbols, metaphors, patterns, and motifs to convey his message. The fact that Ram painstakingly fulfils his duty as a king and ultimately walks into the Sarayu river chanting Sita’s name to bring him solace, stands crucial. In the Indian context, a God is always accompanied by a Goddess, thus reflecting the need to maintain a balance between the two. The existence of &lt;em&gt;Adi Shakti&lt;/em&gt; (Primal Female Energy) points to the same and brings in a much-needed fluidity in modern society. Ram as a God is dependable and Sita as a Goddess is independent. Pattanaik asks, isn’t this what we all aspire to be, dependable but independent? The author scholastically delves into the spirit of the religious text. Rather than drawing superficial inferences from the literal aspects of the text, which has led to myriad misinterpretations from time immemorial, Pattanaik understands an important truth about the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, it is not about the words but the essence behind them. He also brings to light how the binary, didactic Abrahamic Western thought process has discredited the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; or, for that matter, all our religious texts by only taking into account the literal aspects of our vast literature and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is crucial to note that parts of this epic and many other Hindu religious scriptures have been changed by authors, in accordance with the time they lived in and the perils that faced their society. Even in this book, Pattanaik admits to using his vivid imagination and thereby perpetuates the long-standing tradition of adding personal stories to the great epic. As a consequence, it becomes difficult for a lay reader to distinguish between the facts mentioned in the epic and those that have been woven into it by the author’s imagination. Even though this makes Pattanaik’s book slightly unscholarly it’s still not completely discreditable, for it only makes it a tad bit more Hindu in spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book also, very rightly, criticises the manipulation and distortion of religion by Hindu extremist groups. It gives out a message of peace and unity for achieving true &lt;em&gt;Ram Rajya&lt;/em&gt;, which is not restricted to a time or place but is to be found &lt;strong&gt;within&lt;/strong&gt;. To quote Pattanaik, “He [Ram] is our soul.” He criticises the modern education system for teaching one to respect only that which can be proved empirically. He provokes one to think of the debate between religion and science. He also makes a much-needed distinction between linear and cyclical history. However, the book adopts a very idealistic stand which is difficult to grasp in a modern materialistic world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu religious scriptures tell us something crucial through its characters. Humans are made of conflicting truths; there isn’t either a positive side or a negative side to one, Pattanaik shows how one person can be a martyr, a villain, a hero, and a victim. Our books are about diverse human characters; humans of wisdom and of folly who are unpredictable and dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik also draws a parallel between Prince Ram and Lord Krishna. The epic, he rightly states, teaches us that a world governed only by law and not by emotions is not ideal. He talks about the supreme sacrifice made by Lord Ram and Goddess Sita to impart this lesson to a not-so-humane world. The strong, wise and independent hero, the warrior princess, Sita also fulfils her duties and departs leaving Ram on Earth to fulfill his kingly duty and return to the &lt;em&gt;Vaikuntha Loka&lt;/em&gt;, the abode of Vishnu where he sleeps on the Snake of Time, dreaming of creation. The epic, via its protagonist Shri Ram, thus imparts essential lessons of democracy and the beauty of living for people. It imparts valuable lessons of humanity also through King Ram’s character: His supreme uprightness in the face of the darkest of adversities offers peace, stability and hope to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik stands by the statement that liberals today will find their perfect ally in Hindu thought and philosophy. The nonexistence of a Sanskrit word for blasphemy also points to the same. The book speaks of fluidity and inclusivity of the Hindu religion by talking about the acceptance of LGBTQ people in the social order, linking this fact back to Hinduism’s comfort with fluidity in its seemingly gendered motifs and totems. The book also states that in the Hindu religion, one’s &lt;em&gt;Karma&lt;/em&gt; (Action) is supreme and overshadows all else. The &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; is primarily a tale of emotions, be it filial affection, a sense of duty and loyalty, love, lust or malice. It also shows the ill outcome of ego, ambition, and arrogance. Thus, the retelling of the epic provokes profound thought, it expands one’s consciousness inspiring them to cultivate and realise one’s potential by overcoming the fallacies of human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik’s &lt;em&gt;Book of Ram&lt;/em&gt; is a well-researched one. Simplifying the philosophical connotations, it can be said that the author believes that in each person there is a part of Ram-Sita, a Ravan, an Ahilya, a Mandodri or a Surupnakha. Human nature and destiny are determined by the part a human decides to give precedence to. Thus, in essence, it can be said, the Ramayana has never been a tale of Ram’s life. It has always been a tale of how Ram lived for others. Here, I am compelled to reiterate, that the interpretation of Ram’s character will invariably be an interpretation of one’s own character. Isn’t how we see others a reflection of how we see ourselves? Perhaps, the answer is best left untold!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">The Book of Ram is the outcome of Pattanaik’s endeavour to weave magic into the timeless Indian epic tale of the Ramayana. As the title suggests, the book brings to light, the story of Maryada Purushottam Ram, the seventh ‘avatar’ of Lord Vishnu (the one who nurtures and maintains balance in the worldly life), the scion of the Raghu clan, the worthy heir, the jewel of the Solar dynasty, the Prince and the Supreme Upholder of social norms and values, the warrior and the ideal king. The author admits that he felt compelled to write the book when he realised that the epic in question was being used as a tool to fuel anger, animosity, hatred, and violence. Pattanaik’s Ramayana is as informative as it is gripping and riveting. Pattanaik’s simple yet exceedingly well-written book explores the relevance of Shri Ram, the only Hindu deity to be worshipped as The King in the contemporary world.</summary></entry></feed>