<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-09T13:47:28+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Without Adaptive Intervention, Will The ‘War on Drugs’ Ever Succeed?</title><link href="/War-on-Drugs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Without Adaptive Intervention, Will The ‘War on Drugs’ Ever Succeed?" /><published>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/War-on-Drugs</id><content type="html" xml:base="/War-on-Drugs">&lt;p&gt;Besides grappling with the challenges of disappearing jobs, low investment, and a faltering economy, Punjab has a genuinely big issue to solve. This state in northern India has been scourged by the menace of drug abuse, for years now. Punjab’s proximity to Afghanistan and Pakistan, with which it shares its border, has made it an easy target for people involved in the drug smuggling trade. Gradually, the state transformed from a spot on the smuggling trade route to one of the biggest consumer markets for heroin, in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1980’s, Punjab was hit by severe communal violence which took decades to resolve. Now, the residents often comment that, “We got rid of terrorism only for it to be replaced with narcotics-terrorism.” A report by the All India Institute of Medical Sciences, in Delhi, concluded that there were more than two hundred thousand addicts in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of drug abuse is not limited to Punjab. In India’s north-eastern state of Mizoram, the number of drug overdose cases has been on the rise since November of 2012. According to reports from the Department of Health and Family Welfare, Government of Mizoram, 328 cases of overdose and 13 deaths due to overdose have been reported in Mizoram between November 2012 and July 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Globally, after 50 years of the war on drugs, the supply and use of drugs has not only increased—it has created a massive black market that contributes to violence, conflict and corruption. Social marginalisation and health crises across the world have rapidly increased due to the formulation of poorly designed drug policies and criminalisation of drug users. The Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act, 1985 has been instrumental in setting up a legal framework for drug law enforcement in India. The main focus areas include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Surveillance and enforcement at import points and land borders.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Preventive and interdictive efforts along the known drug routes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Control measures at export points, such as air-passenger terminals, cargo terminals and foreign post offices.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improved coordination among the various drug law enforcement agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Identification and eradication of illicit cultivation and the wild growth of cannabis and opium poppy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strengthening of the intelligence apparatus to improve the collection, collation, analysis and dissemination of operational intelligence&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increased international cooperation, both in operational and long term intelligence as well as in investigations and mutual legal assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India, like many other countries, has focused on tackling drug abuse by cracking down on suppliers and reducing supply in the drug market. It has failed as the black market for drugs is too large. Suppliers are constantly making new variants of synthetic drugs and, despite the vigilance of security forces, the market is expanding exponentially. In poorer countries, like Colombia and Mexico, adoption of similar policies has eroded critical civic institutions and created powerful mafia groups that control society and polity. After years of national drug strategies aimed at seizure of illicit drugs, there has been little to no effect on the availability, price and purity of drugs. Drug prohibition, in the short run, has always overshadowed reducing demand and harm by eliciting behavioural changes through effective drug education in the long run. This change is long overdue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no laws governing the establishment and running of treatment centres. This has resulted in the proliferation of unauthorised ‘de-addiction’ centres. Rather than medical care, ‘punishments’ in the form of severe torture, which have led to death in many cases, are meted out to the patients. Further, rehabilitation centres, in the hinterlands of the country, lack access to adequate capital and infrastructure. Thus, facilitating the proper functioning of rehabilitation and treatment centres is an important step that the government must actively take to shrink the market for drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-availability of data, in India, acts as a major hindrance in the framing of a comprehensive drug policy. The nature and extent of drug use, dependence and its associated health implications, which ought to be the most important considerations for a drug policy, remain unknown. The first and only survey estimating the extent of drug use was conducted in 2001-2002, which was more than a decade ago. According to that survey, there were an estimated 8.7 million cannabis users, of which 2.3 million were dependent (26%). The number of opiate users was estimated to be 2 million, of which 0.5 million (22%) were thought to be dependent. A central agency should be established to collect data and analyse trends about the magnitude and scope of the drug market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India, like many other countries in Asia, has adopted extremely punitive measures to control drug usage. Many aspects of the NDPS Act are more barbarous than even those provided by the UN Drug Control conventions, such as provisions related to illegal usage of drugs, death penalty, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crime and addiction have not increased in countries where drug usage is limited to adults only. One notable example is Portugal where consumption of drugs was decriminalised in 2001. This resulted in the drug-related HIV transmission to plummet down by 44% from 1999 to 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drug liberalisation is increasingly becoming an important facet in the battle against drugs as major economies like Canada and the USA have followed suit in the decriminalisation/legalisation of cannabis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time for India to redraft its decades-old drug policy and reignite the battle against drugs through adaptive intervention. Drug liberalisation, infrastructural development and education are becoming essential to the ‘war on drugs’. History stands testament to the fact that drug prohibition is not enough. Better policies led by data collection and analysis will help India combat the ailment of illicit drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Besides grappling with the challenges of disappearing jobs, low investment, and a faltering economy, Punjab has a genuinely big issue to solve. This state in northern India has been scourged by the menace of drug abuse, for years now. Punjab’s proximity to Afghanistan and Pakistan, with which it shares its border, has made it an easy target for people involved in the drug smuggling trade. Gradually, the state transformed from a spot on the smuggling trade route to one of the biggest consumer markets for heroin, in India.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The State of the Millennial in 2019</title><link href="/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The State of the Millennial in 2019" /><published>2019-07-07T01:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-07T01:40:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Millennials (smh). Pampered and nurtured by parents, trying to avoid the
mistakes of a previous generation. You are late to graduate, late to marry and
late to have children. You’re even late to find a job (IF you find a job). To
this ever-determined and ambitious generation, we dedicate the series, ‘for’ and
‘by’ the Millennials, who are most likely still living with their parents. It’s
time we spoke about our host of issues, Gen-Y style.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Millennial, you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be angry. Also, if you’re a Millennial
who’s about to hit the job market, I’ve got disappointing news for you. The
Millennial unemployment rate now stands at an &lt;a href=&quot;https://americansforprosperity.org/?utm_source=GO&amp;amp;utm_medium=banner&amp;amp;utm_campaign=redirect&amp;amp;utm_content=main&quot;&gt;astounding
12.8%&lt;/a&gt;,
dwarfing the US national average. Furthermore, if you are a Millennial who has
gone through the past decade unemployed or not, you have also had to endure the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic&quot;&gt;biggest financial
disaster&lt;/a&gt; of the past
half-century, so kudos to you for sticking around and having a firsthand account
of the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were robbed, I tell you. The Millennials were supposed to be the ‘greatest
generation’ yet, the most technologically advanced and by far the most educated
generation ever. We were expected to come in and revolutionise the industry, do
away with the old-fashioned and bear the torch of progress. Well, so much for
trying. We have still not cracked into the industry as smoothly as we would have
wanted. Employers are unsatisfied with our over-expectant attitudes (Note: most
of them being baby-boomers, the slackers of Generation X never made it).
Overall, it has been a struggle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, we are hard to please, overconfident and maybe a tad bit narcissistic.
We dream too much about having it all, without taking our daily dose of reality.
Flashy cars, jewellery, big condos, champagne and caviar. Well, that’s what was
sold to us ever since we got on to &lt;em&gt;MTV&lt;/em&gt; or were young enough to watch
television. We also focus too much on ourselves, often losing track of the &lt;em&gt;‘Big
Picture’.&lt;/em&gt; But we never had to answer the call of the GI generation or the
rallying cry of growth and economic development in the 80’s and 90’s. How often
were you taught to think as a generation, and not as individuals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what, one thing is for sure. The Millennial Generation or Gen-Y as it
is called, is the most highly educated generation to date, and we are definitely
proud of it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/03/16/how-millennials-compare-with-their-grandparents/ft_millennials-education_031715/&quot;&gt;Pew Research
Center&lt;/a&gt;
recently conducted a study showing that 21% and 27% of men and women (aged
18-33) had a college degree, as compared to the Baby Boomers (17% and 14%) and
Generation X (18% and 20%). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Oh, what do I hear? We aren’t learning interpersonal and communication skills?
Really?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True adulthood only hits us when we realize that these numbers do not mean
anything to the people hiring out there. They say we lack team building and the
ability to communicate effectively, and are more adept at theoretical knowledge
than actual applicable skills. Which in essence is saying that our school and
college education did not really help us at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, that just rubs us off the wrong way, especially with how
increasingly expensive university education has become, with ballooning student
debt plaguing much of the Western world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If the employer is just having a problem with me and my ways, then guess what,
I quit!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//lalalala.gif&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there lies another innate flaw deep within us. Maybe, it is
because a lot of us are still young and haven’t grown out of the habit of
denial. But for many, it is very hard for us to come to terms with our
shortcomings. Much too often we will just dismiss them, or much worse, put the
blame on the employer. But as we all know, that’s just a quicker way to get the
boot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to make up ground, and reach our expectations (sky high!), we will
have to adjust to the ways of the world and not be so adamant as we strive to
perfection. But why ‘perfection’? Why are we so obsessed with getting it right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//millennials1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies with the world that has been built by the last generation to
earn the ‘greatest’ title before us: the baby boomers. As baby boomers emerged
from childhood, they soon had a very jolting experience into the foray of the
professional worker. Their journey into adulthood was not as long and smoothed
out as ours. Most of them emerged from the growing middle class, at a time when
countries all across the world were engaged in a GDP scoring competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, most of this generation were thrust directly into the workforce and found
a way to sustain themselves, thanks to their resilient nature. They ended up
earning far more than their parents, a trend which had been continuing since the
1900’s. Later on in life, most of them ended up giving birth to Generation X as
well as the Millennials. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it seems like the buck stops here, as the Millennials are suited to be the
first generation to earn &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; than their parents. It is not a surprise that
rising difficulties to secure a job coupling with employment opportunities
bottoming out post the Great Recession have led to employment protests
throughout Europe, the USA and Asia. And although Millennials are believed to be
far more open-minded and tolerant, the dire circumstances have led to growing
support for right-wing politics in many European and South Asian nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The super-saturated job market has lead to increasingly weird paradoxes. Here’s
one story from &lt;em&gt;The Huffington Post&lt;/em&gt;, which could be one of many:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“I was literally paying to work,” says Elena, a 29-year-old dietician in Texas.
As part of her master’s degree, she was required to do a yearlong “internship”
in a hospital. It was supposed to be training, but she says she worked the same
hours and did the same tasks as paid staffers. “I took out an extra \$20,000 in
student loans to pay tuition for the year I was working for free,” she says.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse yet, with the increase of contractor companies which deal especially in
security, storage and inventory management, or housekeeping activities, the
future of low-income workers is further at risk. Take the example of Mr Joe, the
security guard at the mall, who is actually signed to a contractor that has
inked a deal with the mall. In this way, the mall just has to pay the contractor
and not the individual person who is doing the job. This cuts out a lot of costs
including any form of pension or benefits. Of course, that goes out of Mr Joe’s
pocket. And out goes any form of career advancement either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Princeton-LSE grad Michael Lewis made a fortune and a legacy out of his book,
&lt;em&gt;Liar’s Poker&lt;/em&gt;, which details the rise of Lewie Ranieri and his team of traders
who made big money at Salomon Brothers back in the late-80’s. In the book he
often spoke of back office workers, including people who worked the fax and
xerox machines, later trying their hand at trading for the company after slowly
rising through the ranks over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, thanks to him for documenting another list of practices that went out the
window during the Financial Crisis. You can wave goodbye to that sort of career
mobility in the 21st century. After all, the Great Crash of 2008 was all about
under-skilled people working over-skilled jobs. Look at where we have arrived
now with the current wave of Millennial underemployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because of things like these that we fear a slip up so much, even a little
one, that could send us hurtling down the tunnel of underemployment,
unemployment, and at last, poverty. No, no, don’t laugh, this is serious. You
might not have gotten out of your post-sack funk by the time you realise that
you have fallen below the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sanford.duke.edu/people/faculty/krishna-anirudh&quot;&gt;Anirudh Krishna&lt;/a&gt;, a
professor at Duke University, has documented over 1,000 cases of people who fell
into poverty, and only some of whom managed to escape it. He conducted his
search throughout India and Kenya, and revealed that poverty arises from a
series of mishaps. One broken leg, one lost job, one sick family member and you
find yourself below the line. And it is this chance of slipping (literally),
coupled with humongous college and healthcare costs, that force us Millennials
to hope against hope to strive for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inverse.com/article/53091-millennials-largest-ever-perfectionism-study&quot;&gt;perfection at every living
moment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, here we stand at the brink of a period of flux and change. Our
generation’s defining moment has come and gone in 2008, we are just afraid
another one might &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2019/06/04/next-recession-2020-predictions/&quot;&gt;come along too
soon&lt;/a&gt;. We might
well be the first generation in decades to earn less than our parents. We will
delay our marriages as well as moving out of home. Yes, buying a home now is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://globalnews.ca/news/3230146/numbers-show-its-harder-for-millennials-to-buy-a-home-than-it-was-for-their-parents/&quot;&gt;exponentially
tougher&lt;/a&gt;
than 30 years ago. Deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/jan/05/perfectionism-mental-health-millennial-social-media&quot;&gt;a
problem&lt;/a&gt;
with that? We don’t, we have no choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the future (FML).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shohan Mukherjee</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Millennials (smh). Pampered and nurtured by parents, trying to avoid the mistakes of a previous generation. You are late to graduate, late to marry and late to have children. You’re even late to find a job (IF you find a job). To this ever-determined and ambitious generation, we dedicate the series, ‘for’ and ‘by’ the Millennials, who are most likely still living with their parents. It’s time we spoke about our host of issues, Gen-Y style. If you are a Millennial, you should be angry. Also, if you’re a Millennial who’s about to hit the job market, I’ve got disappointing news for you. The Millennial unemployment rate now stands at an astounding 12.8%, dwarfing the US national average. Furthermore, if you are a Millennial who has gone through the past decade unemployed or not, you have also had to endure the biggest financial disaster of the past half-century, so kudos to you for sticking around and having a firsthand account of the experience. We were robbed, I tell you. The Millennials were supposed to be the ‘greatest generation’ yet, the most technologically advanced and by far the most educated generation ever. We were expected to come in and revolutionise the industry, do away with the old-fashioned and bear the torch of progress. Well, so much for trying. We have still not cracked into the industry as smoothly as we would have wanted. Employers are unsatisfied with our over-expectant attitudes (Note: most of them being baby-boomers, the slackers of Generation X never made it). Overall, it has been a struggle.  Alright, we are hard to please, overconfident and maybe a tad bit narcissistic. We dream too much about having it all, without taking our daily dose of reality. Flashy cars, jewellery, big condos, champagne and caviar. Well, that’s what was sold to us ever since we got on to MTV or were young enough to watch television. We also focus too much on ourselves, often losing track of the ‘Big Picture’. But we never had to answer the call of the GI generation or the rallying cry of growth and economic development in the 80’s and 90’s. How often were you taught to think as a generation, and not as individuals? No matter what, one thing is for sure. The Millennial Generation or Gen-Y as it is called, is the most highly educated generation to date, and we are definitely proud of it. The Pew Research Center recently conducted a study showing that 21% and 27% of men and women (aged 18-33) had a college degree, as compared to the Baby Boomers (17% and 14%) and Generation X (18% and 20%).  “Oh, what do I hear? We aren’t learning interpersonal and communication skills? Really?” True adulthood only hits us when we realize that these numbers do not mean anything to the people hiring out there. They say we lack team building and the ability to communicate effectively, and are more adept at theoretical knowledge than actual applicable skills. Which in essence is saying that our school and college education did not really help us at all. To be honest, that just rubs us off the wrong way, especially with how increasingly expensive university education has become, with ballooning student debt plaguing much of the Western world.  “If the employer is just having a problem with me and my ways, then guess what, I quit!” Unfortunately, there lies another innate flaw deep within us. Maybe, it is because a lot of us are still young and haven’t grown out of the habit of denial. But for many, it is very hard for us to come to terms with our shortcomings. Much too often we will just dismiss them, or much worse, put the blame on the employer. But as we all know, that’s just a quicker way to get the boot! If we are to make up ground, and reach our expectations (sky high!), we will have to adjust to the ways of the world and not be so adamant as we strive to perfection. But why ‘perfection’? Why are we so obsessed with getting it right? The answer lies with the world that has been built by the last generation to earn the ‘greatest’ title before us: the baby boomers. As baby boomers emerged from childhood, they soon had a very jolting experience into the foray of the professional worker. Their journey into adulthood was not as long and smoothed out as ours. Most of them emerged from the growing middle class, at a time when countries all across the world were engaged in a GDP scoring competition.  Thus, most of this generation were thrust directly into the workforce and found a way to sustain themselves, thanks to their resilient nature. They ended up earning far more than their parents, a trend which had been continuing since the 1900’s. Later on in life, most of them ended up giving birth to Generation X as well as the Millennials.  But it seems like the buck stops here, as the Millennials are suited to be the first generation to earn less than their parents. It is not a surprise that rising difficulties to secure a job coupling with employment opportunities bottoming out post the Great Recession have led to employment protests throughout Europe, the USA and Asia. And although Millennials are believed to be far more open-minded and tolerant, the dire circumstances have led to growing support for right-wing politics in many European and South Asian nations. The super-saturated job market has lead to increasingly weird paradoxes. Here’s one story from The Huffington Post, which could be one of many: “I was literally paying to work,” says Elena, a 29-year-old dietician in Texas. As part of her master’s degree, she was required to do a yearlong “internship” in a hospital. It was supposed to be training, but she says she worked the same hours and did the same tasks as paid staffers. “I took out an extra \$20,000 in student loans to pay tuition for the year I was working for free,” she says. Worse yet, with the increase of contractor companies which deal especially in security, storage and inventory management, or housekeeping activities, the future of low-income workers is further at risk. Take the example of Mr Joe, the security guard at the mall, who is actually signed to a contractor that has inked a deal with the mall. In this way, the mall just has to pay the contractor and not the individual person who is doing the job. This cuts out a lot of costs including any form of pension or benefits. Of course, that goes out of Mr Joe’s pocket. And out goes any form of career advancement either. Princeton-LSE grad Michael Lewis made a fortune and a legacy out of his book, Liar’s Poker, which details the rise of Lewie Ranieri and his team of traders who made big money at Salomon Brothers back in the late-80’s. In the book he often spoke of back office workers, including people who worked the fax and xerox machines, later trying their hand at trading for the company after slowly rising through the ranks over the years.  Well, thanks to him for documenting another list of practices that went out the window during the Financial Crisis. You can wave goodbye to that sort of career mobility in the 21st century. After all, the Great Crash of 2008 was all about under-skilled people working over-skilled jobs. Look at where we have arrived now with the current wave of Millennial underemployment. It is because of things like these that we fear a slip up so much, even a little one, that could send us hurtling down the tunnel of underemployment, unemployment, and at last, poverty. No, no, don’t laugh, this is serious. You might not have gotten out of your post-sack funk by the time you realise that you have fallen below the line. Anirudh Krishna, a professor at Duke University, has documented over 1,000 cases of people who fell into poverty, and only some of whom managed to escape it. He conducted his search throughout India and Kenya, and revealed that poverty arises from a series of mishaps. One broken leg, one lost job, one sick family member and you find yourself below the line. And it is this chance of slipping (literally), coupled with humongous college and healthcare costs, that force us Millennials to hope against hope to strive for perfection at every living moment. Thus, here we stand at the brink of a period of flux and change. Our generation’s defining moment has come and gone in 2008, we are just afraid another one might come along too soon. We might well be the first generation in decades to earn less than our parents. We will delay our marriages as well as moving out of home. Yes, buying a home now is exponentially tougher than 30 years ago. Deal with it. And you have a problem with that? We don’t, we have no choice.  Welcome to the future (FML).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Turkish Diaries</title><link href="/Turkish-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turkish Diaries" /><published>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</updated><id>/Turkish-Diaries</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Turkish-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that
made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My
initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a
greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about
Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I
would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have
decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to
enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey.
Nothing more and nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a
journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of
twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums,
palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional
Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion
about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the
population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity
and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era
while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle
ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two
wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of
Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and
Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the
same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine
surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and
modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had
against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion.
There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me
to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional
dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and
behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western
attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey,
from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more
than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their
body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I
remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at
night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India.
Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in
Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking
does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big
deal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’
for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye
Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the
history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said
that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get
distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the
point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated
argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want
to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This
incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish
Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative
because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to
the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is
considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation,
per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of
Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turkey&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male-Female percentage of population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;49.1% - 50.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;51.8% - 48.2%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population density&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;104.5 people/sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;415.63 people/ sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literacy Rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;95.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;74.04%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;98%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Female literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;92%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;64.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality of Life Index (Rank)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;44/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;52/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population living in Urban areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;70%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;33%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; World Population Review, 2019&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the
above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me
to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the
internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my
eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the
articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political
instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was
distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232
injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of
Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor
boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the
long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the
&lt;em&gt;Women in Statistics 2017&lt;/em&gt; report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years
of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the
confidence I had in Turkish Islam. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip
Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more
conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to
raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded
religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular,
it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim
identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in
the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from
2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country.
However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his
focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that
the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and
make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by
the great Atatürk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger
generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an
increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people
calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018.
People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from
77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely
registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic
nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under
President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was
Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and
embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the
AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it
continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I
would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country
adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage.
There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey. Nothing more and nothing less. Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums, palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people.  It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion. There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey, from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India. Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big deal.   There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’ for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage.  To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation, per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India: &amp;nbsp; Turkey India Male-Female percentage of population 49.1% - 50.9% 51.8% - 48.2% Population density 104.5 people/sq km 415.63 people/ sq km Literacy Rate 95.6% 74.04% Male literacy rate 98% 80.9% Female literacy rate 92% 64.6% Quality of Life Index (Rank) 44/70 52/70 Population living in Urban areas 70% 33% Source: World Population Review, 2019 In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation. My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232 injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the Women in Statistics 2017 report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the confidence I had in Turkish Islam.  Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular, it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from 2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country. However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by the great Atatürk.  These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018. People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from 77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively.  Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage. There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West</title><link href="/The-Fall-of-Religion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West" /><published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Fall-of-Religion</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Fall-of-Religion">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this happening? Why are young people increasingly disassociating themselves from organised religion, especially in what can only be fittingly described as a post-Christian society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four main reasons which I put forward, all of which can be summed up in a single sentence: &lt;strong&gt;Christianity – and, especially, Catholicism - has lost its credibility in the minds of our youth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1: The Dominant Historical Narrative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one of us has heard it sometime or the other. The popular narrative runs thus: human society began well and reached summits of excellence and achievement, especially in the classical age. But when Christianity came, all that progress and achievement, as well as the scientific impulse, came to an end and was effectively destroyed. For centuries, the West was embroiled in a quagmire of oppressive feudalism and religious intolerance, in which free-thinkers were labelled heretics and persecuted fiercely. This was called the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt;, and rightly so, because human civilisation was truly held in captivity in the darkness of religious bigotry and superstition. All of this was the case, until the time of the Renaissance and the Enlightenment when, finally, we were able to break free of the chains of theocracy and emerge into the bright new world, to build our future for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is how countless millennials understand the Medieval period. It is certainly the way history is taught in our schools, and thus the way many millennials understand this era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added to this is the stigma of the Crusades and the Inquisitions, both of which are believed to be butcheries of human life and liberty based on religious (and especially Catholic) dogmatism and fanaticism. Fresh in the mind of many of our fellow millennials is the Galileo Affair, in which – it is believed – the geocentric Catholics tried to murder the heliocentric Galileo for the crime of trying to think rationally and not superstitiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this narrative, however, is myopic, and fails to take into account the various other factors which were at play. But, unfortunately for people like me, many of my fellow millennials believe this to be the Gospel truth. And naturally, it has distanced them from a religion which, they are convinced, is responsible for stifling human civilisation and progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2: The Widening Gap Between the Jesus of History and the Christ of Faith&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Brown is one of the most popular fiction authors in the world today. I have had the chance of reading parts of his books, and have found his style to be most engaging. However, Brown is more than your average thriller writer. Thanks to books like &lt;em&gt;The Da Vinci Code&lt;/em&gt;, Brown has managed to bring the ‘Lost Gospels’ to the forefront of public discourse. And boy, has it fired the imagination of the masses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What people like Brown have managed to do is convince the populace – and especially the youth – that there is big difference between the Jesus of Catholicism and the actual Jesus whom we read about in works like the Gospel of Peter and Phillip, for example. He has also managed to alert people regarding the issue of the Biblical canon; why are these four Gospels part of the Bible and not others? Why has the Church chosen to only highlight these particular narratives and declare others heretical?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way information is put out in books such as these has convinced countless many that in the very early history of Christianity, there emerged a power-hungry faction which sought to glorify their own theology at the expense of others. We are told that there was not one but several ‘Christianities’ in the beginning. But one faction – which today exists as the Catholic Church – gained ascendancy and, with quite a bit of patronage from Romam Emperor Constantine, persecuted the other factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds to the impression that today’s youth already has regarding the Christian faith and leaves them with a deep distrust towards anything related to Catholicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3: The Rise of Philosophical Naturalism and Postmodern Nihilism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone looks at the world through a set of lenses. We all operate with basic metaphysical and epistemological presuppositions. However, in recent times, especially in universities, a particular philosophical perspective has been put forward vociferously, and other points of view have largely been isolated and marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for a while, was an undergraduate philosophy student at a well-respected university in India. And what I encountered from my professors was not a careful treatment of the various opposing perspectives but rather open and brazen bias, especially when it came to the philosophy of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What young undergraduates are consistently taught is that the arguments for the existence of God – as put forward by people like Augustine, Aquinas, Leibniz and others – are all extremely poor and fallacious bits of reasoning which can be so easily debunked that one wonders how such eminent men came to such bizarre conclusions. We are also told that these people were motivated by their own personal religious beliefs, and sought to back them up the best they could. What remained was a set of arguments that would only convince people who already had faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is the dominant narrative in philosophical academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And young philosophers usually accept this without question, without delving deeper into the works of Augustine and Aquinas to see if this is indeed true. Most of them don’t bother to later study the philosophy of religion, but rather end up specialising in other fields. And so what they uncritically accept as true in their early years, they end up carrying throughout life. And it is in this way that a consistent naturalist philosophical narrative has been built up over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this has led our young people to be extremely skeptical of any supernatural claims and has, therefore, led them to the conclusion that this world is all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting development happening simultaneously is the rise of postmodernism. This is entirely different from the dogmatic atheism I have just described. Rather, this is a dogmatic rejection of all dogmatism, an objective denial of all objectivity. It is a position some might characterise as absurd, but this appellation is readily embraced by some of its vociferous proponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postmodernism is basically summed up in three maxims: “Truth is what you make of it. Morality is what you shape of it. God is Who you think He/She/It is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this attitude is the product of the younger generation’s exposure to other cultures, viewpoints and ways of thinking. Young people see heated debates in which scholars on both sides put forward their cases and state their opinions, each backing themselves up with copious argumentation. They see different religions and ways of life, entirely different from the ones they had been exposed to. And having no strong rational grounds to support the religion of their upbringing, they naturally come to the conclusion that ‘man is the measure of all things’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This understanding of life is indeed very attractive since it promises a kind of godhood. One is free to shape one’s reality and one’s destiny as one sees it. One is free to identify as whatever one pleases and be whoever one wishes to be. Above all, one is liberated from the shackles of dogmatism, free to believe whatever they wish to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, anyone addicted to this euphoria of freedom will find organised religion, with all its creeds and ancient affirmations, very unattractive indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4: The Transformation of Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the most important and significant of all, since it strikes not merely at our intellect but also at our emotions. The cultural elite of the West are working very hard to change and transform culture. They do this through books, films, magazines and mass media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: Imagine that you have grown up in a very conservative society, your parents told you that the right thing to do was to dress modestly, especially in front of the opposite sex. What happens when you are constantly exposed to pictures of men and women in states of partial or complete undress, when you can hardly go to the movies or even switch on a television without coming across some scene or advertisement that is either sexually explicit or has strong sexual themes, that too being performed by men and women who are great artists whom you admire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, your perception is going to shift. You would in all likelihood rather imitate your heroes and role models rather than your parents, in this case. And in all probability, your friends have similar attitudes in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these factors come together and compound in such a way that it is possible to change views about something as fundamental as human sexuality across the course of a generation! Changing one’s views on sexual ethics is nothing more and nothing less than a paradigm shift. Instead of being something that is sacred and to be enjoyed within the context of marriage in a reproductively responsible manner, young people are offered the alluring option of ‘sex with no strings attached’. Rather than being the self-giving expression of commitment and love between two spouses (as Christians have traditionally believed), it has become a ‘casual’ affair. It is, therefore, no wonder that our young people are losing their faith in traditional Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular music has played an inestimable role in detaching young people from the Christian faith. Young people see singers who are clearly extraordinarily talented, beloved by all their friends and peer groups, and who sing songs that contain themes that are clearly contrary to Christian faith and morals, in more ways than one. Naturally, over time, one comes to favour one’s friend groups rather than one’s parents and one begins to side with the more secularising culture rather than traditional ways of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I am a millennial myself. But I am not your average millennial. In fact, I am a convert to the Catholic Church, having come from a liberal Hindu background myself. I am the black sheep, so to speak, of this modern and enlightened generation. What causes me to remain traditional and Catholic? Why don’t I simply join the great secular bus and enjoy all the many benefits its offers? Why do I remain in the shadows and willingly disassociate myself from much of the modern world and even isolate myself, at times, enjoying but a few friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons are endless, but I will summarise it in a few brief points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is my firmest conviction that the conventional narrative about the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt; is thoroughly erroneous, and in fact holds little water in academic circles, thank God. This view of the Medieval Church as an oppressive, science-persecuting religion has been increasingly discredited in modern times, not least by the excellent work of the Pulitzer-Prize winning Rodney Stark who, although himself a non-Catholic, has taken it upon himself to work towards exonerating the Catholic Church from baseless myths and lies, as can be seen in his work &lt;em&gt;Bearing False Witness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this idea that the Church persecuted scientists fails to take into account the immense contributions the Church made to science, in the Middle Ages and after as well. It is true that Galileo was persecuted – on charges of heresy. But what is left unmentioned is that Copernicus’s heliocentrism fascinated the Pope of his time, who spoke highly of him on numerous occasions. What is also conveniently left out is the devoutly Christian spirit of the countless intellectuals across the course of history who laid the foundations of modern science, believing that their study and analysis of the natural world was a kind of worship of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we then left with? Is there no future for religion in the West?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion will survive. The Church will always be there in the West, even if it is weakened and marginalised. Popular culture and the mass media already brand the Christian faith as regressive. It is perhaps only a matter of time before popular opinion turns into political legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Church will survive. It always has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, it has found a new homeland. As the West continues to go down this slippery slope and continues to schism itself from its Christian roots, the great African continent has already opened its arms wide open, in welcome of the Gospel and the Church.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?</title><link href="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?" /><published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough">&lt;p&gt;The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexual economy of the world seems to be in danger. Of course, this conclusion is met with evidence from surveys done on American grounds and on Americans but there seems to lie an innate truth to it. &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;’s December cover story threw light on this. I’m sure Kate Julian’s extensive research on the topic and terming of the phenomenon ‘Sexual Recession’ brought her just as much hate as it did fame, but from what I could procure, she left no page unturned, except the veil of obvious bias, but we’ll come to that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a full tell-all, supported by a General Social Survey (GSS) in 2016, conducted at the University of Chicago, she lists out reasons behind the recession―the assumed ones, why it occurred in the first place and why this recession is specific to the Millennials. Her article is a long read―heavy with insight and stories from across her social sphere―and, given a choice, I’d award her. Her article shone light upon something that we were all aware of in parts, and albeit she only showed off the parts that worked in her favour, she did make sure that all was listed, with enough to make us not counter her points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Foucault would say, we love talking about sex, we enjoy discussing it not just as a primal need rather as a form of entertainment. Sexuality, he said, was a construct of human discourse. “We convince ourselves that we have never said enough on the subject,” he wrote in his (four-volume) &lt;em&gt;The History of Sexuality&lt;/em&gt;. “It is possible that where sex is concerned, the most long-winded, the most impatient of societies is our own.” Personally, I’d say, few fields of human behaviour—and none more important—are this hard to explain. As something that has been talked about ever so often, from religious scriptures telling us how and when to do it, oh, and of course, when not to, to trilogies earning billions with 1001 pages of ‘teeth-clenchingly good’ sex. We all know of it, but why and how it became the talk of the town, albeit uttered only in hushed tones, is vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned GSS determined that people who are in their early 20s right now are two and a half times as likely to be abstinent as Gen Xers were at the same age. Specifically, between the years 1990 to 2014, the average adult went from having sex 62 times a year to 54 times a year, therefore, the hoola-hoo about the downfall in the Sexual Economy. If I were to meet the ‘spokesperson’ of this Sexual Economy that we all have now been made aware of, I’d only have one word to say: ‘Damn.’ Just so one is kept in the know, it’s not just an American problem. Most countries don’t track their citizens’ sex lives closely. But those that try, mostly the ones who are extremely wealthy, are reporting their own sex delays and declines. One of the most respected sex studies in the world, Britain’s National Survey of Sexual Attitudes and Lifestyles, reported in 2001 that people between the ages of 16 to 44 were having sex more than six times a month, on average. By 2012, the rate had dropped to fewer than five times. Over approximately the same period, Australians in relationships went from having sex around 1.8 times a week to 1.4 times. Finland’s ‘Finsex’ study found declines in frequency of coitus, coupled with increasing rates of masturbation. In the Netherlands, the median age at which people first have intercourse rose from 17.1 in 2012 to 18.6 in 2017, and other types of physical contact also got pushed back, even kissing. In fertility-challenged Japan, which is already in the midst of a demographic crisis and has become something of a case study in the dangers of sexlessness, a third of single people aged 18 to 34 were virgins as of the year 2005; but by 2015, 43% of people reported the same. Japan has been infiltrated by several cultural complexes: Hikikomori (the phenomenon of complete isolation from society) being one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, whatever’s going on here does not seem like a ‘millennial trend’. It really probably pertains to people in their 20s, so younger millennials or Gen-Z. We tend to talk about millennials as if they are some group that just landed here intact, whereas it’s more useful to talk about what it’s like to be a young person, at this point. Not to mention, the fear of a “sex recession” is misdirected. A drop in sexual encounters from 62 to 54 times a year means that the average adult is still having sex more than once a week. Millennials are having to deal with things previous generations haven’t dealt with, and it’s useful to clarify that. As and when I read more about this, I found that people think online connectivity and smartphones have had a dramatic effect on how people’s lives are shaped and their behaviours. That’s probably true for most generational groups, and for the groups that use technology more, that’d be truer. Tinder has only made things easier, so why the lack? My only problem was why 2 and 2 didn’t add up to 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I went digging, and found a &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; article (yes, I went there) and believe me, if &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; makes you believe you’re not having enough sex, &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; will assure you enough for a lifetime, or well, at least a couple of months. The survey research showed a decline in sex mainly among white, middle-aged, married couples, which, of course, is a very, very small bracket to be construed as an entire generation’s problem. Julian’s tone in &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;––listing a myriad of theories to explain the drop, from smartphones to economic instability to Tinder––was cautionary, I’ll give her that. But, news of the so-called “sex recession” provoked reactions across the internet, from &lt;em&gt;Vox&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Vice&lt;/em&gt;—not to mention the plethora of comments which turned it into madness with no method. Companies have picked up on this, more researches are being based on the same and while all that is great, there’s a problem that doesn’t exist and is yet being worked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are different now; sex is different now. Dictionaries may still consider sex to be vaginal penetration, but to us—it may be anything from second base to the seventh one. Sexuality is explored more. People are more aware of what it is that they want, there’s more to it than just genitals having a meet and greet, pleasure plays a huge role in how sex is seen. I would highly recommend that people read Julian’s article and all the reasons she gives for us to not be having enough sex: from stress to bad, painful encounters, but with a grain of salt. We may be failing to do a gazillion more things, but for once, I can attest sex is something we’re doing a bang-up job of (all puns intended.) Tinder, Bumble and Grindr have only made it more relevant. Nothing one does to explore it can be wrong, not until someone is harmed. There is no ‘normal’ amount of sex. Worrying about how much sex one’s having—which can increase anxiety, decrease body confidence, and hinder healthy communication—is not good for one’s sex life, either. Ironic, isn’t it? In terms of desired sexual activity, every individual, and every couple is different, including people who identify as asexual. Just the idea of #MeToo challenges the notion that we can measure our sex lives by anything other than our own generational values and self-reported satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fundamental level, I share Julian’s concern when she writes that she “was taken aback by what seemed like heartbreaking changes in the way many people were relating—or not relating—to one another.” This is what we should focus our attention on. It turns out, though, that a small drop in aggregate annual sexual frequency has no demonstrable effect on how couples form and sustain, fulfilling relationships. If people aren’t having sex but they’re doing other things they find fulfilling, that’s great. But if people are not having sex, and wish they were, that’s more of a concern, wouldn’t you say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I have to say is that every generation has its faults counted, every generation has to face things the previous ones didn’t have to endure. While one is yet to see how much more can be done, can be changed or morphed, I am sure that our shapeshifter of a generation won’t be a disappointment. Sex or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It</title><link href="/The-Middle-Income-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It" /><published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Middle-Income-Trap</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Middle-Income-Trap">&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Mahatyohar&lt;/em&gt; (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded
with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by
the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were
perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign.
Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of
6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a
decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which
explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as
compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put
more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have
pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations
can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a
part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could
indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the
National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue
of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He
identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what
the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to
lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per
capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has
become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges
from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the
economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good
industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states
that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with
by the government’s &lt;em&gt;PM Awas Yojana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PM Mudra Yojana&lt;/em&gt; schemes respectively,
it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate
the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re
becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital
development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that
we’re heading into. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation
makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but
then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation.
This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101
nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved
high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily
attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital,
lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is
comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been
exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely
crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being
channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar
to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour
is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages
are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the
current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of
Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of
high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s
demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour
supply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related
expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6%
required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its
restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like
&lt;em&gt;Startup India&lt;/em&gt;, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage
investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture
capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty
valuation of the startups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of
2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will
have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic
convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the
developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like
Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and
efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India,
who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour
and must now bear the consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the
early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers.
Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was
absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South
Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The
global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy
perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing
private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was
the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources
from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than
high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other
professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation.
Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human
capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater
urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic
demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because
becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital
account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently
undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the
politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically
left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive
foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment
destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that
before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations,
for capital is faithful to none.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">While the Mahatyohar (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign. Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of 6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence. Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with by the government’s PM Awas Yojana and PM Mudra Yojana schemes respectively, it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that we’re heading into.  The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation. This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101 nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital, lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy.  Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour supply.  As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6% required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like Startup India, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty valuation of the startups.  An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of 2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India, who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour and must now bear the consequences.  The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers. Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation. Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater urgency. Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations, for capital is faithful to none.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Africa Sees a New Dawn</title><link href="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Africa Sees a New Dawn" /><published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated><id>/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn">&lt;p&gt;As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the
unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger,
the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to
realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the
African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being
ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the
African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver
prosperity to all Africans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and
services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will
bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of
more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In
terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s
largest free trade area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services,
and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member
states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market
improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would
benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would
become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of
which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of
the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually
eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an
economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and
consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes
competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and
thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The
relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit
private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract
foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in
consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By
2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a
combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA
shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the
UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the
potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of
evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study
has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply
by being a member of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive
manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the
goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only
about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries.
Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the
continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The
African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2
billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost
advantage over other nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa
such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the
other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the
countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania,
both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known
to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in
violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan
textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local
markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of
COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for
exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to
repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates
ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their
trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends
on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa,
Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has
assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been
satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the
agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.”
“We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and
entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for
finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium
Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their
place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to
account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a
factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal. 
Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more
price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a
rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and
consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place
in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage
to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do
business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and
technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through
competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country
and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be
dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond
their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in
Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of
scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations.
Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The
country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad,
thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa
is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by
opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and
communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the
vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and
peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the
global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the
process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of
“Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the
agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and
oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger, the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver prosperity to all Africans. AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s largest free trade area. A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services, and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies.  The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By 2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply by being a member of the European Union. The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries. Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2 billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost advantage over other nations.  Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania, both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs. AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa, Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.” “We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal.  Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets. Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations. Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad, thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment. In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of “Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Were Ancient (Egyptian) Times More Modern Than We Think?</title><link href="/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Were Ancient (Egyptian) Times More Modern Than We Think?" /><published>2019-07-02T12:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T12:29:00+00:00</updated><id>/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Egypt gave birth to what later would become known as ‘western civilization’;
long before the greatness of Greece and Rome.”&lt;/em&gt; -John Henrik Clark&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hollywood movies have played their part in creating the notion that the Nile’s
gift was a land riddled with mysterious forms of art, sorcery, murder and
extravagant eye makeup. We all grew up with stories of the beautiful seductress
Cleopatra and the great lands of Egypt ruled by the native Egyptians for
millennia before the Greeks finally arrived. The funny part is this: Cleopatra
probably wasn’t very beautiful (incest was a common practice among the royals
back then, and in the absence of genetic diversity, deformed features like
elongated faces were common among them) and the Egyptians had been ruled by
foreigners like the Ethiopians long before the Ptolemaic dynasty, the last
dynasty of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egypt was a rather modern and ahead-of-its-time kind of a society. This fact
finds reflection in their inscriptions, their rulers, their trade affairs and so
on. Let’s start with their family lives and societal norms. The ancient
Egyptians had their own religion and two of their most important Gods and
Goddesses were Osiris and Isis, a brother-sister duo married to each other
(again, incest was okay). Unlike most religions, wherein the man is portrayed as
dominant and the woman as submissive, Isis, the goddess of magic, was the
dominant one in their duo. In fact, every ruler needed a partner in order to
rule Egypt. Unlike most modern societies, the husband and the wife were at the
same pedestal. All of this is evidenced by inscriptions depicting the husband
and the wife (Pharaoh and Queen) together, even showing them commanding an army
of soldiers (best examples include the inscriptions dating back to the Amarna
period) and coins showing faces of both side by side (from the Ptolemaic
period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ancient Egyptian society, virginity was not a requisite for marriage but
loyalty after marriage was expected. If a couple were to fall out of love, they
could get a divorce; a common enough practice and therefore free of stigma. In
countries like India, even today, people who walk away from their marriages
fearing shaming and ostracisation at the hands of society. Nuclear families
dominated their communities and lineage was traced through both parents’ sides
alike. Both of these bear testimony to the fact that the Egyptian lifestyle was
very different from that of its contemporary civilisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Egyptian inscriptions, it seems unlikely that they ever practised slavery,
once again, contrary to popular belief. The labourers who worked on the pyramids
or the temples were well fed and housed. Their mummified bodies also indicate
that they were natives of the land. They lived close to where they worked and
were even buried there, literally in the shadows of the pyramids- the Pharaoh’s
last resting place (considered to be a great honour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their houses were intriguing too. They had courtyards and separate studios.
Another very common feature was a flat roof, where they often cooked or slept
during hot nights. Ancient folk are not expected to share the ideals of
cleanliness that modern society holds. But lo and behold, the Egyptians had
toilets in their homes and their own systems of drainage and cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of ancient Egypt’s greatest contributions include the &lt;strong&gt;papyrus&lt;/strong&gt;. At one
point, the Egyptians mass produced (handwritten, of course) &lt;em&gt;‘The Book of the
Dead’&lt;/em&gt; to be buried with the mummified bodies of their loved ones. Besides,
Kings and Queens used this ‘paper’ to sign away their declarations and orders
too, a practice, surprisingly similar to the present-day passing of bills.
Drinking beer was a common practice, even among the commoners. Ancient Egypt can
also be credited with the development of several methods of contraception and
various pregnancy tests. The Egyptians valued knowledge a lot and this is
evident from the remains of the great library at Alexandria. We might as well
call Egypt &lt;em&gt;the Land of Inventions&lt;/em&gt; because of the numerous inventions that came
out of this particular ancient culture, some of which revolutionised human life
long before the Renaissance or the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most contemporary civilisations, the Egyptians did not have a calendar
based on the moon’s cycle. Instead, their calendar was based on the Earth’s
revolution around the sun (Turns out Copernicus might have had some help in the
form of ancient inspiration!). These ancient humans had 365 days in a year and
an extra day every four years (Julius Caesar later took this idea to Greece
during Cleopatra’s reign). Sounds very familiar, doesn’t it? Surprisingly
enough, their religion lent support to the science that pervaded their society!
In fact, most of their mythological stories revolve around facts that have been
proven to be scientifically correct. The Egyptians were also pioneers in the
field of astronomy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their architectural brilliance proves the fact that they were great engineers
and mathematicians too. The angle of inclination of the pyramids, the lengths of
their sides and so on, were accurate down to minutes and a couple of inches
respectively. Granite blocks used in the Great Pyramid of Giza’s burial chamber
are cut to perfection and fit into each other such that not even a credit card
can slip in between. The pyramids are spectacles that cannot be explained even
today. Each stone block used in its construction weighs at least a couple of
tonnes and the entire structure rises up to a staggering height of 139 metres.
Did I mention that the Egyptians did not even have the wheel? How the pyramids
were constructed is up for debate. What is undeniable is the fact that they were
masters of the art of building and made structures meant to stand the test of
time unlike any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have either heard or read about the Gods and Goddesses of Egypt. As I
learnt more about their culture and society, I came across something that left
me astonished: monotheism- a very modern ideology and isn’t uncommon today. But,
I guess, Pharaoh Akhenaten and his wife Queen Nefertiti were way ahead of their
times. They devoted all their lives to the worship of a single God- Aten (the
Sun). This religion, however, did not address one major question that had always
plagued the Egyptians: ‘What happens after death?’. This obviously did not sit
very well with the priests and the practice was discarded right after
Akhenaten’s reign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous of ancient Egyptian practices is probably the process of
mummification. The method that they developed was nothing short of genius. They
wanted immortality and in some ways, they did achieve it. We know what they did,
ate and entertained themselves with, just like any other civilisation. But,
here, we also have their bodies; their stories &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; have faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, Egyptian inscriptions were located in Australia. It is undeniable
that their trade flourished. With the advent of the Ptolemaic dynasty (after
Alexander the Great’s invasion), coins were introduced in trade. The second
Pharaoh of this dynasty, Queen Arsinoe introduced coins with her face on them -
she wanted everyone to know who held the reigns. Most rulers were well versed in
several languages and were very diplomatic. Cleopatra is claimed to have been
fluent in around 9 languages. That, however, is not the only shocking thing in
her resume. She was intelligent and trained in alchemy, geography, philosophy
and so on and so forth. She knew chemistry too, in fact, she owned a perfume
factory. To me, it all sounds like capitalism might have had some really ancient
roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a pity that the only thing that we usually care about is whether the
Egyptians were black, how beautiful the pyramids are and how was Cleopatra able
to seduce both Mark Anthony and Julius Caesar, and speculations about how
beautiful she was. The Egyptians accomplished tasks their contemporaries could
only ever dream to accomplish–feats involving mind-boggling architecture,
freakishly modern societal norms, mastery in mathematics, astronomy and art, and
unique practices that would later go on to shape the world. They lived up to
every word they ever wrote or spoke:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What I hate is ignorance, smallness of imagination, the eye that sees no
farther than its own lashes. All things are possible… Who you are is limited
only by who you think you are.”&lt;/em&gt; – Egyptian Book of the Dead&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“Egypt gave birth to what later would become known as ‘western civilization’; long before the greatness of Greece and Rome.” -John Henrik Clark Hollywood movies have played their part in creating the notion that the Nile’s gift was a land riddled with mysterious forms of art, sorcery, murder and extravagant eye makeup. We all grew up with stories of the beautiful seductress Cleopatra and the great lands of Egypt ruled by the native Egyptians for millennia before the Greeks finally arrived. The funny part is this: Cleopatra probably wasn’t very beautiful (incest was a common practice among the royals back then, and in the absence of genetic diversity, deformed features like elongated faces were common among them) and the Egyptians had been ruled by foreigners like the Ethiopians long before the Ptolemaic dynasty, the last dynasty of Egypt. Egypt was a rather modern and ahead-of-its-time kind of a society. This fact finds reflection in their inscriptions, their rulers, their trade affairs and so on. Let’s start with their family lives and societal norms. The ancient Egyptians had their own religion and two of their most important Gods and Goddesses were Osiris and Isis, a brother-sister duo married to each other (again, incest was okay). Unlike most religions, wherein the man is portrayed as dominant and the woman as submissive, Isis, the goddess of magic, was the dominant one in their duo. In fact, every ruler needed a partner in order to rule Egypt. Unlike most modern societies, the husband and the wife were at the same pedestal. All of this is evidenced by inscriptions depicting the husband and the wife (Pharaoh and Queen) together, even showing them commanding an army of soldiers (best examples include the inscriptions dating back to the Amarna period) and coins showing faces of both side by side (from the Ptolemaic period). In ancient Egyptian society, virginity was not a requisite for marriage but loyalty after marriage was expected. If a couple were to fall out of love, they could get a divorce; a common enough practice and therefore free of stigma. In countries like India, even today, people who walk away from their marriages fearing shaming and ostracisation at the hands of society. Nuclear families dominated their communities and lineage was traced through both parents’ sides alike. Both of these bear testimony to the fact that the Egyptian lifestyle was very different from that of its contemporary civilisations. From Egyptian inscriptions, it seems unlikely that they ever practised slavery, once again, contrary to popular belief. The labourers who worked on the pyramids or the temples were well fed and housed. Their mummified bodies also indicate that they were natives of the land. They lived close to where they worked and were even buried there, literally in the shadows of the pyramids- the Pharaoh’s last resting place (considered to be a great honour). Their houses were intriguing too. They had courtyards and separate studios. Another very common feature was a flat roof, where they often cooked or slept during hot nights. Ancient folk are not expected to share the ideals of cleanliness that modern society holds. But lo and behold, the Egyptians had toilets in their homes and their own systems of drainage and cleaning. Some of ancient Egypt’s greatest contributions include the papyrus. At one point, the Egyptians mass produced (handwritten, of course) ‘The Book of the Dead’ to be buried with the mummified bodies of their loved ones. Besides, Kings and Queens used this ‘paper’ to sign away their declarations and orders too, a practice, surprisingly similar to the present-day passing of bills. Drinking beer was a common practice, even among the commoners. Ancient Egypt can also be credited with the development of several methods of contraception and various pregnancy tests. The Egyptians valued knowledge a lot and this is evident from the remains of the great library at Alexandria. We might as well call Egypt the Land of Inventions because of the numerous inventions that came out of this particular ancient culture, some of which revolutionised human life long before the Renaissance or the Industrial Revolution. Unlike most contemporary civilisations, the Egyptians did not have a calendar based on the moon’s cycle. Instead, their calendar was based on the Earth’s revolution around the sun (Turns out Copernicus might have had some help in the form of ancient inspiration!). These ancient humans had 365 days in a year and an extra day every four years (Julius Caesar later took this idea to Greece during Cleopatra’s reign). Sounds very familiar, doesn’t it? Surprisingly enough, their religion lent support to the science that pervaded their society! In fact, most of their mythological stories revolve around facts that have been proven to be scientifically correct. The Egyptians were also pioneers in the field of astronomy! Their architectural brilliance proves the fact that they were great engineers and mathematicians too. The angle of inclination of the pyramids, the lengths of their sides and so on, were accurate down to minutes and a couple of inches respectively. Granite blocks used in the Great Pyramid of Giza’s burial chamber are cut to perfection and fit into each other such that not even a credit card can slip in between. The pyramids are spectacles that cannot be explained even today. Each stone block used in its construction weighs at least a couple of tonnes and the entire structure rises up to a staggering height of 139 metres. Did I mention that the Egyptians did not even have the wheel? How the pyramids were constructed is up for debate. What is undeniable is the fact that they were masters of the art of building and made structures meant to stand the test of time unlike any other. We all have either heard or read about the Gods and Goddesses of Egypt. As I learnt more about their culture and society, I came across something that left me astonished: monotheism- a very modern ideology and isn’t uncommon today. But, I guess, Pharaoh Akhenaten and his wife Queen Nefertiti were way ahead of their times. They devoted all their lives to the worship of a single God- Aten (the Sun). This religion, however, did not address one major question that had always plagued the Egyptians: ‘What happens after death?’. This obviously did not sit very well with the priests and the practice was discarded right after Akhenaten’s reign. The most famous of ancient Egyptian practices is probably the process of mummification. The method that they developed was nothing short of genius. They wanted immortality and in some ways, they did achieve it. We know what they did, ate and entertained themselves with, just like any other civilisation. But, here, we also have their bodies; their stories literally have faces. Very recently, Egyptian inscriptions were located in Australia. It is undeniable that their trade flourished. With the advent of the Ptolemaic dynasty (after Alexander the Great’s invasion), coins were introduced in trade. The second Pharaoh of this dynasty, Queen Arsinoe introduced coins with her face on them - she wanted everyone to know who held the reigns. Most rulers were well versed in several languages and were very diplomatic. Cleopatra is claimed to have been fluent in around 9 languages. That, however, is not the only shocking thing in her resume. She was intelligent and trained in alchemy, geography, philosophy and so on and so forth. She knew chemistry too, in fact, she owned a perfume factory. To me, it all sounds like capitalism might have had some really ancient roots. It’s a pity that the only thing that we usually care about is whether the Egyptians were black, how beautiful the pyramids are and how was Cleopatra able to seduce both Mark Anthony and Julius Caesar, and speculations about how beautiful she was. The Egyptians accomplished tasks their contemporaries could only ever dream to accomplish–feats involving mind-boggling architecture, freakishly modern societal norms, mastery in mathematics, astronomy and art, and unique practices that would later go on to shape the world. They lived up to every word they ever wrote or spoke: “What I hate is ignorance, smallness of imagination, the eye that sees no farther than its own lashes. All things are possible… Who you are is limited only by who you think you are.” – Egyptian Book of the Dead</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Voting Rights for Prisoners: A Conundrum</title><link href="/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voting Rights for Prisoners: A Conundrum" /><published>2019-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners">&lt;p&gt;As 2020 US Presidential election campaigning is in full swing, heated debates on contentious issues have taken the centre stage. Among these is the issue of voting rights for incarcerated citizens during their prison terms. A staunch supporter of voting rights for prisoners is Vermont Senator Bernie Sanders. In a CNN town hall on April 22, Bernie supported the right to vote to include even the Boston Marathon bomber Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, who was sentenced to death in July 2015. Sanders believes that the commission of any crime or horrific act should not debar a citizen from his right to vote. To quote him, “I think the right to vote is inherent to our democracy. Yes, even for terrible people because once you start chipping away … you’re running down a slippery slope,” Sanders said, attracting a strong rebuttal from the Republicans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Outlier&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 6.1 million people in the United States have lost their voting rights as a result of felony convictions. The United States is an outlier, compared to many nations across the world where the voting rights of prisoners are protected. Twenty-six European countries protect the voting rights of prisoners who are convicted for non-violent crimes such as drunk driving, possession of a small amount of marijuana or fleeing the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eighteen countries grant this fundamental right even in case of murder convictions. When Britain imposed a blanket ban on voting in 2005, the European Court of Human Rights ruled this to be a grave violation of human rights. Canada, South Africa and Kenya also grant voting rights to their felons. During the Presidential elections in North Macedonia, ballots were brought from prisoner’s home voting district in thirteen prisons of the country. Ahead of the recent referendum, election officers initiated a program to renew expired voting documents of the incarcerated people. In Bosnia and Herzegovina, prisoners convicted for crimes unrelated to the Bosnian War have the right to vote. In Germany, Norway and Portugal, only those convicted for crimes that target the state or democratic order, like terrorism or political violence, are disenfranchised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vermont and Maine are the only two states that allow prisoners to vote in the United States. Twenty-six American states stripped this right away from former prisoners for a lifetime. Joining the bandwagon are Armenia and Chile, where prisoners lost their voting rights. In Belgium, prisoners with sentences longer than seven years are not allowed to vote. In India, prisoners and those under preventive detention lose their voting rights under Section 62(5) of The Representation of People Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Reflection of Racism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A socio-political dimension to the voting rights debate is the political representation of the black community in America, given the disproportionate incarceration of black people in the country. In the colonial era of America, the concept of “civil death” was prevalent. It was believed that some bad actions render a person ineffective in utilising his civil rights. A racial twist to the story came following the Jim Crow laws, enacted in the late 19th and early 20th century. Black Codes were enacted in the South following the Civil War to constrain rights of black people, criminalising disobedience and “disrespect to the employer”. The subjectivity left it to the discretion of the authorities and enforcement targeted and criminalised the black community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most blacks lived in the South and were effectively disenfranchised following the Jim Crow laws. Analysts believe that the 1912 Presidential election was steeply slanted against the interests of the Black Americans. The brunt of poll taxes and literacy requirements was borne by the poor and illiterate Americans (a large proportion belonged to the black community), while European Americans were exempted from meeting these requirements. Literacy testing clauses were consciously used to single out Black Americans in Virginia, Oklahoma and Florida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Barack Obama said at an NAACP convention in 2015, “African-Americans are more likely to be arrested. They are more likely to be sentenced to more time for the same crime.” There were 5.1 times more Black prisoners than white incarcerated in state prisons. According to Ashley Nellis, a senior research analyst with the Sentencing Project, the disparity between black and white felons was more than ten times in five states. New Jersey had the highest disparity, with twelve black people to one in its prison system. This was followed by Wisconsin, Iowa, Minnesota, and Vermont. Oklahoma had 2,625 black inmates per one hundred thousand residents, with only 7.7% of the population being black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the sheer population of black felons, the disenfranchisement results in skewed participation of the community in the elections. This takes a toll on all aspects of the electoral process: from the inclusion of their demands in the agenda to allowing leaders from the community to run for positions. This hampers the socio-political empowerment of the community, an objective that has not been accomplished since the Civil Rights Movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting: A Fundamental Right&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamental rights, by definition, are not meant to expire on the commission of a crime. Other than for crimes related to terrorism and civil strife, depriving the citizen of his right to vote should be an exception and not a norm. Universal suffrage is meant to be universal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question at the heart of the debate is: What is the purpose of a prison? Is it meant to be a punishment which includes restriction of rights, or a place for repentance and rehabilitation? Prisons should be a place for reeducation and providing the inmates with skills and values to reintegrate with society upon their release. Giving them voting rights and making them realise the fundamental rights as well as duties is an important component of the reeducation drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silver Lining&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Florida voted for a constitutional amendment to end the policy of permanent disenfranchisement of felons. The supermajority voting for the motion helped to restore the voting rights of 1.5 million convicted felons. The District of Columbia and fifteen other states joined the bandwagon to end this draconian policy. Those on parole or probation were allowed to vote in New York. With such examples in the neighborhood, the process of rethinking about prisoner rights has begun in the other states as well. This would go a long way in achieving Martin Luther King’s vision of a racially just society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gurleen Kaur</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">As 2020 US Presidential election campaigning is in full swing, heated debates on contentious issues have taken the centre stage. Among these is the issue of voting rights for incarcerated citizens during their prison terms. A staunch supporter of voting rights for prisoners is Vermont Senator Bernie Sanders. In a CNN town hall on April 22, Bernie supported the right to vote to include even the Boston Marathon bomber Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, who was sentenced to death in July 2015. Sanders believes that the commission of any crime or horrific act should not debar a citizen from his right to vote. To quote him, “I think the right to vote is inherent to our democracy. Yes, even for terrible people because once you start chipping away … you’re running down a slippery slope,” Sanders said, attracting a strong rebuttal from the Republicans.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Great Indian Intercourse</title><link href="/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great Indian Intercourse" /><published>2019-06-28T21:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-28T21:29:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse">&lt;p&gt;Of the many things that India, as a subcontinent, has achieved or done, such as
overpopulation, growing disparity between economic classes and the caste system,
probably one of the greatest would be the writing of the &lt;em&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/em&gt;; and even
though we have, as a nation, owned up to most of the country’s achievements,
even the more bizarre ones such as child marriage, in case of sex we tend to
walk right by it without even a cursory glance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might argue that such prudish behaviour is a result of uneven distribution
of cultural capital, but I believe that’s an oxymoron in itself. I’m not here to
talk about how such prudence came into being in Indian culture – that is a topic
for another day. What I would like to draw attention to is the product of such
prudence taking shape in the form of coyness surrounding the topic of sex in
Indian society. Now, if you belong to an extremely liberal Indian family or
reside in the West, you’re probably not aware of the coyness I speak of. But we
plebs have felt it right from our childhood, when our mothers would, almost in a
frenzy, change the channel if we accidentally tuned into some English movie
channel with a couple kissing on the screen. This particular act of maternal
care and horror brought about two things; firstly, a curiosity about the most
basic and prevalent of human natures that would sooner or later manifest into
action, and secondly, through this suppression, we were being conditioned into
suppressing our very understanding of ourselves. If we do not properly accept
and understand the psychology underlying sex and sexuality we become blunt to
our very existence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of things that we, as a society, do are directly or indirectly inspired by
sex. We were taught, rather preached with sincerity that English films are a
matter of disgrace and can bring &lt;em&gt;Mata’s&lt;/em&gt; (the Hindu Mother Goddess’) curse upon
us. Problems started for my mother when Indian advertisements stared getting
liberal with sex as well. She was then left with little choice but to accept her
defeat, while commenting on how Indian culture was getting ‘corrupted’. As is
the norm in India, my parents never talked about sex in front of me, and as I
grew up they started keeping their bedroom door open most of the time, except at
night, so as to not arouse any suspicion in their growing child’s mind! And this
isn’t just the case with families that have children, rather with any family
where there are people besides the couple live. We are a sex hungry nation, lewd
staring in buses and public places are a testimony to that, and yet we continue
with this all-prevailing diktat of silence no matter where we go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this diktat has a silver lining to it and we must not discount it. As sex
has grown to be the giant &lt;strong&gt;taboo&lt;/strong&gt; of Indian society, it has become all the
more &lt;strong&gt;pleasurable&lt;/strong&gt; to consume. Coyness has turned out to be more of a boon
than a bane for most couples around the nation and for one simple reason:
&lt;em&gt;forbidden fruit tastes better&lt;/em&gt;. Society, as a whole, sees sex as immoral. No
one quite imagines that the couple they randomly passed by on the street
actually has sex or to be more precise, one cannot picture them doing it. What
this does psychologically is that it makes one’s intimacy with their partner
ever so special. They choose to remain oblivious of sex happening in any place
besides their own chambers. Couples and other couples collectively, mutedly,
gorge through their disreputable escapades thinking that they are alone in doing
it. And the less they get to do it, the better; because that preserves the idea
of immorality. If talking about sex is normalised, the details, no matter how
small or vague, would start to come forward and one would realise what and how
they do it is the same as everyone else; which isn’t necessarily a bad thing but
it takes away that extra bit of pleasure which comes from the high of
&lt;em&gt;rebellion&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the millennials who probably don’t ‘get it’ and are scratching their heads
thinking, “sex is sex; it is great even without the coyness”, draw an analogy to
when you look for taboo porn or something offbeat on the internet when regular
stuff just doesn’t do it for you anymore. It’s the same with sex, the more it
remains sacred and clandestine, the better it feels when done. This theory
explains to some extent why people have extra-marital affairs, it is that
clandestine factor that makes it all the more coveted and hot. This also
explains why India ranks second in terms of population even with a culture of
muted sexual desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory goes beyond sex, extending to almost everything that is forbidden by
society. The forbidden is a massive source of pleasure, no matter what, because
even when one is part of the chorus of society, rebellion against the same
society that one belongs to is enthralling, to say the least. Revolutions on any
scale are the greatest form of validation a human can enjoy. Although having sex
is not a revolution per se, but doing it, at the end of the day, after not even
hinting at the presence of one’s sexuality or sensuality throughout the day,
does have a massive sense of breaking free and disobeying our own sense of
immorality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the diktat is dying out with the emergence of Generation Y. And although
this brings in a different set of pleasures to consume (in varied manners too),
it will be regretful, at least for me, not to taste the pleasure that came out
of the weird furtiveness our previous generations displayed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Of the many things that India, as a subcontinent, has achieved or done, such as overpopulation, growing disparity between economic classes and the caste system, probably one of the greatest would be the writing of the Kama Sutra; and even though we have, as a nation, owned up to most of the country’s achievements, even the more bizarre ones such as child marriage, in case of sex we tend to walk right by it without even a cursory glance.  One might argue that such prudish behaviour is a result of uneven distribution of cultural capital, but I believe that’s an oxymoron in itself. I’m not here to talk about how such prudence came into being in Indian culture – that is a topic for another day. What I would like to draw attention to is the product of such prudence taking shape in the form of coyness surrounding the topic of sex in Indian society. Now, if you belong to an extremely liberal Indian family or reside in the West, you’re probably not aware of the coyness I speak of. But we plebs have felt it right from our childhood, when our mothers would, almost in a frenzy, change the channel if we accidentally tuned into some English movie channel with a couple kissing on the screen. This particular act of maternal care and horror brought about two things; firstly, a curiosity about the most basic and prevalent of human natures that would sooner or later manifest into action, and secondly, through this suppression, we were being conditioned into suppressing our very understanding of ourselves. If we do not properly accept and understand the psychology underlying sex and sexuality we become blunt to our very existence.  A lot of things that we, as a society, do are directly or indirectly inspired by sex. We were taught, rather preached with sincerity that English films are a matter of disgrace and can bring Mata’s (the Hindu Mother Goddess’) curse upon us. Problems started for my mother when Indian advertisements stared getting liberal with sex as well. She was then left with little choice but to accept her defeat, while commenting on how Indian culture was getting ‘corrupted’. As is the norm in India, my parents never talked about sex in front of me, and as I grew up they started keeping their bedroom door open most of the time, except at night, so as to not arouse any suspicion in their growing child’s mind! And this isn’t just the case with families that have children, rather with any family where there are people besides the couple live. We are a sex hungry nation, lewd staring in buses and public places are a testimony to that, and yet we continue with this all-prevailing diktat of silence no matter where we go.  But this diktat has a silver lining to it and we must not discount it. As sex has grown to be the giant taboo of Indian society, it has become all the more pleasurable to consume. Coyness has turned out to be more of a boon than a bane for most couples around the nation and for one simple reason: forbidden fruit tastes better. Society, as a whole, sees sex as immoral. No one quite imagines that the couple they randomly passed by on the street actually has sex or to be more precise, one cannot picture them doing it. What this does psychologically is that it makes one’s intimacy with their partner ever so special. They choose to remain oblivious of sex happening in any place besides their own chambers. Couples and other couples collectively, mutedly, gorge through their disreputable escapades thinking that they are alone in doing it. And the less they get to do it, the better; because that preserves the idea of immorality. If talking about sex is normalised, the details, no matter how small or vague, would start to come forward and one would realise what and how they do it is the same as everyone else; which isn’t necessarily a bad thing but it takes away that extra bit of pleasure which comes from the high of rebellion.  For the millennials who probably don’t ‘get it’ and are scratching their heads thinking, “sex is sex; it is great even without the coyness”, draw an analogy to when you look for taboo porn or something offbeat on the internet when regular stuff just doesn’t do it for you anymore. It’s the same with sex, the more it remains sacred and clandestine, the better it feels when done. This theory explains to some extent why people have extra-marital affairs, it is that clandestine factor that makes it all the more coveted and hot. This also explains why India ranks second in terms of population even with a culture of muted sexual desires. This theory goes beyond sex, extending to almost everything that is forbidden by society. The forbidden is a massive source of pleasure, no matter what, because even when one is part of the chorus of society, rebellion against the same society that one belongs to is enthralling, to say the least. Revolutions on any scale are the greatest form of validation a human can enjoy. Although having sex is not a revolution per se, but doing it, at the end of the day, after not even hinting at the presence of one’s sexuality or sensuality throughout the day, does have a massive sense of breaking free and disobeying our own sense of immorality. Sadly, the diktat is dying out with the emergence of Generation Y. And although this brings in a different set of pleasures to consume (in varied manners too), it will be regretful, at least for me, not to taste the pleasure that came out of the weird furtiveness our previous generations displayed.</summary></entry></feed>