<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-03T22:46:29+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Chile – A Bright Spot or a Lost Case?</title><link href="/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chile – A Bright Spot or a Lost Case?" /><published>2019-01-03T21:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T21:41:00+00:00</updated><id>/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case">&lt;p&gt;Just like every individual, every country has its own journey. The journey is, without a doubt, the most important aspect because there is no destination or end goal for a country. It has to keep going. Here, we talk about Chile, a country that has seen its fair share of ups and downs, with a journey to remember. Here, we try to point out specifically, those few moments in its history which have actually shaped the course for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin America, a continent overpowered by political fomentation and social unrest, has led to the creation of states which are run by only a few individuals. Most states are witnessing a huge problem of power and wealth disparity, but the bigger problem is that numerous methods have failed to curb such problems. Chile also seems to be in the same zone as its neighbours. However, there are certain things that it has done differently over the last three decades. This has made the country distinct and a potential role model for the other Latin American countries (in both good and bad ways).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start at the beginning. It all started with the advent of the very charismatic military leader, Pinochet. Pinochet came into power after carrying out a coup on September 11, 1973, and he presided over Chile until 1990. However, what is interesting about this military dictator is that he turned the tide by building a nation on the foundation of strong economic reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began with the massive movement of privatisation. And he implemented privatisation successfully even before Thatcher or Reagan. From education to prison to highways, everything was given to private companies. And business was fuelled with aggressive free trade and huge foreign investments. Unlike countries such as Venezuela or Colombia, Chile was a safe bet for western Europeans and Americans, who back then were looking for potential avenues for investment abroad. The way Pinochet implemented his vision is something that till date is a matter of awe for experts all over the globe. Being an emerging nation back then, it had evidently harnessed the benefits of free trade, making the policies attractive for others to follow. Yet, even though this early dive into market-oriented reforms was pretty useful in giving people vast opportunities, Pinochet was still not loved by his nation. It was probably because he was, after all, a military dictator. His political ambition of gaining absolute power as the dictator of Chile made him less likeable to his countrymen. The social restrictions on the people were immense. Pinochet had successfully cancelled all elections and declared himself the supreme leader. Strict monitoring and regulatory laws in place curbed the powers of the media and also of his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people, however, began to achieve their goal of greater democracy when they managed to orchestrate a plebiscite in order to ratify their leaders. Soon, this wave of change and rebellion got them full democracy, which was much needed in order to restore the liberty of the people. However, the next two consecutive leaders followed, more or less, in the footsteps of Pinochet. This led to a crisis and inequality increased manifold, which led to numerous movements by commoners who demanded welfare. In 2006, this led to the first win for the Socialist Party since the end of the Pinochet era. Michelle Bachelet took office, the first woman to do so in Chile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She had won the elections promising reform and redistribution, a deadly combination that can potentially bring a country to its heels. She started with the reforms in the education sector which was highly privatised and had been a massive cause for unrest among the majority. Equal opportunities for all was promised and thus, specific changes were made to favour the underprivileged. However, all these changes had borne one problem, the increase in the size of government. This led to a reform in the taxation policies. The transition mostly affected the domestic enterprises which were at a major disadvantage now. Chile’s corporate tax was placed above the average of the OECD states. And as predicted by experts, this paved way for a slowdown in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebastian Pinera replaced Bachelet in the elections of 2010. His focus, unfortunately,  was not on reforming the taxation policies. We can see that post-2010, most emerging states, especially in Asia, had increased subsidies and loans manifold. This led to a brilliant scope for the businesses to grow which boosted the nation. It had also given leeway for newcomers to enter the market and start their own enterprises. Innovation was rewarded and the masses thrived. However, Chile was at a disadvantage. A major focus on decreasing disparity had not really helped them in the long run. It surely made the rich poorer, but did it make the poor richer? The answer is no. Even with all those policies in place, the commoners were still not satisfied and slowdown of the economy helped no one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Election time had come and Bachelet came into power again. She faced battles of her own. By this time the rich class was weary of the welfare policies which had led to vast losses in a profitable global period. Hence, this obviously started a conflict between the administration and the business class. It took a toll on the polity, economy, and society. Political interferences were prevalent which made it exceedingly hard for the administration to even execute innovative ideas. By the end of her term, Bachelor’s approval ratings had taken a deep dive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chile is run on its traditional sectors, from mining to infrastructure. Innovation and start-ups are generally not favoured by the laws. Most importantly, there are very few patrons of ideas in most formal sectors. Thus, Chile lags behind at the core and its policies make it a stagnant nation. Probably, the major fault on the administration’s part was focusing on equality and not growth. One cannot happen without the other and thus, even attention should have been given to both. Chile’s main drawback is not the fact they couldn’t redistribute the wealth, rather the reality is that the administration is incapable of providing opportunities to people to rise up the ladder. The inhibitions limit the potential of the state. Now, personally, I do believe that yes, it is an honest plight for a government when it doesn’t know what actually works for its people. However, we can deduce one answer from the above instance that quick fixes and aggressive welfare policies are unlikely to benefit any country in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, one must concede that Chile indeed has been a bright spot in the Latin American region, despite all the problems it currently faces. How much hope is left (or lost) with this South American nation, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Just like every individual, every country has its own journey. The journey is, without a doubt, the most important aspect because there is no destination or end goal for a country. It has to keep going. Here, we talk about Chile, a country that has seen its fair share of ups and downs, with a journey to remember. Here, we try to point out specifically, those few moments in its history which have actually shaped the course for the future.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jan Lokpal: The half-waged war for anti-corruption</title><link href="/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jan Lokpal: The half-waged war for anti-corruption" /><published>2019-01-03T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption">&lt;p&gt;India’s “war on corruption”, which erupted in 2011 with the hunger strikes of the activist Anna Hazare in New Delhi, seems to have lost itself underneath a mountain of bureaucratic jargon and political propaganda. Over seven years ago, Anna Hazare, with his unflinching voice and grit, demanded the formulation and approval of the Jan Lokpal Bill, a citizen’s ombudsman bill, that requires the appointment of a Jan Lokpal, an independent body that would investigate corruption cases, complete the investigation within a year and ensure that the trial in the case gets over in the next one year. The Jan Lokpal Bill was passed after the protests started by Hazare spread across the country in 2013. However, the vision of an India rid of corrupt officials and leaders is still quite distant simply because the Lokpal bill was never implemented. Over the years, along with political activists and India’s Central and State governments, the judiciary has also become involved in the process of the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. Yet, national policy has come to a standstill on the issue, and no remarkable progress has been made in over five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lokpal issue has been raging in the country since 1968, when the bill was first introduced in the Indian Parliament. The need for this reform is certainly apparent. In a fast-developing economy like India, which is emerging as a powerful player of the future, accountability and transparency can no longer be compromised. And so, Anna Hazare began his revolution of a “Swachh” or “Clean” economy and polity for the country. His protests in Delhi became a historic symbol of the country’s battle against corruption. In fact, the formulation of the Aam Aadmi Party (AAP), which constitutes the current government of Delhi, is viewed as a product of these protests. It was Mr Hazare’s protests that led to the Jan Lokpal, a committee of eight headed by a chairperson as the country’s ultimate anti-corruption watchdog. The Jan Lokpal bill provides for special protection of the whistleblower and covers all categories of public servants, including the Prime Minister, with only the armed forces being exempted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the ineffective executive mechanisms that run the nation, have once again, proved themselves. Due to vested interests of significant parties and leaders, the Jan Lokpal is not even solving corruption theoretically. The first issue to spark up was related to the procedure of appointment of the Lokpal itself. According to the provisions of the Bill, The Lokpal is appointed by a five-member committee including the Prime Minister, the Parliamentary Speaker, the Chief Justice of India, the Leader of Opposition and a member appointed by the Prime Minister. The problem is India doesn’t have a Leader of Opposition as of now. By definition, the Leader of Opposition is from a party that has 10 percent seats in the Lok Sabha or Lower House and no party satisfies this criterion. Thus, an amendment was introduced that called for the leader of the largest opposition party to be on the panel for selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in 2017, the Indian Supreme Court ruled that the absence of the Leader of the Opposition should not become a hindrance to the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. But this has evidently been ineffective. And the Court was dragged into the matter again in 2018 when the government had made no notable progress. The petition was filed by an NGO called Common Cause, which was represented by senior lawyer Prashant Bhushan. The petition questioned why the Lokpal has not been appointed as yet, despite an order by the apex court in April last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we now move onto January 2019, the Supreme Court has sought a response from the Centre on a plea that the leader of the single largest opposition party be treated as the Leader of the Opposition and be included in high-level committees involved in the appointment of heads of statutory bodies like CBI, CVC, CIC and Lokpal. NGO Common Cause has even suggested that the SC should appoint the Lokpal. But it only seems that with so many layers of executive, legislative and judicial interventions, India has become tangled in an all-too-familiar web of stagnation. The activist Anna Hazare, after a long period of silence, has decided to step up again and restart his hunger strike. He is expected to fast again from January 30, 2019. This can mark a crucial turning point for the Lokpal law, and the half-waged war on corruption. His aura may once again be successful in bringing people together. But can the man, who awed the public once, five years ago, repeat his own feat? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till then, Indians, like always, have to simply cope with a sad reality brought about by perennial administrative bottlenecks. The Jan Lokpal, that once became the torchbearer of India’s struggle for freedom from black money and corruption, has now become a distant issue. The media seems to have “moved on”. But what remains is the fact that the Jan Lokpal is the need of the hour. Public awareness and intervention alone can help save the cause for Lokpal and develop the economically “Swachh Bharat”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">India’s “war on corruption”, which erupted in 2011 with the hunger strikes of the activist Anna Hazare in New Delhi, seems to have lost itself underneath a mountain of bureaucratic jargon and political propaganda. Over seven years ago, Anna Hazare, with his unflinching voice and grit, demanded the formulation and approval of the Jan Lokpal Bill, a citizen’s ombudsman bill, that requires the appointment of a Jan Lokpal, an independent body that would investigate corruption cases, complete the investigation within a year and ensure that the trial in the case gets over in the next one year. The Jan Lokpal Bill was passed after the protests started by Hazare spread across the country in 2013. However, the vision of an India rid of corrupt officials and leaders is still quite distant simply because the Lokpal bill was never implemented. Over the years, along with political activists and India’s Central and State governments, the judiciary has also become involved in the process of the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. Yet, national policy has come to a standstill on the issue, and no remarkable progress has been made in over five years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Universal Healthcare and The India Story</title><link href="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Universal Healthcare and The India Story" /><published>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</updated><id>/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story">&lt;p&gt;A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations has envisaged Universal Health Coverage (UHC) as a possible solution to address this humongous problem. According to the WHO, Universal health coverage (UHC) means, “all people and communities can use the promotive, preventive, curative, rehabilitative and palliative health services they need, of sufficient quality to be effective, while also ensuring that the use of these services does not expose the user to financial hardship”. The underlying idea behind UHC is health for all at an affordable cost. The concept of Universal Health Coverage (UHC) emerged with the World Health Report of 2010 and considering its importance, the United Nation (UN) in 2015 included it as one of the Sustainable Development Goals. It has earmarked December 12 of every year as International Universal Health Coverage (UHC) Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the UHC movement has gained unprecedented momentum globally during the last five-six years, Japan, Singapore, and Thailand in Asia have been doing commendable work in this arena for many of the past decades. More than seventy countries across the world, with the notable exception of USA, have framed policies around the UHC. The common thread running across all such programmes is governmental involvement and action. India, the largest democracy of the world, too, has taken a vital step towards Universal Health Coverage (UHC). The Indian government rolled out a scheme- Ayushman Bharat: the National Health Protection Mission on September 25, 2018. This scheme has been framed after taking into consideration the dismal status of the health-care system in India, and also as a response to the order given by the Supreme Court of India to the Central Government to “do something” when the exorbitant prices of medical care were brought to its attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayushman Bharat is aimed at providing guaranteed access to free treatment to about 40% of India’s population. The population will be selected based on socio-economic factors. About 150,000 wellness clinics will be set up. They will provide comprehensive health care facilities such as free essential drugs, maternal and child health services, treatment for non-communicable diseases and much more. Setting up clinics is a tried and tested component of UHC that many countries like China and Sri Lanka have adopted to improve access to health services to the poor. And, theoretically, it should work in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1977, South Korea gave a strong push to compulsory health insurance and Japan designed national health insurance coverage as early as in 1961. To replicate their success, a second element  of Ayushman Bharat is providing insurance cover to a fixed percentage of the population of the country against expensive in-patient hospital care. They are assured a sum of over 7000 USD (half a million INR) per year per family. Both these elements are integrated to form the base of the policy. The scheme aims to cover 100 million poor and vulnerable families, making it the world’s largest public health-care scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation of any UHC scheme requires huge financial resources. The financing issue is a matter of greater concern in countries like India with low public health care financing. The Indian Government’s public health spending is less than 1.5% of its GDP while the global average is six percent and even the World Health Organisation (WHO) recommends at least 5%. To bridge this huge gap in financing, some countries have devised innovative public finance schemes. The government spending on health care in the Philippines increased from 1.8% to 4.8% within a span of six years after the implementation of the Sin Tax Reform Law of 2012. Sin taxes collected on tobacco and alcohol were used to finance this increased spending. President Jokowi of Indonesia is financing expenditure on providing health care facilities to the poor through savings from cutting fuel subsidies besides increasing taxes on tobacco. In order to raise finance for the country’s public health system, the NITI Aayog, India’s government think-tank, in its Vision Document has proposed raising taxes on tobacco, alcohol and unhealthy foods such as sweetened beverages. The Indian Government has also committed to raising its public health spending to 2.5 percent of GDP by 2025. But that is hardly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor that is important for the success of UHC is cooperation among nations. To take an example, India and Japan have signed an agreement in October to hone the surgery skills of Indian doctors in the treatment of trauma. Countries can enter into arrangements similar to the International Health Partnership (IHP) entered into by the European Union countries to promote Health Systems Strengthening (HSS) and effective development of cooperation in the field of health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a serious look at and resolution of all the related policy issues, UHC could also pass off as mere rhetoric. India has made some progress with Ayushman Bharat, but there are still issues with the policy and major challenges ahead. India’s PM Modi faces elections this year and his underperformance vis-a-vis UHC in India will cost him both policy-wise and politics-wise.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manya Manushi</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding the Absurdity of Life</title><link href="/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Absurdity of Life" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life">&lt;p&gt;What is the meaning of life? This has been perhaps one of the most vexing questions of all time which has transformed several ordinary men into brooding intellectuals. While the world has seen the emergence of diverse theories propounded by the greatest of philosophers, none seem to have completely quenched the ultimate thirst for an objective analysis of life and its meaning. It was in the pursuit of this meaning that philosophers like Sartre, Kierkegaard and Albert Camus sowed the seeds from which eventually sprang a full grown tree of a new philosophical discourse on absurdism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albert Camus, in particular, has spoken at length about absurdity in his manuscript called the “Myth of Sisyphus”. Here, he has endeavoured to explicate the futility of investigating for the absolute meaning of life—which doesn’t really exist. “The absurd” for Camus stems from the discord between “the human need and the unreasonable silence of the universe”. This ultimately culminates into a sense of hopelessness and despair in the human heart. Camus addresses what he considers the most crucial problem of philosophy: suicide, and whether the absurdity of life is a good reason for committing suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men, by their very nature, are seekers of meanings, and in this pursuit, turn to religion and dogmatism to explain a world which in reality is characterised by sheer indifference and ‘irrationality’. An illusionary world embellished with meanings serves as a major source of comfort to humans as it offers false hope and reassurance, but once this world is stripped of all its meanings, man is thrown in an abyss of chaos and upheaval. Men continue to live in their robotic way, pursuing goals and ambitions mindlessly as if they are in a never-ending race. Then comes a day when they suddenly wake up from this deep slumber of ignorance after receiving a huge blow from the absurdity of life. An alien feeling of disharmony dawns upon them, and life, with all its essence and beauty, loses significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to imagine yourself as an invisible person and look at the world around you. It’s nothing but a mechanical interplay of relations with people chasing temporary materialistic pleasures and associating their very being with these short-lived passions. Such an existence is like an exile or punishment, just like the one awarded to the Greek mythological character named Sisyphus who was condemned by the Gods to perform the futile labour of rolling a massive boulder up the hill only to watch it fall down again and again till eternity. It begs Camus’ ever-so-important question: should we live life at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human understanding is only limited to their own standards. Efforts to reduce the enormity of the universe into a set of uniform principles is futile. In an attempt to content himself, man attaches humanistic feelings of love and suffering to the apathetic universe. While a man’s craving for certainty persists, the universe remains still. And, it is from this relationship between the truth-seeking man and an unfeeling universe that the feeling of absurdity emanates. Science, the most authentic form of inquiry is itself based on hypothesis and conjectures. The claims believed to be true centuries ago are being altered and disproved now. In the face of such dynamism, certainty becomes a far-fetched dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is not the individual or the world that is absurd, but the incongruous relation between the two. The absurd originates from comparisons and confrontation. In the case of man and the world, the absurd lies in the clash between the human desire to look for meanings in a meaningless universe. Although a little baffling to comprehend, once man develops faith in the absurd, it plays an active role in guiding his life’s choices. Apart from accepting the absurd, the other option open to men is to either physically end their lives once and for all, or commit a philosophical suicide, where they assume artificial meanings and purpose of life by resorting to theology or religion. While suicide may seem a reasonable option, it simply negates the problem and does not answer it. Camus staunchly denies suicide and refers to it as ‘a repudiation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is to embrace this absurdity and live with it. This produces three consequences - &lt;strong&gt;Revolt, Freedom, and Passion&lt;/strong&gt;. The revolt is identified by the relentless longing for an objective meaning, which is impossible to achieve. Freedom, on the other hand, is characterised by the realisation that an absurd man is free to act and doesn’t have to submit to the restrictions imposed by life. And finally, consequence or passion arises as a result of living life to the fullest by accepting the absurd and caring only about the present rather than the future or past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now go back to our ‘absurd hero’, Sisyphus. His perpetual toil of pushing the boulder up and watching it roll down enables us to acknowledge the melancholic truth of absurdity. And the only way to remove this anguish is by imagining Sisyphus as a happy person, who despite all the struggle, is enjoying the whole process. Likewise, we must also contemplate the absurd and accept the inevitable drudgery of existence, which can only happen when we conquer our fate without expecting anything in return. So, what are you thinking? Go, enjoy your life, so what if you’ve failed a test, missed a deadline or many deadlines. Such occurrences are insignificant in the grand scheme of things. Appreciate and observe the grandeur of the world around you. Feel the sunlight, the delicate touch of petals, the cold droplets of rain and the beauty of nature, and maybe even derive a meaning out of it (bearing in the mind that it’s absurd of course!). Live your life passionately, and above all, cherish every moment. Stay happy because, at the end of the day, that’s what matters the most!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">What is the meaning of life? This has been perhaps one of the most vexing questions of all time which has transformed several ordinary men into brooding intellectuals. While the world has seen the emergence of diverse theories propounded by the greatest of philosophers, none seem to have completely quenched the ultimate thirst for an objective analysis of life and its meaning. It was in the pursuit of this meaning that philosophers like Sartre, Kierkegaard and Albert Camus sowed the seeds from which eventually sprang a full grown tree of a new philosophical discourse on absurdism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Space and Loneliness</title><link href="/On-Space-and-Loneliness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Space and Loneliness" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/On-Space-and-Loneliness</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On-Space-and-Loneliness">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxi Driver’s principle character Travis Bickle outlines these very principles as espoused by the great American author (who I happen to be a big fan of) Thomas Wolfe. Loneliness is a derivative of several complex emotions which arise within the spheres of our consciousness. This article however will not stress on our individual perspective of loneliness but rather a collective sense of loneliness, i.e. the feeling that we could be the only civilization to breed conscious life in a whole goddamn universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1961, Frank Drake, in his very famous equation, discussed the possibility of the existence of the extraterrestrial beings and our chances of actually finding them and making contact with them. This was not to quantify the number of civilizations in the universe but rather a way to stimulate scientific dialogue on the search for extraterrestrial beings. It is just an estimation technique which is popularly known in the scientific community as the Fermi Problem. It provides a back-of-the-envelope solution to the entire problem at hand. The Drake equation features 7 unknown parameters which can be treated as variables in order to find an answer. This includes variables like the number of civilisations in our galaxy with which communication might be possible (i.e. which are on our current past light cone); the average rate of star formation in our galaxy; the fraction of those stars that have planets; the average number of planets that can potentially support life per star that has planets; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inspirations behind these variables was actually an article in the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; journal that was provocatively titled: “Searching for Interstellar Communications”. One of the first known attempts to connect with the extraterrestrial beings was made by the 1977 American Scientific program that employed the use of 2 robotic satellite probes, namely, Voyager 1 and Voyager 2, respectively. It was actually intended to study the outer solar system, i.e. the outer planets of Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune. It was launched under conditions of a favourable alignment of the four planets. The initial plan was to study the four planets, but currently, the Voyagers explore the outer boundary of the heliosphere in interstellar space and the mission has been extended way above it’s time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacecrafts contain very advanced technological instruments in order to collect and transmit proper, accurate data back home. The Voyagers have stabilized guidance systems, controlled by computers, to point their high gain antennas to Earth for efficient transfer of important results and data. The message transmission is also helped by the use of an electronic photography system which has been an instrumental part of the satellites. One thing of immense interest in the spacecraft, however, is the Voyager Golden Record. These records are phonograph records which contain sounds and images , “selected to portray the diversity and culture on Earth” to any intelligent extraterrestrial life that may come across it. Carl Sagan, the renowned astrophysicist who was allocated the duty to decide which records to include on the disk noted that “the spacecrafts will be encountered and the record played only if there are advanced space-faring civilisations in interstellar space”. But the launching of this “bottle” into the cosmic ocean says something very hopeful about life on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl Sagan chose and assembled 115 images and varieties of natural sounds. There are collections of songs and spoken greetings and printed messages from the likes of US President Jimmy Carter and UN Secretary General Kurt Waldheim. It includes an inspirational message which is “per aspera ad astra” or “ through hardships to the stars”, which is what this entire struggle of choices is supposed to signify. There are several photographs from the notable photographer Ansel Adams along with the recorded brain waves of Ann Druyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one song which resonates with this entire struggle is the simple choice of a gospel blues song written and performed by American musician Blind Willie Johnson that was recorded in 1927. The song was named: “Dark was the Night. Cold was the Ground”. It is basically an instrumental song with the self-taught slide style used by Willie and accompanied by his moaning and humming. Johnson was not blind when he was born, but it is speculated that he was blinded by his stepmother when was only 7 years old. Apparently, during an argument, she splashed Willie with a caustic solution of lye water which ended up permanently blinding him. However, that was not the end of his suffering. He used to perform on the streets and had a tin cup tied to his neck to collect money. During his career, he was praised for his style which became quite popular but he was never financially well off. Post the Great Depression, his audience was completely wiped off, and he never recorded again. And in strange series of circumstances in 1945, his home got destroyed in a fire and he continued to live within the ruins of his house, where he was exposed to humidity and dampness, following which he contracted Malaria. His health steadily worsened due to several other factors and hospitals were not willing to admit him owing to his visual impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He passed away on September 18, 1945. His life has been a true testimony of his song, which has immortalized humankind’s search to cure loneliness. His song truly represents the primal feeling which we all have, whether individually or collectively, for a greater purpose and a direction to every event. Floating in the endless space, it represents a sign of hope and a possibility on how loneliness could be a feature which could give us a new path to our existence. But maybe being alone is not bad after all. Maybe we could all be God’s lonely men. I guess we simply need a few aliens to tell us what the truth is.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Helping Hand to Helping Hands</title><link href="/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Helping Hand to Helping Hands" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands</id><content type="html" xml:base="/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands">&lt;p&gt;In February 2018, an Emirati mother and daughter were sentenced to one and a half years of jail for torturing their migrant maid to death. The husband, who was the sponsor of the maid, was penalised for three thousand dinars. Numerous cases like this have surfaced in the media reports in the last few years. Though these reports are just skin-deep when it comes to the extent to which millions of domestic workers all around the world are exploited on a daily basis. The incident brings forth a lot of queries regarding the laws for labour protection present in the host country. In retrospect, it also makes us question the value of a life. Does the status of the person really determine the value of his or her life and mental or physical trauma that he or she endures? Also, does the position of an individual’s work signify how that person should be treated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to ILO reports, the demand for domestic help in Asia has increased by roughly an estimate of 50% over the last 15 years (1995-2012). It might be based on the fact that the disparity is quite extensive in Asia compared to the other continents. The richer states often face a shortage in the supply of workers willing to work in a private household. Therefore, they redeem themselves by importing the services from poorer states. The main importers in Asia are the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC), Singapore, Hong Kong, and Malaysia, whereas the dominant exporters in the market are the Philippines, India, Indonesia, and Sri Lanka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is a huge sector with a lot of potential, there are only a few laws in place which actually regulate the market. This problem is heightened by the fact that labour legislation in most Asian countries doesn’t recognise these workers as a part of the labour body. Also, workers’ trade unions are usually not prevalent in most Asian countries. Thus, low-skilled workers lose out on bargaining power when it comes to their security, wages, working hours and other facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plight of the migrant workers is worse because they solely rely on employment contracts which paves the way for their residence in a foreign country. They are fully dependent on their employers, who act as their sponsors to the host country. They are also responsible for their work visa. On the other hand, the service agencies, the intermediaries between the two parties, also pressurise the employees to work under all circumstances. Most of these workers have no knowledge of the local tongue or the laws of the country. Therefore, this builds a power structure which gives immense control to the employers. Due to this, there is more opportunity for abuse of power and exploitation of labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equal pay for equal content of work is not a reality, even for skilled females in formal sectors. Eighty percent of the domestic workers, globally, are women. Thus, this sector is plagued by low wages. It is fuelled by the popular notion that household work should be done by any woman. Thus, the significance of the workers’ innate skills is minimal. In an investigation conducted by the Singaporean government, it was found that the average income of a housemaid is one-tenth of the average income of a Singaporean. Adding to this is the problem of severe working conditions: no fixed working hours (assumptions of employers that the housemaid should be available around-the-clock), no rest day a week (normally, its consecutive 24 hours of leave for other labour work), no proper paid annual leaves, no overtime compensation, and isolation for the foreign workers in a new country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rectify this situation, the ILO is now asking for the major host countries to define maximum time limits for work in a week. Also, proper laws for overtime work, rest days should be fixed between the worker and employer at the time when the contract is made along with the pre-decided annual holidays. Another problem in this setup is that most contracts do not mention any paid maternity leave. This is the biggest problem for the highly feminised sector and a problem that laws generally don’t focus on. Moreover, in certain countries, discrimination on the basis of ethnicity, religion, and age is extensive in nature. For example, in the GCC countries, a Filipina housemaid is highly valued and is paid higher compared to the workers from other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, the governments of the labour exporting countries have tried to fix a few problems by entering into bilateral memoranda with the host countries. The Philippines is a good example and it has worked extensively to protect the rights of its nationals in foreign countries. They have recently passed the Kasambahay Bill in the parliament in an act of protecting the privacy and freedom of their citizens working abroad. But this is not a fully effective substitute for proper laws which are not present in the employing nations.
For the migrant housemaids, the problem is aggravated by the mere fact that they are completely dependent on the employers for accommodation and basic necessities. It is not uncommon to find the workers complaining about the lack of food and very bad living conditions. Overworking their bodies without a break or proper meals forces a lot of them to run away from their employers. But these cases are still humane compared to other kinds of harassment that are faced by the housemaids on a daily basis. Their complaints fall on deaf ears or no ears at all. There have been a massive number of cases in which the housemaid has been subjected to verbal, physical and sexual abuse from the members of the family that they have to live with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report by ILO states that around 60% of the domestic workers are victims of abuse. It is truly a helpless situation for them. The restriction on freedom to movement (in some countries, they don’t have their passports or their employers lock them in) and imbalances in the power structure make them absolutely vulnerable to all sorts of violence and injustice. According to a report, more than 40% of workers in Singapore have faced some sort of abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is pretty tame compared to the conditions of the workers in the Gulf countries. The GCC countries have a pre-dominant Kafala system which basically confiscates the passports of the labourers as soon as they land in the airport. It seems as if the workers lose all their rights when they step onto the foreign land. Contract labourers at times get no help from the agency and are left at the mercy of the employers. The law, in every way, happens to work against the innocents, who have no option of fleeing from aggressive employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an act to appease the ILO, certain countries of the GCC, like Bahrain and Lebanon, have come forward to repeal the Kafala system to make the confiscation of passports illegal. However, media reports from these countries say that such is not the ground reality. The change is not very evident. All in all, it seems as if the employers don’t really see the housemaids as humans. Until that happens, legal and social change will not occur. It will simply take a lot more time before employers are made to face justice, a justice where they cannot get away with a crime just by paying off penalties or blood money.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In February 2018, an Emirati mother and daughter were sentenced to one and a half years of jail for torturing their migrant maid to death. The husband, who was the sponsor of the maid, was penalised for three thousand dinars. Numerous cases like this have surfaced in the media reports in the last few years. Though these reports are just skin-deep when it comes to the extent to which millions of domestic workers all around the world are exploited on a daily basis. The incident brings forth a lot of queries regarding the laws for labour protection present in the host country. In retrospect, it also makes us question the value of a life. Does the status of the person really determine the value of his or her life and mental or physical trauma that he or she endures? Also, does the position of an individual’s work signify how that person should be treated?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Morality, the Clash of Civilizations and the Democratic Dilemma</title><link href="/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Morality, the Clash of Civilizations and the Democratic Dilemma" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma">&lt;p&gt;“Civilization will not attain to its perfection until the last stone from the last church falls on the last priest.” Émile Zola&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Freedom consists not in doing what we like, but in having the right to do what we ought.” Pope John Paul II&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-1900s, hundreds of millions hoped (and feared) that the “spectre of Communism” would overshadow the world. Less than 100 years later, this hope appears to have all but vanished. The Soviet Union has collapsed. Communism is either dying or dead. Liberal democracy is considered the norm, and societies which deviate from it are considered either barbaric or backward (sometimes both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is all this in aid of? Well, proponents argue, liberal democracy ensures that each person will have an infallible guarantee of their most intrinsic human rights, and that, if they are violated, the guilty party will be swiftly brought to justice. The problem, of course, arises when we consider the question of what constitutes “human rights”. The phrase is rather nebulous and subject to a wide range of possible interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the so-called “Right to Life”. To whom does this extend? Well, the human being, obviously. But can the unborn foetus be considered a “human being”? Who gets to define this term “human being”? At what stage does an entity start to be “human”? And what about criminals? Do they also enjoy the right to life, or have they – by their transgressions and woeful iniquities (again, a very debatable issue at times) – forfeited that right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the problem. There are 1.3 billion Catholics in the world who (if they are good Catholics) affirm that human life begins at conception. They also have (so their apologists claim) a number of medical experts and embryologists to back them up on that. On the other hand, there are countless self-professed “feminists” who believe that to protect without exception the foetus from being aborted would be to endanger the life of the mother. One is, the argument goes, trying to prioritize the life of an unborn, half-developed “creature” over that of a fully developed, free citizen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is clearly a clash of civilizations, a war of opposing ideologies. If the pro-choice crowd is in the right, then the right to abortion is an intrinsic right of the woman. If the pro-life factions are correct, then abortion is the biggest cause of genocide since the Holocaust. Both sides agree that human rights are being violated to this day. This brings us to a very pressing question: Is Liberal Democracy even realistic? Or does it try to bite off more than it can chew? It tries to keep the “religious busybodies” out of government, but at the same time imposes a morality on the rest of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a philosophical perspective, can non-religious people even have objective moral values? According to a sizeable number of atheists and naturalists, morality is simply a human construct, created by societies in order to facilitate greater synergy and efficiency of operation. Each tribe of people, the story goes, tries over time to organize its own affairs and, in order to do so, “invents” a moral code to better facilitate that purpose. But if it is purely a human construct, then it has no intrinsic value – only imparted value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Jews, Christians and Muslims all believe (and together, they constitute more than 3 billion people), that morality is ordained by God. Some go even further and say that morality is nothing other than God’s own eternal, immutable nature. With the rise of postmodernism, moral relativism has been skyrocketing, and the old-school atheists are desperately scrambling to produce a scientific basis for objective moral values. The religious camp is claiming that such an operation is in vain since science (they say) cannot possibly adjudicate on matters on ethics. Only time will tell which side wins out in the end. But both factions are united in an affirmation that relativism is dangerous and toxic. Here is why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If morality is purely a human construct, then there is no universal moral code everyone has to abide by. Each person gets to invent his/her own moral rules and one would have no objective basis to refute that. In a relativistic worldview, if one disagrees with someone else, one cannot say that the other side is “wrong” – merely that they disagree. Now imagine if the Nazis suddenly had a worldwide resurgence. The Christian, Muslim and Jew would be able to unite and condemn them on the basis that they are violating God’s eternal unchangeable law and are &lt;em&gt;ipso facto&lt;/em&gt; condemned. But what can the relativist say? Only that he/she disagrees with their moral code, but since – according to his/her own definition – morality is merely a human construct, he/she cannot make an objective claim that they are “wrong” in an absolute sense of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy must be better delineated. The fact is that there exist in the world irreconcilable worldviews. People of different ethnicities, races, communities and genders might coexist, but can a pro-lifer eat at the same table as an abortionist, when the fact is – according to the pro-lifer – the latter is nothing other than a murderer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cannot live in two worlds. Liberal Democracy cannot not take a stand, but if it does take a stand, it ceases to be liberal. And when it ceases to be liberal, can it be called democracy? In a world of exclusive ideologies, absolute inclusivism is an impossibility. And in a world of conflicting moral systems, the state and the law cannot act as impartial umpires. Either abortion is legal, or it isn’t. The question then remains, that if the state is ready to impose its own moral values on the rest of the populace, then it must ask itself a question: does it have any objective basis for those values or not? If it does not, it undermines its own authority. And if it is non-religious, it is hard to see how it’s ethical code can have any objective basis at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">“Civilization will not attain to its perfection until the last stone from the last church falls on the last priest.” Émile Zola</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">India’s Witness Protection Scheme: Opportunities &amp;amp; Challenges</title><link href="/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="India’s Witness Protection Scheme: Opportunities &amp; Challenges" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme</id><content type="html" xml:base="/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme">&lt;p&gt;India now has a witness protection programme. Indeed, this is a watershed moment for witnesses, who can finally be protected. Yet, the scheme has many potential hurdles to cross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, 4 people moved a petition before the Indian Supreme Court. They had witnessed harassment, intimidation, and threats to witnesses related to them in the infamous Asaram Bapu case, which involved rape allegations against a towering Indian preacher. The SC found the issues of witness protection raised in the petition to be serious, and of pan-India importance, and impleaded the remaining states and UTs as respondents. The views of the states and UTs on a witness protection scheme was sought. The Attorney-General was instructed to frame a draft witness protection scheme. Showing uncommon alacrity, the Home Ministry began soon prepared a draft and placed it before the Court. The states and the UTs were asked to furnish comments on it. Further, the Ministry itself opened a public consultation on the draft, and considered comments from the National Legal Services Authority, High Courts, police personnel and civil society. Finally, taking the comments received from all these stakeholders into account, the Ministry framed the final Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 and placed it before the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Court promptly accepted it. The Scheme is reproduced in full in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sci.gov.in/supremecourt/2016/34388/34388_2016_Judgement_05-Dec-2018.pdf&quot;&gt;the judgment&lt;/a&gt; of the SC. It came into force on the date of the judgment, December 5, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the level of threat during investigation, trial, or post-trial, witnesses have been categorised into 3 categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category A:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat extends to life of witness or his family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category B:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat extends to the safety, reputation, or property of the witness or his family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category C:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat is moderate and extends to harassment or intimidation of the witness or his family members, reputation or property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian States have been directed to set up a State Witness Protection Fund, which shall be the mother goddess feeding the expenditure on the Witness Protection Scheme. Every witness himself, his family members (clearly defined to include only specific relations), his lawyer, and multiple police officers involved in the investigation and imprisonment stage (also clearly defined) have been empowered to file an application for witness protection, preferably to be forwarded through the Prosecutor handling the case. A standard format has been laid down for the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All such applications are to be considered by a Competent Authority to be set up in every district. The entire process is required to take place in private, and must be completed within 10 days of a request reaching the Authority. In the meanwhile, while processing the request, the Authority may order interim witness protection measures if a threat is imminent. Lastly, but most importantly, everyone involved in the entire process is sworn to secrecy. The investigating officer and the courts are required to acquaint witnesses with this scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witnesses in India are indeed a tired, pathetic lot. It is an open secret that many of them have to bear the brunt of every possible imaginable coercive tactic to silence them or make them go turncoat. Harassment, threats, bribes, attacks on one’s body, property and family are not uncommon. Even attempts on their life are not unheard of. The more powerful the accused the witness is testifying against, the more the danger of falling prey to some or all of these. These coercive tactics often make witnesses turn hostile. Witnesses often turn up dead. Cases built on the bulwark of witness testimony thus fall apart. Indeed, a large number of criminal cases in India continue to be built majorly on witness testimony. Justice thus falls prey to muscle power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, most witnesses and their families do not face outrageous threats. The garden variety, and a substantial part, of threats to witnesses can easily be countered by taking very basic steps, some of which are already standard &lt;em&gt;– viz&lt;/em&gt;. concealment of identity, providing police escorts, monitoring communications, etc. Stakeholders should, first and foremost, concentrate on getting these basics right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 has all the features of a world-class witness protection scheme. It provides for global best practices in the field of witness protection to be adopted in India. Properly implemented, this Scheme will be a game changer for the Indian justice system, and a messiah for troubled witnesses across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every successful witness protection scheme is built on the crux of confidentiality. The death of confidentiality is as good as the death of witness protection, and often the reputation, property, and even the life of the witness and his family. In a country where evidence and snippets of the internal working of investigations are often revealed to the media, maintaining the confidentiality of the entire process will be the challenge. The silver lining in the cloud, however, is that India follows an adversarial justice system. Hence, theoretically, every stakeholder in the witness protection scheme―be it the police officers or the prosecutors―works opposite to the defendant[s], and therefore they have an incentive to ensure such confidentiality. The challenge will be to ensure that no other (bad) external incentives &lt;em&gt;– viz&lt;/em&gt;. contacts, mala fide  intentions, etc. – are allowed to interfere with this fine balance. Confidentiality will then be automatically ensured. Instilling a culture of confidentiality amongst all stakeholders, including drilling in the knowledge that a failure to do so can often mean life and death for a person, would also go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manpower and training is another challenge to be overcome. India’s police-people ratio is abysmally low. It will be an uphill task to ensure enough boots on the ground to administer a witness protection programme. This problem is further compounded by the fact that witness protection is often no easy task. It requires specially-trained police officers. Stakeholders may often unwittingly compromise the process if not trained properly. Hence, training of police officers will be a major challenge. Again, the silver lining is that witness protection will be administered by a special Witness Protection Cell of the respective police force. This is a wonderful opportunity to specially train a subset of police officers to be islands of excellence in a sea of mediocrity, who can uphold the ethos of confidentiality and administer witness protection with aplomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 marks a watershed moment in the history of India. It is fraught with opportunities. The time is ripe to make this Scheme into a turning point for the justice system in India. It is now up to us to overcome the hurdles and challenges which lie in the way of its implementation, and make this Scheme the grand success Lady Justice deserves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sagnik Sarkar</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">India now has a witness protection programme. Indeed, this is a watershed moment for witnesses, who can finally be protected. Yet, the scheme has many potential hurdles to cross.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Counting down the biggest economic policy announcements since the Financial Crash</title><link href="/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Counting down the biggest economic policy announcements since the Financial Crash" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic">&lt;p&gt;In economics, recessions and depressions are supposed to have taught us many valuable lessons (Keynes was one of them). What about the last major recession? It’s been a decade since the Global Markets Crash of ’08. As we enter 2019, let’s see how our governments and institutions have used their financial knowledge over the decade. Many of these announcements are a direct cause of the crisis, while the rest were too important to be left out. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is early 2009, the United States, reeling from the Financial Crisis, has the New Year as the only positive yet (besides the new President). Obama outlined throughout his 2008 campaign plans for an economic stimulus package and this was delivery time. On February 17, 2009, President Obama signed the fiscal stimulus passed by Congress, which would raise overall demand in the economy by an initial $780-billion worth of federal spending and tax cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This indeed was a necessary follow-up to President Bush’s Troubled Asset Recovery Program, which bailed out the big banks of Wall Street still at the point of revival (sorry, Lehman Brothers). It was only later in 2012 that Congress added to the ARRA making it stand at &lt;i&gt;eight-hundred-and-forty-billion-dollars&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act was largely successful, ending the Recession in July 2009, just 5 months after the bill’s passing. Although many people were skeptical whether they received any tax benefits, the program was hailed for its effectiveness and served as a model for a country that appears later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 - North Korea ‘Won’, 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, they did not win 2009. There have not been many cases of currency revaluation or demonetization in the 21st Century; in fact, less than the number of fingers on your hand. Yet for an occurrence this rare, the 2nd entry on our list has not had the fanfare it deserves. We travel far East to the Korea of the daily news cycle. You guessed it, welcome to North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2009, the North Korean government decided to devalue their currency, the Won, for the first time in 50 years. Many speculated this was a move either initiated or approved personally by Supreme Leader Kim Jong-Il, father of Kim Jon-Un. Seen as a move against private market activity, it also wiped out many North Koreans’ savings. To make matters worse, the announcement was made to foreign embassies but not to North Korean State media. The old notes ceased to be legal tender on November 30, with new notes not being delivered until December 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only think of ways to &lt;i&gt;spend&lt;/i&gt; that week without monetary transaction possible. Needless to say, things were chaotic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 - The Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can blame the Housing markets all they want. But the reason why banks went overboard was in large part due to the repealing of the Glass-Steagall Act in 1999. The Glass–Steagall Act was enacted after the Great Depression of 1930. It separated commercial banks and investment banks, to avoid potential conflicts of interest between the lending activities of the former and rating activities of the latter. Economist Joseph Stiglitz said the repeal would mean the risk-taking culture of investment banking dominated the more risk-averse commercial banking culture, leading to increased levels of risk-taking and leverage during the boom period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the Dodd-Frank reforms. Spelled out over roughly 2,300 pages, this piece of financial reform intends to decrease various risks in the U.S. financial system. The Act established a number of new government agencies tasked with overseeing various aspects of the banking system. Apart from monitoring the financial stability of major firms whose failure could have a major negative impact on the economy, it also provides for regulations keeping a check on Wall Street, which is why President Trump looks to repeal it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 - Austerity returns—to Ireland, Greece, the U.K., and, perhaps to the U.S.A., 2011&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, dear, Austerity! The things you promised us, and now look at what you did to the PIGS (and Italy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know who or what I’m talking about, the reduction of &lt;i&gt;government budget deficits&lt;/i&gt; through &lt;i&gt;spending cuts, tax increases,&lt;/i&gt; or a &lt;i&gt;combination of both&lt;/i&gt; is referred to as &lt;em&gt;Austerity&lt;/em&gt;. It is a series of strict measures to deal with governments unable to pay their debts, viz. Greece (which lost 25% of its GDP) and the members of the Eurozone who have spectacularly contributed to its economic failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/irelandbust2010.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the European debt crisis, many countries embarked on austerity programs, reducing their budget deficits relative to GDP from 2010 to 2011. According to the CIA World Factbook, Greece decreased its budget deficit from 10.4% of GDP in 2010 to 9.6% in 2011. Iceland, Italy, Ireland, Portugal, France, and Spain also decreased their budget deficits from 2010 to 2011 relative to GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, the European people found it too tough to cope up with the heavy tax burdens and unemployment went from 10.3% in 2011 to 12.1% in 2013. Even Paul Krugman saw no sign of success, “this also implies that 1 euro of austerity yields only about 0.4 euros of reduced deficit, even in the short run. No wonder, then, that the whole austerity enterprise is spiraling into disaster.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 - Cyprus and the Big Bailout, 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a story with a happy ending―but it starts off just as bad as the Eurozone. Back in 2013, Europe looked on in despair as yet another country appeared on the brink of collapse. Panic spread through the Cyprus financial system as government bonds were downgraded to junk status and long queues formed outside cash machines as the country failed to make ends meet. Cyprus struck a last-minute bailout deal worth 10 billion euro ($11 billion) in the early hours of Monday morning, aimed at preventing the island becoming the first country forced out of the single European currency. Guess where the help came from- Russian Oligarchs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyprus’s second-largest bank, Laiki Bank was closed. Its €4.2bn in deposits over €100,000 were wiped out entirely. All lenders to Laiki saw their investments wiped out, in a first for a Eurozone bailout. Bank of Cyprus survived the axe. Fast forward to March 2016 via a rescue package program, raft of reforms and austerity measures (finally worked!)  and the country is exiting its three-year, 10 billion euro financial aid package as one of the more robust Eurozone economies. Voila!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 - Japan’s Quantitative Easing is like the USA on steroids!,  2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States did quantitative easing the right way; with loads and loads of asset purchases by the government. Under the most recent incarnation of monetary easing - dubbed “QE3” - the central bank has purchased around $1.6 trillion in government bonds and mortgage-backed securities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese then went out and did this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Abenomics6036.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Here’s a graph from 2015, showing the BoJ’s asset purchases, source: Haver Analytics)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the Federal Reserve was winding down, the Bank of Japan (BoJ) voted by 5:4 in a hotly-contested decision to boost its asset purchases by a quarter to roughly $700bn a year, covering the fiscal deficit and the lion’s share of Japan’s annual budget. Governor Haruhiko Kuroda said the fresh stimulus was intended to “pre-empt” mounting deflation risks in the world and vowed to do whatever it takes to see through Japan’s &lt;i&gt;“Abenomics”&lt;/i&gt; revolution. “We are at a critical moment in our efforts to break free from the deflationary mindset,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hans Redeker, from Morgan Stanley, believes that Japan’s aggressive measures seem to be putting pressure on the rest of their economic competitors in Asia to raise government spending too. But this is where China finds it tough to compete with a large budget deficit, slowing economy and FDI gradually turning negative. No wonder the Dragon is angry at its eastern neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 - Greece becomes first advanced economy ever to fail in arrears to the IMF, 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2015 was all about Greece”—is an understatement. 2015 saw Greece’s debt crisis, Greece’s referendum, Greece’s bailout, Greece’s election, Greece’s second election. At one point it really seemed that the battered country, which has been through so much, would finally crash out of the eurozone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;No Bailouts&lt;/i&gt; campaign securing 61.31% majority, won the referendum. In a television address, PM Alex Tsipras said the outcome showed that democracy could not be blackmailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a week later, however, he would be forced to accept a bailout of further austerity measures and economic reforms, even more onerous than those the nation had so dramatically rejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/chart6034.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 - India’s Demonetization and the GST Bill, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two polar opposites. One nobody saw coming and the other that had been there all along. No, I’m not referring to the Congress and the BJP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Demonetization Scheme struck like a lightning rod throughout Indian society, affecting both the poor and rich equally (so much for inequality). In a move targeted at debilitating the shadow economy, counterfeit cash and “black money” used to fund illegal activity, Rs. 500 and Rs. 1000 banknotes were demonetized and new Rs. 500 and Rs. 2000 notes were introduced. The GST Bill, on the other hand, was first put forth by the Vajpayee administration almost 20 years ago but only saw the light of day in late 2016. It has successfully eliminated the Cascading effect of taxes (tax on a tax) and taken its place as the Destination tax of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being initially met with protests, litigation, and strikes, it has received support from many eminent bankers and the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 - Venezuela devalues its currency by the crypto, 2018&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have truly reached the advent of technology when Venezuela decides to peg the Bolivar to an oil-backed cryptocurrency called the petro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela under Nicolas Maduro is an economic autocracy at best. Since 2014, they have lied on reports and economic statistics and by 2016, were in an economic collapse, with the IMF estimating a 500% inflation rate and a 10% GDP contraction and as of today, are experiencing Hyperinflation—Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the government decided to slash five zeros off and devalue the currency, and back it by their oil and mineral reserves; the only things not spiraling out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really a sneak peek of the decade to come!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shohan Mukherjee</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">In economics, recessions and depressions are supposed to have taught us many valuable lessons (Keynes was one of them). What about the last major recession? It’s been a decade since the Global Markets Crash of ’08. As we enter 2019, let’s see how our governments and institutions have used their financial knowledge over the decade. Many of these announcements are a direct cause of the crisis, while the rest were too important to be left out. Here you go:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“A Strange Game. The only Winning Move is to not Play.”</title><link href="/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“A Strange Game. The only Winning Move is to not Play.”" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play">&lt;p&gt;The cold war science fiction movie War Games had a very cold yet direct message to its audiences and the dispatch remains important to us, even more so, at this point of time too. A nuclear war has no clear winners and thereby, referring to Sun Tzu’s key principle in the Art of War, thereby “a battle where no one wins must be avoided.” A nuclear war and its implications have always been a source of inspiration for several authors and filmmakers. It stems from a deep fear of a “mutually assured destruction” of civilization as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doomsday Clock has been a representative of how far we are from a situation of nuclear war. The Doomsday Clock is updated by the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists based in Chicago and it has been maintained since 1947. The hypothetical global catastrophe is represented as “midnight” and the minute hand represents how far we are from that midnight. In 1991, post the Soviet collapse, it was the furthest away from the midnight, 17 minutes. The clock has been turned and has changed positions several times, 23 times to be precise, but never has it been more alarming than recently. In 2018, the clock was said to be only 2 minutes away from midnight due to the “looming possibility of climate change and nuclear war”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is funny how Metal fans can relate to it, as epitomised by a famous Iron Maiden song which was quite rightly called “2 minutes to midnight”. The chorus of the song carries a blatant warning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Hands that threaten Doom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two minutes to midnight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To kill the unborn in the womb”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I will not be referring to any political commentary by any world leader in reference to why this has been the most alarming period of human history. But this opportunity will be used to highlight why exactly we are not going to survive a nuclear holocaust if such a situation does arise in the future. We have come a long way since Dr. Oppenheimer’s infamous commentary after the success of the nuclear bomb testing, when he is supposed to have said (allegedly quoting the Bhagavad Gita) , &lt;em&gt;“I am become death, the destroyer of worlds”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we have become destroyers of worlds. The rate of development of nuclear technology peaked amidst the rising tensions during the Cold War, when certain ideologies involving the then Soviet Russia and United States put both of them in a collision course. It was an alarming period of time, but the tension peaked during the testing of the Soviet RDS-220 hydrogen Bomb, commonly known as the Tsar Bomba. The aspect which was truly alarming was that the bomb was named, in a rather unpopular manner, as Kuzma’s mother. This was believed to be a reference to Nikita Khrushchev’s statement in United Nations General Assembly in 1960, when he claimed that he would “show United States Kuzma’s mother”. He was intending to broach a Russian idiom which translates to, “we will show them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tsar Bomba was the most powerful explosive ever detonated, yielding a staggering 50 megatons of TNT. In fact, the initial plan envisioned of 100 megatons of TNT but that never happened, fortunately. The bomb was detonated at Sukhoy Nos cape of Severny Island, part of Novaya Zemlya. It was too big to be placed in a missile and too heavy for the planes to carry it with enough fuel. It was thereby carried in a release plane and the pilot Durnotsev and his crew were only given a dismal 50% chance of survival. The surprising fact was that the bomb which was expected to hit the ground was prevented from doing so by its own shockwave which reflected it back. The fireball was 8 km wide and was visible almost 1000 km away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mushroom cloud was about 64 km high—that is around 8 times the size of Mt. Everest. All buildings around a 55 km radius of ground zero were completely annihilated. It is said that a participant saw the bright flash from 270 km away with dark goggles and still felt the thermal pulse. In fact, the shockwave travelled the world around 3 times before it finally subsided. It was truly an alarming period of time in the midst of the show of power between nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is where the truly sinister shock is found. If an evaluation of the true capabilities of the Tsar Bomba is done, using the NUKEMAP software by Alex Wellerstein, if 10 of these bombs are used at key locations all around the world, around 2 billion of world’s population would get eliminated almost immediately. This does not even account for the long lasting effects of radiation and 3rd degree burns which several people will, inevitably, ultimately succumb to. Even a small scale nuclear war would have devastating effects on the planet. A research article by Dr. Mills proposes that even a local regional nuclear conflict, such as the India-Pakistan conflict would have devastating tolls on the planet’s ozone retention and protection capability. The ozone level would inevitably get decreased to alarming levels never before seen in human history, which would lead to a sudden fall in the Earth’s temperature, leading to possible frosts. Surface temperatures would go on decreasing for more than 25 years due to thermal inertia. This combination of cooling and less protection from the ozone layer would lead to enhanced UV rays from the sun, putting pressure on global food supplies that could lead to a global famine. This is only based on the assumption on equal use of artillery from both the sides though—which is clearly a very generous conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear war would have devastating effects on the planet’s resources and thereby would have a range of climatic effects which would surely spell doom for human civilisation. It is time we finally realized that there are no victors in this war. However, even the eradication of nuclear weapons places us in a catch-22 situation: There are no ways for the safe disposal of these weapons and a failure to handle them would only place them in the wrong hands. The technology which was expected to solve the energy crisis during the initial days of research has ended up being a nuisance of its own. War Games resonates with us as a cold reminder of a dystopia which lies beyond a nuclear catastrophe, that is if we survive it at all. Maybe with all the words and warnings, we could finally strive to push within us a sense of realization and maybe avoid the danger while there is still 2 minutes to the midnight.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The cold war science fiction movie War Games had a very cold yet direct message to its audiences and the dispatch remains important to us, even more so, at this point of time too. A nuclear war has no clear winners and thereby, referring to Sun Tzu’s key principle in the Art of War, thereby “a battle where no one wins must be avoided.” A nuclear war and its implications have always been a source of inspiration for several authors and filmmakers. It stems from a deep fear of a “mutually assured destruction” of civilization as we know it.</summary></entry></feed>