<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-25T12:46:18+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Money Tree</title><link href="/Money-Tree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Money Tree" /><published>2020-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Money-Tree</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Money-Tree">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why countries can’t just print more money to pay off their debts, to feed the homeless, to fix unemployment or for any other issue for that matter? This may seem like a rather silly question but I think it’s one of those questions that people may always wonder about but never ask. The answer can be summed up in just one word - inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inflation is defined as a persistent and substantial increase in the general level of prices related to an increase in the volume of money resulting in a loss of value of the currency, but I’ll get to that later. First, we need to establish what exactly money is. Now, this may seem obvious to many but we still need to clarify that money has absolutely no intrinsic value. This means money in itself is only considered valuable because it can buy things. But if you were stranded on an island, money would be totally useless. Money only has value because we believe it has value. It is called the ‘Tinkerbell Effect’. The tinkerbell effect is used to describe something that only exists because we believe it exists, and this is the case with money. Hypothetically speaking, if we suddenly start believing that money has no value, it wouldn’t have any value. Of course, it wasn’t always this way. Money as a concept has been around for thousands of years, and was first used in the form of commodity money, i.e things that had actual value and uses like salt, wheat, horses and weapons as well as precious metals such as gold and silver, which technically don’t have any intrinsic value either but due to the rarity they were almost universally accepted as currency. Then we have representative money, which makes more sense since carrying around everything you own can be difficult. Basically, you deposit your gold into a bank and they keep it safe for you and in return, they give you a piece of paper acknowledging that you own that gold. These pieces of paper can therefore be used as money. Anyone can go and redeem the gold at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, today almost every country in the world uses fiat money. Fiat money requires faith and trust in the government by the people. The people will have to value their money enough to use it for transactions. If we use a young country as an example, the United States has gone through all three monetary systems within 200 years. In 1790, when the United States stopped using European money as the Coinage Act of 1792 brought the inception of the US Dollar. USD was originally in the form of commodity money, in the form of gold, silver and copper coins. The coins were actually made from real gold, silver and copper, and the value of the metal that was used to make the coins was exactly equal to their face value. The country then moved on to a mixture of commodities and representative money with the Gold Standard Act of 1900. The government issued dollar bills that could be exchanged for gold anytime. The gold standard is a type of representative money that many countries used at the time. This was an effective way to accurately calculate the exchange rates between countries. For example - if one gram of gold costs £1 in Britain and $1.50 in America, then you can easily deduce that £1= $1.5. Later, gold coins were discontinued and silver was removed from other coins, effectively ending commodity money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1971, Richard Nixon officially abandoned the gold standard, and the US moved on to fiat money. So, money today isn’t backed by gold or anything else of value. Now, back to the question at hand: basic economics tells us that an increase in supply results in a fall in price. So, the more the money in the economy, the lower the value of each dollar. This means other countries can purchase more dollars in exchange for their currencies. A second supply and demand analysis shows why this leads to a rise in prices. More money in the economy causes a shift in the demand curve for goods and services, but since this isn’t matched by an increase in economic output, prices must rise. If we use an analogy to demonstrate this, imagine there are 4 people on a desert island, they have 10 pieces of fruit each. All fruits are considered equal in value. Now, imagine they discover a whole forest of apple trees. The total nominal value of the apples have increased because there’s more of them, but the actual value of an apple has gone down due to an increase in supply. Therefore, it now costs 10 apples for 1 banana since the demand for apples is low compared to its supply but the same is high for bananas. Just to make it clear, in this analogy, people represent different countries, the fruits their respective currency and the apple trees are the printed money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just because of economic theory that we know printing too much money is a bad idea, there are several examples throughout history. The most recent one is that of Zimbabwe, which in 2008 suffered extremely high inflation due to printing excess money. This was a result of some awful decisions by President Mugabe. When the economy took a turn for the worse, Mugabe printed more money to pay for government expenditure. This caused inflation to skyrocket and in mid-November 2008, Zimbabwe’s inflation peaked at 6.5 sextillion percent! To put that in perspective actually, first I need to provide some context. The inflation rate in the United States is around 1.5%. Economists generally agree that inflation levels around 1-3% are optimum. First world countries’ inflation rates range from 0 to 5%. A country is said to have entered hyperinflation when its inflation level exceeds 50%. So, with this in mind, Zimbabwe’s inflation at its peak got so bad that prices doubled every 24 hours. The government tried to solve the problem by printing more and more money with higher and higher denominations. They also kept knocking zeroes off the end by revaluing the Zimbabwean dollar 3 times, going through 4 different currencies with 4 different ISO codes. Before the final re-denomination, they were printing 100 trillion ZWR bills. People were literally using wheelbarrows full of cash to buy a loaf of bread. The government even made inflation illegal at one point and people were actually arrested for raising prices. In 2009, the Zimbabwean dollar was abandoned and till this day they still have no national currency, their people use currencies such as the US Dollar, the Pound sterling, or the Euro. Before the hyperinflation, the first Zimbabwean dollar was worth about $1.25. If the 100 trillion-dollar bill was worth that exchange rate, that single bill would be worth more money than there is in the entire world! But as ridiculous as this was, this is only considered to be the second-worst inflation in history after Hungary in 1946. Although Zimbabwe’s inflation peaked mid-November as of 2008, their overall highest monthly inflation was 79.6 billion percent which means prices doubled every 24.7 hours. Whereas Hungary’s highest monthly inflation took place in July 1946 which was 41.9 quadrillion percent with prices doubling every 15 hours. To put that in perspective, a country with a healthy inflation rate of around 3%, prices double every 23 years. In 1941, the exchange rate was about 5 Pengo to $1. In 1946, when the currency was discontinued, things had gotten so out of hand, that if you took every single banknote in the entire country, they would have a total value of one-tenth of a US Penny. Hungary then switched to the Fornit, where 1 Forint equaled 400 octillion Pengos. That number has 29 zeros!!! So, that’s why the government can’t just print money to pay off their debts, it does not end well. I’ll leave you with this final thought and what I think is possibly the best way to sum up why governments can’t just print unlimited amounts of money is &lt;em&gt;“If money grew on trees, wouldn’t it be as valuable as leaves?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Have you ever wondered why countries can’t just print more money to pay off their debts, to feed the homeless, to fix unemployment or for any other issue for that matter? This may seem like a rather silly question but I think it’s one of those questions that people may always wonder about but never ask. The answer can be summed up in just one word - inflation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spirituality and Marketing: An Amalgam</title><link href="/Spirituality-and-Marketing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spirituality and Marketing: An Amalgam" /><published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Spirituality-and-Marketing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Spirituality-and-Marketing">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Amalgam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is a highly inappropriate topic for the workplace, and only has an institutional connotation that manifests into the practice of rituals, adhering to dogmas and attending services. Spirituality, on the other hand, deals with life’s deeper motivations and an emotional connection to God and is a highly appropriate subject for discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that the world is smitten by the spirituality bug and marketing academics are oblivious of this development. Spirituality is increasingly impacting the beliefs and behaviours of consumers around the world. A &lt;em&gt;USA Weekend&lt;/em&gt; poll conducted in July 1998 revealed that 47% of Americans viewed spirituality as the most important element of their happiness. They care deeply about ecology and saving the planet, about relationships, peace, social justice, along with authenticity, self-actualisation, spirituality, and self-expression. They tend to be both inner-directed and socially concerned; they want to be activists, volunteers, and contributors to good causes. It’s 2020 and there is a massive influx of spiritual information, currently crowding the pages of popular newspapers, television programmes, and the glossiest mainstream magazines. Meditation classes are offered at the United Nations, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi uses visualisations and relaxation techniques to inspire the world, while political matters of spiritual and religious importance are the frequent subjects of public questioning and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have increasingly begun to use marketing as a spiritual practice to delve into a deeper wisdom, product offerings, and how they can help clients solve their problems. No jargon, no gimmicks, no trickery, just a deeper ‘wisdom’ in their marketing. Companies have started to use collaborative methods to co-vision with what the customer wants and help them see beyond their limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The root of spiritual marketing is clarity - the unwavering perception of how to do self-promotion. If you are clear about what you want and what you offer, your prospective customers will instantly know whether or not you offer what they need. A deep appreciation for a clear pricing strategy because consumers know the rule, &lt;em&gt;“if you have to ask how much, you probably can’t afford it”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have realised that spirituality is the human response to God’s gracious call to a one-on-one relationship with Him. Therefore, companies encourage customers to trust the transfer of their (profitable) divine goals and perceptions. What follows is a spiritual bond between the two parties where neither can survive without the other, built on a dynamic system of data projections from both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Big Fat Business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has mainstream spirituality gained popularity, but it has also become a big business. New age spirituality is a multi-billion-dollar industry, and some of the most popular contemporary spiritual teachers and gurus are among the wealthiest people in the world. Right from &lt;em&gt;“You can deprive the body, but the soul needs chocolate”&lt;/em&gt; to ‘Yoga-inspired athletic wear’ line of products, established companies and secular corporate firms are increasingly using spiritual appeals to identify and bond with consumers. It is one of the fast-growing industries. India’s estimated spiritual and religious market is over $30 billion. Studies have found that women comprise two-thirds of the active spiritual market consumers, particularly high income, educated, and middle-aged females but the men and youth market is also growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali  and Art of Living’s line of body care products and brands have created a niche for themselves in the market. The ageing of consumers in the western and Indian societies, coupled with their level of affluence, now permits them and the business community the luxury of seeking more meaning in their lives. Organisations like these are widening their reach in the production and distribution of these consumer goods. Furthermore some of these have entered into backward integration to source raw material as well. Once sold only at their &lt;em&gt;ashrams&lt;/em&gt; or particular outlets, today they can be found online or in supermarkets or even in &lt;em&gt;kirana&lt;/em&gt; stores. While FMCG companies need to invest a lot of time, effort, and money in branding and advertising their products, these spiritual gurus already have a huge number of devotees as their loyal consumer base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s to no surprise that such companies come up with unique, targeted and sound vocabulary and phraseology: “oneness”, “loving ourselves”, “we deserve”, “meditation”, “letting go”, “touching the void” among many others. Such marketing campaigns give an exotic edge, help unfurl competitive advantages, pep-up the spiritual image of the company, and facilitate the psychological transfer of ethics. Having a deep connection with clients and the community is what makes these business marketing techniques work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Magical World with Less Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the paucity of research on the topic of spirituality, bountiful opportunities and several interesting issues could be researched. For example, does the incidence of spirituality match with global macro-economic trends and how would these trends impact consumer behaviour and marketing practices? What is the relationship between rising incomes and economic development with the propagation of spiritually inspired ideas? Is spirituality increasingly used as a means of identity preservation and as a reaction to deterritorialisation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain these dynamics in the marketplace would require both strong qualitative and quantitative research. Scales that measure spirituality may be engineered by incorporating spiritual variables comprising both beliefs and practices. The need is to comprehensively conceptualise the concept of spirituality and delimit its boundaries so that its conflation with the concept of religion is not misunderstood and fairly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authentic spirituality is non-conceptual, and this presents a serious dilemma for spirituality in marketing for most of what attracts people is conceptual. Therefore, most authentic companies strike a balance between marketing and propagating non-conceptual bias, so that there is enough conceptualisation to hook people, but not too much to badly interfere with the marketing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said more simply, companies are all doing something inside themselves that is creating their outer results. Their inner state of being is creating their business or lack of it. Their inner spirit is doing their marketing. To paraphrase the famous Swiss psychologist Carl Jung, &lt;em&gt;“Until you make the unconscious conscious, it will direct your life and you will call it fate”.&lt;/em&gt; If you don’t consciously select where you want to go, you go where your unconscious wants you to go. Companies are having a great time skewing our unconscious minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today, spirituality in marketing is still a slippery construct, and only a systematic segmentation program of inquiry will provide meaningful and actionable insights. It’s a mystery yet, but if the business invests in its spiritual aspect, it will reap many unanticipated rewards, both financially and by gaining joy and bliss in doing their own business.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mehul Goyal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Amalgam</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?</title><link href="/Scottish-Independence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?" /><published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Scottish-Independence</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Scottish-Independence">&lt;p&gt;One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel Farage has often suggested that it would be illogical for Scotland to vote to become an independent country under Sturgeon’s leadership because a Scottish National Party (SNP) government would simply choose to pool Scottish sovereignty with Brussels instead of Westminster by re-joining the EU. Regardless of whether Farage’s point holds water, it might be more pertinent to turn his insight on its head: it was illogical, downright delusional in fact, to say Westminster would be totally sovereign over British laws after Brexit, because Parliament still governs the country alongside the regional assemblies in Edinburgh, Cardiff and Belfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-governance with the regional assemblies has been shown to be discordant ample times since ‘Brexit Day’ in January. The differing rules on the coronavirus lockdowns in the four nations of the UK have been immensely confusing, frequently smacking of plain political one-upmanship rather than proper scientific enquiry. On Brexit, it looks as if Sturgeon might disregard the government’s Internal Markets Bill and pass her own trade legislation, calling Johnson’s bill “a full-frontal assault on devolution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a constitutional expert, so I can’t say with certainty whether Sturgeon is right about that. But if the bill does in fact not represent overreach from Westminster, then part of the reason that Sturgeon can assert something which isn’t true is the fact that many of the terms of the relationship between Westminster and the devolved assemblies are poorly defined, arbitrary and hopelessly vulnerable to the transient whims of public opinion. Whilst most members of the commentariat have been focusing on making our relationship with the Europeans as stable and fruitful as possible, major instabilities within the British constitution have been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three devolved Parliaments are not like American state governments, the rights and jurisdictions of which are clearly laid out in the Constitution. If a state believes the Federal Government has overstepped the mark, the Supreme Court refers to the Constitution to assess whether overreach has occurred. All states have the same powers, and state governments are just as inherent a part of the US governance as the Federal government in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliaments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland, by contrast, were all created at different times, and all have slightly different powers. The devolved Parliaments can have their powers altered by the British government as long as the sitting Prime Minister desires it, and has a parliamentary majority to help him. After the Scottish independence referendum, David Cameron promised the Scots “devo-max”, as a way of responding to the close nature of the result. As a gesture of goodwill, he simultaneously enhanced the powers of the Welsh Assembly, but not to the same degree as the Scottish Parliament. However, he offered no explanation for why the Assembly in Cardiff would remain less powerful, or why he had interpreted nationalist fervour in Scotland as a clear sign that the Welsh were on the brink of drifting somewhere into the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the three Parliaments and its mothership in London resembles a rickety old building, the roof of which boasts a series of asymmetric and poorly built extensions. If a constitutional revolution did happen in Britain after 1945, it was devolution, not joining the EU. Random and arbitrary devolution has inhibited Westminster from governing the entire country far more than the European Commission ever did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, dysfunctionality doesn’t make the Scottish Parliament unconstitutional; the British Constitution is malleable and unwritten, which makes it much easier to change than the US Constitution. Ted Heath’s Tory government pooled our sovereignty with the Europeans in 1972 with a simple act of Parliament, thereby changing the British Constitution overnight. But just because something is constitutional doesn’t mean it works well. It doesn’t make it a good idea. The Internal Market Bill won’t be the last time that there are impasses in the years ahead, because the mandates of the Parliaments’ clash and their powers are far too easy to change. I’ve focused on Scotland here, but the potential for disaster in Northern Ireland is just as obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does the Prime Minister enter into the picture in all of this? He’s certainly having a torrid time dealing with Scotland at present. One year into his premiership, it’s obvious that he has few guiding principles. In truth, you didn’t need a year to see this. Whether Johnson’s love for the expedient would extend to advocating independence for Scotland is unlikely. But, privately at least, he must have clocked that not having to listen to those loudmouths over Hadrian’s Wall would definitely make his life easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like the job he’s doing (I count myself among you, by the way), then you might conclude you don’t mind that a by-product of our constitutional disorder is Johnson’s failure to deliver on his manifesto. What is worrying though, is that far from enhancing democracy in our country, devolution is compounding an incipient feeling that Britain is now ungovernable. I don’t blame Sturgeon for this; there is nothing wrong with scrutinising the government and its legislation, but there is an ocean of difference between careful scrutiny and institutional collapse. The former, essential to any democracy, was traditionally the responsibility of the opposition parties, the House of Lords, and an independent judiciary. The country was governed reasonably well with just one government. Creating three regional Parliaments on a whim and handing them new powers arbitrarily has simply led to a pile-up of different mandates, rather than improving accountability. If many different governments squabble over the right to govern, none of them &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; govern. In handing back power to our domestic governments, Brexit seems poised to unleash a crisis of democratic legitimacy far greater in severity than even itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paradiplomacy: A Catalyst for the Government?</title><link href="/Paradiplomacy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paradiplomacy: A Catalyst for the Government?" /><published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Paradiplomacy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Paradiplomacy">&lt;p&gt;We live in a highly globalised world that is undergoing a continuous transformation. That dynamism is especially true in the case of a modern state. The necessity to keep up with the dynamism creates space for a nation-state to employ modern tools to achieve its national interests. Modern states use such tools, for instance, soft power and public diplomacy, in foreign policy. Even as the primary objectives of diplomacy, the security of the state needs to be decided and implemented by the central authority, while other objectives can be implemented by a decentralised authority. One such decentralised tool of foreign policy is &lt;em&gt;paradiplomacy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Paradiplomacy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy can be defined as “foreign policy capacity of sub-state entities, their participation, independent of their metropolitan state, in the international arena in pursuit of their own specific international interests”. Therefore, paradiplomacy involves states (sub-unit of a country; not to be confused with nation-states) and cities as principal actors. Paradiplomacy, in contrast to the conventional foreign policy, makes space for the subnational units to engage in international relations in order to promote their own interests. Paradiplomacy, therefore, acts as a complement to a country’s efforts in carrying out its foreign policy. While the act of paradiplomacy is carried out by many sub-state actors across the world, the phenomenon is much more evident in federal states (e.g. the US and Canada) because the state units have a greater degree of autonomy. One such instance occurred in the US after President Donald Trump decided to withdraw from the Paris Climate Accord. Immediately after the decision was announced, twelve state governors came together to form the United States Climate Alliance to implement the Paris Agreement. 400 mayors across the US have also independently endorsed the accord on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is it Significant?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of paradiplomacy is significant for many reasons. One reason is that any agreement signed by the Central/Federal government cannot be successfully implemented without the cooperation of the state governments. Making the state governments a part of such discussion can yield better results. A second argument for paradiplomacy comes from the perspective of states bordering other countries. It is imperative for the border states to have better connections with their neighbouring countries. Any dispute that arises between two nations can be fruitfully resolved by engaging the border states in the discussions because most of the time these states either have grievances with or interests in solving disputes with the neighbouring nations. Another reason is that by letting the states engage in issues that deal with ‘low policy’, which include environmental issues, investment promotion, cultural and educational exchange, and more, a sense of competition could be fostered among the said states, and eventually, this would lead to better governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy in India is chaotic and less orderly. This is because the Indian Constitution gives the Central government exclusive control over all the matters pertaining to foreign affairs. It is interesting to note that the state governments, legally, are not even allowed to participate in any international conferences. There is no mechanism that allows the states to directly engage with international players. However, since the mid-1990’s, the state governments began to play a crucial role in foreign affairs. Two events facilitated this to happen. The first is the series of economic reforms launched by the Narasimha Rao government, and the second is the beginning of an era of coalition politics in the Indian political landscape. With the regional parties playing a significant role in the formation of the Central government, they started asserting themselves more vociferously; travelling abroad, entering into agreements, and signing memoranda of understanding independently. However, all such agreements still require the approval of the Central government to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;N Chandrababu Naidu, the former Chief Minister of Andhra Pradesh, travelled extensively across the world to sell the idea of Hyderabad as a technological hub and to attract foreign investments into the state. He travelled as many as six times in the nine years (1995-2004) that he was in power in the state. He succeeded in his effort as Microsoft established their office in Hyderabad and the Indian School of Business established their first-ever branch in India in Hyderabad. In 2014, after the partition of the state, upon becoming the Chief Minister once again, he visited Singapore and signed agreements to develop the new state’s capital. Gujarat is another state that has played a key role in the international arena. Narendra Modi, the then Chief Minister of Gujarat, had launched ‘Vibrant Gujarat’ which was a biennial summit with an objective of attracting foreign direct investments into the state. The summit has been a huge success since its launch, with many international dignitaries visiting the summit. It has also become a place for other Indian states to pitch themselves to various international actors. Apart from this, Narendra Modi, taking a cue from the Indian “Look East” policy, had travelled extensively to China, Japan, and Singapore to attract investments. More recently, the Gujarat government has signed a sister-city agreement for cooperation between Ahmedabad and Guangzhou city, in the Guangdong province in China. Furthermore, Telangana, another South Indian state, has also been playing a pivotal role too. Its success can be gauged from the fact that some of the world’s largest tech companies like Facebook, Apple, Microsoft and Amazon have their campuses in Telangana. The state had also signed sister-state agreements with New Jersey and California to extend cooperation ranging from investment promotion to tackling climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these are some of the positive developments, there are also some negatives that resulted due to the extra ‘enthusiasm’ of the states that proved deadly to India. One example is how West Bengal had stalled the Teesta river water treaty between India and Bangladesh. When the two countries had reached an agreement, it could not be signed due to stern opposition from the West Bengal Chief Minister Mamata Banerjee. Another example emerges from Tamil Nadu. When the United States moved a resolution at the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) against Sri Lanka seeking accountability for the horrific excesses of the country’s forces against the minority Tamil population, the Indian government facing pressure from the Tamil Nadu government, had to support the resolution. This had pushed Sri Lanka to move closer to China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy provides a framework for sub-national actors to assert themselves better. It effectively acts as a bridge between globalisation and regionalisation. For the Indian states too, there is a vast potential that the Indian states can exploit using paradiplomacy. Indian states until now have only been concerned with the economic aspect of paradiplomacy. They can also enter into agreements in the fields of tourism promotion, cultural exchange and urban planning. They can also enter into student exchange programs on behalf of public universities in their respective states, which will act as a mechanism for the Indian students to get exposed to bigger platforms or opportunities. Indian states can leverage their potential and use paradiplomacy to catalyse economic growth. All that is needed is the political will to act.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">We live in a highly globalised world that is undergoing a continuous transformation. That dynamism is especially true in the case of a modern state. The necessity to keep up with the dynamism creates space for a nation-state to employ modern tools to achieve its national interests. Modern states use such tools, for instance, soft power and public diplomacy, in foreign policy. Even as the primary objectives of diplomacy, the security of the state needs to be decided and implemented by the central authority, while other objectives can be implemented by a decentralised authority. One such decentralised tool of foreign policy is paradiplomacy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Battle of the Superpowers</title><link href="/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Battle of the Superpowers" /><published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers">&lt;p&gt;The two driving engines of the global economy have been locked in a trade war since July 6, 2018, with the United States imposing a 25% tariff on $34 billion worth of Chinese imports. While Trump claims tariff policy to be a practice to encourage the consumption of American products by making imported goods and services more expensive, it is, in fact, a tool adopted by the US to force China to make changes to its “unfair trade practices” (as termed by the United States). Economists are viewing this trade war as a by-product of the ongoing battle between the two nations for economic and technological world dominance, along with a wave of nationalism, protectionism, and self-reliance growing almost everywhere including the US. The trade war has adversely affected the economic growth of both China and the United States. With the onset of COVID-19, the grievances have increased and a sharp fall in the GDP has been observed in both the nations. The impact of the trade war is not limited to these two parties, the global economy too has witnessed a slowdown owing to the influence that the US and China possess on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial growth rate has hit its seventeen-year low in China, a clear indication of the heavy brunt being felt by China. The trade war continues to threaten the rising global economic influence of China and exerts downward pressure on Chinese economic growth. Experts on the Chinese economy view this war as fatal for business operations and believe that it is likely to leave a long-lasting adverse impact. They view it as the American leadership’s eloquence disguised for selfish national interests and the desire to maintain American hegemony, which has been at play ever since the States ended its cold war with the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR). The domestic reporting on the trade war is censored in China, the situation on the ground is difficult to comment upon, but Chinese social media has managed to throw some light on the adversities by drawing reference from the Marvel Comics wherein Thanos, the villain wipes out half of all the life in the universe using the infinity gauntlet (a superpower); similarly, Trump is believed to wipe out half of China’s investors and businesses using this superpower of tariff policy. The halt in the manufacturing sector in China can be observed by understanding these events from the Chinese industrial city, Dongguan. This sprawling manufacturing hub Dongguan, nicknamed as the ‘Workshop of the World’, is the hardest hit by the ongoing trade war. The impact isn’t limited to the manufacturing sector alone, food joints and other budgeted sources of entertainment in and around the industrial complexes of Dongguan have been shut down too, the bars that were mostly over-crowded during shift changes in the factories now accommodate empty chairs. Dongguan produces and exports a majority of chunk to the United States, and specialises in shoes and brightly coloured plastic bags (for detergents, candies, apparels, dog poop and other essentials needed by Americans in their daily lives), with a double-digit tariff on these goods, the loud noises of the machines in the factories have been muted. Workers residing nearby have begun to migrate back to their native home-towns as America shifts the hub to Vietnam and Indonesia, dropping China’s exports to the US (the country it exported more to than any other country) by 12%. The Chinese economy finds itself in a swamp due to a number of structural lags like the failing banking system, lack of low-skilled workers in the factories, economic over-reliance on manufacturing, ageing workforce, etc., followed by a trade war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tariff policy has not been a cake-walk for the United States too, with 3 million people losing their jobs, the US economy has come to a standstill. The consumers, businessmen, investors and farmers have expressed their dissent on the tariff policy inflicted by Trump’s administration. Though the effect felt on American exports is comparatively smaller than its Asian rival, a number of businesses and various industrialists in the manufacturing sector have felt the brunt. The lower profit margins have infuriated American companies and the farmers protested against the $24 billion worth market they lost in China as a result of retaliatory actions from the American rival in the Asian continent. While America explores new opportunities outside China to compensate for the goods it imported from the dragon, the prices continue to inflate in the American market. Is the trade war worth the pain it has caused to the American economy, which is in the worst shape since the Great Depression?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various emerging economies have been fortunate enough to draw the attention of the American, European and Japanese investors to import the substitutes from countries like Indonesia, Vietnam, Singapore, India and others. A switch in the wave of the global market shall take time to adjust and establish a smooth-sailing ride for the world, but at present, the European market is being strangled the most because of the uncertainty that prevails in the global market. The United States of America and the European Union have always worked in coordination and agreement in like-minded economic organisations and the US continues to be Europe’s most important trade and investment partner. Thus, America’s inward-looking policies have been a matter of great concern for the European countries as well. With the global wind against China amidst the blame-game for the pandemic and China’s furious economic behaviour in the market, the European continent cannot afford to turn its neck towards the Asian giant. Europe too has expressed its grievances on the unfair trade practices by China and has expressed its concerns over the theft of intellectual property by China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the EU can manage to carve its niche in the global market by accommodating the void the two rivals create in each other’s trade. Similarly, Britain too can utilise this opportunity to establish its financial and tech markets in Washington and profit from the growing dissent between the States and the Dragon. Apart from Europe, India too should utilise this opportunity by making a shift in its manufacturing sector as both the US and China are likely to shift their investment flow towards India. Indian exporters should definitely take the risk to explore the gap that the trade war will generate, as the US imposes higher tariffs on Chinese goods and vice versa, this is the most awaited chance for exporters to fiddle and find a space in both the markets. Xiaomi, known as China’s Apple (iPhone), has the largest market in India outside China, India can and should definitely use this opportunity to establish a strong profit margin for itself. While India gained about $775 million additional exports from the US, Apple is likely to shift its base for manufacturing in India, which would make it the largest assembler of iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade war has definitely teetered the global economy to uncertainties and an unprecedented slowdown, the global pandemic made it more difficult for the economies to survive this wind and stand tall in the global market. Whether America continues to maintain its hegemony or China will take over the global market, will remain an unanswered question for a while until the world revives and breathes into a fresh economic environment post the COVID-19 period.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The two driving engines of the global economy have been locked in a trade war since July 6, 2018, with the United States imposing a 25% tariff on $34 billion worth of Chinese imports. While Trump claims tariff policy to be a practice to encourage the consumption of American products by making imported goods and services more expensive, it is, in fact, a tool adopted by the US to force China to make changes to its “unfair trade practices” (as termed by the United States). Economists are viewing this trade war as a by-product of the ongoing battle between the two nations for economic and technological world dominance, along with a wave of nationalism, protectionism, and self-reliance growing almost everywhere including the US. The trade war has adversely affected the economic growth of both China and the United States. With the onset of COVID-19, the grievances have increased and a sharp fall in the GDP has been observed in both the nations. The impact of the trade war is not limited to these two parties, the global economy too has witnessed a slowdown owing to the influence that the US and China possess on the world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey</title><link href="/Russia-and-Turkey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey" /><published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Russia-and-Turkey</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-and-Turkey">&lt;figure style=&quot;margin-bottom: 2em&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Listen to this article:&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;audio-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/2020-09-17-Russia-and-Turkey.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of relations between Turkey and Russia has mostly been one of conflict rather than of peace. This could, of course, be said of Russia’s relations with most countries. But  this relationship merits a new examination since the pair is going through something of a détente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thawing of relations has been relatively quick. Four years ago, things were frosty. In Syria, Russia had just intervened on the side of the Assad government, whereas Turkey backed various rebel groups in the conflict. In 2015, the downing of a Russian fighter jet by the Turkish Air Force saw Russian President Vladimir Putin impose trade sanctions. The assassination of the Russian Ambassador to Turkey in Istanbul a year later, probably caused by Turkish Muslim objections to Putin’s intervention in Syria, exposed the deep rift between the nations with respect to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, though, the countries have shown greater willingness to cooperate. Putin and Turkey’s President Erdogan met regularly (a veritable &lt;em&gt;Guess Who&lt;/em&gt; of world tyrants), Russia ended its sanctions and visa restrictions against the Turks in May 2017, and Turkey purchased the S-400 missile system from the Russian government later that year. In spite of their differences over Syria, the two countries negotiated a ceasefire in Idlib province in March. Such a rapprochement, if it is to continue, will have important implications for Europe and the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Russia and Turkey are clearly a hybrid of the two continents they straddle, the relationship between them has always impacted Europe more than it has impacted Asia. The Crimean War was caused in large part because the Britain and France feared Russian encroachment on the crumbling Ottoman Empire. In the modern-day, the West looks upon the Russian-Turkish rapprochement with bewilderment because Turkey is a North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) member fraternising with the alliance’s traditional adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pertinent question to ask, then, is why the two countries are getting closer. Certainly, with regards to Syria, the countries have little reason to be cuddling with each other. My argument would be that the thawing of relations tells you little about what Russia and Turkey think of each other, but that it does show what both of them think about America, NATO and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin and Erdogan, like all great chauvinists, don’t just claim to rule nation-states, but entire cultures and civilisations. They are the Tsar and the Sultan reanointed. Among other things, this has meant that both have touted the idea of acting unilaterally on the world stage, and a central plank of this foreign policy has been bashing the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncomfortable truth is that NATO and the US have at times given the two leaders ample opportunities to paint the West as a bad-faith actor, especially in the case of Russia. NATO has been expanding eastwards into Russia’s sphere of influence since the end of the Cold War, not just into the Baltics but even into Georgia. US sanctions against Russia and Turkey, imposed in 2014 and 2019 respectively, hurt the economies of the countries and turned ordinary Russians and Turks even more firmly against the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may say that you don’t care much for either Putin or Erdogan, and that you don’t care if the two countries are turning towards each other. It turns out, however, that isolating these countries means that they look elsewhere in the world for allies. Not phased by Turkey? How about by China? Or Iran? Russia now enjoys a relatively friendly relationship with the Chinese, underpinned by trade. It has also moved closer to Tehran, shown earlier this year when the killing of Qasem Soleimani by the US prompted a deeply negative response from Vladimir Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If diplomacy is about anything, it is about choosing allies to support you against your enemies. The US evidently sees China and Iran as threats to the world’s international system. In the fight to contain these countries, Russia and Turkey could have been key allies, especially considering that the history of Russia and China isn’t friendly. In pushing Putin and Erdogan away, the US and NATO have bolstered their adversaries in the world. If the US wishes to intervene in Iran in the future, it will surely face opposition from Russia and Turkey. NATO is now powerless to influence events in Syria, having ostracised Turkey, the one member of the alliance capable of intervening quickly in the Levant. The US and Russia could have collaborated on containing China, in a manner reminiscent of how Nixon and Kissinger courted Mao to contain the Soviets. Sadly, China and Russia now seem to be beating the Americans at their own game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is that the US and NATO cannot stand alone in the world. They need allies. Russia and Turkey seem to understand what the US has forgotten: sometimes, you need to make deals with imperfect actors in order to heap pressure on genuinely malevolent ones. From the West’s perspective, I would put Putin and Erdogan in the former category, and the Chinese Communist Party and the Ayatollahs in the latter. In spurning Russia and Turkey, the US has made its objectives in the world much more difficult to achieve and has made these potential allies look much more adversarial and dangerous than they actually are.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Listen to this article: Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Japan’s Political Paradigm</title><link href="/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Japan’s Political Paradigm" /><published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm">&lt;p&gt;Shinzo Abe announced that he was resigning from his post on August 28, 2020. He stated that he was doing so in light of extreme health issues, and apologised to the people of Japan for failing to complete his term in the office and for leaving the nation in a period of political uncertainty. At the age of 65 years, Abe suffers from a chronic condition called ‘ulcerative colitis’, which he was diagnosed with when he was a teenager. It is an inflammatory bowel disease that has accentuated recently, prompting him to take this drastic precaution for his health. He had resigned even earlier in 2007 due to this condition. After this, his new period in the office started in 2012, and he has been loved by his people ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Abenomics’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A member of the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP), his reputation is that of a strong nationalist and conservative. His right tilted political front with the Liberal Democratic Party has boosted its popularity. Abe has led it in both the houses of Japanese Parliament. He has developed a stronghold in economic policy on a self-named programme known as ‘Abenomics’, which he introduced in 2012. An output plan to jumpstart Japan’s economy, it has been focussed on the stagnant growth of monetary policy, fiscal stimulus and structural reforms. The success of Abenomics has resulted in a double-edged sword with him aggressively focusing on the first two promises, yet sorely lacking in structural reform. Although his win in the consecutive elections has not been entirely because of this policy, it has played a crucial role. Mr Shinzo Abe has mostly been lauded for his representation as a modicum of stability in Japanese political history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abe’s Political Bandwidth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing a rare close personal relationship with Trump, demands erupted for him to pay more to support around 55,000 American troops on bases across the country. He has maintained a coalition of 11 countries around the Pacific Rim in a trade agreement called the Trans-Pacific Partnership. He had a firmer stance on North Korea in his foreign policy plans. In 2014, he developed Japan’s relationship with the Association of South-East Asian Nations and Australia. He became the first Japanese Prime Minister to attend India’s Republic Day parade as a Chief Guest. He had also maintained good relations with Xi Jinping, the supreme leader of China, before the pandemic and the Hong Kong protests. As stated by an Assistant Professor of Asian Studies at the University of Hawaii at Manoa, “&lt;em&gt;He managed to really elevate Japan’s profile on the international stage and make substantial changes in policy across a number of issue areas, and in Japan that is something we have not seen very often&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But right before his resignation, analysts have noticed that the majority were discontented with Abe. The way he handled the coronavirus outbreak in Japan, and in particular its effects on the economy, undid the fame of what Abenomics achieved. A holistic assessment of his tenure has revealed that he prioritised stability over high-handed risks of huge transformations, which is what helped him rise to power and assured him an important position in Japanese history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yoshihide Suga&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Yoshihide Suga has a central role as the Chief Cabinet Secretary in the current administration. The LDP announced on September 14, 2020, that he will be the direct successor of Shinzo Abe as Prime Minister of Japan. This comes as a surprising announcement because there are many leading Japanese lawmakers who are direct descendants of elite political families, but Mr Suga isn’t one of them. Part of his charisma is that he has worked his way up from his middle-class upbringing to such a position. He held his position alongside Shinzo Abe for a long time, signifying his role in continuing Abe’s legacy. Years of gaining shadow power will result in his abilities to handle the top position, as his victory in the LDP has illuminated his formidable political skills. However, there have been glimpses of his politics that have concerned some critics. He is said to have been behind some of Abe’s most authoritative decisions, including consolidating power over Japan’s bureaucracy, and tactics to silence criticism in the media. But despite apprehension from certain voices, more than half the nation supports his takeover as the subsequent Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he has already epitomised a status quo, Mr Suga has been a major catalyst for national change. He has pushed through some contentious security laws that have allowed for Japan’s military power to join overseas combat missions alongside its allies. His vision for Japan will muster fresh outlooks on the country’s deepest problems and challenges. He has proclaimed to pursue some of Abe’s cherished goals that he couldn’t complete. This includes the completion of a revision of Japan’s pacifist Constitution and a promise for the return of Japanese citizens that North Korea had kidnapped. With the global turbulence from the pandemic and the gradually increasing geopolitical threats in Asia, Japan needs a successor such as Mr Suga to run its course by re-establishing a stable political backdrop. Best described by his high school classmate Hiroshi Kawai in Mr Suga’s hometown Yuzawa City, “&lt;em&gt;We have such proverbs as ‘great talents are slow to mature’ and ‘a wise falcon hides its talons’, now I realised that those words were created for Mr Suga&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Shinzo Abe announced that he was resigning from his post on August 28, 2020. He stated that he was doing so in light of extreme health issues, and apologised to the people of Japan for failing to complete his term in the office and for leaving the nation in a period of political uncertainty. At the age of 65 years, Abe suffers from a chronic condition called ‘ulcerative colitis’, which he was diagnosed with when he was a teenager. It is an inflammatory bowel disease that has accentuated recently, prompting him to take this drastic precaution for his health. He had resigned even earlier in 2007 due to this condition. After this, his new period in the office started in 2012, and he has been loved by his people ever since.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?</title><link href="/Stocks-Rallying-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?" /><published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Stocks-Rallying-Again</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Stocks-Rallying-Again">&lt;p&gt;Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus outbreak got worse day-by-day and even now cases are rising every day although if you see the popular stock market indices, they are again back to the point where they were before March lows. A rally is bringing the indices back to their pre-March levels. Are the economies getting better? No. Have we recovered from the virus? No. Is GDP growth recovering? NO, instead most of the nations have announced contraction in GDP and are further expecting it to contract till 2021. Why have stocks been moving up again then? Let’s find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries worldwide went under complete lockdown. People tried looking for sources of income during this time and as the stock market never sleeps people turned to stocks to earn something in their free time. Everyone became a trader. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z&quot;&gt;Robinhood&lt;/a&gt; trading app, the most popular stock trading app in the US that charges zero commission, saw a rise in new account openings during the lockdown. The revenues of Robinhood have doubled in a quarter which clearly shows that retail participation has risen and is continuing to rise as we speak. Retailers with no knowledge of stocks, futures and options are trading just for the sake of earning some extra income during their free time and are buying stocks like grocery items, which is one of the main reasons for the rally of stock indices. All market indicators show that the market is overbought and a second wave of crash is due. Big retailers on seeing a big fall in the market start selling stocks to average out their price, and when they enter the market after a fall, it helps the market to regain again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the big question arises: where do we invest our money right now? Seeing a crash due in the market again, and positive signs not being visible in the short term for the economy, it is best to have a diversified portfolio. Over the years, the investment that is the most promising is gold but becoming wealthy through gold is almost unheard of. Seeing the current scenario one must have around 15-20% of his/her investment in gold, paper gold is preferred as you don’t have to keep it safe and don’t have to worry about it. Around 30% of the portfolio should be in mutual funds (Systematic Investment Plan) and 25% should be allocated to equities that too in ‘blue-chip’ stocks because right now profitability of companies is not important, the most important thing is survival and these companies have a huge amount of capital backing. If you want higher returns then you can switch to mid-caps and small-caps too, but your risk increases as well. 10% should be invested in very safe investments like fixed deposits for safe and a minimum guaranteed return. The remaining portfolio can be kept as cash-in-hand, and then one can wait for dips and add stocks of their choice. This portfolio investment has been advised for people who want to take moderate risk with decent returns. If you wish, you can go for high risk by allocating more to equities and if you want less risk then decrease your dependence on equities. Therefore, investing in such turbulent times depends totally on a person’s risk appetite and the depth of his pockets. No one can predict the movement of markets in such unprecedented times. It would be better to have a well-diversified portfolio and not expose yourself too much to a particular type of investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rachit Kumar</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Past and Future of the Future Group</title><link href="/Past-Future-Future-Group" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Past and Future of the Future Group" /><published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Past-Future-Future-Group</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Past-Future-Future-Group">&lt;p&gt;Kishore Biyani, the retail maverick of India, was the man who took the retail industry by storm. He realised the potential of retail, which oligarchs like the Ambanis and Birlas could not appreciate, and therefore came up with household names like Pantaloons, FBB and Big Bazaar. He is often referred to as the Sam Walton (the owner of Walmart) of India. However, recently, Reliance Industries (RIL) bought Biyani’s Future Group for a whopping ₹247 billion. Let’s understand why Mr Biyani had to sell off his dream, but for starters, let’s get acquainted with his story of rags-to-riches before getting onto the bad part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kishore Biyani, the current pin-up kid of the Indian retail industry, has assumed numerous jobs, however in the long run, he settled to turn into an inventive retailer. In contrast with numerous others of his class, Kishore wasn’t brought into the world with the proverbial silver spoon in his mouth and has, without any help, ascended the halls of India’s business elite. Nevertheless, coming from a family of businessmen, business flowed in his blood. He always knew that he would end up becoming a businessman because of his mindset and his ability to understand the customer. In order to understand the real world and to interpret the consumer’s nerve, he was often seen spending time visiting various shops rather than studying. His career actually started when he neared the end of his graduation by joining his family business Bansi Silk Mills, which traded fabrics. Though he used to go to his office, he wasn’t getting the kick which he wanted. He was unable to feel the enthusiasm and opportunity and was feeling quieted by the organisation’s moderate business culture and used to leave within 2 or 3 hours. He was totally against the manner in which the organisation worked and felt that their demeanour and approach towards the business wasn’t right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he was meeting his friends, he noticed them wearing ‘stonewashed’ fabric, he promptly acted on this new information and contacted a few mill owners and sold it to the garment dealers. Kishore had tasted blood and now he wanted more! He frantically began to search for something new, something other than what’s expected. He launched his own brand of fabric for men’s trousers called, WBB – White, Brown, and Blue. In 1987, he started his own garment manufacturing company, Manz Wear Private Ltd, which he sold under the brand name Pantaloons (he chose the name Pantaloons because it gave the feel of an Italian Fashion House and secondly because it was closer to &lt;em&gt;patloon&lt;/em&gt;, an Urdu word for trouser). During the preliminary stages, Biyani went through a difficult phase as banks didn’t want to extend him loans, family and friends were also sceptical about the business. But &lt;em&gt;“it was fun”&lt;/em&gt; for him as he steered through the rough phase like a sailor with unbridled confidence and faith in himself. In 1992, he entered the stock market to fuel the car. After raising money, he went on a spree to open Pantaloons stores pan India along with some marketing campaigns and by the end of 1994 Pantaloons laid eggs worth ₹6 million annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After tasting initial success with Pantaloons, he forayed into the supermarket business with the brand name Big Bazaar, wooing its core customers into large self-service supermarkets and leveraging his own supply and logistics chain to offer across-the-board discounts on maximum retail prices. Big Bazaar was formed on three pillars of Kishore’s ideology- Food, Fashion, and FMCG. You went to get a few vegetables, yet you needed to go through walkways of kurtas and dresses, and were enticed to purchase them. For budget clothing, Biyani launched the FBB design brand. Future Groups Home Center stores were also launched to force people to redesign their homes with the Future Group. The group also forayed into the tech retail sector with the e-zone varying media item stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the offset of the story, everything seems spick and span but on the inside, the finances weren’t going great. He produced a few films between 2002 and 2003 which turned out to be huge flops. While he was growing at break-neck speed and success seemed to be touching his feet, all the acquisitions and the more than frequent opening up of stores, took him into bucket loads of debt. In fact, in 2012 he sold his flagship Pantaloons retail format to Aditya Birla Group for an estimated ₹16 billion at a time when the group had accumulated a consolidated debt of ₹78.50 billion. In 2014, Future Group acquired the south-based Nilgiris chain of markets for ₹3 billion. In 2011, Foodhall, an upmarket food store, found in luxurious shopping malls, was conceptualised by Biyani’s elder daughter, Avni Biyani. In 2016, a couple of years after Walmart and Bharti Airtel  headed out in different directions and failed to set up retail stores as was agreed under their deal, the Future Group took a plunge and purchased the Bharti Airtel’s Easyday chain of supermarkets. A year ago, it trimmed more than 100 Easyday stores, in an endeavour to cut costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is imperative to think that Mr Biyani tried to put his hands in almost everything from insurance to fashion. But the fact is that it was the fashion outlets which outdid every other business he had. Had he stuck to what he was good at, he would not have had to see these days. It’s not that he shouldn’t have diversified but at a steady pace rather than foraying into every other segment at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon, which had announced an Indian war chest of $5.54 billion, and Flipkart, which further got strengthened after its buyout by Walmart, were wooing customers across all retail segments. Biyani tried to stick with his core competence customers: the middle-income Indians who preferred to shop in physical stores. Sadly, the customer had tasted the best of both worlds, and were swiftly moving online. Future Group tried but missed the e-commerce opportunity largely because of the promoter’s scepticism of making money on selling goods online. In 2017, the Future Retail also unveiled its ‘Retail 3.0’ platform that would enable tech to merge with offline retail. But it was too late as players were already established and people were happy buying from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we can say the speed of expansion, acquisition of several retail assets — both regional and national, a chase to build more private labels and in-house manufacturing capabilities have left the company burdened with debt, and caused rating downgrades across the group’s listed entities. As of September 30, 2019, the combined debt of Future Group’s listed companies increased to ₹127 billion from ₹109 billion as of March 31, 2019. His debt woes were further exacerbated by the lockdown, wherein businesses were stalled but he had to keep servicing his debt. Finally, RIL acquired the retail and wholesale business, and the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot can be said about Mr Biyani but he believed in the ‘Indian Dream’; he always wanted to help the Indian dream fly high and wanted to ensure that the &lt;em&gt;‘Sone Ki Chidiya’&lt;/em&gt; (Golden Bird) soared once again. We’re left with one question: will Biyani bounce back? Too early to tell. He is a brand and I’m optimistic enough that he’ll come back sooner and much stronger!!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aditya Khandelwal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Kishore Biyani, the retail maverick of India, was the man who took the retail industry by storm. He realised the potential of retail, which oligarchs like the Ambanis and Birlas could not appreciate, and therefore came up with household names like Pantaloons, FBB and Big Bazaar. He is often referred to as the Sam Walton (the owner of Walmart) of India. However, recently, Reliance Industries (RIL) bought Biyani’s Future Group for a whopping ₹247 billion. Let’s understand why Mr Biyani had to sell off his dream, but for starters, let’s get acquainted with his story of rags-to-riches before getting onto the bad part.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century</title><link href="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century">&lt;p&gt;The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fintech company incorporated in 1999, joined the Frankfurt stock exchange in 2005 and ascended to the ranking of Germany’s 30 leading companies, also known as the DAX Index. It claimed to have subsidiaries across the globe, with payments being processed for more than 200,000 merchants and clients including major European supermarket chains and airlines. It attracted notable investors such as SoftBank. Wirecard was like any other payment processing company that facilitated transactions between consumers and merchants, and earned a certain percentage per transaction. However what set the company apart from its competitors was its rapid expansion in Asia for the reason that it marketed itself as the leader in this system, claiming to have superior technology and highly capitalising on the shift to a cashless society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, the first allegations of accounting irregularities against the firm came to light and in the wake of the attack, the company appointed Ernst &amp;amp; Young (EY), one of the largest accounting enterprises in the world, to conduct a special audit on these claims. EY soon then became the Chief Auditor of the organisation for the next 10 years, signing off the firm’s balance sheet. As allegations against the firm of inflating its operational numbers in Asia continued to surface over the years, a pattern emerged with how the company dealt with these criticisms. They would aggressively deny any wrongdoings and announce that it was an attempt to manipulate their stock prices. However, the stock prices kept rising, undeterred by any negative news coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As claims of malpractice mounted, BaFin- the German financial regulator, during its probe focussed more on the accusers rather than the claims against the enterprise. Various analysts believe that authorities’ protection stemmed as it was a huge moment to see a European home-grown company competing against tech titans of Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the regulator announced an unprecedented 2-month ban on short-selling of the company’s shares due to its stock price plummeting below €100, citing its importance to the economy and serious threats to market confidence. Some also point to Germany’s corporate culture being wary of foreign speculators, since many allegations were brought forward by the British newspaper &lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt;). However, the regulators denied all allegations against the organisation and even filed a criminal investigation against &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; for colluding with short-sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wirecard mainly functioned by buying shell companies that acted as third party payment processors for the organisation. In return, these companies paid them a commission. However, instead of funds flowing into their Munich bank, it was all transferred to escrow accounts. These are special accounts where multiple parties can use them, hence convincing the public that large sums of money existed in them and were used by its subsidiaries. These accounts held more than $2 billion, all of Wirecard’s profit of more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; published an article after being alerted by a whistle-blower, that the organisation was cooking accounting books, hiking up its sales and profit numbers of Asia and Pacific operations. Hence, to put an end to these allegations, the company, in 2019, hired Klynveld Peat Marwick Goerdeler (KPMG) to conduct a special audit. The audit report stated that it could not verify the authenticity of these escrow accounts. As more events unfolded, the company stated that all of the money was stored in the Philippines, and not in these escrow accounts. When EY went to examine these claims from the Philippines bank, the former was notified that the documents submitted by the company were all spurious and money never really entered their financial system, thus the $2.1 billion never existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This announcement led to the arrest of Markus Braun, CEO and CTO of Wirecard since 2002, on June 23, 2020, on suspicion of inflating the value of the company through feigning business with third parties. Two days later, the company filed for insolvency, making it the biggest accounting scandal in post-war German history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disclosure of malpractice of such a magnitude has eroded the trust in the country’s authorities, giving a heavy blow to Germany’s reputation as a financial centre - impacting its businesses and the confidence of market participants. This revelation has increased the scrutiny of not only accounting firms, especially EY, for failing to inspect the legitimacy of such an account, but also on regulators for their inadequacy. Various critics argued that Germany’s regulatory system is neither equipped to handle large scale processing enterprises like Wirecard nor does it have the power to oversee the investigation of potential malpractices. This highlights the need for transparency in financial systems and various regulatory reforms such as incentives for whistleblowers, a better framework for fintech companies, etc. With the expansion of inquiry, more details are yet to come, nonetheless, investigators worldwide are trying to comprehend how the company used the loopholes to present itself as a profitable business for more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?</summary></entry></feed>