<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-10T21:06:16+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Teasing Bellies to Fill Pockets</title><link href="/Teasing-Bellies-to-Fill-Pockets" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teasing Bellies to Fill Pockets" /><published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Teasing-Bellies-to-Fill-Pockets</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Teasing-Bellies-to-Fill-Pockets">&lt;p&gt;All-you-can-eat (AYCE) restaurants charge a fixed price for access to food, and they allow customers to consume as much food as their heart desires at no extra charge. Simply put, consumers are charged a specified price regardless of how much food they consume. From “&lt;em&gt;Feast unlimited this Monday at Barbeque Nation; lunch at ₹399 and dinner at ₹499&lt;/em&gt;” to sell tandoori feasts in India, to “&lt;em&gt;$24.99 all you can eat buffets&lt;/em&gt;” in Las Vegas as a lure to bring hungry patrons into casinos, AYCE has its roots everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, managers may have several motivations for offering such flat-rate pricing. While some are driven by competitive pricing pressures that may lead to zero marginal cost of production, others seek to reduce costs such as labour by employing a smaller wait staff, made possible by the emphasis on self-service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have ever had an awful stomach after you thought you struck gold at the buffet, you might have just wondered how restaurants manage to keep up their bottom line while you think you seemingly rob them in broad daylight. As you can guess, it is definitely not a loss for the restaurants. They indeed make hefty profits from this scheme. Besides being an ingenious piece of marketing, such restaurants became so popular owing to their wide selection of food and to the freedom given to customers to choose their own portions. People skip their breakfast and lunch to have a buffet dinner. They come with the mentality that they are going to earn their value for money. But little do they know that they come out on the losing side of it, mostly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How then do buffets manage to create and maintain a winning environment whilst also keeping their customers elated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To shed light on how this concept leaves restaurants with money requires an examination of some fundamental microeconomics, psychology and what magic a careful blend of both can do. The high-skilled and trained managers in the hotel industry have succeeded in hitting this sweet spot and manage to leverage customer satisfaction and generate profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Law of Diminishing Marginal Utility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A law inherent to every Econ 101 class. The crux is that the additional benefit we feel from consumption (be it of cake, cigarettes or coffee) decreases as we consume it. You won’t have the same satisfaction from the last bite you have as you have from the first time eating it (your fifth slice of pizza, although good, just doesn’t taste as good as the first). Additional utility (benefit) from the last slice of pizza will be less than that from the first and this goes on until you have a negative utility for each slice that you consume (nobody enjoys a 25th slice, probably). People go to the buffet with a set mentality of making the most of their money. They want to maximise their satisfaction i.e. eat till they drop. However, again with the prospect of an unlimited buffet, their greed takes over and once their satisfaction is maximum, it slowly becomes negative i.e. the satisfaction derived from the buffet initially rises, then becomes maximum, and then falls. This is nothing but the law of Diminishing Marginal Utility. This is why you see exasperated faces after a buffet when people overshoot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this tells us is that no matter what the price paid for a buffet is, you can only continue eating until your satiation point is reached. We’ll see how restaurants are masters at taking you there, quickly and cheaply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunk Costs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In economics and business decision-making, a sunk cost is one which is incurred and cannot be recovered. You’ve invested the money and nothing can be done to take it back. For this reason, sunk costs should not affect decision-making. If the money’s already gone then it should not be affecting our future decisions. But in reality, people let this influence them. People have a habit to chase their losses, unable to quit and move on. We see it predominantly among gamblers, always chasing a winning bet to recoup earlier mistakes. We also witness it in business, it’s the same reason that investors continue with a loss-making entity. They don’t see a world beyond their already sunk dollars. When we buy a ticket to a buffet, we also face the same dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because a customer faces no marginal cost of consumption, conventional utility maximisation implies that he or she should continue to eat until the marginal utility of consumption reaches 0. Economic models of consumer behaviour commonly assume that the utility of consumption is unaffected by the price paid. Rather, the price affects consumption only through a budget constraint. So, in an AYCE setting, price should influence whether one chooses to eat at the restaurant, but it should not affect the amount of food one consumes. But various experiments and test results have proven that price determines the personal evaluation of certain food and indirectly affects consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Food and Brand Lab at Cornell University conducted an experiment to see how the price of a buffet influenced customers. They offered two groups of customers the same pizza buffet, and charged one group $4, while the other group was charged $8. The group who paid more was overwhelmingly more satisfied with the entire experience. We are driven by our personal conception of value for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of revealing this is to demonstrate the sunk cost fallacy in an AYCE context. In an AYCE setting, price positively influences consumption. Additionally, consumption appears to be negatively related to individual evaluations of taste. In contrast to the standard utility model, this provides support to the notion that individuals consider price in evaluating their marginal utility of consumption, even when there is no marginal cost for additional consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more the buffet charges, the more you think the buffet is good. Hence, the buffet is charged more and you still think the buffet is good and within all this, restaurants jump in and book their profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Concept of Bounded Rationality and the Bandwagon Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bounded rationality is the idea that rationality is limited when individuals make decisions by the tractability of the decision problem, the cognitive limitations of the mind, and the time available to make the decision. It is similar to an inability to make a sagacious decision when bombarded with multitudes of options (as in a buffet) leading us unable to follow rational predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bandwagon effect is the tendency of an individual to acquire a particular style, behaviour or attitude because everyone else is doing it. It is a phenomenon whereby the rate of uptake of beliefs, ideas, fads and trends increases with respect to the proportion of others who have already done so. Usually, in a buffet, some items come out to be clear winners and almost everyone starts having more and more of the same, the customers recommend the same to the people they are having lunch/dinner with, who in turn again start having more of the product. This creates a bandwagon effect, people will quickly consume a few items thereby saving the restaurant’s cost on all others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When choices are abundant, rationality is limited, and people have a tendency to follow the bandwagon, the result is skewed option picking. Some dishes emerge to be the most wanted and are generally those that are in abundant supply. Usually, dishes that are cooked in large vessels with cheap ingredients. Hence the restaurant saves on the more expensive dishes and the cost is limited yet again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economies of Scale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economies of scale are cost advantages reaped by companies when production becomes efficient. Companies can achieve economies of scale by increasing production and lowering costs. The larger the business, the more the cost savings. Buffets are large production businesses. A restaurant buffet achieves economies of scale by producing in large quantities, spreading its costs over a larger number of dishes, even though it often demands a serious cut in food quality. Because of tight profit margins, the food quality becomes a second priority. However, this doesn’t matter, they have their footfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, lesser personnel need to be deployed for a buffet. As a result, the restaurant makes large savings in employment costs. These overhead savings are one of the crucial areas in which buffets differ from traditional restaurants. That's because you are doing most of the work for them - and paying for the privilege. You serve yourself, and in some places, you might even get your drinks. This means there's next to no need for waiting staff. And since the menu relies heavily on a series of regular dishes which are prepared in advance, they can hire fewer and cheaper chefs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heck, at some buffets like Korean BBQ places, the customers are even doing the cooking as well as the serving!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you know the economics, you may have the power of defying these principles and &quot;beating the buffet’. Defy the diminishing marginal utility function. Be wise and judge your taste buds independent of price. Be rational and avoid the bandwagon. But buffet designers know this. While most people will be modest, some people will try to get &quot;all-they-can-eat&quot; and go for a ton of pieces of cottage cheese. Some don’t stop from piling it up vertically or going back for another plate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, buffets must cut corners in other ways to make sure they aren't losing out. They achieve this by teasing you in clever ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategic Layouts and Secret Nudges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buffets invest a lot of time into developing the right layout.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expensive items are cut into smaller pieces. Cheap, filling foods such as your salads, veggies, rice and noodles are served at the beginning, offering the consumer the opportunity to load up before the ‘luxury’ items. Relatively expensive offerings will be surrounded by four or five cheaper veggie side dishes, and pricier desserts like cakes will be surrounded by platters of fruit. Coupled with larger serving times for expensive items, buffets usually nudge you to take up the cheaper, more available, readily in flow food items. You can grab a ladle-full of rice and veggies any instant, but when it comes to those small pizza slices, you wait for your turn in line. They'll take longer to get on your plate, and most people don't like the pressure of holding up a line, so they tend to move quickly through. Also, pans with more expensive foods are generally less full — a subtle encouragement to take less, a nudge, while cheap ingredients will be served in giant, overflowing pans. Those are plenty for all, and people like that. They like to believe that must be the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest factors impacting your eating habits at a buffet is the cutlery you're given. You'll seldom see full-sized dinner plates or actual soup bowls. Instead, you'll be given small plates and even tiny dessert bowls to limit the amount of food you take. Restaurant suppliers know this, and buffets even purchase miniature tableware specially designed for buffets. This even includes purchasing silverware, which tends to be smaller — but not small enough you'd notice unless you already know their sneaky tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, buffets will keep extra sweet desserts, so clients are satisfied with lower portions. Complementary to this, buffets will usually have huge water and soft drink glasses. They need you to be full of soda that costs a penny. The more you drink, the less you eat, the more the restaurant saves. For a lot of buffets, things like vegetables, potatoes and rice are staple dishes. That's because they are both super cheap and extremely filling. Buffets entice you into indulging on salads before the meat because salad is cheaper and quickly fills plate space. &lt;em&gt;Psychology Today&lt;/em&gt; took a look at what's occurring in the buffet line, and they call this the &quot;fill the customer's belly cheaply&quot; metric. But remember, if you are truly there to make the most of your money, these items will only fill you up with nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its crudest level, the AYCE buffet restaurant manager’s primary job is simply to fill the customer’s stomach as cheaply and quickly as possible. Minimising waste by using computational data analytics to figure out the customers’ eating habits go a long way in cutting costs. Coupled with the power of using cheap ingredients to prepare worthwhile dishes, AYCE buffets tease your bellies to fill their pockets. But to satisfy customers and bring them back, buffet managers can’t stop there. They must create the perception of providing ample variety and high-quality food items. At the same time, they must manipulate customers’ choices and portion sizes, and ensure that food waste is minimised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With just a few tricks, such as using smaller plates, putting cheap items towards the front, and using drinks to off-set other costs, all-you-can-eat restaurants can accomplish the same goal as any other restaurant: get people in the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you may not want to take the &quot;all-you-can-eat&quot; part quite so literally. People can and have been banned from buffets for eating too much food. For instance, a Wisconsin man named Bill Wisth was not only banned but had the cops called on him for abusing his local buffet. So, before you go back for that fourth slice of pizza, ask yourself how much you might like the taste of jail food. Because the buffets there aren't nearly as good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for a recap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did I teach you about buffet strategy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Grab a small-sized drink and a large-sized plate, start with your high-end entrée, skip veggies and carbs and yeah, ride your own bandwagon.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mehul Goyal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">All-you-can-eat (AYCE) restaurants charge a fixed price for access to food, and they allow customers to consume as much food as their heart desires at no extra charge. Simply put, consumers are charged a specified price regardless of how much food they consume. From “Feast unlimited this Monday at Barbeque Nation; lunch at ₹399 and dinner at ₹499” to sell tandoori feasts in India, to “$24.99 all you can eat buffets” in Las Vegas as a lure to bring hungry patrons into casinos, AYCE has its roots everywhere. In practice, managers may have several motivations for offering such flat-rate pricing. While some are driven by competitive pricing pressures that may lead to zero marginal cost of production, others seek to reduce costs such as labour by employing a smaller wait staff, made possible by the emphasis on self-service. If you have ever had an awful stomach after you thought you struck gold at the buffet, you might have just wondered how restaurants manage to keep up their bottom line while you think you seemingly rob them in broad daylight. As you can guess, it is definitely not a loss for the restaurants. They indeed make hefty profits from this scheme. Besides being an ingenious piece of marketing, such restaurants became so popular owing to their wide selection of food and to the freedom given to customers to choose their own portions. People skip their breakfast and lunch to have a buffet dinner. They come with the mentality that they are going to earn their value for money. But little do they know that they come out on the losing side of it, mostly. How then do buffets manage to create and maintain a winning environment whilst also keeping their customers elated? To shed light on how this concept leaves restaurants with money requires an examination of some fundamental microeconomics, psychology and what magic a careful blend of both can do. The high-skilled and trained managers in the hotel industry have succeeded in hitting this sweet spot and manage to leverage customer satisfaction and generate profits. Law of Diminishing Marginal Utility A law inherent to every Econ 101 class. The crux is that the additional benefit we feel from consumption (be it of cake, cigarettes or coffee) decreases as we consume it. You won’t have the same satisfaction from the last bite you have as you have from the first time eating it (your fifth slice of pizza, although good, just doesn’t taste as good as the first). Additional utility (benefit) from the last slice of pizza will be less than that from the first and this goes on until you have a negative utility for each slice that you consume (nobody enjoys a 25th slice, probably). People go to the buffet with a set mentality of making the most of their money. They want to maximise their satisfaction i.e. eat till they drop. However, again with the prospect of an unlimited buffet, their greed takes over and once their satisfaction is maximum, it slowly becomes negative i.e. the satisfaction derived from the buffet initially rises, then becomes maximum, and then falls. This is nothing but the law of Diminishing Marginal Utility. This is why you see exasperated faces after a buffet when people overshoot. What this tells us is that no matter what the price paid for a buffet is, you can only continue eating until your satiation point is reached. We’ll see how restaurants are masters at taking you there, quickly and cheaply. Sunk Costs In economics and business decision-making, a sunk cost is one which is incurred and cannot be recovered. You’ve invested the money and nothing can be done to take it back. For this reason, sunk costs should not affect decision-making. If the money’s already gone then it should not be affecting our future decisions. But in reality, people let this influence them. People have a habit to chase their losses, unable to quit and move on. We see it predominantly among gamblers, always chasing a winning bet to recoup earlier mistakes. We also witness it in business, it’s the same reason that investors continue with a loss-making entity. They don’t see a world beyond their already sunk dollars. When we buy a ticket to a buffet, we also face the same dilemma. Because a customer faces no marginal cost of consumption, conventional utility maximisation implies that he or she should continue to eat until the marginal utility of consumption reaches 0. Economic models of consumer behaviour commonly assume that the utility of consumption is unaffected by the price paid. Rather, the price affects consumption only through a budget constraint. So, in an AYCE setting, price should influence whether one chooses to eat at the restaurant, but it should not affect the amount of food one consumes. But various experiments and test results have proven that price determines the personal evaluation of certain food and indirectly affects consumption. The Food and Brand Lab at Cornell University conducted an experiment to see how the price of a buffet influenced customers. They offered two groups of customers the same pizza buffet, and charged one group $4, while the other group was charged $8. The group who paid more was overwhelmingly more satisfied with the entire experience. We are driven by our personal conception of value for money. The purpose of revealing this is to demonstrate the sunk cost fallacy in an AYCE context. In an AYCE setting, price positively influences consumption. Additionally, consumption appears to be negatively related to individual evaluations of taste. In contrast to the standard utility model, this provides support to the notion that individuals consider price in evaluating their marginal utility of consumption, even when there is no marginal cost for additional consumption. The more the buffet charges, the more you think the buffet is good. Hence, the buffet is charged more and you still think the buffet is good and within all this, restaurants jump in and book their profits. The Concept of Bounded Rationality and the Bandwagon Effect Bounded rationality is the idea that rationality is limited when individuals make decisions by the tractability of the decision problem, the cognitive limitations of the mind, and the time available to make the decision. It is similar to an inability to make a sagacious decision when bombarded with multitudes of options (as in a buffet) leading us unable to follow rational predictions. The bandwagon effect is the tendency of an individual to acquire a particular style, behaviour or attitude because everyone else is doing it. It is a phenomenon whereby the rate of uptake of beliefs, ideas, fads and trends increases with respect to the proportion of others who have already done so. Usually, in a buffet, some items come out to be clear winners and almost everyone starts having more and more of the same, the customers recommend the same to the people they are having lunch/dinner with, who in turn again start having more of the product. This creates a bandwagon effect, people will quickly consume a few items thereby saving the restaurant’s cost on all others. When choices are abundant, rationality is limited, and people have a tendency to follow the bandwagon, the result is skewed option picking. Some dishes emerge to be the most wanted and are generally those that are in abundant supply. Usually, dishes that are cooked in large vessels with cheap ingredients. Hence the restaurant saves on the more expensive dishes and the cost is limited yet again. Economies of Scale Economies of scale are cost advantages reaped by companies when production becomes efficient. Companies can achieve economies of scale by increasing production and lowering costs. The larger the business, the more the cost savings. Buffets are large production businesses. A restaurant buffet achieves economies of scale by producing in large quantities, spreading its costs over a larger number of dishes, even though it often demands a serious cut in food quality. Because of tight profit margins, the food quality becomes a second priority. However, this doesn’t matter, they have their footfall. In addition to this, lesser personnel need to be deployed for a buffet. As a result, the restaurant makes large savings in employment costs. These overhead savings are one of the crucial areas in which buffets differ from traditional restaurants. That's because you are doing most of the work for them - and paying for the privilege. You serve yourself, and in some places, you might even get your drinks. This means there's next to no need for waiting staff. And since the menu relies heavily on a series of regular dishes which are prepared in advance, they can hire fewer and cheaper chefs.&amp;nbsp; Heck, at some buffets like Korean BBQ places, the customers are even doing the cooking as well as the serving! Now that you know the economics, you may have the power of defying these principles and &quot;beating the buffet’. Defy the diminishing marginal utility function. Be wise and judge your taste buds independent of price. Be rational and avoid the bandwagon. But buffet designers know this. While most people will be modest, some people will try to get &quot;all-they-can-eat&quot; and go for a ton of pieces of cottage cheese. Some don’t stop from piling it up vertically or going back for another plate. So, buffets must cut corners in other ways to make sure they aren't losing out. They achieve this by teasing you in clever ways. Strategic Layouts and Secret Nudges Buffets invest a lot of time into developing the right layout.&amp;nbsp; Expensive items are cut into smaller pieces. Cheap, filling foods such as your salads, veggies, rice and noodles are served at the beginning, offering the consumer the opportunity to load up before the ‘luxury’ items. Relatively expensive offerings will be surrounded by four or five cheaper veggie side dishes, and pricier desserts like cakes will be surrounded by platters of fruit. Coupled with larger serving times for expensive items, buffets usually nudge you to take up the cheaper, more available, readily in flow food items. You can grab a ladle-full of rice and veggies any instant, but when it comes to those small pizza slices, you wait for your turn in line. They'll take longer to get on your plate, and most people don't like the pressure of holding up a line, so they tend to move quickly through. Also, pans with more expensive foods are generally less full — a subtle encouragement to take less, a nudge, while cheap ingredients will be served in giant, overflowing pans. Those are plenty for all, and people like that. They like to believe that must be the right choice. One of the biggest factors impacting your eating habits at a buffet is the cutlery you're given. You'll seldom see full-sized dinner plates or actual soup bowls. Instead, you'll be given small plates and even tiny dessert bowls to limit the amount of food you take. Restaurant suppliers know this, and buffets even purchase miniature tableware specially designed for buffets. This even includes purchasing silverware, which tends to be smaller — but not small enough you'd notice unless you already know their sneaky tricks. You're welcome. Generally, buffets will keep extra sweet desserts, so clients are satisfied with lower portions. Complementary to this, buffets will usually have huge water and soft drink glasses. They need you to be full of soda that costs a penny. The more you drink, the less you eat, the more the restaurant saves. For a lot of buffets, things like vegetables, potatoes and rice are staple dishes. That's because they are both super cheap and extremely filling. Buffets entice you into indulging on salads before the meat because salad is cheaper and quickly fills plate space. Psychology Today took a look at what's occurring in the buffet line, and they call this the &quot;fill the customer's belly cheaply&quot; metric. But remember, if you are truly there to make the most of your money, these items will only fill you up with nonsense. Conclusion At its crudest level, the AYCE buffet restaurant manager’s primary job is simply to fill the customer’s stomach as cheaply and quickly as possible. Minimising waste by using computational data analytics to figure out the customers’ eating habits go a long way in cutting costs. Coupled with the power of using cheap ingredients to prepare worthwhile dishes, AYCE buffets tease your bellies to fill their pockets. But to satisfy customers and bring them back, buffet managers can’t stop there. They must create the perception of providing ample variety and high-quality food items. At the same time, they must manipulate customers’ choices and portion sizes, and ensure that food waste is minimised. With just a few tricks, such as using smaller plates, putting cheap items towards the front, and using drinks to off-set other costs, all-you-can-eat restaurants can accomplish the same goal as any other restaurant: get people in the door. Finally, you may not want to take the &quot;all-you-can-eat&quot; part quite so literally. People can and have been banned from buffets for eating too much food. For instance, a Wisconsin man named Bill Wisth was not only banned but had the cops called on him for abusing his local buffet. So, before you go back for that fourth slice of pizza, ask yourself how much you might like the taste of jail food. Because the buffets there aren't nearly as good. So, for a recap. What did I teach you about buffet strategy? &quot;Grab a small-sized drink and a large-sized plate, start with your high-end entrée, skip veggies and carbs and yeah, ride your own bandwagon.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Opaque Laws and Transparent Intentions : the Omnibus Law of Indonesia</title><link href="/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opaque Laws and Transparent Intentions : the Omnibus Law of Indonesia" /><published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions">&lt;p&gt;The month of October 2020 saw a massive wave of protests and strikes in Indonesia against the newly introduced Omnibus law. The law is a series of amendments to dozens of existing legislation regarding labour, mining and environmental protection. The 900-page bill was passed as a law on October 5, 2020, without so much as a draft being released to the public. In April 2020, trade unions had forced the Parliament to suspend any debate on the bill, but it was passed regardless. Amnesty International, a non-governmental organisation focused on human rights, called the bill’s preparation process “opaque”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trade unions called for a nationwide strike in opposition to the bill, calling the workers to defend their rights. Paramita Supamijoto, a professor at Bina Nusantara University, said that the law effectively eliminated the power of labour unions. For workers, it meant that “&lt;em&gt;whatever you do, your life will be determined by your employers&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cities, protests led to clashes with the police as the government tried to ban gatherings on the grounds of health precautions. The dedication of the government towards curbing COVID-19 was seen in full swing when it came to these gatherings against the undemocratic passing of the bill. On other parameters, it has been unable to show much success. In fact, in mid-February, as cases of the virus were increasing, the Minister of Health had claimed that the country was completely free of the virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Omnibus law was presented by the government as a drive to create jobs and develop the country in the wake of the unemployment caused by the pandemic. They highlighted the need for Foreign Direct Investment to boost the ailing economy. &lt;em&gt;The Economist &lt;/em&gt;even praised the government for cutting back on the “lavish mandatory benefits” that Indonesian workers receive that deter companies from creating more jobs. Even the British Chamber of Commerce in Indonesia declared Indonesian labour as “too expensive” and that in order to be a realistic alternative to China, Indonesia would need to cut labour costs. It seems eerily dystopian that such organisations endorse and aspire to the labour conditions of a country known for its sweatshops, forced work, child labour and hazardous workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law regresses the strides taken by Indonesia in terms of labour protection. The trailblazing menstrual leave has been abolished, along with paid maternity leave. Working hours have been increased, cost of living considerations and inflation correction have been done away with and the protections during employment termination have also been taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The environmental aspect has also drawn harsh criticism. Similar to the Environmental Impact Assessment Amendment 2020 passed in India, the Omnibus law makes it easier for firms to avoid reporting their transgressions when it comes to the environmental impact. The agrarian clauses even allow the government to acquire individually owned land with close to no remuneration. Public participation has been restricted by reducing people’s ability to challenge projects that may cause environmental harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a consortium of 35 global investors, in a letter to the Indonesian government, expressed their concern regarding the law. They said that they recognised Indonesia’s progress in protecting tropical forests in recent years and that this law could hamper those efforts. In response to these concerns, the Indonesian Deputy Foreign Minister Mahendra Siregar said, “&lt;em&gt;The concerns can be understood but [they’re] baseless&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, most of the government responses have been similarly vague and condescending. In relation to the massive rallies across the country, Defense Minister Prabowo Subianto said that most protesters had not read the full legislation and were swayed by fake news. He seems to have forgotten that the draft was not made public before the law was passed, making it difficult for the public to read the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passing legislation like thieves in the night is a trend that all governments would do well to reconsider. There are surely more subtle ways to push an anti-people, anti-environment neo-liberal agenda. If the process of legislation does not even think about what the people want, it seems about time to question the institution of democracy itself. As one of the protesting student’s plaques declared, “&lt;em&gt;Colonisation has ended but colonisation of workers begins&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The month of October 2020 saw a massive wave of protests and strikes in Indonesia against the newly introduced Omnibus law. The law is a series of amendments to dozens of existing legislation regarding labour, mining and environmental protection. The 900-page bill was passed as a law on October 5, 2020, without so much as a draft being released to the public. In April 2020, trade unions had forced the Parliament to suspend any debate on the bill, but it was passed regardless. Amnesty International, a non-governmental organisation focused on human rights, called the bill’s preparation process “opaque”. Trade unions called for a nationwide strike in opposition to the bill, calling the workers to defend their rights. Paramita Supamijoto, a professor at Bina Nusantara University, said that the law effectively eliminated the power of labour unions. For workers, it meant that “whatever you do, your life will be determined by your employers.” In many cities, protests led to clashes with the police as the government tried to ban gatherings on the grounds of health precautions. The dedication of the government towards curbing COVID-19 was seen in full swing when it came to these gatherings against the undemocratic passing of the bill. On other parameters, it has been unable to show much success. In fact, in mid-February, as cases of the virus were increasing, the Minister of Health had claimed that the country was completely free of the virus. The Omnibus law was presented by the government as a drive to create jobs and develop the country in the wake of the unemployment caused by the pandemic. They highlighted the need for Foreign Direct Investment to boost the ailing economy. The Economist even praised the government for cutting back on the “lavish mandatory benefits” that Indonesian workers receive that deter companies from creating more jobs. Even the British Chamber of Commerce in Indonesia declared Indonesian labour as “too expensive” and that in order to be a realistic alternative to China, Indonesia would need to cut labour costs. It seems eerily dystopian that such organisations endorse and aspire to the labour conditions of a country known for its sweatshops, forced work, child labour and hazardous workplaces. The law regresses the strides taken by Indonesia in terms of labour protection. The trailblazing menstrual leave has been abolished, along with paid maternity leave. Working hours have been increased, cost of living considerations and inflation correction have been done away with and the protections during employment termination have also been taken away. The environmental aspect has also drawn harsh criticism. Similar to the Environmental Impact Assessment Amendment 2020 passed in India, the Omnibus law makes it easier for firms to avoid reporting their transgressions when it comes to the environmental impact. The agrarian clauses even allow the government to acquire individually owned land with close to no remuneration. Public participation has been restricted by reducing people’s ability to challenge projects that may cause environmental harm. Even a consortium of 35 global investors, in a letter to the Indonesian government, expressed their concern regarding the law. They said that they recognised Indonesia’s progress in protecting tropical forests in recent years and that this law could hamper those efforts. In response to these concerns, the Indonesian Deputy Foreign Minister Mahendra Siregar said, “The concerns can be understood but [they’re] baseless.” In fact, most of the government responses have been similarly vague and condescending. In relation to the massive rallies across the country, Defense Minister Prabowo Subianto said that most protesters had not read the full legislation and were swayed by fake news. He seems to have forgotten that the draft was not made public before the law was passed, making it difficult for the public to read the bill. Passing legislation like thieves in the night is a trend that all governments would do well to reconsider. There are surely more subtle ways to push an anti-people, anti-environment neo-liberal agenda. If the process of legislation does not even think about what the people want, it seems about time to question the institution of democracy itself. As one of the protesting student’s plaques declared, “Colonisation has ended but colonisation of workers begins.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Grabbing Eyeballs to Sourcing Toxicity: Television News Broadcasting in India</title><link href="/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Grabbing Eyeballs to Sourcing Toxicity: Television News Broadcasting in India" /><published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity">&lt;p&gt;Television has been the dominant form of entertainment in India for over thirty years. Around 850 million people have access to a TV set in India and these numbers not only reflect the large influence of TV in the social and political domains on its viewers but also how it has evolved to become the biggest marketing tool in the media sphere. While many sectors became stagnant with the outbreak of coronavirus, the television industry grabbed the attention of the millions that were confined to their homes during the lockdown. A captive audience celebrated the return of old classics like the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; in the quarantine period. However, the unethical growth and rising TRP of various channels also received huge backlash during the same time. This gave a reality check for the kind of information that was being sourced and the influence of the same on the viewers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Death of Rajiv Tyagi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging deeper into the news sector, which is a major contributor to the television domain, we may consider the sudden passing away of the Indian National Congress National spokesperson Rajiv Tyagi on August 12, 2020. He passed away after a heart attack that occurred soon after a heated debate on a Hindi TV channel. This sparked a debate about the toxic debate culture of TV news. Commenting on this tragic incident, Professor Gaurav Vallabh, a Congress spokesperson, explained how titles of the debate show on news channels are divisive. Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) leader Nawab Malik commented on the format of the debates and how the anchor or the host of the show denies equal opportunity to each speaker, which turns the entire debate show into a bullfighting spectacle. A senior journalist, Abhisar Sharma, who has been a major critic of television debate culture, mentioned the influence of these meaningless debates on vulnerable minds, especially on younger viewers. The Rajiv Tyagi incident exposed the transition of these news debates from facts to fiction and from a platform to tackle important issues to an arena of verbal bloodshed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Changing Nature of TV&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-decided agendas of talk shows during prime time news often peddle hatred and biased opinions to the viewers. Vilification of particular communities and trial by media have become the new normal in the newsrooms. Airing these opinions during prime time with its massive reach of the audience and fixed timings gives legitimacy to biased news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people are openly targeted in the name of live reporting. Despite the recognition of toxicity on news channels, there seems to be no end to the shows that provoke such negativity in the country. A major reason for this is the benefit of such reporting in terms of the ratings and revenue of the news channels. Leading news reporters and editors fight for the same sensational viewership each day, which is why TRPs have become the game-changer and facts have taken backstage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While pursuing my Bachelor’s in Journalism, I read about the Propaganda Model of Communication advanced by&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_S._Herman&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edward S Herman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noam_Chomsky&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Noam Chomsky&lt;/a&gt;. This model explains media biases and the working of corporate media outlets. I see the relevance of this in today’s times. It also answers the question about the future of broadcast in our country, relating to the five filters that are mentioned under the model - ownership, advertising, sourcing, flack and fear. Each filter creates an inherent conflict of interest that drives the propaganda of the news channel in the pursuit of quality journalism. Commenting on media's “societal purpose,” Chomsky wrote in his book&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manufacturing_Consent&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;The mass media are interested in attracting audiences with buying power, not audiences per se; it is affluent audiences that spark advertiser interest today, as in the nineteenth century. The idea that the drive for large audiences makes the mass media ‘democratic’ thus suffers from the initial weakness that its political analogue is a voting system weighted by income!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that broadcast is not going to die anytime soon even though it receives massive backlash and hatred especially from independent media organisations and primarily from new media users because it is still the only source of information that people without internet facility have access to. The privilege of access to news sources plays a large role in news consumption in the country. As much as we look forward to the idea of ‘Digital India’,&amp;nbsp; increasing viewership and regional recognition have made television the biggest revenue grabbing medium in the industry, more than the internet. Ideally, the media industry should work upon the regulation of content that it delivers, which has to be more informational than just persuasive. The ethics of journalism need formal regulation because the selective interpretation of this by news channels has majorly contributed to the spread of biased facts. The tragic death of Rajiv Tyagi should be an eye-opener for public discourse compelling the political leaders, anchors, and the creators of the prime time news and TV shows to think of a media strategy that falls within the walls of what journalism truly stands for- objectivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Himanshi Saini</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Television has been the dominant form of entertainment in India for over thirty years. Around 850 million people have access to a TV set in India and these numbers not only reflect the large influence of TV in the social and political domains on its viewers but also how it has evolved to become the biggest marketing tool in the media sphere. While many sectors became stagnant with the outbreak of coronavirus, the television industry grabbed the attention of the millions that were confined to their homes during the lockdown. A captive audience celebrated the return of old classics like the Ramayana and Mahabharata in the quarantine period. However, the unethical growth and rising TRP of various channels also received huge backlash during the same time. This gave a reality check for the kind of information that was being sourced and the influence of the same on the viewers.&amp;nbsp; The Death of Rajiv Tyagi Digging deeper into the news sector, which is a major contributor to the television domain, we may consider the sudden passing away of the Indian National Congress National spokesperson Rajiv Tyagi on August 12, 2020. He passed away after a heart attack that occurred soon after a heated debate on a Hindi TV channel. This sparked a debate about the toxic debate culture of TV news. Commenting on this tragic incident, Professor Gaurav Vallabh, a Congress spokesperson, explained how titles of the debate show on news channels are divisive. Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) leader Nawab Malik commented on the format of the debates and how the anchor or the host of the show denies equal opportunity to each speaker, which turns the entire debate show into a bullfighting spectacle. A senior journalist, Abhisar Sharma, who has been a major critic of television debate culture, mentioned the influence of these meaningless debates on vulnerable minds, especially on younger viewers. The Rajiv Tyagi incident exposed the transition of these news debates from facts to fiction and from a platform to tackle important issues to an arena of verbal bloodshed.&amp;nbsp; Changing Nature of TV Pre-decided agendas of talk shows during prime time news often peddle hatred and biased opinions to the viewers. Vilification of particular communities and trial by media have become the new normal in the newsrooms. Airing these opinions during prime time with its massive reach of the audience and fixed timings gives legitimacy to biased news. Some people are openly targeted in the name of live reporting. Despite the recognition of toxicity on news channels, there seems to be no end to the shows that provoke such negativity in the country. A major reason for this is the benefit of such reporting in terms of the ratings and revenue of the news channels. Leading news reporters and editors fight for the same sensational viewership each day, which is why TRPs have become the game-changer and facts have taken backstage.&amp;nbsp; While pursuing my Bachelor’s in Journalism, I read about the Propaganda Model of Communication advanced by&amp;nbsp;Edward S Herman&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Noam Chomsky. This model explains media biases and the working of corporate media outlets. I see the relevance of this in today’s times. It also answers the question about the future of broadcast in our country, relating to the five filters that are mentioned under the model - ownership, advertising, sourcing, flack and fear. Each filter creates an inherent conflict of interest that drives the propaganda of the news channel in the pursuit of quality journalism. Commenting on media's “societal purpose,” Chomsky wrote in his book&amp;nbsp;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media, “The mass media are interested in attracting audiences with buying power, not audiences per se; it is affluent audiences that spark advertiser interest today, as in the nineteenth century. The idea that the drive for large audiences makes the mass media ‘democratic’ thus suffers from the initial weakness that its political analogue is a voting system weighted by income!” I feel that broadcast is not going to die anytime soon even though it receives massive backlash and hatred especially from independent media organisations and primarily from new media users because it is still the only source of information that people without internet facility have access to. The privilege of access to news sources plays a large role in news consumption in the country. As much as we look forward to the idea of ‘Digital India’,&amp;nbsp; increasing viewership and regional recognition have made television the biggest revenue grabbing medium in the industry, more than the internet. Ideally, the media industry should work upon the regulation of content that it delivers, which has to be more informational than just persuasive. The ethics of journalism need formal regulation because the selective interpretation of this by news channels has majorly contributed to the spread of biased facts. The tragic death of Rajiv Tyagi should be an eye-opener for public discourse compelling the political leaders, anchors, and the creators of the prime time news and TV shows to think of a media strategy that falls within the walls of what journalism truly stands for- objectivity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bootstrapping vs Funding: The Dilemma</title><link href="/Bootstrapping-vs-Funding-The-Dilemma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bootstrapping vs Funding: The Dilemma" /><published>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bootstrapping-vs-Funding-The-Dilemma</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bootstrapping-vs-Funding-The-Dilemma">&lt;p&gt;Here is the toughest question for an entrepreneur: Should I bootstrap my business, or make an effort and raise capital through a venture fund? While the choice rests on a myriad of divergent factors, it is important to understand these financing methods and how they can influence the future of a business.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In layman’s terms, bootstrapping refers to the act of starting a company with an individual’s personal finances and without external funding. If people are building up a company with whatever money they have in hand and from the profits they are earning, that is ‘Bootstrapping’. In contrast, ‘Venture Capital’ funding is when funding is put into a new business by venture capitalists as an investment in exchange for equity in the business. It allows a startup to move and scale quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More entrepreneurs are showing up to shoot for the stars and go for the gold to fuel their startup by either adopting the guerilla-style bootstrapping path or by trying to raise funds. In determining whether entrepreneurs should bootstrap or seek external funding for their company, it is necessary to weigh up the pros and cons associated with a plethora of significant factors and decide which is the better fit.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several external factors that the company must keep in mind while making a funding decision. Suppose a company is functioning in a highly competitive market, like Uber or Slack, this means that they have to scale as fast as possible and become or remain a dominant player. It most likely implies that investment is required to afford growth in the near future, which makes it suitable for the company to opt for venture capital funding. In juxtaposition to the above market structure, a fragmented market where many mid-sized firms coexist, like Snappa and Buffer, funding may not be necessary. Under these circumstances, entrepreneurs can choose to bootstrap their company and grow it by themselves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s walk through the internal factors that help in deciding between bootstrapping versus funding. The goal that the company strives to achieve affects their decision to bootstrap or seek external funding. For bootstrapped companies, the goal is generally to become more profitable whereas funded companies aim to maximise revenue growth and become the market leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, if the company has the ambition to continue growing forever and founders want to stay with the firm, then bootstrapping is a viable option. On the other hand, if they are planning to exit in a couple of years, then raising venture capital money to scale faster may be the right choice. This is because venture capitalists typically invest with a target to exit in about 3-10 years. Since a bootstrapped company works with limited resources, its growth rate is slower in comparison to the funded companies that gain traction quickly. Bootstrapping becomes successful when a startup can sustain itself over a period of time. After initial hiccups, like investment arranged by the founder, the company starts making profits out of its products and services that carry the business forward. Needless to say, both can achieve good growth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now most importantly, when it comes to the freedom and the control of the owners, there is a lot more flexibility in a bootstrapped company. It allows gung-ho entrepreneurs to experiment with what they can do. They can focus on partnering with someone who brings in the required skill set and industry-specific expertise. The focus is directed towards a clear goal and there is no interference from investors who might have conflicting visions. However, the downside is that this form of financing might also place the entrepreneur under unnecessary financial risk.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, the funded company’s ability to pivot is constrained. This essentially means that the companies have to consult with their venture capitalists in all the decision-making processes. In addition to this, it brings more people into the business with different ideas, expertise and varied backgrounds. Experienced investors can also act as mentors for young entrepreneurs, and guide them through tricky situations. But instead of owning a business, the founders usually end up owning just a smaller portion of a much bigger pie after going through multiple rounds of fundraising that continuously dilute their ownership.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the realm of email newsletters, Atlanta-based MailChimp is a successful giant. Co-founders Ben Chestnut and Dan Kurzius &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/10/06/technology/mailchimp-and-the-un-silicon-valley-way-to-make-it-as-a-start-up.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;started the company in 2000&lt;/a&gt; from a bootstrapped dream and it became one of the biggest companies in its space with due course of time. The company was named &lt;em&gt;Inc.’s&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/magazine/201802/mailchimp-company-of-the-year-2017.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Company of the Year in 2017&lt;/a&gt; and till today it is still 100% founder-owned. Thriving startups like Mailchimp, Spanx, GoPro, Craigslist and so many more have bootstrapped their way to success and have gained mainstream attention that began to attract investors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, RUSSSH started its journey in 2012 as GetMyPeon and was the only errand-running and delivery service in Mumbai, India. The seven-year-old bootstrapped company lacked the capital to fight competition. It could not offer great discounts like other emergent players, and to achieve success in a developing service market proved unnerving. Like RUSSSH, numerous bootstrapped startups such as LoanMeet, Woolpr and Koinex among many others could not survive in the market for long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, giving prominence to the best-funded startups like One97 Communications (Paytm), Ola Cabs, OYO, Snapdeal, Swiggy, BYJU’s, Big Basket and so many more that have funding totalling billions of dollars are flourishing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlikely, Anki Inc, founded in 2010 by three Carnegie Mellon Robotics Institute graduates, focused on creating unique consumer products. The company’s total funding amount was $182 million. According to its long-term roadmap, it could no longer continue as a hardware and software business even after selling 1.5 million robot units due to insufficient funds. Similarly,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Call9, Aria Insights, Stimwave Technologies, Oryx Vision, and many other companies sustained in the market for a very short period of time. Not to mention the world-famous case of Theranos!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, bootstrapping and funding both have their own benefits and drawbacks. There is no one option that is inherently better or worse off than the other. From a finance outlook, funding gives the startup more power to scale, but it also comes with high stakes. When it comes to bootstrapping, it makes it harder for entrepreneurs to scale their company, but while it might grow at a slower pace, there still remains the advantage of owning and controlling the whole pie.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samakshi Garg</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Here is the toughest question for an entrepreneur: Should I bootstrap my business, or make an effort and raise capital through a venture fund? While the choice rests on a myriad of divergent factors, it is important to understand these financing methods and how they can influence the future of a business.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In layman’s terms, bootstrapping refers to the act of starting a company with an individual’s personal finances and without external funding. If people are building up a company with whatever money they have in hand and from the profits they are earning, that is ‘Bootstrapping’. In contrast, ‘Venture Capital’ funding is when funding is put into a new business by venture capitalists as an investment in exchange for equity in the business. It allows a startup to move and scale quickly. More entrepreneurs are showing up to shoot for the stars and go for the gold to fuel their startup by either adopting the guerilla-style bootstrapping path or by trying to raise funds. In determining whether entrepreneurs should bootstrap or seek external funding for their company, it is necessary to weigh up the pros and cons associated with a plethora of significant factors and decide which is the better fit.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; There are several external factors that the company must keep in mind while making a funding decision. Suppose a company is functioning in a highly competitive market, like Uber or Slack, this means that they have to scale as fast as possible and become or remain a dominant player. It most likely implies that investment is required to afford growth in the near future, which makes it suitable for the company to opt for venture capital funding. In juxtaposition to the above market structure, a fragmented market where many mid-sized firms coexist, like Snappa and Buffer, funding may not be necessary. Under these circumstances, entrepreneurs can choose to bootstrap their company and grow it by themselves.&amp;nbsp; Let’s walk through the internal factors that help in deciding between bootstrapping versus funding. The goal that the company strives to achieve affects their decision to bootstrap or seek external funding. For bootstrapped companies, the goal is generally to become more profitable whereas funded companies aim to maximise revenue growth and become the market leaders.&amp;nbsp; Next, if the company has the ambition to continue growing forever and founders want to stay with the firm, then bootstrapping is a viable option. On the other hand, if they are planning to exit in a couple of years, then raising venture capital money to scale faster may be the right choice. This is because venture capitalists typically invest with a target to exit in about 3-10 years. Since a bootstrapped company works with limited resources, its growth rate is slower in comparison to the funded companies that gain traction quickly. Bootstrapping becomes successful when a startup can sustain itself over a period of time. After initial hiccups, like investment arranged by the founder, the company starts making profits out of its products and services that carry the business forward. Needless to say, both can achieve good growth.&amp;nbsp; Now most importantly, when it comes to the freedom and the control of the owners, there is a lot more flexibility in a bootstrapped company. It allows gung-ho entrepreneurs to experiment with what they can do. They can focus on partnering with someone who brings in the required skill set and industry-specific expertise. The focus is directed towards a clear goal and there is no interference from investors who might have conflicting visions. However, the downside is that this form of financing might also place the entrepreneur under unnecessary financial risk.&amp;nbsp; On a similar note, the funded company’s ability to pivot is constrained. This essentially means that the companies have to consult with their venture capitalists in all the decision-making processes. In addition to this, it brings more people into the business with different ideas, expertise and varied backgrounds. Experienced investors can also act as mentors for young entrepreneurs, and guide them through tricky situations. But instead of owning a business, the founders usually end up owning just a smaller portion of a much bigger pie after going through multiple rounds of fundraising that continuously dilute their ownership.&amp;nbsp; In the realm of email newsletters, Atlanta-based MailChimp is a successful giant. Co-founders Ben Chestnut and Dan Kurzius started the company in 2000 from a bootstrapped dream and it became one of the biggest companies in its space with due course of time. The company was named Inc.’s Company of the Year in 2017 and till today it is still 100% founder-owned. Thriving startups like Mailchimp, Spanx, GoPro, Craigslist and so many more have bootstrapped their way to success and have gained mainstream attention that began to attract investors.&amp;nbsp; Conversely, RUSSSH started its journey in 2012 as GetMyPeon and was the only errand-running and delivery service in Mumbai, India. The seven-year-old bootstrapped company lacked the capital to fight competition. It could not offer great discounts like other emergent players, and to achieve success in a developing service market proved unnerving. Like RUSSSH, numerous bootstrapped startups such as LoanMeet, Woolpr and Koinex among many others could not survive in the market for long. Furthermore, giving prominence to the best-funded startups like One97 Communications (Paytm), Ola Cabs, OYO, Snapdeal, Swiggy, BYJU’s, Big Basket and so many more that have funding totalling billions of dollars are flourishing. Unlikely, Anki Inc, founded in 2010 by three Carnegie Mellon Robotics Institute graduates, focused on creating unique consumer products. The company’s total funding amount was $182 million. According to its long-term roadmap, it could no longer continue as a hardware and software business even after selling 1.5 million robot units due to insufficient funds. Similarly, Call9, Aria Insights, Stimwave Technologies, Oryx Vision, and many other companies sustained in the market for a very short period of time. Not to mention the world-famous case of Theranos! At the end of the day, bootstrapping and funding both have their own benefits and drawbacks. There is no one option that is inherently better or worse off than the other. From a finance outlook, funding gives the startup more power to scale, but it also comes with high stakes. When it comes to bootstrapping, it makes it harder for entrepreneurs to scale their company, but while it might grow at a slower pace, there still remains the advantage of owning and controlling the whole pie.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Investor’s Déjà Vu</title><link href="/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Investor’s Déjà Vu" /><published>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu</id><content type="html" xml:base="/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu">&lt;p&gt;Picture this, you’re having a conversation with your parents while opening the refrigerator door. You extend your hand towards the half-eaten chocolate and in a moment of suddenness, it seems you’ve already done this before. But you can’t seem to remember when. That, my friend, is &lt;em&gt;déjà vu&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture another scenario. Say you’re reading the newspaper this time and the S&amp;amp;P index has dipped more than the usual. You think you’ve been here before, except this time, you exactly remember when: 2008. Your memory is bitter about the experience because the last time it happened, it didn’t bode well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2008 Debacle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone with a rough idea of the 2008 housing bubble would know that it wasn’t pretty. To quote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/a-guide-to-the-financial-crisis--10-years-later/2018/09/10/114b76ba-af10-11e8-a20b-5f4f84429666_story.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moody’s&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;The stock market plummeted, wiping out nearly $8 trillion in value between late 2007 and 2009. Unemployment climbed, peaking at 10 percent in October 2009. Americans lost $9.8 trillion in wealth&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, just like the human mood, changes in the stock market come in waves. Where there is a low, there is a high. Thus, it’s no wonder that the stock market made a comeback: the home prices rebounded and the employment rate ticked upward. But unfortunately, the story doesn’t end here. Here’s the catch: the market may forget, but the human cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocks have more than doubled since the financial crisis, and yet, a lot of investors have remarkably tweaked down their equity exposure. (For some context, equity is that part of your investment portfolio which leans towards risk. The same is compensated by the possibility of higher returns). Sounds weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The vast majority of people have some equity holdings in their 401(k) plans&lt;/em&gt;”, said &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.reuters.com/article/us-usa-stocks-retailinvestors/insight-mom-and-pop-investors-miss-out-on-stock-market-gains-idUSBRE88T0AE20120930&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Brian Reid&lt;/a&gt;, Chief Economist at the Investment Company Institute (ICI), but fewer are willing to take above-average or substantial risk than they were in 2008 before the market plummeted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent Cogent Research report found that risk aversion among all age groups has been on the rise since 2006, including Generation X and Y, who have lived through a number of market collapses. To simplify, investors have become more risk-averse since the 2008 financial crisis. But why?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Déjà Vu&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the ramifications of a financial crisis are more profound than we think: they perpetuate biases. The underlying bias observed here is called ‘Experiential Bias’. This occurs when investors' memory of recent events makes them biased or leads them to believe that an event is far more likely to occur again. This culminates in a lot of investors permanently quitting the market or overestimating the impending hardships in a market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facing the Music&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffet once said, “&lt;em&gt;Our favourite holding period is forever&lt;/em&gt;”. According to him, the secret recipe to minting clever money is holding on to stocks, even when their price collapses, for the simple reason that they will bounce back up, over time. But what happens to the investors who left the market at the end of 2008 or early 2009? It wouldn’t take big brains to figure out that they paid a high price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a personal level, quitting the market midway deprives investors of the opportunity of recovering their losses during the recoil. Moreover, reluctance to invest in risky avenues strips you of the prospects of earning fancy rewards. On a larger level, this may also contribute to negative consumer sentiment. Let us see how.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If every second investor hurt by the 2008 crisis exits the stock market, and consciously or subconsciously propels fellow investors to quit too, won’t economic transactions and activity tumble? Sounds unlikely, right? Why would I succumb to and base my decisions on borrowed apprehensions, instead of my own independent analysis? Enter ‘Herd Bias’, yet another fragment of behavioural finance. We’re hard-wired to herd and imitate what other investors are doing. Contrary to traditional beliefs, investors are not invariably rational, they have limits to their self-control and are prone to falling ill to their own biases and fallacies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that the aggrieved investor doesn’t quit the market but instead reads every non-average (but normal) dip in S&amp;amp;P or Dow Jones as the onset of something critical. Consequently and gradually, the investor might begin to disinvest (the move is motivated by a fallacy, but is disinvestment nevertheless). If there are sufficient people believing this idea, it is enough to drive the market down. Note that financial markets are driven by popular beliefs, not logical beliefs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too far-fetched, right? It is. But replicate this on a large scale, and voila, you have investor sentiment tipping a slowdown. Those who are still firmly gripped by the ravages of the crisis, have lost all appetite for risk and thus, shirk any and every opportunity that knocks on their doors. They focus on the preservation of capital, not its growth. Sadly though, escapism isn’t the key. Turns out, a no-risk portfolio leaves you financially unprepared.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking the Bias&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there might be some empiricism and truth driving such behaviour, one must actively try not to fall prey to his/her own biases. Here is some advice to help you steer through the horrors of the past (and life, generally) and take decisions objectively:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be Reflective: There are two approaches to arriving at investment decisions: Reflexive and Reflective. While the former is the default, automatic gut response to situations, the latter is the logical and methodical one. Even though the reflective approach demands efforts and research, it assists in making informed choices. So step back, dwell over the situation from a bird’s eye view, and then decide.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let Bygones be Bygones: Don’t anchor everything in the present to the traumatic events in your past. If it has happened once, don’t be so sure it will happen again. Learn from your mistakes and let the rest go.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most News is Noise: Don’t believe everything you read and don’t shoehorn every market dip into your past trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Indulge in Peer Pressure: To quote Warren Buffet once again, “&lt;em&gt;The most important quality for an investor is temperament, not intellect. You need a temperament that neither derives great pleasure from being with the crowd or against the crowd&lt;/em&gt;”. You do you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, ‘Experiential Bias’ is natural. It’s like holding the umbrella when the rains have ceased. You don’t want to let go of it just yet, because it takes more than just time to shake the trauma out. But you know you’ll have to because it’s going to block the sunlight that comes your way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eeshita Verma</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Picture this, you’re having a conversation with your parents while opening the refrigerator door. You extend your hand towards the half-eaten chocolate and in a moment of suddenness, it seems you’ve already done this before. But you can’t seem to remember when. That, my friend, is déjà vu.&amp;nbsp; Picture another scenario. Say you’re reading the newspaper this time and the S&amp;amp;P index has dipped more than the usual. You think you’ve been here before, except this time, you exactly remember when: 2008. Your memory is bitter about the experience because the last time it happened, it didn’t bode well.&amp;nbsp; The 2008 Debacle Anyone with a rough idea of the 2008 housing bubble would know that it wasn’t pretty. To quote Moody’s, “The stock market plummeted, wiping out nearly $8 trillion in value between late 2007 and 2009. Unemployment climbed, peaking at 10 percent in October 2009. Americans lost $9.8 trillion in wealth”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; However, just like the human mood, changes in the stock market come in waves. Where there is a low, there is a high. Thus, it’s no wonder that the stock market made a comeback: the home prices rebounded and the employment rate ticked upward. But unfortunately, the story doesn’t end here. Here’s the catch: the market may forget, but the human cannot. Stocks have more than doubled since the financial crisis, and yet, a lot of investors have remarkably tweaked down their equity exposure. (For some context, equity is that part of your investment portfolio which leans towards risk. The same is compensated by the possibility of higher returns). Sounds weird, right? “The vast majority of people have some equity holdings in their 401(k) plans”, said Brian Reid, Chief Economist at the Investment Company Institute (ICI), but fewer are willing to take above-average or substantial risk than they were in 2008 before the market plummeted.&amp;nbsp; A recent Cogent Research report found that risk aversion among all age groups has been on the rise since 2006, including Generation X and Y, who have lived through a number of market collapses. To simplify, investors have become more risk-averse since the 2008 financial crisis. But why?&amp;nbsp; The Déjà Vu&amp;nbsp; Apparently, the ramifications of a financial crisis are more profound than we think: they perpetuate biases. The underlying bias observed here is called ‘Experiential Bias’. This occurs when investors' memory of recent events makes them biased or leads them to believe that an event is far more likely to occur again. This culminates in a lot of investors permanently quitting the market or overestimating the impending hardships in a market.&amp;nbsp; Facing the Music Warren Buffet once said, “Our favourite holding period is forever”. According to him, the secret recipe to minting clever money is holding on to stocks, even when their price collapses, for the simple reason that they will bounce back up, over time. But what happens to the investors who left the market at the end of 2008 or early 2009? It wouldn’t take big brains to figure out that they paid a high price. On a personal level, quitting the market midway deprives investors of the opportunity of recovering their losses during the recoil. Moreover, reluctance to invest in risky avenues strips you of the prospects of earning fancy rewards. On a larger level, this may also contribute to negative consumer sentiment. Let us see how.&amp;nbsp; If every second investor hurt by the 2008 crisis exits the stock market, and consciously or subconsciously propels fellow investors to quit too, won’t economic transactions and activity tumble? Sounds unlikely, right? Why would I succumb to and base my decisions on borrowed apprehensions, instead of my own independent analysis? Enter ‘Herd Bias’, yet another fragment of behavioural finance. We’re hard-wired to herd and imitate what other investors are doing. Contrary to traditional beliefs, investors are not invariably rational, they have limits to their self-control and are prone to falling ill to their own biases and fallacies.&amp;nbsp; Let’s say that the aggrieved investor doesn’t quit the market but instead reads every non-average (but normal) dip in S&amp;amp;P or Dow Jones as the onset of something critical. Consequently and gradually, the investor might begin to disinvest (the move is motivated by a fallacy, but is disinvestment nevertheless). If there are sufficient people believing this idea, it is enough to drive the market down. Note that financial markets are driven by popular beliefs, not logical beliefs.&amp;nbsp; Too far-fetched, right? It is. But replicate this on a large scale, and voila, you have investor sentiment tipping a slowdown. Those who are still firmly gripped by the ravages of the crisis, have lost all appetite for risk and thus, shirk any and every opportunity that knocks on their doors. They focus on the preservation of capital, not its growth. Sadly though, escapism isn’t the key. Turns out, a no-risk portfolio leaves you financially unprepared.&amp;nbsp; Breaking the Bias While there might be some empiricism and truth driving such behaviour, one must actively try not to fall prey to his/her own biases. Here is some advice to help you steer through the horrors of the past (and life, generally) and take decisions objectively: Be Reflective: There are two approaches to arriving at investment decisions: Reflexive and Reflective. While the former is the default, automatic gut response to situations, the latter is the logical and methodical one. Even though the reflective approach demands efforts and research, it assists in making informed choices. So step back, dwell over the situation from a bird’s eye view, and then decide.&amp;nbsp; Let Bygones be Bygones: Don’t anchor everything in the present to the traumatic events in your past. If it has happened once, don’t be so sure it will happen again. Learn from your mistakes and let the rest go.&amp;nbsp; Most News is Noise: Don’t believe everything you read and don’t shoehorn every market dip into your past trauma. Don’t Indulge in Peer Pressure: To quote Warren Buffet once again, “The most important quality for an investor is temperament, not intellect. You need a temperament that neither derives great pleasure from being with the crowd or against the crowd”. You do you! To sum up, ‘Experiential Bias’ is natural. It’s like holding the umbrella when the rains have ceased. You don’t want to let go of it just yet, because it takes more than just time to shake the trauma out. But you know you’ll have to because it’s going to block the sunlight that comes your way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One Nation One Ration Card: Forerunner in Fight against Food Insecurity</title><link href="/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Nation One Ration Card: Forerunner in Fight against Food Insecurity" /><published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card</id><content type="html" xml:base="/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card">&lt;p&gt;While the unprecedented COVID-19 crisis has had a calamitous impact on all of us, the poorest of the poor have been the worst sufferers. The daily wage workers in India who migrate from the remote parts of the country to economically advanced cities in search of better opportunities were stripped of their economic security in the blink of an eye. Businesses crashed and all activities came to a complete standstill because of the nationwide lockdown. The lockdown put a full stop on all kinds of mobility and discontinued modes of transport. The public was in a state of frenzy, even the well-off strata was apprehensive about the supply of necessities and hence started hoarding. The government assured a continual supply of essential commodities to us but what about the migrant workers, were they given any certainty? In the absence of food security and of any means to commute, along with no pennies in their pocket, they indulged in reverse migration, back to their families.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food security refers to ensuring adequate food supply for people, especially those who are deprived of basic nutrition, the bare minimum. There are 195 million undernourished people in India, adding up to a quarter of the global hunger burden, as per UN-India. Furthermore, India has recently been ranked 94 out of 107 countries in the Global Hunger Index and has been placed in the ‘serious’ hunger category. As an attempt to alleviate the ill effects of the hunger crisis, the National Food Security Act (NFSA) came into force in 2013. Economist Jean Dreze called this bill an “investment in human capital”. According to the NFSA, 810 million people are entitled to subsidised food grains. The prices of rice, wheat and coarse grain have been set at ₹3, ₹2, and ₹1 per kg respectively. About 235 million ration cards have been issued to nearly 810 million beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ration card holders can lift their share of the food grains from the designated Fair Price Shop (FPS) in their locality, where they reside. For instance, if a family resides in Bastar in Chhattisgarh and a few members move to Delhi to work on a construction site, they will no longer be able to purchase their quota of food at subsidised rates from a Public Distribution Shop (PDS) shop in Delhi. This limitation of the existing system divests a large migratory population of their allotted proportion of ration. The national rollout of ‘One Nation, One Ration Card’ is a welcome move in this light. Under this scheme, the beneficiaries can get their share from any of the 540,000 fair price shops across the length and breadth of India. This reform is expected to attain success at a pan-India level by March 31, 2021. However, two prerequisites for the same are 100% installation of Electronic Point of Sale (ePoS) devices and 100% Aadhaar seeding.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technological solution to the problem posed by the earlier system entails identification through biometric authentication on ePoS devices installed at the FPSs. A question might pop up: What is an ePoS? It is a device that electronically records the distribution of ration to different ration cardholders. Connectivity issues are stated as one major bottleneck in the seamless functioning of the framework. However, ePoS also works in offline mode, according to officials. It will most certainly reduce the manual recording of transactions in registers by the dealers. 90% of the PDS shops have been equipped with these devices. As far as the linkage of ration cards with Aadhaar number is concerned, 90% of the 235 million ration cards issued have been seeded.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrated Management of Public Distribution System (IMPDS) and &lt;em&gt;Annavitran&lt;/em&gt; are two portals that will help in smooth facilitation of the process at the inter and intra-state level correspondingly. Talking about one more intricacy, the card will now be in a bilingual format, one of the languages will be the local one and the other can either be Hindi or English. This is because when the recipient is not in his/her native place, there should be ease in comprehending the details and uniformity should be maintained.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical challenges in realising the goal are studying and record-keeping of labour migration patterns. If a family is scattered in two locations, reconciling data at both locations would be a major task. Food Corporation of India (FCI) godowns and other storage facilities need to function parallel to the demand for grains created by the immigration/emigration of the labour force. Just a recent illustration of the change in demand for goods because of reverse migration is that of the Flipkart and Amazon festive sale. Sales doubled up in the first two days when compared to the 2019 edition. In the wake of discounts, an upswing in new shoppers from Tier 2 and Tier 3 cities has been witnessed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the interstate ration card portability cluster is 28 states and union territories strong. Some states with an influx of labour are still laggards in the instalment of ePoS and undertaking biometric authentication. States like West Bengal and Assam, which are still not on board need to be pushed to complete the necessary requirements for true integration of state portals to that of the centre. Computerisation of the supply network of FCI will boost the efficacy and help translate the chalked down scheme into a wholesome reality. Once fully implemented, the scheme is sure to uplift the country in the&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Global Hunger Index. Will it mitigate the suffering of the downtrodden section dying, helplessly walking miles trying to shelter themselves, unable to feed themselves, let alone two but even one square meal? Let us choose to be optimistic in this regard. Even a step forward in the right direction is progress for humankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushi Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">While the unprecedented COVID-19 crisis has had a calamitous impact on all of us, the poorest of the poor have been the worst sufferers. The daily wage workers in India who migrate from the remote parts of the country to economically advanced cities in search of better opportunities were stripped of their economic security in the blink of an eye. Businesses crashed and all activities came to a complete standstill because of the nationwide lockdown. The lockdown put a full stop on all kinds of mobility and discontinued modes of transport. The public was in a state of frenzy, even the well-off strata was apprehensive about the supply of necessities and hence started hoarding. The government assured a continual supply of essential commodities to us but what about the migrant workers, were they given any certainty? In the absence of food security and of any means to commute, along with no pennies in their pocket, they indulged in reverse migration, back to their families.&amp;nbsp; Food security refers to ensuring adequate food supply for people, especially those who are deprived of basic nutrition, the bare minimum. There are 195 million undernourished people in India, adding up to a quarter of the global hunger burden, as per UN-India. Furthermore, India has recently been ranked 94 out of 107 countries in the Global Hunger Index and has been placed in the ‘serious’ hunger category. As an attempt to alleviate the ill effects of the hunger crisis, the National Food Security Act (NFSA) came into force in 2013. Economist Jean Dreze called this bill an “investment in human capital”. According to the NFSA, 810 million people are entitled to subsidised food grains. The prices of rice, wheat and coarse grain have been set at ₹3, ₹2, and ₹1 per kg respectively. About 235 million ration cards have been issued to nearly 810 million beneficiaries. These ration card holders can lift their share of the food grains from the designated Fair Price Shop (FPS) in their locality, where they reside. For instance, if a family resides in Bastar in Chhattisgarh and a few members move to Delhi to work on a construction site, they will no longer be able to purchase their quota of food at subsidised rates from a Public Distribution Shop (PDS) shop in Delhi. This limitation of the existing system divests a large migratory population of their allotted proportion of ration. The national rollout of ‘One Nation, One Ration Card’ is a welcome move in this light. Under this scheme, the beneficiaries can get their share from any of the 540,000 fair price shops across the length and breadth of India. This reform is expected to attain success at a pan-India level by March 31, 2021. However, two prerequisites for the same are 100% installation of Electronic Point of Sale (ePoS) devices and 100% Aadhaar seeding.&amp;nbsp; The technological solution to the problem posed by the earlier system entails identification through biometric authentication on ePoS devices installed at the FPSs. A question might pop up: What is an ePoS? It is a device that electronically records the distribution of ration to different ration cardholders. Connectivity issues are stated as one major bottleneck in the seamless functioning of the framework. However, ePoS also works in offline mode, according to officials. It will most certainly reduce the manual recording of transactions in registers by the dealers. 90% of the PDS shops have been equipped with these devices. As far as the linkage of ration cards with Aadhaar number is concerned, 90% of the 235 million ration cards issued have been seeded.&amp;nbsp; Integrated Management of Public Distribution System (IMPDS) and Annavitran are two portals that will help in smooth facilitation of the process at the inter and intra-state level correspondingly. Talking about one more intricacy, the card will now be in a bilingual format, one of the languages will be the local one and the other can either be Hindi or English. This is because when the recipient is not in his/her native place, there should be ease in comprehending the details and uniformity should be maintained.&amp;nbsp; Critical challenges in realising the goal are studying and record-keeping of labour migration patterns. If a family is scattered in two locations, reconciling data at both locations would be a major task. Food Corporation of India (FCI) godowns and other storage facilities need to function parallel to the demand for grains created by the immigration/emigration of the labour force. Just a recent illustration of the change in demand for goods because of reverse migration is that of the Flipkart and Amazon festive sale. Sales doubled up in the first two days when compared to the 2019 edition. In the wake of discounts, an upswing in new shoppers from Tier 2 and Tier 3 cities has been witnessed.&amp;nbsp; Currently, the interstate ration card portability cluster is 28 states and union territories strong. Some states with an influx of labour are still laggards in the instalment of ePoS and undertaking biometric authentication. States like West Bengal and Assam, which are still not on board need to be pushed to complete the necessary requirements for true integration of state portals to that of the centre. Computerisation of the supply network of FCI will boost the efficacy and help translate the chalked down scheme into a wholesome reality. Once fully implemented, the scheme is sure to uplift the country in the Global Hunger Index. Will it mitigate the suffering of the downtrodden section dying, helplessly walking miles trying to shelter themselves, unable to feed themselves, let alone two but even one square meal? Let us choose to be optimistic in this regard. Even a step forward in the right direction is progress for humankind.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘Murdochisation’ of the Indian Mediascape: A Critical and Historical Undertaking</title><link href="/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Murdochisation’ of the Indian Mediascape: A Critical and Historical Undertaking" /><published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape">&lt;p&gt;The Indian media landscape is an especially complex web of multimedia conglomerates, market-led infotainment, and a growingly linear form of eroding content. Echoing Prasun Sonwalkar’s sentiments on Indian media and journalism, and Guha’s emphasis on the “phipty-phipty” nature of democracy in India, the relationship between the two is mutually inclusive, almost symbiotic. The colonial cauldron of journalism, press and traditional media unequivocally set the benchmark for the role of media in the long uphill journey of democratic survivability. It was the mere subtlety of journals like the &lt;em&gt;Mirat-ul-Akhbar &lt;/em&gt;by Rammohan Roy, and the palpability of the Indian intelligentsia in editorialising local opinions and concerns that kick-started almost a utopian revolution of journalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, keeping in mind these iconic standards and prime examples of relevance in journalism, today’s mediascape reflects a wildly different spectrum. It has turned into an acutely ignorant mockery, normalising caricaturish reportage and incentivising sensationalisation. Moreover, it is threaded by rampant commercialisation and corruption. Politics features heavily in Indian journalism, logically leading it on a path of public critique of authoritative powers, and a much-needed contribution to the democratic awakening of the national. Alas, this aspect of moral and ethical journalism is dumbed down by the Rupert Murdoch-style of reducing news to its bare minimum quality and standard with the intent for merely commercial gains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought that Indian journalism has only recently seen this 'Murdochising' tendency in their news and newsrooms, it is a bleak misconception - one that ignores the historical contexts of the industry. Since the early 1990's, news content has increasingly focused more on celebrities, cinema, cricket and crime. A rapacious pursuit of profit and internal corruption to showcase Bollywood-like style and imagery in broadcast and the shift from politics to politicians is a noticeable indication of a more stylistic form of reality television than relevant content based on the news value of reportage. The Western-style methods being deployed in a proactively traditional society is plunging the Indian media into new depths of misuse and manipulation. The formulation of paid news, wherein politicians sell propaganda masqueraded as 'news' is an unfortunately common phenomenon.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalism used to be an effective tool for reform, be it political, social, religious or any kind. It was particularly used as a powerful weapon against colonial motives in non-Dominion and non-Settler colonies like India. It attempted to perpetuate awareness, knowledge, thought and wisdom. The evolution of Indian journalism seems to have followed that of journalist James Augustus Hickey. Hickey, who published the first Indian journal to question colonial powers and be critical of any authoritarian decision, ended up piecing a career of publishing scandals, scurrilous personal attacks, and was involved in the unethical advertising of selling “sex and sin”. He did believe in the absolute liberty of the press but connoted the notion of liberty to be coercively tyrannical and vehemently injurious to the community.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the colonial period, even English editors who supported the courage and dignity of Indian journalism found themselves on ships back to England. This included William Duane, editor of &lt;em&gt;Bengal Journal&lt;/em&gt;, who was removed as editor and almost deported in 1791, and finally deported as editor of &lt;em&gt;Indian World&lt;/em&gt; in 1794. Another was Charles Maclean, the editor of &lt;em&gt;Bengal Hurkaru&lt;/em&gt;, who was deported in 1798. Even James Silk Buckingham, editor of &lt;em&gt;Calcutta Journal&lt;/em&gt;, and his assistant Sandford Arnot were deported in 1823 and C J Fair, the editor of &lt;em&gt;Bombay Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, was also deported in 1823. However, these foreign attempts at preserving journalism helped inspire a number of Indian-language journals in the nooks and corners of the nation. The &lt;em&gt;Bengal Gejeti&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Harachandra Roy with the assistance of Gangakishore Bhattacharya, and &lt;em&gt;Samachar Darpan&lt;/em&gt;, launched by the Baptist missionaries at Serampore, were both launched in May 1818.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an enigmatic wonder to imagine a journalistic sphere that is rooted in its foundational principles. Today, its operations have changed. With the convergence of global media technologies and “US-inspired media formats, products and discourse”, the sphere has been reduced to that of market-driven journalism. Integral corrosion is the priority of number value over news value with no regard to protect the public interest. The advent of Rupert Murdoch’s News Corporation had numerous repercussions transnationally, acting as a catalyst for deeply profound institutional and ideological changes, transforming media operations worldwide. From imbibing reluctance in holding an editorial stance to discouraging reporters from providing a critical, educational reportage, and leading an opinion to focusing only on facts rather than furthering a valuable interpretation of those facts - it is all a ruse created to favour the heavy-handed convenience of blurting out facts that don’t add any perceptive depth to a conversation, in order to blatantly chase money and fame. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The Indian media landscape is an especially complex web of multimedia conglomerates, market-led infotainment, and a growingly linear form of eroding content. Echoing Prasun Sonwalkar’s sentiments on Indian media and journalism, and Guha’s emphasis on the “phipty-phipty” nature of democracy in India, the relationship between the two is mutually inclusive, almost symbiotic. The colonial cauldron of journalism, press and traditional media unequivocally set the benchmark for the role of media in the long uphill journey of democratic survivability. It was the mere subtlety of journals like the Mirat-ul-Akhbar by Rammohan Roy, and the palpability of the Indian intelligentsia in editorialising local opinions and concerns that kick-started almost a utopian revolution of journalism. However, keeping in mind these iconic standards and prime examples of relevance in journalism, today’s mediascape reflects a wildly different spectrum. It has turned into an acutely ignorant mockery, normalising caricaturish reportage and incentivising sensationalisation. Moreover, it is threaded by rampant commercialisation and corruption. Politics features heavily in Indian journalism, logically leading it on a path of public critique of authoritative powers, and a much-needed contribution to the democratic awakening of the national. Alas, this aspect of moral and ethical journalism is dumbed down by the Rupert Murdoch-style of reducing news to its bare minimum quality and standard with the intent for merely commercial gains.&amp;nbsp; If you thought that Indian journalism has only recently seen this 'Murdochising' tendency in their news and newsrooms, it is a bleak misconception - one that ignores the historical contexts of the industry. Since the early 1990's, news content has increasingly focused more on celebrities, cinema, cricket and crime. A rapacious pursuit of profit and internal corruption to showcase Bollywood-like style and imagery in broadcast and the shift from politics to politicians is a noticeable indication of a more stylistic form of reality television than relevant content based on the news value of reportage. The Western-style methods being deployed in a proactively traditional society is plunging the Indian media into new depths of misuse and manipulation. The formulation of paid news, wherein politicians sell propaganda masqueraded as 'news' is an unfortunately common phenomenon.&amp;nbsp; Journalism used to be an effective tool for reform, be it political, social, religious or any kind. It was particularly used as a powerful weapon against colonial motives in non-Dominion and non-Settler colonies like India. It attempted to perpetuate awareness, knowledge, thought and wisdom. The evolution of Indian journalism seems to have followed that of journalist James Augustus Hickey. Hickey, who published the first Indian journal to question colonial powers and be critical of any authoritarian decision, ended up piecing a career of publishing scandals, scurrilous personal attacks, and was involved in the unethical advertising of selling “sex and sin”. He did believe in the absolute liberty of the press but connoted the notion of liberty to be coercively tyrannical and vehemently injurious to the community.&amp;nbsp; In the colonial period, even English editors who supported the courage and dignity of Indian journalism found themselves on ships back to England. This included William Duane, editor of Bengal Journal, who was removed as editor and almost deported in 1791, and finally deported as editor of Indian World in 1794. Another was Charles Maclean, the editor of Bengal Hurkaru, who was deported in 1798. Even James Silk Buckingham, editor of Calcutta Journal, and his assistant Sandford Arnot were deported in 1823 and C J Fair, the editor of Bombay Gazette, was also deported in 1823. However, these foreign attempts at preserving journalism helped inspire a number of Indian-language journals in the nooks and corners of the nation. The Bengal Gejeti, edited by Harachandra Roy with the assistance of Gangakishore Bhattacharya, and Samachar Darpan, launched by the Baptist missionaries at Serampore, were both launched in May 1818.&amp;nbsp; It is an enigmatic wonder to imagine a journalistic sphere that is rooted in its foundational principles. Today, its operations have changed. With the convergence of global media technologies and “US-inspired media formats, products and discourse”, the sphere has been reduced to that of market-driven journalism. Integral corrosion is the priority of number value over news value with no regard to protect the public interest. The advent of Rupert Murdoch’s News Corporation had numerous repercussions transnationally, acting as a catalyst for deeply profound institutional and ideological changes, transforming media operations worldwide. From imbibing reluctance in holding an editorial stance to discouraging reporters from providing a critical, educational reportage, and leading an opinion to focusing only on facts rather than furthering a valuable interpretation of those facts - it is all a ruse created to favour the heavy-handed convenience of blurting out facts that don’t add any perceptive depth to a conversation, in order to blatantly chase money and fame.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do Meetings Have Any Agenda?</title><link href="/Do-Meetings-Have-Any-Agenda" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Meetings Have Any Agenda?" /><published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Do-Meetings-Have-Any-Agenda</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Do-Meetings-Have-Any-Agenda">&lt;p&gt;It would take no expert on management to tell you that there's nothing more pissing off than a 'meeting'. To quote David Barry, “&lt;em&gt;Meetings are a highly addictive, self-indulgent activity that corporations and other large organisations engage in only because they cannot actually masturbate&lt;/em&gt;”. But the point, of course, is that despite a huge amount of management literature being spent on decrying the meeting, an American executive - according to research published in the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Business Review &lt;/em&gt;- spends, on average, 300,000 hours on meetings every year. This is astounding since Americans spend around 87,000 hours a year, on average, sleeping. The question is: Why? Why are meetings, at all, addictive, when we know that they are far from productive? Why on earth do we spend more time in meetings instead of getting some shut-eye? The answer requires us to take a deep dive into the nature of production and management in the modern office.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act of making something has, throughout most of history, required an application of physical faculties. The work of a manager has been overseeing the labourer, ensuring that his toils are coordinated and oriented towards the goal of making something.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in a service-based economy, that is simply not possible in a traditional sense. The act of production is now a complex web of mental application. The product, even if made inside a factory, is ultimately an elusive entity that is mentioned in an invoice or a quarterly report. The excel entry called the product is tightly wound within the structure of the mental contrivance called the 'brand'. The brand is what captivates the modern Janus-like 'customer' who again is an email address or a delivery point. The 'market', even if physical, is ultimately a collection of data points, that may be manipulated through 'marketing' to get bigger entries on that column called 'revenue'. Of course, the aim of all this is an 'annual report' where a bunch of numbers indicate that there is 'profit', which is transmitted to the pantheon of gods called 'the shareholders'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the whole idea of production and sale, the idea of a corporation, and its activity is merely a historical imitation of itself. There's no hum of a machine at work, no sound of the worker breaking for lunch after a gong, and no assembly line of men putting different parts together. What we have instead is the receipt of orders, the invoicing and billing, the handover of title through the handover of a bill of lading, the negotiation of a contract via a back-and-forth of emails, the power-point presentations, and so on. The very act of doing business by producing something and selling it for a profit has become a simulation, the corporate executive creates only an imitation of the real at his desk, typing away, caffeinated to the brim.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulation of production represses some very basic needs that a person demands from their work: identity, individuality, a sense of purpose, a feeling of being part of something greater than oneself. And this is not some fancy philosophical takedown, but an assessment based on a very comprehensive body of psychological literature. For instance, a study by K C Madhav and others published in 2017 in the journal of &lt;em&gt;Preventive Medicine Reports&lt;/em&gt; on 3,201 American adults showed that people who spent more than six hours a day looking at a computer screen were highly likely to develop moderate to severe depression. Since the modern workplace requires at least eight hours of work behind a computer screen, we can only imagine how many are silently being pushed into despair by this dehumanising system. Furthermore, according to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cv-library.co.uk/recruitment-insight/brits-suffer-loneliness-workplace/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; of 2,000 working professionals in the UK, around 53.6% of workers admit to feeling lonely, and around 44.4% attribute this to having nothing in common with their colleagues. Clearly, the modern workplace is antithetical to the basic human requirement of socialisation, which as we know, is a crucial component of neuronal health.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting, in such a scenario, and the addictive obsession with it is just a&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;return of the repressed&lt;/em&gt;” (to quote the French psychoanalyst Jacques Lacan). It is a desperate attempt at trying to introduce a feeling of reality and human connection which a simulation of production simply cannot provide. This point becomes even more apparent when we observe how the meeting becomes more and more vague in its mandate and execution. So many meetings are called ‘team-building exercises’, and they have no real discernible purpose, just a way for a manager to look at the people who send him all those emails and feel like he's looking at a factory floor. That apart, there are the ‘brainstorming sessions’, which are about as useful as non-alcoholic beers - with very little thinking happening over the glib and mindless chatter on a few talking points. Finally, there is the ‘feedback meeting’ which is, of course, hardly about genuine feedback.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, the modern meeting is an attempt at dealing with the neurosis of the modern corporation, which most thoroughly fails to actually solve the problem due to the fundamentally artificial setting of simulated production. The question, of course, is how do we actually end this neurosis, how do we give the modern professional his identity and a sense of community and purpose? Is there a way to actually imbue the meeting with meaning? I think it is worth looking at the original medicament to all problems relating to the human condition: religion. And not just any religion, but the oldest one in the world: Hinduism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the grandest meetings ever held in Hindu mythology was the ‘&lt;em&gt;Upanishads&lt;/em&gt;’. They were called by the mythical King Janaka to bring sages and wise men together to engage in great dialogues on philosophy. These dialogues continued for years. King Janaka's daughter, Lady Sita, would sit through these meetings. She would sit and listen intently as the mighty sage Yajnavalkya explained that every man was Brahma - the god of creation - for every man created his own world that was born from his own mind. Yajnavalkya would state, however, that every man or woman could be Brahman - the infinite godhead in Hinduism - and could go beyond his own world by expanding his mind to embrace the worlds of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day Lady Sita realised that as the sages talked, there was almost a magical force that ensured their throats were never parched and that they were always properly fed. She wandered into the royal kitchens to realise why this was so. Lady Sita saw her mother adeptly manage the kitchen to ensure a near-endless supply of food was always available. Lady Sita sat beside her mother, learning how to neatly slice vegetables. She expanded her mind. In other words, she journeyed from Brahma to Brahman because of a truly august meeting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the story of Lady Sita and the Upanishadic meetings may seem too profound to be applicable to a shallow world, it gives us a lot to think about in terms of management theory. Lady Sita and sage Yajnavalkya tell us that a meeting has to become a sacred space - where the neuroses of the modern worker in the simulacra of production are confronted rather than avoided. They tell us that for a meeting to succeed, it has to go beyond just a desperate desire for human connection, serving as a springboard for greater thought and mind-expanding action. In practice, this is easier to implement than one may think, all we need do is ask the worker to expand his mind and truly see. We need to tell him that the sales report under discussion is far more than what appears to a Brahma like him. We need to tell him that the sales report represents the work of so many things coming together to create a Brahman greater than any one worker. In short, we need only remind the worker that the modern corporation now appears only a simulation of itself because the nature of the reality it controls is simply too vast.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A meeting where the manager reminds the modern worker that his typing and emailing on one desk moves mountains in actuality would be the true medicament to the worker's suffering. It would expand his mind to see his co-worker as a compatriot in going beyond their own world of emails and invoices to see the customer, the supplier, and the manufacturer. This would make workers learn from these people, thereby adding true accountability to the corporate process. Most importantly, it would make the worker human again, giving him the tools to fight off real problems like depression and nihilism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">It would take no expert on management to tell you that there's nothing more pissing off than a 'meeting'. To quote David Barry, “Meetings are a highly addictive, self-indulgent activity that corporations and other large organisations engage in only because they cannot actually masturbate”. But the point, of course, is that despite a huge amount of management literature being spent on decrying the meeting, an American executive - according to research published in the Harvard Business Review - spends, on average, 300,000 hours on meetings every year. This is astounding since Americans spend around 87,000 hours a year, on average, sleeping. The question is: Why? Why are meetings, at all, addictive, when we know that they are far from productive? Why on earth do we spend more time in meetings instead of getting some shut-eye? The answer requires us to take a deep dive into the nature of production and management in the modern office.&amp;nbsp; The act of making something has, throughout most of history, required an application of physical faculties. The work of a manager has been overseeing the labourer, ensuring that his toils are coordinated and oriented towards the goal of making something.&amp;nbsp; However, in a service-based economy, that is simply not possible in a traditional sense. The act of production is now a complex web of mental application. The product, even if made inside a factory, is ultimately an elusive entity that is mentioned in an invoice or a quarterly report. The excel entry called the product is tightly wound within the structure of the mental contrivance called the 'brand'. The brand is what captivates the modern Janus-like 'customer' who again is an email address or a delivery point. The 'market', even if physical, is ultimately a collection of data points, that may be manipulated through 'marketing' to get bigger entries on that column called 'revenue'. Of course, the aim of all this is an 'annual report' where a bunch of numbers indicate that there is 'profit', which is transmitted to the pantheon of gods called 'the shareholders'. In short, the whole idea of production and sale, the idea of a corporation, and its activity is merely a historical imitation of itself. There's no hum of a machine at work, no sound of the worker breaking for lunch after a gong, and no assembly line of men putting different parts together. What we have instead is the receipt of orders, the invoicing and billing, the handover of title through the handover of a bill of lading, the negotiation of a contract via a back-and-forth of emails, the power-point presentations, and so on. The very act of doing business by producing something and selling it for a profit has become a simulation, the corporate executive creates only an imitation of the real at his desk, typing away, caffeinated to the brim.&amp;nbsp; The simulation of production represses some very basic needs that a person demands from their work: identity, individuality, a sense of purpose, a feeling of being part of something greater than oneself. And this is not some fancy philosophical takedown, but an assessment based on a very comprehensive body of psychological literature. For instance, a study by K C Madhav and others published in 2017 in the journal of Preventive Medicine Reports on 3,201 American adults showed that people who spent more than six hours a day looking at a computer screen were highly likely to develop moderate to severe depression. Since the modern workplace requires at least eight hours of work behind a computer screen, we can only imagine how many are silently being pushed into despair by this dehumanising system. Furthermore, according to a survey of 2,000 working professionals in the UK, around 53.6% of workers admit to feeling lonely, and around 44.4% attribute this to having nothing in common with their colleagues. Clearly, the modern workplace is antithetical to the basic human requirement of socialisation, which as we know, is a crucial component of neuronal health.&amp;nbsp; The meeting, in such a scenario, and the addictive obsession with it is just a “return of the repressed” (to quote the French psychoanalyst Jacques Lacan). It is a desperate attempt at trying to introduce a feeling of reality and human connection which a simulation of production simply cannot provide. This point becomes even more apparent when we observe how the meeting becomes more and more vague in its mandate and execution. So many meetings are called ‘team-building exercises’, and they have no real discernible purpose, just a way for a manager to look at the people who send him all those emails and feel like he's looking at a factory floor. That apart, there are the ‘brainstorming sessions’, which are about as useful as non-alcoholic beers - with very little thinking happening over the glib and mindless chatter on a few talking points. Finally, there is the ‘feedback meeting’ which is, of course, hardly about genuine feedback.&amp;nbsp; In sum, the modern meeting is an attempt at dealing with the neurosis of the modern corporation, which most thoroughly fails to actually solve the problem due to the fundamentally artificial setting of simulated production. The question, of course, is how do we actually end this neurosis, how do we give the modern professional his identity and a sense of community and purpose? Is there a way to actually imbue the meeting with meaning? I think it is worth looking at the original medicament to all problems relating to the human condition: religion. And not just any religion, but the oldest one in the world: Hinduism.&amp;nbsp; One of the grandest meetings ever held in Hindu mythology was the ‘Upanishads’. They were called by the mythical King Janaka to bring sages and wise men together to engage in great dialogues on philosophy. These dialogues continued for years. King Janaka's daughter, Lady Sita, would sit through these meetings. She would sit and listen intently as the mighty sage Yajnavalkya explained that every man was Brahma - the god of creation - for every man created his own world that was born from his own mind. Yajnavalkya would state, however, that every man or woman could be Brahman - the infinite godhead in Hinduism - and could go beyond his own world by expanding his mind to embrace the worlds of others.&amp;nbsp; One day Lady Sita realised that as the sages talked, there was almost a magical force that ensured their throats were never parched and that they were always properly fed. She wandered into the royal kitchens to realise why this was so. Lady Sita saw her mother adeptly manage the kitchen to ensure a near-endless supply of food was always available. Lady Sita sat beside her mother, learning how to neatly slice vegetables. She expanded her mind. In other words, she journeyed from Brahma to Brahman because of a truly august meeting.&amp;nbsp; While the story of Lady Sita and the Upanishadic meetings may seem too profound to be applicable to a shallow world, it gives us a lot to think about in terms of management theory. Lady Sita and sage Yajnavalkya tell us that a meeting has to become a sacred space - where the neuroses of the modern worker in the simulacra of production are confronted rather than avoided. They tell us that for a meeting to succeed, it has to go beyond just a desperate desire for human connection, serving as a springboard for greater thought and mind-expanding action. In practice, this is easier to implement than one may think, all we need do is ask the worker to expand his mind and truly see. We need to tell him that the sales report under discussion is far more than what appears to a Brahma like him. We need to tell him that the sales report represents the work of so many things coming together to create a Brahman greater than any one worker. In short, we need only remind the worker that the modern corporation now appears only a simulation of itself because the nature of the reality it controls is simply too vast.&amp;nbsp; A meeting where the manager reminds the modern worker that his typing and emailing on one desk moves mountains in actuality would be the true medicament to the worker's suffering. It would expand his mind to see his co-worker as a compatriot in going beyond their own world of emails and invoices to see the customer, the supplier, and the manufacturer. This would make workers learn from these people, thereby adding true accountability to the corporate process. Most importantly, it would make the worker human again, giving him the tools to fight off real problems like depression and nihilism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Retelling of Childhood</title><link href="/A-Retelling-of-Childhood" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Retelling of Childhood" /><published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Retelling-of-Childhood</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Retelling-of-Childhood">&lt;p&gt;All of us have grown up with stories and tales aplenty - that our parents, grandparents and older siblings used to read to us. I had a little corner in my chest of drawers where I kept my A-3 sized colourfully illustrated books about the &lt;em&gt;Little Mermaid, Beauty and the Beast, Thumbelina, Cinderella&lt;/em&gt; and many others. I would take out one copy of those thin, 15-paged books and ask someone to read them to me or even give it a go at reading myself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a kid, I was fascinated with that world and maybe still haven’t lost my touch with it - because who doesn’t enjoy a good Disney&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;movie and some hot chocolate to go with it? Disney&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;is one such institution that has cemented and eternalised the stories that were written hundreds of years ago for children, now told and retold through years, they have changed into a different form - liked by people of all age groups.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while back, I came across the writer behind these beloved stories - Hans Christian Anderson. Even though he revolutionised the world of storytelling through his selected works like - &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; The Snow Queen &lt;/em&gt;(now adapted into the Disney production of &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt;) and&lt;em&gt; The Ugly Duckling &lt;/em&gt;- his work is criticised for being unfit for children. Now that his work, that dates back to 1835, has been adapted into so many plays, productions and movies, one would think that he used to write perfect fairy tales for a blissful childhood. However, the truth is a bit far from that. Anderson is known for his dark and bitter tales that were written for children but without any filters - just blatant truth and atrocities staring oneself in the face.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anderson was born and raised in Denmark in a poor family to a shoemaker father and an illiterate washerwoman mother. Still, he persisted with his education at the local school for the poor, and at night used to listen to the tales of the &lt;em&gt;Arabian Nights&lt;/em&gt; from his father. He had a rough go at childhood and had to move out and provide for himself at an early age - the pain of which is reflected in his early-written pieces. The first and original edition of his stories is unlike the retold versions of them in many ways. For starters, his stories were not as happy-go-lucky as we see them now to be. &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, a classic tale of love and redemption, was actually a disturbing and morbid tale about a mermaid who makes a diabolical bargain with a sea witch and suffers her tongue to be cut out and her tail to be lost, all for the love of a prince. Unfortunately, he completely fails to recognise the enormity of her sacrifice and love for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Disney film adaption of this tale was morphed into a story about love which always unites, as Ariel and Eric get together in the end, and she leaves her world to be with him. Even though Anderson’s story was bitter, it was realistic because it told you that life doesn’t always give you what or whom you desire, and that it’s not okay to give up your life and the things that make you who you are for anyone - because that never ends well. It reflected that no sacrifice will get you eternal love but maybe patience, time and consent would. Even the tale of &lt;em&gt;Thumbelina&lt;/em&gt; was that of grave pain and a torturous existence, unlike the popular idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might not have understood that as a kid, but if something is repeatedly told, from a young age then it can have an impact on you in many ways. The debate around protecting kids from bad and traumatic things is acceptable and justified, but only as long as the truth is harmful to them. If not, even kids have a right to be exposed to the right and wrong of life, to disappointment and failure - so that they learn to take something from it instead of thinking of it as the end. A lot of Anderson’s stories were changed for this reason alone. Because his stories did not twist the truth into entangled sentences about a utopian world but told them things that everyone should know - the reality of this harsh world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only Anderson’s, but many of children’s tales and stories are moulded according to what adults deem right; in fact, some are banned or censored too. A children’s book by the name of &lt;em&gt;And Tango Makes Three&lt;/em&gt; written by Parnell and Richardson was published in 2005, after a real-life incident that occurred in the Central Park Zoo of New York, where two male, chinstrap penguins, Roy and Silo fell in love. The book tells the story of these two male penguins who&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;create a family together. With the help of the zookeeper, Mr Gramsay, Roy and Silo are given an egg which they help hatch. The female chick, that completes their family, is consequently named 'Tango' by the zookeepers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book wasn’t received well by many parents, because according to them, homosexuality in animals suggested homosexuality in humans as well. They argued that they weren’t able to explain to their kids as to why “&lt;em&gt;a male penguin has a baby with another male penguin instead of a mommy penguin&lt;/em&gt;”. After retaliation from parents across the world, the book was consequently banned in Singapore, Hong Kong and places across the United States, like Utah, Missouri and Massachusetts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿It is these ingrained notions and our discomfort with the truth that anything different from what we consider ‘normal’, we try to hide from kids instead of having a conversation with them which they might be completely open to.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;The question that wavers in my mind is, ‘how much of reality is too much’ to be introduced to children? The reason those stories were changed is that it was considered unfit and inappropriate for a child’s brains. Which might be true from one vantage point, however, why must children be veiled from the realities of the world until a certain age only to be exposed to them suddenly at one go? What is really the right age to see the world in its face?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve always wondered how fair it is to concoct a picture of a world that only disappoints you when you grow up. One, it creates unreal expectations from the world and two, it teaches you things that should be shattered as a concept early on while growing up - be it a princess being saved by the valiant hero at the end, kissing someone without their consent (&lt;em&gt;The Sleeping Beauty&lt;/em&gt;) or having to be perfect for people to like you.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I go back and forth in my mind as to why we think of children as weak or want to shield them from the truth? According to many child psychologists, the impulse to protect kids from unpleasant facts is similar to the self-esteem fad practised by educators. The idea rests on the assumption, not backed by any evidence, that high self-esteem must lead to high academic achievement. Similarly, the instinct to protect children from anything unpleasant is simply out of one’s idea of what a child should and shouldn’t know.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if one asks themselves, is this reality protecting your child from long-term pain or is just an area of discussion that you don’t want to deal with, or better answer, and so you choose what is convenient - that is, to digress, to lie and to manoeuvre. You leave your children to figure out the jarring and upsetting realities of life by themselves as they grow up. And more often than not, the sources through which your children consume all the things that were hidden from them during their nascent years are not the most reliable or truthful sources. Thus, as we grow up, we are ambushed with facts and to find answers to them we tend to rely on treacherous sources which skew our ideas all the more. Instead of nurturing our kids with righteousness and practicality from the beginning, we try to mask them from facts, for as long as possible - which might not help them as much as one would hope.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The thing about the ‘real’ world is that unlike fairytales, it’s flawed and filled with imperfections. Which is what drives life ahead, the little or large hiccups in the flow of life. From Anderson’s stories to the truth about sexuality, identity, religion and relationships - a lot is made inconspicuous for the kids so that the information dissemination is controlled according to the norms that we have constructed and reaches them in a palatable form. But the question remains: who gets to decide what is right or wrong for these kids? Are flowery stories with morals sieved through our model of heteronormativity, appropriate culture and paradigms of acceptable behaviour the way to go about raising our kids? Only to impel them later into a world where they stumble as they go through life deconstructing their thoughts and knowledge, indoctrinated throughout childhood and then rebuilding it in a frenzy of emotions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wonder if it would’ve been better, had my parents read me stories of women who didn’t enforce ideals of self-sacrifice to find the truest form of love or tales of women and people in general, who didn’t settle for anything less than what they deserved, did not change themselves only to be accepted by society, and stories that told that life’s utmost purpose was not to find a perfect partner but to find yourself. And in the process of that, you will meet people who will make life worthwhile. But not one of the stories told us, that it is very much okay, even if you don’t. Because in life, there is no blueprint or algorithm like in stories - all the milestones of life are supposed to make your journey easier and not all the more pressurizing. So the moral of this article is maybe that it is okay to chart your own path - because if you find yourself not fitting in with any of the existing stories, you can always write a new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">All of us have grown up with stories and tales aplenty - that our parents, grandparents and older siblings used to read to us. I had a little corner in my chest of drawers where I kept my A-3 sized colourfully illustrated books about the Little Mermaid, Beauty and the Beast, Thumbelina, Cinderella and many others. I would take out one copy of those thin, 15-paged books and ask someone to read them to me or even give it a go at reading myself.&amp;nbsp; As a kid, I was fascinated with that world and maybe still haven’t lost my touch with it - because who doesn’t enjoy a good Disney movie and some hot chocolate to go with it? Disney is one such institution that has cemented and eternalised the stories that were written hundreds of years ago for children, now told and retold through years, they have changed into a different form - liked by people of all age groups.&amp;nbsp; A while back, I came across the writer behind these beloved stories - Hans Christian Anderson. Even though he revolutionised the world of storytelling through his selected works like - The Little Mermaid, The Snow Queen (now adapted into the Disney production of Frozen) and The Ugly Duckling - his work is criticised for being unfit for children. Now that his work, that dates back to 1835, has been adapted into so many plays, productions and movies, one would think that he used to write perfect fairy tales for a blissful childhood. However, the truth is a bit far from that. Anderson is known for his dark and bitter tales that were written for children but without any filters - just blatant truth and atrocities staring oneself in the face.&amp;nbsp; Anderson was born and raised in Denmark in a poor family to a shoemaker father and an illiterate washerwoman mother. Still, he persisted with his education at the local school for the poor, and at night used to listen to the tales of the Arabian Nights from his father. He had a rough go at childhood and had to move out and provide for himself at an early age - the pain of which is reflected in his early-written pieces. The first and original edition of his stories is unlike the retold versions of them in many ways. For starters, his stories were not as happy-go-lucky as we see them now to be. The Little Mermaid, a classic tale of love and redemption, was actually a disturbing and morbid tale about a mermaid who makes a diabolical bargain with a sea witch and suffers her tongue to be cut out and her tail to be lost, all for the love of a prince. Unfortunately, he completely fails to recognise the enormity of her sacrifice and love for him. The Disney film adaption of this tale was morphed into a story about love which always unites, as Ariel and Eric get together in the end, and she leaves her world to be with him. Even though Anderson’s story was bitter, it was realistic because it told you that life doesn’t always give you what or whom you desire, and that it’s not okay to give up your life and the things that make you who you are for anyone - because that never ends well. It reflected that no sacrifice will get you eternal love but maybe patience, time and consent would. Even the tale of Thumbelina was that of grave pain and a torturous existence, unlike the popular idea. I might not have understood that as a kid, but if something is repeatedly told, from a young age then it can have an impact on you in many ways. The debate around protecting kids from bad and traumatic things is acceptable and justified, but only as long as the truth is harmful to them. If not, even kids have a right to be exposed to the right and wrong of life, to disappointment and failure - so that they learn to take something from it instead of thinking of it as the end. A lot of Anderson’s stories were changed for this reason alone. Because his stories did not twist the truth into entangled sentences about a utopian world but told them things that everyone should know - the reality of this harsh world. Not only Anderson’s, but many of children’s tales and stories are moulded according to what adults deem right; in fact, some are banned or censored too. A children’s book by the name of And Tango Makes Three written by Parnell and Richardson was published in 2005, after a real-life incident that occurred in the Central Park Zoo of New York, where two male, chinstrap penguins, Roy and Silo fell in love. The book tells the story of these two male penguins who create a family together. With the help of the zookeeper, Mr Gramsay, Roy and Silo are given an egg which they help hatch. The female chick, that completes their family, is consequently named 'Tango' by the zookeepers.&amp;nbsp; This book wasn’t received well by many parents, because according to them, homosexuality in animals suggested homosexuality in humans as well. They argued that they weren’t able to explain to their kids as to why “a male penguin has a baby with another male penguin instead of a mommy penguin”. After retaliation from parents across the world, the book was consequently banned in Singapore, Hong Kong and places across the United States, like Utah, Missouri and Massachusetts. ﻿It is these ingrained notions and our discomfort with the truth that anything different from what we consider ‘normal’, we try to hide from kids instead of having a conversation with them which they might be completely open to.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;The question that wavers in my mind is, ‘how much of reality is too much’ to be introduced to children? The reason those stories were changed is that it was considered unfit and inappropriate for a child’s brains. Which might be true from one vantage point, however, why must children be veiled from the realities of the world until a certain age only to be exposed to them suddenly at one go? What is really the right age to see the world in its face?&amp;nbsp;I’ve always wondered how fair it is to concoct a picture of a world that only disappoints you when you grow up. One, it creates unreal expectations from the world and two, it teaches you things that should be shattered as a concept early on while growing up - be it a princess being saved by the valiant hero at the end, kissing someone without their consent (The Sleeping Beauty) or having to be perfect for people to like you.&amp;nbsp;I go back and forth in my mind as to why we think of children as weak or want to shield them from the truth? According to many child psychologists, the impulse to protect kids from unpleasant facts is similar to the self-esteem fad practised by educators. The idea rests on the assumption, not backed by any evidence, that high self-esteem must lead to high academic achievement. Similarly, the instinct to protect children from anything unpleasant is simply out of one’s idea of what a child should and shouldn’t know.&amp;nbsp;But if one asks themselves, is this reality protecting your child from long-term pain or is just an area of discussion that you don’t want to deal with, or better answer, and so you choose what is convenient - that is, to digress, to lie and to manoeuvre. You leave your children to figure out the jarring and upsetting realities of life by themselves as they grow up. And more often than not, the sources through which your children consume all the things that were hidden from them during their nascent years are not the most reliable or truthful sources. Thus, as we grow up, we are ambushed with facts and to find answers to them we tend to rely on treacherous sources which skew our ideas all the more. Instead of nurturing our kids with righteousness and practicality from the beginning, we try to mask them from facts, for as long as possible - which might not help them as much as one would hope.&amp;nbsp;The thing about the ‘real’ world is that unlike fairytales, it’s flawed and filled with imperfections. Which is what drives life ahead, the little or large hiccups in the flow of life. From Anderson’s stories to the truth about sexuality, identity, religion and relationships - a lot is made inconspicuous for the kids so that the information dissemination is controlled according to the norms that we have constructed and reaches them in a palatable form. But the question remains: who gets to decide what is right or wrong for these kids? Are flowery stories with morals sieved through our model of heteronormativity, appropriate culture and paradigms of acceptable behaviour the way to go about raising our kids? Only to impel them later into a world where they stumble as they go through life deconstructing their thoughts and knowledge, indoctrinated throughout childhood and then rebuilding it in a frenzy of emotions.I wonder if it would’ve been better, had my parents read me stories of women who didn’t enforce ideals of self-sacrifice to find the truest form of love or tales of women and people in general, who didn’t settle for anything less than what they deserved, did not change themselves only to be accepted by society, and stories that told that life’s utmost purpose was not to find a perfect partner but to find yourself. And in the process of that, you will meet people who will make life worthwhile. But not one of the stories told us, that it is very much okay, even if you don’t. Because in life, there is no blueprint or algorithm like in stories - all the milestones of life are supposed to make your journey easier and not all the more pressurizing. So the moral of this article is maybe that it is okay to chart your own path - because if you find yourself not fitting in with any of the existing stories, you can always write a new one.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SKY Castle: What Happens When Adults Don’t Act Like Adults?</title><link href="/SKY-Castle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SKY Castle: What Happens When Adults Don't Act Like Adults?" /><published>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/SKY-Castle</id><content type="html" xml:base="/SKY-Castle">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We all lie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tell you the truths&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sometimes we laugh and easily lie&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;SKY Castle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a satirical, dark comedy-drama that revolves around the lives of four elite families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood, situated in the suburbs of Seoul. In reality, &lt;em&gt;SKY&lt;/em&gt; is an acronym for the three renowned colleges of South Korea, namely, Seoul National University (SNU), Korea University and Yonsei University. SKY neighbourhood is home to top doctors and a prosecutor turned professor, who all want their children to live a worthy life, which according to them, can only be achieved if they get into one of these above-mentioned colleges. Thus, the story revolves around the Korean National College Exam, &lt;em&gt;Suneung&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show, like most K-drama shows, starts with a straightforward story but manages to leave the audience baffled with its twists and turns. It's a really well-crafted show that makes its audience grip to their screens since the first episode itself. What is commendable about &lt;em&gt;SKY Castle&lt;/em&gt; is that despite its twists, never once does it distract itself from the main plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first episode opens with a party being thrown to celebrate the Park family; whose son got into the Seoul National Medical School. But more than being happy, the other families are interested in knowing the methods that led to his admission. As it turns out, an expensive entrance exam coordinator made this possible. Therefore, this information starts a fight to hire her at an exclusive VVIP party. This coordinator who goes by the name of Kim Joo-Young chooses to teach Ye-Seo, whose only dream has been to get admission in Seoul National Medical College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dark cloud falls over the Park family when Lee Myung-Joo, the mother, decides to take her own life. We notice that Kim Joo-Young, the exceptional coordinator, definitely had something to do with it. However, Ye-Seo’s mother, even after finding it all out, is willing to look past all this because all she wants is to see her daughter get into SNU. With such a tragedy, Park family decides to move out and this opens the door for a new family to move in. This new family, Hwang family, have a simple and relaxed outlook towards life which clearly doesn't sit well with the other families. From questioning Lee So Im’s teaching methods to constantly treating her as an outsider, they really do give the Hwang family a hard time. Even at the hospital, Dr Hwang, who wants to treat the patients and interns with utmost respect, is criticised by Dr Kang, Ye-Seo’s father, who is more inclined towards making money and asserting his authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With each passing episode, we realise that Joo-Young’s flawless result isn’t a work of her own credibility, but her ability to cheat her ways through. Besides, all the families who have hired her have faced consequences similar to the Park family. But by the time Ye-Seo or her mother became aware of this, they are in too deep in to take a step back. What further unfolds is the lie that Joo-Young managed to hide for all these years, which is also the reason behind her desire to destroy each and every family that hires her. At this point, I thought I couldn't possibly dislike this character more, but what happens in the remaining episodes clearly left me speechless.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other two families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood include the Cha and Woo families, who have more of a side role to play. In the&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Cha family, Min-Hyuk (the head of the family) being the prosecutor turned professor, wants his kids to reach the “&lt;em&gt;top of the pyramid&lt;/em&gt;” which he himself failed to do. He forces his dreams on his kids through means that only bear negative results. With the twin boys being average at school, which is obviously something that Min-Hyuk cannot deal with, to the eldest daughter lying about being in Harvard, all of it is a result of him constantly pressuring them. On the other hand, Noh Seung-Hye is an understanding mother who clearly sees through Min-Hyuk’s methods and is willing to end her marriage if that is what it takes to save her children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last is the Woo family, and here we see a mother struggling to find a balance between keeping her child happy but also wanting him to study hard and get into SKY. With Dr Woo working under Dr Kang, we constantly see them trying to be on the good side of the Kang family. Not to mention, this family really adds the much-needed elements of comedy that takes this show on another tangent altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fifth episode, we come across a new character Kim Hye-na, a bold kid studying in the same class as Ye-Seo. Despite her being a poor child, with a sick mother admitted in the hospital, she still manages to surpass Ye-Seo in academics. Ye-Seo, being a child who cannot stand failure, and her mother, who cannot see her child upset, clearly don't take this well. Ye-Seo’s mother even goes out of her way to tell Hye-na to not mess with Ye-Seo and her goal. To be honest, initially, I didn’t think that her role could be any more than a classmate, but the story that revolves around Hye-na's life leaves Ye-Seo’s goal of SNU Medical School, shaken to its very core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This show started with a rating of as low as 1%, and halfway through the show, it managed to reach skyrocketing numbers. It has nothing common with the popular K-dramas that revolve around romance, which is also why it is my favourite show. &lt;em&gt;SKY Castle &lt;/em&gt;is rather a series that very smartly raises some of the darkest issues that exist in societies all across the globe, especially around Korea’s Scholastic Ability Test, &lt;em&gt;Suneung&lt;/em&gt;. With a cast so carefully chosen, and with every actor being true to their role, this show really proves why it received such high ratings. From highlighting the harsh reality of the Korean educational system and how it can take a toll on the mental health of children (since all of them are told is to get into SKY), it also portrays how the elite families are willing to go beyond their means to get their children into a good college, by spending huge sums of money or even adopting ways not available to a normal family. It constantly emphasises how parents tend to force their unachieved dreams and ambitions on their children without asking them what they really want, which can have unforeseen consequences. The other thing that needs to be mentioned is the original soundtrack, &quot;&lt;em&gt;We all lie&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. This soundtrack is so brilliantly curated that it works perfectly with the storyline. And it is definitely one of those songs I found myself going back to. Also, the added bonus being that it's entirely an English song, strategically used to pull international audiences to the show.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I agree with the majority audience that the last episode could have been better, but by no means does it destroy the very essence of the show and what it's trying to put forward. Throughout the show, we are made to realise that if Ye-Seo's mother wasn't so selfish towards her child's goal, this all could have been easily avoided. But then, we wouldn't have gotten this masterpiece to binge-watch. Therefore, I recommend this show to the audiences as it has a message relevant to all age groups. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Priyanshi Mehra</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">“We all lie Tell you the truths Sometimes we laugh and easily lie” &amp;nbsp;SKY Castle is a satirical, dark comedy-drama that revolves around the lives of four elite families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood, situated in the suburbs of Seoul. In reality, SKY is an acronym for the three renowned colleges of South Korea, namely, Seoul National University (SNU), Korea University and Yonsei University. SKY neighbourhood is home to top doctors and a prosecutor turned professor, who all want their children to live a worthy life, which according to them, can only be achieved if they get into one of these above-mentioned colleges. Thus, the story revolves around the Korean National College Exam, Suneung. The show, like most K-drama shows, starts with a straightforward story but manages to leave the audience baffled with its twists and turns. It's a really well-crafted show that makes its audience grip to their screens since the first episode itself. What is commendable about SKY Castle is that despite its twists, never once does it distract itself from the main plot. The first episode opens with a party being thrown to celebrate the Park family; whose son got into the Seoul National Medical School. But more than being happy, the other families are interested in knowing the methods that led to his admission. As it turns out, an expensive entrance exam coordinator made this possible. Therefore, this information starts a fight to hire her at an exclusive VVIP party. This coordinator who goes by the name of Kim Joo-Young chooses to teach Ye-Seo, whose only dream has been to get admission in Seoul National Medical College. A dark cloud falls over the Park family when Lee Myung-Joo, the mother, decides to take her own life. We notice that Kim Joo-Young, the exceptional coordinator, definitely had something to do with it. However, Ye-Seo’s mother, even after finding it all out, is willing to look past all this because all she wants is to see her daughter get into SNU. With such a tragedy, Park family decides to move out and this opens the door for a new family to move in. This new family, Hwang family, have a simple and relaxed outlook towards life which clearly doesn't sit well with the other families. From questioning Lee So Im’s teaching methods to constantly treating her as an outsider, they really do give the Hwang family a hard time. Even at the hospital, Dr Hwang, who wants to treat the patients and interns with utmost respect, is criticised by Dr Kang, Ye-Seo’s father, who is more inclined towards making money and asserting his authority. With each passing episode, we realise that Joo-Young’s flawless result isn’t a work of her own credibility, but her ability to cheat her ways through. Besides, all the families who have hired her have faced consequences similar to the Park family. But by the time Ye-Seo or her mother became aware of this, they are in too deep in to take a step back. What further unfolds is the lie that Joo-Young managed to hide for all these years, which is also the reason behind her desire to destroy each and every family that hires her. At this point, I thought I couldn't possibly dislike this character more, but what happens in the remaining episodes clearly left me speechless.&amp;nbsp; The other two families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood include the Cha and Woo families, who have more of a side role to play. In the Cha family, Min-Hyuk (the head of the family) being the prosecutor turned professor, wants his kids to reach the “top of the pyramid” which he himself failed to do. He forces his dreams on his kids through means that only bear negative results. With the twin boys being average at school, which is obviously something that Min-Hyuk cannot deal with, to the eldest daughter lying about being in Harvard, all of it is a result of him constantly pressuring them. On the other hand, Noh Seung-Hye is an understanding mother who clearly sees through Min-Hyuk’s methods and is willing to end her marriage if that is what it takes to save her children. The last is the Woo family, and here we see a mother struggling to find a balance between keeping her child happy but also wanting him to study hard and get into SKY. With Dr Woo working under Dr Kang, we constantly see them trying to be on the good side of the Kang family. Not to mention, this family really adds the much-needed elements of comedy that takes this show on another tangent altogether. In the fifth episode, we come across a new character Kim Hye-na, a bold kid studying in the same class as Ye-Seo. Despite her being a poor child, with a sick mother admitted in the hospital, she still manages to surpass Ye-Seo in academics. Ye-Seo, being a child who cannot stand failure, and her mother, who cannot see her child upset, clearly don't take this well. Ye-Seo’s mother even goes out of her way to tell Hye-na to not mess with Ye-Seo and her goal. To be honest, initially, I didn’t think that her role could be any more than a classmate, but the story that revolves around Hye-na's life leaves Ye-Seo’s goal of SNU Medical School, shaken to its very core. This show started with a rating of as low as 1%, and halfway through the show, it managed to reach skyrocketing numbers. It has nothing common with the popular K-dramas that revolve around romance, which is also why it is my favourite show. SKY Castle is rather a series that very smartly raises some of the darkest issues that exist in societies all across the globe, especially around Korea’s Scholastic Ability Test, Suneung. With a cast so carefully chosen, and with every actor being true to their role, this show really proves why it received such high ratings. From highlighting the harsh reality of the Korean educational system and how it can take a toll on the mental health of children (since all of them are told is to get into SKY), it also portrays how the elite families are willing to go beyond their means to get their children into a good college, by spending huge sums of money or even adopting ways not available to a normal family. It constantly emphasises how parents tend to force their unachieved dreams and ambitions on their children without asking them what they really want, which can have unforeseen consequences. The other thing that needs to be mentioned is the original soundtrack, &quot;We all lie&quot;. This soundtrack is so brilliantly curated that it works perfectly with the storyline. And it is definitely one of those songs I found myself going back to. Also, the added bonus being that it's entirely an English song, strategically used to pull international audiences to the show.&amp;nbsp; While I agree with the majority audience that the last episode could have been better, but by no means does it destroy the very essence of the show and what it's trying to put forward. Throughout the show, we are made to realise that if Ye-Seo's mother wasn't so selfish towards her child's goal, this all could have been easily avoided. But then, we wouldn't have gotten this masterpiece to binge-watch. Therefore, I recommend this show to the audiences as it has a message relevant to all age groups.</summary></entry></feed>