<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-23T18:30:58+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Puppets of Patriarchy</title><link href="/Puppets-of-Patriarchy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Puppets of Patriarchy" /><published>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Puppets-of-Patriarchy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Puppets-of-Patriarchy">&lt;p&gt;I wake up every morning as a woman in this society, a child of the upper-middle-class, privileged and comfortable in my warm bed. I have the option to choose the course of my day as I like, as do most of the women in my surroundings. However, a lot of us forget amidst the warmth of our mornings that our choices or rather the right to choose weren’t granted to us on a platter of silverware. It has been a long, arduous, gory fight since the beginning of time. From colossal watershed moments like wars and suffrage to societal acceptance, from voting rights and the combat against harassment to as minuscule a subject as walking freely on the streets in a pair of your favourite blue jeans. The world hasn’t been a wish-granting factory for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most men &lt;em&gt;used to, still do, and always will&lt;/em&gt; wake up every day in a society that doesn’t refer to them as ‘The Second Sex’. They don’t have to walk the face of the earth with gills to breathe with on land. And in those moments when you forget what the millions of women, forgotten and faded through history, gave up, the ones who asked &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; and refuted with a staunch &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;, take a swift sift through the past that screams for you to protect this privilege. Yes, it’s a privilege, even if it shouldn’t have been because respecting another human being and walking with them instead of trooping ahead should be as easy as shutting your eyes close and lapsing into sleep. Instead of morphing this system into a more accepting and wholesome one, it might just be easier in a parallel world, where we can go back 200,000 years in time and reset the trail of human life on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is my statement to everyone who has ever questioned me as to why we need feminism anymore. To those who still foolishly think of it as a process with an end date, a time when everything will be idyllic and we’ll stop the ‘train of feminism’. To those who question the label that it has gained over the last few decades, mindless of the fact that it was them who pejoratively stamped in that way- both men and women. Men, who are scared and alarmed at the thought of a world where their kind doesn’t dominate and take precedence anymore but exists in an unruffled state with the environment with all people, all genders. And the women who have so long been repressed and rewired that they don’t think that openly breathing is an option anymore. And to everybody who thinks that feminism is a struggle against men,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vehemently disagree, for these people are way off-target. For two reasons- because I reckon women aren’t in the least powerless, let alone tenuous in front of any gender. And secondly, for those who think that men aren’t subjugated in this society are starkly mistaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchy is a friend to none, no gender; be it men, women or non-binary. It feeds and thrives on the politics of power and authority and throttles whatever comes in its way. Men who aren’t ‘masculine’ enough, women who are too ‘brazen’, ‘impure’ castes and races, and everyone who doesn’t fit inside their box; the icy-cold, suffocating box with pores impossible to permeate, into which it shoves all who refuse to conform to the beliefs of gender. Gender, which is just a socially constructed idea, gradually fabricated into a sheath of rules and norms, which in actuality is as abstract an idea as complex numbers, perhaps. Apart from the normal human physiology that describes a person’s sex, no science explains the attributes we innocently anoint to the ‘two’ genders. They say women are calm and understanding, whereas men are temperamental and impulsive. &lt;em&gt;Of pinks and blues, cooking and driving, dominant and submissive, on top, on the bottom, floral and solid;&lt;/em&gt; gender is a &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; perfected intricately over years, contingent on patriarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judith Butler, a renowned gender theorist, contends that being female is not “natural” and that it appears natural only through repeated performances of gender; these performances in turn reproduce and define the traditional categories of gender. Maybe Shakespeare was right, maybe the world is a stage and we’re all mere players, nay, puppets of patriarchy. These roles assigned to us are bolstered into a cemented building, so tightly plastered that any attempt to subvert that structure is considered a convulsion of the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stereotyping is the soul food of human civilisation, especially when it comes to gender. And a simple explanation for it could be the fact that it is easier on the brain to stereotype, in other words, a heuristic. When faced with a decision to be made quickly, our brain doesn’t have the time or resources to compare all the information before making a choice, and so people often rely on mental shortcuts known as representative heuristics. Stereotyping stems from these heuristics and when inculcated as a habit or unwittingly imbibed since an early age, can be spotted in children as young as six years old. If you take a neutral environment and raise two different sexes with the same treatment and knowledge, bereft of these norms, they will grow up to be free of gender stereotypes. The girl might not necessarily pick up the doll and the boy the copter, but if they do, it will be out of a liking, a choice and not a manoeuvred stereotype that the society has comfortably sunk into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchal violence is not solely against women but nature as well, and when we stand up against the Satanic cousin that is patriarchy, tearing down this concrete-helix structure, we emerge loyal to the posterity and to the planet itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the foundation of ‘Eco-Feminism’, first ideated in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. Eco-feminism is about connectedness and wholeness of the abstract and the actual. It asserts a special strength and integrity of every living thing. Vandana Shiva, a radical eco-feminist from India has changed the conception of this idea in her analysis of links between the degradation of women and the exploitation of nature in modern social setups. It highlights the gall of patriarchy to dominate and destroy not just ‘anything that isn’t masculine’ but the environment we’re living in. Both women and the environment are undervalued in our global system and economies and both are very essential elements of our world, if we are to see a changeover to a more inclusive and sustainable economy. Better use of the world’s female population would increase economic growth, reduce poverty, enhance societal well-being, and help ensure sustainable development in all countries since women have a smaller ecological footprint than men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fight hasn’t gotten any easier than it was before. It started with earning the rights and the place we deserved. And after a good 100 years, only six countries in the world give other genders absolute equal rights, the World Bank found out. And they ask what more do we need? Others do state those (hollow) rights in their constitution, but they don’t uphold them. So now it is about taking those values into everyday life and making them as real and tangible as possible. The fight now is to break down the barrier of being referred to as ‘The Second Sex’ and locomote to a non-ordinal world, where genders aren’t ranked, defined, suffocated, and bifurcated into pink and blue. Instead, they can breathe and identify themselves through the way that they feel and not necessarily their sex, manifesting through a rainbow of colours.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">I wake up every morning as a woman in this society, a child of the upper-middle-class, privileged and comfortable in my warm bed. I have the option to choose the course of my day as I like, as do most of the women in my surroundings. However, a lot of us forget amidst the warmth of our mornings that our choices or rather the right to choose weren’t granted to us on a platter of silverware. It has been a long, arduous, gory fight since the beginning of time. From colossal watershed moments like wars and suffrage to societal acceptance, from voting rights and the combat against harassment to as minuscule a subject as walking freely on the streets in a pair of your favourite blue jeans. The world hasn’t been a wish-granting factory for us.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">False Hope is a Parasite</title><link href="/False-Hope-is-a-Parasite" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="False Hope is a Parasite" /><published>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/False-Hope-is-a-Parasite</id><content type="html" xml:base="/False-Hope-is-a-Parasite">&lt;p&gt;During his childhood days, director Bong Joon Ho used to hike and traverse the hilly landscapes of his hometown Daegu in the country of South Korea, where he gradually became fond of collecting stones with his father. It must have been one of his favourite pastimes and nostalgia-inducing memories of his early days, for one such mystical rock found its way in his Oscar-winning movie, &lt;em&gt;Parasite&lt;/em&gt;, many years after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based around the lives of two Korean families, &lt;em&gt;Parasite&lt;/em&gt; is a tale about many things. The Kims, a poverty-stricken family living out in a semi-basement, slowly infiltrate the lives of the Parks, a rich family living in the home of a world-renowned architect. The Kims’ son, Ki-woo replaces his friend’s position as a tutor for the Parks’ daughter and hence begins a story about lying, cheating and manipulation as the rest of the Kims’ slowly slither their way into the household of the Parks’ as their domestic help. All of the plotting and scheming, when covered and infused with black comedy, thoroughly amuses all of us; however, it is midway through the movie when it takes a horrifying turn of events and a mirror is placed in front of us, to make us see a hard-hitting image of the class divide we all actively participate in perpetuating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked during one of his interviews about where he got the inspiration for incorporating class-consciousness in his art, director Bong Joon Ho replied, &lt;em&gt;“I think all creators, all artists, and even just everyone, we are always interested in class, 24/7. I think it would actually be strange if we’re not. You know, when we’re seeing people on the subway, on the streets, complete strangers, we wonder,&lt;/em&gt; how rich are they? &lt;em&gt;Or you know, people we encounter in the airports, did they ride economy class, business class? We always wonder about this, because we live in the era of capitalism. I think we all have a very sensitive antennae to class, in general.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was during Ki-woo and his friend’s conversation, when he is gifted a mystifying and eccentric-looking rock by his friend. The rock confuses Ki-woo and he exclaims, &lt;em&gt;“It’s so metaphorical!”&lt;/em&gt; when he shows it to his family. Throughout the movie, Ki-woo is shown to be bedazzled and stumped by this rock’s presence, a sentiment mirroring my own. This rock simply fascinated me. One of the few reasons for this was how strange it looked in the dingy basement of the Kims’. Later on in the movie, when it is used as a murder weapon, it perplexed me even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to dig up symbols in movies and I found plenty in this one. Frequent shots of stairs, basements, ascending roads and alleyways, smell and even &lt;em&gt;noodles&lt;/em&gt;; each one of them were beautifully crafted as symbols for depicting the evils of capitalism and the ever-widening gap between the rich and the poor. The Parks’ are always portrayed climbing up the stairs in their home while the Kims’ are mostly shown descending them. One of the most famous scenes of the film depicting Mrs Park fawning over how blissful and lucky she felt that it rained heavily during the preceding night when that same rain caused the Kims’ to almost lose their house to floods is a testament to just how riddled we’ve all become to act class-ignorant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Ki-woo tightly hugs the gifted rock to his chest at a camp after a dreadful rain displaces hundreds like him and his family, it dawned on me that the rock represented a ‘hope’ for him. Whether it was the hope that he could lead a luxurious life as the rock’s original owner, his friend, or the long-dreamt of vision of a better future for him and his family, this rock meant something to him. It meant the unlikely possibility of a life free from the clutches of poverty, hence why he wanted to cling onto it so badly in times of adversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This false hope of dismantling a system forever uplifting the rich and denigrating the poor, by hook or by crook, takes the form of a malicious scheme initiated by Ki-woo himself, which leads to the Kims’ acting like a &lt;em&gt;parasite&lt;/em&gt;, trying dearly to hold onto the Parks’ for their survival. The Parks’ leech off of the Kims’ hard labour, trying to keep them from ‘crossing the line’, in an attempt to maintain their status quo and respectability in the society. During one of the most realistic scenes in the film - the fight between the Kims’ and other members of the working class, it is reiterated that it’s the false hope of re-establishing one’s superiority over the other that is destroying them, when in reality they are all victims of the same evil and must stand in solidarity with each other. This false hope ultimately leads both the families of Kims’ and Parks’ to a disturbingly sad fate, which makes them go down a downward spiral they can probably never emerge from again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the movie, we are shown an ideal representation of what the Kims’ family turns up like many years afterwards. A slightly older Ki-woo moves in with his mother to the house of the Parks and reunites with his father. It is a version of events too hard to believe but we almost believe it, because humans have a tendency to cling onto every last string of hope available, just like Ki-woo in the movie. Suddenly, the scene shifts to a young Ki-woo still sitting in his semi-basement home. The movie ends with a visual of the rock being placed back in the river, probably where it came from originally. This scene stumped me for words because it signified that Ki-woo was finally letting go of his false hope. Even though the ending of &lt;em&gt;Parasite&lt;/em&gt; is deemed sad by most, for me, it was the ideal one. Maybe Ki-woo finally takes his father’s advice of making it all work by not having a plan at all. Maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aarushi Mittal</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">During his childhood days, director Bong Joon Ho used to hike and traverse the hilly landscapes of his hometown Daegu in the country of South Korea, where he gradually became fond of collecting stones with his father. It must have been one of his favourite pastimes and nostalgia-inducing memories of his early days, for one such mystical rock found its way in his Oscar-winning movie, Parasite, many years after.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Insight into the World’s Favourite Hermit State</title><link href="/Hermit-State" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Insight into the World’s Favourite Hermit State" /><published>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Hermit-State</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Hermit-State">&lt;p&gt;A K-Drama that I was watching recently revolved around a North Korean soldier. The drama was great, but what stayed with me post bingeing it was the intrigue for North Korea: a country that calls itself the greatest nation in the world while its people suffer from the worst human rights violations; a country that calls itself a democracy with a 100% voter turnout in any election but has the world’s most authoritarian regime; a country built on the ideology of ‘self-reliance’ but heavily dependent on aid from the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On typing ‘North Korea’ in the search bar on Google, you note that the search results are dominated by nuclear weapons and North Korea’s relationship with the US and South Korea. Most of the articles paint them as enemies. However, this is where the problem lies - we equate the North Korean people with its government. While the leader and the high-ranking officials propagate an ideology and a culture that benefits them, the common man bears it. This is a country where there is no scope for upward mobility. Defecting is the only way that allows them the taste of a better life. However, in doing so, they are exposed to the racist world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Myers notes that an international network on Google Earth is working on identifying structures visible in aerial photographs in North Korea. Yet, the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK) remains a mystery to many. He attributes this to people’s view of DPRK via the lens of economics and nuclear weapons, and not via its propaganda and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea is effectively a totalitarian state run by a dynastic line of dictators. Its cultural and political ideology is based on devotion to leader Kim Il-Sung, whose eternal Presidential authority is written into the Constitution. Three branches constitute the government– executive, legislative and judiciary. The Premier and the Supreme Leader (Kim Jong-un) control the executive branch. The legislative branch is a congress, called the Supreme People’s Assembly, occupied by unopposed candidates from the Workers’ Party of Korea. They, however, rarely meet and have historically passed nearly all proposed laws without debate. The judicial branch is known for secretive trials headed by judges appointed by the SPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a gulag posing as a nation. Everything there is about the great leader: books, newspaper articles, songs and TV programs. The flowers are named after him, and mountains are carved with his slogans. In line with this, only ‘state-approved’ content is produced, as books, newspaper articles, songs and TV programs are all censored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea calls itself a communist country, which it is not, it is also not the last bastion of Confucian patriarchy, as they often characterise it. Rather, it’s guided by a paranoid ideology of race-based nationalism, holding that Koreans are purer than all others. In his book, &lt;em&gt;The Cleanest Race: How North Koreans See Themselves and Why It Matters&lt;/em&gt;, Brian Myers notes that the nation’s race-based ideology has its roots in Japanese fascism. He states the government’s criteria for national identity paints its citizens as innocent and morally virtuous but militarily weak. Thus, they require Kim Il-Sung’s guidance and protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country harbours a population of 25 million, with a low rate of population growth. The population of this ‘mighty’ and ‘prosperous’ is starving. The Soviet Union originally supported North Korea. However, the collapse of the USSR led to DPRK not receiving aid, making food production plummet in the early 1990’s. This, coupled with natural disasters, led to the infamous 1990 famine. In the years since, aid from the US and other countries has helped improve the situation. However, most North Koreans still don’t have access to food with necessary nutrients, subsiding on crops like rice, cabbages, and radish. In poorer regions, boiled grass and ground tree bark serve as food alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korean society is based on a social caste system called–‘songbun’, used to allocate government assistance like housing and rations. The loyalty to the North Korean government is the key factor in determining the ranks of the people, and any real or perceived slight against the government can lead to the demotion of an entire family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no source of outside information, the North Koreans have been ignorant. And in this ignorance lies their safety. It’s a common myth that everyone in North Korea is brainwashed. A considerable number of people are brainwashed, as many committed suicides after the death of Kim Il-Sung as they didn’t know what to do without their leader. But the majority knows the nation is not as prosperous as it shows itself to be and thus, have defected. The fear of punishment has motivated the supposed admiration of the Supreme Leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Juche’ ideology has shaped the lifestyle of these people. Every household in North Korea is supposed to display the portraits of the eternal leaders, Kim Il-Sung and Kim Jong-Il. There are strict rules and fines associated with dusting the pictures regularly, and their placement for maximum respect. As a symbol of the North Korean identity, all citizens wear a red lapel pin with portraits of the eternal leaders on themselves 24/7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea observes an 11-year school for the children. In the formative years, the children are taught the legends of their eternal leader. Subjects like Science and Mathematics are paid less attention compared to North Korean history. Many defectors note that growing up they were taught to believe their great leader was a god working tirelessly for their benefit. The idea of their leader being a god was so deeply entrenched that they used to think he could even hear their thoughts, making them afraid of even thinking negatively about the eternal leader. The students have been simply told what to think, and they obey. In their world, critical thinking isn’t allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 10 and a 3-year military enlistment is compulsory for all men and women, respectively, after they’ve completed their high school. The government assigns jobs to its people, based on industry needs and location, which they’re supposed to do without fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government claims to provide free healthcare to all its citizens. However, reports say it spends less per citizen than almost any other country in the world. The country has a low standard of care, with nearly all regions suffering shortages of medical equipment and medication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public executions are also a common practice in the world’s favourite hermit state. In fact, too common. A defector revealed that her mother was publicly executed for watching a Hollywood movie. It is mandatory for every North Korean, 12 and above, to witness the public execution. Only the Great Leader has absolute human rights; all others are his vassals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way of escaping this regime, other than taking the government’s permission, is by defecting and illegally crossing the border. The most common strategy is to cross the border in northeast China before fleeing to a third country. This third country generally becomes South Korea, the country that is supposed to be their enemy, welcomes them with open arms. If, however, the defectors are caught in China; they are deported back where they often face harsh interrogations and years of punishment or even death in political prison camps. Post the 1990 famine, the number of defectors increased owing to the poor conditions. The number of defectors since then has only been increasing, the reason now being–freedom. To deal with this increase, the DPRK government now punishes 3 generations of the family, if even one member defects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the larger question remains—how does such a country still exist in the 21st century? We can attribute two major reasons for this. First, every conversation in North Korea is overheard, and the propagation of any ideology against the nation leads to immediate persecution. There is also a travel ban in North Korea with permission required from the government for even inter-state transport, hindering collectivisation. The fear of torture and starvation for their entire family has become a deterrent that has forced people to simply follow the government without dissent. Second, if North Korea falls, it will create a massive humanitarian and refugee crisis, a civil war, an insurgency that could have nuclear weapons and a state divided between the ideological difference of South Korea and China. Because of the looming threat of these scenarios, no country has ever done anything more than sanctioning North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future in North Korea seems bleak. In an isolated world, these people are simply getting by each day trying to survive. However, amidst the tyranny, the people have created a world for themselves where they support one another. Many defectors note that while the country was poor, and the people were starving, but, they were warm to one another and cared for each other. Unlike its southern counterpart, where capitalism has induced stress and chasing materialistic needs, the Northern peninsula maintains a lifestyle where they are content even if they’re getting a small surplus. The more well off a person is, the more stressed out they are for instead of thinking about survival, they have time to overthink.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">A K-Drama that I was watching recently revolved around a North Korean soldier. The drama was great, but what stayed with me post bingeing it was the intrigue for North Korea: a country that calls itself the greatest nation in the world while its people suffer from the worst human rights violations; a country that calls itself a democracy with a 100% voter turnout in any election but has the world’s most authoritarian regime; a country built on the ideology of ‘self-reliance’ but heavily dependent on aid from the international community.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fiscal Consolidation: The Choice Between Prudence and Progress</title><link href="/Fiscal-Consolidation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fiscal Consolidation: The Choice Between Prudence and Progress" /><published>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Fiscal-Consolidation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Fiscal-Consolidation">&lt;p&gt;The growth projections for 2020-21 are in, and to hardly anyone’s surprise, it does not look good. It is during times like these, that the age-old ‘Growth vs Welfare’ debates are resurrected. However, as the pandemic curves around the globe get close to flattening themselves, it is only pragmatic to acknowledge that once we pass these anomalistic times, both variables will once again walk hand in hand. The ones monitoring the movements of these variables have assigned a downward revision to the targeted estimates. The recovery speculated to be V-shaped, will lead us through a phase of growth rates as low as -3%, as projected by the IMF, under the assumption that the pandemic fades by the second half of 2020. Governments, too politically motivated, cannot engage in conducting indirect bail-outs just yet, in the increasingly left sympathising world. So, the Central Banks around the globe have stepped in to stretch their balance sheets as usual. Besides the regular rate cuts, nations like the US, where rates have reached the zero base, have resorted to heterodox ways of stimulating the stock markets. The indices, taking mixed signals from the $4 trillion QE influx, and the climbing unemployment rate, close to 8%, have managed to rally against the odds. Other nations follow the lead as they ease out withdrawal norms, EMI payments, etc., attempting to bring a disequilibrium to the trade-off between consumption expenditure and investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India, while still expected to grow at 1.9%, has not attempted to take up any targeted policy measures, save for the Prime Minister Garib Kalyan Scheme, which isn’t an economically motivated initiative. As a result of lack of productivity, the revenue side of the federal budget has nearly entirely collapsed, with states urging the centre to transfer resources sooner as 70% of the revenue via GST streams has ceased. It is evident that the fiscal deficit target of 3% set under the Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management (FRBM) Act (2003) will be violated by a bold margin, giving the markets another reason to panic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need for a consumption-driven nation like India to keep the deficits in check arises from its reliance on foreign investments, due to the dearth of local savings. This stringency gets rationalised by the validation it receives from the economists grumbling at the nation’s twin balance sheet problem, i.e., both fiscal deficit and a trade deficit, which basically arises from running fiscal deficits by cutting taxes. That causes consumption to rise and thus, savings to fall. A reduction in savings prompts the government to borrow funds from abroad to finance their fiscal expenditure. An influx of investment raises the demand for local currency, which in turn results in its appreciation, and that makes domestic commodities relatively expensive to purchase, thus causing a trade deficit, which transforms into a current account deficit. It can be explained mathematically through a simple equation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y = C + I + G + NX can be written as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Y - C - Tax + Transfer) + (Tax - G - Transfer) = I + NX, which signifies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private Savings + Public Saving = Domestic Investment + Net Foreign Investment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine a decline in Public Savings, due to cutting taxes and causing a fiscal deficit. This can be offset by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Rise in Private Savings&lt;/strong&gt;: As per “Ricardian equivalence”, tax cuts prompt people to increase savings, because they expect taxes to rise in the future. This, though economically ideal, is unlikely in the real-life context of the non-rational people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Fall in Domestic Investment&lt;/strong&gt;: The crowding-out effect, it’s never good.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Fall in the Net foreign Investment&lt;/strong&gt;: The Twin Deficits dilemma&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India’s case 2) &amp;amp; 3) have happened more often than any growing economy would be comfortable with. Several economies that are a member of the twin deficits club are the US, UK, Greece, etc. So, it’s safe to say we’re certainly not in great company since the twin deficits in each of these economies have aggravated the impacts of recessions, even cyclical ones. Though as many believe so, we have not managed to escape a crisis while running twin deficits. The 1991 Balance of Payments (BoP) crisis was essentially that of the twin deficits, owed to years of profligacy and the fiscal crisis of the 1980s. Post the FRBM Act, the deficits did come under targets, but the actual figures remained higher as certain bonds were kept off the balance sheets and remained unaccounted for, rendering the actual adjusted figures higher by 0.5% to 1% from what was reported. However, over the decade, with the combination of FRBM guidelines and the Rajan-era monetary policy, we have restrained the fiscal deficit partially and managed to raise enough Forex reserves to keep the Current Account deficits controlled. Additionally, as we move closer to having a higher proportion of capital expenditures, as compared to the previous budgets, we are setting up a base for investment to crowd in rather than crowd out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fiscal consolidation is necessary when the BoP situation is volatile and reliance on international investment is high. However, for an emerging nation like India, it’s irrational to take the 3% target as a divine ordinance. We would only end up creating a psychological benchmark out of it, exacerbating the volatility in exercises over our markets in recessionary periods. Fiscal prudence makes sense in good times to develop a cushion for bad times and allow targeted policies to take over the recovery. Blindly restricting expenditure ends up being counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The growth projections for 2020-21 are in, and to hardly anyone’s surprise, it does not look good. It is during times like these, that the age-old ‘Growth vs Welfare’ debates are resurrected. However, as the pandemic curves around the globe get close to flattening themselves, it is only pragmatic to acknowledge that once we pass these anomalistic times, both variables will once again walk hand in hand. The ones monitoring the movements of these variables have assigned a downward revision to the targeted estimates. The recovery speculated to be V-shaped, will lead us through a phase of growth rates as low as -3%, as projected by the IMF, under the assumption that the pandemic fades by the second half of 2020. Governments, too politically motivated, cannot engage in conducting indirect bail-outs just yet, in the increasingly left sympathising world. So, the Central Banks around the globe have stepped in to stretch their balance sheets as usual. Besides the regular rate cuts, nations like the US, where rates have reached the zero base, have resorted to heterodox ways of stimulating the stock markets. The indices, taking mixed signals from the $4 trillion QE influx, and the climbing unemployment rate, close to 8%, have managed to rally against the odds. Other nations follow the lead as they ease out withdrawal norms, EMI payments, etc., attempting to bring a disequilibrium to the trade-off between consumption expenditure and investing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Story of Easter</title><link href="/The-Story-of-Easter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Easter" /><published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Story-of%20Easter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Story-of-Easter">&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, everyone has a worldview, a lens through which he/she views the world, however implicit this worldview might be. And every worldview is, ultimately, a story. I don’t mean this in a condescending manner – stories can be true! My mother used to tell me stories about my childhood, and I have no doubt concerning the sincerity of her testimony. In fact, it is stories that drive our world. Everyone has their own story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this on the twelfth of April, 2020. It is a Sunday, it is Easter. And what better to write on this occasion than to simply tell the story of Easter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world is a strange, dark and forsaken world. Even in the midst of apparent joy, there is deep and real suffering. Even the ancient Indian prince Siddhartha could not help but realise that the world was filled with pain and anguish. And this realisation was so shocking and heart-wrenching for him that, as the legend goes, he forsook all royalty in search for the enlightenment that he believed would reveal to him the secret of joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things haven’t changed much. In fact, today’s world is filled with Siddharthas, desperate to discover the secret of happiness. Every advertisement you have ever seen, every product you have been keen to buy, every place you have wanted to visit, every prize you have been ambitious to win – in other words, everything you have ever done, you have done it in the hope that what you are about to do will finally bring you the joy and peace that your heart desires – or at the very least, will increase the joy that you already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, here you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I too was a lot like Siddhartha. In fact, my mother wanted to name me Siddhartha, but ultimately decided against it for fear that I would ultimately become a monk. But against all hope, as it turned out, I did have a very ‘monastic’ spirit, even early on. From very early on in my life, I have been searching for answers – answers to the big questions of life. Why am I here? What is my purpose? Why does this world exist? Where am I going?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: what does it all mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thirst to discover these answers eventually became like a madness, like an obsession that had wormed itself deep into my psyche. I’m certain I was the only person in seventh grade who did not know how to play cricket, but who had, in fact, read the entire Bhagavad Gita cover to cover. I was the only kid in high school who was not a Muslim but who wanted to carry the Qur’an with him to read during the tiffin break. I was, in other words, probably exactly the kind of person my mother had initially dreaded I would become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most people, I sought for something that would give purpose to my life: religion, politics, worldly success as a writer or an actor were high on the list. And yet, the questions remained. At one point in my life, I even contemplated raw, naked materialist atheism. I started reading atheist literature and was initially greatly impressed by the force of the rhetoric. Richard Dawkins, in particular, was a crucial influence. There he stood, marshalling all the powers of reason and science in an intellectual assault upon all forms of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, for a while, it seemed the candle had been blown out. There was no god. There was no purpose. There was no meaning to anything. There was no good, there was no evil – there was simply matter, endlessly morphing. As Christopher Hitchens wrote, “To the dumb question, ‘Why me?’ the cosmos barely bothers to return the reply: why not?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atheist ‘enlightenment’ informed me that, at best, I was an accident. I didn’t have to be here, but I was. And I would one day flicker out of existence. I came into being for no reason, and eventually, I would perish for no reason. And all my precious joys, passions, loves, desires, ambitions, fears and sorrows would perish with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the worldview which the atheists presented to me, death was more real than life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was then that I encountered a person who completely changed my life. His name was Dr William Lane Craig. An academic philosopher of religion and a deeply Christian soul, he was a man who had debated leading atheists at universities around the world. He had faced off against big names like Lawrence Krauss, Dan Barker, Sam Harris, Peter Atkins and a whole host of other atheist heavyweights. And with him, for the first time, I saw someone who was able to give a clear and intellectually compelling case in favour of theism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, as I studied more, I came to realise that most militant atheism was more motivated by anger against religion than any careful consideration of the question of whether or not God exists. Many of the arguments atheists had been putting forward, I realised, were extremely poor and shabby, often based upon misunderstandings and caricatures of Christian arguments and theology. And some of the leading atheists like Lawrence Krauss seemed unwilling to even consider the possibility of there being a God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than overthrowing dogmas, at times it seemed that the atheists were championing new dogmas – dogmas based less upon careful intellectual thought and more upon prejudice and hatred for a particular social order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I identify not as an atheist, but as a convinced believer in Jesus Christ. I believe in Jesus – and, even more unthinkably, in the Catholic Church - because I believe Christianity – and Catholicism – are true. And I believe the story of Christianity, which is really the story of Easter, can truly change people’s lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible opens with a very grand and simple line: In the beginning, God created the heavens and earth. In the Biblical worldview, God is the reason why this universe exists. God created us, and we exist because of Him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Bible also tells us that human beings sinned. Though we were originally created holy and good, we turned against God and rebelled against Him. All the evil that exists in the world is merely the outworking of man’s original sin. And the bad news is that none of us is innocent, because we have all participated in this unholy work of sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the good news that Christianity brings is the proclamation that God did not abandon us. On the contrary, He descended from heaven and became one of us. He shared in our misery, our suffering, our loneliness, our pain and our anguish. But He did not share in our sins. He was crucified by men who hated His claims, but as He was dying on the Cross, He offered His life as a sacrifice – to atone for the sins of man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the powers of evil gathered together and climaxed on the Cross of Jesus 2,000 years ago… because there was no sin more grotesque than the murder of God’s only Son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the Christian worldview, death did not have the last word. On the contrary, Jesus Christ rose from the dead, physically, bodily, on the third day, triumphing over the powers of sin and death. Though men murdered Him, death could not hold Him, because He had committed no sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who hold to materialist dogma will scoff at this idea. For countless souls, miracles and resurrections are the stuff of legend. They cannot happen and do not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you doubt the Resurrection, then I highly recommend you to take the time to study it, historically. The Oxford atheist philosopher (and later convert to theism, though not to Christianity) Antony Flew admitted in his debate with the historian Gary Habermas that the Resurrection of Jesus had better evidence than claimed miracles in any other religion. I think he is right in this. The Gospels, after all, are not myths written centuries after the time of Jesus, but rather are biographical accounts that can, more or less, all be traced back to the first century. Though written by various authors, they all testify that Jesus rose bodily from the dead. It is the same with the letters of Paul of Tarsus, an anti-Christian Jew who was later converted after seeing a vision of the resurrected Jesus. His letter to the Galatians contains a moving testimony of his conversion, and his story is corroborated by the Book of Acts, written by a man named Luke. These documents I speak of are not fabrications, but rather the writings of real people, who lived at specific times in history, and whose biographical and at times autobiographical claims largely corroborate each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my mind, the Resurrection of Jesus is the single most extraordinary event of human history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I invite you – whoever you may be – to consider the claims of Christianity for yourself. You have nothing at all to lose. If Christianity is true, then you have everything to gain from discovering its truthfulness. But if it’s false, then a careful study will only reveal its falsity, because the truth cannot ultimately be hidden. Either way, you will increase your knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What convinced me was the intellectual arguments in favour of God’s existence, the extraordinary testimony of the resurrection of Jesus, the fulfilled prophecies of the Old Testament, the beauty and power of the very words of the Saviour, and, of course, my personal experience of grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you might have questions, and you might want to learn more. If this is so, I rejoice in this, and I encourage you wholeheartedly to follow the truth wherever it leads. A good place to start is the YouTube channel Capturing Christianity, which regularly hosts discussions between Christian and atheist intellectuals and scholars. Bishop Robert Barron’s book &lt;em&gt;Catholicism: A Journey to the Heart of the Faith&lt;/em&gt; is also a great place to start. I also highly recommend the work of Edward Feser, an atheist philosopher whose studies in the philosophy of religion and mind eventually led him to convert to Christianity – I especially commend his book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs of the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;, which, in my mind, is the best intellectual and reasoned defence of classical theism that has been made in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, I urge you to take the time out and read the New Testament, which is a collection of these ancient historical writings that testify to the life and works of Jesus of Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that there are people who will read this article of mine and laugh. Why then do I write? Why then do I spend so much time telling people about a man who lived 2,000 years ago, a man I have never met in person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I believe this man is no mere man, but rather the incarnate Son of God. I write because this Man has changed my life, and He can change yours as well, if only you allow Him. And if you do, you will come to possess a joy that the world cannot give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telling people about the amazing person that is Jesus is worth any sacrifice and any cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the faith that has inspired millions, that has shaken empires, that has changed the course of human history. This is the faith of the martyrs, the confessors and the saints of the Cross. And this is the audacity with which I can stare death in the eye and proclaim that Christ is risen and that He lives forever more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part II)</title><link href="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part II)" /><published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II">&lt;p&gt;The similarities between 18th century France and modern America apply not only to the background to the French Revolution but to the early stages of the Revolution in which a moderate, professional bourgeoisie sought to consolidate their power and stem the tide of economic and political radicalism emanating from the peasantry and sans-culottes. This article chronicles the various aspects of this divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Representative Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Blanning, writing in &lt;em&gt;The Pursuit of Glory&lt;/em&gt;, argued that the French Revolution “wrapped into one explosive package the three great abstractions of modern politics: the People, the State, and the Nation”, and that “the French people announced their arrival as the main actors in the nation’s political life.” That sovereignty resided in the nation and that Louis XVI was answerable not to God but to the constitutional law of the State (for the first part of the Revolution anyway), were principles that would lead to the self-assertion of the French people, as mass participation in assemblies and demonstrations and universal conscription under the Jacobins meant that they could no longer be ignored. But for the first part of the Revolution, representation was monopolised by the most middle-class, reformist elements of the French society. America today suffers from a similar problem, as the DNC continuously props up Joe Biden’s campaign, and acts as an obstacle to any substantive change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Estates-General sat on May 5, 1789, Louis XVI having had little choice over its convocation following the difficulties in levying taxes and rents on an increasingly recalcitrant peasantry, coupled with the fears of the bourgeoisie that the loans they had made to the State might not be paid back. The Third Estate was represented by 610 men, about 1/6th of whom were capitalists and bankers, and many of whom were lawyers, indicating that despite representing 95% of the French people, the Third Estate exclusively advanced the interests of the educated middle classes. As such, the Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen, which Lafayette consulted Thomas Jefferson in drawing up, was a crystallisation of Enlightenment principles that affirmed the universal power of reason, the ability of man to surmount all obstacles and control his own government and society, and the principle of equality before the law with noble privileges abolished. Article IV of the Declaration stated that liberty constituted anything that did not harm others by infringing on the rights to liberty, property and security and that only the rule of law could delineate these boundaries. Private property remained a ‘natural right’, and the unchecked ability to accumulate capital and influence the political process did not infringe any of the aforementioned negatively-defined ‘rights’, and so was sanctified by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Eric Hobsbawm, “A constitutional monarchy based on a propertied oligarchy expressing itself through a representative assembly was more congenial to most bourgeois liberals than the democratic republic which might have seemed a more logical expression of their theoretical aspirations.” The demands articulated by the peasantry for the restoration of communal lands and material prosperity could be ignored, and by August 10, 1789, the bourgeoisie had taken up arms against the peasantry in Dauphine and Burgundy. Characterising peasant agitations as the work of ‘brigands’, the troops were called out to crush all men without professions and domiciles. This brutality saw 160 prisoners killed at Cluny, and 80 hanged in Lyon. Following the storming of the Bastille and the August 4 reforms that established equality in taxation and admission to public office, in addition to the redemption of manorial lands, it was clear that the peasantry and sans-culottes were the vessels of social change, repelled by bourgeois anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glaring flaws in a supposedly ‘representative’ system have also shown themselves in the recent Democratic primaries, where Bernie Sanders’ campaign has cratered. In Iowa last month, the app meant to coordinate the results of the Caucus mysteriously crashed, and it later transpired that the app was built by a for-profit company named Shadow Inc. that Pete Buttigieg’s campaign had paid millions of dollars. The US Constitution, like France’s Declaration of the Rights of Man, protects the rights of private business to hike prices, depress wages and lock other competitors out of the market, and the rights of political institutions such as the DNC to sabotage the electoral process in favour of candidates who are more conducive to a capitalist economic setting. Nothing legally prevents the DNC from limiting the number of debates and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-politics/bernie-sanders-democratic-primary-dnc-convention-superdelegates-nomination-2020-election-a9363626.html&quot;&gt;blocking Bernie Sanders from winning the nomination.&lt;/a&gt; The freedoms of speech and voluntary exchange are theoretical abstractions that give way to the realities of market competition and the profit motive, as while individuals enjoy the superficial freedoms to participate in democracy, the real power lies in the hands of multinational corporations or nepotistic political behemoths like the DNC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Shades of Moderation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moderate voices within the National Assembly, who would later go on to form the Legislative Assembly in 1791, recognised that their interests were broadly in line with a limited monarchy, rather than a democratic republic. In what became the National Constituent Assembly, a class of propertied ‘active citizens’ formed a constitutional monarchy that banned trade unions and guild corporations, instituted the enclosure of communal lands and sold off ecclesiastical domains. These reforms were designed to create an internal market for goods, rather than to satiate the demands of the peasantry, as the ensuing price fluctuations led to agitations in rural areas. The distinction between the property-owning moderates of the Legislative Assembly who favoured opening up internal markets and creating a class of landless agrarian wage-labourers, and the peasantry and sans-culottes who favoured the communal ownership of land and higher income and inheritance tax was becoming more evident. The storming of the Tuileries and the establishment of the National Convention in 1792 was the apotheosis of this struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incompatibility of moderate defenders of the status quo with the vast numbers demanding transformative change is also characteristic of the schisms between Bernie Sanders and his supporters with the centrist Democrats. Much like the Girondins and moderates in the National Constituent Assembly, Joe Biden and his supporters pretend to rail against the corruption and despotism of the Trump administration while obscuring how much they have in common with the Republicans. In addition to his already disastrous record of voting in favour of NAFTA, supporting the war in Iraq and playing a key role in the war on drugs that has devastated many families (particularly Black and Hispanic), Biden continues to oppose Medicare for All, even suggesting that he would &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politifact.com/factchecks/2020/mar/10/facebook-posts/when-biden-was-asked-if-he-would-veto-medicare-all/&quot;&gt;veto it if it passed both houses and came to his desk.&lt;/a&gt; Furthermore, the centrist Democrats and Bernie Sanders’ supporters are separated not only by policy disagreements but a profound and seemingly irreconcilable divergence in worldview. The centrist Democrats are consequentialist; it is unsurprising that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2020/03/suburbanites-are-backing-biden/607726/&quot;&gt;base of primarily middle-class professionals&lt;/a&gt; are concerned with results and efficacy above all else, and maintain that the ends (beating Trump) justify the means (nominating Biden). Much like the bureaucratic moderates in the Legislative Assembly, the centrist Democrats view capitalism as a natural accompaniment to their utilitarian, consequentialist worldview. If one believes that man is a rational, utility maximising agent entering into voluntary exchanges with others, then the consequences of mutual trade and transaction are all that matters, and anything not amenable to the rationalist calculus of profitability can be discarded. Bernie Sanders’ supporters are more ideological (and, indeed, deontological), advocating for transformative measures such as Medicare for all and the abolition of ICE as ends in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be mentioned, however, that the situation in France that enabled the storming of the Bastille in 1789 and the Tuileries in 1792 is not entirely analogous to the modern American situation, as the peasantry and sans-culottes in France represented a broadly unified coalition, committed to establishing communally-owned land and preventing monopolisation and speculation. They had both suffered the effects of inflation and famine during the 1770’s and 1780’s, and both saw their enemy as the nobility and bourgeois professionals. The American working class, by contrast, remains divided along racial lines, as well as on geographic and occupational lines. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aese.psu.edu/directory/smm67/Election16.pdf?wpisrc=nl_daily202&amp;amp;wpmm=1&quot;&gt;A study from Penn State University&lt;/a&gt; showed that Donald Trump performed best in swing states that were worst affected by deindustrialisation and the opioid epidemic, and had experienced employment losses over recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political divisions between professional, liberal capitalists who sought to make an existing system more amenable to their interests and the disaffected masses who sought radical change are common to both late Ancien Regime France and 21st century America. The disillusionment with the machinery of governance that led the sans-culottes to believe that the Estates General did not represent them also motivates many Bernie Sanders supporters who view the DNC as an obstacle to power. If the French Revolution was the time for the French people to assert themselves as a prominent force, then the coming economic depression may foreground the schism between unrepresentative political institutions and the people they have disenfranchised.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The similarities between 18th century France and modern America apply not only to the background to the French Revolution but to the early stages of the Revolution in which a moderate, professional bourgeoisie sought to consolidate their power and stem the tide of economic and political radicalism emanating from the peasantry and sans-culottes. This article chronicles the various aspects of this divide.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chaos and Order—How to Bring the Ego to Equilibrium Through an Act of Metamorphosis</title><link href="/Chaos-and-Order" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chaos and Order—How to Bring the Ego to Equilibrium Through an Act of Metamorphosis" /><published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Chaos-and-Order</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Chaos-and-Order">&lt;p&gt;I would like to begin this article by an act of meditation, and would also like to humbly ask you to participate in this process by allowing your mind to freely explore the depth of your imagination and to make links, connections and associations between the following words. Please allow the following words to gently hover in your mind as you are reading this article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;chaos, order, uncertainty, self-discovery, death, rebirth, transcendence, the ego, your grounding, metamorphosis, culture, creation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As human beings, we are all struck by existential problems—we do not know where we come from, we do not know why we are here in this mysterious world, and we also do not know where we are going. All the advances in knowledge should not lead one to be deceived about how much we don’t know. Far too often we like to claim knowledge or understanding because certainty keeps us sane and helps us in our survival. If we all wake up in the morning and start questioning our lives and our choices really honestly as we go through our days, we will be held suspended in a state of inertia and existential angst. There is a point where we act on our beliefs even though we are not sure about them. And, herein lies the conundrum of our lives: we all know that we don’t know but we act as if we know. What is the solution? Or a question to be asked first, is that, why is it that most people from the learned to the unlearned, from the sane to the insane, from the poor to the rich, often act and behave in a manner as if they somehow know the ‘truth’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As animals, human beings are part of the fabric of the evolutionary processes, and as such, much of what we refer to as ‘me’ is simply the by-product of the evolutionary processes. Specifically, in the cortex of the human brain, even though we don’t understand it fully, there are a few observations we can make. Firstly, that in its process of evolution, the two hemispheres of the brain have been both specialised for certain specific functions, with the right hemisphere being the one that is involved in the acts of exploration that opens us up to possibilities, and the left hemisphere being the one that seeks to tie itself down to certainty (see &lt;em&gt;The Master and his Emissary&lt;/em&gt; by Iain McGilchrist). And, the constant interplay of these two hemispheres can be understood as the brain trying to balance between chaos and order. With chaos being that which is beyond our understanding, or that which we do not understand; and order being the polar opposite, that which is within our grasp, or that which we do understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already we can see from evolution’s point of view that it would be overwhelming for the human mind to perceive all the realities surrounding it, and just like the importance of forgetting, it is also important that we only receive certain sensory data from the world in the form of perceptions. And, as evolution is concerned with our survival, the brain also evolved such that it only perceives realities that concerns it for its survival, and as we have already observed, the left hemisphere, and indeed about 25% of the entire brain’s context acts as an inhibitory mechanism. In other words, the brain as observed by Huxley (see &lt;em&gt;The Doors of Perception&lt;/em&gt; by Aldous Huxley) blocks off much of the sensory data produced by the surrounding environment. Now we have addressed the first question, which was that, why do humans act as if they know the truth—simply because our brains give us a very convincing illusion of reality (an incomplete picture of reality, not inaccurate!). Here also lies the problem of the ego, as much of the ego is the result of complex evolutionary processes which formed for a multiplicity of reasons such as self-defense, survival, dominance, self-identify and many more factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, from the very moment we are born, we are inhabited by the spirit of our ancestors, so to speak - a metaphor of this long evolutionary process. The brain of a human child is then nourished and developed through one’s upbringing into his family, society and above all into his culture. This is where the biological foundations of the ego are then built on by the culture. A simple example is the universal thirst for economic prosperity; once a biological drive for survival, it is now transformed to a culturally ego-driven desire to consume with ever-more new products being created for such desire, and with much emphasis being placed upon the acquisition of objects, and sometimes people for that matter! In fact, most aspects of culture are about the creation and maintenance of boundaries and order—and what is the driving mechanism that fuels culture? — The ego of course! It is as deep as the dawn of humanity, it is ancient and present in every single human being. The ego is self-centered, it advocated for its own growth at the cost of everything including nature herself—no reference is needed in the current ecological disaster where man cannot stop himself from constant exploitation of the environment. In short, as Terence McKenna once said, “The ego will become like a cyst if left untreated”, and I actually think that the ego is more like a tumor, that if untreated, it will lead to collective seizures which gets manifested in forms of natural disasters, human bloodshed, exploitation of others, and ultimately, the destruction of our world. And, culture far from balancing this toxic order as fuelled by the ego with the feminine spirit, it further strengthens the ego and advocates for the continuation of its survival. Only after the times of major collective disasters (eg: global pandemics), will we see major change in our attitude towards each other and towards our environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But parts of the ego is necessary. In the book, &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;, Nietzsche explores the necessity of the first stage of human metamorphosis, which he represents as the camel. He writes: “the weight-bearing spirit takes upon itself all these heaviest things: like a camel hurrying laden into the desert, thus hurries into its desert”. Understanding the camel as human beings and the weight that is being carried as tradition and culture, it is a natural stage of man’s development where we acquire our self-identity and become a slave to our cultural values. However, the solution as advocated by Nietzsche’s character as represented in the second and third state of man’s metamorphosis is that of the lion, and then the child. Once we have nourished and developed our ego and learnt the wisdom of the past, it is time to doubt them with a spirit of courage (the lion stage), and then, finally, we must participate in a process of self-discovery, self-exploration, and above all to create one’s own values (the child stage). Thus, the act of creation, and constant death and rebirth of one’s values and beliefs is necessary for the final stage of man’s metamorphosis. But Nietzsche’s abstract ideas can also lead to the re-growth of the ego as one is in total freedom to create one’s values, so why not to create novel ego-driven values? This is where man’s true and complete act of metamorphosis must be in direct harmony with the spirit of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I have delineated the history and the origin of the ego and its processes of development within culture, and explained how the ego becomes not only toxic to ourselves but also to nature herself. But, I also indicated why the ego is necessary and inevitable, it need not be destroyed but it requires to be treated through acts of metamorphosis. Now a question which we asked in the beginning, what is the solution? All these abstract ideas of self-transformation seem all well and good but none are of any practical use. And, that is why the practice of ego-dissolving activity in shamanism is necessary if the ego is to be treated. The other solution as we already alluded to is to wait for major disasters so that the ego can observe the effects of himself, and in an act of pathetic self-preservation, mutate and change course, but don’t be fooled, this is only for the short term. Whereas, activities like community, love, caring and connecting to nature and each other, connection and the bringing together of people on the internet, the use of psychedelic plant medicines all act as a cure for the toxic elements of the ego. Particularly, the proper use of psychedelics in its shamanic context with right intentions can bring about a shift in consciousness and a dissolution of the ego such that our values become aligned with planetary values—that of care and love for nature and one another. The chaos that psychedelics introduce into the cultural machinery is one reliable way to bring the ego to equilibrium. But, as I have already indicated, the ego need not be completely dissolved but only treated, as we do need our personal identities and we should be grateful for some of the achievement of the ego like our advanced civilization, or my act of writing this very article until 5 am in the morning for a girl that I have a crush on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Omidvar</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">I would like to begin this article by an act of meditation, and would also like to humbly ask you to participate in this process by allowing your mind to freely explore the depth of your imagination and to make links, connections and associations between the following words. Please allow the following words to gently hover in your mind as you are reading this article:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban</title><link href="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban" /><published>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalyst for the aforementioned sad tale, the US-Taliban peace accord, signed February 29, 2020 holds the US time-bound to remove its troops within the decided 14-month time period, but not the Taliban to keep its promises. The removal of UN sanctions under the peace deal further weakens any leverage that the US might hold in Afghanistan. With the removal of the US-Troops, and a burgeoning Taliban influence, the people of Afghanistan have a bleak future to look forward to, and India, perhaps not as worse off, is definitely in the line of fire.s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No individual who has ever witnessed an India-Pakistan cricket match can be ignorant of the 70-year old festering wound between the two countries. The unceasing tussle for power between the two countries and Pakistan’s inclination towards providing refuge to terrorist organisations as a way to one-up India is not a secret. And, consequently, Pakistan’s close friendship with and ideological alikeness to the Taliban is the primary impetus to the threat to India’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan has been responsible for harbouring prominent terrorist organisations such as JeM and LeT on its territory and providing them protection after attacks on India. While Taliban promises not to allow Al-Qaeda in Afghanistan, the aforementioned organisations have been left out of the deal, allowing these terrorist organisations the opportunity to garner support and refuge in Afghanistan as well. Pakistan was a staunch supporter of having the Taliban as an active participant in the 2001 Bonn Agreement which was intended to establish an Afghani government after the Taliban’s removal. Furthermore, Pakistan’s support of a Taliban-led government in Afghanistan only makes Pakistan dearer to them. Juxtaposed with India’s past dealings (or lack thereof) with Taliban, India is likely to find itself in an ‘enemy of my friend’ situation. India has historically vehemently refused to acknowledge the Taliban as anything other than a terrorist organisation and has always supported the Afghanistan government. On a quest to counter Pakistani influence in Afghanistan, India has spent considerable time, money and effort to build a trusting relationship with the Afghan government through its multiple development and infrastructure projects, posing them as a direct adversary to the Taliban. And now that the Afghan government is itself in a precarious position, India’s assurance of relative peace on the India-Afghanistan border is dwindling and its efforts conclude to be naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another facet of this predicament is the apparent and sudden benevolence shown by the US to Pakistan. Pakistan has been a key player in bringing the Taliban to the table long enough for a peace accord to be established. And considering that President Trump’s re-election campaign is contingent on him bringing the American troops back, he currently considers Pakistan to be in his good books. Hence, Pakistan finds itself in a far more favourable position to cause considerable damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the US is by association to the Taliban making deals with the Haqqani network as well. The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008. Hence, America is giving legitimacy and validation to a terrorist group which has posed a threat to India in the past. This legitimisation and validation by a country that India considers to be an ally is only an affirmation of the USA’s indifference to any more peace violations by the Taliban in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to this, the instability currently in India over the abrogation of Article 370 in Kashmir and the mass unrest and chaos due to the CAA/NRC protests, India finds itself in a pernicious position. The Al-Qaeda and the Haqqani network have made attempts and calls to fight India on the issue of Kashmir and on behalf of Pakistan. With the newly-minted support in Afghanistan and far more freedom once US-troops leave, India will have its hands full dealing with them. Much like Afghanistan, India’s dependence upon the US troops to fight a war not their own proves to be its Achilles heel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one was to consider the possibility of India stepping up to protect its borders, it doesn’t seem improbable, however, it is the approach that remains to be seen. India could increase border security, employ more force and troops, it can hope for the peace accord to hold and pray that the Taliban does not establish a government and Pakistan does not use this to its advantage to attempt an ambush. Or perhaps, less likely and more smartly, India can continue to build and facilitate growth and development projects in Afghanistan, making India a friend to anyone in authority, very much like it did with the previous Ghani-led government. One cannot tell for sure what the currently-ruling BJP government will do, and keeping in mind their almost negligible previous response to the peace accord, we can only hope for some undertaking. The consequences of the deal may not be apparent right now especially when currently, the COVID-19 pandemic takes precedence, as it should, yet it will not always be so and India must be ready with a water-proof plan for when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?</title><link href="/British-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?" /><published>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/British-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/British-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recently introduced skills-focused points-based immigration policy by PM Boris Johnson is going to have a huge impact on the economy. More than one-third of doctors, pharmacists, and dentists in the UK are foreign-born, as are more than 20% of nurses. Seven in 10 workers in the meat-processing industry are from the EU. However, next year onwards, the UK’s Byzantine immigration system for non-EU migrants will also apply to those from the EU. While immigration criteria for skilled labour will be loosened, it will be almost impossible for non-skilled labour to obtain a work visa. One of the hardest-hit sectors will be ‘care for’ the elderly. There is already a shortage of workers in this sector. Moreover, ‘care for’ work is the occupation with the most projected employment growth in the coming years. The UK under the guise of treating EU and non-EU migrants equally on the basis of skills is actually turning away industrious and enterprising individuals who help power its economy and provide for the basic needs of its greying population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the recent examples of what the British government is doing wrong. There are certain structural problems as well that need to be addressed. Capital spending as a share of GDP has fallen to around 17% from 20% in 2007. Capital investment is required in order to ensure long-term economic growth by increasing future production capacity. Moreover, the expenditure on R&amp;amp;D remains persistently below 2% of the GDP. In addition to this, the output per person has remained well below than what would have been termed as satisfactory. The unemployment figures have been relatively good recently, however, these have come at the cost of stagnating real wages and lower labour productivity per hour. Moreover, there has been a constant increase in the number of &lt;em&gt;zero-hour&lt;/em&gt; contracts. In such contracts, the workers have no guarantee of how many hours of work they will be getting. This could be one of the major reasons for under-employment in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2019, the manufacturing activity took a turn for the worse with the sharpest deterioration in output in more than seven years. The IHS Markit/CIPS manufacturing Purchasing Managers’ Index sank to 47.5 in December from 48.9 in November, although it was marginally higher than an initial flash estimate of 47.4. The figure marks the eighth consecutive month with a reading below 50, which indicates a majority of businesses reporting deteriorating activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has a large current account deficit as well. It was around 4.6% of the GDP in 2019. This has been majorly due to negative investor sentiments because of all the political instability. Also, the UK economy has been hit badly by the economic slowdown in the major trading partners, namely, China and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another worrying aspect is the monopoly power in public utility services like electricity and gas. A lack of competition keeps prices high and affects the real incomes of millions of consumers. Moreover, economic, social and demographic pressures continue to mount on public services such as the NHS. Some economists argue that the NHS needs a major injection of extra funding over the next 5-10 years; others believe that there are enough savings still to be achieved by addressing inefficiencies in public health care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With economic forecasts suggesting that the UK’s GDP growth won’t exceed 1.5%, the government will have to watch its discretionary spending even if a recession is avoided, because of spending on national services like the NHS. Moreover, there is also an additional threat to the economy posed by coronavirus. Much remains to be seen how the policymakers will tackle this burden and if the economy will be able to overcome this. The current situation doesn’t leave room for high hopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to plunging stock markets worldwide, the Bank of England cut its key rate by half a percentage point to 0.25%.  The Bank of England introduced a new program for cheap credit and reduced a special capital buffer to give banks more room to lend as well. Rishi Sunak, the Chancellor of the Exchequer,  also scrapped business rates for small firms to help them deal with the disruption caused by the outbreak of coronavirus. Business rates are taxes to help pay for UK local services, charged on most commercial properties. Britain’s retail sector has complained for the longest time that the current business rates system was unfair and needed reform. While the retail sector accounts for 5% of the UK economy, it is burdened with 10% of all business taxes, and 25% of business rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chancellor Sunak also scrapped a planned cut in corporation tax, and he is expected to raise around £6 billion from scrapping a planned drop, money he indicated could be spent on hospitals and doctors across the country. He also announced that the government would establish a coronavirus job retention scheme for all employers, large or small, that will cover 80% of wages, up to £2,500 a month. This scheme was introduced for an initial period of three months but can also be extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a month after stepping into the new job, Rishi Sunak has a lot to prove. There are a lot of expectations for the new Chancellor. Additionally, when the UK is facing an increasing threat from the coronavirus, his job becomes all the more important. It remains to be seen whether Rishi Sunak will break free of any puppet strings or be swept aside by a Treasury insider. Brexit coupled with the coronavirus outbreak has left the country on borrowed time to revamp the economy. What happens in the next few weeks could possibly define the future of the country in the coming years. What we need to wait and watch is whether the government and its policies fall into place in order to break free the shackles of a never-ending system of going back and forth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sexism and the City</title><link href="/Sexism-and-the-City" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sexism and the City" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Sexism-and-the-City</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Sexism-and-the-City">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism can affect anyone, however, there have been few men on the receiving end. It affects men and boys when they don’t conform to gender roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this article, we will restrict the ambit of our discussion to only the University level in India. Sexist attitudes are not just limited to boys rating girls on a scale of 0-10 based on their physical appearances. It has transcended into limiting the opportunities for women, imposing draconian rules and observing traditions that are misogynistic and chauvinist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often consider academia as the citadel of everything fair and progressive. However, we don’t live in a utopian world. Just like other institutions that have these notions of male superiority deep-rooted in their practices and norms, so does education. Many people benefit from these power dynamics in the status quo, and thus, have no incentive to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a stark imbalance in the male to female ratio in many courses such as law, management, and STEM disciplines. Considered the holy grail of education and achievement, Indian Institutes of Technology (IITs), suffer from the worst gender imbalance with only 9.3% of females. This gap further increases with progression in these careers, with an utter lack of women in leadership positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see this trend across central universities in India. Out of 46 central universities, only 5 have women placed as the heads of the institutions. Even in India’s most liberal universities, like Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU), no women has ever been the head of the institute. The selection committees are dominated by men, who give little weightage to women candidates as many view women as someone who has stolen a job a man was entitled to do. This perception has risen from the cultural view that men are the bread-earners of the family while women are the homemakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In colleges with extreme gender disproportion, the environment becomes testosterone-driven, leading to women students being subjected to sexual innuendos and sexist remarks. Language and communication make people recognise or demean their contribution to society. Our language shapes our thoughts, and the way we think influences our actions. Gender-discriminatory language reinforces sexist attitudes and behaviours. Thus, female students become conditioned to accept subtle sexism and lewd remarks as the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism in Indian universities isn’t just limited to leadership positions but encompasses norms that affect the day-to-day lives of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many colleges across India, dress codes are imposed on women. For example, The Government Medical College, Kerala issued a dress code for its female students instructing them not to wear jeans, leggings, short tops or noisy ornaments. Many girls’ hostels also follow curfews, thus increasing the red tape for them to step out. Many institutions like Jamia Milia University, IITs and the University of Delhi have come under the light in the past for such rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such draconian measures show how expecting equality remains a far-off dream for girls. These rules concretise the notion that the price for the safety of women is curbing their freedom rather than bringing a systemic change in the attitude of men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symbiosis Center for Media and Communication (SCMC) Pune is widely recognised for its option of ‘film and television’ specialisation as a part of its three-year undergraduate program. In her article for &lt;em&gt;The Print&lt;/em&gt;, Vaishnavi Suresh, an SCMC alumnus highlights the rampant sexism in the coveted institution. Being a media college, the students spend a large amount of time in classes watching films. Vaishnavi, however, notes how the students barely had any female filmmakers as role models. In an incident where some people from her class suggested they study a female filmmaker, the professor shot down their requests and instead taught them about another male filmmaker. She also noted how by the time they came to their 3rd year, only 2 women out of her batch were still invested in the camera by practising photography or videography. She cites the reason for this to be the “reality of the industry drilled into them constantly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A college that prides itself on being liberal lacks showing its students that women could be role models too. Having female role models is important for breaking the stereotype of men being better than women to propagate for a more inclusive world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, while the #MeToo movement was still in its nascent stage, the students of Women Centred Practices at Tata Institute of Social Sciences (TISS), Mumbai organised a ‘Gender Sensitisation Week’ in their campus. Amidst the gender sensitisation week, a signed comment was noticed on a banner that was put up for people to anonymously share accounts of sexist instances on campus. It read, “Sexism is an accusation, sluts level against dissenting voices for recognising that a slut is a slut.” Instances like these make one realise that the notion of some campuses being ‘more sensitive and liberal than the rest of the world’, is nothing but a facade. People still trivialise sexual harassment, use the word ‘slut’ as a derogatory term and push aside voices of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a few pre-university colleges in Bengaluru set higher cut-off marks for girls for admission into the courses. On inquiring about the reason behind this move, the Vice-Chancellor of Christ PU College, Fr Abraham VM, commented - “Girls are smart, and this is not a new trend. If there is no higher cut-off, the college will have only girls. The higher cut-off is to bring in gender balance.” Subsequently, the cut-off for science stream in Christ college was fixed at 93.92% for girls and 91.04% for boys. This move begs the question that in a society where historically almost every classroom has been dominated by men, why do we fear if women step into those shoes. It seems like a move to &lt;em&gt;punish&lt;/em&gt; women for breaking the glass ceiling despite being on the worse off end of the access to opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most famous sexist tradition would be the regressive Virgin Tree ‘Pooja’ on Valentine’s Day at Hindu College (University of Delhi). The Pooja is a customary tradition wherein the boys’ hostel decorates a ‘virgin tree’ on campus with condoms and posters of an actress naming her the Damdami Mai. This actress, seen as a sex symbol, is ‘worshipped’ on Valentine’s Day and according to legend, the people partaking in this practice lose their virginity in the coming six months or at least get into a relationship. In a university space, where we regard sexuality-related conversations as a taboo, they often term such a celebration as ‘liberatory.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V-Day pooja, which has been taking place since 1953, is ridden in a Brahmanical and casteist notion of prayer and reward. Highly offensive and misogynistic, the pooja follows a hollow notion of ‘sex-positivity’ while overlooking homosexual relationships. The celebration reinforces the existing patriarchal structures which have ingrained insecurity in the minds of young women by reducing their value to just the pleasure of and determined by an external male gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;College is the first encounter of the young adults with reality by giving them a peek into the larger world out there. It introduces us to the workings of the ‘real world’ and underpins many of our perspectives and expectations in a social context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexist practices create a climate of fear and insecurity by producing feelings of worthlessness, self-censorship, and changes in behaviour. This further leads to the deterioration of people’s mental health and makes them acceptable to violence, as they now think they &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When students are exposed to these ideas in college, it either normalises these ideas for many by ingraining notions of male superiority. Or it makes people recognise and fight the problem. The wave of social consciousness and woke culture have made the youth today more liberal than their predecessors, leading to more inclusive spaces for women and homosexuals in institutions. They, however, remain a minority faction and their wokeness hasn’t led to a ripple effect big enough to shake down sexism on a bigger level. The boy’s hostel at Hindu College plans to host the Virgin Tree Pooja in 2021, many girls’ hostels continue to follow the archaic dress codes and curfews, and conversations among men will continue to be casually sexist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All over the world, people have celebrated 46 International Women’s Days and 6 Zero Discrimination Days and will celebrate many more, but until we abolish all discriminatory and sexist practices, we won’t be celebrating these days in their true essence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’</summary></entry></feed>