<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-27T22:59:16+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Transgender Bill 2019: A Step Taken Backwards?</title><link href="/Transgender-Bill-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgender Bill 2019: A Step Taken Backwards?" /><published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Transgender-Bill-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Transgender-Bill-2019">&lt;p&gt;On November 26, 2019, the Indian Parliament passed the Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill which provides us with the definition of a transgender as ‘someone whose gender does not match the one assigned at birth’. It also allows the self-perception of gender identity and criminalises begging. The entire process, presentation, amendments, drafting, and passing of the bill faced varied opinions from the public sphere as well as the entire community of LGBTQIA in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill prohibits discrimination against transgenders in educational institutions, government establishments, while using public services, etc. It also allows the right to ‘self-perceived’ gender identity. The policymakers argue that the bill leads to the development of the community with the formation of a National Council for Transgender Persons (NCPT) that will help and advise the government on formulation policies for the community, monitor implementation, address grievances, etc. There have been many instances where families disown their children when they come out about their identity at home. The bill will, hence, provide rehabilitation centre placement for transgenders whose family is unable to take care of them. This enforces a minor’s right of residence of compelling any trans person below 18 years to cohabit with their natal family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the communities and the people opposing the bill feel that it is straight-up against the right to dignity and bodily autonomy of transgenders. Grace Banu, a Dalit transgender rights activist, said that the bill was a “murder of gender and justice” and it did not uplift the community. According to gender activist, Harish Iyer, the Bill is regressive in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill was passed without approaching anyone from the community of transgenders. The process to obtain a transgender certificate has many fallouts. Apart from being an expensive procedure, it raises questions of violation of privacy. Also, there is no classification on how District Magistrate will examine the person based on their documents. The bill does not specify the ‘kind’ of surgery it is expecting because there is more than one type. This also contradicts 2014 NALSA (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Legal_Services_Authority_v._Union_of_India&quot;&gt;National Legal Services Authority v. Union of India&lt;/a&gt;) judgment by the Supreme Court that gave the right to self-identify and did not mandate surgery. Reflecting upon the lack of education, the bill conflates transgenders with intersex people. It fails to define what sexual abuse is. Even the punishment is not fully justified. In case of the rape of a woman, jail of 7 years or life sentence is given as punishment to the person who committed the crime, whereas, if the same happens with a transgender, a minimum of 6 months of jail which can be extended to just 2 years has been defined under the bill. There is no mention of marriage rights, property rights, and reservations for those who belong to disadvantaged groups, social security, or pension. This is nothing but deprivation of basic fundamental rights to the community, I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, I would like to address the problem with rehabilitation centre provision in the bill. Domestic violence has prevailed against transgenders and is clearly evident through examples from the past and present. Here’s what will happen now. A person will be forced to come out to their family which will not only violate their right to privacy but will also lead to mental pressure of how things will turn out. The intensity of ‘what ifs’ is something that cannot be measured by someone who is not facing anything close to this and in a country like India, domestic households do not operate with same ideologies and beliefs for immediate acceptance due to many reasons, lack of education being the primary factor in this case. People join LGBTQ groups or NGOs because they find a home away from their own. If a person in today’s situation wants to leave home then they will be placed in a rehabilitation centre without choice. This denies the rights of a person to join the trans community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the bill makes a feeble attempt at understanding the concept and difference between sex and gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entire process of the bill- from its presentation to its implementation- didn’t make to the headlines as it was concealed by other headliners in the news. When the bill was presented in Lok Sabha, it was overshadowed by the revocation of Article 370 and 35A in the Indian Constitution. When Rajya Sabha passed the bill, the political crisis of Uddhav Thackeray being elected as the new Chief Minister of Maharashtra on November 28, 2019, took over the media platforms. By the time the bill came into effect, the novel coronavirus disease took most of the headliners in news. Although through the efforts of independent media organisations, online social media coverage, art and activism, and voices from the trans communities, LGBTQIA groups and NGOs did grab the attention of the public of India. Some of them feel that Transgender Bill 2019 is transphobia in action. It is a direct violation of the Supreme Court judgment that was passed in 2014 (NALSA vs UOI) that acknowledged the fundamental rights of transgender people in India. The bill reduces the people to just their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, the stigma towards transgenders is prevalent in the Indian society, and when an act like this is passed without consultation of the very people it is designed for, the country as a whole takes a step backwards in its development process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Himanshi Saini</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">On November 26, 2019, the Indian Parliament passed the Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill which provides us with the definition of a transgender as ‘someone whose gender does not match the one assigned at birth’. It also allows the self-perception of gender identity and criminalises begging. The entire process, presentation, amendments, drafting, and passing of the bill faced varied opinions from the public sphere as well as the entire community of LGBTQIA in India.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reliance Jio: The Next Big Thing?</title><link href="/The-Green-Paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reliance Jio: The Next Big Thing?" /><published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Green-Paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Green-Paradox">&lt;p&gt;There have been several tremendous investments and operations undertaken by large corporations in the past, which have changed the world as we know it. One such investment that hopefully turned out to be absolutely triumphant was the Reliance Industries’ new telecom venture named ‘Reliance Jio’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukesh Ambani, the head of Reliance Industries, India’s largest conglomerate, shelled out $35 billion of the company’s money to provide the South Asian nation with its first all-4G network. By offering free calls and data for peanuts, the telecom latecomer upended the industry, setting off a cheap internet tsunami that is opening the market of 1.3 billion people to global tech and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to analyse how Reliance Jio turned the telecom industry upside down, how successful Jio has been, and what allowed them to have such a clear path to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gadgets.ndtv.com/tags/reliance-jio&quot;&gt;Reliance Jio&lt;/a&gt; officially launched its commercial operation on September 5, 2016, and it has drastically changed the telecom sector with its free voice calls and cheap 4G services that changed the way Indian users consumed data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukesh Ambani was well versed in the revenue streams of the existing players in the market. Upwards of 60-70% of the revenue was generated through voice call charges. Also, there existed a strong price war for voice call charges. The telecom industry was absolutely saturated with the negligible scope of any growth or outsider’s entry. But, Ambani being one of the greatest business minds on the face of the Earth, knew exactly where to strike and reap the benefits. The mobile data market in India was very limited mostly because of the high prices. Out of the 1.05 billion connections, only 10% used 4G and internet and therefore, mobile data lacked competition and had the biggest headroom for growth and development. Ambani found a sweet spot to invest in within such a saturated market and created an all-new space in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He brought in the latest 4G technology in India whereas other service providers such as Airtel, Vodafone, and Idea needed huge capital to upgrade their existing 2G and 3G networks to 4G. He invested a whopping $35 billion into the new technology which was 3 times bigger than the combined capital of all the three major service providers at the time. Other service providers did not have the resources to counter and bring in the latest technology. Additionally, there existed an exit barrier for them as they had already invested huge sums of money in the older technology whereas Jio didn’t have any such obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having invested so heavily in Reliance Jio, the biggest hurdle for the company to be successful was to attract customers, and this is where the genius business model of Jio comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jio used a loss-leading strategy for the first six months after launch, providing free unlimited voice calls and mobile data. The company’s 4G data services provided consumers the option to watch more online videos and other content than ever before, something that became apparent when India jumped ahead of the US and China to take the position of world’s biggest consumer of mobile data. Eventually, the company’s services did become paid, but that did not stop the Jio juggernaut– primarily because of the ultra-low tariff the company levied for its data. This strategy not only shifted the customer base towards Jio but also acted as an entry barrier for other providers in the industry as they could not operate under such conditions which, eventually, helped Jio to create a sort of monopoly in the mobile data market. The biggest advantage Jio had was its low cost of capital. Reliance used the cash flow from its traditional businesses to subsidise cheap prices to potential subscribers, and to kill off weaker competitors that had to rely on expensive bank loans. Moreover, they extended their free services to March 31, 2017, in order to retain the customer base and also expand it even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at how the telecom industry revolutionised after Jio’s entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultra-cheap data: Before the entry of Reliance Jio, data was rather expensive and consumers had to shell out up to ₹450 (on some networks) for 1GB of data. The highlight of Jio’s launch offer was the free data it was offering to consumers, with 4GB of high-speed 4G data per day, followed by continued data at 128kbps speed. Eventually, the company had to launch chargeable plans after incumbent operators protested, but even then the tariff was so low that consumers paid roughly Rs. 10 per GB of 4G data - something other operators also started to offer in response.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increased consumption of online content: India saw an exponential rise in the consumption of online content with the availability of free data. Jio claims India’s data consumption went from 200 million GB to 1200 million GB in six months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Free voice calls: Voice calls became free for all consumers across networks when Jio launched operations. The company has said both local and STD calls will always be free on its network, to all networks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Proliferation of 4G smartphones: The market for 4G smartphones exploded as a result of the gun and bullet strategy after Jio services were launched as everyone had access to the company’s 4G network for free.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Faster mobile data: With 4G becoming the norm in the market, mobile data speeds rose too, considering most people were on 3G networks before that. According to the latest data by the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (TRAI), Jio offers an average download speed of around 18mbps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A record in user acquisition: In February, Jio claimed its telecom network had garnered 100 million users in less than six months of operations. At the time, Chairman Mukesh Ambani had said this growth is faster than even what global giants such as Facebook and WhatsApp recorded. The Jio user base currently stands at more than 387 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improved broadband internet availability: With the free internet, millions of people got access to high-speed 4G services, and Jio became the country’s biggest provider of broadband internet – and that’s without even counting in the JioFiber service that the company recently started.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has Jio revolutionised the telecom industry, but it is also bringing in changes in society and education. With the easy availability of internet services in every remote corner of the country, people are now much more aware than they ever were about what is happening around the globe. Additionally, the online education industry has seen a boom with companies like Byju’s and Unacademy making great progress as every student with a mobile phone can now access the resources which earlier were not available to them. Kids living in villages where teachers often never show up for classes can now use their Jio smartphones to study online. Offsprings of the elite- who are sent to expensive cram schools to prepare for entrance exams- will now face competition from kids who have studied online in the hinterlands, thanks to Jio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jio is on the way to transforming itself into a platform for the vast population of India. A platform from whose ecosystem people cannot escape. We have been witnesses to the meteoric rise of many such platforms across the globe. Not only that, but we have also been the victims of such platforms for the last decade. Today, people’s lives seem incomplete without WhatsApp or Instagram, which is Facebook’s way of confining us within its limits. Google, Amazon, Apple, every major global player you name has a way of limiting our reach to their own services. And Jio’s move to be that platform provider for India has attracted global attention in these past few months. Everyone wants to be a part of this revolution and wants to get access to the large market that India offers to the world. Because of this, Reliance has been able to make Jio net debt-free ahead of its goal of March 31, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is very simple that after the white and green revolutions, Jio has brought a digital revolution in India. In the 21st century, data is the new oxygen and Jio has provided a way to access this data and bring a change. The success of Jio shows how a single man’s vision can bring a change in the lives of 1.3 billion people.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">There have been several tremendous investments and operations undertaken by large corporations in the past, which have changed the world as we know it. One such investment that hopefully turned out to be absolutely triumphant was the Reliance Industries’ new telecom venture named ‘Reliance Jio’.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stemming Democracy in the Time of a Pandemic</title><link href="/Stemming-Democracy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stemming Democracy in the Time of a Pandemic" /><published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Stemming-Democracy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Stemming-Democracy">&lt;p&gt;What kind of emotions do we feel when we fail someone close to us? Is there a surge of anger, remorse, or guilt within oneself? Does an institution, like a corporate company or a government, feel the same when they fail someone? Or is it a quality only available to true living beings, like animals and humans? That’s a question, I suppose, that all of us want to ask– to the world that failed us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is a web– a web of laws and money, a web of power and the misuse of it, a web of governments, a web of people and their opinions, as well as the lack of it. And when an unwanted entrant makes it to this web of ours, it tends to make us uncomfortable. Just as the COVID-19 pandemic has made not just us, but also the governments of all countries across the world, uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads me to the fact that humans have always more or less relied on their governments and the system to cater to their issues, and therefore, the responsibility of managing a country and its people’s lives during a virus outbreak also falls onto the shoulders of the governments of all countries. But the pressing concern here is to understand how governments essentially do the decision making, and how many mistakes they make on their way, hereby, failing the humans that rely on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies&lt;/strong&gt;– While for most countries, the first and foremost response was to implement interventionist policies such as a travel ban, shutting the borders, prevention of public gatherings and using police force wherever necessary, and most importantly, lockdowns and social distancing; many countries delayed their response to the pandemic outbreak and hence, found themselves in the mud in terms of protecting their people. This led to a lot of countries hiding the true figures of people testing positive or even worse, testing a lesser number of people so that their figures remain to a minimum. On the other hand, there were countries, like Japan and Sweden, that could not impose lockdowns because of constitutional barriers which led to Sweden adopting an approach that placed the faith on the public by implementing ‘voluntary cooperation’, but not a lot of people were found to be cooperating. It is also safe to say that a few developing countries, like India and Greece, which have a lack of proper healthcare services and not enough resources to cater to a large number of patients, were quick in their reflexes in implementing a police-backed lockdown knowing their limitations in the healthcare sector. On one hand, where a few countries saw a power dynamic tussle between the central and the state governments which made their responses slower, a few countries found themselves doing good when the state governments took charge of their people because of how well they understood the demographics of that particular state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade-offs&lt;/strong&gt; – In this globalised world of ours, the last few decades saw betterment in overall livelihoods and living standards all across the world when measured in terms of national income, but while the wages of workers in developing countries rose, the wages of unskilled workers in developed countries fell. Even in developing countries, when the workers earned better, it was still negligible in comparison to the rich elite classes of these countries. This economic disparity begets various forms of social disparities and gives rise to societal discontentment because there is never a single decision that can be implemented on every citizen and not all of them react to it similarly. That is why all the governments, of both developing and developed nations, had to make trade-offs to please not just their respective national interests but also to maintain their positions on the economic spectrum of this world. The best example would be of the USA, which hasn’t implemented a lockdown to date when the virus has managed to seep into our lives in the past four months. The USA, under President Trump, has found itself valuing the economy more than its own people and their lives. New York has seen a surge in the numbers of positive testing patients and thousands of deaths, but thanks to the New York Stock Exchange, a lockdown was never implemented. A lot of democracies have failed to take public opinions and willingness to stay in prolonged periods of a lockdown into account. However, Brazil, under authoritarian leader Jair Bolsonaro, did not implement an effective lockdown to maintain its image of being an apparent democracy that does not bind its people. Countries that respect people’s freedom and privacy were compelled to make a trade-off between long-term healthcare of the public versus their willingness to obey an imposed lockdown. Developing countries like Pakistan have also taken to certain unprecedented measures such as encouraging tourism in the midst of a pandemic owing to the lack of revenues for the normal functioning of the government, while India resorted to opening liquor stores to fill up their pockets, hence, making a trade-off between long-term health consequences of the public due to alcohol consumption as well as disobeying norms of social distancing versus stabilising the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding on a broad spectrum, the responses of various countries bring us to the fact that most countries have had to ignore one end of a scale to benefit the other which has given tendencies of anti-liberalism in these countries a rise. The realisation has hit the public that the private factors in our globalised world can do no collective good in times of a crisis. Even state machinery is not one hundred percent reliable, and questions have been raised on the market-based economic policies that all countries adopted and implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution, you may ask? Well, the solution is not simple, and most definitely not uniform. But what’s best that can be suggested is the fact that it is time for us to realise that our lives’ responsibility cannot be put solely on politicians sitting at the top of the pyramid. We need expertise. Most countries have for long seen its citizens as self-proclaimed experts who are either misinformed or uninformed and are able to climb to the top of the ladder by using tools of condemnation at best. Therefore, the call for experts is legit and urgent. Most politicians and leaders have a disregard for expertise because of how experts failed to predict the 2008 recession which affected the whole world. But now is the time to act on reason, coherence, and most importantly, transparent facts. Hence, scientific reliance on experts to survive the economy and sustain all possible human life is imperative to make the governments not fail humans, when humans need their governments the most.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">What kind of emotions do we feel when we fail someone close to us? Is there a surge of anger, remorse, or guilt within oneself? Does an institution, like a corporate company or a government, feel the same when they fail someone? Or is it a quality only available to true living beings, like animals and humans? That’s a question, I suppose, that all of us want to ask– to the world that failed us.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paying You to Study: Does it Work?</title><link href="/Paying-You-to-Study" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paying You to Study: Does it Work?" /><published>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Paying-You-to-Study</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Paying-You-to-Study">&lt;p&gt;Policies can sometimes have serious ramifications. A policy rolled out with good intentions can have devastating consequences in the long (or medium) run. Let me talk about one such policy in the state of erstwhile Andhra Pradesh (AP), a state in southern India. This had led to the development of a separate industry and excessive concentration in one particular field of study which is ‘engineering’. In this article, I try to explain the story behind a policy that led to the (excessive) supply of underproductive workforce into the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The years between 1995-2000 marked the beginning of the technology boom in India. With the arrival of Information Technology (IT) industries, allied services started to spring up in India. It was the time when N Chandrababu Naidu (CBN) had been the Chief Minister of the state of Andhra Pradesh. Taking into cognizance the fact that agriculture alone wouldn’t help the state grow, he wanted to leverage the IT boom for the state’s progress. He would tour countries, especially the US, and meet with the company heads and would convince them to set up their company in Hyderabad, the capital city of Andhra Pradesh. For all these efforts, industry people used to call him, and rightly so, the ‘CEO Chief Minister’. Though Hyderabad lost to Bengaluru in the race to become the Silicon Valley of India, it today has big companies like Microsoft, Google, Facebook, etc. and the famous Indian School of Business. Amazon today has its largest campus outside its headquarters in Hyderabad. All thanks to the CEO Chief Minister. Even as the industry grew, engineering colleges emerged to meet the needs of the industry. With that context, let us delve into the actual story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the subsequent general elections in 2004, CBN lost and his rival YS Rajasekhar Reddy came into power. The IT boom was in its golden period at this time and India’s macroeconomic stability was sanguine. In 2008, with an intention to bring technical education closer to the backward classes, he announced his famous policy: ‘Fee Reimbursement’. What the policy meant was that all those meeting the criteria laid down by the government, would get subsidised education in professional courses, i.e. engineering, medicine and pharmaceutical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beneficiaries of the policies were students that belonged to the OBC, SC, and ST categories. The Economically Weaker Section (EWS) quota has also recently been included. The criteria today is that OBC and EWS students with a rank below 10,000 in the ECET (engineering common entrance test; it was originally called EAMCET- engineering and medicine common entrance test) and income less than ₹100,000 per annum would get the reimbursement of their total tuition fee for all 4 years of their education. Students belonging to the same category with a rank above 10,000 and meeting the income criterion would receive a sum of ₹35,000. While students of SC and ST categories with an income less than ₹200,000 are eligible for full reimbursement of fee, irrespective of their ranks. The decision of fee reimbursement was revolutionary and gained massive public support. The number of students in engineering had risen rapidly. The intake of students in engineering colleges increased from &lt;a href=&quot;https://shodhganga.inflibnet.ac.in/bitstream/10603/124153/11/11_chapter%201.pdf&quot;&gt;91,716 in 2006&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aicte-india.org/sites/default/files/Perspective%20Plan%20for%20Telangana.pdf&quot;&gt;172,994 in 2013-14&lt;/a&gt;. While the numbers had been on the rise since 1997, this policy had further bolstered the expectations of engineering education and the lucrative life it brought. Thus, more and more people started pursuing this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned two happenings had also led to an increase in the number of educational institutions that offered engineering courses in the state. Anticipating the demand for bachelors in engineering, the State government allowed for private universities to be set up liberally, and granted, to a majority of them, autonomous status. According to a proposal sent by the State government to the All India Council for Technical Education, a central government body that oversees technical and medical education in the country, there were as many as 353 engineering colleges in the state. In 2016-17, however, this number had reduced to 220 (by this time AP had been bifurcated to form Telangana). Out of these 220, 146 colleges are situated in and around the state’s capital, Hyderabad. It is also shocking to know that in 2016-17, out of 31 districts in the state, 11 districts did not have a single engineering college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy that had the objective to take technical education to the doorsteps of the backward classes clearly had had its first set back. This is because Hyderabad is relatively a costly place to live in. Also, the colleges around Hyderabad are located in areas where there is pretty much nothing but the college. This is the first drawback of the policy. Second, colleges started misusing the policy to their favour. The colleges are required to maintain 1:2:6 ration among Professors, Associate Professors, and Assistant Professors. This would mean that over 11,000 professors with a PhD are required across all the colleges. On the contrary, the government itself had expressed its concerns &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aicte-india.org/sites/default/files/Perspective%20Plan%20for%20Telangana.pdf&quot;&gt;saying&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;“…it would not be surprising if hardly 1500 such staff members could be found…in the State.”&lt;/em&gt; Even if you wanted to let go of this one, the nadir quality of the infrastructure convinces you of the extant scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing that the colleges do is to employ agents to bring them admissions and pay the agents a cut from their ‘earnings’. These agents are responsible for showcasing the colleges as something with the ‘best’ infrastructure to have ever existed on the planet and lure students. The colleges in the argument are the ones that solely run on the reimbursement money. As it is said, profit maximisation is the key for any business and these colleges can do so only when they cut costs. So, taking a cue from the popular meme ‘modern problems require modern solutions’, they ditch the ideas to create infrastructure and make reasonable payments to faculties. Economics tells us when there are a large number of firms, competition increases efficiency. The market in question, is clearly not an oligopoly (300+ colleges, remember?). It is also important to note that the fee colleges charge is decided by the government. While this is one side of the coin, the other side is how students misutilised this scheme. The important criterion for determining who should be allowed to avail this scheme is income. Students produce fake income certificates obtained by bribing the concerned officer (from whom the act requires the income certificate be issued) to avail the reimbursement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now talk about the effects this policy had on intermediate education (or inter, as classes, 11th and 12th are called). The ECET ( the entrance exam I mentioned earlier) is taken by the students who pursue engineering from the colleges in the state. Somewhere around 2008, two prominent educational institutions that run schools up to 10th grade, had ventured into inter colleges business promising that they would coach students for the JEE (entrance exam to the premier IITs) and the ECET. Initially, when the JEE test had weightage for the intermediate marks in determining the final rank, there used to be a relatively greater number of selections from the state to IITs- thanks to the lenient marking by the intermediate board in class 12 final examinations. The duopoly of the two firms meant these students would come from either of the two institutions. This clubbed with the marketing techniques employed by the institutions attracted larger and larger crowds year over year. But when the weightage was dropped, the number of ranks also plummeted. Yet, the fascination for these institutions continues. It is no exaggeration to say that you’d be disgusted at what new lows these institutions have sunk to promote themselves when they really have no ground. These institutions charge between ₹90,000 - ₹250,000 per annum for two years. It comes as no surprise, when you read all this, to know that the timings of these colleges range between 12 hours to 14 hours a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of this article is in no way to criticise the policy. The state always has the responsibility of taking care of the have-nots. There are stories of many students who couldn’t dream of even studying who have benefitted from the policy and had become engineers. But it is imperative that we acknowledge that a set of decisions and actions led to something that can be categorised as a negative externality for society. &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/hyderabad/engineers-from-city-least-employable-reveals-study/articleshow/58555002.cms&quot;&gt;One study&lt;/a&gt; found that only 0.7% of students in Hyderabad area “were able to write functionally and logically correct code”. The wanting of skill among people is shifting the costs of training the workforce onto the industry and thus, driving down the salaries paid to the employed graduates. If this doesn’t indicate a policy failure, I don’t know what does. When skills of the students couldn’t be improved and make them ready for the future through the policy, it is necessary to think of ways to correct the loopholes, if not bring in a totally new policy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Policies can sometimes have serious ramifications. A policy rolled out with good intentions can have devastating consequences in the long (or medium) run. Let me talk about one such policy in the state of erstwhile Andhra Pradesh (AP), a state in southern India. This had led to the development of a separate industry and excessive concentration in one particular field of study which is ‘engineering’. In this article, I try to explain the story behind a policy that led to the (excessive) supply of underproductive workforce into the market.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair: Afghanistan’s War Within</title><link href="/Fair-is-Foul" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair: Afghanistan's War Within" /><published>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Fair-is-Foul</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Fair-is-Foul">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When Daesh came to our area, they killed a lot of people because they said we would have helped the Taliban. But now the Taliban have returned and they are saying we helped the Daesh.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Masooma, resident of the Aqsa Area of Darzab (as stated in a &lt;em&gt;Reuters&lt;/em&gt; report)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masooma’s desperate predicament is a perfect one-liner to highlight the political chaos of present-day Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 12, 2020, a crowd of gunmen stormed the Doctors Without Borders (Médecins Sans Frontières) administered maternity clinic at Dashti Barchi, in the western part of the capital of Afghanistan, Kabul, leaving 24 people dead including two new-born babies. The attack drew condemnation from nations across the globe, with the Amnesty International South Asia, regarding them as “The unconscionable war crimes in Afghanistan targeting a maternity hospital and a funeral, must awaken the world to the horrors civilians continue to face.” ISIL (the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant) had claimed responsibility for the barbaric attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About two months prior to the attack on the hospital, on March 25, 2020, assassins raided the Gurdwara Har Rai Saheb in Kabul, Afghanistan killing 25 Sikh worshippers. ISIL subsequently stated its explicit support for the bloodbath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two subsequent events can be said to have been a part of the broader picture in the spectrum of Afghanistan’s war within its frontiers. These attacks are examples from the series of ongoing battles for supremacy between ISIL and the Taliban in their bid to exercise supremacy and dominance over the nation. Its significance is further highlighted as they come within months of the US-Taliban peace deal in February at Doha ending their 18-year long conflict, the roots of which can be traced back to the immediate aftermath of 9/11 and the global war on terror. However, the deal came with a resounding foreboding by the US President Donald Trump, who announced that “If bad things happen, we will go back with a force like no one’s ever seen”. Mike Pompeo, US Secretary of State had made it clear to the militant group to “keep your [their] promises to cut ties with al-Qaeda”. It is interesting to note, a UN Assistance Mission in Afghanistan report (May 2020) had said that since the signing of the peace deal, civil casualties caused by the Afghan government and the Taliban-ISIL conflicts have escalated by more than a quarter when compared with the same month in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Background&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Taliban-ISIL conflict is a phrase used to denote an ongoing armed conflict between the factions of ISIL in Afghanistan, besides counting those within its ambit, groups affiliated with ISIL, and splintered factions of the Taliban, generally opposed to the primary power loci in the central Taliban organisational hierarchy. The conflict may have been said to have begun on November 11, 2015, when fighting began between assailants who were loyal to Akhtar Mansoor, the new Taliban leader, and Mullah Mansoor Dadullah, who exhibited a tilt in favour of the pro-ISIL faction. This fragment received enormous aid from ISIL, including arms and men from Chechnya and Uzbekistan. The turf war ended with the triumph of Mansoor’s faction over that of Dadullah. More than 100 lives on both sides were lost in Southern Afghanistan, as reported by the provincial director of security in Kabul’s Arghandab district. The next year was marked by Muhammad Rasul leading the ISIL faction against the Mansoor loyalists. However, the war escalated from the month of April in 2017 onwards and gained international attention, with the ISIL capturing drug dealers who had been reportedly selling opium in the Jowzjan province. The drug pedlars had alleged Taliban connections. The connections came to light, with the clashes erupting between groups of the Taliban and the ISIL faction to ensure the forcible release of the three drug dealers, who were paying 10 million Afghanis to the Taliban to clinch a deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May 24 marked the largest clash between the two hostile entities near the border shared between Afghanistan and Iran. It had been sparked off by an attack on the ISIL camp by the Taliban, who had agreed not to enter into armed struggle prior to mutual dialogue. An ISIL commander had reportedly told NBC News that the Taliban was entering into a coordinated alliance with the Iranian Military and receiving generous support from them. Fidai Mahaz, also known as the Sacrifice Front, led by Mullah Najibullah, a Taliban splinter group had been strongly opposed to the Taliban-Iran nexus, claiming that the Taliban had received $3 million in cash, 3,000 arms and 40 trucks and ammunition from the Iran government to wage a war against ISIL. The Iranian government implied that they were concerned about the steady gain of territory by ISIL and their increasing status in Afghanistan affected the regional security of Iran; 2018 marked by the Battle of Darzab, in which the Taliban and the Islamic State, in the Khorasan province, engaged in conflict for hegemony over the Darzab district in the Jowzjan province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the June talks between the Russian government and the Taliban, the US criticised the Russian position of extending support to the Taliban to defeat ISIL as they believed it granted legitimacy to the Taliban, discrediting the recognised Afghan government. The resultant fighting left 3,500-7,000 civilians homeless and thousands dead on either side. However, by early August, ISIL’s hold was reduced to two villages, with most ISIL fighters pleading for clemency and protection from the Afghan government against the Taliban. The US-Taliban negotiation in 2018 echoed the Taliban’s plea to end US airstrikes as well as to provide support to combat splinter groups and ISIL. Last year marked heavy clashes at Kunar, with ISIL circulating photos of weapons captured from the Taliban, followed by a video of the fighters renewing their oath to Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi criticising the prospect of US-Taliban peace talks. Further, on October 1, ISIL claimed to have killed 20 Taliban soldiers in Tora Bora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What lies ahead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deeper dig into the causes of conflict between ISIL and the Taliban go beyond the primary causes for the fight to secure more land in accordance with Dabiq, the Islamic State manifesto, since ideology and long term objectives between the two differ strongly. ISIL (or ISIS in the broader spectrum) aims at establishing an Islamic Caliphate worldwide, while the Taliban aims to secure an Islamic State, ruled by Quranic law or their own interpretation of the Shariat. Hence, there can be increasing speculation about the future of Afghanistan, post the US-Afghan peace talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US-Afghan peace deal may result in ironical consequences which might include an increase in the membership of ISIL, as a major chunk of the Taliban foot soldiers who would be dissatisfied with the peace negotiations might join ISIL. It might have a significant impact on the Southeast Asian nations too, with many nations including India eyeing the Taliban with suspicion as a terrorist group and refusing to engage in bilateral or multilateral talks with obvious specifics towards its stand on the Kashmir issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question lingers whether a civil war is imminent in Afghan soil in the decades to come if ISIL strengthens itself or if it is an improbability, or whether a war with obvious outcomes is going to ensue, now that US assistance may help the Taliban in their war against ISIL. The world meanwhile grapples with the timeless words of the three witches in &lt;em&gt;Macbeth&lt;/em&gt;, “Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair”, as US special envoy Zalmay Khalilzad defends the Taliban and their efforts to achieve “peace”, the same Taliban with whom they waged an 18-year long battle. So in diplomacy, fair or foul whichever you choose, (that is if you don’t consider them to be the two sides of the same coin), the great gamble for Afghanistan proceeds between ISIL, Taliban, and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“When Daesh came to our area, they killed a lot of people because they said we would have helped the Taliban. But now the Taliban have returned and they are saying we helped the Daesh.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Oppression Matters, The Rioting Matters</title><link href="/The-Oppression-Matters" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Oppression Matters, The Rioting Matters" /><published>2020-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Oppression%20Matters</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Oppression-Matters">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Slavery was not born out of racism, but racism was born out of slavery.”&lt;/em&gt; – Eric Williams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often use the word &lt;em&gt;racism&lt;/em&gt; with a feeling of ‘otherness’ and a sense of disconnect, as if participating in racism is something that we’re all immune to. Yet, the history of racism dates back to hundreds of years, and after tens and thousands of revolutions led by Black folks, racism in all of its forms - ideological and systematic, is just as prevalent now as it was back then. The United States of America has been revolting and fighting for justice for Black lives after George Floyd’s institutionalised murder in the recent weeks. Many citizens have expressed their extreme discontent by looting and targeting multi-billion-dollar organisations. My question is, who are we to police how oppressed communities should fight against the system? Isn’t this an integral part of the fight against racism itself? Aren’t capitalism and racism inherently linked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us are equipped with the knowledge about the Atlantic slave trade. In summary, thousands of African Americans were enslaved by European colonizers in the 1600’s, when they, on a ludicrous quest to loot and colonise nations to facilitate trade and make profits, stumbled upon mass profiteering potential in the Caribbean, Africa and America, where valuable crops were aplenty. They were sold as slaves and made to work for hours extending to days at plantations. Many people mistake the enslavement of Black people as a product of racism, ignoring the capitalist intentions with which these atrocities were committed. A capitalist society rests on the principle of exploitation of the working class - the European colonisers treated Black people as a means of making profits; racial prejudices didn’t necessarily drive this motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the rich and elite slave-owners wished to create a divide between the working class so as to retain their influence and ‘divide and rule’, they introduced a system within a system; a system built on the colour and culture of a community. As a result, racism gradually emerged as a tool for many economic elites worldwide to keep the working class from uniting against a system making profits off of their hard labour. Racism was used as a justification for slavery, citing all the negative stereotypes relating to Black people - they are “lazy, unintelligent and violent”. Many modern-day American billionaires and millionaires are guilty of perpetuating the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to the modern-day scenario, capitalism and racism work together to establish a system fundamentally against Black and non-Black people of colour. Capitalism will never thrive at full employment - it works on the existence of a certain percentage of unemployment. You ask how? When people fear being replaced, they’d be willing to work at the lowest of wages. The rich feed off of this fear and make profits in billions. Unemployment and poverty won’t deter many from scraping for money and food for their family, leading them to indulge in illegal ways of earning money. More often than not, racism is deployed as a tool to put Black people at the extreme bottom of income distribution, leading to higher rates of unemployment among them. So, when the rich threaten White people with unemployment, the latter think “No, I am not like them (Black people). I must earn enough money and become rich”. This is how capitalism and racism work in partnership and keep the cycle of exploitation and discrimination spinning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Marxist theory has laid out the foundations of two social evils we witness in our society. However, opponents of this argument deem that proponents of this theory often indulge in class-reductionist behaviour and that to reduce racism down to only class instead of addressing the years of social conditioning and building negative stereotypes is a huge disservice to Black folks, and I agree. Citing that the real issue is only class and not race propagates the notion that rich and middle-class Black citizens don’t face racism, which is nowhere near the truth. Racism has definitely emerged out of economics; however, it has also turned into a social exclusionary tool, stripping so many Black people of their rights and dignity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a debate has ensued on the extent to which looting billion-dollar corporations aids the fight against police brutality and racism. The answer lies in the question itself. The police serve the elite; they work for the protection of their interests and wishes in order to uphold the status quo. During the 1900’s, when more and more immigrant working citizens entered the economy, the ruling class employed hundreds of armed men to maintain ‘order’ within the working class. This has extended to the modern-day police who disproportionately target poor Black and Latino people. The use of the police force over Black people is significantly biased and racially-motivated. They are 3x times as likely to be victims of police brutality as their White counterparts. George Floyd was just one of many Black people to lose his life to a system so antagonistic toward people of his community. Under the farce of serving and protecting people of an area, the police are responsible for inflicting violence upon hundreds of unarmed citizens. Whose interest is the police upholding if not the ruling class? Why can’t citizens democratically vote for a police force rather than letting strangers exercise so much power over them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the origins of things affecting us and thousands of lives everyday is of paramount importance. Racism didn’t appear out of nowhere; it was carefully woven into the very economic system of the US. In the same way, the police weren’t introduced to protect the common citizen, instead they are meant to control the ‘violence’ of the working class and resistors of the system, which in the American scenario, are mostly Black people. Racism and capitalism are the two sides of the same coin; each depends on the other to survive.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aarushi Mittal</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“Slavery was not born out of racism, but racism was born out of slavery.” – Eric Williams</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Guess the Average!</title><link href="/Guess-the-Average" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guess the Average!" /><published>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Guess-the-Average</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Guess-the-Average">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll try to explain it to you and we’ll reason our way to the answer. This game is played under the condition known to the game theorists as ‘common knowledge’. Not only does every player have the same information, but each player also knows that every other player knows this. Now, the highest possible average that can occur is 100 which is possible only if every person guessed 100. In that case, two-thirds of the average would be 66.66. Since everyone can figure this out, it wouldn’t make sense to guess anything higher than 67. If every player comes to the same conclusion, no one will guess higher than 67.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now 67 is the new highest possible average so no reasonable guess should be higher than two-thirds of that which is 44. This logic can be extended further and further. With each step, the highest possible logical answer keeps getting smaller. So it would seem sensible to guess the lowest number possible and indeed if everyone chose zero, the game would reach what is known as ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Rational-Pirates&quot;&gt;Nash Equilibrium&lt;/a&gt;’ (which I extensively explained in my previous article on game theory). This is a state where every player has chosen the best possible strategy for themselves given everyone else playing, and no individual player can benefit by choosing differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that’s not what happens in the real world. People, as it turns out, either aren’t perfectly rational or they don’t expect each other to be perfectly rational. Or, perhaps, it might be some combination of the two. When this game is played in real-world settings, the average tends to be somewhere between 20 and 35. Danish newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Politiken&lt;/em&gt;, ran the game with over 19000 readers participating, resulting in an average of roughly 22, making the correct answer 14. Economic game theorists have a way of modelling this interplay between rationality and practicality called ‘K-level Reasoning’, where ‘K’ stands for the number of times a cycle of reasoning is repeated. A person playing at ‘K-level zero’ would approach our game naively and guess a number randomly without thinking about other players. At ‘K-level-1’, a player would assume everyone else is playing at level zero, resulting in an average of 50 (everyone choosing integers at random between 0 to 100 gives an average of 50) and thus guess 33. At ‘K-level-2’, they’d assume that everyone else is playing at level-1 leading them to guess 22. It will take twelve K-levels to reach zero. The pieces of evidence and various studies suggest that most people stop at 1 or 2 K-levels and that’s useful to know because K-level thinking comes into play at high stake situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, stock traders evaluate stocks not only based on earning reports, but also on the value that others place on those numbers. Another example is during penalty kicks in soccer, both the shooter and the goalie decide whether to go right or left based on what they think the other person is thinking. Goalies often memorise the pattern of their opponents well in advance but penalty shooters know that and can play accordingly. In each case, participants must weigh their own understanding of the best course of action against how well they think other participants understand the situation but 1 or 2 K-levels is by no means a hard and fast rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I think you would wonder what would happen if people played this game after understanding the difference between the most logical approach and the most common? The answer is that it is up to the person’s understanding and intuition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Error 404: Democracy Unachievable in your Region</title><link href="/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Error 404: Democracy Unachievable in your Region" /><published>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region">&lt;p&gt;For Hong Kong, the year 2019 has been a monumental one. In April last year, the citizens of Hong Kong took to the streets to protest against the controversial extradition bill. This bill could have potentially undermined the judicial independence of Hong Kong and silenced the dissidents by exposing the Hongkongers to unfair trials by Beijing. In September, after 5 months of protests, the bill was withdrawn. However, this has led to a bigger uprising: one against Beijing as Hong Kong now demands full democracy and an inquiry into the police’s actions. With this, the protests continue. However, as the entire world got caught up by COVID-19, the protestors withdrew from the streets to escape the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An opportunist Beijing swooped in during this period with the National People’s Congress (NPC) approving to impose a highly contentious national security law in Hong Kong on May 28, 2020. The legislation seeks to ban secession, subversion of state power, terrorism, foreign intervention, and allow mainland China’s state security agencies to operate in Hong Kong. This essentially means that the harshest criticism of China and the ruling party will be criminalised. Detailed legislation, however, still needs to be drafted and enacted, which could be done within the next few months. Critics fear it threatens the political and civil freedoms enjoyed by the semi-autonomous territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong’s government has signalled support for the legislature and said it would cooperate with China to enforce the laws in Hong Kong. Carrie Lam, Hong Kong’s Chief Executive, has also made a public statement reiterating China’s stance saying that the law will only target a handful of people involved in terrorism or subversion. On the other hand, the Hongkongers have retaliated with a series of protests despite fears of coronavirus. On a forum popular with protestors, LIHKG (often referred to as the Hong Kong version of Reddit), users have called for a ‘hundred-day war’, calling it the last opportunity to protest before the law comes into force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Pompeo, US Secretary of State, condemned the legislation by calling it a ‘disastrous proposal’. He also stated that Hong Kong is no longer autonomous from China and threatened to revoke the special status it enjoys in trade with the USA. In a joint statement, Australia, Canada, the UK and the US have expressed their ‘deep concern’ regarding the law. They have also called on Beijing to work with the Hong Kong government and people to find a “mutually acceptable accommodation”. Taiwan, Japan and Germany are also standing in solidarity with Hong Kong and have called for China to not undermine Hong Kong’s freedoms. As these countries line up in support of Hong Kong, Beijing is getting more suspicious that these foreign efforts aim to exploit its domestic weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong was handed over to China in 1997 by the United Kingdom after 150 years of colonisation. As a part of China, it operates under the ‘one country, two systems’ principle ensuring Hong Kong enjoys independence in its legislature, judiciary and economy. Set to expire in 2047, the arrangement allows Hong Kong to enjoy autonomy and freedom of speech and assembly. These freedoms, however, don’t exist in mainland China. To aid this, a document called the Basic Law – Hong Kong’s mini-constitution - was drafted which ensured Hong Kong its freedom and set out a structure for governance of the territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article 23 of the Basic Law already calls for Hong Kong to enact national security laws to prohibit “treason, secession, sedition [and] subversion” against the Chinese government. While the article already exists as a part of the Basic Law, it has never been enacted. In 2003, a similar attempt was made by Hong Kong’s first Chief Executive, Tung Chee-hwa but was abandoned post mass protests. The next three successors never attempted to repeat this out of fear of protests, despite repeated warnings from China stating that they were obliged to do so. This time, however, China plans to enact the law without Hong Kong’s approval by pursuing an ‘unconstitutional’ method. The laws will be enacted through a provision that bypasses Hong Kong’s legislature and therefore, public debate and consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draconian legislation comes when China is already under the scrutiny of the international community after the coronavirus outbreak. It is said to be China’s way of tightening its grip on Hong Kong after a year of pro-democracy protests. Seeing how the legislation eerily echoes the mainland’s current legal framework, it is safe to believe that the drafted legislation will not be compatible with international human rights obligations binding on Hong Kong. Provisions regarding anti-terrorism and sedition under existing laws are already inconsistent with global standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong has acted as a haven for dissent with its freedom of speech and assembly. The legislation, however, seeks to attack these freedoms and silence the loudest voice against China. Many are afraid that China will set up its institutions in Hong Kong under the garb of ‘national security’ that could introduce China’s law enforcement to the city. This could further affect the judicial system of Hong Kong. According to Professor Johannes Chan, a scholar at the University of Hong Kong, the security law poses a major problem. “Almost all trials involving national security are conducted behind closed doors. It [is] never clear what exactly the allegations and the evidence are, and the term national security is so vague that it could cover almost anything,” said the Professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislation, additionally, bans all “activities of foreign forces” interfering in Hong Kong’s affairs. People also worry that this could affect Hong Kong’s attractiveness as a business and economic powerhouse. This is a troubling aspect for an economy already struggling with tourism in the past year because of protests and COVID-19. This, however, isn’t the first step taken by China to counter the rising pro-democracy narrative in Hong Kong. In February 2020, China announced Xia Baolong, the man known for the clampdown on Christian churches in the Zhejiang province during 2014-15, as the head of the Hong Kong &amp;amp; Macau Office. China also revamped the reporting structure that crystalised the clear chain of command from Hong Kong to Beijing. Additionally, Luo Huining, known for executing Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption campaign, was appointed to head the Chinese Liaison Office in Hong Kong. “They’ve got two guys who are not familiar with Hong Kong issues, and who have governed provinces in China in a heavy-handed way and think they can do the same in Hong Kong,” said Kwok, who has a law degree from King’s College, University of London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, on June 4, 2020, Hong Kong’s legislature passed a contentious bill that makes insulting the Chinese national anthem, illegal. Anyone who shall intentionally insult the anthem will face up to 3 years in prison plus fines worth at least $6,000. The bill was introduced by Beijing last year in response to the Hong Kong soccer fans booing at the anthem at the 2015 FIFA matches. Post the bill being passed, students at the Hong Kong University held a silent protest at the Pillar of Shame, a sculpture commemorating the victims of the Tiananmen crackdown. With a foggy future ahead, Hongkongers tread on a narrow road to democracy with no destination in sight. More clashes between the two parties are to be expected in the future, but it’s going to take a long time before either party backs down. Hong Kong’s pro-democracy fire will not burn out anytime soon. In a world where the global community blames China for the coronavirus outbreak and the USA further imposes tariffs on Chinese goods, China will do all it can to retain its power and reputation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">For Hong Kong, the year 2019 has been a monumental one. In April last year, the citizens of Hong Kong took to the streets to protest against the controversial extradition bill. This bill could have potentially undermined the judicial independence of Hong Kong and silenced the dissidents by exposing the Hongkongers to unfair trials by Beijing. In September, after 5 months of protests, the bill was withdrawn. However, this has led to a bigger uprising: one against Beijing as Hong Kong now demands full democracy and an inquiry into the police’s actions. With this, the protests continue. However, as the entire world got caught up by COVID-19, the protestors withdrew from the streets to escape the virus.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘Vultures’ 2020</title><link href="/Vultures-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Vultures’ 2020" /><published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Vultures-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Vultures-2020">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;I’m really, really sorry. The pain of life overrides the joy to the point that joy does not exist. …depressed … without (a) phone … money for rent … money for child support … money for debts … money!!! … I am haunted by the vivid memories of killings &amp;amp; corpses &amp;amp; anger &amp;amp; pain … of starving or wounded children, of trigger-happy madmen, often police, of killer executioners …&lt;/em&gt;” - Kevin Carter (an excerpt from his suicide note)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 28, 2020, during an Indian Supreme Court hearing on the humanitarian crisis faced by the intra-state migrant workers due to the nationwide lockdown, Tushar Mehta, the Solicitor General (SG) of India, referred to the story of Kevin Carter, a South African photojournalist who won the Pulitzer Prize for depicting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1993_Sudan_famine&quot;&gt;1993 famine in Sudan&lt;/a&gt; through a photograph titled “The Vulture and The Little Girl.” Troubled by all that he had seen, Carter committed suicide at the age of 33.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/nostri-imago/5000121934&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//sudan_famine1993.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narrating this from an archival perspective, Tushar Mehta aimed this towards the way the media is reporting the ongoing migrant crisis; by displaying their visuals, using mounting death tolls as headlines. According to Mehta, the ones documenting this are nothing but ‘vultures’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this very documentation led the Supreme Court to issue a notice to all governments, ordering the Indian Central government and the State governments to immediately provide free-of-cost transport, food, and shelter to migrant workers on May 26, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faye D’Souza, a journalist, retweeted the Supreme Court’s entire conversation and raised a very relevant question – “Would he (SG) prefer if these stories were never told?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a journalism student, I have had and have read plenty of comments and opinions towards the media. I have tried to differentiate criticism from mockery and take the constructive part out of the two. However, statements like the one made by the SG make me feel that even the courts in my country aren’t democratic but just political in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine, &lt;em&gt;Caravan&lt;/em&gt;, in an article on May 28, 2020, reflects upon the plight of the journalists reporting during the pandemic. A snippet from the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Every journalist who has been reporting on the pandemic has been traumatised by what they saw or reported. No one has done it for a moral license to feel better about themselves—this work, in fact, has the opposite effect on journalists. Over time, it changes you forever. The activist, filmmaker, and writer Susan Sontag summed up this journalistic dilemma best: “The person who intervenes cannot record; the person who is recording cannot intervene.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SG, however, told &lt;em&gt;The Times of India&lt;/em&gt; that his statement was being misread as he was referring to some of the pseudo-NGO (Non-Governmental Organisation) workers who have just been criticising the government and the Court for doing nothing when they themselves also haven’t contributed enough to make the situation better for the migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, I personally feel that the justification given here is not exactly matching with the description the SG gave about the journalists in the court. The fact that the SG thought that the documentation could have been done in a better way is nothing but a step back towards blurring the lines of reality presentation by the fourth pillar of democracy. Is this not against the ethics of journalism? Has journalism been reduced to comfort news and neglecting the underprivileged? Is journalism NOT about grabbing the attention of the authorities in charge that have turned too blind to see the plight of the very people that made them sit in power today? Is journalism NOT about raising the voices of the voiceless? Yet the journalists who have been doing all this as responsible media personnel, at the expense of their own health during the pandemic, have been termed as ‘vultures’ in the Court? The SG has forgotten that the ones he claims to be vultures also got the country THREE Pulitizer Prizes 2020 for feature photography depicting the plight of Kashmir after the revocation of Article 370 by the Indian government in August 2019. In places like Kashmir, journalists themselves become stories and their work instead of being appreciated is reduced to zero or charged under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA) by its very own government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journalists like Barkha Dutt have been on road since the past 70-80 days covering the pandemic crisis and helping the migrants get adequate attention so that they reach their homes safely. They are out on the field and are away from their quarantined safe places, documenting stories of the ones who want to go to their own homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So probably for the next time, I can only hope there is a decent amount of respect for the ones who are actually contributing to help the fellow members of the society instead of passing a generalised bland statement for all the media because, in that way, you not only disrespect the journalists working on the documentation but also the sufferers who want to be voiced.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Himanshi Saini</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“I’m really, really sorry. The pain of life overrides the joy to the point that joy does not exist. …depressed … without (a) phone … money for rent … money for child support … money for debts … money!!! … I am haunted by the vivid memories of killings &amp;amp; corpses &amp;amp; anger &amp;amp; pain … of starving or wounded children, of trigger-happy madmen, often police, of killer executioners …” - Kevin Carter (an excerpt from his suicide note)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?</title><link href="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?" /><published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me">&lt;p&gt;Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The birth of a child is considered a moment of unbound joy and is believed to provide families with a wholesome experience. What follows next is a series of sleepless nights, great anxiety, and several &lt;em&gt;potty&lt;/em&gt; training sessions. Raising a child in today’s world is no piece of cake, be it in terms of personal devotion, child-care responsibilities or financial needs. Families, rich and poor alike, face their own set of challenges with respect to the same. Putting this into perspective, these issues arising from varied aspects add up to one big question: what is in it for the parents? Let alone going through the process more than once, is it all truly worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raising this question, we believe children born in different set-ups, in terms of beliefs and economic backing, add varied sorts of value to the particular household. A family belonging to the lower-income group generally believes that having a larger number of children means more hands to work in the field or otherwise, completely negating the cost of actually raising these children. For those poor, rural families, children are not only seen as an economic asset but also as an insurance policy for old age, especially in societies with zero state pension and health care. However, we observe that as the income of a family increases, the smaller the family is, i.e. they prefer to have fewer children. With rising incomes, families don’t need their children to be an economic asset; the family can afford for their children to be an economic liability. Furthermore, people with a superior economic standing believe in providing better education and lifestyle to their children. Hence, while, children in impoverished communities contribute to their family income, children in the developed world subtract from family finances through the cost of their education and upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can also be measured by weighing the marginal cost against the marginal utility of procreating. The marginal cost and utility, incurred and reaped respectively, largely depend upon the budget constraint of each household. Hence, so does the optimum number of children. This brings us to the conclusion that there is a negative correlation between family income and family size which further leads to a trade-off between the quantity and the quality of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the idea that having a higher number of children reduces the cost of raising each additional child; in short, highlighting diminishing marginal cost. The reason behind this is that most of the necessary child raising equipment- like high chairs, cribs, and clothes - can be passed onto the next child, and no additional money is required to be spent on the same. Moreover, with many family and parent-child health insurance plans, the monthly premium remains the same, irrespective of the number of children. This points to a lower cost per person. Additionally, there are several universities in the States that provide various benefits to families with more than one child. Therefore, it could so happen that due to these benefits the cost per unit of putting ten children through college could be less than that of putting one. Who says houses cannot be run on economies of scale?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of the economies of scale, there are substantial costs that remain fixed: a large number of children leads to the dilution of parental resources- financial as well as time. These fixed costs include expenses on food, healthcare, and basic clothes for lower-income groups. Similarly, the fixed costs of higher-income groups are much larger as they involve education, and extra-curricular activities amongst others. Moreover, these children also give their parents a fair share of headaches. Being anxious about everything pertaining to their children forms a crucial part of a parent’s identity. This leads us to another opportunity cost which is the personal freedom of these caregivers. This causes the parents to juggle between giving time to their children and finding time for themselves and their work. Therefore, as the number of children increases, there is a marked drop in the time spent with each child. Many of them might grow up feeling neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like identified in the foregoing paragraphs, the utility and benefits that the parents reap from their children can be seen in the form of economic and old-age support. However, it is also important to realise that as the number of children that a couple has increases, there is a decline in the marginal utility. This is because, with each additional child, there is a decreasing extra satisfaction that the couple will gain. This can be seen in the way that if a couple has 5 children then they will receive more satisfaction with their firstborn than they did from their last born (5th child in this case). Hence, as the number of children a couple has increases, the law of diminishing returns starts to hold true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, what is truly in it for the parents purely depends upon the type of income groups that they belong to. Thus, regardless of whether couples want children for personal attachment or joy, it all eventually boils down to the economic cost and utility of having one!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kabir.kochar sanya.puri</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.</summary></entry></feed>