<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-06T12:50:59+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West</title><link href="/The-Fall-of-Religion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West" /><published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Fall-of-Religion</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Fall-of-Religion">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this happening? Why are young people increasingly disassociating themselves from organised religion, especially in what can only be fittingly described as a post-Christian society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four main reasons which I put forward, all of which can be summed up in a single sentence: &lt;strong&gt;Christianity – and, especially, Catholicism - has lost its credibility in the minds of our youth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1: The Dominant Historical Narrative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one of us has heard it sometime or the other. The popular narrative runs thus: human society began well and reached summits of excellence and achievement, especially in the classical age. But when Christianity came, all that progress and achievement, as well as the scientific impulse, came to an end and was effectively destroyed. For centuries, the West was embroiled in a quagmire of oppressive feudalism and religious intolerance, in which free-thinkers were labelled heretics and persecuted fiercely. This was called the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt;, and rightly so, because human civilisation was truly held in captivity in the darkness of religious bigotry and superstition. All of this was the case, until the time of the Renaissance and the Enlightenment when, finally, we were able to break free of the chains of theocracy and emerge into the bright new world, to build our future for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is how countless millennials understand the Medieval period. It is certainly the way history is taught in our schools, and thus the way many millennials understand this era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added to this is the stigma of the Crusades and the Inquisitions, both of which are believed to be butcheries of human life and liberty based on religious (and especially Catholic) dogmatism and fanaticism. Fresh in the mind of many of our fellow millennials is the Galileo Affair, in which – it is believed – the geocentric Catholics tried to murder the heliocentric Galileo for the crime of trying to think rationally and not superstitiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this narrative, however, is myopic, and fails to take into account the various other factors which were at play. But, unfortunately for people like me, many of my fellow millennials believe this to be the Gospel truth. And naturally, it has distanced them from a religion which, they are convinced, is responsible for stifling human civilisation and progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2: The Widening Gap Between the Jesus of History and the Christ of Faith&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Brown is one of the most popular fiction authors in the world today. I have had the chance of reading parts of his books, and have found his style to be most engaging. However, Brown is more than your average thriller writer. Thanks to books like &lt;em&gt;The Da Vinci Code&lt;/em&gt;, Brown has managed to bring the ‘Lost Gospels’ to the forefront of public discourse. And boy, has it fired the imagination of the masses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What people like Brown have managed to do is convince the populace – and especially the youth – that there is big difference between the Jesus of Catholicism and the actual Jesus whom we read about in works like the Gospel of Peter and Phillip, for example. He has also managed to alert people regarding the issue of the Biblical canon; why are these four Gospels part of the Bible and not others? Why has the Church chosen to only highlight these particular narratives and declare others heretical?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way information is put out in books such as these has convinced countless many that in the very early history of Christianity, there emerged a power-hungry faction which sought to glorify their own theology at the expense of others. We are told that there was not one but several ‘Christianities’ in the beginning. But one faction – which today exists as the Catholic Church – gained ascendancy and, with quite a bit of patronage from Romam Emperor Constantine, persecuted the other factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds to the impression that today’s youth already has regarding the Christian faith and leaves them with a deep distrust towards anything related to Catholicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3: The Rise of Philosophical Naturalism and Postmodern Nihilism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone looks at the world through a set of lenses. We all operate with basic metaphysical and epistemological presuppositions. However, in recent times, especially in universities, a particular philosophical perspective has been put forward vociferously, and other points of view have largely been isolated and marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for a while, was an undergraduate philosophy student at a well-respected university in India. And what I encountered from my professors was not a careful treatment of the various opposing perspectives but rather open and brazen bias, especially when it came to the philosophy of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What young undergraduates are consistently taught is that the arguments for the existence of God – as put forward by people like Augustine, Aquinas, Leibniz and others – are all extremely poor and fallacious bits of reasoning which can be so easily debunked that one wonders how such eminent men came to such bizarre conclusions. We are also told that these people were motivated by their own personal religious beliefs, and sought to back them up the best they could. What remained was a set of arguments that would only convince people who already had faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is the dominant narrative in philosophical academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And young philosophers usually accept this without question, without delving deeper into the works of Augustine and Aquinas to see if this is indeed true. Most of them don’t bother to later study the philosophy of religion, but rather end up specialising in other fields. And so what they uncritically accept as true in their early years, they end up carrying throughout life. And it is in this way that a consistent naturalist philosophical narrative has been built up over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this has led our young people to be extremely skeptical of any supernatural claims and has, therefore, led them to the conclusion that this world is all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting development happening simultaneously is the rise of postmodernism. This is entirely different from the dogmatic atheism I have just described. Rather, this is a dogmatic rejection of all dogmatism, an objective denial of all objectivity. It is a position some might characterise as absurd, but this appellation is readily embraced by some of its vociferous proponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postmodernism is basically summed up in three maxims: “Truth is what you make of it. Morality is what you shape of it. God is Who you think He/She/It is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this attitude is the product of the younger generation’s exposure to other cultures, viewpoints and ways of thinking. Young people see heated debates in which scholars on both sides put forward their cases and state their opinions, each backing themselves up with copious argumentation. They see different religions and ways of life, entirely different from the ones they had been exposed to. And having no strong rational grounds to support the religion of their upbringing, they naturally come to the conclusion that ‘man is the measure of all things’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This understanding of life is indeed very attractive since it promises a kind of godhood. One is free to shape one’s reality and one’s destiny as one sees it. One is free to identify as whatever one pleases and be whoever one wishes to be. Above all, one is liberated from the shackles of dogmatism, free to believe whatever they wish to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, anyone addicted to this euphoria of freedom will find organised religion, with all its creeds and ancient affirmations, very unattractive indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4: The Transformation of Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the most important and significant of all, since it strikes not merely at our intellect but also at our emotions. The cultural elite of the West are working very hard to change and transform culture. They do this through books, films, magazines and mass media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: Imagine that you have grown up in a very conservative society, your parents told you that the right thing to do was to dress modestly, especially in front of the opposite sex. What happens when you are constantly exposed to pictures of men and women in states of partial or complete undress, when you can hardly go to the movies or even switch on a television without coming across some scene or advertisement that is either sexually explicit or has strong sexual themes, that too being performed by men and women who are great artists whom you admire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, your perception is going to shift. You would in all likelihood rather imitate your heroes and role models rather than your parents, in this case. And in all probability, your friends have similar attitudes in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these factors come together and compound in such a way that it is possible to change views about something as fundamental as human sexuality across the course of a generation! Changing one’s views on sexual ethics is nothing more and nothing less than a paradigm shift. Instead of being something that is sacred and to be enjoyed within the context of marriage in a reproductively responsible manner, young people are offered the alluring option of ‘sex with no strings attached’. Rather than being the self-giving expression of commitment and love between two spouses (as Christians have traditionally believed), it has become a ‘casual’ affair. It is, therefore, no wonder that our young people are losing their faith in traditional Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular music has played an inestimable role in detaching young people from the Christian faith. Young people see singers who are clearly extraordinarily talented, beloved by all their friends and peer groups, and who sing songs that contain themes that are clearly contrary to Christian faith and morals, in more ways than one. Naturally, over time, one comes to favour one’s friend groups rather than one’s parents and one begins to side with the more secularising culture rather than traditional ways of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I am a millennial myself. But I am not your average millennial. In fact, I am a convert to the Catholic Church, having come from a liberal Hindu background myself. I am the black sheep, so to speak, of this modern and enlightened generation. What causes me to remain traditional and Catholic? Why don’t I simply join the great secular bus and enjoy all the many benefits its offers? Why do I remain in the shadows and willingly disassociate myself from much of the modern world and even isolate myself, at times, enjoying but a few friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons are endless, but I will summarise it in a few brief points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is my firmest conviction that the conventional narrative about the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt; is thoroughly erroneous, and in fact holds little water in academic circles, thank God. This view of the Medieval Church as an oppressive, science-persecuting religion has been increasingly discredited in modern times, not least by the excellent work of the Pulitzer-Prize winning Rodney Stark who, although himself a non-Catholic, has taken it upon himself to work towards exonerating the Catholic Church from baseless myths and lies, as can be seen in his work &lt;em&gt;Bearing False Witness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this idea that the Church persecuted scientists fails to take into account the immense contributions the Church made to science, in the Middle Ages and after as well. It is true that Galileo was persecuted – on charges of heresy. But what is left unmentioned is that Copernicus’s heliocentrism fascinated the Pope of his time, who spoke highly of him on numerous occasions. What is also conveniently left out is the devoutly Christian spirit of the countless intellectuals across the course of history who laid the foundations of modern science, believing that their study and analysis of the natural world was a kind of worship of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we then left with? Is there no future for religion in the West?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion will survive. The Church will always be there in the West, even if it is weakened and marginalised. Popular culture and the mass media already brand the Christian faith as regressive. It is perhaps only a matter of time before popular opinion turns into political legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Church will survive. It always has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, it has found a new homeland. As the West continues to go down this slippery slope and continues to schism itself from its Christian roots, the great African continent has already opened its arms wide open, in welcome of the Gospel and the Church.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="millennial" /><summary type="html">One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?</title><link href="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?" /><published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough">&lt;p&gt;The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexual economy of the world seems to be in danger. Of course, this conclusion is met with evidence from surveys done on American grounds and on Americans but there seems to lie an innate truth to it. &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;’s December cover story threw light on this. I’m sure Kate Julian’s extensive research on the topic and terming of the phenomenon ‘Sexual Recession’ brought her just as much hate as it did fame, but from what I could procure, she left no page unturned, except the veil of obvious bias, but we’ll come to that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a full tell-all, supported by a General Social Survey (GSS) in 2016, conducted at the University of Chicago, she lists out reasons behind the recession―the assumed ones, why it occurred in the first place and why this recession is specific to the Millennials. Her article is a long read―heavy with insight and stories from across her social sphere―and, given a choice, I’d award her. Her article shone light upon something that we were all aware of in parts, and albeit she only showed off the parts that worked in her favour, she did make sure that all was listed, with enough to make us not counter her points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Foucault would say, we love talking about sex, we enjoy discussing it not just as a primal need rather as a form of entertainment. Sexuality, he said, was a construct of human discourse. “We convince ourselves that we have never said enough on the subject,” he wrote in his (four-volume) &lt;em&gt;The History of Sexuality&lt;/em&gt;. “It is possible that where sex is concerned, the most long-winded, the most impatient of societies is our own.” Personally, I’d say, few fields of human behaviour—and none more important—are this hard to explain. As something that has been talked about ever so often, from religious scriptures telling us how and when to do it, oh, and of course, when not to, to trilogies earning billions with 1001 pages of ‘teeth-clenchingly good’ sex. We all know of it, but why and how it became the talk of the town, albeit uttered only in hushed tones, is vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned GSS determined that people who are in their early 20s right now are two and a half times as likely to be abstinent as Gen Xers were at the same age. Specifically, between the years 1990 to 2014, the average adult went from having sex 62 times a year to 54 times a year, therefore, the hoola-hoo about the downfall in the Sexual Economy. If I were to meet the ‘spokesperson’ of this Sexual Economy that we all have now been made aware of, I’d only have one word to say: ‘Damn.’ Just so one is kept in the know, it’s not just an American problem. Most countries don’t track their citizens’ sex lives closely. But those that try, mostly the ones who are extremely wealthy, are reporting their own sex delays and declines. One of the most respected sex studies in the world, Britain’s National Survey of Sexual Attitudes and Lifestyles, reported in 2001 that people between the ages of 16 to 44 were having sex more than six times a month, on average. By 2012, the rate had dropped to fewer than five times. Over approximately the same period, Australians in relationships went from having sex around 1.8 times a week to 1.4 times. Finland’s ‘Finsex’ study found declines in frequency of coitus, coupled with increasing rates of masturbation. In the Netherlands, the median age at which people first have intercourse rose from 17.1 in 2012 to 18.6 in 2017, and other types of physical contact also got pushed back, even kissing. In fertility-challenged Japan, which is already in the midst of a demographic crisis and has become something of a case study in the dangers of sexlessness, a third of single people aged 18 to 34 were virgins as of the year 2005; but by 2015, 43% of people reported the same. Japan has been infiltrated by several cultural complexes: Hikikomori (the phenomenon of complete isolation from society) being one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, whatever’s going on here does not seem like a ‘millennial trend’. It really probably pertains to people in their 20s, so younger millennials or Gen-Z. We tend to talk about millennials as if they are some group that just landed here intact, whereas it’s more useful to talk about what it’s like to be a young person, at this point. Not to mention, the fear of a “sex recession” is misdirected. A drop in sexual encounters from 62 to 54 times a year means that the average adult is still having sex more than once a week. Millennials are having to deal with things previous generations haven’t dealt with, and it’s useful to clarify that. As and when I read more about this, I found that people think online connectivity and smartphones have had a dramatic effect on how people’s lives are shaped and their behaviours. That’s probably true for most generational groups, and for the groups that use technology more, that’d be truer. Tinder has only made things easier, so why the lack? My only problem was why 2 and 2 didn’t add up to 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I went digging, and found a &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; article (yes, I went there) and believe me, if &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; makes you believe you’re not having enough sex, &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; will assure you enough for a lifetime, or well, at least a couple of months. The survey research showed a decline in sex mainly among white, middle-aged, married couples, which, of course, is a very, very small bracket to be construed as an entire generation’s problem. Julian’s tone in &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;––listing a myriad of theories to explain the drop, from smartphones to economic instability to Tinder––was cautionary, I’ll give her that. But, news of the so-called “sex recession” provoked reactions across the internet, from &lt;em&gt;Vox&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Vice&lt;/em&gt;—not to mention the plethora of comments which turned it into madness with no method. Companies have picked up on this, more researches are being based on the same and while all that is great, there’s a problem that doesn’t exist and is yet being worked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are different now; sex is different now. Dictionaries may still consider sex to be vaginal penetration, but to us—it may be anything from second base to the seventh one. Sexuality is explored more. People are more aware of what it is that they want, there’s more to it than just genitals having a meet and greet, pleasure plays a huge role in how sex is seen. I would highly recommend that people read Julian’s article and all the reasons she gives for us to not be having enough sex: from stress to bad, painful encounters, but with a grain of salt. We may be failing to do a gazillion more things, but for once, I can attest sex is something we’re doing a bang-up job of (all puns intended.) Tinder, Bumble and Grindr have only made it more relevant. Nothing one does to explore it can be wrong, not until someone is harmed. There is no ‘normal’ amount of sex. Worrying about how much sex one’s having—which can increase anxiety, decrease body confidence, and hinder healthy communication—is not good for one’s sex life, either. Ironic, isn’t it? In terms of desired sexual activity, every individual, and every couple is different, including people who identify as asexual. Just the idea of #MeToo challenges the notion that we can measure our sex lives by anything other than our own generational values and self-reported satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fundamental level, I share Julian’s concern when she writes that she “was taken aback by what seemed like heartbreaking changes in the way many people were relating—or not relating—to one another.” This is what we should focus our attention on. It turns out, though, that a small drop in aggregate annual sexual frequency has no demonstrable effect on how couples form and sustain, fulfilling relationships. If people aren’t having sex but they’re doing other things they find fulfilling, that’s great. But if people are not having sex, and wish they were, that’s more of a concern, wouldn’t you say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I have to say is that every generation has its faults counted, every generation has to face things the previous ones didn’t have to endure. While one is yet to see how much more can be done, can be changed or morphed, I am sure that our shapeshifter of a generation won’t be a disappointment. Sex or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="millennial" /><summary type="html">The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It</title><link href="/The-Middle-Income-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It" /><published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Middle-Income-Trap</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Middle-Income-Trap">&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Mahatyohar&lt;/em&gt; (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded
with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by
the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were
perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign.
Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of
6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a
decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which
explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as
compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put
more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have
pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations
can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a
part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could
indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the
National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue
of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He
identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what
the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to
lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per
capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has
become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges
from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the
economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good
industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states
that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with
by the government’s &lt;em&gt;PM Awas Yojana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PM Mudra Yojana&lt;/em&gt; schemes respectively,
it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate
the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re
becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital
development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that
we’re heading into. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation
makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but
then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation.
This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101
nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved
high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily
attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital,
lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is
comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been
exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely
crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being
channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar
to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour
is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages
are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the
current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of
Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of
high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s
demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour
supply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related
expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6%
required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its
restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like
&lt;em&gt;Startup India&lt;/em&gt;, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage
investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture
capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty
valuation of the startups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of
2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will
have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic
convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the
developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like
Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and
efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India,
who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour
and must now bear the consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the
early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers.
Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was
absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South
Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The
global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy
perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing
private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was
the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources
from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than
high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other
professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation.
Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human
capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater
urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic
demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because
becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital
account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently
undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the
politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically
left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive
foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment
destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that
before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations,
for capital is faithful to none.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">While the Mahatyohar (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign. Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of 6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence. Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with by the government’s PM Awas Yojana and PM Mudra Yojana schemes respectively, it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that we’re heading into.  The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation. This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101 nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital, lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy.  Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour supply.  As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6% required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like Startup India, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty valuation of the startups.  An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of 2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India, who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour and must now bear the consequences.  The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers. Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation. Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater urgency. Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations, for capital is faithful to none.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Africa Sees a New Dawn</title><link href="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Africa Sees a New Dawn" /><published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated><id>/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn">&lt;p&gt;As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the
unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger,
the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to
realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the
African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being
ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the
African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver
prosperity to all Africans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and
services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will
bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of
more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In
terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s
largest free trade area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services,
and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member
states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market
improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would
benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would
become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of
which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of
the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually
eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an
economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and
consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes
competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and
thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The
relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit
private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract
foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in
consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By
2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a
combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA
shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the
UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the
potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of
evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study
has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply
by being a member of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive
manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the
goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only
about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries.
Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the
continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The
African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2
billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost
advantage over other nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa
such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the
other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the
countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania,
both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known
to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in
violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan
textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local
markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of
COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for
exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to
repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates
ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their
trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends
on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa,
Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has
assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been
satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the
agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.”
“We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and
entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for
finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium
Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their
place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to
account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a
factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal. 
Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more
price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a
rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and
consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place
in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage
to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do
business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and
technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through
competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country
and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be
dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond
their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in
Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of
scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations.
Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The
country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad,
thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa
is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by
opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and
communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the
vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and
peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the
global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the
process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of
“Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the
agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and
oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger, the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver prosperity to all Africans. AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s largest free trade area. A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services, and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies.  The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By 2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply by being a member of the European Union. The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries. Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2 billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost advantage over other nations.  Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania, both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs. AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa, Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.” “We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal.  Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets. Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations. Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad, thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment. In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of “Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Were Ancient (Egyptian) Times More Modern Than We Think?</title><link href="/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Were Ancient (Egyptian) Times More Modern Than We Think?" /><published>2019-07-02T12:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T12:29:00+00:00</updated><id>/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Egypt gave birth to what later would become known as ‘western civilization’;
long before the greatness of Greece and Rome.”&lt;/em&gt; -John Henrik Clark&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hollywood movies have played their part in creating the notion that the Nile’s
gift was a land riddled with mysterious forms of art, sorcery, murder and
extravagant eye makeup. We all grew up with stories of the beautiful seductress
Cleopatra and the great lands of Egypt ruled by the native Egyptians for
millennia before the Greeks finally arrived. The funny part is this: Cleopatra
probably wasn’t very beautiful (incest was a common practice among the royals
back then, and in the absence of genetic diversity, deformed features like
elongated faces were common among them) and the Egyptians had been ruled by
foreigners like the Ethiopians long before the Ptolemaic dynasty, the last
dynasty of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egypt was a rather modern and ahead-of-its-time kind of a society. This fact
finds reflection in their inscriptions, their rulers, their trade affairs and so
on. Let’s start with their family lives and societal norms. The ancient
Egyptians had their own religion and two of their most important Gods and
Goddesses were Osiris and Isis, a brother-sister duo married to each other
(again, incest was okay). Unlike most religions, wherein the man is portrayed as
dominant and the woman as submissive, Isis, the goddess of magic, was the
dominant one in their duo. In fact, every ruler needed a partner in order to
rule Egypt. Unlike most modern societies, the husband and the wife were at the
same pedestal. All of this is evidenced by inscriptions depicting the husband
and the wife (Pharaoh and Queen) together, even showing them commanding an army
of soldiers (best examples include the inscriptions dating back to the Amarna
period) and coins showing faces of both side by side (from the Ptolemaic
period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ancient Egyptian society, virginity was not a requisite for marriage but
loyalty after marriage was expected. If a couple were to fall out of love, they
could get a divorce; a common enough practice and therefore free of stigma. In
countries like India, even today, people who walk away from their marriages
fearing shaming and ostracisation at the hands of society. Nuclear families
dominated their communities and lineage was traced through both parents’ sides
alike. Both of these bear testimony to the fact that the Egyptian lifestyle was
very different from that of its contemporary civilisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Egyptian inscriptions, it seems unlikely that they ever practised slavery,
once again, contrary to popular belief. The labourers who worked on the pyramids
or the temples were well fed and housed. Their mummified bodies also indicate
that they were natives of the land. They lived close to where they worked and
were even buried there, literally in the shadows of the pyramids- the Pharaoh’s
last resting place (considered to be a great honour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their houses were intriguing too. They had courtyards and separate studios.
Another very common feature was a flat roof, where they often cooked or slept
during hot nights. Ancient folk are not expected to share the ideals of
cleanliness that modern society holds. But lo and behold, the Egyptians had
toilets in their homes and their own systems of drainage and cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of ancient Egypt’s greatest contributions include the &lt;strong&gt;papyrus&lt;/strong&gt;. At one
point, the Egyptians mass produced (handwritten, of course) &lt;em&gt;‘The Book of the
Dead’&lt;/em&gt; to be buried with the mummified bodies of their loved ones. Besides,
Kings and Queens used this ‘paper’ to sign away their declarations and orders
too, a practice, surprisingly similar to the present-day passing of bills.
Drinking beer was a common practice, even among the commoners. Ancient Egypt can
also be credited with the development of several methods of contraception and
various pregnancy tests. The Egyptians valued knowledge a lot and this is
evident from the remains of the great library at Alexandria. We might as well
call Egypt &lt;em&gt;the Land of Inventions&lt;/em&gt; because of the numerous inventions that came
out of this particular ancient culture, some of which revolutionised human life
long before the Renaissance or the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most contemporary civilisations, the Egyptians did not have a calendar
based on the moon’s cycle. Instead, their calendar was based on the Earth’s
revolution around the sun (Turns out Copernicus might have had some help in the
form of ancient inspiration!). These ancient humans had 365 days in a year and
an extra day every four years (Julius Caesar later took this idea to Greece
during Cleopatra’s reign). Sounds very familiar, doesn’t it? Surprisingly
enough, their religion lent support to the science that pervaded their society!
In fact, most of their mythological stories revolve around facts that have been
proven to be scientifically correct. The Egyptians were also pioneers in the
field of astronomy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their architectural brilliance proves the fact that they were great engineers
and mathematicians too. The angle of inclination of the pyramids, the lengths of
their sides and so on, were accurate down to minutes and a couple of inches
respectively. Granite blocks used in the Great Pyramid of Giza’s burial chamber
are cut to perfection and fit into each other such that not even a credit card
can slip in between. The pyramids are spectacles that cannot be explained even
today. Each stone block used in its construction weighs at least a couple of
tonnes and the entire structure rises up to a staggering height of 139 metres.
Did I mention that the Egyptians did not even have the wheel? How the pyramids
were constructed is up for debate. What is undeniable is the fact that they were
masters of the art of building and made structures meant to stand the test of
time unlike any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have either heard or read about the Gods and Goddesses of Egypt. As I
learnt more about their culture and society, I came across something that left
me astonished: monotheism- a very modern ideology and isn’t uncommon today. But,
I guess, Pharaoh Akhenaten and his wife Queen Nefertiti were way ahead of their
times. They devoted all their lives to the worship of a single God- Aten (the
Sun). This religion, however, did not address one major question that had always
plagued the Egyptians: ‘What happens after death?’. This obviously did not sit
very well with the priests and the practice was discarded right after
Akhenaten’s reign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous of ancient Egyptian practices is probably the process of
mummification. The method that they developed was nothing short of genius. They
wanted immortality and in some ways, they did achieve it. We know what they did,
ate and entertained themselves with, just like any other civilisation. But,
here, we also have their bodies; their stories &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; have faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, Egyptian inscriptions were located in Australia. It is undeniable
that their trade flourished. With the advent of the Ptolemaic dynasty (after
Alexander the Great’s invasion), coins were introduced in trade. The second
Pharaoh of this dynasty, Queen Arsinoe introduced coins with her face on them -
she wanted everyone to know who held the reigns. Most rulers were well versed in
several languages and were very diplomatic. Cleopatra is claimed to have been
fluent in around 9 languages. That, however, is not the only shocking thing in
her resume. She was intelligent and trained in alchemy, geography, philosophy
and so on and so forth. She knew chemistry too, in fact, she owned a perfume
factory. To me, it all sounds like capitalism might have had some really ancient
roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a pity that the only thing that we usually care about is whether the
Egyptians were black, how beautiful the pyramids are and how was Cleopatra able
to seduce both Mark Anthony and Julius Caesar, and speculations about how
beautiful she was. The Egyptians accomplished tasks their contemporaries could
only ever dream to accomplish–feats involving mind-boggling architecture,
freakishly modern societal norms, mastery in mathematics, astronomy and art, and
unique practices that would later go on to shape the world. They lived up to
every word they ever wrote or spoke:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What I hate is ignorance, smallness of imagination, the eye that sees no
farther than its own lashes. All things are possible… Who you are is limited
only by who you think you are.”&lt;/em&gt; – Egyptian Book of the Dead&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“Egypt gave birth to what later would become known as ‘western civilization’; long before the greatness of Greece and Rome.” -John Henrik Clark Hollywood movies have played their part in creating the notion that the Nile’s gift was a land riddled with mysterious forms of art, sorcery, murder and extravagant eye makeup. We all grew up with stories of the beautiful seductress Cleopatra and the great lands of Egypt ruled by the native Egyptians for millennia before the Greeks finally arrived. The funny part is this: Cleopatra probably wasn’t very beautiful (incest was a common practice among the royals back then, and in the absence of genetic diversity, deformed features like elongated faces were common among them) and the Egyptians had been ruled by foreigners like the Ethiopians long before the Ptolemaic dynasty, the last dynasty of Egypt. Egypt was a rather modern and ahead-of-its-time kind of a society. This fact finds reflection in their inscriptions, their rulers, their trade affairs and so on. Let’s start with their family lives and societal norms. The ancient Egyptians had their own religion and two of their most important Gods and Goddesses were Osiris and Isis, a brother-sister duo married to each other (again, incest was okay). Unlike most religions, wherein the man is portrayed as dominant and the woman as submissive, Isis, the goddess of magic, was the dominant one in their duo. In fact, every ruler needed a partner in order to rule Egypt. Unlike most modern societies, the husband and the wife were at the same pedestal. All of this is evidenced by inscriptions depicting the husband and the wife (Pharaoh and Queen) together, even showing them commanding an army of soldiers (best examples include the inscriptions dating back to the Amarna period) and coins showing faces of both side by side (from the Ptolemaic period). In ancient Egyptian society, virginity was not a requisite for marriage but loyalty after marriage was expected. If a couple were to fall out of love, they could get a divorce; a common enough practice and therefore free of stigma. In countries like India, even today, people who walk away from their marriages fearing shaming and ostracisation at the hands of society. Nuclear families dominated their communities and lineage was traced through both parents’ sides alike. Both of these bear testimony to the fact that the Egyptian lifestyle was very different from that of its contemporary civilisations. From Egyptian inscriptions, it seems unlikely that they ever practised slavery, once again, contrary to popular belief. The labourers who worked on the pyramids or the temples were well fed and housed. Their mummified bodies also indicate that they were natives of the land. They lived close to where they worked and were even buried there, literally in the shadows of the pyramids- the Pharaoh’s last resting place (considered to be a great honour). Their houses were intriguing too. They had courtyards and separate studios. Another very common feature was a flat roof, where they often cooked or slept during hot nights. Ancient folk are not expected to share the ideals of cleanliness that modern society holds. But lo and behold, the Egyptians had toilets in their homes and their own systems of drainage and cleaning. Some of ancient Egypt’s greatest contributions include the papyrus. At one point, the Egyptians mass produced (handwritten, of course) ‘The Book of the Dead’ to be buried with the mummified bodies of their loved ones. Besides, Kings and Queens used this ‘paper’ to sign away their declarations and orders too, a practice, surprisingly similar to the present-day passing of bills. Drinking beer was a common practice, even among the commoners. Ancient Egypt can also be credited with the development of several methods of contraception and various pregnancy tests. The Egyptians valued knowledge a lot and this is evident from the remains of the great library at Alexandria. We might as well call Egypt the Land of Inventions because of the numerous inventions that came out of this particular ancient culture, some of which revolutionised human life long before the Renaissance or the Industrial Revolution. Unlike most contemporary civilisations, the Egyptians did not have a calendar based on the moon’s cycle. Instead, their calendar was based on the Earth’s revolution around the sun (Turns out Copernicus might have had some help in the form of ancient inspiration!). These ancient humans had 365 days in a year and an extra day every four years (Julius Caesar later took this idea to Greece during Cleopatra’s reign). Sounds very familiar, doesn’t it? Surprisingly enough, their religion lent support to the science that pervaded their society! In fact, most of their mythological stories revolve around facts that have been proven to be scientifically correct. The Egyptians were also pioneers in the field of astronomy! Their architectural brilliance proves the fact that they were great engineers and mathematicians too. The angle of inclination of the pyramids, the lengths of their sides and so on, were accurate down to minutes and a couple of inches respectively. Granite blocks used in the Great Pyramid of Giza’s burial chamber are cut to perfection and fit into each other such that not even a credit card can slip in between. The pyramids are spectacles that cannot be explained even today. Each stone block used in its construction weighs at least a couple of tonnes and the entire structure rises up to a staggering height of 139 metres. Did I mention that the Egyptians did not even have the wheel? How the pyramids were constructed is up for debate. What is undeniable is the fact that they were masters of the art of building and made structures meant to stand the test of time unlike any other. We all have either heard or read about the Gods and Goddesses of Egypt. As I learnt more about their culture and society, I came across something that left me astonished: monotheism- a very modern ideology and isn’t uncommon today. But, I guess, Pharaoh Akhenaten and his wife Queen Nefertiti were way ahead of their times. They devoted all their lives to the worship of a single God- Aten (the Sun). This religion, however, did not address one major question that had always plagued the Egyptians: ‘What happens after death?’. This obviously did not sit very well with the priests and the practice was discarded right after Akhenaten’s reign. The most famous of ancient Egyptian practices is probably the process of mummification. The method that they developed was nothing short of genius. They wanted immortality and in some ways, they did achieve it. We know what they did, ate and entertained themselves with, just like any other civilisation. But, here, we also have their bodies; their stories literally have faces. Very recently, Egyptian inscriptions were located in Australia. It is undeniable that their trade flourished. With the advent of the Ptolemaic dynasty (after Alexander the Great’s invasion), coins were introduced in trade. The second Pharaoh of this dynasty, Queen Arsinoe introduced coins with her face on them - she wanted everyone to know who held the reigns. Most rulers were well versed in several languages and were very diplomatic. Cleopatra is claimed to have been fluent in around 9 languages. That, however, is not the only shocking thing in her resume. She was intelligent and trained in alchemy, geography, philosophy and so on and so forth. She knew chemistry too, in fact, she owned a perfume factory. To me, it all sounds like capitalism might have had some really ancient roots. It’s a pity that the only thing that we usually care about is whether the Egyptians were black, how beautiful the pyramids are and how was Cleopatra able to seduce both Mark Anthony and Julius Caesar, and speculations about how beautiful she was. The Egyptians accomplished tasks their contemporaries could only ever dream to accomplish–feats involving mind-boggling architecture, freakishly modern societal norms, mastery in mathematics, astronomy and art, and unique practices that would later go on to shape the world. They lived up to every word they ever wrote or spoke: “What I hate is ignorance, smallness of imagination, the eye that sees no farther than its own lashes. All things are possible… Who you are is limited only by who you think you are.” – Egyptian Book of the Dead</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Voting Rights for Prisoners: A Conundrum</title><link href="/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voting Rights for Prisoners: A Conundrum" /><published>2019-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners">&lt;p&gt;As 2020 US Presidential election campaigning is in full swing, heated debates on contentious issues have taken the centre stage. Among these is the issue of voting rights for incarcerated citizens during their prison terms. A staunch supporter of voting rights for prisoners is Vermont Senator Bernie Sanders. In a CNN town hall on April 22, Bernie supported the right to vote to include even the Boston Marathon bomber Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, who was sentenced to death in July 2015. Sanders believes that the commission of any crime or horrific act should not debar a citizen from his right to vote. To quote him, “I think the right to vote is inherent to our democracy. Yes, even for terrible people because once you start chipping away … you’re running down a slippery slope,” Sanders said, attracting a strong rebuttal from the Republicans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Outlier&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 6.1 million people in the United States have lost their voting rights as a result of felony convictions. The United States is an outlier, compared to many nations across the world where the voting rights of prisoners are protected. Twenty-six European countries protect the voting rights of prisoners who are convicted for non-violent crimes such as drunk driving, possession of a small amount of marijuana or fleeing the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eighteen countries grant this fundamental right even in case of murder convictions. When Britain imposed a blanket ban on voting in 2005, the European Court of Human Rights ruled this to be a grave violation of human rights. Canada, South Africa and Kenya also grant voting rights to their felons. During the Presidential elections in North Macedonia, ballots were brought from prisoner’s home voting district in thirteen prisons of the country. Ahead of the recent referendum, election officers initiated a program to renew expired voting documents of the incarcerated people. In Bosnia and Herzegovina, prisoners convicted for crimes unrelated to the Bosnian War have the right to vote. In Germany, Norway and Portugal, only those convicted for crimes that target the state or democratic order, like terrorism or political violence, are disenfranchised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vermont and Maine are the only two states that allow prisoners to vote in the United States. Twenty-six American states stripped this right away from former prisoners for a lifetime. Joining the bandwagon are Armenia and Chile, where prisoners lost their voting rights. In Belgium, prisoners with sentences longer than seven years are not allowed to vote. In India, prisoners and those under preventive detention lose their voting rights under Section 62(5) of The Representation of People Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Reflection of Racism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A socio-political dimension to the voting rights debate is the political representation of the black community in America, given the disproportionate incarceration of black people in the country. In the colonial era of America, the concept of “civil death” was prevalent. It was believed that some bad actions render a person ineffective in utilising his civil rights. A racial twist to the story came following the Jim Crow laws, enacted in the late 19th and early 20th century. Black Codes were enacted in the South following the Civil War to constrain rights of black people, criminalising disobedience and “disrespect to the employer”. The subjectivity left it to the discretion of the authorities and enforcement targeted and criminalised the black community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most blacks lived in the South and were effectively disenfranchised following the Jim Crow laws. Analysts believe that the 1912 Presidential election was steeply slanted against the interests of the Black Americans. The brunt of poll taxes and literacy requirements was borne by the poor and illiterate Americans (a large proportion belonged to the black community), while European Americans were exempted from meeting these requirements. Literacy testing clauses were consciously used to single out Black Americans in Virginia, Oklahoma and Florida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Barack Obama said at an NAACP convention in 2015, “African-Americans are more likely to be arrested. They are more likely to be sentenced to more time for the same crime.” There were 5.1 times more Black prisoners than white incarcerated in state prisons. According to Ashley Nellis, a senior research analyst with the Sentencing Project, the disparity between black and white felons was more than ten times in five states. New Jersey had the highest disparity, with twelve black people to one in its prison system. This was followed by Wisconsin, Iowa, Minnesota, and Vermont. Oklahoma had 2,625 black inmates per one hundred thousand residents, with only 7.7% of the population being black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the sheer population of black felons, the disenfranchisement results in skewed participation of the community in the elections. This takes a toll on all aspects of the electoral process: from the inclusion of their demands in the agenda to allowing leaders from the community to run for positions. This hampers the socio-political empowerment of the community, an objective that has not been accomplished since the Civil Rights Movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting: A Fundamental Right&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamental rights, by definition, are not meant to expire on the commission of a crime. Other than for crimes related to terrorism and civil strife, depriving the citizen of his right to vote should be an exception and not a norm. Universal suffrage is meant to be universal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question at the heart of the debate is: What is the purpose of a prison? Is it meant to be a punishment which includes restriction of rights, or a place for repentance and rehabilitation? Prisons should be a place for reeducation and providing the inmates with skills and values to reintegrate with society upon their release. Giving them voting rights and making them realise the fundamental rights as well as duties is an important component of the reeducation drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silver Lining&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Florida voted for a constitutional amendment to end the policy of permanent disenfranchisement of felons. The supermajority voting for the motion helped to restore the voting rights of 1.5 million convicted felons. The District of Columbia and fifteen other states joined the bandwagon to end this draconian policy. Those on parole or probation were allowed to vote in New York. With such examples in the neighborhood, the process of rethinking about prisoner rights has begun in the other states as well. This would go a long way in achieving Martin Luther King’s vision of a racially just society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gurleen Kaur</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">As 2020 US Presidential election campaigning is in full swing, heated debates on contentious issues have taken the centre stage. Among these is the issue of voting rights for incarcerated citizens during their prison terms. A staunch supporter of voting rights for prisoners is Vermont Senator Bernie Sanders. In a CNN town hall on April 22, Bernie supported the right to vote to include even the Boston Marathon bomber Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, who was sentenced to death in July 2015. Sanders believes that the commission of any crime or horrific act should not debar a citizen from his right to vote. To quote him, “I think the right to vote is inherent to our democracy. Yes, even for terrible people because once you start chipping away … you’re running down a slippery slope,” Sanders said, attracting a strong rebuttal from the Republicans.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Great Indian Intercourse</title><link href="/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great Indian Intercourse" /><published>2019-06-28T21:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-28T21:29:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse">&lt;p&gt;Of the many things that India, as a subcontinent, has achieved or done, such as
overpopulation, growing disparity between economic classes and the caste system,
probably one of the greatest would be the writing of the &lt;em&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/em&gt;; and even
though we have, as a nation, owned up to most of the country’s achievements,
even the more bizarre ones such as child marriage, in case of sex we tend to
walk right by it without even a cursory glance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might argue that such prudish behaviour is a result of uneven distribution
of cultural capital, but I believe that’s an oxymoron in itself. I’m not here to
talk about how such prudence came into being in Indian culture – that is a topic
for another day. What I would like to draw attention to is the product of such
prudence taking shape in the form of coyness surrounding the topic of sex in
Indian society. Now, if you belong to an extremely liberal Indian family or
reside in the West, you’re probably not aware of the coyness I speak of. But we
plebs have felt it right from our childhood, when our mothers would, almost in a
frenzy, change the channel if we accidentally tuned into some English movie
channel with a couple kissing on the screen. This particular act of maternal
care and horror brought about two things; firstly, a curiosity about the most
basic and prevalent of human natures that would sooner or later manifest into
action, and secondly, through this suppression, we were being conditioned into
suppressing our very understanding of ourselves. If we do not properly accept
and understand the psychology underlying sex and sexuality we become blunt to
our very existence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of things that we, as a society, do are directly or indirectly inspired by
sex. We were taught, rather preached with sincerity that English films are a
matter of disgrace and can bring &lt;em&gt;Mata’s&lt;/em&gt; (the Hindu Mother Goddess’) curse upon
us. Problems started for my mother when Indian advertisements stared getting
liberal with sex as well. She was then left with little choice but to accept her
defeat, while commenting on how Indian culture was getting ‘corrupted’. As is
the norm in India, my parents never talked about sex in front of me, and as I
grew up they started keeping their bedroom door open most of the time, except at
night, so as to not arouse any suspicion in their growing child’s mind! And this
isn’t just the case with families that have children, rather with any family
where there are people besides the couple live. We are a sex hungry nation, lewd
staring in buses and public places are a testimony to that, and yet we continue
with this all-prevailing diktat of silence no matter where we go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this diktat has a silver lining to it and we must not discount it. As sex
has grown to be the giant &lt;strong&gt;taboo&lt;/strong&gt; of Indian society, it has become all the
more &lt;strong&gt;pleasurable&lt;/strong&gt; to consume. Coyness has turned out to be more of a boon
than a bane for most couples around the nation and for one simple reason:
&lt;em&gt;forbidden fruit tastes better&lt;/em&gt;. Society, as a whole, sees sex as immoral. No
one quite imagines that the couple they randomly passed by on the street
actually has sex or to be more precise, one cannot picture them doing it. What
this does psychologically is that it makes one’s intimacy with their partner
ever so special. They choose to remain oblivious of sex happening in any place
besides their own chambers. Couples and other couples collectively, mutedly,
gorge through their disreputable escapades thinking that they are alone in doing
it. And the less they get to do it, the better; because that preserves the idea
of immorality. If talking about sex is normalised, the details, no matter how
small or vague, would start to come forward and one would realise what and how
they do it is the same as everyone else; which isn’t necessarily a bad thing but
it takes away that extra bit of pleasure which comes from the high of
&lt;em&gt;rebellion&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the millennials who probably don’t ‘get it’ and are scratching their heads
thinking, “sex is sex; it is great even without the coyness”, draw an analogy to
when you look for taboo porn or something offbeat on the internet when regular
stuff just doesn’t do it for you anymore. It’s the same with sex, the more it
remains sacred and clandestine, the better it feels when done. This theory
explains to some extent why people have extra-marital affairs, it is that
clandestine factor that makes it all the more coveted and hot. This also
explains why India ranks second in terms of population even with a culture of
muted sexual desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory goes beyond sex, extending to almost everything that is forbidden by
society. The forbidden is a massive source of pleasure, no matter what, because
even when one is part of the chorus of society, rebellion against the same
society that one belongs to is enthralling, to say the least. Revolutions on any
scale are the greatest form of validation a human can enjoy. Although having sex
is not a revolution per se, but doing it, at the end of the day, after not even
hinting at the presence of one’s sexuality or sensuality throughout the day,
does have a massive sense of breaking free and disobeying our own sense of
immorality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the diktat is dying out with the emergence of Generation Y. And although
this brings in a different set of pleasures to consume (in varied manners too),
it will be regretful, at least for me, not to taste the pleasure that came out
of the weird furtiveness our previous generations displayed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Of the many things that India, as a subcontinent, has achieved or done, such as overpopulation, growing disparity between economic classes and the caste system, probably one of the greatest would be the writing of the Kama Sutra; and even though we have, as a nation, owned up to most of the country’s achievements, even the more bizarre ones such as child marriage, in case of sex we tend to walk right by it without even a cursory glance.  One might argue that such prudish behaviour is a result of uneven distribution of cultural capital, but I believe that’s an oxymoron in itself. I’m not here to talk about how such prudence came into being in Indian culture – that is a topic for another day. What I would like to draw attention to is the product of such prudence taking shape in the form of coyness surrounding the topic of sex in Indian society. Now, if you belong to an extremely liberal Indian family or reside in the West, you’re probably not aware of the coyness I speak of. But we plebs have felt it right from our childhood, when our mothers would, almost in a frenzy, change the channel if we accidentally tuned into some English movie channel with a couple kissing on the screen. This particular act of maternal care and horror brought about two things; firstly, a curiosity about the most basic and prevalent of human natures that would sooner or later manifest into action, and secondly, through this suppression, we were being conditioned into suppressing our very understanding of ourselves. If we do not properly accept and understand the psychology underlying sex and sexuality we become blunt to our very existence.  A lot of things that we, as a society, do are directly or indirectly inspired by sex. We were taught, rather preached with sincerity that English films are a matter of disgrace and can bring Mata’s (the Hindu Mother Goddess’) curse upon us. Problems started for my mother when Indian advertisements stared getting liberal with sex as well. She was then left with little choice but to accept her defeat, while commenting on how Indian culture was getting ‘corrupted’. As is the norm in India, my parents never talked about sex in front of me, and as I grew up they started keeping their bedroom door open most of the time, except at night, so as to not arouse any suspicion in their growing child’s mind! And this isn’t just the case with families that have children, rather with any family where there are people besides the couple live. We are a sex hungry nation, lewd staring in buses and public places are a testimony to that, and yet we continue with this all-prevailing diktat of silence no matter where we go.  But this diktat has a silver lining to it and we must not discount it. As sex has grown to be the giant taboo of Indian society, it has become all the more pleasurable to consume. Coyness has turned out to be more of a boon than a bane for most couples around the nation and for one simple reason: forbidden fruit tastes better. Society, as a whole, sees sex as immoral. No one quite imagines that the couple they randomly passed by on the street actually has sex or to be more precise, one cannot picture them doing it. What this does psychologically is that it makes one’s intimacy with their partner ever so special. They choose to remain oblivious of sex happening in any place besides their own chambers. Couples and other couples collectively, mutedly, gorge through their disreputable escapades thinking that they are alone in doing it. And the less they get to do it, the better; because that preserves the idea of immorality. If talking about sex is normalised, the details, no matter how small or vague, would start to come forward and one would realise what and how they do it is the same as everyone else; which isn’t necessarily a bad thing but it takes away that extra bit of pleasure which comes from the high of rebellion.  For the millennials who probably don’t ‘get it’ and are scratching their heads thinking, “sex is sex; it is great even without the coyness”, draw an analogy to when you look for taboo porn or something offbeat on the internet when regular stuff just doesn’t do it for you anymore. It’s the same with sex, the more it remains sacred and clandestine, the better it feels when done. This theory explains to some extent why people have extra-marital affairs, it is that clandestine factor that makes it all the more coveted and hot. This also explains why India ranks second in terms of population even with a culture of muted sexual desires. This theory goes beyond sex, extending to almost everything that is forbidden by society. The forbidden is a massive source of pleasure, no matter what, because even when one is part of the chorus of society, rebellion against the same society that one belongs to is enthralling, to say the least. Revolutions on any scale are the greatest form of validation a human can enjoy. Although having sex is not a revolution per se, but doing it, at the end of the day, after not even hinting at the presence of one’s sexuality or sensuality throughout the day, does have a massive sense of breaking free and disobeying our own sense of immorality. Sadly, the diktat is dying out with the emergence of Generation Y. And although this brings in a different set of pleasures to consume (in varied manners too), it will be regretful, at least for me, not to taste the pleasure that came out of the weird furtiveness our previous generations displayed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up</title><link href="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up" /><published>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up</id><content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up">&lt;p&gt;Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 237&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated UFC 237 saw a Brazilian takeover in the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, with the Fight of the Night being awarded to the epic war between then Strawweight Champion Rose Namajunas and ‘Bate Estaca’ (Pile Driver) Jessica Andrade, who demonstrated her superb strength with a vicious slam knockout to claim the Strawweight belt much to the delight of the Brazilian fans, who all together had enjoyed a torrid evening full of disappointment, with Andrade being one of only four Brazilians to taste victory on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil has always been notorious for showcasing undoubtedly the most hostile fans in MMA. Their unwelcoming spirit to any competitor from outside Brazil was exemplified best in Jared Cannonier’s victory over Anderson Silva in the frustrating co-main event. A leg kick from Cannonier to the knee of Silva ended the fight in unfortunate fashion in the first round, much to the displeasure of the Brazilian fans, who proceeded to boo Cannonier throughout his post-fight interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the match-up between Australia’s Alexander ‘The Great’ Volkanovski and the hometown hero José Aldo did not disappoint. With the crowd expecting the -145 betting favourite José Aldo to pull off a victory that would put him back in title contention, Volkanovski came into the cage relaxed and confident. ‘The Great’ Volkanovski quickly demonstrated why he is considered the Number 1 contender, dominating Aldo for all three rounds with leg kicks and strikes, earning himself a unanimous decision victory, extending his fight win streak to sixteen, and his record in MMA to 19-1-0. This leaves Volkanovski waiting to face the winner of Max Holloway versus Frankie Edgar at UFC 240, whilst José Aldo drops down the rankings to Number 3 in the division, potentially opening up a window for a fight with Number 2 ranked Brian Ortega.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event of UFC 237 saw ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas take on Jessica ‘Bate Estaca’ Andrade in a title showdown for the Women’s Strawweight Title. With Namajunas returning to the Octagon for the first time in over a year after recovering from neck surgery, many expected her not to perform to the same level as her incredible two previous victories over former Strawweight champion Joanna Jedrzejczyk. However, it appeared that Rose was as sharp as ever in the first round, completely out-striking and dominating Andrade for the first five minutes. An attempted but unsuccessful arm-bar submission from Namajunas exemplified the narrative of the first round, with the victory appearing to be merely a formality and an inevitability for the American. Nevertheless, with the backing of her hometown fans, Andrade showed her endurance and determination coming out in the second round pressing Namajunas up to the fence and working for the clinch in order to utilise her far superior strength. Once Andrade secured the clinch, she was able to perform a High Crotch Slam, living up to her nickname ‘Pile Driver’, dumping Namajunas onto the canvas and gaining the KO victory. Andrade’s knockout of Namajunas was only the fourth ever slam KO performed in a UFC title fight, and the first slam KO since Matt Hughes defeated Carlos Newton at UFC 34 in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fight, Namajunas cast doubt over her future in the organisation, hinting at a potential retirement due to the strain it was placing on her life and relationship with husband and coach Pat Barry. All MMA fans hope that this won’t be the end of ‘Thug’ Rose’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Andrade, she will now wait to see whether a rematch with Namajunas is the next step or whether she will face the likes of undefeated contender Tatiana Suarez, who holds massive potential and has been likened to current Men’s Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov due to her superior wrestling ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 238&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prelims saw wins for rising stars such as Tatiana Suarez, Aljamain Sterling and Calvin Kattar. Sterling, who is currently ranked third in the bantamweight division, defeated Pedro Munhoz via unanimous decision, with Munhoz riding high after his KO win over former champion Cody Garbrandt. Sterling controlled the fight with ease, utilising his striking and unique style to win the fight 30-27 on all score cards. This should set Sterling up for a shot at the title, unless Moraes is granted a rematch with Cejudo, in which case it is likely Sterling will face Number 2 ranked Raphael Assuncao.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calvin Kattar showcased exactly why MMA fans are so excited about him with a beautiful first round knockout of Ricardo Lamas. A clean lead left hook followed by a precise and brutal straight right hand ended the fight and catapulted Kattar within touching distance of the top ten of the division. There is certainly a lot on the horizon for the 31 year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tatiana Suarez displayed her talent despite a late rally from opponent Nina Ansaroff to earn a unanimous decision victory and set herself up for a potential title shot against champion Jessica Andrade. Suarez showed persistence and perseverance to secure a takedown early in the first, and proceeded to demonstrate superb top control during the 15 minutes to secure the victory, despite Ansaroff showing great heart in the third round with a great striking game on the feet, winning her the round albeit in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main card began with a heavyweight slugfest between Australia’s Tai Tuivasa and Bulgaria’s Blagoy Ivanov. Ivanov took the fight via unanimous decision. The Bulgarian dropped ‘Bam Bam’ Tuivasa in the first with a fantastic combination and would have won the fight via guillotine choke in the second had the bell not sounded. Despite huge shots from ‘Bam Bam’ threatening throughout the third round, Ivanov saw off Tuivasa to earn the victory with a confident performance that could see him potentially enter the top ten in the Heavyweight division.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petr Yan continued to show why he should be taken seriously at Bantamweight as he defeated Jimmie Rivera, dropping him twice, once in the first and then again in the second round. Rivera rallied to muster the performance he needed in the third round, however the knockdowns gifted Yan two 10-8 rounds, so only a stoppage would have given Rivera the victory. Despite landing shots on Yan in the final round, it was ineffectual as Yan claimed the unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aptly titled People’s Main Event saw two savages in Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson and Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone go to war at Lightweight. The opening round saw the two men stand and trade shots in the centre of the octagon, with Ferguson edging the round by outlanding Cowboy with significant strikes to the head and body. Ferguson’s endurance and pressure fighting style began to pay dividends in the second round, with Cerrone appearing to be slowly broken down by the accuracy of Ferguson’s punches and kicks. The end of the fight came shortly after the bell to end round 2, after Ferguson landed a late blow on Cowboy. Cerrone’s right eye was swollen shut. In an effort to clear the swelling he blew his nose, however, this only worsened the swelling and caused the doctor to call off the fight, awarding Ferguson the TKO victory. Whilst the fight did not end the way many had wished, it was in my opinion a correct decision for the bout to be ended despite protests from Cerrone. Ferguson was visibly upset by the way the fight ended, evidently disappointed in himself for landing the late strike. However, in his post-fight interview with Joe Rogan, Cerrone insisted that his injury was not a result of the strike. An anticlimactic ending but without a doubt one of the most entertaining fights of the night. ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson proved that he deserves a shot against the Lightweight champion Khabib Nurmagomedov by defeating Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone to confirm his position as the man to take on the winner of Khabib versus Dustin Poirier at UFC 242.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The co-main and main event did not hold such disappointment. Here we saw Valentina ‘Bullet’ Shevchenko cement her status as one of the most terrifying female competitors in MMA after defending her Flyweight title in style. Number 1 contender Jessica ‘Evil’ Eye was Shevchenko’s opponent in the Kyrgyzstani’s first defence of the title. Shevchenko showed exactly why she is one of the most devastating and feared fighters in women’s MMA, finishing the fight with a right head-kick that left Eye unconscious and twitching on the canvas for several minutes. In my opinion, Shevchenko has truly reached her peak, and produced one of the scariest KO’s in all of MMA history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Cejudo has arguably experienced the most meteoric rise in success in recent times. This success was furthered by his performance in the main event of UFC 238 at the United Centre in Chicago against Marlon Moraes. Cejudo looked to make history by becoming the first fighter to win an Olympic gold medal and be a 2 division UFC champion. In his way was Brazilian Marlon Moraes, who had been on a 4 fight win streak, finishing the likes of Jimmie Rivera and Raphael Assuncao prior to his title shot. With the vacant bantamweight title up for grabs, both men were plenty fired up in the build up, trading trash talk since the bout was announced. Having beaten TJ Dillashaw in his last fight, Cejudo leapt at the opportunity to become Champ Champ once Dillashaw vacated the title due to him testing positive for EPO in his fight with Cejudo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round saw Moraes take the early initiative, peppering Cejudo with hard leg kicks and strikes, easily winning the round. Moraes was on track to make the fight a one-sided contest, however Cejudo had other plans. ‘The Messenger’ came out in round 2 throwing hard right hands that effectively halted Moraes’ progress and Cejudo was also able to land some hard knees in the clinch, awarding him the second round. The third round showed just how determined and driven Cejudo was to become a double champion. Gaining top position on the ground, Cejudo landed devastating elbows and hammer fists on the visibly broken Moraes, which led to the referee stepping in and ending the fight as Cejudo became the 4th UFC fighter to hold belts in multiple divisions, following in the footsteps of the likes of Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Amanda Nunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This victory undoubtedly puts Cejudo in the conversation for the pound for pound best fighter at this moment in time. Certainly, the likes of Jon Jones and Khabib Nurmagomedov cannot be discounted due to the number of title defences from Jones and Khabib’s phenomenal 27-0 record. However, as Cejudo is the only athlete to have an Olympic gold medal on his resume, he has to, in my opinion, be included within the top 3 or at least the top 5 pound for pound greats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up on the calendar is perhaps the most anticipated card of the year. On July 6th in Las Vegas, UFC 239 sees Jon Jones look to defend his Light Heavyweight title against Thiago Santos, on a card that contains the likes of Amanda Nunes, Ben Askren, Jorge Masvidal, Luke Rockhold and many more. This card promises to be explosive and I believe it will be one of the best events of 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Eakin</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="mma" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League</title><link href="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League" /><published>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</updated><id>/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola">&lt;p&gt;A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for
the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition
in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning
whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically,
whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his
contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition
in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of
all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola
despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions
of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders
such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower
win rate in the competition than Guardiola.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manager&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;UEFA Champions League Finals &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;loss&lt;/span&gt; record (year)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL semi-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL quarter-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of seasons managed in CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL win percentage (%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luis Enrique&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jupp Heynckes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 -1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;98&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zinedine Zidane&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louis Van Gaal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;95&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;96&lt;/span&gt;, 10)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diego Simeone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carlo Ancelotti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Alex Ferguson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;99&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Mourinho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jürgen Klopp&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners
medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and
Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high
standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team
capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a
victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of
having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble
(Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had
sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of
the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester
United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force
that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively
starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first
leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal,
the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the
penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their
‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were
trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a
breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and
the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by
the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever,
again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s
former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with
Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to
play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the
defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to
pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper
Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this
tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg
out of reach for Guardiola’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria
as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time
losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74%
possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled
at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style
being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter
attacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the
understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize.
But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the
semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League
on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which
included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo
Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score
6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering
Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to
an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael
Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club,
were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the
young French side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120
million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these
costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at
Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s
premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham
Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming
performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy
Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical
decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City
largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals
stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a
fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal
could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was
ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning
that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year
of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third
season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals,
having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s
Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable
decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg
between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were
unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with
their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as
Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the
ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading
Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to
win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from
questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta
was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed
them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in
Madrid was incorrectly ruled out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s
success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A
plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way
or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John
Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only
one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped
mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply
luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the
woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only
have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches
higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty
in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have
been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired
straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no
control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end
results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to
be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and
whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade,
he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager
that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions
League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the
trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season).
Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European
campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those
expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City
have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that
has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time
for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League
with multiple clubs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>samuel.hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically, whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team. When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower win rate in the competition than Guardiola. Manager UEFA Champions League Finals win/loss record (year) CL semi-finals reached CL quarter-finals reached Number of seasons managed in CL CL win percentage (%) Luis Enrique 1-0 (15) 1 3 3 73 Jupp Heynckes 2 -1 (98, 12, 13) 4 4 4 70 Zinedine Zidane 3-0 (16, 17, 18) 3 3 4 70 Pep Guardiola 2-0 (09, 11) 7 9 10 61 Louis Van Gaal 1-2 (95, 96, 10) 5 6 10 60 Diego Simeone 0-2 (14, 16) 3 4 6 56 Carlo Ancelotti 3-1 (03, 05, 07, 14) 8 12 17 55 Sir Alex Ferguson 2-2 (99, 08, 09, 11) 7 12 19 54 José Mourinho 2-0 (04, 10) 8 8 16 53 Jürgen Klopp 0-2 (13, 18) 3* 4 6 51 Arsène Wenger 0-1 (06) 3 7 20 47 On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble (Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure.  After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal, the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their ‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo. Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever, again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg out of reach for Guardiola’s side. More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74% possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter attacking. Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize. But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final.  In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score 6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club, were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the young French side. Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120 million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals, having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition.  Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in Madrid was incorrectly ruled out. Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match. Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade, he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season). Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League with multiple clubs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review: The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and His Empire of Truth</title><link href="/The-Calling-of-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and His Empire of Truth" /><published>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Calling-of-History</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Calling-of-History">&lt;p&gt;The first thought that would possibly flash through a person’s mind, after reading Dipesh Chakrabarty’s &lt;em&gt;The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and his Empire of Truth&lt;/em&gt;, is the precision of the title—it effortlessly sums it all up. The book narrates the coming into being of ‘History’  as a discipline in colonial India. This is done beautifully through the character of Jadunath Sarkar – India’s preeminent historian – and his fixation with facts. Spread over a meticulously penned introduction and eight insightful chapters, it is a journey that concerns itself with historical research, and in itself is not a biography of Jadunath Sarkar. But it is based on about 250 private letters, exchanged from 1907 to 1952, between Sarkar and his comrade-in-arms, Govindrao Sakharam Sardesai. The book poignantly recounts the anxieties, struggles and tests of these two historians concerning the craft of historical writing during the initial days of ‘History’ in India. Chakrabarty draws from other archival sources and refers to anecdotes to project a very balanced assessment of Sarkar’s character, which is essential for the purpose of the book. I’m tempted to point out here that, interestingly, in doing so Chakrabarty adopts Sarkar’s technique of constructing characters of historical figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While mapping the birth of History, which was undeniably troubled, Chakrabarty draws attention to the interactions between its ‘public’ and ‘cloistered’ lives, and how each patterned the other. Such interactions concerned Sarkar and Sardesai who called for a ‘scientific’ approach based on &lt;em&gt;facts&lt;/em&gt; to overcome the limitations of histories emerging from the public domain. They adopted the Rankean model where truth is held sacred and history is to be written without compromising on facts. Chakrabarty identifies this as the most contentious issue between Sarkar, Sardesai et al, on the one hand, and the scholars of the &lt;em&gt;Bharat Itihas Samshodhak Mandal&lt;/em&gt; (Indian Historical Records Commission) on the other. There were clashes of ideas, bitter debates, personal condemnations and struggles for control over the Indian Historical Records Commission that, according to Chakrabarty, eventually charted the trajectory of the discipline of History and the institutions associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his lifetime, Sarkar’s positivism and dedication to truth made him resolute enough to accurately document the past - even the unpleasant things that could put one to shame. In fact, Chakrabarty observes, Sarkar was against any form of identity politics of nationalism that compromised on truth, leading to many intellectual skirmishes which earned him the wrath of anti-colonial nationalist historians. Chakrabarty rescues Sarkar from this ignominy though and sets forth to bring out the patriot in him. Sarkar was no doubt a patriot, but not an anti-colonial nationalist. Chakrabarty elaborates, if Ranke intended to serve God, Sarkar’s mission was to serve his nation by writing ‘scientific’ history. Sarkar believed such history writing was the first step towards national development. He recognised not only the glories but also the tragedies and unpleasant facts of the past that would facilitate the building of a strong nation. And for this, Sarkar was of the opinion that the historians needed to be of ‘strong character’. Here, Chakrabarty makes an interesting intervention. He identifies ‘strong character’ as a crucial component of Sarkar’s historical method and notes that, undeniably a man of strong character, Sarkar himself was a part of his method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter deserves a special mention as it is distinct in style as compared to the rest of the book. It is in the form of an imaginary dialogue between Sarkar and the author. It is an imaginary conversation between two historians of two generations having distinct understandings of History. What Chakrabarty does brilliantly is, by staging a dialogue between the two, he reconstructs the character of Sarkar and clarifies Sarkar’s method of history writing and patriotism. The chapter is masterfully crafted and one feels as if a live interview of Sarkar is being taken by the author. Though the two do not see eye-to-eye during the course of this imagined conversation, one feels that there is an attempt to resurrect Sarkar as a historian, and herein lies the skill of the author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final analysis, it seems, the spirit of Sarkar hovers over Chakrabarty who adopts Sarkar’s method of history writing in this book. Drawing from archival sources and remaining faithful to facts, both pleasant and unpleasant, the author sketches a balanced character of Sarkar to tell a larger story—a technique Sarkar fought for throughout his life. While doing so, the author emphasises that Sarkar was a child of the Empire and many of its abstract ideals shaped his ideas. But one wonders whether it would have been more helpful for the readers to conjure a clearer image of Sarkar and understand his ideas better, if Chakrabarty took recourse to the category of class, delving more into Sarkar’s Bengali middle-class location rather than making a couple of passing references. This absence, intentional or otherwise, strikes one particularly when he recalls Chakrabarty’s use of what he classifies as Bengali middle-class material in his more famous &lt;em&gt;*Provincializing Europe&lt;/em&gt;: Postcolonial Thought and Historical Difference&lt;em&gt;, and when one reads his article ‘Limits of Bourgeois Model?’ in Sanjay Joshi’s *The Middle Class in Colonial India&lt;/em&gt;. The point here is not to relate these works of Chakrabarty with the book, but to remind the readers of his authoritative understanding of the Bengali middle-class psyche, as evident from most of his works, and emphasise that they would have benefited more had Chakrabarty elaborated on Jadunath Sarkar’s Bengali middle-class position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before concluding this review let us not miss out on something interesting. Two eminent scholars of South Asian origin, namely Dipesh Chakrabarty and Bhikhu Parekh came up with two fascinating books in 2015. Chakrabarty’s book is the one being reviewed here and Bhikhu Parekh’s is &lt;em&gt;Debating India: Essays on Indian Political Discourse&lt;/em&gt;, a collection of essays written over a span of twenty years. The two books have undoubtedly different themes yet after reading these, one will be compelled to locate commonalities. Both these books focus on debates from the past taking place in India while strongly reflecting on the idea of truth. Also, Chakrabarty’s work, based primarily on letters exchanged privately between two friends, gives us a glimpse of the nature of their friendship, and Parekh’s book has an exclusive chapter on friendship and its different levels and forms. Furthermore, both have taken recourse to a not so common technique of writing dialogically in a chapter in their respective books—Chakrabarty has a chapter in the form of an interview and Parekh has one in the form of letters. It leaves one wondering whether these two scholars were themselves in conversation with each other while working on their respective books! Even if history may not repeat itself, historians certainly seem to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The first thought that would possibly flash through a person’s mind, after reading Dipesh Chakrabarty’s The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and his Empire of Truth, is the precision of the title—it effortlessly sums it all up. The book narrates the coming into being of ‘History’ as a discipline in colonial India. This is done beautifully through the character of Jadunath Sarkar – India’s preeminent historian – and his fixation with facts. Spread over a meticulously penned introduction and eight insightful chapters, it is a journey that concerns itself with historical research, and in itself is not a biography of Jadunath Sarkar. But it is based on about 250 private letters, exchanged from 1907 to 1952, between Sarkar and his comrade-in-arms, Govindrao Sakharam Sardesai. The book poignantly recounts the anxieties, struggles and tests of these two historians concerning the craft of historical writing during the initial days of ‘History’ in India. Chakrabarty draws from other archival sources and refers to anecdotes to project a very balanced assessment of Sarkar’s character, which is essential for the purpose of the book. I’m tempted to point out here that, interestingly, in doing so Chakrabarty adopts Sarkar’s technique of constructing characters of historical figures.</summary></entry></feed>