<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-09-14T14:06:52+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Art for Thought</title><link href="/Art-for-Thought" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art for Thought" /><published>2021-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Art-for-Thought</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Art-for-Thought">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It would be a no-brainer today to say that the world is lacking in beauty and happiness. COVID-19 has wreaked havoc on our lives. So many people have lost their jobs. So many people have succumbed to the plague. So much despair colours the air. In all of this turmoil, it is not only easy to believe that there is no light at the end of the tunnel but also stupid to think that happiness can be more than a dream. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, we know that we cannot give in to the demons that beset the path of our whole species. We already know that we must give ourselves hope. For without hope there can be no survival. But the question is how? How can we overcome our human limitations? How do we convince a mind so affected by malaise to believe in a better tomorrow? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The answer lies in art. Art is the yearning of the human soul for something greater than itself. Art screams out to every human being out there that no matter how small they may be, they’re capable of wonderful things. Art is salvation for our restless minds in these times, when our bodies stay caged within four walls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We need art not just in some magnificent Da Vinci painting, but in every-day items: small but necessary things which remind us that life is worth living and that all is not lost. It is here that Vantheshoe comes to our aid. This small start-up, run by a charming young lady, by definition, refuses to give up on the soul of humanity. With charming floral prints and vivacious colours on all kinds of items like handbags, phone covers, and so on, Vantheshoe reminds you that this pandemic cannot take away the beauty that is within you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;No, this is not just some pithy advertorial trying to sell you a product by exploiting your deeper unhappiness. Rather, it is a heartfelt article telling you about the work of someone who is genuinely interested in giving you something that you can truly cherish. We are here not to sell Vantheshoes’s products, but to tell you why at all they are worth buying. In other words, we’re here in true solidarity with the depth of human feeling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, we implore you to explore &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vantheshoe.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vantheshoe’s products&lt;/a&gt;, to appreciate the designs and the hours of work that have gone into making them. We will not ask you to buy the products, that would be presumptuous, but we will ask you to see for yourselves that in every mobile cover, in every handbag, every coaster, there is the soul of an artist trapped inside waiting to be adored by the right person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/vantheshoe1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/vantheshoe2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>.</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="sponsored" /><summary type="html">It would be a no-brainer today to say that the world is lacking in beauty and happiness. COVID-19 has wreaked havoc on our lives. So many people have lost their jobs. So many people have succumbed to the plague. So much despair colours the air. In all of this turmoil, it is not only easy to believe that there is no light at the end of the tunnel but also stupid to think that happiness can be more than a dream. Nevertheless, we know that we cannot give in to the demons that beset the path of our whole species. We already know that we must give ourselves hope. For without hope there can be no survival. But the question is how? How can we overcome our human limitations? How do we convince a mind so affected by malaise to believe in a better tomorrow? The answer lies in art. Art is the yearning of the human soul for something greater than itself. Art screams out to every human being out there that no matter how small they may be, they’re capable of wonderful things. Art is salvation for our restless minds in these times, when our bodies stay caged within four walls.&amp;nbsp; We need art not just in some magnificent Da Vinci painting, but in every-day items: small but necessary things which remind us that life is worth living and that all is not lost. It is here that Vantheshoe comes to our aid. This small start-up, run by a charming young lady, by definition, refuses to give up on the soul of humanity. With charming floral prints and vivacious colours on all kinds of items like handbags, phone covers, and so on, Vantheshoe reminds you that this pandemic cannot take away the beauty that is within you. No, this is not just some pithy advertorial trying to sell you a product by exploiting your deeper unhappiness. Rather, it is a heartfelt article telling you about the work of someone who is genuinely interested in giving you something that you can truly cherish. We are here not to sell Vantheshoes’s products, but to tell you why at all they are worth buying. In other words, we’re here in true solidarity with the depth of human feeling. Thus, we implore you to explore Vantheshoe’s products, to appreciate the designs and the hours of work that have gone into making them. We will not ask you to buy the products, that would be presumptuous, but we will ask you to see for yourselves that in every mobile cover, in every handbag, every coaster, there is the soul of an artist trapped inside waiting to be adored by the right person.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Women in Corporations: Breaking the Glass Ceiling or Standing at the Glass Cliff?</title><link href="/Women-in-Corporations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women in Corporations: Breaking the Glass Ceiling or Standing at the Glass Cliff?" /><published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Women-in-Corporations</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Women-in-Corporations">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While listening to Ava Max’s song &lt;em&gt;Kings and Queens&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;whenever the line ‘&lt;em&gt;If all of the kings had queens on their throne, we would pop champagne and raise a toast’ &lt;/em&gt;comes,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;a gush of enthusiasm runs through my veins and the thought of women leading everywhere leaves me in awe of the world that they would create. However, as I sit down to write this article today, contemplating upon the lyrics, I am left baffled by the thought of whether the problem of gender discrimination is really solved by passing of thrones or is there more to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Historically, men have been perceived to be natural leaders while women and other minority groups have fought for their way upwards in any organisation. Around only 8.1% of the latest fortune 500 companies are being run by women CEOs. Though it is a milestone in itself that should be celebrated, yet the numbers are not so encouraging.&amp;nbsp; This underrepresentation of women in the higher positions of an organisation is called the ‘glass ceiling effect’. But there’s more to the story. Even if a small portion of determined and strong women break the glass ceiling and demonstrate their innate talent of being a leader, they are faced with yet another patriarchal barrier – the glass cliff effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Recently, Blizzard Company appointed Jen Oneal as its first female lead. Though it would have been an encouraging move under normal circumstances, currently it is a testimony to the prevalence of the glass cliff effect. Why? The promotion of Jen was preceded by a big lawsuit of sexual harassment that the company is tackling. More like a sister to the glass ceiling effect, the glass cliff effect refers to the phenomenon whereby women are promoted to higher positions during a precarious situation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This term was coined by two researchers at the University of Exeter, Michelle Ryan and Alexander Haslam in 2005. Haslam and Ryan looked at the 100 companies that were a part of the FTSE 100 Index listed on the London Stock Exchange to analyse what happened at those firms before and after men and women board members were brought on board. The findings suggested that during periods of stock market decline, firms that brought women on their board were more likely to have experienced constantly bad performance in the preceding five months than those who brought men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The glass cliff effect assumes greater importance as it fuels the traditionally-existing stereotypes about women leaders. When women leaders are unable to perform under precarious situations they are dismissed as being not competent enough to hold positions of power. The effect is closely knit with the saviour effect. When women are not able to deliver results under a glass cliff appointment they are immediately replaced by men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, I believe there’s more to the glass cliff effect than just research backed by statistics. I believe the roots of the glass cliff effect go to the way girls are conditioned from the beginning. Apart from painting the picture of a damsel in distress waiting to be saved by a prince in shining armour, a lot of women are conditioned to believe that they are responsible for cleaning the 'mess' that has so far been created by dominant patriarchal characters in their life. The submissive and complacent attitude that is imbibed in girls during their childhood adds up to become a phenomenon like the glass cliff effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Why do women choose to accept an offer of being promoted to a higher stature if they know that the company is currently in a dangerous situation? Well, women as a group have to face a lot of struggles to climb up the corporate ladder. The offer of a C-suite position is just too lucrative for a lot of women to pass on. So, instead, they take up a chance and try to fight the situation; and if we look at the flip side, there have been a lot many instances where women have vigorously fought against the glass cliff effect, pulled companies out of crisis and proved their acumen. Mary Barra, CEO and Chairman of General Motors is one such example. When she was promoted after a controversial bail-out, the odds of her succeeding&amp;nbsp;were low. However, she defied all the odds and succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Though the saddening part still remains. Imagine that you’ve been trying hard to break through the glass and finally succeed. You let out a sigh of relief. However, as soon as you look around, you find yourself standing at the edge of a cliff. You are disheartened. This is what a glass cliff effect looks like. The glass cliff effect is a lesser-known fact however it impacts the lives of almost millions of women working in the corporate sector. Will women ever break out of these shackles or are there more glass barriers waiting for them?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shiksha Mody</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">While listening to Ava Max’s song Kings and Queens, whenever the line ‘If all of the kings had queens on their throne, we would pop champagne and raise a toast’ comes, a gush of enthusiasm runs through my veins and the thought of women leading everywhere leaves me in awe of the world that they would create. However, as I sit down to write this article today, contemplating upon the lyrics, I am left baffled by the thought of whether the problem of gender discrimination is really solved by passing of thrones or is there more to it? Historically, men have been perceived to be natural leaders while women and other minority groups have fought for their way upwards in any organisation. Around only 8.1% of the latest fortune 500 companies are being run by women CEOs. Though it is a milestone in itself that should be celebrated, yet the numbers are not so encouraging.&amp;nbsp; This underrepresentation of women in the higher positions of an organisation is called the ‘glass ceiling effect’. But there’s more to the story. Even if a small portion of determined and strong women break the glass ceiling and demonstrate their innate talent of being a leader, they are faced with yet another patriarchal barrier – the glass cliff effect. Recently, Blizzard Company appointed Jen Oneal as its first female lead. Though it would have been an encouraging move under normal circumstances, currently it is a testimony to the prevalence of the glass cliff effect. Why? The promotion of Jen was preceded by a big lawsuit of sexual harassment that the company is tackling. More like a sister to the glass ceiling effect, the glass cliff effect refers to the phenomenon whereby women are promoted to higher positions during a precarious situation.&amp;nbsp; This term was coined by two researchers at the University of Exeter, Michelle Ryan and Alexander Haslam in 2005. Haslam and Ryan looked at the 100 companies that were a part of the FTSE 100 Index listed on the London Stock Exchange to analyse what happened at those firms before and after men and women board members were brought on board. The findings suggested that during periods of stock market decline, firms that brought women on their board were more likely to have experienced constantly bad performance in the preceding five months than those who brought men. The glass cliff effect assumes greater importance as it fuels the traditionally-existing stereotypes about women leaders. When women leaders are unable to perform under precarious situations they are dismissed as being not competent enough to hold positions of power. The effect is closely knit with the saviour effect. When women are not able to deliver results under a glass cliff appointment they are immediately replaced by men.&amp;nbsp; However, I believe there’s more to the glass cliff effect than just research backed by statistics. I believe the roots of the glass cliff effect go to the way girls are conditioned from the beginning. Apart from painting the picture of a damsel in distress waiting to be saved by a prince in shining armour, a lot of women are conditioned to believe that they are responsible for cleaning the 'mess' that has so far been created by dominant patriarchal characters in their life. The submissive and complacent attitude that is imbibed in girls during their childhood adds up to become a phenomenon like the glass cliff effect. Why do women choose to accept an offer of being promoted to a higher stature if they know that the company is currently in a dangerous situation? Well, women as a group have to face a lot of struggles to climb up the corporate ladder. The offer of a C-suite position is just too lucrative for a lot of women to pass on. So, instead, they take up a chance and try to fight the situation; and if we look at the flip side, there have been a lot many instances where women have vigorously fought against the glass cliff effect, pulled companies out of crisis and proved their acumen. Mary Barra, CEO and Chairman of General Motors is one such example. When she was promoted after a controversial bail-out, the odds of her succeeding&amp;nbsp;were low. However, she defied all the odds and succeeded. Though the saddening part still remains. Imagine that you’ve been trying hard to break through the glass and finally succeed. You let out a sigh of relief. However, as soon as you look around, you find yourself standing at the edge of a cliff. You are disheartened. This is what a glass cliff effect looks like. The glass cliff effect is a lesser-known fact however it impacts the lives of almost millions of women working in the corporate sector. Will women ever break out of these shackles or are there more glass barriers waiting for them?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Far Past Outrage into Indifference</title><link href="/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Far Past Outrage into Indifference" /><published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference">&lt;p&gt;I could not read it again. I promise I tried. I would take a deep breath and try to ignore the prickling sensation behind my eye. But the pages would feel as heavy as boulders. So I stopped trying to read and flipped over to random pages to search for the sentences that would help the readers understand the reason behind my failure to reread one of my favourite books; &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Splendid Suns &lt;/em&gt;by&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Khaled Hosseini&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;You will find those sentences italicised as you progress through this article. I cannot sum up the despair that the women in Afghanistan might be feeling at the moment, in a thousand or so words, but I hope I can give you an inkling of what they are to face in the coming months.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Thousand Splendid Suns&lt;/em&gt;, this heart-achingly beautiful book can be interpreted in different ways. When I read it for the first time at 15, it was a love story between Tariq and Laila. When I read it for the second time at 17, it was a story about fate and sisterhood. Now that I wish to reread it at 21, it is a warning. A foreboding tale of what is to become of the women and children in Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The freedoms and opportunities that women had enjoyed between 1978 and 1992 were a thing of the past now --- Laila could still remember Babi saying of those years of communist rule, ‘It’s a good time to be a woman in Afghanistan, Laila’.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is based amidst the Taliban's rule from 1996-2001. While not free from the Taliban’s terror, women in Afghanistan had enjoyed relative freedom according to reports during the twenty long years of the US army’s presence. They were allowed to go to school, university and work. The US army’s presence was the distraction that turned the Taliban’s focus from oppressing individual liberty to battling the US forces. However, now with the withdrawal of the US troops, there is nothing to prevent the Taliban from shifting back to oppressing the women and children of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It was the raids, the reason why they were in the yard digging. Sometimes monthly raids, sometimes weekly. Of late, almost daily. Mostly, the Taliban confiscated stuff, gave a kick to someone's rear, whacked the back of a head or two. But sometimes there were public beatings, lashings of soles and palms.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns )&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the US has chosen to negotiate with terrorists&lt;em&gt; (&lt;/em&gt;The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008)&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; the rest of the world is wary of openly condemning US leadership’s haste in withdrawal and blatant disregard of the plight faced by the people in Afghanistan. The United States President Joe Biden had tweeted “our goal was never nation-building”; a statement that effortlessly pulled the curtain over their overt and aggressive involvement in Afghanistan and puppeteering of the Afghanistan Government. It makes one wonder whether their willingness to pretend that all will be well and their trust in the Taliban’s promises, stems from their guilt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban's promises for women's safety and leniency are being considered a positive sign by many. However, their promises of freedom of choice for women are an illusion. Is it freedom if the bounds are determined and restricted by the men toting guns and firing at any sign of dissent? Many may have adopted blind optimism and faith in the Taliban’s words, however, trusting an organisation that has a history of broken promises doesn’t seem to be a smart move.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broken promises aside, the Taliban poses a huge threat to women’s education. A &lt;em&gt;Human Rights Watch&lt;/em&gt; article reported that as of 2017, only “37 per cent of adolescent girls were literate, compared to 66 per cent of adolescent boys.” (&lt;em&gt;Afghanistan: Girls Struggle for an Education, Human Rights Watch&lt;/em&gt;). UNICEF had reported in 2016 that “&lt;em&gt;an estimated 3.7 million children are out-of-school in Afghanistan-60% of them are girls.&lt;/em&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;Education&lt;/em&gt;. UNICEF Afghanistan)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pre-Taliban statistics were attributed to constant conflict in the region, violence, lack of government support and infrastructure, and backward traditional practices and outdated ideas of women’s role in society. However, there was still hope that women’s education would be prioritised because the government was willing to let international organisations and NGOs take the lead in the education sector. The Taliban, however, has made no such proposals, and if their past actions are considered, they would not be open to any such interference. The Taliban’s rule in Afghanistan will only uphold the backward traditional practices and the medieval ideologies about women’s role in society.&amp;nbsp; This will lead to equal rights for women and their proper education being a distant dream in a country with over 14.2 million female population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another frightening statistic would be the data on different forms of violence used against women. The global database on violence against women reports that at least 51% of women have experienced Lifetime Physical and/or Sexual Intimate Partner Violence, whereas it reported 35% of women reported being coerced into marriage before the age of 18 (UNICEF global databases 2018). These numbers present a devastating picture and yet there exists the possibility that the data might be understated. A country like Afghanistan which was ranked 154 on the Gender Inequality Index Rank in 2015, with the ascent of the Taliban regime, is likely to fall lower.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the Taliban wishes to form a government. And it would seem that even this organisation is not immune to the scrutiny of social media. It is a fact that the Taliban does not have a good reputation. Whether it is because of their terror activities in other nations or human rights violations in their own nation, it cannot be determined. However, it no longer wishes to be seen as just a terrorist organisation. Consequently, we have read reports of the Taliban claiming to have changed. They promise that no longer they shall shut women up in homes or publicly flog them for not wearing a burqa. They have promised that &lt;em&gt;this time &lt;/em&gt;they would rule differently. Women may even be allowed to work and study. There would not be prejudice or violence against women, and they would be allowed to participate in society “within the bounds of Islamic Law”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“They want us to operate in a burqa”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;the doctor explained….to the nurse at the door. “She keeps (a) watch. She sees them coming; I cover” She said this in a pragmatic, almost indifferent tone, and Mariam understood that this is a woman far past outrage. Here is a woman, she thought, who had understood that she was lucky to be even working, that there was always something, someone else, that they could take away”. (&lt;/em&gt;Hosseini, K. &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Thousand Splendid Suns)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this how it will be from now on? Should the women of Afghanistan be grateful that they may be allowed the liberties that should have been their birthright? Should they beg and settle for scraps that the Taliban tosses at them to appease the guilty conscience of the global superpowers and the world watching from the safety of their screens abroad? Women will be the biggest victims in this transition.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Laila and Mariam of the book may have found an escape but millions of Laila and Mariam of this world will disproportionately suffer for decisions they did not make, and the world will turn a blind eye.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">I could not read it again. I promise I tried. I would take a deep breath and try to ignore the prickling sensation behind my eye. But the pages would feel as heavy as boulders. So I stopped trying to read and flipped over to random pages to search for the sentences that would help the readers understand the reason behind my failure to reread one of my favourite books; A Thousand Splendid Suns by Khaled Hosseini. You will find those sentences italicised as you progress through this article. I cannot sum up the despair that the women in Afghanistan might be feeling at the moment, in a thousand or so words, but I hope I can give you an inkling of what they are to face in the coming months.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A Thousand Splendid Suns, this heart-achingly beautiful book can be interpreted in different ways. When I read it for the first time at 15, it was a love story between Tariq and Laila. When I read it for the second time at 17, it was a story about fate and sisterhood. Now that I wish to reread it at 21, it is a warning. A foreboding tale of what is to become of the women and children in Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp; “The freedoms and opportunities that women had enjoyed between 1978 and 1992 were a thing of the past now --- Laila could still remember Babi saying of those years of communist rule, ‘It’s a good time to be a woman in Afghanistan, Laila’.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns) The book is based amidst the Taliban's rule from 1996-2001. While not free from the Taliban’s terror, women in Afghanistan had enjoyed relative freedom according to reports during the twenty long years of the US army’s presence. They were allowed to go to school, university and work. The US army’s presence was the distraction that turned the Taliban’s focus from oppressing individual liberty to battling the US forces. However, now with the withdrawal of the US troops, there is nothing to prevent the Taliban from shifting back to oppressing the women and children of Afghanistan. “It was the raids, the reason why they were in the yard digging. Sometimes monthly raids, sometimes weekly. Of late, almost daily. Mostly, the Taliban confiscated stuff, gave a kick to someone's rear, whacked the back of a head or two. But sometimes there were public beatings, lashings of soles and palms.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns ) While the US has chosen to negotiate with terrorists (The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008), the rest of the world is wary of openly condemning US leadership’s haste in withdrawal and blatant disregard of the plight faced by the people in Afghanistan. The United States President Joe Biden had tweeted “our goal was never nation-building”; a statement that effortlessly pulled the curtain over their overt and aggressive involvement in Afghanistan and puppeteering of the Afghanistan Government. It makes one wonder whether their willingness to pretend that all will be well and their trust in the Taliban’s promises, stems from their guilt.&amp;nbsp; The Taliban's promises for women's safety and leniency are being considered a positive sign by many. However, their promises of freedom of choice for women are an illusion. Is it freedom if the bounds are determined and restricted by the men toting guns and firing at any sign of dissent? Many may have adopted blind optimism and faith in the Taliban’s words, however, trusting an organisation that has a history of broken promises doesn’t seem to be a smart move.&amp;nbsp; Broken promises aside, the Taliban poses a huge threat to women’s education. A Human Rights Watch article reported that as of 2017, only “37 per cent of adolescent girls were literate, compared to 66 per cent of adolescent boys.” (Afghanistan: Girls Struggle for an Education, Human Rights Watch). UNICEF had reported in 2016 that “an estimated 3.7 million children are out-of-school in Afghanistan-60% of them are girls.” (Education. UNICEF Afghanistan)&amp;nbsp; The pre-Taliban statistics were attributed to constant conflict in the region, violence, lack of government support and infrastructure, and backward traditional practices and outdated ideas of women’s role in society. However, there was still hope that women’s education would be prioritised because the government was willing to let international organisations and NGOs take the lead in the education sector. The Taliban, however, has made no such proposals, and if their past actions are considered, they would not be open to any such interference. The Taliban’s rule in Afghanistan will only uphold the backward traditional practices and the medieval ideologies about women’s role in society.&amp;nbsp; This will lead to equal rights for women and their proper education being a distant dream in a country with over 14.2 million female population. Another frightening statistic would be the data on different forms of violence used against women. The global database on violence against women reports that at least 51% of women have experienced Lifetime Physical and/or Sexual Intimate Partner Violence, whereas it reported 35% of women reported being coerced into marriage before the age of 18 (UNICEF global databases 2018). These numbers present a devastating picture and yet there exists the possibility that the data might be understated. A country like Afghanistan which was ranked 154 on the Gender Inequality Index Rank in 2015, with the ascent of the Taliban regime, is likely to fall lower.&amp;nbsp; Now, the Taliban wishes to form a government. And it would seem that even this organisation is not immune to the scrutiny of social media. It is a fact that the Taliban does not have a good reputation. Whether it is because of their terror activities in other nations or human rights violations in their own nation, it cannot be determined. However, it no longer wishes to be seen as just a terrorist organisation. Consequently, we have read reports of the Taliban claiming to have changed. They promise that no longer they shall shut women up in homes or publicly flog them for not wearing a burqa. They have promised that this time they would rule differently. Women may even be allowed to work and study. There would not be prejudice or violence against women, and they would be allowed to participate in society “within the bounds of Islamic Law”. “They want us to operate in a burqa” the doctor explained….to the nurse at the door. “She keeps (a) watch. She sees them coming; I cover” She said this in a pragmatic, almost indifferent tone, and Mariam understood that this is a woman far past outrage. Here is a woman, she thought, who had understood that she was lucky to be even working, that there was always something, someone else, that they could take away”. (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns) Is this how it will be from now on? Should the women of Afghanistan be grateful that they may be allowed the liberties that should have been their birthright? Should they beg and settle for scraps that the Taliban tosses at them to appease the guilty conscience of the global superpowers and the world watching from the safety of their screens abroad? Women will be the biggest victims in this transition.&amp;nbsp; The Laila and Mariam of the book may have found an escape but millions of Laila and Mariam of this world will disproportionately suffer for decisions they did not make, and the world will turn a blind eye.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Combating the Menace of Counterfeits</title><link href="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combating the Menace of Counterfeits" /><published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits">&lt;p&gt;How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhinav Gupta</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp; The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp; The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products. There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp; From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp; Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp; Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp; Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp; The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp; The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp; Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too. The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp; Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp; This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp; In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status. While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp; The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp; Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp; Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp; Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp; High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp; In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp; There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp; For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp; However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked. The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp; Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp; Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Economic Case for a Federal UK</title><link href="/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Economic Case for a Federal UK" /><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK">&lt;p&gt;With regard to economic prosperity, the UK is one of the most divided and unequal countries in Europe. Over the past thirty years, London’s economy has accelerated ahead of the rest of the country, such that by 2020, average wages in Northern Ireland and Wales were only 70% of average wages in London as stated in the 2021 report titled &lt;em&gt;Levelling up the UK’s regional economies&lt;/em&gt; published by the Centre of Cities. This is reflected in a marked national productivity gap, with London having a gross value added (GVA) of £51,000 per worker, compared to £27,000 in the East of England, £23,000 in Yorkshire and £21,000 in the North East of England as suggested in the &lt;em&gt;Median annual earnings for full-time employees in the United Kingdom in 2020, by region&lt;/em&gt; authored by Statista.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These inequalities have led to a much-touted government agenda to ‘level up’ the UK economy. However, a crucial element of the policy debate in the UK that has so far gone under-examined is the fact that the economic difficulties of the North and Midlands of England have coincided with the atrophy of the UK’s system of governance. Whilst Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland now boast powerful regional governments, England has been left underrepresented. The introduction of metropolitan mayoralties in England’s major cities has gone some way in redressing this imbalance, though England’s smaller towns and rural areas are still without sufficient regional representation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic and political inequality are not unrelated phenomena. To level up the economy in the UK's poorer regions, levelling up of the politics needs to happen first. What follows is an argument in favour of federalising the UK government, so that each region of England, along with the three smaller kingdoms, has equal political representation, in the form of powerful regional governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem with Governing a Divided Country&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The socioeconomic disparities within the country mean both major political parties struggle to appeal to different factional interests simultaneously. In 2019, Labour failed to unite conservative, patriotic voters in their heartlands with liberal internationalist voters in metropolitan areas. For the Conservatives, however, there is increasing evidence that a chasm exists within their voter base too, but this divide is fundamentally economic, not social in nature. The recent Chesham and Amersham by-election delivered a bloody nose to the Tories, courtesy of centre-right Southern English voters displeased with a government agenda that seems to prioritise addressing the concerns of traditional Labour voters in the so-called 'red-wall'- namely, Brexit and levelling up. There is certainly a faction of not-so-shy Tory and Liberal Democrat-leaning voters that interpret levelling up the North and Midlands of England as nothing more than levelling down the prosperous South East, and they are unlikely to change their minds anytime soon.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the government deems bold policy agendas as high-risk strategies likely to alienate a generous portion of its voter coalition, the economic policy pursued from Westminster will resemble little more than the path of least resistance; a bland aggregation of the sections of public opinion least likely to offend. For this reason, the power to direct industrial and infrastructure policy must be taken away from the UK government and given to heads of new regional governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the strong divergence of opinion about economic policy (among other issues) within England, it makes little sense for the prime minister to have to make policy for people in North Yorkshire, knowing full well that people in Buckinghamshire will not like it. Instead, it would be much more prudent for a regional government in the North West of England to organise the levelling up agenda for their region, and for a separate authority to do the same for the South East. Under such a system, the details of important economic and infrastructure plans such as levelling up and the green agenda would not be jeopardised due to a change of government policy in Westminster, because the fundamental responsibility for maintaining such details would lie with regional leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of a situation in which greater devolution of responsibility is needed is the rollout of electric vehicles. Whilst the UK government has a target of achieving net-zero carbon emissions by 2050, Greater Manchester’s Combined Authority (GMCA) has a net-zero target of 2038. The largest single source of carbon emissions in Greater Manchester is the transport sector, making an efficient rollout of electric vehicles crucial to achieving the 2038 target. However, Greater Manchester does not have the power to ban the sale of petrol and diesel cars; this power still lies with the government in Westminster, which currently aims to ban sales of these vehicles by 2030. If this is pushed back to 2035, Greater Manchester’s 2038 target for net-zero will likely not be reached, exposing the reliance that local or regional governments have upon the UK government for achieving their own objectives. Such reliance would be eliminated if GMCA were given the considerable devolution powers it desires.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Federalism versus Devolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main criticism of federalism is that having a system of multi-level governments would lead to gridlock during times of disagreement between Westminster and regional governments. Critics of federalism often point to the United States, where the competing mandates of the federal and state governments made it difficult to coordinate concerted responses to the 2008 financial crisis and the COVID-19 pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, my reading is that a federal system would lead to far less gridlock than the current system of devolved parliaments does. In a federal system, the powers of the federal and regional governments are set out in stone, and cannot be changed easily. Crucially, the rights of all the regional governments are equal in relation to one another, and in relation to the central authority. This is not how the UK works currently; here, the powers of the governments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are not equal by default.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the Scottish and Welsh parliaments both now have the power to set their own levels of income tax, they were not granted this power at the same time, and the assembly in Northern Ireland still does not have tax-raising powers. Furthermore, England does not have its own regional parliament at all. This has made the relationship between Westminster and Edinburgh much more dysfunctional than the relationship between the federal government in Washington DC and the US state governments, the rights of which are at least codified in the Constitution. The confusion over different rules in the four kingdoms during the pandemic demonstrated the dysfunctionality of the UK system very well. The cause of gridlock is not devolution, but asymmetrical devolution, and the egalitarian nature of a federal system would eliminate the imbalances within the current UK order.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, recent history has shown that when new regional or local governments are established in the UK, their constituents prefer them to the government in Westminster. Labour ran a lacklustre and unpopular national campaign for the 2021 local elections, losing eight councils, but Mark Drakeford’s Welsh Labour increased its majority in the Welsh Parliament, and Labour retained its mayoralties in London, Manchester, the West of England, and Liverpool, as stated in the report titled &lt;em&gt;Combined authority mayoral elections 2021&lt;/em&gt; published by the UK Parliament.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic rationale for greater, symmetrical devolution is clear. However, radical diffusion of responsibility and power away from London cannot mean that the government in Westminster takes a back seat on levelling up the economy. Whilst regions must be free to choose their own economic future, leadership of overarching innovation missions must still come from the centre. First and foremost, this means making R&amp;amp;D spending levels equitable across the country as a precursor to radical devolution, which will not happen overnight. It also means taking more seriously the fact that the challenges of the COVID-recovery, the advance towards net-zero emissions, and yes, the levelling up agenda, are not separate challenges from improving regional governance, but counterparts to it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal UK would not be a utopia. It would not prevent disagreements between governments in different parts of the country, it would not prevent novel viruses from entering the UK on boats and aeroplanes. It would also not, in and of itself, make the country more effective at reducing its carbon emissions. Ultimately, our ability to reach net-zero emissions or level up the North and Midlands will depend not on which government is solving these problems, but which policies our governments implement to solve them. However, it is clear that regional governments, each responsible for the needs of only a slice of the country rather than the country in its entirety, would be more adept at choosing the right policies for their own respective regions than the far-away government in Westminster.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">With regard to economic prosperity, the UK is one of the most divided and unequal countries in Europe. Over the past thirty years, London’s economy has accelerated ahead of the rest of the country, such that by 2020, average wages in Northern Ireland and Wales were only 70% of average wages in London as stated in the 2021 report titled Levelling up the UK’s regional economies published by the Centre of Cities. This is reflected in a marked national productivity gap, with London having a gross value added (GVA) of £51,000 per worker, compared to £27,000 in the East of England, £23,000 in Yorkshire and £21,000 in the North East of England as suggested in the Median annual earnings for full-time employees in the United Kingdom in 2020, by region authored by Statista.&amp;nbsp; These inequalities have led to a much-touted government agenda to ‘level up’ the UK economy. However, a crucial element of the policy debate in the UK that has so far gone under-examined is the fact that the economic difficulties of the North and Midlands of England have coincided with the atrophy of the UK’s system of governance. Whilst Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland now boast powerful regional governments, England has been left underrepresented. The introduction of metropolitan mayoralties in England’s major cities has gone some way in redressing this imbalance, though England’s smaller towns and rural areas are still without sufficient regional representation.&amp;nbsp; Economic and political inequality are not unrelated phenomena. To level up the economy in the UK's poorer regions, levelling up of the politics needs to happen first. What follows is an argument in favour of federalising the UK government, so that each region of England, along with the three smaller kingdoms, has equal political representation, in the form of powerful regional governments.&amp;nbsp; The Problem with Governing a Divided Country The socioeconomic disparities within the country mean both major political parties struggle to appeal to different factional interests simultaneously. In 2019, Labour failed to unite conservative, patriotic voters in their heartlands with liberal internationalist voters in metropolitan areas. For the Conservatives, however, there is increasing evidence that a chasm exists within their voter base too, but this divide is fundamentally economic, not social in nature. The recent Chesham and Amersham by-election delivered a bloody nose to the Tories, courtesy of centre-right Southern English voters displeased with a government agenda that seems to prioritise addressing the concerns of traditional Labour voters in the so-called 'red-wall'- namely, Brexit and levelling up. There is certainly a faction of not-so-shy Tory and Liberal Democrat-leaning voters that interpret levelling up the North and Midlands of England as nothing more than levelling down the prosperous South East, and they are unlikely to change their minds anytime soon.&amp;nbsp; If the government deems bold policy agendas as high-risk strategies likely to alienate a generous portion of its voter coalition, the economic policy pursued from Westminster will resemble little more than the path of least resistance; a bland aggregation of the sections of public opinion least likely to offend. For this reason, the power to direct industrial and infrastructure policy must be taken away from the UK government and given to heads of new regional governments.&amp;nbsp; Given the strong divergence of opinion about economic policy (among other issues) within England, it makes little sense for the prime minister to have to make policy for people in North Yorkshire, knowing full well that people in Buckinghamshire will not like it. Instead, it would be much more prudent for a regional government in the North West of England to organise the levelling up agenda for their region, and for a separate authority to do the same for the South East. Under such a system, the details of important economic and infrastructure plans such as levelling up and the green agenda would not be jeopardised due to a change of government policy in Westminster, because the fundamental responsibility for maintaining such details would lie with regional leaders.&amp;nbsp; A good example of a situation in which greater devolution of responsibility is needed is the rollout of electric vehicles. Whilst the UK government has a target of achieving net-zero carbon emissions by 2050, Greater Manchester’s Combined Authority (GMCA) has a net-zero target of 2038. The largest single source of carbon emissions in Greater Manchester is the transport sector, making an efficient rollout of electric vehicles crucial to achieving the 2038 target. However, Greater Manchester does not have the power to ban the sale of petrol and diesel cars; this power still lies with the government in Westminster, which currently aims to ban sales of these vehicles by 2030. If this is pushed back to 2035, Greater Manchester’s 2038 target for net-zero will likely not be reached, exposing the reliance that local or regional governments have upon the UK government for achieving their own objectives. Such reliance would be eliminated if GMCA were given the considerable devolution powers it desires.&amp;nbsp; Federalism versus Devolution The main criticism of federalism is that having a system of multi-level governments would lead to gridlock during times of disagreement between Westminster and regional governments. Critics of federalism often point to the United States, where the competing mandates of the federal and state governments made it difficult to coordinate concerted responses to the 2008 financial crisis and the COVID-19 pandemic.&amp;nbsp; However, my reading is that a federal system would lead to far less gridlock than the current system of devolved parliaments does. In a federal system, the powers of the federal and regional governments are set out in stone, and cannot be changed easily. Crucially, the rights of all the regional governments are equal in relation to one another, and in relation to the central authority. This is not how the UK works currently; here, the powers of the governments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are not equal by default.&amp;nbsp; Though the Scottish and Welsh parliaments both now have the power to set their own levels of income tax, they were not granted this power at the same time, and the assembly in Northern Ireland still does not have tax-raising powers. Furthermore, England does not have its own regional parliament at all. This has made the relationship between Westminster and Edinburgh much more dysfunctional than the relationship between the federal government in Washington DC and the US state governments, the rights of which are at least codified in the Constitution. The confusion over different rules in the four kingdoms during the pandemic demonstrated the dysfunctionality of the UK system very well. The cause of gridlock is not devolution, but asymmetrical devolution, and the egalitarian nature of a federal system would eliminate the imbalances within the current UK order.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, recent history has shown that when new regional or local governments are established in the UK, their constituents prefer them to the government in Westminster. Labour ran a lacklustre and unpopular national campaign for the 2021 local elections, losing eight councils, but Mark Drakeford’s Welsh Labour increased its majority in the Welsh Parliament, and Labour retained its mayoralties in London, Manchester, the West of England, and Liverpool, as stated in the report titled Combined authority mayoral elections 2021 published by the UK Parliament.&amp;nbsp; Policies matter The economic rationale for greater, symmetrical devolution is clear. However, radical diffusion of responsibility and power away from London cannot mean that the government in Westminster takes a back seat on levelling up the economy. Whilst regions must be free to choose their own economic future, leadership of overarching innovation missions must still come from the centre. First and foremost, this means making R&amp;amp;D spending levels equitable across the country as a precursor to radical devolution, which will not happen overnight. It also means taking more seriously the fact that the challenges of the COVID-recovery, the advance towards net-zero emissions, and yes, the levelling up agenda, are not separate challenges from improving regional governance, but counterparts to it.&amp;nbsp; A federal UK would not be a utopia. It would not prevent disagreements between governments in different parts of the country, it would not prevent novel viruses from entering the UK on boats and aeroplanes. It would also not, in and of itself, make the country more effective at reducing its carbon emissions. Ultimately, our ability to reach net-zero emissions or level up the North and Midlands will depend not on which government is solving these problems, but which policies our governments implement to solve them. However, it is clear that regional governments, each responsible for the needs of only a slice of the country rather than the country in its entirety, would be more adept at choosing the right policies for their own respective regions than the far-away government in Westminster.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixating on The Male Gaze</title><link href="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixating on The Male Gaze" /><published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve seen&lt;em&gt; Emily in Paris&lt;/em&gt;, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “&lt;em&gt;Is it ‘sexy or sexist?&lt;/em&gt;’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook post&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/movies/bollywood/story/depicting-women-in-bollywood-222702-2014-10-11&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;India Today&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt; decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or &lt;em&gt;'the weaker sex'&lt;/em&gt; (Sana Ranaut from &lt;em&gt;Rajjo&lt;/em&gt;), 'Sanskari Ladki' or &lt;em&gt;'the traditional woman' &lt;/em&gt;(Amrita Rao from &lt;em&gt;Vivah&lt;/em&gt;), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from &lt;em&gt;Deewar&lt;/em&gt;) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from &lt;em&gt;Cocktail&lt;/em&gt;) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spectre&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Grown Ups&lt;/em&gt;, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: &lt;a href=&quot;https://talkiewood.com/2014/07/megan-vs-rosie-vs-nicola-who-was-the-best-transformers-girl-2/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl?&lt;/a&gt; (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (&lt;em&gt;Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman'&lt;/em&gt;) to men being okay with any colour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&quot;&lt;em&gt;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to &lt;em&gt;Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle&lt;/em&gt;, or almost every second rap song. As per a&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt;, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like &lt;em&gt;Chikni Chameli&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Hotline Bling&lt;/em&gt; or Jason Derulo’s &lt;em&gt;Swalla.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors&lt;/a&gt;) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (&lt;em&gt;The Phantom&lt;/em&gt;), Lois Lane (&lt;em&gt;Superman&lt;/em&gt;), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by &lt;em&gt;Downs and Smith&lt;/em&gt;, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lara Croft’s (&lt;em&gt;Tomb Raider&lt;/em&gt; series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.studiobinder.com/blog/what-is-the-male-gaze-definition/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;studiobinder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”&lt;/em&gt;, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;&lt;em&gt;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the first&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;seven women selected&lt;/a&gt; to join the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;VS Collective&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;’&lt;/em&gt; are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice is yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eeshita Verma</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">If you’ve seen Emily in Paris, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less. Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “Is it ‘sexy or sexist?’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is. The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point. The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting Facebook post I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’. Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it): An India Today article decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or 'the weaker sex' (Sana Ranaut from Rajjo), 'Sanskari Ladki' or 'the traditional woman' (Amrita Rao from Vivah), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from Deewar) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from Cocktail) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp; Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like Transformers, Wolf of Wall Street, Spectre, Grown Ups, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films. If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl? (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face). &amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get: “To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function. Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters.” As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for Transformers as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp; This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists and Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman') to men being okay with any colour. &amp;nbsp;&quot;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp; Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot; A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks. It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle, or almost every second rap song. As per a recent study, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp; The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like Chikni Chameli&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s Hotline Bling or Jason Derulo’s Swalla. Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy? Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge. Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry. The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point. Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (The Phantom), Lois Lane (Superman), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk. The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books. In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by Downs and Smith, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze. Lara Croft’s (Tomb Raider series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players. Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp; A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film Aladdin, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A studiobinder article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for Aladdin.&amp;nbsp; I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across: “Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities. Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men. Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him. The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter. Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’. Among the first seven women selected to join the ‘VS Collective’ are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything! Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it? Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them? Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate. Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now. It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off your attention. The choice is yours. Until then.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Financial Crime in a Disrupted Global Environment</title><link href="/Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Financial Crime in a Disrupted Global Environment" /><published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment">&lt;p&gt;Albert Einstein famously said: “&lt;em&gt;In the midst of every crisis, lies great opportunity,&lt;/em&gt;” and criminals got a little too inspired by the sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Since time immemorial, the financial services sector has been at the receiving end of various risks ranging in magnitudes. In contemporary times, there is perhaps nothing as disconcerting as the risk of financial crimes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Financial crimes have an impact on large and small entities alike and include a broad spectrum of violations, including internet phishing, money laundering, identity fraud, terrorist financing, and tax evasion. This trillion-dollar threat has profound repercussions, and combating it is an unenviable task for all participants in the global financial economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, COVID-19 has brought the world to the forefront of the fight against financial crime and led institutions to turbocharge what had generally been a glacial stroll towards remote working, the paramount concern remains to ensure safe access to data. Around the world, many have seized the opportunity presented by the crisis to exploit the antecedent vulnerabilities of an already distressed financial system, leading to even common concerns being exacerbated by extraordinary circumstances.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On a micro level, there are broadly two types of financial crime. Firstly, activities that dishonestly generate wealth for those engaged in the act in question. For instance, exploitation of insider information or acquisition of another person’s property by deceit, done with the intention of securing a material benefit. Secondly, there are activities where there is no direct involvement of such dishonest gain but rather protection or facilitation of such unethical rewards. An example of such an act can be someone who attempts to launder the criminal proceeds of another offence in order to place the revenue beyond the reach of the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Anecdotal evidence suggests a rise in financial crime, including money laundering and rogue trading, during the pandemic. Opportunities for perpetrating cyber-enabled crimes have also increased, and data shows an exponential surge in cyber attacks over baseline levels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Not even the most extreme scenarios would ever have envisaged a global lockdown with such high levels of online activity over such a period and subject to such high degree of uncertainty, as in the present time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mckinsey.com/business-functions/risk-and-resilience/our-insights/financial-crime-and-fraud-in-the-age-of-cybersecurity&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-08-15-Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment_image1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Translating the financial threat into quantitative terms, the United Nations estimates that the annual cost of money laundering and associated crimes is $1.4-3.5 trillion, out of which banks are only able to put a stop to less than a percent. Regulators have fined the world’s biggest banks more than $320 billion for breaches to date.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Each of the world's largest banks spends $1 billion annually on financial crime operations, with most of this amount being allocated to compliance rather than actively targeting the aforementioned criminal activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This considerable spending corresponds to an ever more growing onus on institutions to know precisely who their benefactors are and where their money is coming from. This situation also imposes enormous ramifications on cyber resilience capabilities at financial institutions and third-party technology service providers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The industry has been making progress towards adopting a common cyber lexicon, implementing a robust cybersecurity framework, and enhancing international cooperation. Banks and financial institutions are employing new technologies and approaches to detect financial crime, which is highly appreciated by regulators and consumers alike.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Banks can now automate and improve their Know Your Customer (KYC) and Suspicious Activity Reporting (SAR) processes using Robotic Process Automation (RPA), Artificial Intelligence, and other newer technologies; they can use these nextgen technologies and capabilities to review scenarios and spot money laundering, insider trading and other illicit activities via identifying suspicious behaviour, reducing the number of false positives and improving the response time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nonetheless, before they can use these technologies effectively, institutions need to upgrade their data and advanced behavioural analytics capabilities to lay a stronger foundation for success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mckinsey.com/business-functions/risk-and-resilience/our-insights/financial-crime-and-fraud-in-the-age-of-cybersecurity&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-08-15-Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment_image2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To assess other facets of financial crime, it is essential to monitor the growth in the payments space, which is primarily driven not only by a renewed focus on customer-centricity but also by offering a plethora of novel payment options, including digital wallets, cross-border payments, cryptocurrencies and other financial technologies which reduce payment friction and support transactions through the use of blockchain. These payment methods have brought forth new financial crime risks that existing regulations and infrastructure are not equipped to address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Owing to the new wave of digital transformation, vulnerabilities manifest in tandem with advancements in technologies. These are explicitly apparent in cross-border transactions and between multiple economies governed by a varied spectrum of lax to stringent regulatory requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Anyhow, the baseline expectations of regulators are that institutions must ensure market integrity, effective customer due diligence processes, and ongoing monitoring, specifically concerning counter-financing of terrorism (CFT), and anti-money laundering (AML) norms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As a consequence, the financial crime compliance dimension is on the cusp of transformation. There is increasing recognition of the need to innovate towards a more agile, efficient, and resilient approach to compliance of financial crime regulations and proactive targeting of criminal behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The offshoring of activities in financial services, either to captives or by outsourcing them to third parties, has also witnessed a turbulent trend during the pandemic. Many organisations offshore their AML and related financial crime prevention processes like transaction monitoring, alert management, and customer due diligence to managed service partners in emerging markets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The critical criteria for choosing a location for offshoring remains political stability, availability of competent labour and technology at low costs. However, offshoring hubs such as India have revealed pitfalls in offshoring/outsourcing models, owing to the stringent lockdowns that have prompted institutions to consider bringing their financial crime functions back in-house while aggressively pursuing their use of digital tools to reduce manual effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover, while offshoring may be cost-effective, it is often suboptimal for achieving the objective of preventing financial crime, partly due to the additional risks of complex and intransparent offshore structures, dispersed responsibilities, and lack of power to enforce technical control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Bank for International settlements (BIS) suggests that firms can reduce risks by taking steps to draw up clear outsourcing policies, and establishing effective risk management programmes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Despite all the challenges mentioned above, the pandemic has presented an opportunity for criminals to commit extraordinary amounts of financial crime; as regulatory pressures continue to mount and new entrants render the marketplace more competitive. There is a newfound prerequisite of the agility context of this industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Luckily, there seems to be newfound cognisance that a reactive response to crime and compliance requirements is not the way of the future, as it is costly and suboptimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There needs to be a proactive approach to detect, prevent and mitigate threats using enhanced data and analytics capabilities. The integration of fraud and cybersecurity operations is a crucial step, given their interrelation. To maintain a competitive advantage, financial crime officers need to pursue strategic investments in offshoring and outsourcing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Consequently, if this world presents criminals an opportunity amidst the crisis, it provides crime regulators with a more significant opportunity to improve and uplift themselves to emerge victorious.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Maanya Oberoi</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Albert Einstein famously said: “In the midst of every crisis, lies great opportunity,” and criminals got a little too inspired by the sentiment. Since time immemorial, the financial services sector has been at the receiving end of various risks ranging in magnitudes. In contemporary times, there is perhaps nothing as disconcerting as the risk of financial crimes.&amp;nbsp; Financial crimes have an impact on large and small entities alike and include a broad spectrum of violations, including internet phishing, money laundering, identity fraud, terrorist financing, and tax evasion. This trillion-dollar threat has profound repercussions, and combating it is an unenviable task for all participants in the global financial economy.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, COVID-19 has brought the world to the forefront of the fight against financial crime and led institutions to turbocharge what had generally been a glacial stroll towards remote working, the paramount concern remains to ensure safe access to data. Around the world, many have seized the opportunity presented by the crisis to exploit the antecedent vulnerabilities of an already distressed financial system, leading to even common concerns being exacerbated by extraordinary circumstances.&amp;nbsp; On a micro level, there are broadly two types of financial crime. Firstly, activities that dishonestly generate wealth for those engaged in the act in question. For instance, exploitation of insider information or acquisition of another person’s property by deceit, done with the intention of securing a material benefit. Secondly, there are activities where there is no direct involvement of such dishonest gain but rather protection or facilitation of such unethical rewards. An example of such an act can be someone who attempts to launder the criminal proceeds of another offence in order to place the revenue beyond the reach of the law. Anecdotal evidence suggests a rise in financial crime, including money laundering and rogue trading, during the pandemic. Opportunities for perpetrating cyber-enabled crimes have also increased, and data shows an exponential surge in cyber attacks over baseline levels.&amp;nbsp; Not even the most extreme scenarios would ever have envisaged a global lockdown with such high levels of online activity over such a period and subject to such high degree of uncertainty, as in the present time.&amp;nbsp; Translating the financial threat into quantitative terms, the United Nations estimates that the annual cost of money laundering and associated crimes is $1.4-3.5 trillion, out of which banks are only able to put a stop to less than a percent. Regulators have fined the world’s biggest banks more than $320 billion for breaches to date.&amp;nbsp; Each of the world's largest banks spends $1 billion annually on financial crime operations, with most of this amount being allocated to compliance rather than actively targeting the aforementioned criminal activities.&amp;nbsp; This considerable spending corresponds to an ever more growing onus on institutions to know precisely who their benefactors are and where their money is coming from. This situation also imposes enormous ramifications on cyber resilience capabilities at financial institutions and third-party technology service providers.&amp;nbsp; The industry has been making progress towards adopting a common cyber lexicon, implementing a robust cybersecurity framework, and enhancing international cooperation. Banks and financial institutions are employing new technologies and approaches to detect financial crime, which is highly appreciated by regulators and consumers alike.&amp;nbsp; Banks can now automate and improve their Know Your Customer (KYC) and Suspicious Activity Reporting (SAR) processes using Robotic Process Automation (RPA), Artificial Intelligence, and other newer technologies; they can use these nextgen technologies and capabilities to review scenarios and spot money laundering, insider trading and other illicit activities via identifying suspicious behaviour, reducing the number of false positives and improving the response time.&amp;nbsp; Nonetheless, before they can use these technologies effectively, institutions need to upgrade their data and advanced behavioural analytics capabilities to lay a stronger foundation for success. To assess other facets of financial crime, it is essential to monitor the growth in the payments space, which is primarily driven not only by a renewed focus on customer-centricity but also by offering a plethora of novel payment options, including digital wallets, cross-border payments, cryptocurrencies and other financial technologies which reduce payment friction and support transactions through the use of blockchain. These payment methods have brought forth new financial crime risks that existing regulations and infrastructure are not equipped to address. Owing to the new wave of digital transformation, vulnerabilities manifest in tandem with advancements in technologies. These are explicitly apparent in cross-border transactions and between multiple economies governed by a varied spectrum of lax to stringent regulatory requirements. Anyhow, the baseline expectations of regulators are that institutions must ensure market integrity, effective customer due diligence processes, and ongoing monitoring, specifically concerning counter-financing of terrorism (CFT), and anti-money laundering (AML) norms.&amp;nbsp; As a consequence, the financial crime compliance dimension is on the cusp of transformation. There is increasing recognition of the need to innovate towards a more agile, efficient, and resilient approach to compliance of financial crime regulations and proactive targeting of criminal behaviour. The offshoring of activities in financial services, either to captives or by outsourcing them to third parties, has also witnessed a turbulent trend during the pandemic. Many organisations offshore their AML and related financial crime prevention processes like transaction monitoring, alert management, and customer due diligence to managed service partners in emerging markets.&amp;nbsp; The critical criteria for choosing a location for offshoring remains political stability, availability of competent labour and technology at low costs. However, offshoring hubs such as India have revealed pitfalls in offshoring/outsourcing models, owing to the stringent lockdowns that have prompted institutions to consider bringing their financial crime functions back in-house while aggressively pursuing their use of digital tools to reduce manual effort. Moreover, while offshoring may be cost-effective, it is often suboptimal for achieving the objective of preventing financial crime, partly due to the additional risks of complex and intransparent offshore structures, dispersed responsibilities, and lack of power to enforce technical control. The Bank for International settlements (BIS) suggests that firms can reduce risks by taking steps to draw up clear outsourcing policies, and establishing effective risk management programmes.&amp;nbsp; Despite all the challenges mentioned above, the pandemic has presented an opportunity for criminals to commit extraordinary amounts of financial crime; as regulatory pressures continue to mount and new entrants render the marketplace more competitive. There is a newfound prerequisite of the agility context of this industry.&amp;nbsp; Luckily, there seems to be newfound cognisance that a reactive response to crime and compliance requirements is not the way of the future, as it is costly and suboptimal. There needs to be a proactive approach to detect, prevent and mitigate threats using enhanced data and analytics capabilities. The integration of fraud and cybersecurity operations is a crucial step, given their interrelation. To maintain a competitive advantage, financial crime officers need to pursue strategic investments in offshoring and outsourcing. Consequently, if this world presents criminals an opportunity amidst the crisis, it provides crime regulators with a more significant opportunity to improve and uplift themselves to emerge victorious.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kickstarting Revival: The Battered Indian Economy</title><link href="/Kickstarting-Revival-The-Battered-Indian-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kickstarting Revival: The Battered Indian Economy" /><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Kickstarting-Revival-The-Battered-Indian-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Kickstarting-Revival-The-Battered-Indian-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Oxygen cylinders, hospital beds, exhausted crematoriums and medicines weren’t the mere struggles that India faced when the second wave of COVID-19, disguised as the tsunami, struck India. What was ravaged too was the Indian economy, which was already struggling to find a grip after it was derailed in the first wave.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There was no national lockdown imposed this time, keeping in mind the ramifications it could have generated on revenue and livelihood. The government was not in a position to politically afford another labour migration like in 2020.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, individual states were forced to impose a lockdown which caused India to lose $8 billion per week in May 2021.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decoding the Slowdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As per S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings, several companies have revised their growth estimate from 11% at the beginning of 2021 to 8%. It is vital to note that the Indian Economy will experience a loss of&amp;nbsp; ₹6-6.7 trillion by this fall of 3% in growth estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The second wave induced shutdown resulted in an unemployment rate of 17.4% and 13.5% in urban and rural areas respectively. As per the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), almost nine million salaried jobs were lost between February, 2021- April, 2021.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In addition to the already alarming situation, 97% of Indian households witnessed a tremendous fall in their incomes. Owing to the tremors felt by the Indian economy in 2020, people have started moving back to agricultural activities and are being forced into disguised unemployment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Lack of demand, the root cause of this economic mire, has continuously missed the eyes of the government. The choked sales of fast-moving consumer goods (FMCG), consumer durable goods, apparel, footwear and car sales that witnessed a dip of 25% have contributed to the degrowth of India’s GDP.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prescription for Revival&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India finds itself in a dual set of challenges. On one hand, it strives to swim its way through the crisis at hand and on the other, it needs to build a stronger exchequer for long term growth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To begin with, providing the jobless with financial assistance should be the stepping stone. The states are struggling to keep up with the inflation rate while they lend a helping hand. The Central government should come forward and pay the due GST compensations that it owes to the states, amounting to ₹ 63,000 crores, as it shall ease the financial strain of states.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The time calls for a sector-specific approach to be adopted by the policymakers in the Central government. Identification of sectors that are struggling to keep their heads above the water should be the first step in this direction. The stressed sectors like automobile, retail, tourism and Micro Small and Medium Enterprises (MSMEs) should receive targeted stimulus.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another crucial step for pushing towards equitable growth is restoring employment by kick-starting the infrastructure projects that have been halted due to the pandemic. Additionally, the multi-billion developmental projects shall help companies generate revenue and in turn enable individuals to pay their bills.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Reserve Bank of India has done its job by managing the liquidity. The ball to support the entrepreneurs is in the Central government’s court now.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Monitoring the price movement of top 10 raw materials being used by MSMEs and reduction of import duties on such materials should be taken into account, to make survival easier for such firms. Furthermore, experts have time and again advised the policymakers to expand the Emergency Credit Linked Guarantee Scheme (ECLGS) from ₹3 trillion to ₹5 trillion.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This might look like a 1991 moment for the Narendra Modi-led government, but the problem at hand is grave and far more complex. In 1991, the Indian economy was already in the growth momentum owing to the aggressive expansionary policy followed in the previous decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, this time, the economy was already experiencing negative growth since 2016, and 2020-21 brought itself not only a GDP contraction of 7-8%&amp;nbsp; but also a humanitarian crisis. Such a scenario cannot possibly be solved by simple policy tools.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the present scenario, the government must adopt a step-by-step approach to reform, especially because of the limited resources available to it. Speeding-up vaccinations should be on the priority list, as this will result in the revival of contact-based services like hospitality and tourism, which contribute a major chunk to India’s GDP.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This must be followed by increased government spending. The National Infrastructure Pipeline released by the government in 2019, which outlined capital expenditure worth ₹120 trillion over a period of five years, needs to be accelerated. This project can be easily accommodated, despite the government running deficits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A fantastic sector, to begin with, is healthcare. This has been the talk for many years and the pandemic has exacerbated the importance of a robust healthcare sector. Initiating development in this sector by building well-equipped hospitals across the 700 districts of the country will boost employment and revenue generation by many folds.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The middle-class of the Indian economy is the driver of consumption-demand. The pandemic has resulted in a lack of money in their hands, thus bringing the demand-driven economy to a screeching halt. The first wave resulted in 32 million Indians being pushed out of the middle class.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Why is this a cause of concern?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A middle-class person in India is defined with an income between ₹724 to ₹1,449 per day, and even this meagre income-earning group has shrunk by one-third. The government needs to provide tax relief to this class which will enable them to re-start their consumption-demand expenditure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There is a dire need of imposing a progressive tax system in the country.&amp;nbsp; Reports suggest that the top 10 rich families of the country were able to expand their wealth during this time, thus widening the already huge gap between the rich and the poor. Many other countries across the globe have begun charging higher taxes from the richest class and have cut down tax rates for the service class.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The continuous boost to exports along with the above-mentioned measures shall help India meet the challenges while it medicates the deep-rooted wounds of the second wave. Well-planned and efficiently executed policies by the government will decide the future of India’s rebound after the second-wave. But the question obviously remains if that will actually happen or not.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Oxygen cylinders, hospital beds, exhausted crematoriums and medicines weren’t the mere struggles that India faced when the second wave of COVID-19, disguised as the tsunami, struck India. What was ravaged too was the Indian economy, which was already struggling to find a grip after it was derailed in the first wave.&amp;nbsp; There was no national lockdown imposed this time, keeping in mind the ramifications it could have generated on revenue and livelihood. The government was not in a position to politically afford another labour migration like in 2020.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; However, individual states were forced to impose a lockdown which caused India to lose $8 billion per week in May 2021.&amp;nbsp; Decoding the Slowdown As per S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings, several companies have revised their growth estimate from 11% at the beginning of 2021 to 8%. It is vital to note that the Indian Economy will experience a loss of&amp;nbsp; ₹6-6.7 trillion by this fall of 3% in growth estimates. The second wave induced shutdown resulted in an unemployment rate of 17.4% and 13.5% in urban and rural areas respectively. As per the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), almost nine million salaried jobs were lost between February, 2021- April, 2021.&amp;nbsp; In addition to the already alarming situation, 97% of Indian households witnessed a tremendous fall in their incomes. Owing to the tremors felt by the Indian economy in 2020, people have started moving back to agricultural activities and are being forced into disguised unemployment.&amp;nbsp; Lack of demand, the root cause of this economic mire, has continuously missed the eyes of the government. The choked sales of fast-moving consumer goods (FMCG), consumer durable goods, apparel, footwear and car sales that witnessed a dip of 25% have contributed to the degrowth of India’s GDP.&amp;nbsp; Prescription for Revival India finds itself in a dual set of challenges. On one hand, it strives to swim its way through the crisis at hand and on the other, it needs to build a stronger exchequer for long term growth.&amp;nbsp; To begin with, providing the jobless with financial assistance should be the stepping stone. The states are struggling to keep up with the inflation rate while they lend a helping hand. The Central government should come forward and pay the due GST compensations that it owes to the states, amounting to ₹ 63,000 crores, as it shall ease the financial strain of states.&amp;nbsp; The time calls for a sector-specific approach to be adopted by the policymakers in the Central government. Identification of sectors that are struggling to keep their heads above the water should be the first step in this direction. The stressed sectors like automobile, retail, tourism and Micro Small and Medium Enterprises (MSMEs) should receive targeted stimulus.&amp;nbsp; Another crucial step for pushing towards equitable growth is restoring employment by kick-starting the infrastructure projects that have been halted due to the pandemic. Additionally, the multi-billion developmental projects shall help companies generate revenue and in turn enable individuals to pay their bills.&amp;nbsp; The Reserve Bank of India has done its job by managing the liquidity. The ball to support the entrepreneurs is in the Central government’s court now.&amp;nbsp; Monitoring the price movement of top 10 raw materials being used by MSMEs and reduction of import duties on such materials should be taken into account, to make survival easier for such firms. Furthermore, experts have time and again advised the policymakers to expand the Emergency Credit Linked Guarantee Scheme (ECLGS) from ₹3 trillion to ₹5 trillion.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; This might look like a 1991 moment for the Narendra Modi-led government, but the problem at hand is grave and far more complex. In 1991, the Indian economy was already in the growth momentum owing to the aggressive expansionary policy followed in the previous decade. However, this time, the economy was already experiencing negative growth since 2016, and 2020-21 brought itself not only a GDP contraction of 7-8%&amp;nbsp; but also a humanitarian crisis. Such a scenario cannot possibly be solved by simple policy tools.&amp;nbsp; In the present scenario, the government must adopt a step-by-step approach to reform, especially because of the limited resources available to it. Speeding-up vaccinations should be on the priority list, as this will result in the revival of contact-based services like hospitality and tourism, which contribute a major chunk to India’s GDP.&amp;nbsp; This must be followed by increased government spending. The National Infrastructure Pipeline released by the government in 2019, which outlined capital expenditure worth ₹120 trillion over a period of five years, needs to be accelerated. This project can be easily accommodated, despite the government running deficits.&amp;nbsp; A fantastic sector, to begin with, is healthcare. This has been the talk for many years and the pandemic has exacerbated the importance of a robust healthcare sector. Initiating development in this sector by building well-equipped hospitals across the 700 districts of the country will boost employment and revenue generation by many folds.&amp;nbsp; The middle-class of the Indian economy is the driver of consumption-demand. The pandemic has resulted in a lack of money in their hands, thus bringing the demand-driven economy to a screeching halt. The first wave resulted in 32 million Indians being pushed out of the middle class.&amp;nbsp; Why is this a cause of concern? A middle-class person in India is defined with an income between ₹724 to ₹1,449 per day, and even this meagre income-earning group has shrunk by one-third. The government needs to provide tax relief to this class which will enable them to re-start their consumption-demand expenditure.&amp;nbsp; There is a dire need of imposing a progressive tax system in the country.&amp;nbsp; Reports suggest that the top 10 rich families of the country were able to expand their wealth during this time, thus widening the already huge gap between the rich and the poor. Many other countries across the globe have begun charging higher taxes from the richest class and have cut down tax rates for the service class.&amp;nbsp; The continuous boost to exports along with the above-mentioned measures shall help India meet the challenges while it medicates the deep-rooted wounds of the second wave. Well-planned and efficiently executed policies by the government will decide the future of India’s rebound after the second-wave. But the question obviously remains if that will actually happen or not.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Have We Judged the Abrogation Too Quickly?</title><link href="/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Have We Judged the Abrogation Too Quickly?" /><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly">&lt;p&gt;On August 5, 2019, India awoke to a bewildering, unanticipated change of heart. The Modi government abrogated Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution, which rendered the Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir ineffectual, revoked the state’s special status, and bifurcated it into two union territories: J&amp;amp;K and Ladakh, besides many other blatant measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I proceed, I’d like to clarify that I am not here to criticise what the government did, nor am I here to defend the Right against attacks by the Left, I am simply here to present the Right’s case rightfully, which yet remains undone and is long overdue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move comes off as unconstitutional to many, and in all fairness, it was. Prime Minister Narendra Modi's modern solution to the Kashmir problem was to turn the tables at a time when there was no state government to defy it. Critics of the move also reason that one cannot simply change the jurisprudence that governs a people, without them having so much as an inkling of the move. However, deep down, we would all concur, there is no other way in which this could have been enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might argue that indeed, there is no other way this could have been enforced because the move itself is groundless and insensitive, since it deprives the Kashmiris of their well-deserved rights. But I would like to point out that whatever has been taken away was never a right, but a privilege, for the humble reason that if it were a right, it could simply not be taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LPG, 1999 and the Abrogation, 2019: a Parallel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To strengthen my case, I’d like to draw a parallel from the archives of our very own history, the New Economic Policy of 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NEP, to sum up in three words, introduced Liberalisation-Privatisation-Globalisation, contracted to LPG. Before LPG, domestic producers enjoyed what can be described as an era of protectionism, a euphemism for ‘privilege’. The affairs of the outside world did not concern them whatsoever, neither did they deem it important to step out of their comfort zone, and justifiably so. Mind you, when I use the word ‘privilege’, in no way do I try to imply that it has a negative connotation. Whatever growth we have come to witness over the past years, can be easily credited to protectionism, which stood sentinel for years, providing the necessary time and space for the Indian producers to stand, fall and get back up again. However, every wave of privilege offered comes with a period of validity, beyond which the privilege has a negative impact. And so came the reversal of protectionism in 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though a sensible move, the reversal was widely resisted by domestic producers, and with good reason, because no one would ever willingly forgo their privilege. As apprehended, it also brought in a wave of destruction, a creative one nonetheless. However, in hindsight, Indians embrace the move, despite its disruptive nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I submit that the abrogation of Article 370 is much like the NEP: a reform that was long overdue and will benefit India in the long run&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I admit that it is not my domain to decide what is and what is not right for the Kashmiris, I would like to highlight a rather obvious proposition - the Kashmiris would dissent even if the move is right, considering it is their privilege in question.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, given the history and trauma of Kashmir, it undoubtedly deserved the privileges conferred upon the state (a separate constitution, a separate flag, permanent residency, bar on foreign ownership of property in J&amp;amp;K among other benefits, now revoked). But what is worth noting here is that Article 370 was originally supposed to be a ‘temporary provision’. As much as we might like to ignore it, one cannot live in denial forever, and keep stalling the decision to open up Kashmir’s economy, given that the privilege period has long lost its validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Good Part&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to LPG, since 1991, the Budget of the Union government has grown 19 times in size, the economy has grown nine times, and your income, five times. Empirically, poverty has descended, standards of living have shot up, as have capital flows and foreign investment. Visibly, the country is more integrated with the world economy, which has led to increased opportunities for all. In the words of the former Indian Finance Minister the Late Arun Jaitley,&lt;em&gt; “What decades of state hand-outs could not accomplish for the backward communities, economic opportunities have. Caste barriers are eroding and today we can speak of Dalit entrepreneurship in a way that would have been unimaginable decades ago and in a way that would have pleased Dr. Ambedkar. The geographical spread of opportunities and the increase in migration have contributed to nation-building.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now before I dwell upon the welfare the abrogation pours in, I’d like to elucidate how Articles 370 and 35A inadvertently entrenched Kashmir’s liberty and growth prospects. The former entailed rules defining permanent residency in the state of Jammu and Kashmir while the latter conferred certain privileges to the class so defined. A point worth noting here is that this residency does not necessarily cover all those who have thrived in J&amp;amp;K for the required period. To quote an example, West Pakistan Refugees, who came to India in 1947, could not enjoy the basic rights and privileges as enjoyed by the permanent residents, which is to say, being Indian citizens, they could vote in the Parliamentary elections, but being non-permanent residents of J&amp;amp;K, they could not vote in the local body elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employment in public offices, admission in government educational institutes, access to government scholarship, rights of acquisition of property in J&amp;amp;K are certain privileges offered to and reserved exclusively for permanent citizens. After all these years, whether these privileges still hold significance or not is an issue open to deliberation, just like the incessant debate on whether Indians lower castes deserve quotas in government jobs and institutions. However, coming back to my first point, it is certain that these are not privileges one will conveniently dispense with. Besides, just like J&amp;amp;K has a stake in the rest of India, the rest of India deserves one in J&amp;amp;K too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t come as a surprise that these privileges act as an impediment in letting opportunities flow into J&amp;amp;K. The healthcare, education, and industrial sector reforms have stagnated, since there is no impetus driving the private sector to invest in the state, and it’s only natural, given the bar on land acquisition for non-residents. There is no competition-driven growth since children of non-state subjects cannot get admission to state colleges and skilled human capital would not permanently migrate to the state. Among all the states, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir had the highest monthly average unemployment rate of 15% between January 2016 and July 2019. New investments declined by over 19 per cent in 2018-19 compared to the previous financial year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By rescinding the privileges offered to the chosen ones, the move will overturn the above-mentioned deterrents and bring peace and development, at least in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Deciding Trials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is completely valid and healthy to dissent and be concerned over something that renders your future uncertain, because the move is but a gamble. However, I don’t find it justified to judge something that may take decades to bring in the required change, within one or two years. This brings me to my last point - the issue of expecting concrete results to kick-in immediately. It has been less than two years since the revocation was effected, and while everyone is talking about how the tourism sector has been crippled and how the unemployment rate has been rising, what happened to patience? Everything takes time. And while there are contradictory sets of statistics available for both sides of the coin, I won't cite them, simply because it's too soon to judge.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, COVID-19 has been giving us company for the major part of the observation period. Yes, J&amp;amp;K’s statistics are saddening, but so are those of other states, some even worse off, and it is largely attributable to the pandemic. It all boils down to relativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cons and Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be it privileges offered and enjoyed, or the reluctance to give them up; the unpredictable nature of the action, or the uncertainty regarding the tenure one must wait out before it’s showtime - we have faced it all before, and we’re facing it again. Clearly, the Modi move is so much more than LPG, but in essence, both matters intend to place a frog out of its well, into the ocean, simply because it deserves to see and participate in what goes on beyond the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all objectivity, it would be unfair on my part, to not point out the defects of the move: it is far from perfect with regard to its unconstitutional implementation, clampdown on dissent (communication blackout, unforeseen curfew, internet shutdown), and most importantly, the reduction of the state of J&amp;amp;K to a union territory. However, while the move is far too complex to be labelled ‘right’ or ‘wrong’, it certainly deserves a moment of objective evaluation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I’d like to ask you the same question I posed in the title, and while I don’t expect answers right away, I’d like you to think about it. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eeshita Verma</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">On August 5, 2019, India awoke to a bewildering, unanticipated change of heart. The Modi government abrogated Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution, which rendered the Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir ineffectual, revoked the state’s special status, and bifurcated it into two union territories: J&amp;amp;K and Ladakh, besides many other blatant measures. Before I proceed, I’d like to clarify that I am not here to criticise what the government did, nor am I here to defend the Right against attacks by the Left, I am simply here to present the Right’s case rightfully, which yet remains undone and is long overdue.&amp;nbsp; The move comes off as unconstitutional to many, and in all fairness, it was. Prime Minister Narendra Modi's modern solution to the Kashmir problem was to turn the tables at a time when there was no state government to defy it. Critics of the move also reason that one cannot simply change the jurisprudence that governs a people, without them having so much as an inkling of the move. However, deep down, we would all concur, there is no other way in which this could have been enforced. One might argue that indeed, there is no other way this could have been enforced because the move itself is groundless and insensitive, since it deprives the Kashmiris of their well-deserved rights. But I would like to point out that whatever has been taken away was never a right, but a privilege, for the humble reason that if it were a right, it could simply not be taken away. LPG, 1999 and the Abrogation, 2019: a Parallel To strengthen my case, I’d like to draw a parallel from the archives of our very own history, the New Economic Policy of 1991.&amp;nbsp; The NEP, to sum up in three words, introduced Liberalisation-Privatisation-Globalisation, contracted to LPG. Before LPG, domestic producers enjoyed what can be described as an era of protectionism, a euphemism for ‘privilege’. The affairs of the outside world did not concern them whatsoever, neither did they deem it important to step out of their comfort zone, and justifiably so. Mind you, when I use the word ‘privilege’, in no way do I try to imply that it has a negative connotation. Whatever growth we have come to witness over the past years, can be easily credited to protectionism, which stood sentinel for years, providing the necessary time and space for the Indian producers to stand, fall and get back up again. However, every wave of privilege offered comes with a period of validity, beyond which the privilege has a negative impact. And so came the reversal of protectionism in 1991.&amp;nbsp; Though a sensible move, the reversal was widely resisted by domestic producers, and with good reason, because no one would ever willingly forgo their privilege. As apprehended, it also brought in a wave of destruction, a creative one nonetheless. However, in hindsight, Indians embrace the move, despite its disruptive nature. I submit that the abrogation of Article 370 is much like the NEP: a reform that was long overdue and will benefit India in the long run While I admit that it is not my domain to decide what is and what is not right for the Kashmiris, I would like to highlight a rather obvious proposition - the Kashmiris would dissent even if the move is right, considering it is their privilege in question.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, given the history and trauma of Kashmir, it undoubtedly deserved the privileges conferred upon the state (a separate constitution, a separate flag, permanent residency, bar on foreign ownership of property in J&amp;amp;K among other benefits, now revoked). But what is worth noting here is that Article 370 was originally supposed to be a ‘temporary provision’. As much as we might like to ignore it, one cannot live in denial forever, and keep stalling the decision to open up Kashmir’s economy, given that the privilege period has long lost its validity. The Good Part Coming back to LPG, since 1991, the Budget of the Union government has grown 19 times in size, the economy has grown nine times, and your income, five times. Empirically, poverty has descended, standards of living have shot up, as have capital flows and foreign investment. Visibly, the country is more integrated with the world economy, which has led to increased opportunities for all. In the words of the former Indian Finance Minister the Late Arun Jaitley, “What decades of state hand-outs could not accomplish for the backward communities, economic opportunities have. Caste barriers are eroding and today we can speak of Dalit entrepreneurship in a way that would have been unimaginable decades ago and in a way that would have pleased Dr. Ambedkar. The geographical spread of opportunities and the increase in migration have contributed to nation-building.” Now before I dwell upon the welfare the abrogation pours in, I’d like to elucidate how Articles 370 and 35A inadvertently entrenched Kashmir’s liberty and growth prospects. The former entailed rules defining permanent residency in the state of Jammu and Kashmir while the latter conferred certain privileges to the class so defined. A point worth noting here is that this residency does not necessarily cover all those who have thrived in J&amp;amp;K for the required period. To quote an example, West Pakistan Refugees, who came to India in 1947, could not enjoy the basic rights and privileges as enjoyed by the permanent residents, which is to say, being Indian citizens, they could vote in the Parliamentary elections, but being non-permanent residents of J&amp;amp;K, they could not vote in the local body elections. Employment in public offices, admission in government educational institutes, access to government scholarship, rights of acquisition of property in J&amp;amp;K are certain privileges offered to and reserved exclusively for permanent citizens. After all these years, whether these privileges still hold significance or not is an issue open to deliberation, just like the incessant debate on whether Indians lower castes deserve quotas in government jobs and institutions. However, coming back to my first point, it is certain that these are not privileges one will conveniently dispense with. Besides, just like J&amp;amp;K has a stake in the rest of India, the rest of India deserves one in J&amp;amp;K too. It doesn’t come as a surprise that these privileges act as an impediment in letting opportunities flow into J&amp;amp;K. The healthcare, education, and industrial sector reforms have stagnated, since there is no impetus driving the private sector to invest in the state, and it’s only natural, given the bar on land acquisition for non-residents. There is no competition-driven growth since children of non-state subjects cannot get admission to state colleges and skilled human capital would not permanently migrate to the state. Among all the states, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir had the highest monthly average unemployment rate of 15% between January 2016 and July 2019. New investments declined by over 19 per cent in 2018-19 compared to the previous financial year. By rescinding the privileges offered to the chosen ones, the move will overturn the above-mentioned deterrents and bring peace and development, at least in the long run. The Deciding Trials It is completely valid and healthy to dissent and be concerned over something that renders your future uncertain, because the move is but a gamble. However, I don’t find it justified to judge something that may take decades to bring in the required change, within one or two years. This brings me to my last point - the issue of expecting concrete results to kick-in immediately. It has been less than two years since the revocation was effected, and while everyone is talking about how the tourism sector has been crippled and how the unemployment rate has been rising, what happened to patience? Everything takes time. And while there are contradictory sets of statistics available for both sides of the coin, I won't cite them, simply because it's too soon to judge.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, COVID-19 has been giving us company for the major part of the observation period. Yes, J&amp;amp;K’s statistics are saddening, but so are those of other states, some even worse off, and it is largely attributable to the pandemic. It all boils down to relativity. Cons and Conclusions Be it privileges offered and enjoyed, or the reluctance to give them up; the unpredictable nature of the action, or the uncertainty regarding the tenure one must wait out before it’s showtime - we have faced it all before, and we’re facing it again. Clearly, the Modi move is so much more than LPG, but in essence, both matters intend to place a frog out of its well, into the ocean, simply because it deserves to see and participate in what goes on beyond the wall. In all objectivity, it would be unfair on my part, to not point out the defects of the move: it is far from perfect with regard to its unconstitutional implementation, clampdown on dissent (communication blackout, unforeseen curfew, internet shutdown), and most importantly, the reduction of the state of J&amp;amp;K to a union territory. However, while the move is far too complex to be labelled ‘right’ or ‘wrong’, it certainly deserves a moment of objective evaluation.&amp;nbsp; In the end, I’d like to ask you the same question I posed in the title, and while I don’t expect answers right away, I’d like you to think about it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy</title><link href="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy" /><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy">&lt;p&gt;Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1933, Mead wrote &lt;em&gt;Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies&lt;/em&gt;. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in &lt;em&gt;The Infants’ Department&lt;/em&gt; stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp; For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp; In 1933, Mead wrote Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in The Infants’ Department stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp; Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp; These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex. Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp; On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp; The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp; The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp; Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp; Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp; 'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp; Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp; Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp; All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry></feed>