<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-11-12T17:36:21+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Women of Ancient Egypt</title><link href="/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women of Ancient Egypt" /><published>2019-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt">&lt;p&gt;With the rise of movements like #MeToo and #TimesUp, it is abundantly clear to us that women have been and continue to be discriminated against across the world, whether it is in the most modern of societies like the USA or the ones that are not as modern like Saudi Arabia. Feminists say that women have been historically marginalised and their talents underestimated. They believe that societal structures and social machinery work in a way to favour men, disregarding women’s capabilities, preferences, freedoms or requirements. Today, the fight for equal opportunities and equal pay are not just limited to the efforts of non-males. Men who realise that there exists a disparity that needs to be rectified have started joining in. But have women always been subjected to the kind of treatment that is meted out to them today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common notion that ancient civilisations were in fact extremely backward when it comes to their social lives and societies. For instance, Athenian democracy allowed only adult males of the “&lt;em&gt;polis&lt;/em&gt;” to run it. Non-males were completely barred from activities like administration, security and so on. In fact, women were not permitted to own property. They were often excluded from getting a part of the inheritance as well. Females were not citizens of the &lt;em&gt;polis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scene in ancient Egypt was very different. Surprisingly, they were much better off than the Greeks and perhaps, some of the modern societies too. Now, don’t get me wrong; society was primarily patriarchal. But this did not, in any way, imply that women could not hold high positions in religious institutions, the administration and so on. They did own property and had a right to inheritance. Their words had equal weight as that of men in court. Besides, lineage was traced back through the lines of &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; parents. This kind of equality of treatment is possibly because of their mythology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egyptian mythology revolves around a fantastic brother-sister duo married to each other - Isis, the goddess of magic, and Osiris, the god of the afterlife. Astonishingly, Isis is the dominant partner in this relationship. She is often depicted as being extremely powerful and possessed of great knowledge. In fact, she was even believed to have the power to resurrect dead humans. In one of the legends, she brings Osiris back to life after his death, a feat that remains unimaginable for the rest of the deities, men and women alike. This was reflected in the social lives of the Egyptians too as women were often depicted as holding their husband’s hands and sometimes even protecting them. Besides this godly pair, there were several other deities; and male and female gods were equally abundant and powerful. However, some rather important positions were occupied by goddesses alone, unlike most other religions or mythologies. For example, the four gods depicted on the four corners of a tomb, symbolising the fact that they were entrusted with the job of guarding the tomb, are all female. The domain of healing also comes under a goddess, Sekhmet. Besides, the patron deity of cats, an animal sacred to the Egyptians, was female too - Bastet. And the feminine influence was not just limited to the realm of the gods: it penetrated the domain of humans too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of the high positions of administration were generally reserved for men, it is not unusual to find several exceptions to the rule in the case of Egypt. The women of this ancient society were certainly not exclusively stay-at-home mothers; they frequently engaged in several professions, some of which would have proven to be rather unorthodox in patriarchal societies - weavers, farmers, etc. The vizier was the highest state official after the Pharaoh. Nebet, a woman of great talent and importance took the office as early as Sixth Dynasty Egypt. She would inspire several other women to do the same. The first of the female rulers of ancient Egypt, Merneith’s reign dates back to the first dynasty. The highest positions in religious institutions were not exclusive to men, either, and thus, were often occupied by women, who did not necessarily have to be from a noble background either. Motherhood was very sacred to this ancient civilisation. Very often, mothers were honoured more than fathers and this found manifestation in their literature, scriptures and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest position that an ancient Egyptian could possibly hold was the position of a pharaoh. Egyptians preferred to be ruled by a woman of the royal bloodline rather than a man who wasn’t blue-blooded. Besides, whenever there was a crisis involving succession, no one really objected to giving the throne to a woman. At least fifteen great queens have ruled ancient Egypt and their stories are just as sparkling with tales of success as their male counterparts. Unfortunately our preference for a male-dominated history meant that their stories were easily forgotten or grossly misinterpreted or distorted by later civilisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular of these queens was Hatshepsut or Matcaray. After the death of her husband, she took over the affairs of the palace as the heir to the throne was far too young to take on royal responsibilities. Very soon, she took up the royal title of the pharaoh. Eventually, her daughter, Neferure assumed roles beyond that of a conventional princess, almost that of a queen. Hatshepshut happens to have been a very controversial figure in the history of Egypt because she found it necessary to wear a fake beard to make herself look more like a pharaoh and legitimise her authority. In fact, her statues that have survived the millenia distinctly show that her beard was fake. The fact that she was a woman was no secret. Many Egyptologists today suspect that several other pharaohs might have been female too. The 20 years of Hatshepsut’s reign was full of remarkable accomplishments - her temple at Luxor, Egypt’s tallest standing obelisk at the temple complex of Karnak, new trade contracts with Punt and military conquests that she herself headed, among others. Egyptologists believed that most stories about her, that were obtained from the scriptures on the temple walls, were exaggerations of what she did for her country for the longest time. However, we know today that she did indeed achieve everything that has found a place on those walls because of the various artifacts like cups of raisin from Punt and so on that have been found. Her existence was, however, unknown for a very long time. This is probably because the later pharaohs were ashamed of the fact that a woman ruled as the pharaoh and they believed that this affected ‘Ma’at’- balance. Scriptures were destroyed, temples taken down, obelisks demolished to remove all signs of her existence. Hatshepsut was however, never meant to be completely forgotten or to be the last female pharaoh to lead Egypt. She would go on to inspire several other female leaders of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsinoë, the second pharaoh of the last dynasty is much less celebrated and yet, just as charismatic as Hatshepsut herself. After the death of her first husband, she fled Greece to return to Egypt where she persuaded her younger brother to marry her. This would eventually pave her way to become the pharaoh of not just Egypt, but also the Greek Mediterranean. Arsinoë would go on to bring prosperity to Egypt like no other. She established trade contracts with distant civilisations like India and the Far East. Under Arsinoë, coins started being used and slowly began to replace the barter system. Being the intelligent woman that she was, she knew that she could use coins to establish her authority. Her face appeared on these coins, making it abundantly clear to all who was in power. Arsinoë was extremely proud of the feminine history of Egypt. In one of her temples, she is shown wearing a grand crown which is today the object of a lot of research. Her crown had several parts symbolising various aspects of Egypt. The red crown represented Upper Egypt and the fact that she ruled from the new capital of Alexandria. Two tall feathers and a bull horn represented Neferari, the wife of pharaoh Ramses II, who was known for her skills in diplomacy. Twisted ram horns represented Amun-Ra who also happened to be the favourite god of Hatshepsut. Finally the sun disc, often associated with the Old Kingdom and Hetepheres, the mother of Pharaoh Khufu, who built the Great Pyramid of Giza, completed her crown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous of all the pharaohs is probably Cleopatra. However, she is famous for all the wrong reasons - reasons that might as well be made up and undermine her talents. Cleopatra has absolutely no comparison. She is the first of the Ptolemaic dynasty (they are of Macedonian-Greek descent and became the ruling family after Alexander the Great’s successful conquest of Egypt in 332 BC) to learn the Egyptian tongue. She is known to be multilingual, having command over at least 9 languages. This greatly helped her in her administrative role. Remains of written declarations with her signature show that she was a very able and respected administrator. Cleopatra was extremely educated in chemistry, astronomy, literature and so on. She even owned a perfume factory and is frequently associated with several advancements in the alchemy of the time. Popular media today depicts her as a woman of unparalleled beauty who seduced both Julius Caesar and Mark Antony with her beauty and charm, leading to the notion that she was a characterless seductress. However, objections to her ‘character’ in ancient times comes primarily from Roman writers, who often objected to her reign solely because she was a woman. They claimed that she was responsible for several conflicts because of her ways. Sadly, they failed to realise that both Mark Antony and Julius Caesar had equal responsibility as Cleopatra in their respective relationships. People often question Cleopatra’s character and, yet, fail to do the same for Julius Caesar, who was married when he started his affair with Cleopatra and at one point, even refused to claim his son with the queen as his own. In fact, today most egyptologists believe that she was not even conventionally beautiful as Hollywood movies often portray her. She, just like most other members of the royal family, was a product of incest, and the lack of genetic diversity would have, without a doubt, left its marks in the form of deformed bodily features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleopatra was the last of the great pharaohs of ancient Egypt. Her reign ended with her suicide and it put an end to over 3000 years of glory. However, as many might think, Egypt did not die because of Cleopatra’s inadequacy in the position of power, but rather due to the fact that Rome was not ready to see a woman rule, at least not as well as the male pharaohs and certainly not better. What would have happened had the Roman belief of female inferiority not interfered with this great civilisation is something that we probably will never get to know. Some might say that Egypt would have eventually made its way to a truly egalitarian society. However, we cannot be so sure, especially since examples like the Vedic ages of India exist in which a society where women were considered equal to men gradually becomes not only patriarchal but also cruelly oppressive towards women over time. What is undeniable is that ancient Egypt was certainly far ahead of its time and remains one of the most feminist civilisations to have ever existed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">With the rise of movements like #MeToo and #TimesUp, it is abundantly clear to us that women have been and continue to be discriminated against across the world, whether it is in the most modern of societies like the USA or the ones that are not as modern like Saudi Arabia. Feminists say that women have been historically marginalised and their talents underestimated. They believe that societal structures and social machinery work in a way to favour men, disregarding women’s capabilities, preferences, freedoms or requirements. Today, the fight for equal opportunities and equal pay are not just limited to the efforts of non-males. Men who realise that there exists a disparity that needs to be rectified have started joining in. But have women always been subjected to the kind of treatment that is meted out to them today?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who Won The Race at The Last Leg? Putin: 1 Trump: 0</title><link href="/Who-Won-The-Race" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Won The Race at The Last Leg? Putin: 1 Trump: 0" /><published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Who-Won-The-Race</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Who-Won-The-Race">&lt;p&gt;On October 6, 2019, during a phone call with the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, US President Donald Trump decided to withdraw US troops from northern Syria. His declaration has had unfathomable seismic impact, not just in the Middle East but all across the globe. The US had, for long, been acting as the truce-keeper between Syrian Kurds and Turkey, both of whom are American allies. But the US’ sudden withdrawal and abandonment not only caused a proxy war within three days, but also left a significant part of the war-torn country without proper leadership and command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To gain a deeper perspective of how things spiralled out of control, we need to step into the history of Syria, Turkey and a common ethnic group, the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who are the Kurds?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kurds constitute a community of a predominantly Muslim ethnic group. Most of them speak one of the two significant dialects of the Kurdish language and have distinct cultural and linguistic traditions. The Kurdish conflict dates back to an attempt by the Ottoman Empire to end the 300-year-old autonomy of the Kurdish principalities in Kurdistan. Even after the end of the Ottoman Era, the Kurds were granted neither their independence nor their autonomy. In fact, when it collapsed, all of the new nation states that eventually emerged – Turkey, Syria, Iraq and Iran – inherited their own Kurdish conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1919, the Kurds and Turks together fought and won a war for independence against the Allied Forces. The Treaty of Sevres, signed after World War I, promised the Kurds their own homeland. Even though the Turkish regained their identities with the formation of the Republic of Turkey in 1923, a later agreement decided that the Kurds would remain divided among Turkey, Syria, Iran and Iraq. The Turkish identity was represented as a unifying force, and the Kurds were expected to accept this imposed reality, despite the social and cultural differences between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kurds constitute one of the most violently suppressed ethnic groups of the Middle East. Within Turkey, power was increasingly centralised in Ankara, and Turkish domination became normative. The Turkish government chose to create a homogenous and centralised society by using violent tactics. The resistance and revolts of the Kurdish were met by state-backed oppression. Repressive policies of assimilation were later implemented to transform the Kurds into ‘civilised and secular Turks’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, Turkey’s suppression sowed the seeds of decades of animosity and violence between the communities. The most serious challenge to Turkish administration rose in 1984 with the emergence of PKK or Kurdistan Workers’ Party. PKK has been identified as a terrorist organisation by both the US and Turkey, and is responsible for destructive armed conflict in south-eastern Turkey as well as bombings in Ankara and Istanbul. The PKK claims to represent the aspiration of ‘democratic autonomy’ for the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did this buried conflict resurface in US-Syria ties?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The years-long armed civil war in Syria started with peaceful protests against Bashar Al-Assad in 2011. In 2012, when the country began its descent into violent chaos, various factions tried to capture control and power in different sections of Syria. These included pro-government militias, rebels fighting for a more democratic state, Islamist extremists and militias from ethnic and religious minorities seeking to protect their areas from attack. One such faction was called the People’s Protection Units or the YPG, which was composed of Kurdish militia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of this humanitarian crisis, the Islamic State started to gain ground and power. The chaos of the civil war helped them capture swaths of land in both Iraq and Syria. In 2014, the US decided to intervene and fight against ISIS. The US led an international coalition that conducted airstrikes and established military bases in the strife-torn Syria. However, the US needed local support, and the Kurdish militant group - People’s Protection Units - emerged as the safest choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YPG transformed into a true American ally and fought alongside US troops to capture nearly a quarter of the total Syrian land mass, including most of the border with Turkey and areas mostly populated by Arabs and other ethnic groups. With the US, it also successfully drove the Islamic State from northern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Turkey was not too happy. The YPG was an off-shoot of the Kurdistan Workers’ Party, the group that led the insurgent movement against the Turkish government. The growing power of the YPG, especially close to the Syria-Turkey border was viewed as a significant security threat. The US was also caught in a tight diplomatic spot since Turkey, a NATO member and the Kurdish militia group, YPG had transformed into vital allies for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did the US respond?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Obama administration tried to slowly decelerate the tensions between the two parties. Firstly, the name of YPG was changed to SDF, or Syrian Democratic Forces and people from different ethnic backgrounds were encouraged to enlist in the SDF. Next, American troops transformed into de-facto peacekeepers and conducted patrols of the border in tandem with the Turkish forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the slow but sustainable path of diplomatic peacekeeping didn’t suit Trump. Saying that the US must avoid ‘endless wars,’ President Trump has long wanted to withdraw American forces from Syria. On October 6, 2019, Trump finally removed US troops from the Turkey-Syria border and this decision wreaked nothing but havoc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With renewed access to a weakened border, the Turkish forces began an invasion of northern Syria on October 9. The Pentagon has now ordered all troops deployed in northern Syria to withdraw. Trump has threatened to impose sanctions on Turkey if the attacks on Kurds aren’t stopped. And has also said that he was halting trade negotiations with Turkey and doubling tariffs on imports of Turkish steel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assad and Putin: The beneficiaries of US foreign policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Kurds, history seems to have repeated itself. After fighting and laying their lives with the troops of the US-led coalition, the Syrian Kurds have been abandoned in the midst of a proxy war against Turkey. Pathetic diplomacy and foreign policy of the US has resulted in an unexpected beneficiary: Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 13, the Kurds announced a deal with the regime of Syrian President Bashar al-Assad, agreeing that its troops could advance into the zone that had not been controlled by Damascus since 2012, right up to the border with Turkey. This is a huge victory for Russia and Iran-backed Assad government. But the consolidation of the victory didn’t end there. On October 23, the Turkish forces halted their incursion of Syria after a deal between the Turkish and Russian governments. The announcement followed an agreement on Tuesday night between Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his Russian counterpart, Vladimir Putin, which significantly redrew the battle lines of the eight-year-old Syrian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US’ hasty decision to withdraw from the Syria-Turkey border, without proper consideration of the ramifications, has led to great instability in the region. Not only that, it has strengthened the position of Assad and Putin, against whom, a part of the intervention was targeted. The US not only weakened its own position in the region but left an ally to fend for itself, without any support. This ill-guided and rushed foreign policy decision will cost Trump heavily. The sad truth at the moment is that the Syrian civil war can never be determined by Syrians; its outcome lies with foreign powers, and the US, after investing for years in this war, just lost a diplomatic and proxy battle to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">On October 6, 2019, during a phone call with the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, US President Donald Trump decided to withdraw US troops from northern Syria. His declaration has had unfathomable seismic impact, not just in the Middle East but all across the globe. The US had, for long, been acting as the truce-keeper between Syrian Kurds and Turkey, both of whom are American allies. But the US’ sudden withdrawal and abandonment not only caused a proxy war within three days, but also left a significant part of the war-torn country without proper leadership and command.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Feminism Ought To Be?</title><link href="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Feminism Ought To Be?" /><published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be">&lt;p&gt;There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The #metoo movement has been both shocking yet brilliant in exposing the rot beneath the veneer of equality. But has this exposition led to meaningful change? Or, for that matter, do passionate supporters of the #metoo movement really seek to bring about changes in, say, sexual harassment legislation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent seminar organised by the Calcutta High Court and American embassy in Calcutta, I was woken up to the reality of how precious little had changed with regard to America’s Civil Rights Act of 1964 or India’s Sexual Harassment of Women at Workplace (Prevention, Prohibition and Redressal) Act, 2013 in the wake of the #metoo movement. There are umpteen criticisms that can be made of both these laws, but one with regard to each should suffice to illustrate why these laws are programmed to protect the Harvey Weinsteins of our age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Act contemplates an Internal Complaints Committee to function as a redressal mechanism for aggrieved women in a workplace of more than ten employees. The Committee does require an external member who is familiar with issues relating to sexual assault or from an organisation committed to the cause of women, but the nagging sense that this is a mechanism where the “fox is guarding the hen’s house” disturbingly remains. In the case of the American Civil Rights Act, the same ends up happening even though complaints are supposed to be filed with the external US Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. This is because of two American Supreme Court decisions in &lt;em&gt;Faragher v. City of Boca Raton&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Burlington v. Ellerth&lt;/em&gt;. While both these decisions attempted to clarify the law, they inadvertently laid down a point of law that has, in the words of &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5319966/sexual-harassment-scotus-anniversary/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; magazine, “contributed to a key reason why workplace sexual harassment lawsuits are still hard to file today”. The Supreme Court ruled in these cases that an employer may not be liable under the Civil Rights Act for sexual harassment if, inter alia, the complainant fails to take advantage of any internal mechanisms for redressal of the complaint provided by the employer. In other words, we have a situation not dissimilar to the state of the Indian law, where a potential victim of sexual harassment must reckon with the fox before she can truly reach the hen’s house. This, quite obviously, means that numerous sexual harassment claims simply go unnoticed and are, quite simply, suppressed in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That these and other legal issues have been significant contributors to the extent of harassment and abuse exposed by the #metoo movement ought to be apparent to anyone with a brain. However, a call for reforms to such laws is hardly the defining conversation of today’s feminist movements. Indeed, one can appreciate that perhaps the nitty-gritties of legal reform cannot form part of an exoteric conversation. But one cannot deny that if feminists engaged in advocating meaningful legislative reform with half the passion that they use to ‘destroy’ incels and dudebros online, we would be living in a better world. This is not an anti-feminist rant from a privileged little boy, it is a Greta Thunbergesque (&lt;em&gt;bless her&lt;/em&gt;) “how dare you?!” to all those who claim to stand for women’s rights but are so pathetic at delivering those rights to women. Of course, it is important that society evolves to develop zero tolerance for misogynistic bigots, but to pay more attention to a hurtful tweet instead of the silent suffering of so many working women is rather dystopian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of misplaced priorities, we must address the representation of women in the workplace, and, of course, the feminist’s refusal to do anything real about it. As was pointed out by Baroness Arden of Heswall, Deputy President of the UK Supreme Court, in a guest lecture at the University of Bristol (which I had the privilege to attend), the percentage of women who were partners in London law firms in 2019, 100 years after women got the right to practice law in England, was a mere 29%. What’s more, Lady Arden stated that when she, as a Judge of the English Court of Appeal, proposed that a daycare centre be set up for women barristers near the Royal Courts of Justice, the other male Judges simply dismissed her by stating that this would be a nuisance to male barristers. That Lady Arden was a Judge of the Court of Appeal from 2000-2018 should serve to indicate that such horrendous attitudes are definitely not from some distant age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern feminist’s response to these facts and realities is not very different from the dialogues delivered by Samuel L Jackson in &lt;em&gt;Pulp Fiction&lt;/em&gt;, they are expressions of “furious anger” that seek to lay their vengeance upon men. But these responses are, to quote The Merovingian from the second &lt;em&gt;Matrix&lt;/em&gt; movie, “so boring, so obvious, so bourgeoisie.” They very simply ignore the import of Lady Arden’s arguments: that the next step towards a greater representation of women in the workplace requires some important tangible changes. For instance, one needs to ensure mandatory maternity leave as well as paternity leave is a reality in all big organisations—something that is far from being a reality in a country as developed as America. Secondly, one needs to concentrate on making daycare cheaper and more accessible to women so that the beauty of becoming a mother doesn’t end up penalising a booming career. Thirdly, one needs to change office culture and, sorry right-wing crackpots, that includes ensuring that air conditioning is not set in accordance with the metabolism of middle-aged men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, battling against the patriarchy to implement such changes sounds awfully hard, it is far easier to just obsess over cats (okay, fair enough, they are amazing) and share disgustingly bad feminist slam poetry. Why challenge patriarchs to be better and to do better when one can simply raise one’s hands and declare that they’re trash. And not to mention, how could we possibly change attitudes surrounding women without changing the colour of people’s toys. All of this is not for some comedic effect, it is to expose the Goebbellian lie that is modern feminism, a movement (if it can be called one) that concentrates less on change and more on empty expressions of supposed solidarity with the numerous problems faced by women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous effects of this is borne out by the feminist’s treatment of rape culture. Speaking logically, one would presume that the only way to destroy an oppressive social construct like rape culture is to teach people to know better. But that definitely is not what today’s feminist does. Today’s feminist hardly seeks to bat for rigorous consent classes in universities and schools. They rarely seek to educate people on understanding the humanity of women and they are loathe to contemplate on how men can be used as allies in combating rape culture. This not only fails to go to the root of the problem by dealing with the cultural rot that a priori drives men’s most problematic behaviours, it has far more nefarious effects. This misandry-is-feminism attitude of so many feminists incentivises a lot of men to simply pretend to be feminists in a bid to get sex. And it should go without saying that this is a most poisonous kind of objectification that relies on its antithesis to survive and grow. This verily means that feminists end up giving traction to a very fundamental sabotage of their own movement by refusing to actually deal with a problem and by stooping to lowly instinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that being said, credit must be given where credit is due, modern feminism has been very sharp in changing broader culture to simply not be accommodative of abusers and bigots. It has created a rightfully hostile environment for those who would dare say that women are lesser than men and it has clarified that sexist attitudes are simply not going to fly anymore. However, that is simply not enough. One has to go beyond a great grand shriek about how sexist and patriarchal the world is to actually contemplate upon how it could look better. And one has to understand that without such a constructive contemplation, one is going to have a world with a smokescreen of verbose activism but with a ground reality of festering oppression.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War</title><link href="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War" /><published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War">&lt;p&gt;So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit
presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the
region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of
wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question
about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the
perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the
conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict
between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in
constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but
only do so with the use of proxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi
Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered.
Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and
the USA was its ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things
chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was
set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This
scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was
overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the
pliant Shah of Iran. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was
immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in
1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the
Shah and established an Islamic Shia government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia.
It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed
that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly
Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it
is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to
govern most alliances in the region today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a
CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan
to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US
alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries
except Iraq. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In
1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian
Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring
about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the
war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise
of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further
plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for
Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the
government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia,
Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially
quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on
September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed
on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions
have been placed on Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the
race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and
beyond their own boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yemeni Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is
important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict
has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi
armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This
will need some backtracking again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially
called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals
include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to
combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while
seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, however, is against &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; popular movement as it wants to maintain
the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the
Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the
Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of
the Houthi rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war.
Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces
the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving.
Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote
a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council,
a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secession&quot;&gt;secessionist&lt;/a&gt; organisation
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemen&quot;&gt;Yemen&lt;/a&gt;. Before unification in 1990,
Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with
the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of
the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as
extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi
Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a
common enemy in the Houthi rebellion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not
accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed
the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals,
Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many
refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple
conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more
difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Syrian Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East,
but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions
of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the
President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the
disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict
into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join
them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign
states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist
prisoners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called
Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from
Assad’s Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf
states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012,
Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support
Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia
countries were supporting Assad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used
chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike;
however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They
convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of
Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was
its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers
dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and
formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the
formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and
not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also
shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS
poses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training
program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They
struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian
Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish
militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but
Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA.
However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls
with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the
cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image
that barely resembles a state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Israeli-Palestine Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would
be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially
recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more
sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for
the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which
demands Israeli withdrawal from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli-occupied_territories&quot;&gt;occupied
territories&lt;/a&gt; and
full equality for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_citizens_of_Israel&quot;&gt;Arab-Palestinian citizens of
Israel&lt;/a&gt;, among other
things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite
(even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to
the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that
constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees
at their borders (although not always amiably). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of
Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied
land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart
and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of
any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements
violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population
into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is
another stain on its record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian
Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant
organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions,
which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank,
meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks
significantly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge
everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims
would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will
annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of
Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over
peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the
Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless
Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring
and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a
disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the
consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of
external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a
few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by
world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most
negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the
conflicts is bound to fail.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way. When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself.  As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East.  The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but only do so with the use of proxies. To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered. Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and the USA was its ally. Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the pliant Shah of Iran.  The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in 1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the Shah and established an Islamic Shia government.  The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia. It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to govern most alliances in the region today. As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries except Iraq.  Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In 1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire.  In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum. Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia, Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind.  Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions have been placed on Iran. This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and beyond their own boundaries. The Yemeni Civil War The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This will need some backtracking again. Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country.  Saudi Arabia, however, is against any popular movement as it wants to maintain the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of the Houthi rebels.  The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war. Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving. Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen. Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council, a secessionist organisation in Yemen. Before unification in 1990, Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a common enemy in the Houthi rebellion.  UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals, Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’. The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more difficult.  The Syrian Civil War The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East, but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries.  The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist prisoners.  Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from Assad’s Syria. In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012, Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia countries were supporting Assad.  Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike; however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels.  In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS poses. In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad. Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA. However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image that barely resembles a state. Israeli-Palestine Conflict Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which demands Israeli withdrawal from the occupied territories and full equality for Arab-Palestinian citizens of Israel, among other things. Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite (even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees at their borders (although not always amiably).  Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is another stain on its record. Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions, which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank, meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks significantly.  Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books. These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the conflicts is bound to fail.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality</title><link href="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality" /><published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality">&lt;p&gt;We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions
about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to
buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like
to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out
how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries,
workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding
things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an
inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This,
however, is just the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set
out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term
inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs
because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his
novel &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some
common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his
original paper: &lt;em&gt;invulnerability&lt;/em&gt; in the belief that they can never be defeated,
&lt;em&gt;rationalising&lt;/em&gt; all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the
group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s &lt;em&gt;moral high ground&lt;/em&gt; without
actually considering the consequences, &lt;em&gt;stereotyping&lt;/em&gt; the enemy, &lt;em&gt;peer
pressure&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;self-censorship&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;unanimity&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mindguards&lt;/em&gt; that prevent
unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision.
It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being
in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can
gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this
circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the
phenomenon of groupthink arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for
college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably
afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather
go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very
least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You
don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting
life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit
this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking
about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led
American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy
administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could
prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed
that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the
capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s
circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar
vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly
believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad
and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely
that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly
but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders,
and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings.
The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain
into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t
piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy
speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that
prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The
Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power
plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction
to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and
immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what
caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that
led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people
were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration
camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere
without consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how
groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of
the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming
the opposition to be &lt;em&gt;inherently stupid&lt;/em&gt;. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then
collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this
group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it
due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in
how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with
a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that
all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride
rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the
aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world
(who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to
societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive.
Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around
politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud,
sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald
Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The
financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever
default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could
be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on
these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early
2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was
virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment
led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which
combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow
stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today,
with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings.
WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by
the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO.
Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how
groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply
on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt,
have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis
like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the
bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful
criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what
truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members.
People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely
possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised.
Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce
their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were
not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo
can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate
specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to
yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of
thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong,
then no &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a
group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be
made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative,
then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times
that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards
the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pranav Manie</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries, workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This, however, is just the tip of the iceberg. This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his novel 1984). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his original paper: invulnerability in the belief that they can never be defeated, rationalising all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s moral high ground without actually considering the consequences, stereotyping the enemy, peer pressure, self-censorship, unanimity and mindguards that prevent unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision. It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the phenomenon of groupthink arises. Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it. It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders, and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings. The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath. The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere without consequence. Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming the opposition to be inherently stupid. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world (who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive. Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud, sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base. Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early 2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today, with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings. WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO. Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt, have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing. How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members. People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised. Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to yours. Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong, then no single individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative, then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Makes Bengal Bangla?</title><link href="/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Makes Bengal Bangla?" /><published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla">&lt;p&gt;This year, on our (India’s) Independence Day, a group of my friends were talking
about the celebrations when one of them mentioned that he feels that Bengalis
are the most patriotic of all in India. I had never really given this a lot of
thought before but the comment got me thinking: do we Bengalis really put our
country before everything? Do we put India before Bengal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always lived in the state of West Bengal, India. Now that I am studying
in Goa with people of different backgrounds and from different states, I see a
lot of differences between our culture and that of the rest of the country.
While we do share similar sentiments of pride towards our culture as the other
Indian states, the way our love for our traditions and heritage finds
manifestation is wildly different from anywhere else, possibly in the whole
world. For the longest time, India has taken pride in its diversity. The country
seeks unity in acknowledging, respecting and preserving the diversity in
culture, lineage and heritage. When politicians come up with ideas involving
linguistic homogenization of the country, India and her people respond with
passionate protests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Language, an integral part of an ethnic group’s culture and an essence of their
non-material heritage, is a powerful political tool. It has the power to unify
nations like it did for Italy and Germany and on the other hand, create
conflicts like Catalonia and Spain. Language has been a central factor in the
demarcation of states in India. The ethno-linguistic divisions are definitely
not perfect for there exists over a hundred languages and more of their dialects
in the country. As a result, the political map of India is forever changing with
Telangana being born in 2014 and the fight for the Nepali majority Darjeeling
district of West Bengal’s fight for a separate state, Gorkhaland, still being
on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way Bengalis feel about their language is slightly different though. They
have never been afraid of giving up their lives to preserve their
mother-language, Bangla (or Bangali as non-Bengalis would call it). Unlike
France and groups of Gandhian ideologues, Bengalis do not seek to elevate their
mother-tongue to a higher pedestal only to counter the supremacy of English
(colonial language for the Indians). It is our love for our language,
literature, art and so on and so forth that make us do so, all thanks to the
Bangali Renaissance of the 1700s-1900s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1947, when British India was partitioned into the Republic of India and the
Islamic Republic of Pakistan right before their independence from colonial rule,
East Bengal became East Pakistan, solely because of the fact that it was home to
a majority of the Muslim population. Besides, the 200 years of the British
colonial policy of ‘Divide and Rule’ had proven to be remarkably efficacious,
resulting in alienating and pitting the Hindus and Muslims against each other in
the erstwhile state of Bengal. This helped in the Partition of Bengal into East
and West Bengal by the then British viceroy, Lord Curzon in 1905. Various
movements sprung up against the partition. Famous freedom fighter and future
Nobel-laureate, Rabindranath Tagore encouraged the celebration of
Raksha-Bandhan, a Hindu festival to honour the bond between a brother and a
sister, between Hindus and Muslims instead. Songs celebrating the unity between
the two religions found popularity as battle-cries of the energetic protests
against the actions of the English. However, Indians failed to stop what in my
personal opinion has been one of the most strategic ways to destroy Bengal’s
unity and a future as a unified state. The Partition of Bengal was later
annulled in 1911 but the province was never to be the same again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India was similarly partitioned, yet again, right before the transfer of power
in 1947. East Bengal was handed over to Prime Minister Jinnah’s Pakistan in a
platter that year. 55% of Pakistan’s population resided in East Pakistan and
yet, the distant minority residing in West Pakistan was to rule over them. This
lead to a great deal of resentment and problems, and they were not just limited
to the communication issues resulting from the uncomfortable fact that the two
halves of the country were separated by the state of India. Urdu was to be given
the status of the national language, effectively making it a language superior
to East Pakistan’s beloved mother-tongue Bangla. The Bangladesh Liberation
Movement, which finally concluded with the birth of yet another country,
Bangladesh in 1971, found momentum because of the Bangali population’s love for
their &lt;em&gt;Bangaliayana&lt;/em&gt;- the Bangali culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dhaka University played a central role in this movement. No wonder it had to see
blood spilt multiple times. One of the most shocking incidents of this movement,
fuelled by the love for Bangla also happens to be one of those incidents that
Bangalis, across borders, hold very close to heart. It took place on February
21st, 1952, when 4 students of Dhaka University were killed by the Pakistani
forces for opposing the sole use of Urdu in educational institutions across the
Bangali majority region. Today, the UN commemorates this day (21st of February)
as the International Mother Language Day every year. Every Bangali looks back at
this massacre with pride and respect because it symbolises the fact that their
love for their language is stronger than anything else can ever be.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, Bangalis have always been a very politically active culture. They
have never shied away from a revolution. The fact that most revolutionaries of
the Independence Movement were Bangali bears testimony to this fact. Even today,
West Bengal finds itself amidst protests and revolutions against what it
considers wrong throughout the year. It has already witnessed the &lt;em&gt;Doctor’s
Revolution&lt;/em&gt; and the protest against ABVP and RSS’s Hindutva-centric actions in
Jadavpur University this year itself. People of West Bengal’s love for
revolutions, change and socialism lies in stark contrast to the political
compass of most of the other parts of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sentimental views of how Bangladesh and the Bangali majority regions of India
ought to be a single country has existed for quite some time now. In fact, Prime
Minister Clement Attlee of UK predicted that Bengal would want to be united
under a single banner- it would want to rise above the religious demarcations
that virtually defined the rest of the country and unify for the love of Bangla
in 1946. HS Suhrawardy, the then premier of Bengal explained his stance in
support of an ‘independent, undivided and sovereign Bengal’ and appealed to the
masses on April 27th of 1947:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Let us pause for a moment to consider what Bengal can be if it remains united.
It will be a great country, indeed the richest and the most prosperous in India
capable of giving to its people a high standard of living, where a great people
will be able to rise to the fullest height of their stature, a land that will
truly be plentiful. It will be rich in agriculture, rich in industry and
commerce and in the course of time it will be one of the most powerful and
progressive states of the world. If Bengal remains united this will be no dream,
no fantasy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the appeal to the Bangali exceptionalism, left-wingers supported this
cause, blaming all of Bengal’s ills on the non-Bangali capitalists. GD Birla was
quoted saying: “I am in favour of separation, and I do not think it is
impracticable or against the interest of Hindus” as early as 1942, on behalf of
the Marwari business community in Kolkata. If only the plan for Bengal
unification had been all about catering to the sole interests of Hindus. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even MA Jinnah supported the cause instead of wanting Bengal for Pakistan
although he had a slightly different reasoning, stating: “what is the use of
Bengal without Calcutta?” The most influential supporter of the plan to make
Bengal a separate nation was Sarat Chandra Bose, a popular congressman and the
elder brother of the celebrated freedom fighter, Subhash Chandra Bose. The
proposal for United Bengal involved equal quotas for Hindus and Muslims in the
military and the police, which were to be indigenised and ‘manned by Bangalis’.
The plan that was eventually made public on May 24th of 1947, 10 days before the
final Partition plan was announced, provided for a Hindu-Muslim coalition
Government in Unified Bengal. The Prime Minister was to be a Muslim and the Home
Minister a Hindu. However, the Hindu-Muslim riots in Kolkata around the same
time and the open opposition to the unification of Bengal by Sardar Vallabhai
Patil, Jawaharlal Nehru and later even Gandhiji, eventually led to this plan
being discarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why most non-Bangali Indian leaders failed to support the idea of the
formation of a third country is because they thought that it would lay down a
precedent for other states to follow and demand independence. On May 27th, 1947,
Nehru made a formal declaration that he would support the unification only if
Bengal was to remain as a part of the Indian Union. This sparked a response from
the last British Governor of Bengal, Sir Frederick Burrows: “Bengal will be
sacrificed at the altar of Nehru’s all-India outlook.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentiments did not, however, die with the failure of the plan to unify
Bengal in 1947. The Brihot Bangla or Bishal Bangla Movement (Greater Bengal
Movement) is a nationalist political ideology which seeks to unite all bangali
speaking regions of today’s India, Bangladesh and Myanmar into a single nation.
If I am to draw an analogy (although it is very difficult to find one for it is
as unique as it can possibly get), I would say that it is like Kurdistan. The
Kurds are a nation without a state. The Bangalis too are unified by their
language but not by land. bangali literature has always referred to their
country as ‘Bangla’, the same word as they use to refer to their language.
However, Bangla does not refer to either India or Bangladesh, it refers to the
Unified Bengal. So yes, Bangalis are patriotic. But, they are patriotic towards
Bangla before any country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Nehru thought Bengal was just like other Indian states and that the
unification of Bengal and a consequent separate state would result in similar
sentiments in other states like Tamil Nadu, I disagree. The sentiments are
stronger among Bangalis because half of our own state (or country, for a
Bangladeshi) is a separate country. People from West Bengal have grown up with
stories of Bangla and how some of our ancestors had to cross borders during the
Partition and how they still long to go back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nostalgia, the resentment of the Hindu-Muslim divide and the love for
Bangla, both the language and the motherland keeps the emotions and nationalist
sentiments alive even today. For every Bangali, half of their identity lies in
West Bengal and the remaining half lies in Bangladesh. For every Bangali,
language is the identity- not religion, not dialects but Bangla. Whether or not
we are destined to ever be unified is a question yet to be answered. What
doesn’t change is the fact that even though we do not have a separate country of
Bangla, we are still unified as Bangalis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">This year, on our (India’s) Independence Day, a group of my friends were talking about the celebrations when one of them mentioned that he feels that Bengalis are the most patriotic of all in India. I had never really given this a lot of thought before but the comment got me thinking: do we Bengalis really put our country before everything? Do we put India before Bengal? I have always lived in the state of West Bengal, India. Now that I am studying in Goa with people of different backgrounds and from different states, I see a lot of differences between our culture and that of the rest of the country. While we do share similar sentiments of pride towards our culture as the other Indian states, the way our love for our traditions and heritage finds manifestation is wildly different from anywhere else, possibly in the whole world. For the longest time, India has taken pride in its diversity. The country seeks unity in acknowledging, respecting and preserving the diversity in culture, lineage and heritage. When politicians come up with ideas involving linguistic homogenization of the country, India and her people respond with passionate protests.  Language, an integral part of an ethnic group’s culture and an essence of their non-material heritage, is a powerful political tool. It has the power to unify nations like it did for Italy and Germany and on the other hand, create conflicts like Catalonia and Spain. Language has been a central factor in the demarcation of states in India. The ethno-linguistic divisions are definitely not perfect for there exists over a hundred languages and more of their dialects in the country. As a result, the political map of India is forever changing with Telangana being born in 2014 and the fight for the Nepali majority Darjeeling district of West Bengal’s fight for a separate state, Gorkhaland, still being on.  The way Bengalis feel about their language is slightly different though. They have never been afraid of giving up their lives to preserve their mother-language, Bangla (or Bangali as non-Bengalis would call it). Unlike France and groups of Gandhian ideologues, Bengalis do not seek to elevate their mother-tongue to a higher pedestal only to counter the supremacy of English (colonial language for the Indians). It is our love for our language, literature, art and so on and so forth that make us do so, all thanks to the Bangali Renaissance of the 1700s-1900s.  In 1947, when British India was partitioned into the Republic of India and the Islamic Republic of Pakistan right before their independence from colonial rule, East Bengal became East Pakistan, solely because of the fact that it was home to a majority of the Muslim population. Besides, the 200 years of the British colonial policy of ‘Divide and Rule’ had proven to be remarkably efficacious, resulting in alienating and pitting the Hindus and Muslims against each other in the erstwhile state of Bengal. This helped in the Partition of Bengal into East and West Bengal by the then British viceroy, Lord Curzon in 1905. Various movements sprung up against the partition. Famous freedom fighter and future Nobel-laureate, Rabindranath Tagore encouraged the celebration of Raksha-Bandhan, a Hindu festival to honour the bond between a brother and a sister, between Hindus and Muslims instead. Songs celebrating the unity between the two religions found popularity as battle-cries of the energetic protests against the actions of the English. However, Indians failed to stop what in my personal opinion has been one of the most strategic ways to destroy Bengal’s unity and a future as a unified state. The Partition of Bengal was later annulled in 1911 but the province was never to be the same again. India was similarly partitioned, yet again, right before the transfer of power in 1947. East Bengal was handed over to Prime Minister Jinnah’s Pakistan in a platter that year. 55% of Pakistan’s population resided in East Pakistan and yet, the distant minority residing in West Pakistan was to rule over them. This lead to a great deal of resentment and problems, and they were not just limited to the communication issues resulting from the uncomfortable fact that the two halves of the country were separated by the state of India. Urdu was to be given the status of the national language, effectively making it a language superior to East Pakistan’s beloved mother-tongue Bangla. The Bangladesh Liberation Movement, which finally concluded with the birth of yet another country, Bangladesh in 1971, found momentum because of the Bangali population’s love for their Bangaliayana- the Bangali culture. Dhaka University played a central role in this movement. No wonder it had to see blood spilt multiple times. One of the most shocking incidents of this movement, fuelled by the love for Bangla also happens to be one of those incidents that Bangalis, across borders, hold very close to heart. It took place on February 21st, 1952, when 4 students of Dhaka University were killed by the Pakistani forces for opposing the sole use of Urdu in educational institutions across the Bangali majority region. Today, the UN commemorates this day (21st of February) as the International Mother Language Day every year. Every Bangali looks back at this massacre with pride and respect because it symbolises the fact that their love for their language is stronger than anything else can ever be.    Historically, Bangalis have always been a very politically active culture. They have never shied away from a revolution. The fact that most revolutionaries of the Independence Movement were Bangali bears testimony to this fact. Even today, West Bengal finds itself amidst protests and revolutions against what it considers wrong throughout the year. It has already witnessed the Doctor’s Revolution and the protest against ABVP and RSS’s Hindutva-centric actions in Jadavpur University this year itself. People of West Bengal’s love for revolutions, change and socialism lies in stark contrast to the political compass of most of the other parts of India. Sentimental views of how Bangladesh and the Bangali majority regions of India ought to be a single country has existed for quite some time now. In fact, Prime Minister Clement Attlee of UK predicted that Bengal would want to be united under a single banner- it would want to rise above the religious demarcations that virtually defined the rest of the country and unify for the love of Bangla in 1946. HS Suhrawardy, the then premier of Bengal explained his stance in support of an ‘independent, undivided and sovereign Bengal’ and appealed to the masses on April 27th of 1947: “Let us pause for a moment to consider what Bengal can be if it remains united. It will be a great country, indeed the richest and the most prosperous in India capable of giving to its people a high standard of living, where a great people will be able to rise to the fullest height of their stature, a land that will truly be plentiful. It will be rich in agriculture, rich in industry and commerce and in the course of time it will be one of the most powerful and progressive states of the world. If Bengal remains united this will be no dream, no fantasy.” Besides the appeal to the Bangali exceptionalism, left-wingers supported this cause, blaming all of Bengal’s ills on the non-Bangali capitalists. GD Birla was quoted saying: “I am in favour of separation, and I do not think it is impracticable or against the interest of Hindus” as early as 1942, on behalf of the Marwari business community in Kolkata. If only the plan for Bengal unification had been all about catering to the sole interests of Hindus.  Even MA Jinnah supported the cause instead of wanting Bengal for Pakistan although he had a slightly different reasoning, stating: “what is the use of Bengal without Calcutta?” The most influential supporter of the plan to make Bengal a separate nation was Sarat Chandra Bose, a popular congressman and the elder brother of the celebrated freedom fighter, Subhash Chandra Bose. The proposal for United Bengal involved equal quotas for Hindus and Muslims in the military and the police, which were to be indigenised and ‘manned by Bangalis’. The plan that was eventually made public on May 24th of 1947, 10 days before the final Partition plan was announced, provided for a Hindu-Muslim coalition Government in Unified Bengal. The Prime Minister was to be a Muslim and the Home Minister a Hindu. However, the Hindu-Muslim riots in Kolkata around the same time and the open opposition to the unification of Bengal by Sardar Vallabhai Patil, Jawaharlal Nehru and later even Gandhiji, eventually led to this plan being discarded.  The reason why most non-Bangali Indian leaders failed to support the idea of the formation of a third country is because they thought that it would lay down a precedent for other states to follow and demand independence. On May 27th, 1947, Nehru made a formal declaration that he would support the unification only if Bengal was to remain as a part of the Indian Union. This sparked a response from the last British Governor of Bengal, Sir Frederick Burrows: “Bengal will be sacrificed at the altar of Nehru’s all-India outlook.”  The sentiments did not, however, die with the failure of the plan to unify Bengal in 1947. The Brihot Bangla or Bishal Bangla Movement (Greater Bengal Movement) is a nationalist political ideology which seeks to unite all bangali speaking regions of today’s India, Bangladesh and Myanmar into a single nation. If I am to draw an analogy (although it is very difficult to find one for it is as unique as it can possibly get), I would say that it is like Kurdistan. The Kurds are a nation without a state. The Bangalis too are unified by their language but not by land. bangali literature has always referred to their country as ‘Bangla’, the same word as they use to refer to their language. However, Bangla does not refer to either India or Bangladesh, it refers to the Unified Bengal. So yes, Bangalis are patriotic. But, they are patriotic towards Bangla before any country.   While Nehru thought Bengal was just like other Indian states and that the unification of Bengal and a consequent separate state would result in similar sentiments in other states like Tamil Nadu, I disagree. The sentiments are stronger among Bangalis because half of our own state (or country, for a Bangladeshi) is a separate country. People from West Bengal have grown up with stories of Bangla and how some of our ancestors had to cross borders during the Partition and how they still long to go back. The nostalgia, the resentment of the Hindu-Muslim divide and the love for Bangla, both the language and the motherland keeps the emotions and nationalist sentiments alive even today. For every Bangali, half of their identity lies in West Bengal and the remaining half lies in Bangladesh. For every Bangali, language is the identity- not religion, not dialects but Bangla. Whether or not we are destined to ever be unified is a question yet to be answered. What doesn’t change is the fact that even though we do not have a separate country of Bangla, we are still unified as Bangalis.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What if Veritaserum was Real?</title><link href="/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if Veritaserum was Real?" /><published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real">&lt;p&gt;For those of you who don’t know what Veritaserum is (seriously?), it is a
magical truth potion from the universe of Harry Potter. As a collegiate debater,
I have faced my fair share of &lt;em&gt;meta&lt;/em&gt; motions. One of the most intriguing ones
that I have come across is: ‘This house prefers a world where no one can lie.’
Although it sounds like a very common, overused motion, it got me thinking, is
it really possible? What would the world be like? And would I want to live in
that world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start with the first question: can Veritaserum indeed be a reality one
day? Well, let me break this to you- truth serums very much exist. In fact, they
have been available since the 1920’s. They are primarily mind-altering
(psychoactive) drugs which slow down the process of transfer of messages from
the spinal cord to the brain. Lying usually requires a lot of effort, unless you
are a compulsive liar. These drugs simply hinder your capability to concentrate
and thus, make it difficult to lie. They don’t, however, completely inhibit your
ability to lie. Some common examples include &lt;em&gt;sodium thiopental&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;scopolamine&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;sodium amytal&lt;/em&gt;. Historically, they have been used for various other
purposes. During World War II, they were used as anti-anxiety drugs on soldiers.
Until 2011, they were also used as anaesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very rarely have truth serums been used for interrogation though, due to ethical
conflicts. A myriad of historical examples, however, portray the positives of
using such drugs in a criminal investigation. The 2007 Noida serial killer case
(in India) could only be solved when the suspect confessed, under the influence
of &lt;em&gt;sodium amytal&lt;/em&gt;, to the heinous crimes that had been committed by him.
However, the use of truth serums during interrogation is considered to be a
direct violation of the Fifth Amendment of the US Constitution (the Right to
remain silent) and is, thus, illegal in the US. Many consider the administration
of truth serums, in order to extract information, to not only be a violation of
the human right to be free from degrading treatment but also a form of torture.
Besides, these drugs have some serious side-effects, including the development
of false memories, addiction and even death in case of an overdose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of such concerns, research is on to find and develop a drug that can
completely prevent a person from lying, including compulsive liars, without any
grave side-effects: &lt;em&gt;the ultimate Veritaserum&lt;/em&gt;. But just because something can
be done doesn’t mean that it should be done. Whether it is morally right or
wrong requires thinking through a lot of different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side of the debate might argue that taking away the right to lie is a severe
encroachment upon the right to choose. At times, it might, in fact, be necessary
to lie- white lies. Thomas Paine once said, “He who dares not offend cannot be
honest”. In a world where being polite is deemed a great virtue, it is
impossible to get by without lying, if one hopes to follow the etiquettes set by
a genteel society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a child, still in the formative years, tries to learn something new, we
provide them encouragement shrouded in little lies. This is necessary to prevent
them from losing interest or giving up. It is also unfortunate that the modern
world isn’t very progressive when it comes to accepting the LGBTQIA+ community,
often forcing people of the community to lie about their sexuality or gender to
save themselves from questions, comments and bullies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, lies are crucial to one’s safety. Celebrities lie about where they
live to prevent stalkers from breaking in, spies put on a disguise and lie to
unveil the secrets of underground institutions and terrorist cells, while also
ensuring personal safety against potential harm from the people they spy upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doctors fail to see alternative options to save a person’s life, they often
resort to placebo. This involves actively lying to the patient about the effects
the drugs have been having on the person’s health- telling them that the
medicines have actually been working well and that they will get well soon when
that is probably not the case. In some cases, patients actually have a positive
response to this. While many see this practice as unethical, owing to the fact
that a doctor has to blatantly lie to a patient, others think that using placebo
as a last resort to help them is justified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of these cases are rather niche, there are many which are not as
individualistic. Taking a step back and looking at the big picture, reveals
other interesting aspects. The avenues that greatly affect our day to day lives
like politics, religion, media, etc. tend to hurt us mostly when lies in some
form or the other are involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk politics. Populist demagogues, who tend to make fake promises based
on what the majority of the populace desires instead of using rational
arguments, are the biggest disgrace to modern politics. Their campaigns and
popularity are based on lies. Commoners fall prey to their words because these
leaders pander to what people already want to hear. Examples of such leaders
include Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini. Stephen Hawking once tagged even
Donald Trump as a demagogue. It isn’t unknown to any of us what their ‘reigns’
have been like. Even though stripping politicians of the ability to lie won’t
solve the problems that pervade politics, it does ensure that commoners do not
get cheated into hoping for something that is never meant to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to affect our lives immensely is crime. False charges, corruption
and plantation of fake evidence are not unusual. It is common practice among
convicts, facing the possibility of a long sentence, to lie about the severity
of their crimes to hinder the prosecution. Psychopaths and sociopaths are able
to lie without any remorse whatsoever. Most serial killers can be classified as
either of the two and their flawless lying makes them incredibly difficult to
spot. The problems of adjudication, conviction and prosecution will simply fail
to exist in a world where people are unable to lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unethical marketing cheats people into believing that a product provides certain
benefits which it actually doesn’t. Tech giants like Google, Amazon, Facebook,
Qualcomm and so on have come under a lot of heat in recent years. Immense
capital is spent on investigating these companies to find the truth. In a
lie-less world, these problems would simply cease to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cases of fraud often take several years to be solved and have justice served
for, like the Enron scandal. It is easier to live in a world where committing
fraud is an impossibility than to have so many duped before spending big bucks
to rectify the situation. The morality of the work done by certain companies
itself is questionable. Take Ashley Madison for example, it is a dating site
catering to those who are currently in a committed relationship or married. The
profits of this company are based on how well they are able to lie without
taking into consideration the fact that they hurt people in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is widespread misinformation in the world owing to the phenomena of ‘fake
news’. Lies about the intentions of a party creates misunderstandings, leading
to conflict and divided masses. Social media has enabled lying to a whole new
extent. It is fashionable to lie about not having make-up on or not having had
plastic surgery in the past, or even about living perfect lives. These set
unrealisable standards of lifestyle and beauty for everyone. This eventually
culminates in depression among teenagers and adults who fail to achieve these
unreal standards- something that is more common now than ever. In fact,
celebrities, like K-Pop idols, are forced to undergo surgeries to comply with
certain beauty standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that shapes society drastically is religion. Problems arise from
lies about what God desires. While this can be used as a powerful positive tool
too, there exist other alternatives to achieve the same. For example, it is
better to tell a person not to cut a tree because they provide us with oxygen
rather than using some religious reference to drive the point home. This is
because, for one, atheism is on the rise and will, in the future, be the
dominant ‘belief’ (atheism is expected to overtake religion by 2041). These
atheists associate religion with regressiveness of thought and religious
justifications are unacceptable to them. Secondly, religious beliefs do not have
the same appeal among people belonging to different religions or sects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While freedom of choice is essential for everyone, this freedom cannot affect
someone else- hurt the other person or encroach upon their freedom. Social
contract theorists argue that everyone in a society moves into a contract with
each other and the government, and the government can partially take away
certain rights of individuals to ensure greater benefits for society at large.
If this ‘sacrifice’ is what society operates upon, I personally feel that it is
justified to take away the right to lie if greater benefits can be ensured in
the process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all problems can be solved by just stopping people from lying. A world where
no one can lie is not the ideal world. Crimes will be committed. Bad people will
continue to exist. They will have evil intentions; they just will not be able to
lie about them. While it might seem that taking away the right to lie infringes
upon individual rights, the greater benefits it provides makes me question if
the argument of ‘rights’ is sufficient grounds to argue against it. A world like
this, however, is a reality left in store for those who come after us (unless
someone is secretly preparing for a Nobel Prize). For now, we are doomed to live
in a world of lies, fraud and betrayal where we can only hope that the ones we
trust the most do not lie to us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">For those of you who don’t know what Veritaserum is (seriously?), it is a magical truth potion from the universe of Harry Potter. As a collegiate debater, I have faced my fair share of meta motions. One of the most intriguing ones that I have come across is: ‘This house prefers a world where no one can lie.’ Although it sounds like a very common, overused motion, it got me thinking, is it really possible? What would the world be like? And would I want to live in that world? Let us start with the first question: can Veritaserum indeed be a reality one day? Well, let me break this to you- truth serums very much exist. In fact, they have been available since the 1920’s. They are primarily mind-altering (psychoactive) drugs which slow down the process of transfer of messages from the spinal cord to the brain. Lying usually requires a lot of effort, unless you are a compulsive liar. These drugs simply hinder your capability to concentrate and thus, make it difficult to lie. They don’t, however, completely inhibit your ability to lie. Some common examples include sodium thiopental, scopolamine and sodium amytal. Historically, they have been used for various other purposes. During World War II, they were used as anti-anxiety drugs on soldiers. Until 2011, they were also used as anaesthetics. Very rarely have truth serums been used for interrogation though, due to ethical conflicts. A myriad of historical examples, however, portray the positives of using such drugs in a criminal investigation. The 2007 Noida serial killer case (in India) could only be solved when the suspect confessed, under the influence of sodium amytal, to the heinous crimes that had been committed by him. However, the use of truth serums during interrogation is considered to be a direct violation of the Fifth Amendment of the US Constitution (the Right to remain silent) and is, thus, illegal in the US. Many consider the administration of truth serums, in order to extract information, to not only be a violation of the human right to be free from degrading treatment but also a form of torture. Besides, these drugs have some serious side-effects, including the development of false memories, addiction and even death in case of an overdose. In spite of such concerns, research is on to find and develop a drug that can completely prevent a person from lying, including compulsive liars, without any grave side-effects: the ultimate Veritaserum. But just because something can be done doesn’t mean that it should be done. Whether it is morally right or wrong requires thinking through a lot of different things. One side of the debate might argue that taking away the right to lie is a severe encroachment upon the right to choose. At times, it might, in fact, be necessary to lie- white lies. Thomas Paine once said, “He who dares not offend cannot be honest”. In a world where being polite is deemed a great virtue, it is impossible to get by without lying, if one hopes to follow the etiquettes set by a genteel society. When a child, still in the formative years, tries to learn something new, we provide them encouragement shrouded in little lies. This is necessary to prevent them from losing interest or giving up. It is also unfortunate that the modern world isn’t very progressive when it comes to accepting the LGBTQIA+ community, often forcing people of the community to lie about their sexuality or gender to save themselves from questions, comments and bullies. At times, lies are crucial to one’s safety. Celebrities lie about where they live to prevent stalkers from breaking in, spies put on a disguise and lie to unveil the secrets of underground institutions and terrorist cells, while also ensuring personal safety against potential harm from the people they spy upon. When doctors fail to see alternative options to save a person’s life, they often resort to placebo. This involves actively lying to the patient about the effects the drugs have been having on the person’s health- telling them that the medicines have actually been working well and that they will get well soon when that is probably not the case. In some cases, patients actually have a positive response to this. While many see this practice as unethical, owing to the fact that a doctor has to blatantly lie to a patient, others think that using placebo as a last resort to help them is justified. While most of these cases are rather niche, there are many which are not as individualistic. Taking a step back and looking at the big picture, reveals other interesting aspects. The avenues that greatly affect our day to day lives like politics, religion, media, etc. tend to hurt us mostly when lies in some form or the other are involved. Let’s talk politics. Populist demagogues, who tend to make fake promises based on what the majority of the populace desires instead of using rational arguments, are the biggest disgrace to modern politics. Their campaigns and popularity are based on lies. Commoners fall prey to their words because these leaders pander to what people already want to hear. Examples of such leaders include Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini. Stephen Hawking once tagged even Donald Trump as a demagogue. It isn’t unknown to any of us what their ‘reigns’ have been like. Even though stripping politicians of the ability to lie won’t solve the problems that pervade politics, it does ensure that commoners do not get cheated into hoping for something that is never meant to happen. Another thing to affect our lives immensely is crime. False charges, corruption and plantation of fake evidence are not unusual. It is common practice among convicts, facing the possibility of a long sentence, to lie about the severity of their crimes to hinder the prosecution. Psychopaths and sociopaths are able to lie without any remorse whatsoever. Most serial killers can be classified as either of the two and their flawless lying makes them incredibly difficult to spot. The problems of adjudication, conviction and prosecution will simply fail to exist in a world where people are unable to lie. Unethical marketing cheats people into believing that a product provides certain benefits which it actually doesn’t. Tech giants like Google, Amazon, Facebook, Qualcomm and so on have come under a lot of heat in recent years. Immense capital is spent on investigating these companies to find the truth. In a lie-less world, these problems would simply cease to exist. Cases of fraud often take several years to be solved and have justice served for, like the Enron scandal. It is easier to live in a world where committing fraud is an impossibility than to have so many duped before spending big bucks to rectify the situation. The morality of the work done by certain companies itself is questionable. Take Ashley Madison for example, it is a dating site catering to those who are currently in a committed relationship or married. The profits of this company are based on how well they are able to lie without taking into consideration the fact that they hurt people in the process. There is widespread misinformation in the world owing to the phenomena of ‘fake news’. Lies about the intentions of a party creates misunderstandings, leading to conflict and divided masses. Social media has enabled lying to a whole new extent. It is fashionable to lie about not having make-up on or not having had plastic surgery in the past, or even about living perfect lives. These set unrealisable standards of lifestyle and beauty for everyone. This eventually culminates in depression among teenagers and adults who fail to achieve these unreal standards- something that is more common now than ever. In fact, celebrities, like K-Pop idols, are forced to undergo surgeries to comply with certain beauty standards. Another thing that shapes society drastically is religion. Problems arise from lies about what God desires. While this can be used as a powerful positive tool too, there exist other alternatives to achieve the same. For example, it is better to tell a person not to cut a tree because they provide us with oxygen rather than using some religious reference to drive the point home. This is because, for one, atheism is on the rise and will, in the future, be the dominant ‘belief’ (atheism is expected to overtake religion by 2041). These atheists associate religion with regressiveness of thought and religious justifications are unacceptable to them. Secondly, religious beliefs do not have the same appeal among people belonging to different religions or sects. While freedom of choice is essential for everyone, this freedom cannot affect someone else- hurt the other person or encroach upon their freedom. Social contract theorists argue that everyone in a society moves into a contract with each other and the government, and the government can partially take away certain rights of individuals to ensure greater benefits for society at large. If this ‘sacrifice’ is what society operates upon, I personally feel that it is justified to take away the right to lie if greater benefits can be ensured in the process.   Not all problems can be solved by just stopping people from lying. A world where no one can lie is not the ideal world. Crimes will be committed. Bad people will continue to exist. They will have evil intentions; they just will not be able to lie about them. While it might seem that taking away the right to lie infringes upon individual rights, the greater benefits it provides makes me question if the argument of ‘rights’ is sufficient grounds to argue against it. A world like this, however, is a reality left in store for those who come after us (unless someone is secretly preparing for a Nobel Prize). For now, we are doomed to live in a world of lies, fraud and betrayal where we can only hope that the ones we trust the most do not lie to us.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Nakba of Israel and Palestine</title><link href="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nakba of Israel and Palestine" /><published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Torn between the Jewish Zionist movement and the Palestinian nationalist movement lies a piece of land and millions of people. Whom does this land belong to? Is there more to this conflict than a piece of land? What has this conflict led to? Is there a way out of this labyrinth of suffering? Within Israeli and Palestinian societies, the conflict has generated a wide variety of opinions. A hallmark of the conflict has been the level of violence conducted by rebel armies, paramilitary groups, terror cells and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conflict has its roots in history. In the 1900’s, the area which is now known as Israel and Palestine was under Ottoman rule. The Ottoman Empire was religiously diverse with Muslims, Christians, and Jews living together. This happily ever after was hindered when Muslims in the area started developing a sense of not just being Arabs but also having a distinct national identity: Palestinian. Concurrently, the Zionism movement started emerging in Europe. They believed Judaism was not just a religion but also a national identity and so, Jews deserved a home in their ancestral land. Their idea was similar to how the French live in France and the Indians live in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As both groups started working towards developing this area as their homeland, the peace they had been living in vanished forever. Between 1896 and 1948, millions of Jews migrated to British-controlled Palestine, with many fleeing the Holocaust in Germany. Palestinians regarded this as another form of European colonisation. As more Jews settled into farming communes, tension rose between Jews and Arabs, with both sides committing acts of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jewish population in British Palestine and violence between the two groups continued to rise. And so, in 1947, the United Nations (UN) approved a plan to divide the land into two areas, with distinct borders, to form Israel and Palestine. The plan was meant to give the Jews a state and to establish Palestinian independence. It declared Jerusalem a ‘special international zone’ , owing to its religious importance, whose administration was to be controlled by the UN. Jerusalem has a place of importance in three vital religions: Islam, Christianity and Judaism. Because of this, both countries consider Jerusalem as their capital. But the map largely looked like a jigsaw puzzle. An average Palestinian citizen who lived in West Bank had no idea about what would be happening in Gaza (and still doesn’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of a Jewish majority state in the Middle East didn’t sit well with the rest of the Arab countries. They saw the UN’s plan as another way of the Europeans stealing their land. Many of the Arab states came together and declared war on Israel, in 1948, to establish a unified Arab Palestine. Despite being a new-born country, Israel defeated them and proved its military might. In doing so, Israel pushed past its borders and took control of a significant portion of Palestine. The war forced hundreds of Palestinians to flee their homes and become refugees in the surrounding Arab countries, making them stateless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1967, a six-day war took place between Israel and the Arab nations. Again, Israel won. Not only did it annex the whole of Palestine but also territories from Egypt, Syria and Jordan. Israel got the right to govern the Palestinians. In the decades that followed, the Arab countries made peace with Israel. This allowed them to get their Israeli annexed territories back. The broader Israeli-Arab conflict now morphed into a more specific Israeli-Palestinian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rise of the Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO) in 1964, the founder, Yasser Arafat, used military tactics including attacks on Israeli civilians. The PLO oversaw guerrilla groups on the one hand and used non-violent approaches on the other. Meanwhile, the Israeli started moving into West Bank and East Jerusalem, establishing Israeli settlements. They undertook this for three main reasons: (i) religious reasons so that people could live close to Jerusalem, (ii) to claim the land as Israeli territory and (iii) cheap housing. As more civilians settled into Palestinian territories, the military followed. This led to increased checkpoints for Palestinians and forced Palestinians off their land. In effect, it blurred the boundaries of any future Palestinian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 1980’s, the frustration among Palestinians grew, and they launched the First Intifada (meaning uprising). This began by boycotting Israeli products and services, and refusing to pay taxes or working jobs in Israel. However, when the Israeli military cracked down on the protestors, violence ensued. The Intifada led to the rise of Hamas in Gaza, an extremist group dedicated to Israel’s destruction, which considered the PLO too compromise-minded. Till date, Hamas has garnered support not just because of its military strength but because of the social welfare projects undertaken by it in Gaza. They have built schools, mosques and clinics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1993, the PLO accepted Israel’s right to exist and in exchange wanted Israel to recognize it as the legitimate representative of Palestinians. That was the beginning of real peace negotiations between the two sides. Leaders from both sides signed the American-brokered Oslo Accords. This allowed Palestinians more freedom to govern themselves. Hard-liners on both sides, however, were not happy with the terms of the peace process and ensued violence to sabotage this process. After signing the second round of the Oslo Accords, the far-right Israeli groups shot Israeli PM Yitzhak Rabin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has been pro-Israel since the Cold War. US politicians view the pro-Israel propaganda as a method to garner support from their citizens by appealing to their anti-Muslim sentiments. This, however, has larger implications. The domino effect of the US supporting Israel is that the US’ allies have started to support Israel too. A good example is India. India aligned itself with Palestine after the partition in 1948, but since it has aligned with the US now, they have forced India to support Israel. In 2018, the USA shifted its embassy from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem in Israel, internationally recognizing Jerusalem as the capital of Israel. As a consequence, other countries such as Guatemala and Paraguay also shifted their embassies to Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of this conflict remains the same till date. Both parties want a country to exert their distinct identity, and none will compromise with the other. Caught in the crossfire between the two governments and extremist groups, it’s the voices and lives of the citizens that are being compromised. Everyone who identifies as either a Palestinian or an Israeli knows at least one person who lost their life because of this conflict. Most Jews see the Palestinians’ demand for an independent state as just. Most Palestinians prefer a two-state solution. Both Israelis and Palestinians are afraid of the people in charge on the other side. The people can’t trust their information sources because they know it’s fueled with propaganda. The settlements resemble regular suburbs from any part of the world, with people trying to live peacefully in a place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestinian governance is divided between the Palestinian Authority and Hamas. The Israeli government is skeptical of Hamas and its goal of Israel’s destruction. As violence continues, there seems to be little political will for peace. Any successful peace initiative would need resolving the issues: West Bank settlements, Israeli security, Palestinian refugees and their right to return, Jerusalem, mutual recognition and water rights. However, there are three major hurdles: (i) Israeli settlements continue expanding, (ii) the PLO, and Hamas cannot negotiate jointly and (iii) everyone is unsure regarding how to get the talks started. The truth of the matter is the governments aren’t solving the conflict anymore, they are just managing it. Israel constructed walls and checkpoints after the second Intifada, leaving Palestinians to believe they have no future as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent Israeli elections have not given a clear mandate but Likud party’s chief, incumbent Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu is likely to head a coalition government. It remains to be seen whether there would be any change in attitude of leaders on both sides of the fence. For this to happen, it is necessary that both parties trust each other, and explore the possibility of coexistence and the legitimacy of each other’s historical narrative. The United Nations should come out of the shadow of the US and mediate a solution for the welfare of the people in this war torn area.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modern Slavery: Inside the Transgender Communities of India and Pakistan</title><link href="/Modern-Slavery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Slavery: Inside the Transgender Communities of India and Pakistan" /><published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Modern-Slavery</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Modern-Slavery">&lt;p&gt;Our world is imbued with contradictions and opposing realities which inform our lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in our social setting. While some reap benefits of the rights and privileges bestowed upon them, others remain tangled in the subjugating mesh of society. The trapped transgenders either end up mangled under the massive burden of gender roles or end up conforming to the gender expectations ascribed to the sex in which they were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; born, as a means of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accident of birth has had serious ramifications on many, but none have been affected as gravely as the transgender. Betrayed by their bodies, and disowned by their families and communities, the transgender (including the eunuch and the intersex), popularly termed as &lt;em&gt;hijras&lt;/em&gt; in India and Pakistan, live as social outcasts, misfits for committing the grave crime of expressing their identities. Their existence itself poses a great threat to social conceptions of gender and sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in such countries, especially Pakistan where a manic obsession with gender roles reigns over every soul, certainly isn’t easy. The slightest deviation from societal conventions may result in ostracisation and humiliation; primarily the reason why the community is forced into darkness, into total seclusion. The expression of individuality comes at the great price of losing honour and respect. Having been stripped of all rights and dignity, they are forced into begging, prostitution, dancing as a means to earn their living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of mankind has largely revolved around freedom, power and recognition. It is a human need to be recognised and respected by others. Our identities form the very basis of our personhood. This is primarily why we assert ourselves wherever we go. We want our presence to be felt. But what if somebody just takes it all away from us? It would cause a massive dent on our personhood. This is precisely what the transgender community undergoes. Society robs them of their personhood. Life for them is suffering; it begins with gender dysphoria and their struggle to recognise themselves and ends with society deeming them as weeds unfit to be with others; the &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forced to remain hidden from the public eye, they form secret communities that observe their own mysterious codes and customs. One such custom is the rite of initiation, where every new transgender wishing to join the community must go through the painful procedure of emasculation and then be accepted by a &lt;em&gt;guru&lt;/em&gt;, who assumes a paternalistic role in the life of the newly initiated novice. The guru – novice relationship forms the bedrock of the transgender community. This is where things start turning really dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initiate or the novice, who is purchased in exchange of money, is literally at the mercy of the guru. She is penalised and punished severely if she fails to discharge the duties imposed on her. And if at all she decides to leave, she is shunned from the entire community. After being purchased, the novice is then forced by the guru into performing professions like begging, dancing, etc. to earn money; a major chunk of which goes to the guru. This practice almost seems like a modern form of slavery, but because of how inherent it is to the culture, it goes unquestioned and unopposed. Sadly, the tradition which was created to protect starts fettering them and taking away their freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the tremendous pressure imposed by the gurus, the novices at times may even have to indulge in sex work for money. Since they are denied all respectable jobs, several transgenders have to undergo this torment. They are coerced, tortured, raped- all under the knowledge of their gurus. Unable to complain to the authorities and fearing further harassment, they are forced to remain silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the young transgender, there remains no respite. On one end, they have to deal with repression from society and on the other, the monopoly of the greedy gurus. Another threat looming over their reality is the possibility of acquiring sexually transmitted diseases. Living in denial, they refuse to get themselves medically examined and continue living in unsafe conditions. They, nevertheless, continue existing, because for them nothing can surpass the feeling of power that comes along with expressing oneself and getting acknowledged as the person one wishes to be. The exhibition of identity becomes the sole purpose of their existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the guru-novice relationship, it’s important to understand that no cultural practice is free of fault. As in the case of this relationship, every cultural practice harbours in itself certain forms of darkness, often hidden from the rest of the world. The only way out here, is for change to come from the outside, so that these cultural practices automatically dismantle and disintegrate, without being meddled with. Change is slowly coming about; transgenders in India and Pakistan are being recognised as a third gender. With a state-issued identity of their own, they can now avail opportunities previously known only to the two genders, and therefore, reduce their dependence on the guru-novice practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acceptance in society can only come with greater visibility. For an all-inclusive world, the transgender community, with all its eccentricity and richness, must be integrated into the mainstream of society. There exists a need to create space for identity to breathe, which must then be recognised and respected. Especially in Asian countries where these groups are attached to labels of abnormality, there is a necessity to uproot the social stigma surrounding their existence. This can only happen when we begin to recognise them as humans before ascribing a gender identity to them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Our world is imbued with contradictions and opposing realities which inform our lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in our social setting. While some reap benefits of the rights and privileges bestowed upon them, others remain tangled in the subjugating mesh of society. The trapped transgenders either end up mangled under the massive burden of gender roles or end up conforming to the gender expectations ascribed to the sex in which they were not born, as a means of expression.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Corruption - Cynicism or Pragmatism</title><link href="/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corruption - Cynicism or Pragmatism" /><published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years back, post the implementation of certain paramount structural reforms, Nigerian social media platforms were bizarrely flooded with a rather idiosyncratic hashtag ‘BBOC’, or ‘BringBackOurCorruption’. The laws that were partially aimed at enabling transparency, accountability and a greater oversight of government revenue, with penalisation for infringement extended to incarceration, did not sit well with the public. The government had apparently stolen the ‘grease’ to their economic cycle, which eventually showed in the levels of inflation in the Nigerian economy as well as in a plummeting Nigerian Naira in international markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corruption is bad. There is a large consensus that corroborates its corrosive impact on society. Macro level studies, that have used country-level data to explore cross country variations in both governance and economic indicators, have managed to consistently establish a correlation between low-income countries and greater levels of bureaucratic corruption. But if we look beyond conventional wisdom, it doesn’t take a genius to figure out that while the former argument is purely moral in its reasoning, rather than rational, the latter is also weak in its inability to establish a coherent causational relation between the two variables involved. Rose-Ackerman (1996), through their works, further helped carve into stone the idea that corruption is detrimental to the health of an economy, leading to the rise of a school of thought that opposed the idea of corruption as a positive for the economy (something which was extensively worked upon by various scholars in the 1960’s). It was popularly believed that corruption ‘sands’ the wheels of the economy. One might never be able to debunk the moral argument against corruption, but as for the empirical data backing the second argument, one must note that for every poor and corrupt African nation, there is an equally corrupt but rich Asian nation, leading many to believe that corruption has got nothing to do with the level of growth in an economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one had to defend corruption, it would be difficult, nearly impossible, to do so from an ethical perspective. Any possible argument in its defense would be highly situational. But when it comes to the economic perspective, one might become much more tolerant. It is then simply considered a ‘grease’ that ensures smoother functioning of the economy, like a tax you pay to cut through the bureaucratic red tape. Although corruption is popularly believed to be an aspect inherent to socialism, it arises out of a society’s need to come closer to its capitalistic features. In a free-market, demand and supply balance in a manner that ensures that all goods and services eventually reach their intrinsic value in the market, eliminating any arbitrage opportunities for an individual seller, given perfect knowledge. As soon as there is intervention, this cycle breaks down. This is an issue that was highlighted in Ludwig Von Mises’ Socialist Calculation Debate in the 1920’s. Mises argued for the inability of the socialist system to get through one of the fundamental economic problems: what to produce? The state makes that decision and sets the prices, but since there is a lack of market determination of the eventual prices, a seller may not be able to gauge the demand that exists for his product and may end up believing that the prices are not at par with the intrinsic value, that is what he deserves. In order to get closer to that figure, the seller may resort to hoarding a product or charging a little under-the-table fee, and it’s only fair. However the inability to estimate this intrinsic figure is also something that perpetuates corruption. A public servant in India may demand a bribe to get a service done because he feels that his salary is too low to compensate for his efforts. This behavioural aspect may not go away even if his salary is raised, not simply because it becomes habitual but because he tends to measure his reward relatively. Well, also because human wants are never ending (but this has nothing to do with the intrinsic aspect, here he will charge higher for as long as he can). In this example, even if the given behavioural aspect does go away, that is the employee is satisfied with the salary hike, he would be disincentivised from even showing up to work because he is getting a satisfactory remuneration for a job which has no stringent regulatory mechanism and is known to turn people lethargic. This example counter-intuitively explains how a bribe would proves to be much better for the economy than a salary hike for public servants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this perspective offers an analysis based on the degree of intervention, many believe that the existence of corruption is inherent to any developing economy, citing how all the major developed economies of the modern world went through phases of deep corruption and social unrest to get where they are. In fact, Leff, N.H. (1964) found empirical evidence that anti-corruption campaigns in developing nations, like the then-China, depress economic growth by slowing down investment levels. Another argument states that developing nations have a poorly drafted constitutional and policy framework. When they don’t, it is considered overambitious due to their inability to constantly keep up with redesigning policies, resulting in them falling victim to various perverse incentives. This paucity of appropriate laws and policies is an aspect that was hypothesised by Samuel Huntington in the 1960’s. He believed that in such cases the only way to drive growth and revive businesses stuck in legislative red tape is corruption. It becomes a mechanism to circumvent thoughtless regulations in developing nations and provides rationality to the rising income inequality in these economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncanny response of Nigeria, a barely developing nation, to the anti-corruption crackdown was exactly what Huntington attempted to explain. The reforms happening at a stage when a majority of the population is reliant on the informal economy was an evident policy mis-step that exacerbated the economy that was already bearing the wrath of low oil prices. This can perhaps help us generate a sound ethical justification because here, corruption is not an optional add-on to the system, it is the system itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">A couple of years back, post the implementation of certain paramount structural reforms, Nigerian social media platforms were bizarrely flooded with a rather idiosyncratic hashtag ‘BBOC’, or ‘BringBackOurCorruption’. The laws that were partially aimed at enabling transparency, accountability and a greater oversight of government revenue, with penalisation for infringement extended to incarceration, did not sit well with the public. The government had apparently stolen the ‘grease’ to their economic cycle, which eventually showed in the levels of inflation in the Nigerian economy as well as in a plummeting Nigerian Naira in international markets.</summary></entry></feed>