<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-10T18:21:49+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Vision 20/20</title><link href="/Vision-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vision 20/20" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Vision-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Vision-2020">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Info Edge, it seems, has mastered the maths of running online classifieds in India. Industry observers attribute this success to the fact that customers don’t pay anything to use these platforms, except for Jeevansathi. From listings of jobs, real estate, and education, the company earns most of its revenue from businesses, advertisements, listing fees, and subscription products. This is in sharp contrast to the likes of OLX and Quikr, where a customer has the option to buy a paid listing, but the vast majority of users don’t pay to have their products listed; consequently, they have also burnt through millions of dollars to acquire new customers. However, Info Edge founders do not believe in this philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country’s largest employment website, Naukri, boasts about 67 million résumés and currently has 500,000 job listings on its platform. More than 60% of its revenue comes from the fees it charges from employers for access to its huge résumé database. 99acres, another successful venture of the Info Edge brand was founded in 2005 and is also a leader in its category. As of December 31, 2019, the site had total listings of 1,004,378 properties. It competes with Magicbricks, Commonfloor, and Housing. However, between 2013 and 2016, VC funding was abundantly available, triggering a mushrooming of players in the real estate sector. Backed by the likes of NewsCorp, SoftBank, and Tiger Global Management, startups such as Proptiger, Commonfloor, Housing, Quikr, OLX, Indiahomes, and Indiaproperty started giving 99Acres a tough fight. However, 99acres has held its ground. Jeevansathi is the third-largest matrimonial site in India, after Bharat Matrimony and Shaadi. Online spending on the business is likely to grow to ₹11-12 billion by 2023-24 from ₹7-8 billion in 2020-21. This is expected to give a huge boost to Info Edge’s matrimonial website. Shiksha, the portal providing information on careers, examinations, colleges, and courses is facing stiff competition as there are a lot many major players in the EdTech sector. With the likes of Byju’s, it has become tough for Shiksha to make a strong presence in the Indian EdTech sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bikhchandani had seen potential in classifieds websites when there were just around 14,000 internet accounts in the country and a few thousand users comparing that to the around 500 million users in India now, second only to China’s more than 800 million. It became the early mover in the internet economy, taking many essentials online as India’s population started discovering the joys of a virtually connected world. But as an early mover, Bikhchandani knows the downside of the treadmill. He is aware of the need to continuously make innovations in the fast-changing technological world. For that, Info Edge will leverage its advantage of two decades’ worth of data, using artificial intelligence, data analytics, and machine learning to drive informed change through improved user experiences and new products. Also, Info Edge will continue its 12-year-long practice of investing in ‘ideas’ with the ₹1 billion ‘Info Edge Venture Fund’, launched in January, to fund early-stage startups across categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the first fund by Info Edge, but the company has already invested ₹1.03 billion in 16 startups, including the likes of Zomato and PolicyBazaar. Overall the company has 21 active investments worth ₹1.108 billion at the end of 2020-21. In fact, one of its most successful bets has been restaurant aggregator and food delivery platform Zomato. Bikhchandani, a foodie, had been using Foodiebay (rebranded as Zomato only in 2010). A subsequent conversation with founder Deepinder Goyal set the tone for a business association, and Bikhchandani made an initial investment of ₹40.5 million. Its investment till date is ₹1.52 billion with about 22.7% stake. Zomato has already successfully acquired Uber’s food delivery business in India, Uber Eats. Moreover, PolicyBazaar is expected to receive investment from Google in its bid to expand its digital presence in India. Additionally, the insurance aggregator is also expected to raise $500 million from its Initial Public Offering (IPO) sometime next year. So the prospects of Info Edge cashing out big are right around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While making investments, Bikhchandani not only focuses on the business model but also takes into consideration the commitment, capability, and integrity of founders, and good governance. The importance of these qualities can be understood when fiascos like WeWork and Wirecard occur. Of course, some of the newer business models ask for cash burn to gain market share which is not how Bikhchandani runs his companies. He has always advised startups to get ‘customer money’ before ‘investor money’. Maybe some of the larger funds can learn from this strategy instead of blindly burning cash.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JioMart: The Disruptor?</title><link href="/JioMart" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JioMart: The Disruptor?" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/JioMart</id><content type="html" xml:base="/JioMart">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Don’t find customers for your products, find products for your customers”&lt;/em&gt;, they say, and truly, those who have always thought about their consumers, are the ones whose products have been the most successful. I would not be wrong in saying that the economic development of any country starts and ends with the consumers of that country. Any consumer-related business can rise to great heights if the creators of that business model cater to the needs of the consumers and provide them with efficient services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving along these lines, Mukesh Ambani has now become the fourth richest in the Forbes Global Rich List 2020 as Reliance Industries’ market capitalisation, including the partly paid shares, topped the ₹13 trillion mark. With the recent rise in the e-commerce sector, Reliance Industries has aimed to extend its reach here, which is in contrast with its previous approach wherein they limited themselves to the oil refinery and petroleum sector. To put this in context, we have to take a look at the facts to see why Reliance Industries is where it is today. In the last few years, the launch of Reliance Jio Infocomm Ltd has been able to attract customers even from other rivals such as Vodafone-Idea, Airtel and other telecom operators in India, with its cheap data plans, free calls, and other exciting features. Due to this, it now has the largest user base in India. The launch of Jio was game-changing for India because it redefined the limits of internet usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its e-commerce platform JioMart, Reliance plans to cause a similar disruption that Jio caused in the telecom sector. The aim is to “completely transform”  India’s unorganised retail market of mostly mom-and-pop stores, which account for nearly 90% of the nation’s retail industry. Through this online-offline model, JioMart won’t sell products to the customers directly but instead, it would link the online buyers with offline retailers in their locality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reliance estimates that through this platform it would be able to link 30 million offline retailers with 200 million households. The digital platform, unlike other foreign competitors, would link producers, traders, small merchants, consumer brands, and consumers under a common shed. Hence, JioMart is a strategically planned holistic model that aims to usher in opportunities not only to Reliance Industries but also to other people directly linked to the same industry. Moreover, at a time when other ventures of Reliance in the grocery segment such as Reliance Retail and Reliance Fresh, which have a strong offline presence over the country, are doing quite well, we can expect this online platform to be a ‘cash cow’ for the giant. To make them completely digitised, JioMart claims to integrate local &lt;em&gt;kirana&lt;/em&gt; (corner) stores and provide them with Points of Sale (PoS) terminals, educate them about inventory management skills, supply chain management, and Goods and Service Tax (GST) compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysts and experts are of the view that Facebook’s recent investment in Jio could help JioMart grow. The deal is expected to bear fruits for both the giants. On one side, Jio would gain from the technological expertise that Facebook brings to the table. At the same time, the payments made on the platform through WhatsApp Pay would help the messaging app to overcome the regulatory issues it has been facing. Moreover, Reliance being an already established brand in India would increase the customer base of the Facebook-owned company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to market the online retail platform, Jio has been sending invites to all its users to avail the preliminary discounts. Furthermore, it claims that all its listed products are sold at 5% below the Maximum Retail Price (MRP), this feature is quite similar to DMart’s model that made it quite successful overnight. Additionally, it is still offering the cash-on-delivery option that a lot of existing competitors have stopped. Claims have also been made that JioMart delivers 400,000 orders in a single day which is significantly higher than other grocery home delivery companies. Hence, if JioMart continues working in the same direction, it is bound to give a tough competition to its counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the launch of JioMart, rivals such as Amazon, have started taking steps to maintain their foothold. Amazon has signed a deal with Kishore Biyani’s Future Group to deliver its products. It has also started to broaden the options it provides and has resorted to selective discounting. Amazon has also launched ‘Local Shops’ which has enabled 5,000 offline retailers to set up shop online and has established 10 new warehouses to expand their storage capacity. Additionally, Flipkart said that it would reapply for a food retail license in India. Most importantly, Flipkart has bought Walmart India’s wholesale business in July and is expected to launch a digital marketplace, Flipkart Wholesale in August. So, these already established online platforms have identified the threat being posed by JioMart, and have buckled themselves up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At present, all that we can expect is that with the launch of JioMart, competitive intensity is likely to increase and nothing can be said about who will win the race. Everything is completely dependent upon who would be able to gain the eyes of more consumers and attract them easily with their lucrative offers, but it also seems to be a stiff competition since both JioMart and other established e-commerce websites are leaving no stone unturned. So, whether established e-commerce platforms retain their place or JioMart takes over is what remains to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cherry Sharma</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“Don’t find customers for your products, find products for your customers”, they say, and truly, those who have always thought about their consumers, are the ones whose products have been the most successful. I would not be wrong in saying that the economic development of any country starts and ends with the consumers of that country. Any consumer-related business can rise to great heights if the creators of that business model cater to the needs of the consumers and provide them with efficient services.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Elyments: A Step Towards ‘Atma Nirbhar’ Tech</title><link href="/Elyments" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elyments: A Step Towards ‘Atma Nirbhar’ Tech" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Elyments</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Elyments">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Friends, we have been hearing since the last century that the 21st century belongs to India. This is not our dream, rather a responsibility for all of us.”&lt;/em&gt;  These were the words of the Indian Prime Minister when the ‘Atma Nirbhar’ COVID-19 stimulus package was introduced. The PM seems to be determined to make this dream a reality and has successfully commenced India’s venture in the tech world. Indian Vice President Venkaiah Naidu launched India’s first social media app &lt;em&gt;Elyments&lt;/em&gt; on July 5, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After implementing a ban on Chinese apps, the Indian government decided to set its foot in the tech market and secure a powerful position. The app offers various features of video/voice call, instant messaging as well as social networking. It has encouraged the ‘Make in India’ initiative as it employed 1000 Information Technology (IT) professionals who created the app in a very short period. The aim was to boost confidence and faith in the campaign among fellow citizens. It has been downloaded more than 5 million times since its launch which is huge, considering it’s only been a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the app is being known as the “super app” because of the numerous features it has to offer, it does leave us with a few questions to ponder upon. The success is still undetermined and data security is a big concern among the users. Questions were frequently raised regarding data security in the case of Aadhaar and thus, it makes it difficult for us to trust this app as well. The developers have guaranteed safety and assurance that all data will be stored with the Indian servers itself. No data will be transferred to any third party without the user’s consent. A considerable amount of effort has been made just to ensure data safety and that no lapses are being experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition in this field is tough, with tech giants like Facebook and WhatsApp being the rivals. It becomes more important for the government to offer something new to the consumers. It won’t be a cakewalk for Elyments to secure its position as a strong player. The moment it fails to do so, the investments will boil down to zero making it difficult for the government to establish India in the tech space. The success of an app is determined by its active user base, which isn’t much in the case of Elyments. Developers should prioritise maximum sign-ups in the coming days. I feel the government is seriously lacking in the aspect of marketing the product that they have created. Strategising their moves and giving adequate attention to the required areas will definitely help it grow at a steady and smooth pace. Amid the Indo-Sino standoff, Elyments suffered a cyberattack and successfully recovered from it, which shows that it is capable of competing at a global level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these times of COVID-19 pandemic, when the economy is paying a heavy cost due to it, a failed attempt will be faced with major backlash, and people would not hesitate to highlight it as a waste of the taxpayer’s money. Further, this one failure will allow the rivals to regain control, thus making it even more difficult to enter the circle again. On the bright side, if it turns out to be a success, it will boost the economy and open up the gateway to ‘Made in India’ tech. This beginning will ensure a promising future for our young minds and a strong foothold of India in this domain. The vision of Atma Nirbhar Bharat will become a reality and the faith will be restored. Furthermore, there have never been any doubts regarding the brainpower that India possesses in terms of IT. Being the manufacturer of CEOs for tech companies around the world, it is time for India to focus on a homegrown giant and take over the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“Friends, we have been hearing since the last century that the 21st century belongs to India. This is not our dream, rather a responsibility for all of us.” These were the words of the Indian Prime Minister when the ‘Atma Nirbhar’ COVID-19 stimulus package was introduced. The PM seems to be determined to make this dream a reality and has successfully commenced India’s venture in the tech world. Indian Vice President Venkaiah Naidu launched India’s first social media app Elyments on July 5, 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accountability: An Illusion in Reality</title><link href="/An-Illusion-in-Reality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accountability: An Illusion in Reality" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/An-Illusion-in-Reality</id><content type="html" xml:base="/An-Illusion-in-Reality">&lt;p&gt;India is grappling with a spike in COVID-19 cases—even by the current earliest estimates, the peak is anywhere but close. Amidst the escalating tensions with neighbours Nepal and China, it has set the ball rolling for what is the most difficult test of governance for the incumbent Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what still remains obscure amidst this pandemonium is India’s interminable tryst with sustainable development—maintaining an equipoise of biodiversity and urbanisation. As the country went through phases of lockdowns, the Indian Environment Ministry, led by Prakash Javedkar, uploaded the reformed version of the EIA, which was last amended in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new legislation has led to a huge outcry among environmentalists, for it dilutes the ‘green law’­­—which compelled infrastructure projects to clear the scrutiny of its impact on the environment, and also involved the public. This update was approved by Javedkar and his predecessor, Dr Harsh Vardhan, after being drafted and updated within two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister, who spoke parables and platitudes pertaining to self-reliance, exhorted people to support indigenous brands and products. The growing Sinophobia has culminated with multinational brands such as Apple announcing shift of its manufacturing facilities to India, much to the delight of the average Indian, thumping to celebrate it as an embellishment to the nationalistic pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, what most Indians fail to notice, or passively take cognizance of, is the toll such ambitious manufacturing would take on the environment. This sets a dangerous premise, especially when India’s track record in sustainable development has been mediocre, to be modest, it dates back to the Nehru days. Jawaharlal Nehru famously said to the villagers displaced by the Hirakud Dam in 1948, &lt;em&gt;“If you must suffer, you should suffer in the interest of the country”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s obsession with building dams, despite most studies highlighting their futility, continues to haunt the tribal people living in the hinterlands. The Sardar Sarovar Dam is the country’s prime example of the environmental racism that continues to elude the front pages of the newspapers. Harrowing tales narrated by Man Booker Prize-winning author Arundhati Roy exposes the deepest trenches of social and economic oppression that the tribal landowners are subjected to after being deprived of the very land that is paramount to their survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unaware of how money works in urban dwellings, the displaced people are often stuffed into slum-like residences, sardonically quoted as urban ghettos. Not only are the displaced people forced to work as labourers, the conditions in which they live, far away from their homeland, raise concerns, especially with the country neck-deep in the contagion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To salvage themselves from the perils of a recession looming large at the economy, the government also decided to auction off 41 of its coal mines, many of which are located in the Hasdeo Arand region of Chhattisgarh—which is home to many tribal communities, for it is one of the largest contiguous dense forest areas in India. Privatisation would definitely place them under the threat of being displaced as well as the perils of pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arunachal Pradesh, which is one of the most diverse regions in the country with 26 tribal groups and 100 sub-tribal groups, is home to a 3,097-megawatt Etalin Dam. It is expected to submerge over 300,000 trees and affect Idu Mishmi, an indigenous tribe with a population of over 13,000. Additionally, the 2,880-megawatt Dibang Multipurpose Project, one of the largest planned projects in India, is set to displace nearly 2,000 Mishmi people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the dilution of the EIA, new biodiversity hotspots like Arunachal Pradesh would be set up, especially after the aforementioned projects having been approved without a dialogue with the major stakeholders - the displaced tribal groups. With only 3 Members of Parliament from Arunachal Pradesh, this minuscule representation has also been attributed to environmental racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EIA is essential for India, especially when the country has projects operational without proper environmental clearance. It was found out that the LG Polymer Plant in Vishakapatnam, from which styrene gas was leaked on May 7, was functional for over 20 years without any clearance. A similar incident was reported in Assam where the natural gas of Oil India Limited in the Tinsukia district was incinerated, causing severe damage to local biodiversity. The local environmental authority later released a statement accusing that the plant was running without their approval for the past 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conflagrating a movement for the environment with a law meant for seditious and extremism activities is alarming. A shallow EIA favouring builders with easy environmental clearances can increase incidents in Assam and Andhra Pradesh. It would further push a hitherto obscure yet an important section of the population residing for generations into oblivion. Meanwhile, an EIA report has recently stated that an estimated 33,000 trees would be cut to make way for the proposed Peripheral Ring Road in Bengaluru, from the proposed 200 trees in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unchecked environmental legislation could not only be the final blow to an already bludgeoning biodiversity but can also fan the flames of a humanitarian crisis, for fulfilling the fetishes of the rich.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Kant</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">India is grappling with a spike in COVID-19 cases—even by the current earliest estimates, the peak is anywhere but close. Amidst the escalating tensions with neighbours Nepal and China, it has set the ball rolling for what is the most difficult test of governance for the incumbent Prime Minister.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Icarus Paradox: Why Successful Ventures Fail?</title><link href="/Icarus-Paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Icarus Paradox: Why Successful Ventures Fail?" /><published>2020-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Icarus-Paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Icarus-Paradox">&lt;p&gt;Though most people deem pride as transgression, some appraise it as a trait that can be capitalised upon. Research teams at the University of Montreal and UC Santa Barbara’s Center for Evolutionary Psychology (CEP) suggest that pride is an evolutionary by-product of the trait of self-preservation. Because of the frequent lethal reversals that our ancestors faced, they needed their fellow band members to value them enough during hardships to pull them through. Therefore, in making choices, humans had to weigh their self-interest over the approval of others, so that when they needed help, others would value them enough to give it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though we have come a long way, &lt;em&gt;hubris&lt;/em&gt; is still not hard to come across. Irrespective of the peculiarity of its radix, pride is not limited to individuals - organisations also emanate it. The anomaly, however, is that organisational hubris is just a compendium of the egos of individuals who comprise it, but people in an organisation struggle to keep their individual pride in parity with the organisational one. Therefore, in theory, there is no comprehensible line distinguishing individual pride from organisational pride, as one is a concoction of the other. The practical aspect, however, differentiates between the magnitude and gravity of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanity is believed to be the root of all sin by cultures across the globe. While the widely followed Abrahamic religions talk about the spiritual descent of Lucifer into Satan as a result of his pride, the Greeks present the tale of Icarus. Icarus was the son of Daedalus - a famous Greek inventor. While in captivity, Daedalus crafted two pairs of wings which would enable him and his son to escape certain execution. Before taking off, Daedalus specifically instructed his son not to fly too high. Ignoring the words of his father, Icarus soared too near to the clouds, which ultimately led to his wings failing him. The boy plummeted to his death in the sea because his pride clouded his judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Danny Miller coined the term ‘Icarus Paradox’ in 1990. The term, alluding to the Greek tale, refers to the phenomenon of businesses suddenly failing after a period of success, where this failure is brought about by the very elements that led to their initial uprise. Miller noted that it’s the victories of the past that conceit a successful organisation, lulling them into complacency. The very values that usher companies upwards in the pecking order - such as tried-and-true business strategies, dauntless and self-assured management, and the overall combination of all these elements - may be rendered blunt and platitudinous, ultimately leading to business catastrophes. Managers tend to make injudicious decisions, as they cling onto the past success of their manoeuvres and fail to factor in the revamp in the external business environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most successful firms owe their fortune to a unique competitive algorithm which guides the formulation and execution of their policies. It helps it gain momentum and reach a higher pedestal, but cloaks its dynamism and its ability to acclimatise because the management’s confidence in this winning formula is bolstered. Eventually, the firm ends up focusing only on refining and extending these strategies, products and values. Activities/policies that do not conform to the paradigm are neglected or even discouraged. This may be profitable in the short run as companies continue to specialise and improve in a certain product or strategy, leading to higher efficiency, sales and growth as they develop a competitive advantage in a particular area. However, its viability is leached away in the long run, as the stereotypical aspect ingrained in their corporate culture barres them from keeping up with the threats of new competitors, changing consumer demands, newly developed business models and changes in the external environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standard economic theory explains the high rate of failures as an inevitable result of companies taking rational risks in the face of peaky situations. The rewards of a few successes outweigh losses incurred from many failures in the long run. Executives know this and accept the risk. Anyhow, this theory absolves them from blame as they simply obey rationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lovallo and Kahneman from the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/em&gt;, however, argue that most failures are actually the results of flawed decision making. While predicting the outcomes of potentially risky projects, executives easily fall victim to what psychologists call the ‘planning fallacy’. They make decisions based on delusional optimism instead of rational computation of gains, losses, and probabilities, dwelling in situations of hypothetical success while overlooking potential problems. Consequently, they are overly optimistic and pursue opportunities that are unlikely to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prime example of the paradox at work would be Tesco’s experimental venture into the US market – Fresh &amp;amp; Easy. Tesco opened the chain in 2007- right before the economic recession which took a severe toll on consumer spending. Tesco also did not anticipate the upshot in the popularity of online grocery shopping. Additionally, Tesco’s research segment misconstrued the spending habits of their consumer base. While their Metro stores in the UK were popular, there was not enough demand in the US as the population was not accustomed to grab-and-go meals. Most of the Americans would usually order take out or cook their own meals - as purchasing such meals would be comparatively costlier than grocery shopping. Lastly, an elementary point of distinction was the statistics indicating that most people in the US buy their groceries once a week, with bulk and diversity of purchase being the key takeaways. Conversely, Europeans tend to make more frequent, but smaller trips to the grocery stores. After they took a hit of approximately £1.2bn ($1.8bn), Tesco’s net profit slithered down by 96%, compelling them to abandon the US market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, Tesco’s confidence in bringing its successful concept of ready meals to the US market contributed heavily to its failure. The intensive marketing required to change people’s daily consumption proclivities takes time and money, neither of which Tesco invested enough of. Tesco was also confident enough to continue to hang on for over 5 years despite indications of possible failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above example highlights &lt;em&gt;hubris&lt;/em&gt; in its raw essence, which can be used as a base for conceptual bifurcation, creating multiple subdivisions rooted in the same basic concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Humans have a natural tendency to amplify their own talents, which leads a lot of executives to believe that they transcend the rest in ability and output. This is further reinforced by the tendency to misperceive causes of certain events and attribute success to their abilities when it might have been out of pure luck.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People also display keenness to take credit for positive outcomes and ascribe undesirable ones to external factors. A study of letters to shareholders in annual reports, for example, found that managers tend to attribute favourable outcomes to variables under their control, like corporate strategy or R&amp;amp;D (research and development) programs, while inimical ones were more likely to be attributed to uncontrollable external factors like the weather or inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A company’s values unify its people. Strong, meaningful credos can help inculcate employee loyalty, strengthen the bonds between a company and its customers, attract like-minded partners, and hold together a company’s far-flung operations. However, as companies mature, these values may morph into commandments- which contribute more towards suppressing novelty and flexibility, rather than inspiring moral conduct.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A peculiar observation made in business process analysis is that, as more investment is made in information technology, worker productivity may go down instead of going up. This observation has been firmly supported by empirical evidence from the 1970’s to the early 1990’s. Prior to the upward jolt in IT investment, the expected return on investment in terms of productivity was 3-4%. The aberration, however, was that with IT, the normal return on investment was only 1% from the 1970’s to the early 1990’s. Thus, the investment in IT - done for performance enhancement - led to contradictory outcomes that threatened to pick the organisation apart. This is known as the ‘paradox of information technology’- a concept encapsulated by the Icarus paradox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it may seem easy to deal with, the paradox is a trap that is too hard to escape, with companies like Lehman Brothers, Xerox, Atari, Digital Equipment, Tupperware and Revlon on the victim list. Also, a lot of unforeseen complications arise upon the initial implementation of solutions. The key is an optimum blend of flexibility, innovation, and diversification, which needs to be instilled in the bedrock of the organisational structure of business entities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aryaman Dhiman</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Though most people deem pride as transgression, some appraise it as a trait that can be capitalised upon. Research teams at the University of Montreal and UC Santa Barbara’s Center for Evolutionary Psychology (CEP) suggest that pride is an evolutionary by-product of the trait of self-preservation. Because of the frequent lethal reversals that our ancestors faced, they needed their fellow band members to value them enough during hardships to pull them through. Therefore, in making choices, humans had to weigh their self-interest over the approval of others, so that when they needed help, others would value them enough to give it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shutting Our Doors?</title><link href="/Shutting-Our-Doors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shutting Our Doors?" /><published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Shutting-Our-Doors</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Shutting-Our-Doors">&lt;p&gt;Observation has reached its peak for me as I find my eyes looking for details behind each jar of Nutella or on the side of our microwave. All thanks to the lockdown that has dragged me back home from college and given me enough free time to look around the house with a magnifying glass, which I wouldn’t have done otherwise on my busy school days as a child. And observation, mixed with a little bit of research, has led me to the understanding that my house, which in fact buys everything from local stores, actually reeks of products from China. From the water geyser to the processor in the ceiling fan, from the dinner crockery to the food processor, from parts of our mobile phones to our daily t-shirts, nothing is spared from the clenching claws of China. The fact that all these products were available to us in the local stores at prices comfortable enough for our pockets, speaks volumes about the kind of consumerism China has created in each and every household, office, company, factory, industry and restaurant in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calls to boycott Chinese goods had started gaining momentum when the martyrdom of twenty Indian soldiers in the Ladakh stand-off against China aroused public sentiment, and they took to their hands to avenge the soldiers’ deaths by publicly breaking TV sets of Chinese brands. These calls couldn’t have gone unnoticed by the government which then had to take a step to show India’s hostility towards China. A violent uprising, that had cost us our soldiers’ lives, very recently, was discarded as a move from our end, also taking into account that China had retreated from the Indian borders. Now the question was :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Can India afford to boycott China?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feasibilities of numbers of steps like - import reduction, import-substitution, self-reliance, and lastly, a blanket ban - were pondered upon. While the other options were on the table, considering the sentimental charge of the public, the possible implications of a blanket ban were considered. A blanket ban is a complete prohibition, which in this case would mean banning not just imports from China but also trade and investment. A superpower like the US has openly made hate speeches on China and has also taken moves such as shutting down a Chinese consulate in Texas. But considering the Indian economy’s huge dependence on China, can India really impose a blanket ban on China and move to self-reliance as quickly as we think? A step-by-step analysis will help us understand the implications of this move better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade:&lt;/strong&gt; The Indian economy is heavily dependent on Chinese imports that include intermediate and finished goods. Intermediate goods from China, such as chemicals, pharmaceuticals, electronic components, have long helped industries in India sustain. But if India wishes to take a few steps back in its trading chain with China, India will have to adopt medium to long-term policy moves. These include, but are not restricted to, financial support or subsidising micro, small and medium businesses that can actually manufacture the products that we import from China. The informal sector in the production chain in India, with the right kind of policy support, can eventually lead us to self-reliance in a matter of a few years. However, a step backwards in the import chain from China could also mean opening doors to imports from other countries. For India to become a favourable import destination, certain financial supports like import duty exemption and cash subsidy on imports from other countries are necessary to match the cost of Chinese imports. In the short-term, expediting Free Trade Agreements (FTAs) to lure imports and investments from other countries is one of the most viable options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investment:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian start-ups, with the right kind of investment boost, have a tendency of growing big in this ever-evolving capitalistic world of ours. But a lot of local start-ups fail to garner the kind of investment from major Indian ventures, which is what China has taken advantage of for close to a decade now. Alibaba, invested in an Indian start-up Paytm, back in 2015 when the future of Paytm itself was bleak, but China slyly took advantage of the gap in investment that existed. Moreover, China has not blinked an eye before investing in a lot of local start-ups, knowing very well that like most other start-ups, these too may be loss-making. The reason behind this is that China is ready to make a trade-off of investing in a loss-making start-up to be able to get a footing in the market share of the Indian market. Eventually, when the local start-ups grow enough to have a valuation of over $1 billion and come under the category of ‘Unicorns’, is when it finally comes to our eyes that the major Indian start-ups, like Snapdeal, Ola, Swiggy, Paytm, Flipkart and so many more, have a Chinese investor. To combat the issue of Chinese investors, like Alibaba, monopolising in the Indian market by investing in most Indian unicorns and creating an obvious outsized impact, the Indian government decided to amend the Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) rules to cap off the number of companies an investor can invest in, so as to prevent any hostile takeovers of the Indian market by any foreign investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology:&lt;/strong&gt; We’re no aliens to the fact that China practically holds the lion’s share in the smartphone market of India, while India has little to no alternatives in the smartphone arena. It would require huge amounts of investment in research and technology to be able to reduce dependence on China for smartphone technology and components. In addition, Chinese tech firms, like Alibaba, and apps like TikTok, reach the Indian consumers as much as applications like Google, Amazon, Facebook, and Instagram. The Indian government has recently made a move to ban the likes of these Chinese applications that actually have local alternatives, and this as a strategic move has a lasting impact on the kind of hostility India wants to opt for. In fact, a restriction in the telecommunications sector, such as banning Huawei, is also a feasible move considering that Indian alternatives, such as Jio and BSNL, are easily available to the Indian consumers. To top it off, Huawei could also be banned from India’s 5G rollout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, answering the bigger question: &lt;em&gt;Can India really shut its doors by imposing a blanket ban on China&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, a blanket ban on China will result in a very quick supply disruption leaving the Indian consumers exposed to only a minimal amount of not-so-pocket friendly alternatives. Furthermore, the economy will have to bear high input costs and therefore, this move will prove to be a costly one for India. Instead, the viable solution would be to allow steady withdrawal of Chinese products by allowing import substitution as well as funding the budding industries in the unorganised sector. India will have to take slow steps forward, keeping in mind cost-effectiveness and affordability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Observation has reached its peak for me as I find my eyes looking for details behind each jar of Nutella or on the side of our microwave. All thanks to the lockdown that has dragged me back home from college and given me enough free time to look around the house with a magnifying glass, which I wouldn’t have done otherwise on my busy school days as a child. And observation, mixed with a little bit of research, has led me to the understanding that my house, which in fact buys everything from local stores, actually reeks of products from China. From the water geyser to the processor in the ceiling fan, from the dinner crockery to the food processor, from parts of our mobile phones to our daily t-shirts, nothing is spared from the clenching claws of China. The fact that all these products were available to us in the local stores at prices comfortable enough for our pockets, speaks volumes about the kind of consumerism China has created in each and every household, office, company, factory, industry and restaurant in India.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gandhi, a ‘Mahatma’?</title><link href="/Gandhi-a-Mahatma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gandhi, a 'Mahatma'?" /><published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Gandhi-a-Mahatma</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Gandhi-a-Mahatma">&lt;p&gt;In June 2020, an online petition to remove Mahatma Gandhi’s statue in the British city of Leicester was filed which had garnered 6,052 signatures, as of July 30, 2020. The bronze statue in Leicester, which captures Gandhi in his walking stride, was unveiled in the city in 2009. The petition titled ‘Remove the Gandhi Statue in Leicester’ accuses him of being “a fascist, racist and sexual predator”. It further says, “&lt;em&gt;For years he has been idolised and taught in the school curriculum. For many people in my community, he has brought inconsolable suffering against my people. As a result, I do not wish to see a statue and praise of that kind of character. Therefore, I want to take action to remove it&lt;/em&gt;”. According to the Leicester City Council, the petition hasn’t been submitted to the authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar online petition was filed in the Canadian city of Ottawa in June 2020 calling for the removal of Gandhi’s statue from the Carleton University Campus. As of July 30, 2020, it had garnered 2,563 signatures. Echoing similar sentiments as the Leicester petition, it says, “&lt;em&gt;Why should an institution continue to yield the statue of an individual who was publicly anti-black, referred to Africans as savages, likening them to animals, and slept naked with his grandniece to ‘test his willpower’? It is inexplicable and inexcusable. As an institution, we cannot claim to champion diversity and seek to eradicate institutionalised racism as long as symbols like this are still present on our campus. The time for action is now&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These petitions come after a series of statues of racist people being removed. On May 25, 2020, an African-American man, George Floyd, was murdered in Minneapolis by a white Police officer. His death sparked a series of protests against police brutality and racial inequality all over the world. The Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement of 2020, has put the past to scrutiny by targeting the monuments and statues of people who carry the legacy of slavery and colonialism: the Confederate General Robert E Lee in Virginia, Theodore Roosevelt in New York City, Christopher Columbus in many US cities, the Belgian king Leopold II in Brussels, the slave trader Edward Colston in Bristol, Jean-Baptiste Colbert, Finance Minister for Louis XIV and author of the infamous Code Noir in France, Indro Montanelli, and so on. Their statues are being toppled, defaced, destroyed and vandalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi is known as the renowned Indian lawyer-turned-activist who led India to independence. However, he, too, was an imperfect human being. Rajmohan Gandhi, Gandhi’s biographer, and grandson has previously admitted that his grandfather was “at times ignorant and prejudiced towards South Africa’s blacks”. Several academics have noted reports of Gandhi’s derogatory views towards native Africans while he lived in South Africa in the late 19th century. Gandhi wrote to the Natal Parliament in 1893, “&lt;em&gt;A general belief seems to prevail in the Colony that the Indians are a little better, if at all, than savages or the Natives of Africa&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1904, he wrote to a health officer in Johannesburg that the council “must withdraw Kaffirs” from an unsanitary slum called the “Coolie Location” where a large number of Africans lived alongside Indians. He wrote, “&lt;em&gt;About the mixing of the Kaffirs with the Indians, I must confess I feel most strongly&lt;/em&gt;”. The same year he wrote that unlike the African, the Indian had no “war-dances, nor does he drink Kaffir beer”. During the Durban plague in 1905, Gandhi wrote that the problem would persist as long as Indians and Africans were being herded together indiscriminately at the hospital. The term *&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-34265882&quot;&gt;kaffi*r&lt;/a&gt; is considered a racial slur used to refer to indigenous Black South Africans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book, &lt;em&gt;The South African Gandhi: Stretcher-Bearer of Empire&lt;/em&gt;, Ashwin Desai and Goolam H Vahed wrote that during his stay in Africa, Gandhi kept the Indian struggle separate from Africa’s, despite the fact that the latter was also being denied political rights based on colour. Further, Ashwin Desai, professor of Sociology at the University of Johannesburg, described Gandhi as a man who “supported more taxes on impoverished African people and turned a blind eye to the brutality of the Empire on Africans”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, owing to his work during the Indian independence struggle, many people have come to defend the statue. Leicester East Member of Parliament Claudia Webbe called the petition a “massive distraction” from the BLM movement. Comparing Gandhi to Martin Luther King, the Labour politician said, &lt;em&gt;“Gandhi, too, created a movement the same way Martin Luther King did, which became a force for change&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faisal Devji, a professor of Indian history at Oxford University, described the debate to remove the statue as absurd. He added, “&lt;em&gt;He’s a fallible man as all men are, but to lump him in with slave owners, that’s a bit much&lt;/em&gt;”. Citing the importance of the statue, he calls it a representation of the large refugee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-leicestershire-53025407&quot;&gt;Gujarati community in the city&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This protest is not the first time people have called out Gandhi’s racist beliefs. London had witnessed protests against Gandhi’s statues in 2003 and 2008. Similarly, American states like California, San Francisco, Michigan and Texas have witnessed such protests in 2013, 2011, 2010, and 2014, respectively. Johannesburg too witnessed one in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2016, an online petition started by professors at the University of Ghana called for the removal of Gandhi’s statue from the university’s Legon campus. The statue was erected in June 2016 at the Recreational Quadrangle and is the only statue of a historical personality on campus. Supporting the BLM movement, Dr Obadele Kambon, the creator of the petition, told BBC, “&lt;em&gt;At the end of the day, we need images of ourselves for our psychosocial well-being and not images of those who called us savages. May Gandhi fall that Africa may rise!&lt;/em&gt;” In 2018, this statue was removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2019, students from Manchester called for a similar statue of Gandhi given to the city by Shrimad Rajchandra Mission Dharampur (SRMD) to be removed because of his “well-documented anti-black racism”. In an open letter, the students demanded the Council acknowledge his vile comments and issue an apology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statues of historical figures don’t help people learn about history, but merely place certain figures on pedestals. While the past can no longer be changed, and society evolves to become more cognizant of other identities, we need to take a stand about whom we place on a celebration. The protests against these statues do just that. For instance, in the city of Bristol, England, a statue of Black Lives Matter protester Jen Reid was placed on an empty plinth where a monument to a 17th-century slave trader had stood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, while the statues in Leicester and Ottawa still stand tall, we must also question the actions of those whom we glorify. Additionally, to what extent shall we pedestalise these people? If you focus on only one part of their life, are you ignoring their other work? Does their noble work negate their wrongdoings? Can we hold them accountable for their wrongdoings? And if so, what is the best method?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While discriminating against any section of people is unacceptable, I hold the opinion that we cannot view our ancestor’s actions with a presentist lens - the tendency to interpret past events in terms of modern values and concepts. We all too often colour history with our lens of current prejudices. Fritz Fischer, a German historian, was against presentism as it allowed people to skew history in a way that would validate their own political beliefs. Thus, a 21st-century inclusive society must also take note of the attitudes and cultural values that existed in the past. Gandhi grew up in an orthodox Hindu family. Thus, his actions were a product of his time and a manifestation of the attitudes that existed then. This, however, is not to say that we should let him off the hook. Instead, we shall create a space where all of his actions can equally co-exist, instead of seeing him in the binary of a good or a bad person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our forebears will always fail to measure up to our modern standards, but it is not to say that any of these findings are irrelevant. While bygones will be bygones, we can accept the past and readily evolve ourselves, as a society, to ensure we no longer make similar mistakes. This also encompasses being tolerant of diverging opinions, especially those which stem out of lived experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In June 2020, an online petition to remove Mahatma Gandhi’s statue in the British city of Leicester was filed which had garnered 6,052 signatures, as of July 30, 2020. The bronze statue in Leicester, which captures Gandhi in his walking stride, was unveiled in the city in 2009. The petition titled ‘Remove the Gandhi Statue in Leicester’ accuses him of being “a fascist, racist and sexual predator”. It further says, “For years he has been idolised and taught in the school curriculum. For many people in my community, he has brought inconsolable suffering against my people. As a result, I do not wish to see a statue and praise of that kind of character. Therefore, I want to take action to remove it”. According to the Leicester City Council, the petition hasn’t been submitted to the authority.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What We Misunderstand about Eastern Europe’s ‘Populists’</title><link href="/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What We Misunderstand about Eastern Europe’s 'Populists'" /><published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists">&lt;p&gt;The world is full of unsavoury leaders, and the media does its best to cover the worst of them. I felt real pride for the BBC last week when Andrew Marr took apart the Chinese Ambassador live on air for the Chinese human rights abuses against the Uighurs. The Prime Minister of India is truly low-calibre; when I type his surname, I chuckle as I see “Modi” hasn’t yet made it into Microsoft Word’s dictionary. Even “Uighurs” is in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That aside, I have been bemused in recent years at how much time the BBC and other news sites have devoted to covering one loose group of world leaders - Eastern Europe’s conservative populists. I remember last year Channel 4 followed a short segment on the murder of Jamal Khashoggi with a half-an-hour report on the worrying trend towards nationalism in Hungary, Poland and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with Eastern European politics, it is true that populists have firmly broken into the mainstream in the region since the early 2010’s. Hungary and Poland both have nationalist Prime Ministers in Viktor Orban and Mateusz Morawiecki respectively, and Russia’s Vladimir Putin has taken a noticeably more conservative line since he returned to the Presidency in 2012. All these leaders claim to be bastions of sovereignty, economic independence and Christian morality. In the social sphere, this means trashing multiculturalism, LGBT rights and urban elites. Economically, they are social democrats; Poland’s governing Law and Justice Party gives families a stipend for having children, and Orban took control of Hungary’s central bank to increase social spending. Although their outlooks are similar, there is some water between the three leaders; Orban is agnostic on Russia, while Poland is a strong North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) backer. Neither Orban nor Law and Justice have good words to say about bad press, but they are not as heavy-handed as Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of all this, I struggle to muster up much concern about these governments. Would I vote for these people myself? Probably not. Like any reasonable person, I condemn Putin’s shameless attacks on his opponents. I grew up in the English city where elements of the Russian ‘securocracy’ tried to poison two of its own citizens. In Poland, Law and Justice’s attempt to hold an election at the peak of the coronavirus was a naked power-grab. I’m not a religious zealot. So, on balance, I wouldn’t choose these leaders for my own country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is exactly the point. They are not running my country, they are running theirs. Instead of assessing these leaders based on our own standards and norms, we should look at developments in Eastern Europe in perspective and context. To those who spend their time attacking these governments, I would make two points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly on democracy, don’t fall into the trap of thinking the world started the day the Berlin Wall fell. We might have a rosy view of European politics, where democracy knows no bounds, but this isn’t a perspective shared by many in Poland and Hungary. While my grandparents’ generation was enjoying the sleepy prosperity of 1950’s Britain, Hungarians were being gunned down on the Danube by Soviet tanks. It would be a big stretch to draw an equivalency between the current leaders of these countries and their communist predecessors. Modern Hungarians and Poles do not, thankfully, live under a police state. Putin may be more sinister, but he isn’t engaged in an ideological battle to take over the world, in the mould of Stalin or Khrushchev. He doesn’t shoot anyone who tries to flee his country. Real authoritarianism is woven deep into the Eastern subconscious, which helps to explain why the people there are willing to tolerate a level of thuggery and brashness in their politics, which we would not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, if you don’t like these leaders, you ought to ask yourself whether Western dealings with Eastern Europe has made nationalism more or less appealing to the people who live there. I think the answer is obvious. If they must be grouped together, Orban, Putin and Morawiecki, all represent a reaction against economically and socially liberal policies imposed quite forcefully on their countries by the US State Department, the EU and the IMF from the 1990’s onwards: freer trade, privatisation, state secularism and free elections. In all these countries, especially in Russia, most of these policies proved to be a disaster. In Hungary and Poland, inflation and unemployment surged to double digits, and the end of state subsidies and protections meant that Hungary lost over two-thirds of its export markets in four years. The Russian democratic process was quickly colonised by old Soviet politicians eager to line their pockets, a period harrowingly recounted in Svetlana Alexievich’s &lt;em&gt;Second-hand Time&lt;/em&gt;. Russia, along with most of Eastern Europe, is far more unequal now than it was thirty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people in these countries, especially the poor, did not want these policies. They still don’t want them now, and they have voted for people who articulate something different. I would wager that in years to come, other European countries will do the same, and they shouldn’t be berated for that. In fact, I often find myself wishing that we, in Britain, France or Scandinavia, had the guts to reject the parties and policies of the last twenty years which have brought us such unhappiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I feel the need to state that I don’t have much time for Putin and Co.’s treatment of the press. I’m not trying to justify their brand of politics. What I am saying, though, is that if we are going to criticise these governments, we at least ought to understand why people voted for them. It’s worth pointing out that polls tend to show that Eastern Europeans are now more optimistic about their futures than the British, French and Italians are about theirs. Sure, optimism alone is no indicator of good government, but it does suggest a degree of contentment. And I’d take contentment over whatever it is we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guest</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The world is full of unsavoury leaders, and the media does its best to cover the worst of them. I felt real pride for the BBC last week when Andrew Marr took apart the Chinese Ambassador live on air for the Chinese human rights abuses against the Uighurs. The Prime Minister of India is truly low-calibre; when I type his surname, I chuckle as I see “Modi” hasn’t yet made it into Microsoft Word’s dictionary. Even “Uighurs” is in there.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal</title><link href="/Online-Delivery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal" /><published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Online-Delivery</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Online-Delivery">&lt;p&gt;Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This market inversion has led to a growth of online delivery marketplaces, with even bigger market players in other segments pivoting their business strategies around home delivery. Delivery service marketplaces have inverted from demand-constrained to supply-constrained almost overnight, but new entrants in the delivery space have reportedly struggled with profits, reporting a boost in sales but thin margins. They claim that it is not terribly profitable, and it probably gets unprofitable with more orders. While many restaurants and supermarkets prefer the lower costs and hassle of having customers collect orders at stores, others see it as a threat to their existing customer relationships that could have been better taken care of, had the customers walked into the store. Online delivery was never a core part of these supplier’s revenue and made up only a small chunk of the total orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues and challenges that marketplaces face today are logistical and reputational, arising from increased demand and customer awareness rather than challenges arising from low consumer penetration and slim demand for services. Consumers are holding brands and companies to a higher standard than previously, favouring those perceived as doing more for society. Pre-crisis, a common complaint on the platforms was that drivers weren’t receiving enough orders. Now, those same drivers are overwhelmed with demand, and platforms have to figure out how to build product solutions to help stores balance their delivery loads. There have been inventory stockouts, closed stores, and supply chain disruptions due to COVID-19 — all while the customer service team has been inundated with order volume. That’s consistent with the experience of all mid-sized delivery platforms, and even that of Amazon. These platforms have had to switch their focus overnight and develop expertise around the new supply-side constraints. The bigger problem here is that many suppliers didn’t have the infrastructure set up to make delivery work at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among all vociferous trumpets about ‘the demise of commuting’, ‘the death of retail’, and ‘the collapse of globalisation’, many executives have come to assume that everything will change accordingly when the recipe for survival is supposed to be a thorough transformation. The economic crisis does not necessarily spell the end of entire industries or companies but it does weed out business models that fail to pivot towards the new reality characterised by shorter value chains, remote work, social distancing, consumer introspection, and enhanced usage of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, now is the time for marketplaces to help their suppliers invest in infrastructure and technology, and indulge in business practices that will enable them to compete in a world in which having a delivery sales presence is essential. Now is the time for them to shift their focus from customer acquisition and retention to investment in metrics for supporting retailer operations. Platforms can be a part of the supplier side transition which, in fact, is happening organically. With in-person retail restricted or outright eliminated, suppliers have been reimagining their store layouts and operations around online fulfilment and omnichannel retail, simultaneously leveraging marketplace platforms, a self-managed online presence, and traditional in-person sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can identify and share best practices around staffing and delivery processes, and provide technology solutions to help small businesses optimise their operations around delivery, with, for example, cloud-based inventory logs and modern point-of-sale systems. Marketplace platforms have vision into the whole market, which enables them to predict demand — an advantage they should use to the benefit of their suppliers. This could be helpful in forecasting when to schedule extra drivers on an hour-by-hour basis, and staffing driver teams in direct proportion to order volume. This can also increase capital efficiency by helping stores match inventory levels to predict future demand. Platforms can lower their tax rates to increase supplier participation — especially among chains and other established supplier networks. Food delivery marketplaces’ supplier-weighted cost structure may have worked when restaurants saw having a small stream of delivery orders as a promotional subsidy for in-person traffic — but it isn’t working in the current, in-person demand constrained marketplace environment. Likewise, some fees should be shifted over to the consumers, since they’re now the ‘long’ side of the market. In particular, it might make sense to institute per-order delivery fees, to encourage consumers to place large delivery orders instead of more frequent small ones, as well as to make it more valuable for a retailer to take an additional order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before COVID-19, a delivery service’s performance was mostly determined by convenience, speed and price. Now, by contrast, safety, availability and breadth of selection are the new priorities. Customers are placing bigger orders and are comfortable with longer lead times with ‘acceptable’ estimated time of arrival windows widening. Platforms also have the leeway to shift customer service efforts to prioritise responsiveness to retailers and allocate developer resources towards solving suppliers’ operational problems. All these solutions will help keep in place, exactly the right products on the supplier’s shelves. These improvements will benefit both parties but would require information sharing and communication on the part of the platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When suppliers make the best or most effective use of marketplace transactions, the consumer experience on the platform improves too — often due to increased availability, selection and price options. Overall, this results in much higher conversion rates: a customer with three stores and 1,000 items to choose from spends 67% more per session than a customer facing just one store with 300 items. Orders are processed more smoothly, and with fewer errors that will help translate fleeting customer relations into stronger consumer engagement post-crisis. Better and more optimised choices lead to more bargaining power in the hands of the customers, thereby increasing satisfaction and chances of application reuse. Bars and restaurants will eventually reopen and consumers will become comfortable shopping for goods in-person again but the supplier networks that marketplace platforms build will remain. When platforms invest in suppliers as partners, those suppliers will come out of the crisis stronger, improving the customer experience in the long run. It’s a three-way win — for suppliers, platforms and consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As worried consumers move to shop more online, choosing online platforms is an easy decision — with a click of the button, they can buy almost anything. But for sellers, doing business with them is a less straightforward proposition. Although partnering opens up access to more customers and offers operational efficiencies, brands risk leveraging power in favour of the platforms. Thus, they face an unavoidable dilemma — form the partnership and risk ceding profits, or eschew the partnership and forgo the operational cost savings and access to new customers. A big threat to these established brands is consumers’ increased willingness to experiment with different offerings during the crisis. Research suggests that consumers react badly even when the bad news extends beyond the company to its supply chain. They are more likely to believe that a company’s product is inferior in quality when there is a supply chain mishap, even when the product quality has nothing to do with the supply chain problem. They assume a product has decreased in quality whether the supply chain problems are related to an economic issue (like consistently low profits), a social issue (like racial discrimination in the hiring process), or an environmental issue (like polluting). Brands must, therefore, realise that pivots must be a lateral extension of the firm’s existing capabilities, cementing — not undermining — its strategic intent.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mehul Goyal</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lost Vision: The Many Failures of Masayoshi Son</title><link href="/Lost-Vision" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost Vision: The Many Failures of Masayoshi Son" /><published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Lost-Vision</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Lost-Vision">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;45 minutes, $45 billion, $1 billion per minute&lt;/em&gt;”, this is how SoftBank’s Chief Executive Officer Masayoshi Son, described his meeting with Saudi Arabia’s Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman. After this meeting, the Public Investment Fund of Saudi Arabia (PIF) became the largest investor in SoftBank’s outrageous $93 billion technology investment fund, the Vision Fund. This fund was unlike any other fund that anyone had ever seen before - &lt;em&gt;bigger, bolder, and better&lt;/em&gt;. The CEO’s exuberance was even highlighted in the size of the fund which was introduced. With this particular fund, Son wanted to make a presence in tech companies working in artificial intelligence, robotics and the Internet of Things. The fund did fulfil its purpose by giving the company a major share in some of the world’s ‘up and coming’ startups like OYO, Paytm, WeWork, Didi, Uber, Ola, Flipkart, along with 83 others. However, at what cost?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masayoshi Son has always been famous for his gut-led investment style, and it seems that he invests in people rather than in companies. One such person in whom Son invested was Alibaba founder, Jack Ma. Son himself said that Ma had no business plan, but he had “strong eyes”. However unconventional that might sound, it did turn out to be the most profitable investment of SoftBank till date. The investment in Alibaba, $20 million in 2000, turned into $60 billion when the company went public in September 2014. Masa expects every person in whom he invests to become the next Jack Ma. This strategy seemed to be working for the company as it reported a 62% return in the mid of 2019, after making 71 investments for a total of $64.2 billion, and the ride was supposed to be smooth from this point. On the flip side, the company has started facing hurdles and the return on the fund is negative 6%, compared with 62% just a year ago. The fund has lost more for the company than it has earned for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Son’s weakness for charismatic and flashy founders led him to invest in WeWork’s Adam Neumann. Through a combination of glamour and millennial charm, Adam was able to sell WeWrok to Son. It wasn’t even a tech company. Although Son was impressed, the company failed to impress financial analysts. People couldn’t understand the business model of WeWork and were reluctant to invest in it. Even after these speculations, the company decided to go public and as a result of this, their valuation came down to $3 billion from $47 billion in just a year. WeWork’s struggling finances, huge losses, hard-partying culture, and the CEO’s antics sank the ship. Eventually, SoftBank had to step in and buy the company. It came up with a $9.5 billion ‘rescue package’ and took over 80% of the shares. This takeover added dead weight to the company’s balance sheet as the onus to make the real estate firm profitable lay on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such investment that might come to haunt SoftBank in the near future would be OYO. Son invested $1.5 billion in the company and asked the 26-year old founder, Ritesh Agarwal, to make it the world’s largest hotel operator by room count. The business model that worked so well in India wasn’t an obvious fit for the US and European markets, which already had well established, quality hotel chains. In a hasty attempt to expand outside India, OYO faced many logistical and technological challenges. These included double booking of rooms, failing to keep track of the keys, and reducing the rent of the landlords to mere pennies and taking days to fix these glitches. All these failures left the consumers as well as the vendors highly unsatisfied. OYO’s figures haven’t been impressive either, the company had revenue of $951 million for the fiscal year ending in March 2019, while losses surged six-fold to $335 million year-on-year. Furthermore, the young founder has further borrowed $2 billion, to buy out some investors. The loan has been personally guaranteed by Son, in a bizarre deal. The cash-pumping strategy has hampered the company’s natural course and put it on a path to become what many experts believe ‘the next WeWork’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ongoing pandemic, tech companies have faced the most brutal brunt of the lockdowns across the globe. These unicorns have had to let go of people, lose consumers and face burgeoning costs. Uber, another major investment of SoftBank, has been one of the hardest hit. It had merely recovered from the saga of its poor-performing IPO that it had to face the impact of the virus. This has further added to the tensions of the Son-led company. The current scenario has dimmed the hopes of the CEO who was hoping for a $108 billion Vision Fund part-two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to tackle the mounting problems, the company has had to sell shares in Alibaba, its most valuable holding, to raise $11.5 billion. SoftBank is also likely to sell stock in its Japanese telecom unit SoftBank Corp and T-Mobile US Inc. Furthermore, the Japanese company also plans to spend up to ¥500 billion to buy back shares through March 2021, on top of an existing repurchase plan of the same size. That has helped to stabilise SoftBank shares giving them a boost of more than 75% from their low in March. The massive buyback remains the only good news for the shares. The company did not announce any dividend for the first time in its history this year and it has no plans to announce one next year as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, SoftBank said Jack Ma will step down as a director. Additionally, three new directors have been nominated. Son’s increasingly risky bets over the past few years coincided with departures from its board of some of its most outspoken members. With no famous outside directors left on SoftBank’s board, it’s not clear who is going to hold Son responsible anymore. It remains to be seen how that bodes for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, the Vision Fund has made massive losses for the company, it can still be argued that Masayoshi Son has faced worse after he made $70 billion in losses after the dot-com bubble burst and bounced back even stronger. However, to ensure that there is a comeback this time as well, the company needs to make some strategic changes. Instead of investing huge sums of money in these startups in their early stages and making them cash-burning machineries, they should let them grow according to their organic speed. The kind of ‘growth at all costs’ that comes with an asterisk with such large investments is what ruins a good company with a good business plan. Moreover, focussing on profitability rather than on growth solely would help in making the situation better for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson to learn here is that money can’t always buy success. The cheques that Son was blindly cutting for the companies were harming them more than they were helping. He was actually creating bigger and bigger bubbles, which came back to burst right in his face. Although, the enthusiastic CEO has reiterated several times during the past few months that he has learnt his lesson. It remains to be seen as to what he actually does to turn the situation around. Maybe, his self-confidence and stubbornness will help the company after all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“45 minutes, $45 billion, $1 billion per minute”, this is how SoftBank’s Chief Executive Officer Masayoshi Son, described his meeting with Saudi Arabia’s Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman. After this meeting, the Public Investment Fund of Saudi Arabia (PIF) became the largest investor in SoftBank’s outrageous $93 billion technology investment fund, the Vision Fund. This fund was unlike any other fund that anyone had ever seen before - bigger, bolder, and better. The CEO’s exuberance was even highlighted in the size of the fund which was introduced. With this particular fund, Son wanted to make a presence in tech companies working in artificial intelligence, robotics and the Internet of Things. The fund did fulfil its purpose by giving the company a major share in some of the world’s ‘up and coming’ startups like OYO, Paytm, WeWork, Didi, Uber, Ola, Flipkart, along with 83 others. However, at what cost?</summary></entry></feed>