<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-19T22:09:16+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Amazon: The Deal Breaker?</title><link href="/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazon: The Deal Breaker?" /><published>2020-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker">&lt;p&gt;The Reliance and Future Group deal has been in the headlines since a few days now. The recent development which involved Amazon sending a legal notice has spiced it up even more. We are all obsessed with conflicts especially when three multinational corporations are involved. To get a better understanding of the on-going feud, we need to look at the previous developments and understand what actually led to the present-day situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future Group, owned by Kishore Biyani, had been facing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Past-Future-Future-Group&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;crisis&lt;/a&gt; for a few years. They were in huge debt and the reason might have been the diverse and over-ambitious investments made by the company. The group started out with a unique idea that gained success and their retail stores like Pantaloons and Big Bazaar became common household names. The greed to expand business in diverse areas might have turned out to be a big mistake. The group was burdened under debts but still continued to invest and make useless purchases. As the debt accumulated over time, the only option left was to sell their retail chains and shut down useless businesses. At the same time, online platforms like Amazon and Flipkart had already established themselves in the Indian market as retail giants. This increased the threat to all retail businesses as people were switching to e-commerce quicker than ever. Biyani saw this as an opportunity to extend his business to online platforms as well and thus decided to launch '&lt;em&gt;Retail 3.0&lt;/em&gt;'. It was too late to enter as the market had already been saturated and was now under the control of corporations like Amazon and Flipkart. Things didn’t work out for the group as planned. As of March 31, 2019, the combined debt of the Future Group was valued at ₹1.2 trillion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only viable option left for Biyani was to sell off the entire group. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), which is looking to increase its presence in the retail business, acquired the retail and wholesale business as well as the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion in 2020. Soon after the announcement was made public, Amazon jumped in between and turned the tables around. It not only slapped a legal notice but also approached the Singapore International Arbitration Centre (SIAC) claiming that the Future Group had breached the contract according to which Amazon owns a 49% stake in the Future Coupons Pvt Ltd, the parent company which owns all the retail stores, and thus has the first rights to refuse or acquire an even larger stake in the Future Group (after 3 years and before 10 years). Amazon has requested the SIAC to halt the deal between RIL and the Future Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments in defence of the deal state that pre-conditions that exist in the Amazon deal only come into effect after 2022, thus the allegations do not stand. Also, it is claimed that Future Coupons has nothing to do with the Ambani-Biyani deal, and hence, the legal notice doesn’t matter and won’t affect the deal for long. Well, we can’t really be sure of these points and thus have the avenue to make an opinion about the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal was still awaiting completion by the authorities but now it seems to be kinda blurry! We know how prominent Amazon and RIL are in the Indian markets. They have expanded their businesses and the results have been profitable too. This deal definitely plays a crucial role considering the fact that the Future Group has a huge consumer base which will now benefit the new owner. Reliance Industries is owned by the richest Indian, Mukesh Ambani, and the company is in good shape and thus was looking forward to taking over the Future Group. It has plans to enter the e-commerce business via Jiomart. This will expand their business empire in the world of e-retail which will be beneficial in the long run. As we know, Amazon is the boss of e-commerce and won’t enjoy this new entrant in their arena. Thus, going ahead and flashing a legal notice which further halts the deal seems like a smart move to hamper the growth of RIL. We have grown up reading about business rivalries but we also know that profit is the only thing that matters at the end of the day. At this point in time, Amazon should be considerate of the fact that expansion within the subcontinent won’t be an easy task if they make RIL their rivals. The kind of control and authority RIL enjoys within the Indian markets is massive and thus the support will be of much help for expanding businesses. Amazon has the option to negotiate outside the courts and find a solution that satisfies the two parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever be the case, the Future Group has lost its shine and is now being juggled between two companies who only care about their profits and will prioritise their self-interests. Both Amazon and Reliance have been expanding their shares in the Indian markets. With or without the battle, both corporations are winning in a way that benefits them exclusively. The kind of power and authority they have is unbeatable so this case won’t really matter to them. For us, however, it is going to be an interesting battle to look forward to!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Reliance and Future Group deal has been in the headlines since a few days now. The recent development which involved Amazon sending a legal notice has spiced it up even more. We are all obsessed with conflicts especially when three multinational corporations are involved. To get a better understanding of the on-going feud, we need to look at the previous developments and understand what actually led to the present-day situation. Future Group, owned by Kishore Biyani, had been facing a crisis for a few years. They were in huge debt and the reason might have been the diverse and over-ambitious investments made by the company. The group started out with a unique idea that gained success and their retail stores like Pantaloons and Big Bazaar became common household names. The greed to expand business in diverse areas might have turned out to be a big mistake. The group was burdened under debts but still continued to invest and make useless purchases. As the debt accumulated over time, the only option left was to sell their retail chains and shut down useless businesses. At the same time, online platforms like Amazon and Flipkart had already established themselves in the Indian market as retail giants. This increased the threat to all retail businesses as people were switching to e-commerce quicker than ever. Biyani saw this as an opportunity to extend his business to online platforms as well and thus decided to launch 'Retail 3.0'. It was too late to enter as the market had already been saturated and was now under the control of corporations like Amazon and Flipkart. Things didn’t work out for the group as planned. As of March 31, 2019, the combined debt of the Future Group was valued at ₹1.2 trillion. The only viable option left for Biyani was to sell off the entire group. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), which is looking to increase its presence in the retail business, acquired the retail and wholesale business as well as the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion in 2020. Soon after the announcement was made public, Amazon jumped in between and turned the tables around. It not only slapped a legal notice but also approached the Singapore International Arbitration Centre (SIAC) claiming that the Future Group had breached the contract according to which Amazon owns a 49% stake in the Future Coupons Pvt Ltd, the parent company which owns all the retail stores, and thus has the first rights to refuse or acquire an even larger stake in the Future Group (after 3 years and before 10 years). Amazon has requested the SIAC to halt the deal between RIL and the Future Group. Arguments in defence of the deal state that pre-conditions that exist in the Amazon deal only come into effect after 2022, thus the allegations do not stand. Also, it is claimed that Future Coupons has nothing to do with the Ambani-Biyani deal, and hence, the legal notice doesn’t matter and won’t affect the deal for long. Well, we can’t really be sure of these points and thus have the avenue to make an opinion about the same. The deal was still awaiting completion by the authorities but now it seems to be kinda blurry! We know how prominent Amazon and RIL are in the Indian markets. They have expanded their businesses and the results have been profitable too. This deal definitely plays a crucial role considering the fact that the Future Group has a huge consumer base which will now benefit the new owner. Reliance Industries is owned by the richest Indian, Mukesh Ambani, and the company is in good shape and thus was looking forward to taking over the Future Group. It has plans to enter the e-commerce business via Jiomart. This will expand their business empire in the world of e-retail which will be beneficial in the long run. As we know, Amazon is the boss of e-commerce and won’t enjoy this new entrant in their arena. Thus, going ahead and flashing a legal notice which further halts the deal seems like a smart move to hamper the growth of RIL. We have grown up reading about business rivalries but we also know that profit is the only thing that matters at the end of the day. At this point in time, Amazon should be considerate of the fact that expansion within the subcontinent won’t be an easy task if they make RIL their rivals. The kind of control and authority RIL enjoys within the Indian markets is massive and thus the support will be of much help for expanding businesses. Amazon has the option to negotiate outside the courts and find a solution that satisfies the two parties. Whatever be the case, the Future Group has lost its shine and is now being juggled between two companies who only care about their profits and will prioritise their self-interests. Both Amazon and Reliance have been expanding their shares in the Indian markets. With or without the battle, both corporations are winning in a way that benefits them exclusively. The kind of power and authority they have is unbeatable so this case won’t really matter to them. For us, however, it is going to be an interesting battle to look forward to!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 and the Indian Labour Market</title><link href="/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and the Indian Labour Market" /><published>2020-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market</id><content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market">&lt;p&gt;The outbreak of coronavirus has resulted in an unparalleled public health and socio-economic crisis. COVID-19 has heavily impacted the daily lives of people and has thwarted their ability to earn their livelihood. The case is no different for India. With the view of maintaining social distancing and other preventive health measures followed, work-from-home has become the new normal. However, it is important to understand that not all the segments of the labour market are able to function this way. The dual shock of the lockdown and pandemic has thus resulted in major disruptions in the labour market, and job and income losses of millions of people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of coronavirus has been rampant in India, with a steep increase in the number of cases being reported on a daily basis. Before the outbreak of COVID-19, India had already been experiencing an economic slowdown, with the growth rate in GDP declining to 3.1% in Jan-March quarter 2020. However, in the Apr-Jun quarter of the financial year 2020-21, the GDP growth rate has fallen to a negative 23.9%, the worst ever in economic history. All the crucial parameters like manufacturing, construction, trade and the hotel industry have witnessed a steep decline, registering negative growth rates as well. According to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MOSPI), India's Industrial Production (IIP) fell by 16.7% year-on-year in March 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact on the Indian Labour Market&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the worst-hit in this situation has been the labour market. According to the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), a Mumbai-based think tank, during the period of lockdown (March-May), the unemployment rate went up from 8% to 24.3%. As of April 2020, 122 million people have suffered a job loss, with casual workers and self-employed accounting for a major proportion of this, pegging at 90 million. The effect of the shocks induced by the ongoing crisis has been particularly harsh for a specific group of people in the labour market. They can be identified as less educated individuals with low incomes who are engaged in risky and unstable working conditions. These individuals form a major portion of the informal sector. On the other hand, only a small share of the labour force is employed in salaried jobs with the perks of social security benefits. Hence, an outcome of this scenario will be a sheer rise in income inequalities. The most recent data available on the labour force is the Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS 2018-19). According to the survey, the labour force participation rate in 2018-19 stands at 37.5%. The share of people self-employed, as casual labourers and as regular salaried workers in rural and urban areas can be observed in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pib.gov.in/PressReleaseIframePage.aspx?PRID=1629366&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/periodiclabourforcesurvey.png&quot; /&gt;Source: Periodic Labour Force Survey 2018-19&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the regular salaried workers, white-collar professionals and other employees have witnessed the biggest loss of jobs. These include software engineers, physicians, teachers, accountants, analysts and the type who are professionally qualified and are employed in some private or government organisation. According to CMIE, the employment of these professionally qualified white-collar workers fell steeply to 12.2 million during the wave of May-August 2020. This is the lowest employment of these professionals since 2016. An unprecedented 21 million salaried employees had lost their jobs by the end of August. All the gains made in their employment over the past four years were washed away during the lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, those who are self-employed, only a minor proportion of them can be classified as employers. Of these 57.4% rural self-employed households, most of them are marginal cultivators and petty artisans, while 38.7% of self-employed households in urban areas are engaged in small shops, low-scale businesses or intermediation activities. Similarly, the casual labour households that make up almost 20% of the labour force are also extremely vulnerable and fragile in coping up with this economic downturn.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the people categorised as self-employed or as casual workers are faced with no income stability or job security and are outside the umbrella of the employment benefits offered by firms. Compared to them, the regular salaried workers do receive a salary on a periodic basis, but even then, not all of them have access to social security benefits or secure job contracts. It is thus these casual workers that are at the bottom of the hierarchy and are financially vulnerable. A sudden loss of income to these people will lead them to fall into deep poverty. The impact of the pandemic has been the worst for these sectors where the options for remote work are limited or negligible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the World Bank, the shock of the pandemic is expected to push 12 million people into extreme poverty in India. Some reports have suggested that poverty in India had started rising even before the COVID-19 crisis, therefore the above estimates might even be higher. With the cloud of uncertainty looming over their heads, and the loss of jobs and incomes, the poor and the illiterate do not have the option to stay unemployed or wait for a job which serves their needs. In rural areas, we still have Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) as a fallback employment option. But such a safety net doesn’t exist for the urban labourers, who are also faced with high costs of living. The ones rendered unemployed have taken up low income and low productivity jobs, while some have migrated back to their homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As was expected, with the declaration of a nationwide lockdown, there was an unprecedented large-scale reverse migration of labour wherein millions of workers travelled across the state borders amidst food shortages and uncertainty about their work prospects in the future. While the government schemes ensure the availability of rations, the distribution system failed to be effective. Penniless and stranded, workers left cities for their villages on foot or bicycles, cramped in trucks and later by trains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inter-state migration has thus put some of India’s biggest sectors at risk. Sectors such as manufacturing, retail and wholesale trade, mining and hospitality services are heavily dependent on migrants from other states, as analysed by India Ratings and Research. “A consequence of this is a labour crunch that might hit capacity utilisation for several firms. The manufacturing sector which employs over 6 million migrant workers from other states, highest as compared to other sectors, has started suffering. The sector contributes almost 8% of the country’s GDP. Thus the manufacturing sector might face a labour shortage in the near term if labourers do not return in the coming months. This will lead to an increase in wages in the short run and a fall in profits. Another obvious impact is on the mining sector, which has been observing a decline in the past few months.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amidst all this, many state governments have repealed labour laws. The government of the North Indian state of Uttar Pradesh has cleared an ordinance that suspends all the labour laws for a period of three years with the exceptions of laws related to the abolishment of bonded labour, ex gratia payments to workers in case of work-related diseases and disabilities and timely wage payments. Similar actions have been taken by the state governments of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat with a few variations. The decision has been taken to encourage new investments, setting up of new infrastructure, and for the upliftment of existing industries and factories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Lies Ahead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the latest estimates by CMIE, the unemployment rates have dropped to 6.4%, which is the lowest rate seen in a while, but this is hardly a cause for celebration. Other weekly labour metrics have only deteriorated, for example, the average labour participation rate fell down to 20.7% in the first three weeks of September as opposed to 40.96% in August. Similarly, the average employment rate during the first three weeks of August at 37.9% is substantially higher than the rates seen recently. But the slope is negative since the recovery is distinctly negative.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the country recently declared ‘Unlock 5.0’, the economy is still far from being on a path of recovery. The economy is still worse off as compared to the conditions before the lockdown. The recent labour statistics only highlight the fear of India slipping from this ‘incomplete’ recovery unless the government comes up with a well-calculated recovery plan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rajsi Sah</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The outbreak of coronavirus has resulted in an unparalleled public health and socio-economic crisis. COVID-19 has heavily impacted the daily lives of people and has thwarted their ability to earn their livelihood. The case is no different for India. With the view of maintaining social distancing and other preventive health measures followed, work-from-home has become the new normal. However, it is important to understand that not all the segments of the labour market are able to function this way. The dual shock of the lockdown and pandemic has thus resulted in major disruptions in the labour market, and job and income losses of millions of people.&amp;nbsp; The spread of coronavirus has been rampant in India, with a steep increase in the number of cases being reported on a daily basis. Before the outbreak of COVID-19, India had already been experiencing an economic slowdown, with the growth rate in GDP declining to 3.1% in Jan-March quarter 2020. However, in the Apr-Jun quarter of the financial year 2020-21, the GDP growth rate has fallen to a negative 23.9%, the worst ever in economic history. All the crucial parameters like manufacturing, construction, trade and the hotel industry have witnessed a steep decline, registering negative growth rates as well. According to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MOSPI), India's Industrial Production (IIP) fell by 16.7% year-on-year in March 2020.&amp;nbsp; Impact on the Indian Labour Market&amp;nbsp; One of the worst-hit in this situation has been the labour market. According to the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), a Mumbai-based think tank, during the period of lockdown (March-May), the unemployment rate went up from 8% to 24.3%. As of April 2020, 122 million people have suffered a job loss, with casual workers and self-employed accounting for a major proportion of this, pegging at 90 million. The effect of the shocks induced by the ongoing crisis has been particularly harsh for a specific group of people in the labour market. They can be identified as less educated individuals with low incomes who are engaged in risky and unstable working conditions. These individuals form a major portion of the informal sector. On the other hand, only a small share of the labour force is employed in salaried jobs with the perks of social security benefits. Hence, an outcome of this scenario will be a sheer rise in income inequalities. The most recent data available on the labour force is the Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS 2018-19). According to the survey, the labour force participation rate in 2018-19 stands at 37.5%. The share of people self-employed, as casual labourers and as regular salaried workers in rural and urban areas can be observed in the table below: Source: Periodic Labour Force Survey 2018-19 Among the regular salaried workers, white-collar professionals and other employees have witnessed the biggest loss of jobs. These include software engineers, physicians, teachers, accountants, analysts and the type who are professionally qualified and are employed in some private or government organisation. According to CMIE, the employment of these professionally qualified white-collar workers fell steeply to 12.2 million during the wave of May-August 2020. This is the lowest employment of these professionals since 2016. An unprecedented 21 million salaried employees had lost their jobs by the end of August. All the gains made in their employment over the past four years were washed away during the lockdown. Furthermore, those who are self-employed, only a minor proportion of them can be classified as employers. Of these 57.4% rural self-employed households, most of them are marginal cultivators and petty artisans, while 38.7% of self-employed households in urban areas are engaged in small shops, low-scale businesses or intermediation activities. Similarly, the casual labour households that make up almost 20% of the labour force are also extremely vulnerable and fragile in coping up with this economic downturn.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the people categorised as self-employed or as casual workers are faced with no income stability or job security and are outside the umbrella of the employment benefits offered by firms. Compared to them, the regular salaried workers do receive a salary on a periodic basis, but even then, not all of them have access to social security benefits or secure job contracts. It is thus these casual workers that are at the bottom of the hierarchy and are financially vulnerable. A sudden loss of income to these people will lead them to fall into deep poverty. The impact of the pandemic has been the worst for these sectors where the options for remote work are limited or negligible.&amp;nbsp; According to the World Bank, the shock of the pandemic is expected to push 12 million people into extreme poverty in India. Some reports have suggested that poverty in India had started rising even before the COVID-19 crisis, therefore the above estimates might even be higher. With the cloud of uncertainty looming over their heads, and the loss of jobs and incomes, the poor and the illiterate do not have the option to stay unemployed or wait for a job which serves their needs. In rural areas, we still have Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) as a fallback employment option. But such a safety net doesn’t exist for the urban labourers, who are also faced with high costs of living. The ones rendered unemployed have taken up low income and low productivity jobs, while some have migrated back to their homes.&amp;nbsp; As was expected, with the declaration of a nationwide lockdown, there was an unprecedented large-scale reverse migration of labour wherein millions of workers travelled across the state borders amidst food shortages and uncertainty about their work prospects in the future. While the government schemes ensure the availability of rations, the distribution system failed to be effective. Penniless and stranded, workers left cities for their villages on foot or bicycles, cramped in trucks and later by trains.&amp;nbsp; This inter-state migration has thus put some of India’s biggest sectors at risk. Sectors such as manufacturing, retail and wholesale trade, mining and hospitality services are heavily dependent on migrants from other states, as analysed by India Ratings and Research. “A consequence of this is a labour crunch that might hit capacity utilisation for several firms. The manufacturing sector which employs over 6 million migrant workers from other states, highest as compared to other sectors, has started suffering. The sector contributes almost 8% of the country’s GDP. Thus the manufacturing sector might face a labour shortage in the near term if labourers do not return in the coming months. This will lead to an increase in wages in the short run and a fall in profits. Another obvious impact is on the mining sector, which has been observing a decline in the past few months.&amp;nbsp; Amidst all this, many state governments have repealed labour laws. The government of the North Indian state of Uttar Pradesh has cleared an ordinance that suspends all the labour laws for a period of three years with the exceptions of laws related to the abolishment of bonded labour, ex gratia payments to workers in case of work-related diseases and disabilities and timely wage payments. Similar actions have been taken by the state governments of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat with a few variations. The decision has been taken to encourage new investments, setting up of new infrastructure, and for the upliftment of existing industries and factories.&amp;nbsp; What Lies Ahead? According to the latest estimates by CMIE, the unemployment rates have dropped to 6.4%, which is the lowest rate seen in a while, but this is hardly a cause for celebration. Other weekly labour metrics have only deteriorated, for example, the average labour participation rate fell down to 20.7% in the first three weeks of September as opposed to 40.96% in August. Similarly, the average employment rate during the first three weeks of August at 37.9% is substantially higher than the rates seen recently. But the slope is negative since the recovery is distinctly negative.&amp;nbsp; While the country recently declared ‘Unlock 5.0’, the economy is still far from being on a path of recovery. The economy is still worse off as compared to the conditions before the lockdown. The recent labour statistics only highlight the fear of India slipping from this ‘incomplete’ recovery unless the government comes up with a well-calculated recovery plan.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Spotlight on Indian-American Voters: 2020 US Presidential Elections</title><link href="/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters-2020-US-Presidential-Elections" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Spotlight on Indian-American Voters: 2020 US Presidential Elections" /><published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters--2020-US-Presidential-Elections</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters-2020-US-Presidential-Elections">&lt;p&gt;The 2020 US presidential election campaign has been heating up, with Americans set to vote on November 3, 2020. In the face of the coronavirus pandemic, this election is certainly going to be different. What remains the same is the age-old voter’s dilemma of whom to cast their vote for.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spotlight is on Indian-American voters this election. Though Indian-Americans constitute a mere 1.5% of the population, their impact on American politics is often disproportionate. Indian-Americans are among the wealthiest and most educated immigrant groups within the US. Their vote would be especially important in battleground states such as Michigan, Pennsylvania and Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a report by South Asian Americans Leading Together (SAALT),&amp;nbsp; the number of Indian-Americans increased from 29 million to 40 million between 2010 and 2017, nearly a 40% rise. In 18 states, the number of Indian immigrants is higher than any other immigrant group. According to the American Community Survey 2017, the largest number of Indians have settled in California (730,000) followed by New York (370,000), New Jersey (370,000), Texas (350,000), Illinois (230,000) and Florida (150,000). In terms of the proportion of the population, the largest number of Indians are in New Jersey (4.1%), Rhode Island (3.36%),&amp;nbsp; New York (1.88%), Illinois (1.81%), California (1.8%) and Delaware (1.61%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These numbers show the importance of catering to the interests of this section of the electorate because even a few thousand votes have the potential to turn the tables. So, will the Democratic Party’s Indian-origin Vice Presidential candidate win the hearts of these voters or will their affection towards Trump continue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US Senator Kamala Harris has become a focal point in the election, grabbing the attention of voters with her logical and opinionated speeches as well as her down to earth personality. While being immensely proud of her American identity, she has held on to her heritage and flaunts it with pride. Her mother, Shyamala Gopalan, was a biologist from Chennai while her father, Donald Harris, an economist, hailed from Jamaica. After her parents got divorced, her mother raised Kamala Harris and her sister as members of an African American Church but also took them to Hindu temples. Her history presents a chance of a deeper connection with the Indian American electorate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Donald Trump has expressed surety in the fact that Indian Americans will vote Republican, highlighting the good relationship that he has developed with Indian Prime Minister Narender Modi. Their twin events of ‘&lt;em&gt;Howdy Modi&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;Namaste Trump&lt;/em&gt;’ were just one of their many public shows of support for each other. In fact ‘&lt;em&gt;Namaste Trump&lt;/em&gt;’ which took place in Gujarat was also in anticipation of the 2020 election and was very carefully planned. According to the US census data, 20% of the entire population of Indian-Americans constitutes Gujaratis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a White House press conference, Trump said, “&lt;em&gt;We have great support from India. We've got great support from Prime Minister Modi. I might think that the Indian (American) people would be voting for Mr Trump.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;He did not miss a chance to reaffirm his bond with Mr Modi and continued to say,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Prime Minister Modi may be a friend of mine and he’s doing a really good job. Nothing easy, but he’s done a really good job&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic leaders are apprehensive that Mr Trump’s friendship with Modi might sway their traditional vote bank during the upcoming elections. These attempts to please Indian Americans have often led to slip-ups in public debates where Trump has ended up making a joke of his support for India. While praising the number of COVID-19 tests taking place worldwide, President Trump showered India with admiration for their vigilant testing, albeit with incorrect data and statistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite such great attempts to woo this section of voters, it would be presumptuous on the part of Trump to assume that he has their votes in the bag. This year, the Indian-American electorate is on the radar of both Democrats and Republicans. Around 56% of Indian-American registered voters told the AAPI data pollsters that they had been contacted by the Democrats within the past year and 48% said that they were approached by the Republicans. Surprisingly, a recent Asian American and Pacific Islanders (AAPI) data survey found that only 28% of Indian-Americans expressed support for Trump while two-thirds of them said that they are going to vote for Biden. In the face of this data, it seems that it would do India well to build the base of a relationship with Biden as well, lest they lose out on the favour of the most powerful country in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons for the support shown towards Biden. Firstly, the former Vice President’s long history as a supporter of India, dating back to his Senate days, has clearly left a mark on the minds of the Indian-American voters. Secondly, Trump’s approach to India, very similar to his approach to politics and governing, has primarily been one of rhetoric instead of consistency in terms of policy positions. Finally, Indian-Americans, similar to many other voters in the US, perceive the Trump Presidency as one of excessive chaos and confrontation for the US and consequently for India and the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aberjhani, an American historian,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;had succinctly put forth the responsibility that lies on the shoulders of an American voter. He said, “&lt;em&gt;The job facing American voters… in the days and years to come, is to determine which hearts, minds and souls command those qualities best suited to unify a country rather than further divide it, to heal the wounds of a nation as opposed to aggravate its injuries, and to secure for the next generation a legacy of choices based on informed awareness rather than one of reactions based on unknowing fear”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It must be kept in mind that the 2020 elections come at a time of great turmoil. The results will determine how the US deals with the ongoing issues of the pandemic as well as the uproar against racism and police violence. Additionally, owing to the centrality of the US in world politics, the election will cause a ripple effect throughout the world. Indian-Americans have an important role to play in determining this future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aniba Junaid</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The 2020 US presidential election campaign has been heating up, with Americans set to vote on November 3, 2020. In the face of the coronavirus pandemic, this election is certainly going to be different. What remains the same is the age-old voter’s dilemma of whom to cast their vote for.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The spotlight is on Indian-American voters this election. Though Indian-Americans constitute a mere 1.5% of the population, their impact on American politics is often disproportionate. Indian-Americans are among the wealthiest and most educated immigrant groups within the US. Their vote would be especially important in battleground states such as Michigan, Pennsylvania and Ohio. According to a report by South Asian Americans Leading Together (SAALT),&amp;nbsp; the number of Indian-Americans increased from 29 million to 40 million between 2010 and 2017, nearly a 40% rise. In 18 states, the number of Indian immigrants is higher than any other immigrant group. According to the American Community Survey 2017, the largest number of Indians have settled in California (730,000) followed by New York (370,000), New Jersey (370,000), Texas (350,000), Illinois (230,000) and Florida (150,000). In terms of the proportion of the population, the largest number of Indians are in New Jersey (4.1%), Rhode Island (3.36%),&amp;nbsp; New York (1.88%), Illinois (1.81%), California (1.8%) and Delaware (1.61%). These numbers show the importance of catering to the interests of this section of the electorate because even a few thousand votes have the potential to turn the tables. So, will the Democratic Party’s Indian-origin Vice Presidential candidate win the hearts of these voters or will their affection towards Trump continue? US Senator Kamala Harris has become a focal point in the election, grabbing the attention of voters with her logical and opinionated speeches as well as her down to earth personality. While being immensely proud of her American identity, she has held on to her heritage and flaunts it with pride. Her mother, Shyamala Gopalan, was a biologist from Chennai while her father, Donald Harris, an economist, hailed from Jamaica. After her parents got divorced, her mother raised Kamala Harris and her sister as members of an African American Church but also took them to Hindu temples. Her history presents a chance of a deeper connection with the Indian American electorate.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, Donald Trump has expressed surety in the fact that Indian Americans will vote Republican, highlighting the good relationship that he has developed with Indian Prime Minister Narender Modi. Their twin events of ‘Howdy Modi’ and ‘Namaste Trump’ were just one of their many public shows of support for each other. In fact ‘Namaste Trump’ which took place in Gujarat was also in anticipation of the 2020 election and was very carefully planned. According to the US census data, 20% of the entire population of Indian-Americans constitutes Gujaratis.&amp;nbsp; At a White House press conference, Trump said, “We have great support from India. We've got great support from Prime Minister Modi. I might think that the Indian (American) people would be voting for Mr Trump.” He did not miss a chance to reaffirm his bond with Mr Modi and continued to say, “Prime Minister Modi may be a friend of mine and he’s doing a really good job. Nothing easy, but he’s done a really good job”. Democratic leaders are apprehensive that Mr Trump’s friendship with Modi might sway their traditional vote bank during the upcoming elections. These attempts to please Indian Americans have often led to slip-ups in public debates where Trump has ended up making a joke of his support for India. While praising the number of COVID-19 tests taking place worldwide, President Trump showered India with admiration for their vigilant testing, albeit with incorrect data and statistics.&amp;nbsp; Despite such great attempts to woo this section of voters, it would be presumptuous on the part of Trump to assume that he has their votes in the bag. This year, the Indian-American electorate is on the radar of both Democrats and Republicans. Around 56% of Indian-American registered voters told the AAPI data pollsters that they had been contacted by the Democrats within the past year and 48% said that they were approached by the Republicans. Surprisingly, a recent Asian American and Pacific Islanders (AAPI) data survey found that only 28% of Indian-Americans expressed support for Trump while two-thirds of them said that they are going to vote for Biden. In the face of this data, it seems that it would do India well to build the base of a relationship with Biden as well, lest they lose out on the favour of the most powerful country in the world. There are many reasons for the support shown towards Biden. Firstly, the former Vice President’s long history as a supporter of India, dating back to his Senate days, has clearly left a mark on the minds of the Indian-American voters. Secondly, Trump’s approach to India, very similar to his approach to politics and governing, has primarily been one of rhetoric instead of consistency in terms of policy positions. Finally, Indian-Americans, similar to many other voters in the US, perceive the Trump Presidency as one of excessive chaos and confrontation for the US and consequently for India and the rest of the world. Aberjhani, an American historian, had succinctly put forth the responsibility that lies on the shoulders of an American voter. He said, “The job facing American voters… in the days and years to come, is to determine which hearts, minds and souls command those qualities best suited to unify a country rather than further divide it, to heal the wounds of a nation as opposed to aggravate its injuries, and to secure for the next generation a legacy of choices based on informed awareness rather than one of reactions based on unknowing fear”.&amp;nbsp; It must be kept in mind that the 2020 elections come at a time of great turmoil. The results will determine how the US deals with the ongoing issues of the pandemic as well as the uproar against racism and police violence. Additionally, owing to the centrality of the US in world politics, the election will cause a ripple effect throughout the world. Indian-Americans have an important role to play in determining this future.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19: RBI’s Take and What Now?</title><link href="/RBI-Take-What-Now" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19: RBI’s Take and What Now?" /><published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/RBI-Take-What-Now</id><content type="html" xml:base="/RBI-Take-What-Now">&lt;p&gt;The Central bank of a nation is tasked with multiple responsibilities to maintain the dynamic, complex and entangled macroeconomic variables with the sole objective of economic development of the country. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) follows the same pursuit of growth by working out the price and financial stability of the state. The gigantic wave of virus that swept the world in late 2019 and hit India in early 2020 has inevitably accelerated the socio-economic division, the footprint of which will be felt for years to come. With the advent of such unprecedented times, all eyes are turned to the Central bank and to the government for rescue from the ramifications of this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the late evening of March 24, 2020, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced a 21-day complete lockdown which got extended for months due to the rising number of COVID-19 cases in the country. This declaration meant an absolute halt for businesses leading to complete disruption of market forces of demand and supply, money creation, etc. In short, it was a difficult affair for the economy. Nonetheless, the RBI sailed through it almost effortlessly, supporting the economy through the various tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) &lt;strong&gt;Rate cuts&lt;/strong&gt;: To incentivise investments and loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) &lt;strong&gt;Liquidity Infusion&lt;/strong&gt;: Increasing the availability of funds in banks via various policy rates like CRR, Repo rate, Reverse Repo Rate, OMOs, and special windows for financial institutions to borrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) &lt;strong&gt;Regulatory Easing&lt;/strong&gt;: Via mechanisms like a moratorium, etc to support the borrowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps resulted in a liquidity spree in the banking system, drawing concerns of inflationary pressure in an already high inflation economy (CPI inflation rate in July was 6.93%). In addition to this, the influx of dollars in the country through Foreign Direct Investments (FDIs) and Foreign Portfolio Investments (FPIs) fuelled the additional circulation of Indian currency in the economy. This, supported by collapsing net imports, led to the pile-up of RBIs forex kitty to an all-time high of $541billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s language, it looks like a rosy picture. However from an economist’s point of view, this means appreciation of the Indian rupee with respect to the mighty US dollar. Thus, putting exports at a disadvantage. It adds to the already concerning topic of inflation as now excess money will be spent on the imported items, increasing our dependence on imported goods. At the same time, we will be letting go of the opportunity of utilising the liquidity available in the system which could have been used to build productive capacities like infrastructure that will lead to the creation of employment, income and welfare of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, inflation will only occur when the monetary surplus in the banking system actually reaches the hands of the consumers via businesses and loans, but banks are averse in lending out due to skyrocketing Non-Performing Assets (NPAs). Hence the overflowing liquidity is limited within these financial intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to an article published in &lt;em&gt;Business Today&lt;/em&gt;, despite the Central bank reducing the Reverse Repo Rate (RRR) from 4.9% to 3.35%, the number of deposits increased during the period of the pandemic. Unused funds in the financial system have further been increasing as businesses and firms are reluctant in taking loans for investments due to low production and capacity utilisation. Moreover, rising COVID-19 cases engulf the future with a blanket of uncertainty for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jump in the deposits with the RBI is a cause of worry as the excess money sitting idle with banks now requires the Central bank to pay interest on these deposits. Additionally, the money is never actually entering the productive sector for money creation, which was the prime motive of slashing the RRR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, governments too have a vital role in reviving the economy through its targeted expenditures. But the Union government’s fiscal deficit has soared to 109% of the budgeted target in just 5 months of the current financial year. State governments have been facing a shortage of funds owing to the shortfall of revenues due to sluggish economic activities and failure on part of the Union government to settle the compensation for Goods and Services Tax (GST). Hence, the governments’ bank stepped in to facilitate the reduction of that deficit by borrowing from the bond market. The Center has stuck to its borrowing plan of ₹12 trillion in 2020-21. The superfluity of funds in the financial system is managing to keep the yields in the bond market low, benefitting the borrowers in borrowing funds at low-interest rates. The Central government borrowed ₹7.66 trillion at a weighted rate of 5.82%, the lowest in 15 years, in the first half of the ongoing fiscal year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting the rate of economic expansion back on track is a daunting task and RBI has managed the situation quite decently, but the major chunk of work now lies on the government to use their borrowing for capital expenditure and revival of demand. Better demand sentiments would enable restoration of the market disruptions and lead to an expansion in the trade deficit which would perhaps reduce the balance of payment surplus and minimise the intervention by the Central bank to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest projection by the US Federal Reserve to keep its interest rate near zero till 2023 would result in a sustained flow of foreign funds into countries like India. Therefore, the bankers’ bank needs to be watchful and avoid unnecessary currency appreciation which will not only affect exports but also other macroeconomic variables, thus risking the financial stability of the nation. The biggest challenge will perhaps come when pandemic recedes and activity picks back up but for now, the Reserve Bank needs to maintain a fine balance between the intertwined variables of inflation, bond yields, and currency market for the economic interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Central bank of a nation is tasked with multiple responsibilities to maintain the dynamic, complex and entangled macroeconomic variables with the sole objective of economic development of the country. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) follows the same pursuit of growth by working out the price and financial stability of the state. The gigantic wave of virus that swept the world in late 2019 and hit India in early 2020 has inevitably accelerated the socio-economic division, the footprint of which will be felt for years to come. With the advent of such unprecedented times, all eyes are turned to the Central bank and to the government for rescue from the ramifications of this situation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?</title><link href="/Germany-s-Future" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?" /><published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Germany-s-Future</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Germany-s-Future">&lt;p&gt;Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the height of the Greek debt crisis, photographs of protesters in Athens brandishing placards of Angela Merkel, the Chancellor of Germany, dressed as Hitler made the headlines across the world. In Britain, the sight was met with mixed emotions, ranging from bewilderment to hilarity, but not so in Germany. For Merkel’s government and its people, the placards were far more than an unfunny joke. Such a blatant reference to Germany’s ugly history was a suggestion that even after several decades of apologising for the atrocities of the Nazi regime, people across the continent still mistook German assertiveness and leadership for fascistic belligerence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merkel is renowned world over for her understated leadership style. Commentators abroad often applaud the Chancellor’s love for detail, her skill in consensus-building and her conviction. Economically, this may well be true; her government spared little mercy for Greece, even after the Greeks played the Nazi card. However in the social sphere, underpinning Merkel’s major decisions has always been a fear of causing a stir and there is a desire to prevent any association with what has passed before, no matter how far fetched these comparisons might be. In Germany, you really &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; mention the War. These earnest attempts to please all sides haven’t been good for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious example of Merkel’s reluctance to take difficult decisions was during the migrant crisis of 2015 when millions of migrants from across the Levant, Sub-Saharan Africa and Central Asia cascaded into Europe over a matter of a few months. Merkel’s decision not to turn away any of these people who were trying to enter Germany, in essence dissolving the inner borders of the continent, was largely born out of a desire to definitively break with German history. She wanted to present Germany in a different light from what it had been shown as earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, whilst it was presented as the ultimate show of tolerance, the great irony of Merkel’s migrant policy is that it has made Germany a more racist place. Before 2015, nobody would have made a Nazi salute on the streets of a German city. Now, it is commonplace at far-right protests. The protests in Chemnitz two years ago showed that. The failure to integrate Muslim migrants into German society was the driving cause of the success of the Alternative fur Deutschland (AfD) party in 2017, the first far-right party to win seats in the German Bundestag since the Second World War. The migrant crisis was the best thing that ever happened to Europe’s populist parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that the German government’s constant attempts to apologise for the horrors of the Nazi era don’t help the Europe of today. What Germany did to Europe was unthinkable and no amount of money would ever repay the Jewish community for the atrocities committed after 1942. But we all know Angela Merkel isn’t Adolf Hitler. Her party is not the National Socialists. The world should distinguish between perfectly reasonable projections of German soft power on the one hand and Nazi dog-whistles on the other. Germany, though, must also learn to live with its own past. There will always be new crises around the corner for Europe, but only they have the clout to coordinate a European response to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December, the most important European election in recent years is taking place. Merkel’s party will most likely choose her successor as the German Chancellor. She leaves behind a party in power, but a party that is unsure of its future. Many in Merkel’s Christian Democratic Union (CDU) wish for Germany to take a tougher stance on issues such as immigration and German identity. For the most part, they are uniting around Friedrich Merz. Merz is a strong NATO backer and supports the formation of an EU army. He also raised controversy two decades ago when he became the first centre-right politician to open a debate around &lt;em&gt;leitkultur&lt;/em&gt; (translated as leading culture). In practical terms, this translates to formulating a more concrete idea of ‘German-ness’, based on a forthright endorsement of Judeo-Christian values and a rejection of multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of the rise of the AfD, such talk makes the centrist wing of Merkel’s party nervous of sounding overly chauvinistic. The centrists are leaning towards Armin Laschet for the party leadership, who has been a strong defender of Merkel’s migrant policy. Laschet seems less interested than Merz in winning back voters who peeled off to the AfD at the 2017 election and would likely follow Merkel’s quiet leadership style on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake; Merz is no Trump. He’s a mainstream politician who briefly held the CDU leadership before Merkel in the early 2000’s. But his election as a CDU leader would signal to the world that Germany intends to become more self-assured and unabashed in its international decision-making. This would be a welcome change, though, as established, it would not come without controversy. It is difficult to say whether Germans would see this new assertiveness as a throwback to something dark in their history. In this sense, the split within the CDU is about much more than party bureaucracy. It represents the airing of an uncomfortable question at the heart of the German psyche: how do we project ourselves? How Germany answers that question will impact us all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Another Test Article</title><link href="/Another-Test-Article" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Another Test Article" /><published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Another-Test-Article</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Another-Test-Article">&lt;p&gt;This is a test Article&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kheeran Naidu</name></author><summary type="html">This is a test Article</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Robot Tax to Fund Humans?: Analysing Future Prospects of Universal Basic Income</title><link href="/A-Robot-Tax-to-Fund-Humans-Analysing-Future-Prospects-of-Universal-Basic-Income" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Robot Tax to Fund Humans?: Analysing Future Prospects of Universal Basic Income" /><published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Robot-Tax-to-Fund-Humans---Analysing-Future-Prospects-of-Universal-Basic-Income</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Robot-Tax-to-Fund-Humans-Analysing-Future-Prospects-of-Universal-Basic-Income">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;There would be fewer and fewer jobs that the robot cannot do better.&lt;/em&gt;” &lt;em&gt;- &lt;/em&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world that we are very quickly creating, we are going to see more and more things that look like science fiction and fewer things that look like jobs. A recent study put lawyers and Artificial Intelligence (AI) against each other. Their task was to review non-disclosure agreements. It took AI 26 seconds to finish a task with 94% accuracy. The same task took the human manifestation 92 minutes with 85% accuracy. Hedge funds managed by AI gave an average return of 8% for which the humans could barely manage a 2%. AI could see in X-rays what an experienced doctor could not and was also better at predicting the risk an underlying disease poses to the patient. From supermarket checkout staff to truck drivers, everything is on the verge of getting automated. Thanks to human ingenuity, we no longer interact with the staff at &lt;em&gt;Blockbuster&lt;/em&gt;, rather we have &lt;em&gt;Netflix&lt;/em&gt; doing the work for us. &lt;em&gt;McKinsey&lt;/em&gt; has reported that whether it is repetitive low-skilled labour or high-skilled jobs, both are at risk of automation and as much as 30% of all jobs would be automated by 2030. The reality is that there is no clear limit to what AI can automate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no doubt that we are going to need lawyers and doctors in the future as there are some key things such as complex decision making and empathy that can’t be automated. Additionally, just because AI performs well in test settings doesn’t mean that it’s ready for the market just yet. We may need fewer humans to do the same amount of work and it’s not just AI we should be concerned about. The problem has gotten so bad that a new term has been coined- the ‘working poor’: people who earn below the poverty line despite actively working. What happens to these people when the basic entry-level jobs become obsolete in the face of reality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governments around the world need a narrative that helps people feel that they do belong and that they are being heard. One general solution to this is Universal Basic Income (UBI). That’s one of the ways through which governments can start rebuilding trust. What is it and what would the future of work look like with the implementation of&amp;nbsp; UBI?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Solution, how UBI can help?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though UBI may be the most ambitious policy of our times, it’s gaining popularity and momentum around the world fueled by the coronavirus pandemic and a whole legacy of unemployment and poverty that it is leaving behind. The idea of guaranteeing every person with a minimum living wage income is appealing. Andrew Yang, one of the former 2020 Democratic Presidential candidates, has based most of his campaign around the UBI. According to him, “&lt;em&gt;Technology is the oil of the 21st century&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 200,000 people in South Korea's Gyeonggi province are a part of a radical experiment in UBI. They receive about $220 every three months. No questions asked. During the coronavirus pandemic, ‘Gyeonggi Pay’&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;was expanded to 13 million people in the province including new-borns to help people ride out the economic slowdown. There was one catch though, people had to spend the money only in their neighbourhoods to help stimulate the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The popularity of the local program during the pandemic has now drawn attention at the national level and there's another big reason. South Korea is one of the most automated countries in the world and about 15% of jobs in the country are projected to be automated by 2024. So some politicians, especially in the manufacturing hub of Gyeonggi, want to give all citizens about $430 every month to help prepare for a future with robots. The success of South Korea's experiment could change how other countries think about adopting their own UBI programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now people can’t decide what UBI is and what it should be. Though UBI in its raw sense is a fairly simple concept, its implementation has several ramifications. There are different schools of thought that pertain to evaluating UBI. While some see it in the setting where all other welfare schemes are scrapped and bureaucracy is eliminated, others demand UBI as an add-on to the existing welfare programs and want to keep UBI so high that work becomes optional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we hand out enough free money and people just spend it on booze and stop working? Well, that is not true. According to a 2013 &lt;em&gt;World Bank&lt;/em&gt; study which specifically examined whether poor people waste their handouts on tobacco and alcohol if they receive it in the form of cash. The clear answer was, no they don't. The opposite is true. Other studies have shown that the richer you are, the more drugs and alcohol you consume. The lazy and drunk poor person is a stereotype rather than a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A test run in Canada in the 1970’s showed that only 1% of the working population stopped working after UBI was rolled out and that too was attributed to child care reasons. On average, Canadians reduced their work time by less than 10% which was then dedicated to looking out for better jobs and going back to school. UBI aims to address that there are more motivations to work than to just cover up the necessities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if laziness and drugs are not a huge deal, why don’t our current welfare state programs solve poverty?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Many Strings Attached&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing welfare schemes have loopholes somewhere. Welfare or unemployment programmes often come with a lot of strings attached, taking part in courses, applying to a certain number of jobs every month, and taking any kind of job offer no matter if it is a good fit or what it pays. Besides the loss of personal freedom, these conditions are often a huge waste of time and only served to make the unemployment statistics seem less bad. Often your time would be much better spent looking for the right job, continuing education or starting a business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another unwanted side effect of many welfare programmes is that they trap people in poverty and promote passive behaviour. Imagine a benefit of $1000 every month. In a lot of programs, if you earn a single dollar extra, the whole thing is taken away. If you take a job which is paying $1200, you might not only lose your benefits but because of your taxes and other costs, you might end up having lesser money than before. So if you actively try to improve your situation and your total income is not rising or actually shrinking, welfare can create a ceiling that traps people in poverty and rewards passive behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A basic income can never be cut and therefore getting a job and additional income would always make your financial situation better. Work is always rewarded. Instead of a ceiling, it creates a floor from which people can lift themselves, and unlike unemployment benefits that run out over time, these payments are a stable flow of income.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if UBI is the better model, is it economically feasible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does it come from?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although a Universal Basic Income contributes to the vitalisation of the consumer economy and increases small business revenue, it has its dark enemy: inflation. While demand props up and everything is rosy, prices inflate leaving everything just as it was before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the inflation problem and how to tackle it since the money is not being created by magic or printers, it needs to be transferred from somewhere. It is more of a shift of funds than the creation of new ones. Hence, no inflation. But how do we pay for it? There's no right answer here because the world is too diverse. How well-off the country is, what the local values are, are things like high taxes or cutting the defence budget politically acceptable or not? How much welfare state is already in place and is it effective? Each country has its own individual path to UBI. The easiest way to pay for UBI is to end all existing welfare and use the free funds to finance it. Not only would this make several government agencies disappear, which in itself saves money, it would also eliminate a lot of bureaucracy on the other hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, cutting them could leave many people worse off than before. If the goal is to have a foundation for everybody there still needs to be a program of some sort because just like countries, all people are not the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second way to finance UBI is by imposing higher taxes especially on the very wealthy and rich. The tax is to avenge the wealthy for reaping the most benefits of economic growth. The wealth gap is rapidly widening and many argue that it might be time to distribute the spoils more evenly to preserve social peace. Top percentiles get wealthier while the rest of the population stagnates. Inequality is increasingly getting skewed. There could be taxes on financial transactions, capital, land value, carbon or even robots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, UBI is not necessarily expensive. It can be balanced out with GDP growth as more spending stimulates the demand side of the economy. According to a recent study, a UBI of $1000 per month in the US could grow the GDP by 12% over eight years because it would enable poor people to spend more and increase overall demand. What about the people who do the dirty work? Who will work in the fields, crawl through sewers or lift bricks and stones? If you don't need to for survival, will people still do hard, boring and unfulfilling labour? UBI might give them enough leverage to demand better pay and working conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A study calculated that every extra dollar going to wage earners would add about $1.21 to the national economy, while every extra dollar going to high-income Americans would add only 39 cents. Making poor citizens better off could be a smart economic tactic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who demand enough UBI to cover all their costs and do no work, I have a problem. For me, the concept of work itself not being essential for survival is appalling. It would be unfair to portray work as just a chore. Work gives us something to do. It challenges us, it motivates us to improve, it forces us to engage. Many find friends or partners at work. We work for social status, wealth and for our place in the world. We're looking for something to do with our lives, and for many people work gives them meaning. Money alone wouldn't be enough to make people live a happy life. People need a differentiated and delineated purpose and simply giving people money without that purpose is a wrong solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other concerns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, there are other concerns associated with UBI too. If all welfare programs were exchanged for one single payment, this gives the government a lot of leverage. Individual programs are easier to attack or cut than a multitude. Populists might promise drastic changes to the UBI to get into power and a universal basic income does not tackle all problems when it comes to equality. For example, rents. While $1000 might be great in the countryside, it's not a lot for expensive metropolitan areas which could lead to poor people moving outwards and the difference between rich and poor becoming even more extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the catch? South Korean people had to spend locally. That they can’t spend it in a McDonalds? Telling people where they can spend money sounds like an efficient way to boost local consumption but this policy has a loophole. Money is fungible and that what people can spend locally means they're saving on whatever other money they have. That other money was earlier being spent on non-local or non-eligible types of goods and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one grave concern of governments using Universal Basic Income to practice political influence. The huge chunks of personal data collected about the preferences and choices of the consumer could lead to a massive data breach to achieve self-motivated interests. Although the South Korean government claims that it only analyses aggregate demand and not the individual data points, there’s still much obscurity. Governor Lee of the Gyeonggi&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;province is using the success of Gyeonggi Pay&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;as a pitch for the 2022 Presidential election and he's now leading in the polls. He plans to partly fund the UBI scheme through what he calls a ‘&lt;em&gt;Robot Tax&lt;/em&gt;’, essentially a levy on factories that have automated their production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is UBI a good idea? The honest answer is that we don't know yet. There needs to be a lot more research and bigger test runs. We need to think about what kind of UBI we want and what we're prepared to give up to pay for it. The potential is huge. It might be the most promising model to sustainably eliminate poverty. It might seriously reduce the amount of desperation in the world and make us all much less stressed out. There would still be very rich and poor people but we could eliminate fear, suffering and existential panic for a significant part of the population. A recent pilot program in Finland found that UBI didn't help in getting people who were unemployed into jobs but it did make them happier and less stressed. About 50% of participants reported being healthier and having better overall well-being while the rest remained the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human nature has an inherent desire to be productive and to contribute something meaningful to the world. Sure, a lot of people do complain about their work and they dream of winning the lottery and never having to work again, perhaps these people may be happy for the first few months of not working but a few years down the road they may get the feeling of a life without purpose. When it comes to UBI, people often flippantly say that now everyone is free to pursue their passion but they forget the empathetic angle- everyone isn't them. There are also a lot many people in this world without passions or hobbies. It can be said that curiosity is the start of a passion. Follow the trail of what you're curious about and then develop that into a passion. Others still might even find that hard to do. So what happens to them? If technology does replace their jobs and they're unable to retrain, then what meaning will they find in life? That's personal to them and only they can solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So automation is on the way. Advances in technology are too great to ignore. The people at the bottom of the workforce are going to start being replaced. UBI may be able to solve the issue of how everyone will be able to feed themselves in this future but what about that more burning question of purpose? Now that might be harder to solve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mehul Goyal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“There would be fewer and fewer jobs that the robot cannot do better.” - Elon Musk In the world that we are very quickly creating, we are going to see more and more things that look like science fiction and fewer things that look like jobs. A recent study put lawyers and Artificial Intelligence (AI) against each other. Their task was to review non-disclosure agreements. It took AI 26 seconds to finish a task with 94% accuracy. The same task took the human manifestation 92 minutes with 85% accuracy. Hedge funds managed by AI gave an average return of 8% for which the humans could barely manage a 2%. AI could see in X-rays what an experienced doctor could not and was also better at predicting the risk an underlying disease poses to the patient. From supermarket checkout staff to truck drivers, everything is on the verge of getting automated. Thanks to human ingenuity, we no longer interact with the staff at Blockbuster, rather we have Netflix doing the work for us. McKinsey has reported that whether it is repetitive low-skilled labour or high-skilled jobs, both are at risk of automation and as much as 30% of all jobs would be automated by 2030. The reality is that there is no clear limit to what AI can automate.&amp;nbsp; There’s no doubt that we are going to need lawyers and doctors in the future as there are some key things such as complex decision making and empathy that can’t be automated. Additionally, just because AI performs well in test settings doesn’t mean that it’s ready for the market just yet. We may need fewer humans to do the same amount of work and it’s not just AI we should be concerned about. The problem has gotten so bad that a new term has been coined- the ‘working poor’: people who earn below the poverty line despite actively working. What happens to these people when the basic entry-level jobs become obsolete in the face of reality? Governments around the world need a narrative that helps people feel that they do belong and that they are being heard. One general solution to this is Universal Basic Income (UBI). That’s one of the ways through which governments can start rebuilding trust. What is it and what would the future of work look like with the implementation of&amp;nbsp; UBI? The Solution, how UBI can help? Though UBI may be the most ambitious policy of our times, it’s gaining popularity and momentum around the world fueled by the coronavirus pandemic and a whole legacy of unemployment and poverty that it is leaving behind. The idea of guaranteeing every person with a minimum living wage income is appealing. Andrew Yang, one of the former 2020 Democratic Presidential candidates, has based most of his campaign around the UBI. According to him, “Technology is the oil of the 21st century”. Nearly 200,000 people in South Korea's Gyeonggi province are a part of a radical experiment in UBI. They receive about $220 every three months. No questions asked. During the coronavirus pandemic, ‘Gyeonggi Pay’ was expanded to 13 million people in the province including new-borns to help people ride out the economic slowdown. There was one catch though, people had to spend the money only in their neighbourhoods to help stimulate the local economy. The popularity of the local program during the pandemic has now drawn attention at the national level and there's another big reason. South Korea is one of the most automated countries in the world and about 15% of jobs in the country are projected to be automated by 2024. So some politicians, especially in the manufacturing hub of Gyeonggi, want to give all citizens about $430 every month to help prepare for a future with robots. The success of South Korea's experiment could change how other countries think about adopting their own UBI programs. Right now people can’t decide what UBI is and what it should be. Though UBI in its raw sense is a fairly simple concept, its implementation has several ramifications. There are different schools of thought that pertain to evaluating UBI. While some see it in the setting where all other welfare schemes are scrapped and bureaucracy is eliminated, others demand UBI as an add-on to the existing welfare programs and want to keep UBI so high that work becomes optional. But what if we hand out enough free money and people just spend it on booze and stop working? Well, that is not true. According to a 2013 World Bank study which specifically examined whether poor people waste their handouts on tobacco and alcohol if they receive it in the form of cash. The clear answer was, no they don't. The opposite is true. Other studies have shown that the richer you are, the more drugs and alcohol you consume. The lazy and drunk poor person is a stereotype rather than a reality. A test run in Canada in the 1970’s showed that only 1% of the working population stopped working after UBI was rolled out and that too was attributed to child care reasons. On average, Canadians reduced their work time by less than 10% which was then dedicated to looking out for better jobs and going back to school. UBI aims to address that there are more motivations to work than to just cover up the necessities.&amp;nbsp; But if laziness and drugs are not a huge deal, why don’t our current welfare state programs solve poverty? Many Strings Attached The existing welfare schemes have loopholes somewhere. Welfare or unemployment programmes often come with a lot of strings attached, taking part in courses, applying to a certain number of jobs every month, and taking any kind of job offer no matter if it is a good fit or what it pays. Besides the loss of personal freedom, these conditions are often a huge waste of time and only served to make the unemployment statistics seem less bad. Often your time would be much better spent looking for the right job, continuing education or starting a business. Another unwanted side effect of many welfare programmes is that they trap people in poverty and promote passive behaviour. Imagine a benefit of $1000 every month. In a lot of programs, if you earn a single dollar extra, the whole thing is taken away. If you take a job which is paying $1200, you might not only lose your benefits but because of your taxes and other costs, you might end up having lesser money than before. So if you actively try to improve your situation and your total income is not rising or actually shrinking, welfare can create a ceiling that traps people in poverty and rewards passive behaviour. A basic income can never be cut and therefore getting a job and additional income would always make your financial situation better. Work is always rewarded. Instead of a ceiling, it creates a floor from which people can lift themselves, and unlike unemployment benefits that run out over time, these payments are a stable flow of income.&amp;nbsp; But even if UBI is the better model, is it economically feasible? Where does it come from? Although a Universal Basic Income contributes to the vitalisation of the consumer economy and increases small business revenue, it has its dark enemy: inflation. While demand props up and everything is rosy, prices inflate leaving everything just as it was before. For the inflation problem and how to tackle it since the money is not being created by magic or printers, it needs to be transferred from somewhere. It is more of a shift of funds than the creation of new ones. Hence, no inflation. But how do we pay for it? There's no right answer here because the world is too diverse. How well-off the country is, what the local values are, are things like high taxes or cutting the defence budget politically acceptable or not? How much welfare state is already in place and is it effective? Each country has its own individual path to UBI. The easiest way to pay for UBI is to end all existing welfare and use the free funds to finance it. Not only would this make several government agencies disappear, which in itself saves money, it would also eliminate a lot of bureaucracy on the other hand. On the other hand, cutting them could leave many people worse off than before. If the goal is to have a foundation for everybody there still needs to be a program of some sort because just like countries, all people are not the same. The second way to finance UBI is by imposing higher taxes especially on the very wealthy and rich. The tax is to avenge the wealthy for reaping the most benefits of economic growth. The wealth gap is rapidly widening and many argue that it might be time to distribute the spoils more evenly to preserve social peace. Top percentiles get wealthier while the rest of the population stagnates. Inequality is increasingly getting skewed. There could be taxes on financial transactions, capital, land value, carbon or even robots. So, UBI is not necessarily expensive. It can be balanced out with GDP growth as more spending stimulates the demand side of the economy. According to a recent study, a UBI of $1000 per month in the US could grow the GDP by 12% over eight years because it would enable poor people to spend more and increase overall demand. What about the people who do the dirty work? Who will work in the fields, crawl through sewers or lift bricks and stones? If you don't need to for survival, will people still do hard, boring and unfulfilling labour? UBI might give them enough leverage to demand better pay and working conditions. A study calculated that every extra dollar going to wage earners would add about $1.21 to the national economy, while every extra dollar going to high-income Americans would add only 39 cents. Making poor citizens better off could be a smart economic tactic. For those who demand enough UBI to cover all their costs and do no work, I have a problem. For me, the concept of work itself not being essential for survival is appalling. It would be unfair to portray work as just a chore. Work gives us something to do. It challenges us, it motivates us to improve, it forces us to engage. Many find friends or partners at work. We work for social status, wealth and for our place in the world. We're looking for something to do with our lives, and for many people work gives them meaning. Money alone wouldn't be enough to make people live a happy life. People need a differentiated and delineated purpose and simply giving people money without that purpose is a wrong solution. Other concerns Apart from this, there are other concerns associated with UBI too. If all welfare programs were exchanged for one single payment, this gives the government a lot of leverage. Individual programs are easier to attack or cut than a multitude. Populists might promise drastic changes to the UBI to get into power and a universal basic income does not tackle all problems when it comes to equality. For example, rents. While $1000 might be great in the countryside, it's not a lot for expensive metropolitan areas which could lead to poor people moving outwards and the difference between rich and poor becoming even more extreme. Remember the catch? South Korean people had to spend locally. That they can’t spend it in a McDonalds? Telling people where they can spend money sounds like an efficient way to boost local consumption but this policy has a loophole. Money is fungible and that what people can spend locally means they're saving on whatever other money they have. That other money was earlier being spent on non-local or non-eligible types of goods and services. There is one grave concern of governments using Universal Basic Income to practice political influence. The huge chunks of personal data collected about the preferences and choices of the consumer could lead to a massive data breach to achieve self-motivated interests. Although the South Korean government claims that it only analyses aggregate demand and not the individual data points, there’s still much obscurity. Governor Lee of the Gyeonggi province is using the success of Gyeonggi Pay as a pitch for the 2022 Presidential election and he's now leading in the polls. He plans to partly fund the UBI scheme through what he calls a ‘Robot Tax’, essentially a levy on factories that have automated their production. Conclusion So, is UBI a good idea? The honest answer is that we don't know yet. There needs to be a lot more research and bigger test runs. We need to think about what kind of UBI we want and what we're prepared to give up to pay for it. The potential is huge. It might be the most promising model to sustainably eliminate poverty. It might seriously reduce the amount of desperation in the world and make us all much less stressed out. There would still be very rich and poor people but we could eliminate fear, suffering and existential panic for a significant part of the population. A recent pilot program in Finland found that UBI didn't help in getting people who were unemployed into jobs but it did make them happier and less stressed. About 50% of participants reported being healthier and having better overall well-being while the rest remained the same. Human nature has an inherent desire to be productive and to contribute something meaningful to the world. Sure, a lot of people do complain about their work and they dream of winning the lottery and never having to work again, perhaps these people may be happy for the first few months of not working but a few years down the road they may get the feeling of a life without purpose. When it comes to UBI, people often flippantly say that now everyone is free to pursue their passion but they forget the empathetic angle- everyone isn't them. There are also a lot many people in this world without passions or hobbies. It can be said that curiosity is the start of a passion. Follow the trail of what you're curious about and then develop that into a passion. Others still might even find that hard to do. So what happens to them? If technology does replace their jobs and they're unable to retrain, then what meaning will they find in life? That's personal to them and only they can solve that problem. So automation is on the way. Advances in technology are too great to ignore. The people at the bottom of the workforce are going to start being replaced. UBI may be able to solve the issue of how everyone will be able to feed themselves in this future but what about that more burning question of purpose? Now that might be harder to solve.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Wonderful Test Article</title><link href="/A-Wonderful-Test-Article" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Wonderful Test Article" /><published>2020-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Wonderful-Test-Article</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Wonderful-Test-Article">&lt;p&gt;Recent events have inspired me to culminate minutes worth of ideas into this article. These ideas are argued against and for, with a guarantee that you will have made up your mind by the last word of the last sentence of this article.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Whitby_Abbey_image.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/v7l2gGPk_x401PmY6gEj4Ms8wbrjSl6SnWlLlm8a0iG_KGjRYx1xEDSCLInxPDymfaKo7vtz5cO3Vezs56qiR6i05_fL7jiAWbbV4EKcWxafUrHqAuTRBFUhTBGb_YM09dvaLuze&quot; /&gt;“Always caption the pictures” - Harsh Tiwari (13th Oct 2020)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For:&lt;/strong&gt; Sed ut perspiciatis unde omnis iste natus error sit voluptatem accusantium doloremque laudantium, totam rem aperiam, eaque ipsa quae ab illo inventore veritatis et quasi architecto beatae vitae dicta sunt explicabo. Nemo enim ipsam voluptatem quia voluptas sit aspernatur aut odit aut fugit, sed quia consequuntur magni dolores eos qui ratione voluptatem sequi nesciunt. Neque porro quisquam est, qui dolorem ipsum quia dolor sit amet, consectetur, adipisci velit, sed quia non numquam eius modi tempora incidunt ut labore et dolore magnam aliquam quaerat voluptatem. Ut enim ad minima veniam, quis nostrum exercitationem ullam corporis suscipit laboriosam, nisi ut aliquid ex ea commodi consequatur? Quis autem vel eum iure reprehenderit qui in ea voluptate velit esse quam nihil molestiae consequatur, vel illum qui dolorem eum fugiat quo voluptas nulla pariatur&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/photos/tree-sunset-amazing-beautiful-736885/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/YDA4dy0x3sYCDpwuTwwnd2z1RvcbLMJXk8J7Eu3MI5VJyIMkoR3yanPdvenBglkvwwlmDX3TrA7Q6fsBbKhrE4gjwxGXkMG0MZwIOAXp-wicb_5Tndrj2gzqwx9jsNBDIHFRn1Q1&quot; /&gt;This one too! &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Against&lt;/strong&gt;: At vero eos et accusamus et iusto odio dignissimos ducimus qui blanditiis praesentium voluptatum deleniti atque corrupti quos dolores et quas molestias excepturi sint occaecati cupiditate non provident, similique sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollitia animi, id est laborum et dolorum fuga. Et harum quidem rerum facilis est et expedita distinctio. Nam libero tempore, cum soluta nobis est eligendi optio cumque nihil impedit quo minus id quod maxime placeat facere possimus, omnis voluptas assumenda est, omnis dolor repellendus. Temporibus autem quibusdam et aut officiis debitis aut rerum necessitatibus saepe eveniet ut et voluptates repudiandae sint et molestiae non recusandae. Itaque earum rerum hic tenetur a sapiente delectus, ut aut reiciendis voluptatibus maiores alias consequatur aut perferendis doloribus asperiores repellat.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kheeran Naidu</name></author><category term="test" /><summary type="html">Recent events have inspired me to culminate minutes worth of ideas into this article. These ideas are argued against and for, with a guarantee that you will have made up your mind by the last word of the last sentence of this article.&amp;nbsp; “Always caption the pictures” - Harsh Tiwari (13th Oct 2020) For: Sed ut perspiciatis unde omnis iste natus error sit voluptatem accusantium doloremque laudantium, totam rem aperiam, eaque ipsa quae ab illo inventore veritatis et quasi architecto beatae vitae dicta sunt explicabo. Nemo enim ipsam voluptatem quia voluptas sit aspernatur aut odit aut fugit, sed quia consequuntur magni dolores eos qui ratione voluptatem sequi nesciunt. Neque porro quisquam est, qui dolorem ipsum quia dolor sit amet, consectetur, adipisci velit, sed quia non numquam eius modi tempora incidunt ut labore et dolore magnam aliquam quaerat voluptatem. Ut enim ad minima veniam, quis nostrum exercitationem ullam corporis suscipit laboriosam, nisi ut aliquid ex ea commodi consequatur? Quis autem vel eum iure reprehenderit qui in ea voluptate velit esse quam nihil molestiae consequatur, vel illum qui dolorem eum fugiat quo voluptas nulla pariatur This one too! Against: At vero eos et accusamus et iusto odio dignissimos ducimus qui blanditiis praesentium voluptatum deleniti atque corrupti quos dolores et quas molestias excepturi sint occaecati cupiditate non provident, similique sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollitia animi, id est laborum et dolorum fuga. Et harum quidem rerum facilis est et expedita distinctio. Nam libero tempore, cum soluta nobis est eligendi optio cumque nihil impedit quo minus id quod maxime placeat facere possimus, omnis voluptas assumenda est, omnis dolor repellendus. Temporibus autem quibusdam et aut officiis debitis aut rerum necessitatibus saepe eveniet ut et voluptates repudiandae sint et molestiae non recusandae. Itaque earum rerum hic tenetur a sapiente delectus, ut aut reiciendis voluptatibus maiores alias consequatur aut perferendis doloribus asperiores repellat.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Wonderful Test Article 2</title><link href="/A-Wonderful-Test-Article-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Wonderful Test Article 2" /><published>2020-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Wonderful-Test-Article-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Wonderful-Test-Article-2">&lt;p&gt;Recent events have inspired me to culminate minutes worth of ideas into this article. These ideas are argued against and for, with a guarantee that you will have made up your mind by the last word of the last sentence of this article.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Whitby_Abbey_image.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/a-wonderful-test-article-2-image1.png&quot; /&gt;“Always caption the pictures” - Harsh Tiwari (13th Oct 2020)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For:&lt;/strong&gt; Sed ut perspiciatis unde omnis iste natus error sit voluptatem accusantium doloremque laudantium, totam rem aperiam, eaque ipsa quae ab illo inventore veritatis et quasi architecto beatae vitae dicta sunt explicabo. Nemo enim ipsam voluptatem quia voluptas sit aspernatur aut odit aut fugit, sed quia consequuntur magni dolores eos qui ratione voluptatem sequi nesciunt. Neque porro quisquam est, qui dolorem ipsum quia dolor sit amet, consectetur, adipisci velit, sed quia non numquam eius modi tempora incidunt ut labore et dolore magnam aliquam quaerat voluptatem. Ut enim ad minima veniam, quis nostrum exercitationem ullam corporis suscipit laboriosam, nisi ut aliquid ex ea commodi consequatur? Quis autem vel eum iure reprehenderit qui in ea voluptate velit esse quam nihil molestiae consequatur, vel illum qui dolorem eum fugiat quo voluptas nulla pariatur&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/photos/tree-sunset-amazing-beautiful-736885/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/a-wonderful-test-article-2-image2.png&quot; /&gt;This one too! &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Against&lt;/strong&gt;: At vero eos et accusamus et iusto odio dignissimos ducimus qui blanditiis praesentium voluptatum deleniti atque corrupti quos dolores et quas molestias excepturi sint occaecati cupiditate non provident, similique sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollitia animi, id est laborum et dolorum fuga. Et harum quidem rerum facilis est et expedita distinctio. Nam libero tempore, cum soluta nobis est eligendi optio cumque nihil impedit quo minus id quod maxime placeat facere possimus, omnis voluptas assumenda est, omnis dolor repellendus. Temporibus autem quibusdam et aut officiis debitis aut rerum necessitatibus saepe eveniet ut et voluptates repudiandae sint et molestiae non recusandae. Itaque earum rerum hic tenetur a sapiente delectus, ut aut reiciendis voluptatibus maiores alias consequatur aut perferendis doloribus asperiores repellat.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kheeran Naidu</name></author><summary type="html">Recent events have inspired me to culminate minutes worth of ideas into this article. These ideas are argued against and for, with a guarantee that you will have made up your mind by the last word of the last sentence of this article.&amp;nbsp; “Always caption the pictures” - Harsh Tiwari (13th Oct 2020) For: Sed ut perspiciatis unde omnis iste natus error sit voluptatem accusantium doloremque laudantium, totam rem aperiam, eaque ipsa quae ab illo inventore veritatis et quasi architecto beatae vitae dicta sunt explicabo. Nemo enim ipsam voluptatem quia voluptas sit aspernatur aut odit aut fugit, sed quia consequuntur magni dolores eos qui ratione voluptatem sequi nesciunt. Neque porro quisquam est, qui dolorem ipsum quia dolor sit amet, consectetur, adipisci velit, sed quia non numquam eius modi tempora incidunt ut labore et dolore magnam aliquam quaerat voluptatem. Ut enim ad minima veniam, quis nostrum exercitationem ullam corporis suscipit laboriosam, nisi ut aliquid ex ea commodi consequatur? Quis autem vel eum iure reprehenderit qui in ea voluptate velit esse quam nihil molestiae consequatur, vel illum qui dolorem eum fugiat quo voluptas nulla pariatur This one too! Against: At vero eos et accusamus et iusto odio dignissimos ducimus qui blanditiis praesentium voluptatum deleniti atque corrupti quos dolores et quas molestias excepturi sint occaecati cupiditate non provident, similique sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollitia animi, id est laborum et dolorum fuga. Et harum quidem rerum facilis est et expedita distinctio. Nam libero tempore, cum soluta nobis est eligendi optio cumque nihil impedit quo minus id quod maxime placeat facere possimus, omnis voluptas assumenda est, omnis dolor repellendus. Temporibus autem quibusdam et aut officiis debitis aut rerum necessitatibus saepe eveniet ut et voluptates repudiandae sint et molestiae non recusandae. Itaque earum rerum hic tenetur a sapiente delectus, ut aut reiciendis voluptatibus maiores alias consequatur aut perferendis doloribus asperiores repellat.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Test Article with Images</title><link href="/Test-Article-with-Images" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Test Article with Images" /><published>2020-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Test-Article-with-Images</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Test-Article-with-Images">&lt;p&gt;Shinzo Abe announced that he was resigning from his post on August 28, 2020. He stated that he was doing so in light of extreme health issues, and apologised to the people of Japan for failing to complete his term in the office and for leaving the nation in a period of political uncertainty. At the age of 65 years, Abe suffers from a chronic condition called ‘ulcerative colitis’, which he was diagnosed with when he was a teenager. It is an inflammatory bowel disease that has accentuated recently, prompting him to take this drastic precaution for his health. He had resigned even earlier in 2007 due to this condition. After this, his new period in the office started in 2012, and he has been loved by his people ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Abenomics'&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/slsIXVC3zyCu9LcqXHyNk_PVvU46hJe8_dkwxLa3uVMx9WC1jbObQHKR5yAc1ivXMN21DL0yljtJ0EqrSFPuuiyE7bDxn7eTww5ILxak85NB4-U5LlIUogA_L0YI4XrQI5cQ0vVC&quot; /&gt;First Caption&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A member of the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP), his reputation is that of a strong nationalist and conservative. His right tilted political front with the Liberal Democratic Party has boosted its popularity. Abe has led it in both the houses of Japanese Parliament. He has developed a stronghold in economic policy on a self-named programme known as 'Abenomics', which he introduced in 2012. An output plan to jumpstart Japan's economy, it has been focussed on the stagnant growth of monetary policy, fiscal stimulus and structural reforms. The success of Abenomics has resulted in a double-edged sword with him aggressively focusing on the first two promises, yet sorely lacking in structural reform. Although his win in the consecutive elections has not been entirely because of this policy, it has played a crucial role. Mr Shinzo Abe has mostly been lauded for his representation as a modicum of stability in Japanese political history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thepangean.com&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/Zy0EhYFsdRl1tInH9vK8H-eknjPsZkLf7stwfHYBHwglThL9T1t3uIXlgsMUuW1AQSnVONUVAj4jea_xIDuxZgOvT7WvVJK_6XMLdEmc0V1OFKc5uKUSsjfx5_hssb622eYTnEoI&quot; /&gt;Second Caption&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kheeran Naidu</name></author><summary type="html">Shinzo Abe announced that he was resigning from his post on August 28, 2020. He stated that he was doing so in light of extreme health issues, and apologised to the people of Japan for failing to complete his term in the office and for leaving the nation in a period of political uncertainty. At the age of 65 years, Abe suffers from a chronic condition called ‘ulcerative colitis’, which he was diagnosed with when he was a teenager. It is an inflammatory bowel disease that has accentuated recently, prompting him to take this drastic precaution for his health. He had resigned even earlier in 2007 due to this condition. After this, his new period in the office started in 2012, and he has been loved by his people ever since. ‘Abenomics' First CaptionA member of the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP), his reputation is that of a strong nationalist and conservative. His right tilted political front with the Liberal Democratic Party has boosted its popularity. Abe has led it in both the houses of Japanese Parliament. He has developed a stronghold in economic policy on a self-named programme known as 'Abenomics', which he introduced in 2012. An output plan to jumpstart Japan's economy, it has been focussed on the stagnant growth of monetary policy, fiscal stimulus and structural reforms. The success of Abenomics has resulted in a double-edged sword with him aggressively focusing on the first two promises, yet sorely lacking in structural reform. Although his win in the consecutive elections has not been entirely because of this policy, it has played a crucial role. Mr Shinzo Abe has mostly been lauded for his representation as a modicum of stability in Japanese political history. Second Caption</summary></entry></feed>