<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-18T22:00:59+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality</title><link href="/Transgenders-in-Sports" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality" /><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Transgenders-in-Sports</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Transgenders-in-Sports">&lt;p&gt;Throughout the U.S., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators&lt;/a&gt; that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Issue at Hand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's &lt;strong&gt;100 meters&lt;/strong&gt; lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.duke.edu/sports/sex-sport/comparative-athletic-performance/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds&lt;/a&gt;. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6391653/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges&lt;/a&gt; (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.olympic.org/the-ioc&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International Olympic Committee&lt;/a&gt; (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/01/sports/transgender-idaho-ban-sports.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ki.se/new-study-on-changes-in-muscle-mass-and-strength-after-gender-affirming-treatment-may-have-an&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-connecticut-girl-challenges-male-domination-of-female-sports-11562885421#&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year&lt;/a&gt;. Within just three years, girls across the state were &lt;a href=&quot;https://mspolicy.org/an-interview-with-selina-soule-a-brave-young-woman-standing-up-for-womens-sports/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/news/hsph-in-the-news/transgender-youth-at-risk-for-depression-suicide/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/trumps-plan-to-redefine-gender-makes-no-scientific-sense/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the limits of what science can offer&lt;/a&gt;, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions still unsolved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moving on, what about Intersex people?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eeshita Verma</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Throughout the U.S., roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about? Terminology Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand. The Issue at Hand The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’ To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly: Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's 100 meters lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp; Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories. So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp; One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the International Olympic Committee (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year.&amp;nbsp; But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (Source) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women. One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp; Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year. Within just three years, girls across the state were denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions. Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp; The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’ To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete. A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established. However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier. Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity. And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge. These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp; This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender? Possible Solutions One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp; For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against the limits of what science can offer, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp; Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels? Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task. If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions. Questions still unsolved To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders? Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago. Moving on, what about Intersex people? Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex. To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well. Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Indian Pharma Industry: Present and Future</title><link href="/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Pharma Industry: Present and Future" /><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared the coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 to be a pandemic. More than a year after the outbreak, over three million people have lost their lives with approximately 152 million cases across the globe. The pandemic has managed to cause a complete upheaval in people’s lifestyle along with businesses running losses and workers losing their jobs. Amidst this scenario, it is the pharmaceutical industry that has taken centre stage in the fight against this menace, assisting world governments in fulfilling their population's needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The global pharmaceutical industry in 2019 achieved a market value of approximately $1,217 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 6.7%. This value is expected to decline to $1,209 billion in 2020 owing to the COVID-19 outbreak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pharmaceutical (or pharma) industry can be defined as a “&lt;em&gt;complex system of processes, operations, and organisations involved in the discovery, development, and manufacturing of drugs&lt;/em&gt;”. Firms functioning in the industry are responsible for research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities, development and manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients and manufacturing of drugs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, Germany occupied the top position in the pharma industry with a 14.5% share in the export of drugs and medicines. It was followed by Switzerland and Netherlands with a share of 12.2% and 7.9% respectively. Among other countries, Denmark, Netherlands and Italy are the fastest growing exporters of drugs and medicines since 2015. However, three countries have witnessed a decline in the exported drugs and medicines sales in the last five years. These are, namely, the United Kingdom (26.7%), Ireland (18.9%) and the United States (6.1%).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In recent years, growth patterns in developed economies have observed a flat trend which has induced firms to shift their focus to emerging markets, thus finding new sources of revenue and profitability. The same has been witnessed for the pharmaceutical industry. The pharmaceutical emerging markets, or 'pharmerging' markets hold the potential of an extraordinary growth story.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2016, emerging markets accounted for over 30% of the development in pharma markets. This shift has been attributed to the economic and demographic development in these economies with a rise in health expectancy, access to healthcare services and improved funding for the healthcare sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another major factor is the sharp decline in firms’ revenue as a result of the expiration of patents. This is known as the patent cliff, which is now affecting several branded drugs that have been in the market for years. The shift towards the use of generic drugs worldwide, increasing availability of biosimilar drugs, a significant differential in manufacturing costs and prices, and change in disease patterns in emerging countries are some of the other major reasons for the shift being observed in the pharmaceutical industry. These factors have induced the emerging economies into becoming the key drivers of the global pharmaceutical market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Among the emerging markets, five countries namely China, Brazil, Russia, India and South Africa are the ones in domination with their role becoming increasingly important in the coming decade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pharmaceutical Industry in India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the last fifty years, India’s pharmaceutical industry has grown by leaps and bounds. From having a 5% share of the total medicine consumption in India in 1969, Indian pharma holds an 85% share of the same in 2020. Today, India is not only able to meet its domestic needs but has also established itself as a leader in the global pharma landscape and is known as the ‘pharmacy of the world’. The industry today is recognised for the quality and cost-effectiveness of its products. Widely known as the ‘archetype of affordable healthcare’, the Indian industry has had a significant contribution towards the improvement of public health outcomes, both within India and across the globe.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With a market size of $41 billion in 2018-19 and a market growth rate of 10-12%, the Indian pharma industry exported $16.3 billion worth of bulk drugs, intermediates, drug formulations, herbal products, surgical equipment and other goods in 2019-20. Particularly, the industry contributes more than 20% by volume to the global generics market and 62% of the global demand for vaccines. Fourteenth largest in the world in terms of value and 3rd largest in terms of volume, the industry is expected to grow to $100 billion by 2025.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Within India, the industry plays an important role in India’s economic growth and is recognised as one of the top sectors attracting foreign direct investment (FDI) and reducing the trade deficit. The sector attracted a total of $16.54 billion worth of FDI inflow between April 2000 and June 2020. The sector’s importance is further underlined due to the amount of trade surplus generated with exports accounting for $20.7 billion and imports at $2.31 billion in the year 2020. The industry generates employment for over 2.7 million people, directly or indirectly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COVID-19 and Opportunity for India in Post-Pandemic World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The outbreak of the virus has challenged healthcare systems around the globe. From the United States, a country that undertakes the highest expenditure on its healthcare system, to the sophisticated European healthcare systems, each country is struggling to contain the spread. Despite the plethora of measures undertaken by countries, the massive inpouring of coronavirus infected patients has exceeded the existing infrastructure and resources in several countries, with the disease causing huge loss of life and human suffering. Additionally, there is a shortage of essential equipment, medicinal supplies and even medicines. The pandemic has also brought forth the existing inequalities in access to healthcare globally.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst these challenges, the global pharmaceutical markets are facing major discontinuities. For instance, there have been concerns regarding global over-dependence on China for active pharmaceutical ingredients (API), particularly in India, the US and Europe. As a result, in the past few months, several countries have been experiencing disruption in the pharma supply chain. The pandemic has also reinforced issues like re-shoring, nearshoring and shortening supply chains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Indian pharmaceutical industry has been a key contributor in improving the healthcare outcomes in the country with the pandemic presenting several opportunities and challenges for the industry. The growing distrust in China comes as an opportunity for India even so the economy will be facing increased competition from countries like Vietnam and Malaysia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To utilise the post-pandemic potential to the fullest, the industry has to build on its strength along with taking a giant leap towards innovation. The introduction of new capabilities is necessary to bring efficiencies to facilitate the industry to move up the value chain. A two-fold approach can be adopted to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, India needs to explore opportunities in complex generics, biosimilars, vaccines and preventives and other complex products. Having attained leadership in the generic market globally, India now needs to consolidate its position in other markets to move up the value chain. Focusing on complex products for this matter will help to achieve long-term sustained growth for the sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;These complex generics involve a comparatively more difficult production process, face less competition and involve higher margins. Similarly, biosimilars can play an equally important role in expanding India’s pharma sector. Domestically, India is leading in the world when it comes to launching biosimilars, however, only a few Indian companies are able to infiltrate US and European markets due to the non-alignment of India's regulatory guidelines with the regulations in these markets. In addition to the generics market, India has also established itself as a strong contender in the global vaccines market, with the country supplying 60% of the world's vaccine requirements. The step further is thus to develop new and complex vaccines, especially in times like these.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The second approach should be with respect to innovation. India needs to set up an environment conducive to innovation by bringing together academia, pharma companies, entrepreneurs and medical institutions. A look at the global scenario reveals that there is a concentration of research and development activities in the US and Europe, reflecting their dominance in innovation. India also does not compare well with its counterpart China which has twice the number of R&amp;amp;D sites and innovation centres. Therefore, there exists tremendous scope for India to establish itself as a global innovation hub.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In conclusion, the increasing shift of pharmaceutical firms from western economies to emerging economies presents India with a golden opportunity to enhance its pharma production along with emerging as a strong contender in the R&amp;amp;D sector. Even though the pandemic has resulted in innumerable challenges to the economy and the pharma industry in particular, it has also presented the industry with an opportunity to rise to the occasion and establish itself as a leading global player. Whether the country is able to perform on this front remains to be seen!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rajsi Sah</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared the coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 to be a pandemic. More than a year after the outbreak, over three million people have lost their lives with approximately 152 million cases across the globe. The pandemic has managed to cause a complete upheaval in people’s lifestyle along with businesses running losses and workers losing their jobs. Amidst this scenario, it is the pharmaceutical industry that has taken centre stage in the fight against this menace, assisting world governments in fulfilling their population's needs.&amp;nbsp; The global pharmaceutical industry in 2019 achieved a market value of approximately $1,217 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 6.7%. This value is expected to decline to $1,209 billion in 2020 owing to the COVID-19 outbreak.&amp;nbsp; The pharmaceutical (or pharma) industry can be defined as a “complex system of processes, operations, and organisations involved in the discovery, development, and manufacturing of drugs”. Firms functioning in the industry are responsible for research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities, development and manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients and manufacturing of drugs.&amp;nbsp; In 2019, Germany occupied the top position in the pharma industry with a 14.5% share in the export of drugs and medicines. It was followed by Switzerland and Netherlands with a share of 12.2% and 7.9% respectively. Among other countries, Denmark, Netherlands and Italy are the fastest growing exporters of drugs and medicines since 2015. However, three countries have witnessed a decline in the exported drugs and medicines sales in the last five years. These are, namely, the United Kingdom (26.7%), Ireland (18.9%) and the United States (6.1%).&amp;nbsp; In recent years, growth patterns in developed economies have observed a flat trend which has induced firms to shift their focus to emerging markets, thus finding new sources of revenue and profitability. The same has been witnessed for the pharmaceutical industry. The pharmaceutical emerging markets, or 'pharmerging' markets hold the potential of an extraordinary growth story.&amp;nbsp; In 2016, emerging markets accounted for over 30% of the development in pharma markets. This shift has been attributed to the economic and demographic development in these economies with a rise in health expectancy, access to healthcare services and improved funding for the healthcare sector.&amp;nbsp; Another major factor is the sharp decline in firms’ revenue as a result of the expiration of patents. This is known as the patent cliff, which is now affecting several branded drugs that have been in the market for years. The shift towards the use of generic drugs worldwide, increasing availability of biosimilar drugs, a significant differential in manufacturing costs and prices, and change in disease patterns in emerging countries are some of the other major reasons for the shift being observed in the pharmaceutical industry. These factors have induced the emerging economies into becoming the key drivers of the global pharmaceutical market.&amp;nbsp; Among the emerging markets, five countries namely China, Brazil, Russia, India and South Africa are the ones in domination with their role becoming increasingly important in the coming decade.&amp;nbsp; Pharmaceutical Industry in India In the last fifty years, India’s pharmaceutical industry has grown by leaps and bounds. From having a 5% share of the total medicine consumption in India in 1969, Indian pharma holds an 85% share of the same in 2020. Today, India is not only able to meet its domestic needs but has also established itself as a leader in the global pharma landscape and is known as the ‘pharmacy of the world’. The industry today is recognised for the quality and cost-effectiveness of its products. Widely known as the ‘archetype of affordable healthcare’, the Indian industry has had a significant contribution towards the improvement of public health outcomes, both within India and across the globe.&amp;nbsp; With a market size of $41 billion in 2018-19 and a market growth rate of 10-12%, the Indian pharma industry exported $16.3 billion worth of bulk drugs, intermediates, drug formulations, herbal products, surgical equipment and other goods in 2019-20. Particularly, the industry contributes more than 20% by volume to the global generics market and 62% of the global demand for vaccines. Fourteenth largest in the world in terms of value and 3rd largest in terms of volume, the industry is expected to grow to $100 billion by 2025.&amp;nbsp; Within India, the industry plays an important role in India’s economic growth and is recognised as one of the top sectors attracting foreign direct investment (FDI) and reducing the trade deficit. The sector attracted a total of $16.54 billion worth of FDI inflow between April 2000 and June 2020. The sector’s importance is further underlined due to the amount of trade surplus generated with exports accounting for $20.7 billion and imports at $2.31 billion in the year 2020. The industry generates employment for over 2.7 million people, directly or indirectly.&amp;nbsp; COVID-19 and Opportunity for India in Post-Pandemic World The outbreak of the virus has challenged healthcare systems around the globe. From the United States, a country that undertakes the highest expenditure on its healthcare system, to the sophisticated European healthcare systems, each country is struggling to contain the spread. Despite the plethora of measures undertaken by countries, the massive inpouring of coronavirus infected patients has exceeded the existing infrastructure and resources in several countries, with the disease causing huge loss of life and human suffering. Additionally, there is a shortage of essential equipment, medicinal supplies and even medicines. The pandemic has also brought forth the existing inequalities in access to healthcare globally.&amp;nbsp; Amidst these challenges, the global pharmaceutical markets are facing major discontinuities. For instance, there have been concerns regarding global over-dependence on China for active pharmaceutical ingredients (API), particularly in India, the US and Europe. As a result, in the past few months, several countries have been experiencing disruption in the pharma supply chain. The pandemic has also reinforced issues like re-shoring, nearshoring and shortening supply chains.&amp;nbsp; The Indian pharmaceutical industry has been a key contributor in improving the healthcare outcomes in the country with the pandemic presenting several opportunities and challenges for the industry. The growing distrust in China comes as an opportunity for India even so the economy will be facing increased competition from countries like Vietnam and Malaysia.&amp;nbsp; To utilise the post-pandemic potential to the fullest, the industry has to build on its strength along with taking a giant leap towards innovation. The introduction of new capabilities is necessary to bring efficiencies to facilitate the industry to move up the value chain. A two-fold approach can be adopted to achieve this. First, India needs to explore opportunities in complex generics, biosimilars, vaccines and preventives and other complex products. Having attained leadership in the generic market globally, India now needs to consolidate its position in other markets to move up the value chain. Focusing on complex products for this matter will help to achieve long-term sustained growth for the sector.&amp;nbsp; These complex generics involve a comparatively more difficult production process, face less competition and involve higher margins. Similarly, biosimilars can play an equally important role in expanding India’s pharma sector. Domestically, India is leading in the world when it comes to launching biosimilars, however, only a few Indian companies are able to infiltrate US and European markets due to the non-alignment of India's regulatory guidelines with the regulations in these markets. In addition to the generics market, India has also established itself as a strong contender in the global vaccines market, with the country supplying 60% of the world's vaccine requirements. The step further is thus to develop new and complex vaccines, especially in times like these.&amp;nbsp; The second approach should be with respect to innovation. India needs to set up an environment conducive to innovation by bringing together academia, pharma companies, entrepreneurs and medical institutions. A look at the global scenario reveals that there is a concentration of research and development activities in the US and Europe, reflecting their dominance in innovation. India also does not compare well with its counterpart China which has twice the number of R&amp;amp;D sites and innovation centres. Therefore, there exists tremendous scope for India to establish itself as a global innovation hub.&amp;nbsp; In conclusion, the increasing shift of pharmaceutical firms from western economies to emerging economies presents India with a golden opportunity to enhance its pharma production along with emerging as a strong contender in the R&amp;amp;D sector. Even though the pandemic has resulted in innumerable challenges to the economy and the pharma industry in particular, it has also presented the industry with an opportunity to rise to the occasion and establish itself as a leading global player. Whether the country is able to perform on this front remains to be seen!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Political Drama Worthy of Shakespeare: The Case of Malaysia</title><link href="/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Political Drama Worthy of Shakespeare: The Case of Malaysia" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare">&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Najib Razzak, who had become Prime Minister with the campaign promise of liberal politics, lost a general election to his former mentor, Mahathir Mohamad. The Barisan Nasional (BN) coalition, which had governed the country since its independence in 1957, was voted out of power. Following the downfall, Najib's properties were raided. Both he and his wife were charged with a string of offences and since then been found guilty on seven charges of corruption linked to the multibillion-dollar state investment fund 1MDB.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Najib’s history with corruption allegations is a long one. He has consistently denied the allegations and had been cleared by the country's authorities while still in office. During his tenure, he reformed strict laws on public gatherings and reinstated the controversial Internal Security Act in 2011 allowing detention without trial. The following year, he also went back on a pledge to repeal a controversial sedition law and instead strengthened it. Critics say the laws were a way for Najib to silence his political opponents and pander to the ethnic Malay-Muslim majority who formed his political party's most significant support base. In 2015, opposition leader and former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim was convicted of sodomy for the second time. In 2016, a security act aimed at combating terrorism was used to detain electoral reform activists. Ahead of the 2018 election, Najib's government set up a law against spreading &quot;fake news”, inadvertently used to silence campaigns by his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a string of numerous allegations, the real blight of Najib's political career has been his mismanagement of the state investment fund, 1Malaysia Development Berhad. The 1MDB fund was set up in 2009 to turn Kuala Lumpur into a financial hub and boost the economy through strategic investments. It began to draw negative attention in early 2015 after it missed payments due for some of the $11 billion it owed to banks and bondholders. The fund was then indicted for money laundering and sending hundreds of millions of dollars into private pockets to acquire assets globally, including yachts, paintings, jewellery and real estate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Department of Justice began investigating 1MDB, finding a diversion of $4.5 billion. Najib Razak was accused of pocketing nearly $700 million from the fund he set up. Ahead of the 2018 election, mass protests in Kuala Lumpur called on him to resign. The claims of corruption at 1MDB were a significant cause of Najib's election loss to Mahathir Mohamad, the world's oldest elected leader. Shortly after his victory, Malaysia's new Prime Minister reopened the 1MDB investigations and swore that Najib &quot;would face the consequences&quot; if he was guilty. Najib was forbidden from leaving the country, and properties linked to him were raided. Policemen state they recovered $273 million in luxury goods and cash, calling the seizure of valuables the biggest in Malaysian history.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US prosecutors had hinted that an anonymous individual dubbed &quot;Malaysian Official 1&quot; had received more than $1 billion from 1MDB, and that person is broadly believed to be Najib. Another target of the investigation is Malaysian businessman Low Taek Jho, who helped set up the fund, and is accused of diverting money to himself and his associates. He, too, has consistently rebuffed any wrongdoing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, Najib was arrested by anti-corruption authorities. He faces 21 counts of money laundering and 4 for abuse of power and negates all wrongdoing. The 12-year jail term for Malaysia's ex-Prime Minister serves as a warning that no matter how powerful one becomes, the sceptre of democracy hangs low over the heads of all public officials.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samakshi Garg</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 2018, Najib Razzak, who had become Prime Minister with the campaign promise of liberal politics, lost a general election to his former mentor, Mahathir Mohamad. The Barisan Nasional (BN) coalition, which had governed the country since its independence in 1957, was voted out of power. Following the downfall, Najib's properties were raided. Both he and his wife were charged with a string of offences and since then been found guilty on seven charges of corruption linked to the multibillion-dollar state investment fund 1MDB.&amp;nbsp; Najib’s history with corruption allegations is a long one. He has consistently denied the allegations and had been cleared by the country's authorities while still in office. During his tenure, he reformed strict laws on public gatherings and reinstated the controversial Internal Security Act in 2011 allowing detention without trial. The following year, he also went back on a pledge to repeal a controversial sedition law and instead strengthened it. Critics say the laws were a way for Najib to silence his political opponents and pander to the ethnic Malay-Muslim majority who formed his political party's most significant support base. In 2015, opposition leader and former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim was convicted of sodomy for the second time. In 2016, a security act aimed at combating terrorism was used to detain electoral reform activists. Ahead of the 2018 election, Najib's government set up a law against spreading &quot;fake news”, inadvertently used to silence campaigns by his opponents. Despite a string of numerous allegations, the real blight of Najib's political career has been his mismanagement of the state investment fund, 1Malaysia Development Berhad. The 1MDB fund was set up in 2009 to turn Kuala Lumpur into a financial hub and boost the economy through strategic investments. It began to draw negative attention in early 2015 after it missed payments due for some of the $11 billion it owed to banks and bondholders. The fund was then indicted for money laundering and sending hundreds of millions of dollars into private pockets to acquire assets globally, including yachts, paintings, jewellery and real estate.&amp;nbsp; The US Department of Justice began investigating 1MDB, finding a diversion of $4.5 billion. Najib Razak was accused of pocketing nearly $700 million from the fund he set up. Ahead of the 2018 election, mass protests in Kuala Lumpur called on him to resign. The claims of corruption at 1MDB were a significant cause of Najib's election loss to Mahathir Mohamad, the world's oldest elected leader. Shortly after his victory, Malaysia's new Prime Minister reopened the 1MDB investigations and swore that Najib &quot;would face the consequences&quot; if he was guilty. Najib was forbidden from leaving the country, and properties linked to him were raided. Policemen state they recovered $273 million in luxury goods and cash, calling the seizure of valuables the biggest in Malaysian history.&amp;nbsp; US prosecutors had hinted that an anonymous individual dubbed &quot;Malaysian Official 1&quot; had received more than $1 billion from 1MDB, and that person is broadly believed to be Najib. Another target of the investigation is Malaysian businessman Low Taek Jho, who helped set up the fund, and is accused of diverting money to himself and his associates. He, too, has consistently rebuffed any wrongdoing.&amp;nbsp; Eventually, Najib was arrested by anti-corruption authorities. He faces 21 counts of money laundering and 4 for abuse of power and negates all wrongdoing. The 12-year jail term for Malaysia's ex-Prime Minister serves as a warning that no matter how powerful one becomes, the sceptre of democracy hangs low over the heads of all public officials.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy</title><link href="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What seeds medical tourism?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Home Front&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, &lt;em&gt;atithi-devo-bhava &lt;/em&gt;(guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp; Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp; Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility. What seeds medical tourism? Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp; India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp; While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp; The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp; The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes. India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp; Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp; On the Home Front The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp; Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp; The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp; Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, atithi-devo-bhava (guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca</title><link href="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca">&lt;p&gt;When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Abhinav Gupta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guest</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products. Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp; Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp; The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp; Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&amp;nbsp;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp; If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production. The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp; The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market. Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology. LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp; The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp; While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp; The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp; There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp; The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp; The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp; LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp; -Abhinav Gupta Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A 23 on The Test</title><link href="/A-23-on-The-Test" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A 23 on The Test" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-23-on-The-Test</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-23-on-The-Test">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is not often that one gets to do what one enjoys the most, and I do. I get to announce to the world my life and web history. Unfortunately, the latter is almost always more exciting than the former and that is completely on me.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As an emotionally stunted child who wore the ugliest orange-brown clothes, I wondered which vehicle would zoom me out of my very own, personally customised hell. Turns out, it all begins with writing the lyrics of &lt;em&gt;Turning Page&lt;/em&gt; (from &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt;, duh) in a yellow, Winnie-the-Pooh diary. That and more, enveloped between multiple pages about overbearing mothers and underwhelming crushes can pave you the perfect path. My road to this pleasured life - wherein one learns to write like a jilted lover who married Freud’s second cousin, while may not have been easy, but it surely has been interesting to talk about. I may think I am all snark and sass, but underneath it all, I believe I am just an underdeveloped adult (read: kid) who barely has any control over herself and her relationships. Seldom have I ever given thought to who I would be if not me (not that I know who I am to begin with). A narcissistic go-getter? A quiet soul that fills everyone around them with peace? A bubbly know-it-all? Who!? Hold up, what if I am all of these or worse, none of them? What if I am just an unseasoned cardboard? Ah, the suspense.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Narcissism, come to think of it, is a word quite widely used and abused. Have you not called your ex one when he forgot your birthday? Or when your best friend buys that pair of jeans you had chosen for yourself? Often, the term is shrouded with the veil of self-love, and is even explained as vanity. But to be able to completely comprehend what it means, maybe we ought to step into the shoes of a narcissist. But first, should we test ourselves? How narcissistic are we? I have managed to find us all a risqué, not-all-that-legit &lt;a href=&quot;https://openpsychometrics.org/tests/NPI/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;test&lt;/a&gt;. If you tell me your scores, I will tell you mine (wink, wink), and then we can open a club!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The word ‘narcissism’ commonly describes someone who is excessively self-absorbed, selfish and egotistical, self-enhancing, arrogant, and shameless; but it is also used to explain individuals who are headstrong and may as well be used in a positive connotation. You see, before the Pandemic of Foreverland, they trended the idea of ‘Narcissism Epidemic’. It was based on the foundation of the ‘ME! ME! ME!’ life that many of us (us being Millennials and Gen Z) are leading. The social media influencers amidst us, have both literally and figuratively made a living out of just talking about and being concerned about oneself. From ‘OOTDs’ to ‘My Skincare Routine’- we’ve all been witnesses to the magic. I will watch Zendaya, or Harry Styles put on sunscreen any day, any time, no questions asked. And that may just be me with a keen level of fascination - but to each of them, the artists, they have to live with the idea of being famous for being ‘them’. This ‘Me’ culture quite vividly personifies the definition of Narcissism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This is not to say - any and every celebrity is a narcissist, just the ones who do not care about anyone else but them, such as Trump- (Melania, of course. Since the other Trump is irrelevant). It has been found that narcissistic traits afflict almost 10% of people in their 20s, compared to the 3% of people in their 60s, suggesting that as we grow older, our personalities are more settled and well-formed. I must say, this proves me right about how babies are just cute li’l narcissistic tiny-humans. All they care about is their milk and toys, the ‘me’ time never ends for them (oh the absolute joy!). I wonder if my suggestion of being a narcissist is also narcissistic. I wonder if we have made it so that anything but downgrading oneself beyond humility is how you prove you are not a narcissist. I wonder if only at the DSM’s criteria can we lay down the damage of narcissism and anything else is just immaculate fake news. The personality disorder of Narcissism is not something I’ve delved into, maybe due to the inconsistencies it may bring to our lives (self-fulfilling prophecy is real, people) or perhaps because no collection of symptoms is worth the trauma of self-diagnosis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Authority, self-sufficiency - a belief that one has achieved everything on their own, superiority, exhibitionism, exploitative-ness, vanity, and entitlement: these are the factoids used by the aforementioned risqué test, all quite all-encompassing, all traits of serial killers and great actors. All not all that bad sounding. Hitherto, the true problem that underlies narcissistic traits is not that they are problematic but that they are unrealistic. However much one is to believe otherwise, the belief in one’s own extraordinariness will sooner or later come to an end. Disillusionment is at bay. Now, one may choose to cross the bay, or stay stagnant and enjoy life while giving others’ plight - it's obviously a fair choice.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;You see, with a topic such as this, I can go on and on - hell, who am I kidding, I can go on and on about the most mundane of things - but today is special. I type all this knowing I might not get to do this again for some time now. Each time that I have penned down my thoughts, I have thought about how maybe it's just me and my editor who get a good chuckle out of these. Each time I tell myself my editor probably does not chuckle at all. Each time I am glad for the opportunity, upset about my own expectations and ecstatic over having been able to transfer my head-junk on paper. Narcissistic or not, I’m glad to be here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Disclaimer- I did score a 23 on the test, and if you did, too- please let’s form a Club! We can name it “Harshita’s”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><summary type="html">It is not often that one gets to do what one enjoys the most, and I do. I get to announce to the world my life and web history. Unfortunately, the latter is almost always more exciting than the former and that is completely on me.&amp;nbsp; As an emotionally stunted child who wore the ugliest orange-brown clothes, I wondered which vehicle would zoom me out of my very own, personally customised hell. Turns out, it all begins with writing the lyrics of Turning Page (from Twilight, duh) in a yellow, Winnie-the-Pooh diary. That and more, enveloped between multiple pages about overbearing mothers and underwhelming crushes can pave you the perfect path. My road to this pleasured life - wherein one learns to write like a jilted lover who married Freud’s second cousin, while may not have been easy, but it surely has been interesting to talk about. I may think I am all snark and sass, but underneath it all, I believe I am just an underdeveloped adult (read: kid) who barely has any control over herself and her relationships. Seldom have I ever given thought to who I would be if not me (not that I know who I am to begin with). A narcissistic go-getter? A quiet soul that fills everyone around them with peace? A bubbly know-it-all? Who!? Hold up, what if I am all of these or worse, none of them? What if I am just an unseasoned cardboard? Ah, the suspense.&amp;nbsp; Narcissism, come to think of it, is a word quite widely used and abused. Have you not called your ex one when he forgot your birthday? Or when your best friend buys that pair of jeans you had chosen for yourself? Often, the term is shrouded with the veil of self-love, and is even explained as vanity. But to be able to completely comprehend what it means, maybe we ought to step into the shoes of a narcissist. But first, should we test ourselves? How narcissistic are we? I have managed to find us all a risqué, not-all-that-legit test. If you tell me your scores, I will tell you mine (wink, wink), and then we can open a club! The word ‘narcissism’ commonly describes someone who is excessively self-absorbed, selfish and egotistical, self-enhancing, arrogant, and shameless; but it is also used to explain individuals who are headstrong and may as well be used in a positive connotation. You see, before the Pandemic of Foreverland, they trended the idea of ‘Narcissism Epidemic’. It was based on the foundation of the ‘ME! ME! ME!’ life that many of us (us being Millennials and Gen Z) are leading. The social media influencers amidst us, have both literally and figuratively made a living out of just talking about and being concerned about oneself. From ‘OOTDs’ to ‘My Skincare Routine’- we’ve all been witnesses to the magic. I will watch Zendaya, or Harry Styles put on sunscreen any day, any time, no questions asked. And that may just be me with a keen level of fascination - but to each of them, the artists, they have to live with the idea of being famous for being ‘them’. This ‘Me’ culture quite vividly personifies the definition of Narcissism.&amp;nbsp; This is not to say - any and every celebrity is a narcissist, just the ones who do not care about anyone else but them, such as Trump- (Melania, of course. Since the other Trump is irrelevant). It has been found that narcissistic traits afflict almost 10% of people in their 20s, compared to the 3% of people in their 60s, suggesting that as we grow older, our personalities are more settled and well-formed. I must say, this proves me right about how babies are just cute li’l narcissistic tiny-humans. All they care about is their milk and toys, the ‘me’ time never ends for them (oh the absolute joy!). I wonder if my suggestion of being a narcissist is also narcissistic. I wonder if we have made it so that anything but downgrading oneself beyond humility is how you prove you are not a narcissist. I wonder if only at the DSM’s criteria can we lay down the damage of narcissism and anything else is just immaculate fake news. The personality disorder of Narcissism is not something I’ve delved into, maybe due to the inconsistencies it may bring to our lives (self-fulfilling prophecy is real, people) or perhaps because no collection of symptoms is worth the trauma of self-diagnosis.&amp;nbsp; Authority, self-sufficiency - a belief that one has achieved everything on their own, superiority, exhibitionism, exploitative-ness, vanity, and entitlement: these are the factoids used by the aforementioned risqué test, all quite all-encompassing, all traits of serial killers and great actors. All not all that bad sounding. Hitherto, the true problem that underlies narcissistic traits is not that they are problematic but that they are unrealistic. However much one is to believe otherwise, the belief in one’s own extraordinariness will sooner or later come to an end. Disillusionment is at bay. Now, one may choose to cross the bay, or stay stagnant and enjoy life while giving others’ plight - it's obviously a fair choice.&amp;nbsp; You see, with a topic such as this, I can go on and on - hell, who am I kidding, I can go on and on about the most mundane of things - but today is special. I type all this knowing I might not get to do this again for some time now. Each time that I have penned down my thoughts, I have thought about how maybe it's just me and my editor who get a good chuckle out of these. Each time I tell myself my editor probably does not chuckle at all. Each time I am glad for the opportunity, upset about my own expectations and ecstatic over having been able to transfer my head-junk on paper. Narcissistic or not, I’m glad to be here.&amp;nbsp; Disclaimer- I did score a 23 on the test, and if you did, too- please let’s form a Club! We can name it “Harshita’s”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Specter of Blood Cotton</title><link href="/The-Specter-of-Blood-Cotton" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Specter of Blood Cotton" /><published>2021-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Specter-of-Blood-Cotton</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Specter-of-Blood-Cotton">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&quot;Being an Uyghur is a Crime&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;Mihrigal Tursun&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;(detained at an Uyghur camp for the third time in 2015)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Mid-March witnessed an unprecedented boycott of a number of western brands including H&amp;amp;M and Nike all over China. This can be best described as cotton-sourcing juxtaposed against political gamesmanship. The incident traces its origins to the Xinjiang region of China, infamous for systematic allegations of exploiting forced Uyghur labour and dubbed as the tip of the iceberg concealing a larger problem of forced detention and China’s severe ill-treatment of its minorities. However, this recent upsurge has great economic and political ramifications in the supply chains of multinational fashion retailers such as Adidas, Lacoste, H&amp;amp;M, Ralph Lauren and Tommy Hilfiger.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In January 2016, the Trump administration had banned all cotton imports from Xinjiang as well as consumer items manufactured in the area. The administration reiterated the US stance of declaring the existence of genocide in the Xinjiang region. This was a significant shift as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.workersrights.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Workers Rights Consortium&lt;/a&gt; estimated that the material imported from Xinjiang was used in the manufacture of 1.5 billion garments that were manufactured by American brands and retailers. The question arises as to why the issue has gained the spotlight in March 2021 when it has long been a publicly contested subject in the international arena.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Many observers have attributed this to the widening of political differences between China and the Western Nations in the aftermath of the pandemic. The tensions further escalated on March 22 when Britain, Canada and the European Union imposed sanction on China for its abominable treatment towards the Uyghurs. Soon there was a circulation of September 2020 screenshots of an H&amp;amp;M statement that cited &quot;deep concerns&quot; regarding forced labour in Xinjiang along with the confirmation that the organisation had stopped buying cotton from Xinjiang cultivators. China denied all such claims and in retaliation, the products of the protesting brands were removed from China’s e-commerce platforms including&amp;nbsp; JD.COM&amp;nbsp; and Alibaba Group’s Tmall.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Not all brands chose to raise their voice. Hugo Boss, the German brand being a notable dissenter posting on its website: &quot;We will continue to purchase and support Xinjiang cotton.&quot; However, later they claimed it to be unauthorized and it was deleted.&amp;nbsp; The foreign brands have repeatedly faced challenges regarding selling off their products to the 1.4 billion strong Chinese customer base and simultaneously adhering to the global customer’s demand for adherence to certain ethical norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The exploitation of the Uyghur minority however demands a greater exposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Dehumanization of the Uyghur Community&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In its 2020 report, the &lt;em&gt;BBC&lt;/em&gt; had revealed that China is forcing hundreds and thousands of Uyghurs into manual labour in the cotton fields at Xinjiang, which produces a fifth of the world’s cotton. The Uyghurs are a Muslim minority that ethnically and culturally identify with Central Asian communities. They even speak in a language similar to that of Turkish. They have been detained in camps and allegedly subjected to torture, forced labour, sexual, psychological abuse, and forced sterilisation attempts. China has veiled such atrocities under the garb of such camps being ‘re-education’ sites aimed at salvaging the Uyghurs out of poverty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The mass migration of the Han Chinese (ethnic majority) to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR) has birthed a threat perception among the Uyghurs that their culture and livelihood are under threat by the ethnic majority. The crackdown upon this community can be traced to the Anti-Han and separatist movements that arose in the 1990's, spiralling into violence in 2009 when 200 people were killed in clashes at Xinjiang. The Chinese state laid the blame on the Uyghurs’ demand for a separate state. Since 2015, a million Uyghurs have been detained in camps in complete adherence to Xi Jinping’s goal of national ideology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The justifications have been based on the ground of threats of extremism directed at Chinese national integration and unity. The Chinese government maintains its actions are justified by citing the extremist and terrorist activities linked to the Uyghurs in the Baren Township riot, 1997 Urumqi bus bombings, 2014 Urumqi attack, 2011 Holtan attacks and the 2015 Aksu colliery attack, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The China Cables, a collection of secret government documents leaked by Uyghurs in exile, had earlier revealed that the detention camps were run as high-security prisons marked by the autocratic disciplining of Uyghurs. A report by the China scholar Adrian Zenz revealed that Uyghur women who had more children than the legally permitted number were forced to receive intrauterine devices and injected with syringes that stopped their menstrual cycle, resulting in a massive decline of the population growth, with growth rates falling by 84% in the two largest Uyghur districts between 2015 and 2018.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Gang rapes, sexual torture, forcible co-habitation of Uyghur homes by government workers are common under the ‘Pair up and Become a Family’ policy with the aim of promoting ‘ethnic unity’. The extensive use of surveillance technology includes intelligent monitoring systems, police checkpoints and drones, and the Ministry of Public Security has invested in the Skynet and Sharp Eyes Project for video camera facial recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When President Xi Jinping declared that all practising religions in China should be Chinese in orientation, the crackdowns rose to unprecedented scales, resulting in the complete eradication of Uyghur culture. Wearing headscarves, veils and other Islamic dress in the region is completely forbidden which led to a 2014 protest in Alakaga, Xinjiang, when 25 women were detained for wearing headscarves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The attack on Islamic religion is evidenced by the systematic destruction of mosques, Muslim shrines and cemeteries, with &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt; stating that over one-third of the mosques and religious sites in China suffered ‘significant structural damage’. There has been a complete breakdown of fundamental rights such as freedom of speech and expression, with the Uyghur economist Ilham Tohti being sentenced to life imprisonment in 2014, and the disappearance of Rahile Dawut, an Uyghur anthropologist. The cultural assimilation and integration of the Uyghurs is encouraged by promoting marriages between the Uyghurs and the Han Chinese through schemes such as the ‘Incentive Measures Encouraging Uighur-Chinese Intermarriage’ scheme which includes a cash reward of $1,450 per annum for the first five years of marriage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The International Reaction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;22 countries have sent a joint letter to the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) condemning the mass detention of Uyghurs. The European Union had in March 2021 sanctioned Zhu Hailun, the proponent of the indoctrination program. The United States Customs and Border Protection had issued five Withhold Release Orders (WRO) on products produced by state-sponsored forced labour such as hair products made in the industrial park at Xinjiang and cotton produced by the Yili Zhouwan Garment Manufacturing Company and Baoding LYSZD Trade and Business Company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It has to be noted that Pakistani Prime Minister Imran Khan, a vocal critic of Islamophobia has maintained silence on Uyghur persecution, stating that he didn’t &quot;know much about&quot; the scale of Uyghur mistreatment and stating that China had helped them when &quot;they were at the rock bottom&quot;. The 57 country Organization of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) has, however, mentioned &quot;disturbing reports&quot; of China’s crackdown on Muslims, but has backtracked on its publication.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The process of Sinicization is perhaps best amplified in the words: &quot;You people are not Turks. Uighurs are Chinese. You are one of us, Chinese&quot; as recalled by Mohammed, an Uyghur from Southern Xinjiang, who had been detained for seven months in June 2018, held in a camp with his hands chained together in a room with 35 others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The tale of Blood Cotton haunts the collective conscience of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">&quot;Being an Uyghur is a Crime&quot; Mihrigal Tursun&amp;nbsp; (detained at an Uyghur camp for the third time in 2015) Mid-March witnessed an unprecedented boycott of a number of western brands including H&amp;amp;M and Nike all over China. This can be best described as cotton-sourcing juxtaposed against political gamesmanship. The incident traces its origins to the Xinjiang region of China, infamous for systematic allegations of exploiting forced Uyghur labour and dubbed as the tip of the iceberg concealing a larger problem of forced detention and China’s severe ill-treatment of its minorities. However, this recent upsurge has great economic and political ramifications in the supply chains of multinational fashion retailers such as Adidas, Lacoste, H&amp;amp;M, Ralph Lauren and Tommy Hilfiger.&amp;nbsp; In January 2016, the Trump administration had banned all cotton imports from Xinjiang as well as consumer items manufactured in the area. The administration reiterated the US stance of declaring the existence of genocide in the Xinjiang region. This was a significant shift as the Workers Rights Consortium estimated that the material imported from Xinjiang was used in the manufacture of 1.5 billion garments that were manufactured by American brands and retailers. The question arises as to why the issue has gained the spotlight in March 2021 when it has long been a publicly contested subject in the international arena.&amp;nbsp; Many observers have attributed this to the widening of political differences between China and the Western Nations in the aftermath of the pandemic. The tensions further escalated on March 22 when Britain, Canada and the European Union imposed sanction on China for its abominable treatment towards the Uyghurs. Soon there was a circulation of September 2020 screenshots of an H&amp;amp;M statement that cited &quot;deep concerns&quot; regarding forced labour in Xinjiang along with the confirmation that the organisation had stopped buying cotton from Xinjiang cultivators. China denied all such claims and in retaliation, the products of the protesting brands were removed from China’s e-commerce platforms including&amp;nbsp; JD.COM&amp;nbsp; and Alibaba Group’s Tmall.&amp;nbsp; Not all brands chose to raise their voice. Hugo Boss, the German brand being a notable dissenter posting on its website: &quot;We will continue to purchase and support Xinjiang cotton.&quot; However, later they claimed it to be unauthorized and it was deleted.&amp;nbsp; The foreign brands have repeatedly faced challenges regarding selling off their products to the 1.4 billion strong Chinese customer base and simultaneously adhering to the global customer’s demand for adherence to certain ethical norms. The exploitation of the Uyghur minority however demands a greater exposition. The Dehumanization of the Uyghur Community In its 2020 report, the BBC had revealed that China is forcing hundreds and thousands of Uyghurs into manual labour in the cotton fields at Xinjiang, which produces a fifth of the world’s cotton. The Uyghurs are a Muslim minority that ethnically and culturally identify with Central Asian communities. They even speak in a language similar to that of Turkish. They have been detained in camps and allegedly subjected to torture, forced labour, sexual, psychological abuse, and forced sterilisation attempts. China has veiled such atrocities under the garb of such camps being ‘re-education’ sites aimed at salvaging the Uyghurs out of poverty.&amp;nbsp; The mass migration of the Han Chinese (ethnic majority) to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR) has birthed a threat perception among the Uyghurs that their culture and livelihood are under threat by the ethnic majority. The crackdown upon this community can be traced to the Anti-Han and separatist movements that arose in the 1990's, spiralling into violence in 2009 when 200 people were killed in clashes at Xinjiang. The Chinese state laid the blame on the Uyghurs’ demand for a separate state. Since 2015, a million Uyghurs have been detained in camps in complete adherence to Xi Jinping’s goal of national ideology.&amp;nbsp; The justifications have been based on the ground of threats of extremism directed at Chinese national integration and unity. The Chinese government maintains its actions are justified by citing the extremist and terrorist activities linked to the Uyghurs in the Baren Township riot, 1997 Urumqi bus bombings, 2014 Urumqi attack, 2011 Holtan attacks and the 2015 Aksu colliery attack, among others. The China Cables, a collection of secret government documents leaked by Uyghurs in exile, had earlier revealed that the detention camps were run as high-security prisons marked by the autocratic disciplining of Uyghurs. A report by the China scholar Adrian Zenz revealed that Uyghur women who had more children than the legally permitted number were forced to receive intrauterine devices and injected with syringes that stopped their menstrual cycle, resulting in a massive decline of the population growth, with growth rates falling by 84% in the two largest Uyghur districts between 2015 and 2018.&amp;nbsp; Gang rapes, sexual torture, forcible co-habitation of Uyghur homes by government workers are common under the ‘Pair up and Become a Family’ policy with the aim of promoting ‘ethnic unity’. The extensive use of surveillance technology includes intelligent monitoring systems, police checkpoints and drones, and the Ministry of Public Security has invested in the Skynet and Sharp Eyes Project for video camera facial recognition. When President Xi Jinping declared that all practising religions in China should be Chinese in orientation, the crackdowns rose to unprecedented scales, resulting in the complete eradication of Uyghur culture. Wearing headscarves, veils and other Islamic dress in the region is completely forbidden which led to a 2014 protest in Alakaga, Xinjiang, when 25 women were detained for wearing headscarves. The attack on Islamic religion is evidenced by the systematic destruction of mosques, Muslim shrines and cemeteries, with The Guardian stating that over one-third of the mosques and religious sites in China suffered ‘significant structural damage’. There has been a complete breakdown of fundamental rights such as freedom of speech and expression, with the Uyghur economist Ilham Tohti being sentenced to life imprisonment in 2014, and the disappearance of Rahile Dawut, an Uyghur anthropologist. The cultural assimilation and integration of the Uyghurs is encouraged by promoting marriages between the Uyghurs and the Han Chinese through schemes such as the ‘Incentive Measures Encouraging Uighur-Chinese Intermarriage’ scheme which includes a cash reward of $1,450 per annum for the first five years of marriage.&amp;nbsp; The International Reaction 22 countries have sent a joint letter to the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) condemning the mass detention of Uyghurs. The European Union had in March 2021 sanctioned Zhu Hailun, the proponent of the indoctrination program. The United States Customs and Border Protection had issued five Withhold Release Orders (WRO) on products produced by state-sponsored forced labour such as hair products made in the industrial park at Xinjiang and cotton produced by the Yili Zhouwan Garment Manufacturing Company and Baoding LYSZD Trade and Business Company. It has to be noted that Pakistani Prime Minister Imran Khan, a vocal critic of Islamophobia has maintained silence on Uyghur persecution, stating that he didn’t &quot;know much about&quot; the scale of Uyghur mistreatment and stating that China had helped them when &quot;they were at the rock bottom&quot;. The 57 country Organization of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) has, however, mentioned &quot;disturbing reports&quot; of China’s crackdown on Muslims, but has backtracked on its publication.&amp;nbsp; The process of Sinicization is perhaps best amplified in the words: &quot;You people are not Turks. Uighurs are Chinese. You are one of us, Chinese&quot; as recalled by Mohammed, an Uyghur from Southern Xinjiang, who had been detained for seven months in June 2018, held in a camp with his hands chained together in a room with 35 others. The tale of Blood Cotton haunts the collective conscience of the world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sinews of an Industrialised Economy</title><link href="/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sinews of an Industrialised Economy" /><published>2021-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The industrial sector, manufacturing, in particular, plays an important role in transforming a country from a low-income one, with agriculture dominating the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) composition, to a high-income, services-oriented country. The industrialisation of a country is a crucial phase in this transformation. Industrialisation is not only about a country becoming a manufacturing hub. There is a huge societal transformation that accompanies such industrialisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Though the process of industrialisation is disruptive, it results in an increase in the income of the people. People become more refined in their behaviour, and education becomes a top priority in industrial society. Thus giving top priority to human investment. The state gains a monopoly over violence, the institutions of the state become more competent, and many other changes are observed. But the initiation of the process of industrialisation begins with the sectoral composition of the GDP moving from agriculture to industry, along with a similar shift in employment patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The transition from agriculture to an industrial economy is an important transformation that places a country on a high growth path. There is a tranche of changes that occur in different domains that facilitate a country in kick-starting its progression into a developed country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, emerging as an industrial society increases the income of the people. There will be a guaranteed income flow for the average person in the society, unlike an agrarian economy where there is too much uncertainty in income generation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, with large scale migrations from rural to urban areas, whole new sectors emerge on the stage (e.g. daycare centres, dog walkers etc.) and the demand in the economy as a whole goes up.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Third, as people become more urban there is a deep social change that occurs, a change for good; this includes an increase in women's participation in the labour force, women becoming more independent and having a say in many things. Industrialisation can also be a factor that eases out the population pressure on society. Industrialisation also paves the way for education to become a major aspect in society. People hitherto employing their children on fields will send their kids to school because their income will suffice to support the family without the children having to work in the fields. But in all this, it is important to remember that industrialisation is a very disruptive activity. It, therefore, demands a strong state with strong enforcement mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The initial stages of industrialisation are, however, characterised by a population that has had only the experiences of a pre-industrial society. Literacy levels are generally low, most people are uneducated. This is where manufacturing comes into the picture. Manufacturing has the potential to absorb a large pool of labour. This is because of its fundamental characteristic of being dependent on labour for various reasons, despite the onset of technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An increase in manufacturing also leads to a division of labour which increases mamifold the productivity of all sectors. To encourage manufacturing, however, there are a set of factors that need to be set in place. To discuss the factors that have to be put in place we may take the example of India, a textbook example of a country in the midst of the transformation from an agrarian society to an industrial one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, India has reformed its archaic labour laws, which are a nightmare to anyone starting an industry. While regulation is desirable anytime, Indian labour laws are a case of over-regulation and need reform.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, India has to bring about land reforms. The Land Acquisition Bill, which was introduced in the Indian Parliament in 2014, was withdrawn due to a lack of political will. It is high time now that India passes that bill and makes land acquisitions easier.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, a consistent effort must be made to transition from an agricultural economy to an industrial economy. For this, a two-fold approach may be recommended. The Indian government should take all necessary steps to encourage industry, especially manufacturing; at the same time, it must improve the urban facilities of the country so as to accommodate the migration that occurs in the process of urbanisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the context of transforming India into an industrial economy, looking at China may offer some lessons. China began its reform process with agriculture by moving from the commune-based system to the household responsibility system, and by revising agricultural prices upwards by more than 20%, the results were for everyone to see. The agricultural growth rate jumped to 7.1% per annum during 1978-84, up from 2.5% during the pre-reform period of 1966-1977. This was followed by a dramatic reduction of poverty from 33% to 15% in the reform period between 1978 and 1984. Farm income in China grew by almost 14% per annum. It is high growth in farm incomes that boosted demand for manufacturing goods produced by town and village enterprises, kick-starting the manufacturing revolution in China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In this context, Indian farm reforms are a welcome first step; though, a lot more could be done. India also has the necessary requirements in place. For instance, the Make in India scheme encourages the setting up of industries in India. It is imperative to back it up with other necessary steps. Initiatives like Skill India can be used for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Today, the Indian industry is complaining that rural demand is collapsing. One reason for that is the consistent reduction in rural population in India since the 1991 economic reforms. Another reason for this outcome is that India never had any major reforms with respect to its labour laws, land laws and agriculture laws; and farmers’ incomes have remained very low. However, it is also important to note that industry is not a substitute for agriculture, rather they are complementary to one another. Both these sectors are so intertwined that it is not possible to increase the growth of one sector without the improvement of the other sector. Industrialisation is also important to increase farm incomes in the country. This is because industrialisation moves people from farms to industries, thus consolidating the land holdings and thereby increasing productivity in the agriculture sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the long term, it is also imperative that India plan to address the issues of education and employment. There is a two-way correlation between industrialisation and education. In education, India seriously lacks skills-based education as the primary focus is always scoring marks rather than problem-solving and skills enhancement. To address this issue the government can partner with the industry to tailor the curriculum to suit the needs of the industry. The focus should shift to develop problem-solving skills. The government can also ask companies to spend their CSR amount on skills development programs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The elasticity of employment generation has been constantly falling and has come down to near zero in the last decade. This shows the grave danger that is in store in regards to job creation. In India, more often than not, entrepreneurs focus on price controls to cut down costs rather than on efficiency. In many cases, producers compete on the basis of price rather than efficiency. This should also change and for that, the government should incentivise firms to focus on efficiency rather than prices. India should act fast to take advantage of the changing scenario on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The economic reforms of 1991 have transformed the lives of the Indian people in many ways. The reforms led to new aspirations among the people, as the expectation was that the Indian economy would grow and India was going to be the next big thing on the world stage. Since the 1991 economic reforms were not adequately followed up, India has witnessed jobless growth for most of the period of its golden economic period of 2003-2008. Despite this, the Indian economy remained among the fastest-growing large economies of the world. Yet, it might appear paradoxical that with respect to achievements in human development, India is ranked at 129 out of 189 countries, according to the human development report 2019.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing has been the engine of modern economic growth, be it in Britain and the USA of the 19th century or Russia of the 20th century or China of the 21st century. India’s first plans to industrialise go as far back in time as the 1950's. The second Five-Year Plan spoke at lengths about the need for industrialisation and outlined the steps for the same. Unfortunately, India failed to industrialise. The Nehruvian model that the Indian state adopted subsequently proved disastrous for the country. Today, the time frame for India to take off and reap benefits of its demographic dividend is too small. India should act fast. Else, the future might be bleaker than we imagine today.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The industrial sector, manufacturing, in particular, plays an important role in transforming a country from a low-income one, with agriculture dominating the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) composition, to a high-income, services-oriented country. The industrialisation of a country is a crucial phase in this transformation. Industrialisation is not only about a country becoming a manufacturing hub. There is a huge societal transformation that accompanies such industrialisation.&amp;nbsp; Though the process of industrialisation is disruptive, it results in an increase in the income of the people. People become more refined in their behaviour, and education becomes a top priority in industrial society. Thus giving top priority to human investment. The state gains a monopoly over violence, the institutions of the state become more competent, and many other changes are observed. But the initiation of the process of industrialisation begins with the sectoral composition of the GDP moving from agriculture to industry, along with a similar shift in employment patterns. The transition from agriculture to an industrial economy is an important transformation that places a country on a high growth path. There is a tranche of changes that occur in different domains that facilitate a country in kick-starting its progression into a developed country.&amp;nbsp; First, emerging as an industrial society increases the income of the people. There will be a guaranteed income flow for the average person in the society, unlike an agrarian economy where there is too much uncertainty in income generation.&amp;nbsp; Second, with large scale migrations from rural to urban areas, whole new sectors emerge on the stage (e.g. daycare centres, dog walkers etc.) and the demand in the economy as a whole goes up.&amp;nbsp; Third, as people become more urban there is a deep social change that occurs, a change for good; this includes an increase in women's participation in the labour force, women becoming more independent and having a say in many things. Industrialisation can also be a factor that eases out the population pressure on society. Industrialisation also paves the way for education to become a major aspect in society. People hitherto employing their children on fields will send their kids to school because their income will suffice to support the family without the children having to work in the fields. But in all this, it is important to remember that industrialisation is a very disruptive activity. It, therefore, demands a strong state with strong enforcement mechanisms. The initial stages of industrialisation are, however, characterised by a population that has had only the experiences of a pre-industrial society. Literacy levels are generally low, most people are uneducated. This is where manufacturing comes into the picture. Manufacturing has the potential to absorb a large pool of labour. This is because of its fundamental characteristic of being dependent on labour for various reasons, despite the onset of technology.&amp;nbsp; An increase in manufacturing also leads to a division of labour which increases mamifold the productivity of all sectors. To encourage manufacturing, however, there are a set of factors that need to be set in place. To discuss the factors that have to be put in place we may take the example of India, a textbook example of a country in the midst of the transformation from an agrarian society to an industrial one.&amp;nbsp; First, India has reformed its archaic labour laws, which are a nightmare to anyone starting an industry. While regulation is desirable anytime, Indian labour laws are a case of over-regulation and need reform.&amp;nbsp; Second, India has to bring about land reforms. The Land Acquisition Bill, which was introduced in the Indian Parliament in 2014, was withdrawn due to a lack of political will. It is high time now that India passes that bill and makes land acquisitions easier.&amp;nbsp; However, a consistent effort must be made to transition from an agricultural economy to an industrial economy. For this, a two-fold approach may be recommended. The Indian government should take all necessary steps to encourage industry, especially manufacturing; at the same time, it must improve the urban facilities of the country so as to accommodate the migration that occurs in the process of urbanisation. In the context of transforming India into an industrial economy, looking at China may offer some lessons. China began its reform process with agriculture by moving from the commune-based system to the household responsibility system, and by revising agricultural prices upwards by more than 20%, the results were for everyone to see. The agricultural growth rate jumped to 7.1% per annum during 1978-84, up from 2.5% during the pre-reform period of 1966-1977. This was followed by a dramatic reduction of poverty from 33% to 15% in the reform period between 1978 and 1984. Farm income in China grew by almost 14% per annum. It is high growth in farm incomes that boosted demand for manufacturing goods produced by town and village enterprises, kick-starting the manufacturing revolution in China.&amp;nbsp; In this context, Indian farm reforms are a welcome first step; though, a lot more could be done. India also has the necessary requirements in place. For instance, the Make in India scheme encourages the setting up of industries in India. It is imperative to back it up with other necessary steps. Initiatives like Skill India can be used for this purpose. Today, the Indian industry is complaining that rural demand is collapsing. One reason for that is the consistent reduction in rural population in India since the 1991 economic reforms. Another reason for this outcome is that India never had any major reforms with respect to its labour laws, land laws and agriculture laws; and farmers’ incomes have remained very low. However, it is also important to note that industry is not a substitute for agriculture, rather they are complementary to one another. Both these sectors are so intertwined that it is not possible to increase the growth of one sector without the improvement of the other sector. Industrialisation is also important to increase farm incomes in the country. This is because industrialisation moves people from farms to industries, thus consolidating the land holdings and thereby increasing productivity in the agriculture sector. In the long term, it is also imperative that India plan to address the issues of education and employment. There is a two-way correlation between industrialisation and education. In education, India seriously lacks skills-based education as the primary focus is always scoring marks rather than problem-solving and skills enhancement. To address this issue the government can partner with the industry to tailor the curriculum to suit the needs of the industry. The focus should shift to develop problem-solving skills. The government can also ask companies to spend their CSR amount on skills development programs.&amp;nbsp; The elasticity of employment generation has been constantly falling and has come down to near zero in the last decade. This shows the grave danger that is in store in regards to job creation. In India, more often than not, entrepreneurs focus on price controls to cut down costs rather than on efficiency. In many cases, producers compete on the basis of price rather than efficiency. This should also change and for that, the government should incentivise firms to focus on efficiency rather than prices. India should act fast to take advantage of the changing scenario on the world stage. The economic reforms of 1991 have transformed the lives of the Indian people in many ways. The reforms led to new aspirations among the people, as the expectation was that the Indian economy would grow and India was going to be the next big thing on the world stage. Since the 1991 economic reforms were not adequately followed up, India has witnessed jobless growth for most of the period of its golden economic period of 2003-2008. Despite this, the Indian economy remained among the fastest-growing large economies of the world. Yet, it might appear paradoxical that with respect to achievements in human development, India is ranked at 129 out of 189 countries, according to the human development report 2019.&amp;nbsp; Manufacturing has been the engine of modern economic growth, be it in Britain and the USA of the 19th century or Russia of the 20th century or China of the 21st century. India’s first plans to industrialise go as far back in time as the 1950's. The second Five-Year Plan spoke at lengths about the need for industrialisation and outlined the steps for the same. Unfortunately, India failed to industrialise. The Nehruvian model that the Indian state adopted subsequently proved disastrous for the country. Today, the time frame for India to take off and reap benefits of its demographic dividend is too small. India should act fast. Else, the future might be bleaker than we imagine today.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Spirit of Brahminism and the Capitalist Reckoning</title><link href="/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Spirit of Brahminism and the Capitalist Reckoning" /><published>2021-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning">&lt;p&gt;The Indian caste system was (or is) a most dehumanising, totalitarian and rigid system of social hierarchy and control. The oldest Hindu religious text, the Rig Veda, in its canto 10, hymn 90 defines how mankind came to be from the different parts of the supreme primordial being. It declares that &lt;em&gt;&quot;The Brahmin was His [i.e. the primordial being's] mouth; the Kshatriya His arms became. His thighs were the Vaisya; of His feet the Sudra was born.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These four castes: the Brahmins (the priestly and intellectual class), the Kshatriyas (the landowners and warriors), the Vaisya (the business class) and the Sudra (the labourer) represent the idealised division of social groups in the feudal social order of ancient India. The castes do not intermarry, they do not undertake work outside the profession assigned to their caste and the lowest castes and the outcastes are considered 'untouchable'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that capitalism, as the fundamental counterfoil to a feudal social order, has nothing to do with the caste system or anything like it. After all, capitalism is supposed to be a system in which the invisible hand of the market determines productive activity, rather than a system where a rigid hierarchy dictates social outcome. It is supposed to be based on open competition, where the best product wins, a rational social order, as Max Weber argued, instead of an irrational social order based on blood purity and ancient hymns on a primordial being.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But funny enough, the adaptability of the capitalist mode of production to varied challenges means that capitalism is evolving itself into a social hierarchy that looks very much like the caste system. More specifically, it is evolving to give us a group of people who are verily like the Brahmins of the Hindu social order, the mouths of the primordial being that is Capital.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group I speak of here is quite easily recognisable and thoroughly glamourised (and demonised) in world culture. Their activities are difficult to understand. They deal in items of pure abstraction, building nothing themselves but exercising control over all that is built. They are an exclusive club of people with an iron grip over power and money, whilst not being owners of any of those things themselves. They are the investment bankers, the equity analysts, the financiers and the asset managers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the Brahmin of yore who technically lived on alms but amassed vast wealth, the asset manager and the investment banker only shift wealth around but is rich &quot;via commission motherf*cker&quot; (to quote Matthew McConaughey's character from &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;). Like the Brahmin who would zealously guard his secret knowledge of the sacred mantras and rituals which could make a mere warlord into a king, so does the Wall Street professional speak in the complex technical jargon of 'bonds', 'short-selling', 'derivatives' and 'collateralised debt obligations' which turn a mere productive activity into a sophisticated web of transactions. Like the killing of a Brahmin was the highest crime under ancient Hindu law, so is not bailing out the big banks and financial firms an impossibility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These parallels are not some mere curiosity, they showcase how capitalism is so eminently adaptable to changing social conditions and how it verily controls the change in material conditions through its social architecture. In fact, this parallel upsets the fundamental assumptions that both pro-capitalist and many anti-capitalist thinkers make. It is not just the chains of economic power which define social relations, it is also the makeup of social relations that determines where economic power resides. The lords of high finance do not derive their power by owning and controlling the means of production. Instead, they define the interrelationships between economic power and those subject to its dominion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can really appreciate this with a comparative example of the exercise of Brahminical power and the exercise of the power of the financiers. In the ancient Hindu fire rituals called the&lt;em&gt; yagna&lt;/em&gt;, the Brahmin priest would declare the officiator of the ritual as the '&lt;em&gt;yajaman'&lt;/em&gt;, he would make oblations to the various gods in the name of the &lt;em&gt;yajaman&lt;/em&gt;. The fruits of the &lt;em&gt;yagna&lt;/em&gt; would technically be available to the &lt;em&gt;yajaman&lt;/em&gt; alone, for it is his financial resources that make the &lt;em&gt;yagna&lt;/em&gt; possible. The Brahmin is a mere functionary in the entire process. But it is the Brahmin who knows the liturgy, it is the Brahmin who understands the secrets of the various rituals which confer wealth and power. In other words, it is the Brahmin who creates the&lt;em&gt; yajaman&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;yagna.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar way, the financier of today creates the capital and the capitalist. It is he who decides if a company can go public, it is he who sells its shares with an asking price and aims to raise capital with it. While the Brahmin made oblations to the gods, as a mere agent of the capitalist, the financier makes his oblations to the market. Technically, the financier is a mere agent. But it is he who knows the viability of the assets of the company, it is he who knows how to appease the market in favour of the capitalist.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as already alluded to, there is a stark difference between the Brahmin and the financiers: while one functions in a mystical social order, the other works in a rationalist one. So the interesting question is: why does this similarity emerge at all? Why is capitalism starting to look like feudalism?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is at once simple and complicated. It resides in that confusing term - 'human nature’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is known that we hunger, not just for food or shelter but also for meaning and security. We are, on some level, aware of our mortality and of how the universe is an uncaring void. At a time when there was no guarantee that the next harvest would give yield when natural disaster and disease could so easily destroy so many lives, the &lt;em&gt;yagna &lt;/em&gt;or the fire rituals gave humanity a sense of security. They made humanity feel a sense of control over its destiny in a fundamentally uncertain time. That is why the Brahmin was given a place of pride and of supreme importance in such an order, for on him rested society's basic sense of peace and order.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present time, while our fears are not related to the next harvest, our fundamental existential dread remains the same. We do not know what exactly the market will demand next year, we do not know whether the invisible hand will drive prices up or down, whether wages will increase or decrease. Even if our order is rational, our fears of hunger and pain are not, we cannot live with the uncertainty of knowing that a mechanism of market forces will determine our bank balance, especially when the world is buffeted by the COVID-19 pandemic. The financier, by exercising influence and control over the market, gives us certainty. That is why he (or she) has so much power.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go even deeper, the emergence of late capitalism represents the ultimate reckoning of the Age of Reason with its own assumptions. And the financier in late capitalism, advisedly or inadvertently, represents the reckoner. He confronts humanity with the limitations of his own rationalist systems. Nowhere is this more obvious than in the 2008 crisis. That crisis was, in many ways, completely and utterly the consequence of human beings trying to be too smart for their own good. Bankers so cleverly thought that if debts on homes were combined and converted into their own kind of mega debt, with that mega debt being sold in a market as a good, then money would just flow forever.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mega debts or ‘mortgage-backed securities’ as they were called, were a pure abstraction. They had no existence outside a system of pure formal logic, where obligations to pay back a home loan, which has no palpable existence, could be treated as a commodity and combined and sold as another obligation to pay back a loan, which also had no palpable existence. The real thing, the palpable thing: the home and the homeowner who undertook to pay back the loan was an eminently forgettable assumption in the hyper-rational mind of the financier. Needless to say, the results of this near-mystical, Brahminical rationalism are for all to see and they represent how there is such great folly in assuming that man is a creature of reason.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the ultimate question is: where do we go now? Will this inherent contradiction within capitalism unravel the same? (As Marx suggested) I think not. If the strength of the Brahmanical social order is any guide, a social order, no matter how flawed, no matter how decidedly routed by reality can maintain its spell, for that very weakness called human nature which in its yearning for security would rather believe the immediate lie than imagine a greater truth. So, the only thing that late capitalism and its Brahmin, the financier, tells us that it is here to stay no matter how many crises come and go. Unless, of course, humanity plucks up the courage to say: &quot;creatures of the heart and the flesh unite, we have nothing to lose but our rational brains''.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The Indian caste system was (or is) a most dehumanising, totalitarian and rigid system of social hierarchy and control. The oldest Hindu religious text, the Rig Veda, in its canto 10, hymn 90 defines how mankind came to be from the different parts of the supreme primordial being. It declares that &quot;The Brahmin was His [i.e. the primordial being's] mouth; the Kshatriya His arms became. His thighs were the Vaisya; of His feet the Sudra was born.&quot;&amp;nbsp; These four castes: the Brahmins (the priestly and intellectual class), the Kshatriyas (the landowners and warriors), the Vaisya (the business class) and the Sudra (the labourer) represent the idealised division of social groups in the feudal social order of ancient India. The castes do not intermarry, they do not undertake work outside the profession assigned to their caste and the lowest castes and the outcastes are considered 'untouchable'.&amp;nbsp; One would think that capitalism, as the fundamental counterfoil to a feudal social order, has nothing to do with the caste system or anything like it. After all, capitalism is supposed to be a system in which the invisible hand of the market determines productive activity, rather than a system where a rigid hierarchy dictates social outcome. It is supposed to be based on open competition, where the best product wins, a rational social order, as Max Weber argued, instead of an irrational social order based on blood purity and ancient hymns on a primordial being.&amp;nbsp; But funny enough, the adaptability of the capitalist mode of production to varied challenges means that capitalism is evolving itself into a social hierarchy that looks very much like the caste system. More specifically, it is evolving to give us a group of people who are verily like the Brahmins of the Hindu social order, the mouths of the primordial being that is Capital.&amp;nbsp; The group I speak of here is quite easily recognisable and thoroughly glamourised (and demonised) in world culture. Their activities are difficult to understand. They deal in items of pure abstraction, building nothing themselves but exercising control over all that is built. They are an exclusive club of people with an iron grip over power and money, whilst not being owners of any of those things themselves. They are the investment bankers, the equity analysts, the financiers and the asset managers.&amp;nbsp; Like the Brahmin of yore who technically lived on alms but amassed vast wealth, the asset manager and the investment banker only shift wealth around but is rich &quot;via commission motherf*cker&quot; (to quote Matthew McConaughey's character from Wolf of Wall Street). Like the Brahmin who would zealously guard his secret knowledge of the sacred mantras and rituals which could make a mere warlord into a king, so does the Wall Street professional speak in the complex technical jargon of 'bonds', 'short-selling', 'derivatives' and 'collateralised debt obligations' which turn a mere productive activity into a sophisticated web of transactions. Like the killing of a Brahmin was the highest crime under ancient Hindu law, so is not bailing out the big banks and financial firms an impossibility.&amp;nbsp; These parallels are not some mere curiosity, they showcase how capitalism is so eminently adaptable to changing social conditions and how it verily controls the change in material conditions through its social architecture. In fact, this parallel upsets the fundamental assumptions that both pro-capitalist and many anti-capitalist thinkers make. It is not just the chains of economic power which define social relations, it is also the makeup of social relations that determines where economic power resides. The lords of high finance do not derive their power by owning and controlling the means of production. Instead, they define the interrelationships between economic power and those subject to its dominion.&amp;nbsp; We can really appreciate this with a comparative example of the exercise of Brahminical power and the exercise of the power of the financiers. In the ancient Hindu fire rituals called the yagna, the Brahmin priest would declare the officiator of the ritual as the 'yajaman', he would make oblations to the various gods in the name of the yajaman. The fruits of the yagna would technically be available to the yajaman alone, for it is his financial resources that make the yagna possible. The Brahmin is a mere functionary in the entire process. But it is the Brahmin who knows the liturgy, it is the Brahmin who understands the secrets of the various rituals which confer wealth and power. In other words, it is the Brahmin who creates the yajaman and the yagna.&amp;nbsp; In a similar way, the financier of today creates the capital and the capitalist. It is he who decides if a company can go public, it is he who sells its shares with an asking price and aims to raise capital with it. While the Brahmin made oblations to the gods, as a mere agent of the capitalist, the financier makes his oblations to the market. Technically, the financier is a mere agent. But it is he who knows the viability of the assets of the company, it is he who knows how to appease the market in favour of the capitalist.&amp;nbsp; However, as already alluded to, there is a stark difference between the Brahmin and the financiers: while one functions in a mystical social order, the other works in a rationalist one. So the interesting question is: why does this similarity emerge at all? Why is capitalism starting to look like feudalism? The answer is at once simple and complicated. It resides in that confusing term - 'human nature’.&amp;nbsp; It is known that we hunger, not just for food or shelter but also for meaning and security. We are, on some level, aware of our mortality and of how the universe is an uncaring void. At a time when there was no guarantee that the next harvest would give yield when natural disaster and disease could so easily destroy so many lives, the yagna or the fire rituals gave humanity a sense of security. They made humanity feel a sense of control over its destiny in a fundamentally uncertain time. That is why the Brahmin was given a place of pride and of supreme importance in such an order, for on him rested society's basic sense of peace and order.&amp;nbsp; In the present time, while our fears are not related to the next harvest, our fundamental existential dread remains the same. We do not know what exactly the market will demand next year, we do not know whether the invisible hand will drive prices up or down, whether wages will increase or decrease. Even if our order is rational, our fears of hunger and pain are not, we cannot live with the uncertainty of knowing that a mechanism of market forces will determine our bank balance, especially when the world is buffeted by the COVID-19 pandemic. The financier, by exercising influence and control over the market, gives us certainty. That is why he (or she) has so much power.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; To go even deeper, the emergence of late capitalism represents the ultimate reckoning of the Age of Reason with its own assumptions. And the financier in late capitalism, advisedly or inadvertently, represents the reckoner. He confronts humanity with the limitations of his own rationalist systems. Nowhere is this more obvious than in the 2008 crisis. That crisis was, in many ways, completely and utterly the consequence of human beings trying to be too smart for their own good. Bankers so cleverly thought that if debts on homes were combined and converted into their own kind of mega debt, with that mega debt being sold in a market as a good, then money would just flow forever.&amp;nbsp; The mega debts or ‘mortgage-backed securities’ as they were called, were a pure abstraction. They had no existence outside a system of pure formal logic, where obligations to pay back a home loan, which has no palpable existence, could be treated as a commodity and combined and sold as another obligation to pay back a loan, which also had no palpable existence. The real thing, the palpable thing: the home and the homeowner who undertook to pay back the loan was an eminently forgettable assumption in the hyper-rational mind of the financier. Needless to say, the results of this near-mystical, Brahminical rationalism are for all to see and they represent how there is such great folly in assuming that man is a creature of reason.&amp;nbsp; So, the ultimate question is: where do we go now? Will this inherent contradiction within capitalism unravel the same? (As Marx suggested) I think not. If the strength of the Brahmanical social order is any guide, a social order, no matter how flawed, no matter how decidedly routed by reality can maintain its spell, for that very weakness called human nature which in its yearning for security would rather believe the immediate lie than imagine a greater truth. So, the only thing that late capitalism and its Brahmin, the financier, tells us that it is here to stay no matter how many crises come and go. Unless, of course, humanity plucks up the courage to say: &quot;creatures of the heart and the flesh unite, we have nothing to lose but our rational brains''.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rise of the New Age Nazis</title><link href="/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the New Age Nazis" /><published>2021-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis">&lt;p&gt;On December 14, 2020, the UK Labour party leader Keir Starmer appeared on the radio show LBC with host Nick Ferrari when a caller, introducing herself as ‘Gemma from Cambridge,’ took the opportunity to propagate the Neo-Nazi ‘Great Replacement’ conspiracy theory on a national media platform. She stated: “in the wake of organisations such as BLM and other racial advocacy groups pushing what’s best for their people, I just want to ask, should white people also start playing identity politics now, before they become a minority themselves by 2066?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bizarre event was made even more bewildering when a Twitter user &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/redflareinfo/status/1338453892661714945&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt; that ‘Gemma from Cambridge’ was in fact Jody Swingler, a yoga teacher and musician living in Ibiza, a far cry from the archetypal image of the hapless neo-nazi social outcast in their parents’ basement, pulling the wings off flies and ranting on obscure online messageboards about how The Jews had prevented them from securing a girlfriend. Swingler had also &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/redflareinfo/status/1338453897258668033&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt; two YouTube shows with Mark Collett and Laura Melia, leaders of the white nationalist political party Patriotic Alternative, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hopenothate.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/HnH_Patriotic-Alternative-report_2020-08-v3.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;opposes&lt;/a&gt; the “replacement and displacement” of white Britons by people who “have no right to these lands.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem striking that people who advocate new age, spiritual beliefs, previously associated with ‘flower power’ and the countercultural movement of the 1960's, could wind up on the same side as the far right. But in fact, the link between new age spirituality and extremist politics is not new. The Nazis drew support from the occultist Thule Society, and prominent Nazi figures such as Heinrich Himmler and Rudolf Hess endorsed homeopathy and alternative medicine, with Himmler supporting using plant extracts to cure cancer. In 1934, Hess set up an alternative medicine centre in Dresden. Their embrace of holism and spirituality, broadly, was underpinned by a rejection of the precepts of the Enlightenment, which posited that the world could be understood through logical processes, subordinating religious and monarchical obscurantism to the supremacy of the faculty of reason. Many Nazi figures saw a romanticised, agrarian age as a solution to the modern menaces of industrialisation and materialism. For example, Ernst Lehmann, a Nazi professor of botany, stated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We recognize that separating humanity from nature, from the whole of life, leads to humankind’s own destruction and to the death of nations. Only through a reintegration of humanity into the whole of nature can our people be made stronger… This striving toward connectedness with the totality of life, with nature itself, a nature into which we are born, this is the deepest meaning and the true essence of National Socialist thought.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A desire to undo the crude, materialist logic that undergirded liberal democracy, and to restructure the relationship between the citizen and the State, therefore, spawned the Nazis’ fascination with holism and the reintegration of man with nature. 'Blood and soil' meant an organic connection with one’s homeland that could not be expressed through the civic or legal frameworks engendered by the minority protection clauses of the League of Nations, but only through the maintenance of racial purity. Mark Mazower wrote in his book &lt;em&gt;Dark Continent &lt;/em&gt;that:“The League (of Nations) , after all, was an organisation of States. But what was the State? According to Hitler’s biological view of politics, it was no less than a ‘living organism,’” adding: “Hitler’s own vision of geopolitics unlike that of many geopoliticians — rested upon race: the State itself was merely an expression of the racial ‘Volk.’” Railing against the ‘juridification of politics,’ many Nazi legal theorists saw the nation as a biological organism, corruptible by outside influences and requiring protection from alleged Jewish subversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Marquette University history professor Peter Staudenmeier &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/154971/rise-ecofascism-history-white-nationalism-environmental-preservation-immigration&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;describes&lt;/a&gt; as the “link between a yearning for purity in the environmental sphere and a desire for racialized purity in the social sphere” also undergirds the ecofascist tendencies common to many modern neo-nazis such as Anders Brevik and the El Paso shooter, who characterised non-white populations as invaders seeking to despoil the environment through having more children and consuming more resources. This was also reflected in the writings of ecologist Garrett Hardin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/individual/garrett-hardin&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;listed&lt;/a&gt; by the SPLC (Southern Poverty Law Centre) as a white nationalist, who wrote about the supposed threats that overpopulation posed to the Earth’s future. The myth of overpopulation has, however, been roundly debunked; a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2020/sep/21/worlds-richest-1-cause-double-co2-emissions-of-poorest-50-says-oxfam#:~:text=1%20month%20old-,World's%20richest%201%25%20cause%20double%20CO2,of%20poorest%2050%25%2C%20says%20Oxfam&amp;amp;text=The%20wealthiest%201%25%20of%20the,2015%2C%20according%20to%20new%20research.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; from Oxfam showed that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, the contention that COVID-19 is a hoax has been a point of convergence between new age hippies and the far-right. Back in October, thousands of anti-vaxxers marched through Trafalgar Square in London at the COVID-sceptic ‘Unite for Freedom’ event, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nicktolhurst/status/1299729414767497219?lang=en&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;during which&lt;/a&gt; a BUF (British Union of Fascists) flag was spotted. The event was hosted by notorious conspiracy theorist David Icke, whose theories have been endorsed by both neo-nazis groups such as Combat 18, and the new age spiritual movement. It was also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-election-2020/jake-angeli-qanon-shaman-stormed-capitol-b1784091.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt; that Jake Angeli, a Trump supporter nicknamed the ‘QAnon shaman’ who stormed the Capitol, had stated that COVID-19 was a hoax. According to his mother, he had also refused to eat non-organic food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two groups are united in their rejection of the perceived infringement on their liberties; in the case of the far-right, the supposed stifling of their ability to criticise the unaccountable technocracy that is allegedly imposing open borders and multiculturalism, and in the case of the new age conspiracists, the personal, bodily autonomy connoted by 'natural' methods of healing, which are at odds with modern, scientific forms of inoculation such as vaccines. The excoriation of Bill Gates as a central figure in a supposed global plot to undermine civil liberties by using vaccines as a method of social control, including implanting microchips into unfortunate victims, has also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymotion.com/video/x64vj4&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;propagated&lt;/a&gt; by conspiracy theorist Alex Jones, who has suggested that vaccines are part of a government-induced eugenics programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A theory known as the ‘Great Reset’ has also taken root in many far right circles, pushed by websites such as &lt;em&gt;Breitbart&lt;/em&gt;, which asserts that COVID-19 represents an attempt by a cabal of wealthy politicians, financiers and bureaucrats to establish a global government, eroding national sovereignty and dictating fiscal and monetary policy. During a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ugRnjpXEwTo&amp;amp;t=114s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;conversation&lt;/a&gt; with former Alex Jones acolyte Paul Joseph Watson, &lt;em&gt;Breitbart&lt;/em&gt; columnist James Delingpole described the Great Reset as “another variation on the theme of the New World Order,” stating: “it’s a technocratic elite — an unelected technocratic elite — deciding how you and I should live our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scepticism towards authority and heightened awareness of the erosion of civil liberties by governments using crises as a pretext to usher in technocratic dominance is not without merit. In an era characterised by the technocratic monopolisation of communications by companies whose business models are predicated on mining consumer data, in which a global pandemic has drastically increased the purview of the State’s influence over the lives of ordinary citizens, and in which finance, industry and production have all been centralised in the hands of a few multinational corporations, it is not unreasonable to be wary of authoritarian overreach.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the vague criticisms of systems of power enunciated by new age hippies, and the wild, conspiratorial denunciations of the ‘New World Order’ or the ‘Great Reset,’ common to extreme right wing political figures lack an empirical, material analysis. While it is certainly true that in Britain, at least, the pandemic has seen a worrying development in outsourcing the ‘Test and Trace’ system to companies such as G4S and Serco, which have been involved in nefarious operations from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-51573510&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;setting up&lt;/a&gt; immigration detention centres to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justice.gov.uk/about/hmps/contracted-out&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;developing&lt;/a&gt; some of Britain’s first for-profit prisons, the potential for government overreach is no grounds for denying the existence, or the severity, of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As outlined above, both aforementioned groups reject a materialist, empirically rigorous analysis of the global economy and the role of the State in abrogating civil liberties, idealising a preindustrial, agrarian past and asserting that the world’s problems are caused by a shadowy cabal (the root of most antisemitic conspiracy theories). This pandemic has shown that these groups, though widely considered to have diametrically opposed political interests, are more similar than they appear, and have been willing to set aside their ideological differences for the pursuit of wider goals. Unless their scepticism of the technocratic impulses of governments seeking to curtail civil liberties, much of which is justified, can be countered with a thorough and precise refutation of conspiratorial political narratives, the implications of this unholy alliance could be significant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">On December 14, 2020, the UK Labour party leader Keir Starmer appeared on the radio show LBC with host Nick Ferrari when a caller, introducing herself as ‘Gemma from Cambridge,’ took the opportunity to propagate the Neo-Nazi ‘Great Replacement’ conspiracy theory on a national media platform. She stated: “in the wake of organisations such as BLM and other racial advocacy groups pushing what’s best for their people, I just want to ask, should white people also start playing identity politics now, before they become a minority themselves by 2066?” This bizarre event was made even more bewildering when a Twitter user revealed that ‘Gemma from Cambridge’ was in fact Jody Swingler, a yoga teacher and musician living in Ibiza, a far cry from the archetypal image of the hapless neo-nazi social outcast in their parents’ basement, pulling the wings off flies and ranting on obscure online messageboards about how The Jews had prevented them from securing a girlfriend. Swingler had also recorded two YouTube shows with Mark Collett and Laura Melia, leaders of the white nationalist political party Patriotic Alternative, which opposes the “replacement and displacement” of white Britons by people who “have no right to these lands.” It may seem striking that people who advocate new age, spiritual beliefs, previously associated with ‘flower power’ and the countercultural movement of the 1960's, could wind up on the same side as the far right. But in fact, the link between new age spirituality and extremist politics is not new. The Nazis drew support from the occultist Thule Society, and prominent Nazi figures such as Heinrich Himmler and Rudolf Hess endorsed homeopathy and alternative medicine, with Himmler supporting using plant extracts to cure cancer. In 1934, Hess set up an alternative medicine centre in Dresden. Their embrace of holism and spirituality, broadly, was underpinned by a rejection of the precepts of the Enlightenment, which posited that the world could be understood through logical processes, subordinating religious and monarchical obscurantism to the supremacy of the faculty of reason. Many Nazi figures saw a romanticised, agrarian age as a solution to the modern menaces of industrialisation and materialism. For example, Ernst Lehmann, a Nazi professor of botany, stated: “We recognize that separating humanity from nature, from the whole of life, leads to humankind’s own destruction and to the death of nations. Only through a reintegration of humanity into the whole of nature can our people be made stronger… This striving toward connectedness with the totality of life, with nature itself, a nature into which we are born, this is the deepest meaning and the true essence of National Socialist thought.” A desire to undo the crude, materialist logic that undergirded liberal democracy, and to restructure the relationship between the citizen and the State, therefore, spawned the Nazis’ fascination with holism and the reintegration of man with nature. 'Blood and soil' meant an organic connection with one’s homeland that could not be expressed through the civic or legal frameworks engendered by the minority protection clauses of the League of Nations, but only through the maintenance of racial purity. Mark Mazower wrote in his book Dark Continent that:“The League (of Nations) , after all, was an organisation of States. But what was the State? According to Hitler’s biological view of politics, it was no less than a ‘living organism,’” adding: “Hitler’s own vision of geopolitics unlike that of many geopoliticians — rested upon race: the State itself was merely an expression of the racial ‘Volk.’” Railing against the ‘juridification of politics,’ many Nazi legal theorists saw the nation as a biological organism, corruptible by outside influences and requiring protection from alleged Jewish subversion. What Marquette University history professor Peter Staudenmeier describes as the “link between a yearning for purity in the environmental sphere and a desire for racialized purity in the social sphere” also undergirds the ecofascist tendencies common to many modern neo-nazis such as Anders Brevik and the El Paso shooter, who characterised non-white populations as invaders seeking to despoil the environment through having more children and consuming more resources. This was also reflected in the writings of ecologist Garrett Hardin, listed by the SPLC (Southern Poverty Law Centre) as a white nationalist, who wrote about the supposed threats that overpopulation posed to the Earth’s future. The myth of overpopulation has, however, been roundly debunked; a study from Oxfam showed that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%. More recently, the contention that COVID-19 is a hoax has been a point of convergence between new age hippies and the far-right. Back in October, thousands of anti-vaxxers marched through Trafalgar Square in London at the COVID-sceptic ‘Unite for Freedom’ event, during which a BUF (British Union of Fascists) flag was spotted. The event was hosted by notorious conspiracy theorist David Icke, whose theories have been endorsed by both neo-nazis groups such as Combat 18, and the new age spiritual movement. It was also revealed that Jake Angeli, a Trump supporter nicknamed the ‘QAnon shaman’ who stormed the Capitol, had stated that COVID-19 was a hoax. According to his mother, he had also refused to eat non-organic food. The two groups are united in their rejection of the perceived infringement on their liberties; in the case of the far-right, the supposed stifling of their ability to criticise the unaccountable technocracy that is allegedly imposing open borders and multiculturalism, and in the case of the new age conspiracists, the personal, bodily autonomy connoted by 'natural' methods of healing, which are at odds with modern, scientific forms of inoculation such as vaccines. The excoriation of Bill Gates as a central figure in a supposed global plot to undermine civil liberties by using vaccines as a method of social control, including implanting microchips into unfortunate victims, has also been propagated by conspiracy theorist Alex Jones, who has suggested that vaccines are part of a government-induced eugenics programme. A theory known as the ‘Great Reset’ has also taken root in many far right circles, pushed by websites such as Breitbart, which asserts that COVID-19 represents an attempt by a cabal of wealthy politicians, financiers and bureaucrats to establish a global government, eroding national sovereignty and dictating fiscal and monetary policy. During a conversation with former Alex Jones acolyte Paul Joseph Watson, Breitbart columnist James Delingpole described the Great Reset as “another variation on the theme of the New World Order,” stating: “it’s a technocratic elite — an unelected technocratic elite — deciding how you and I should live our lives.” Scepticism towards authority and heightened awareness of the erosion of civil liberties by governments using crises as a pretext to usher in technocratic dominance is not without merit. In an era characterised by the technocratic monopolisation of communications by companies whose business models are predicated on mining consumer data, in which a global pandemic has drastically increased the purview of the State’s influence over the lives of ordinary citizens, and in which finance, industry and production have all been centralised in the hands of a few multinational corporations, it is not unreasonable to be wary of authoritarian overreach.&amp;nbsp; However, the vague criticisms of systems of power enunciated by new age hippies, and the wild, conspiratorial denunciations of the ‘New World Order’ or the ‘Great Reset,’ common to extreme right wing political figures lack an empirical, material analysis. While it is certainly true that in Britain, at least, the pandemic has seen a worrying development in outsourcing the ‘Test and Trace’ system to companies such as G4S and Serco, which have been involved in nefarious operations from setting up immigration detention centres to developing some of Britain’s first for-profit prisons, the potential for government overreach is no grounds for denying the existence, or the severity, of COVID-19. As outlined above, both aforementioned groups reject a materialist, empirically rigorous analysis of the global economy and the role of the State in abrogating civil liberties, idealising a preindustrial, agrarian past and asserting that the world’s problems are caused by a shadowy cabal (the root of most antisemitic conspiracy theories). This pandemic has shown that these groups, though widely considered to have diametrically opposed political interests, are more similar than they appear, and have been willing to set aside their ideological differences for the pursuit of wider goals. Unless their scepticism of the technocratic impulses of governments seeking to curtail civil liberties, much of which is justified, can be countered with a thorough and precise refutation of conspiratorial political narratives, the implications of this unholy alliance could be significant.</summary></entry></feed>