<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-29T09:17:26+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">‘What Do You Believe?’ How Ideology Will Shape the Culture Wars of the 21st Century</title><link href="/What-Do-You-Believe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘What Do You Believe?’ How Ideology Will Shape the Culture Wars of the 21st Century" /><published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/What-Do-You-Believe</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-Do-You-Believe">&lt;p&gt;In a way, all of human history is an endless cycle of war and peace. As the old proverb goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hard times create strong men.&lt;br /&gt;
Strong men create good times.&lt;br /&gt;
Good times create weak men.&lt;br /&gt;
Weak men create hard times.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all at war – in some way or the other, with something or the other. We are all fighting, even for our daily bread. Whether it be bargaining with the local shopkeeper or actually taking up arms against an invader, conflict of some sort or the other pervades our very social existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In centuries past, certain nations decided that the best way to promote their own interest would be to colonise faraway lands located across the seas. This was the age of Conquest, the age of Empires. The result was that entire nations and civilisations came under the commercial and political dominance of unreachable overlords, living in another world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people of these subjugated races and tribes suddenly found themselves living as if on rent on the very land which their ancestors had tilled, ploughed and reaped for their own benefit. Hardship led to resentment. Resentment led to anger. Anger led to rage. Rage led to rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tired of being mocked, of being made to feel ashamed for the colour of their skin or the rhythm of their tongue or the lyric of their songs, they rose in revolt against the imperialist yoke. Those who were wise, left. But those who underestimated the fury of an oppressed race came to rue it to their very last breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nation fought nation; tribe fought tribe. People of one language ostracised those who spoke a different tongue. Those of a particular hue of skin detested those who looked different. These were the ways of a time when one’s loyalty and one’s pride was still rooted to the soil upon which one lived and toiled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that age is no more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War remains, perhaps ever more keenly than before. But it is a different kind of war. Out of the crucible of human conflict, a new world is being forged. There are several things which have led to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the shocking discovery that this Earth could indeed be tamed by the force of human ingenuity. We were told that only the sky is the limit – but even this has proven to be false. The Earth has shown itself to be a very small place indeed, and a new frontier has emerged – the great dark horizon of space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this contraction has only brought people closer together – geographically speaking. We are no longer bound to the soil on which our ancestors lived, moved and had their being. The coming together of continents, facilitated by the meteoric rise of modern transport, has led to the birth of multicultural and multi-ethnic societies around the world, where people of different beliefs and various walks of life have been forced to live their lives side-by-side. Seldom do we think of this, but the fact remains that what we see today – people of myriad ethnicities working together in the same office – would have been unthinkable even a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has led to the trivialisation of what originally divided mankind. The white man has come to see in the black man not an inferior creature, but a fellow human being. And the black man has come to see in his white neighbour not a fiendish oppressor from the pits of the underworld, but rather a mere man – with faults and flaws, just like everyone else. The close contact of daily interaction has ensured this. And this has led to a radical change in thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow’s battles will not be fought on the basis of race, language or ethnicity. Tomorrow’s wars will be wars of ideology, wars of belief, wars of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideology, you see, is not like skin colour or tribal identity. It cannot be as easily brushed aside. Abortion is either right or wrong. It cannot be both right and wrong. Pornography is either moral or immoral. Giving condoms to high school students is either a magnificent step forward in promoting safe sex and sexual freedom, or it is a sign of growing decadence and degeneracy in a society which shamelessly normalises the divorce of sex from marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when an unstoppable force meets an immovable mass? What happens when one belief system clashes with another? Two world views which are diametrically opposed to each other cannot coexist peacefully. One must prevail; the other must fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political scientist Samuel P. Huntington famously argued that what the post-Cold War era was about to see was not conflict between countries, but rather between cultures. He called it &lt;em&gt;The Clash of Civilizations&lt;/em&gt;, and hypothesised that ideology – and especially religion – would play a crucially important role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you lived, say, three thousand years ago, you would probably have been born in a monolithic homogeneous society, where there would have been one main philosophy of life, which would have answered all the big questions for you. And in all likelihood, you could have lived your entire life without questioning it – quite natural, given that everyone you knew believed the same things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that is no longer true. The confluence of cultures has resulted in people being exposed to a myriad of different philosophies and beliefs, each quite distinct from their own. Man can no longer be satisfied with accepting answers by faith alone. He has to think and rethink the big questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is his place in the world? Where does he come from? What does it all mean? And what ought one to do while one lives in this changing, transient world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are big questions, and this sudden clash of civilisations has forced the different camps to stop and regroup. And since interaction between different communities is all but inevitable, the conflict of ideas has begun anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result can easily be seen. Muslims are studying the New Testament and trying to understand what implications it might have on their own beliefs. Christians are studying Arabic and seeking to understand what the Quran actually says. Atheists are studying theology in universities and devout religious believers are devouring the works of Nietzsche and Russell with vigour. And this very happy situation is causing conversions on all sides, of the most lucrative and imaginative kinds. The clash certainly continues and democracy has played a crucial role in ensuring this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The struggle for power is natural to all human societies. In the Middle Ages, it was restricted mostly to the ruling class – aristocrats, nobles, princes, royal families and the like. But the advent of democracy has ensured that the vast citizenry have a vital and crucial say in who ultimately becomes King. And this means that people are much more informed and critical than ever before. Everyone has a vested interest. And everyone is trying to realize their own vision of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;belief&lt;/em&gt; plays a crucial role in all this. What do people &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; would be the best for their country, and for the world? Should abortion be legalised or criminalised? Is patriarchy real or is it a myth? Should borders be opened or closed? Is climate change real or is it a hoax? Should churches be taxed or should they be exempted? Should we seek to establish a one world government or do we support the idea of independent, autonomous nation states?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideology shapes the world we live in. And this naturally means that every election – which inevitably guarantees a victory for one side and a defeat for all others – is a microcosm of the great culture war playing out around the world. Whichever side wins, the other naturally feels aggrieved, oppressed and persecuted, and blames the ‘decadent’ victor for ruining the world. This is the sad, but unavoidable result, of a small world in which beliefs and philosophies of life are this varied and polarised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fruits of this are often surprising and, at times, humorous. Today, conservative white Christian folk would rather have fellow Christians of different ethnicities, races and cultures as their neighbours and citizens rather than those of their own race who don’t hold similar values. It’s the same with the Muslim community. Generally speaking, racial differences are becoming less and less relevant, and ideological differences are becoming more pronounced and prominent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, ironically, means that religion and philosophy will come to enjoy an influence they perhaps have not had in the immediate past. The new world war will not be over race or national identity, but over one’s vision for life. The main question our young people will be asked is not “Where do you come from?” but rather “What do you believe?”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">In a way, all of human history is an endless cycle of war and peace. As the old proverb goes:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt</title><link href="/Nefertiti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt" /><published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Nefertiti</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Nefertiti">&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so &lt;em&gt;special&lt;/em&gt; about her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camille Paglia would tell you- “Nefertiti is like Athena. Born from the brow of Zeus, a head-heavy armored goddess. She is beautiful but desexed.” Well, at least, that is how she sees it. My answer to the same, however, is multifold. For one, she was a powerful symbol of love in ancient Egypt. Never before were ancient Egyptian Kings and Queens portrayed in the writings, statues and inscriptions of the time as a couple madly in love. This was probably because most of the royal couples were siblings. But, this was not the case for Nefertiti and her husband, Akhenaten. They were not siblings. Absolutely nothing is known about Nefertiti’s parents. Many have speculated that she might have been the daughter of Ay, in line to the throne after Tutankhamun. Some have even linked her to a Mitanni princess, Tadukhipa. However, nothing exists to confirm either of the theories. In my opinion, given the amount of information we currently have, it is possible that she was a commoner. Remains from 14th century Egypt, however, show the couple publicly holding hands, embracing or riding chariots and kissing. In fact, Akhenaten even wrote a poem for his beloved Nefertiti. This adequately proves that they were indeed in love with each other and were certainly not, at least directly, related. This is rather surprising because incest was the norm among members of the royal family. Deviation from the norm did not, however, affect her position and Nefertiti soon became the principal wife and chief consort of Pharaoh Akhenaten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other beloved queen of the ancient world, Nefertiti was a symbol of great beauty. Her name literally translates to ‘the beautiful one has come’. Ideals of beauty were largely defined by what the rulers looked like at the time. Artefacts from this period of history, however, are vastly different from the reigns of other Pharaohs. This is because Akhenaten, his daughter Meritaten, and other members of the royal court are depicted with drastically elongated skulls, extremely narrow rib cages, chicken legs and protruding bellies. It goes without saying that that is very different from contemporary standards of beauty, they’d probably “ugly” and not regal today. Of course, it is possible that they took pride in what they looked like and did not want to be depicted any differently. As for the seemingly disfigured body parts, it wasn’t very uncommon because incest was a common practice. Lack of genetic diversity led to genetic deformations. The issue arises when we start inspecting Nefertiti, for she too was depicted with a long, bald head and a swan-like neck, and she was, almost certainly, not a product of incest. Many have questioned if her portrayal was so because Akhenaten and perhaps, Nefertiti herself wanted to be portrayed in this manner. Some pseudo-scientific theorists have also speculated the possibility of her being an extraterrestrial being. This would indeed explain her unusual looks. It is, however, in my opinion, likely that she was in fact a product of incest or that her elongated head was only a decorated head gear meant to give her a specific look. As for now, there is no direct evidence to support or reject any claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to how most historical characters of this period in Egyptian history are depicted, Nefertiti is showcased as much more ‘beautiful’. In fact she even meets modern standards of beauty. We know this because of one of the most famous finds of all time: the bust of Nefertiti. Currently housed in a museum in Berlin, the bust was found by German archaeologist, Ludwig Borchardt, on the 6th of December, 1912, in an artist’s studio in the then mostly unexcavated South-West Amarna. The British carried out expeditions in 1891 and 1892 in Tell-el Amarna, and concluded their endeavour with the statement that all that was left to be discovered had been retrieved by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bust is extremely beautiful and exceptionally well preserved, in stark contrast to the other busts found nearby that date back to the same time period. In fact, a bust of Akhenaten, found almost alongside that of Nefertiti’s, was found to be completely disfigured by nature. This raised some questions about the authenticity of the find. &lt;em&gt;Is the famous bust of Nefertiti even real?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What bothers me the most is how Nefertiti looks like a modern beauty- olive skin, impeccable eyebrows, long neck and high cheekbones. A missing eye has also led to speculation that she might have suffered from an ophthalmic infection. It is weird to even think of the sculpture as a 3,000 year old object because, as many Egyptologists say, ‘it is simply too beautiful’, both in terms of conservation and good looks. Careful investigation reveals something even more strange, the style is inconsistent with the time period. The shoulders, in the case of Nefertiti’s bust, are cut vertically as opposed to the usual horizontal cut along the shoulder line. However, another piece of work found during Borchardt’s excavation has the same kind of cut. Thus, there exists, at least one other bust from the same time period, sculpted in the same style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borchardt left behind extensive notes on his dig and findings at Amarna. He claims that the bust was found 50 cm under gravel. He explains that the artwork was sitting on a shelf, about 1.5 m from the ground, when the city was abandoned. As time passed, the walls decayed and the bust fell face down. The problem with this theory is that only the ears in the bust are damaged. If it did fall from such a height, that too face down, the nose would have been damaged, most definitely, especially because it is a delicate limestone sculpture. Is it possible that the bust was forged, then? Some modern experiments do reveal, however, that the plaster used in the bust is from the Amarna period. Although it is certainly possible that usable plaster, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign found in the same dig, was used if the bust is indeed fake. One thing that makes this theory less plausible, however, is the fact that the person who did forge the bust would have to have known all about ancient Egyptian hand and finger measurements. This is unlikely as the forger must have been a local Egyptian, probably not well versed with Egyptology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the question of why. &lt;em&gt;Why forge something like this?&lt;/em&gt; When Kaiser William realised that Germany was lagging behind in the field of Egyptology, he ordered German Egyptologists to get him something, whatever might be the cost, to shock the world. In addition, one of Germany’s princely families was in Egypt at the time of the dig. Borchardt, who specialised in the domestic lives of ancient Egyptians, might have hired an artist to work on the limestone and plaster, in an attempt to understand the process involved. When the German princely family arrived at the dig, he just couldn’t explain to them that the bust was fake, fearing that he might commit the crime of disrespecting the royalty and be prosecuted for it. As a matter of fact, he did not allow the sculpture to be displayed publicly for almost 10 years after it was found. As for now, it is difficult to be sure as to what exactly underwent on the 6th of December, 1912.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Nefertiti’s importance in the modern perception of ancient history is highly limited, it is undeniable that Nefertiti, in fact, commanded immense power and was incredibly important in her time. She quickly rose to the post of a co-regent; a position equivalent to that of a Pharaoh himself. In most paintings, she is shown to be of equal size as her husband. This is rather rare because size was often used as a metaphor for power. In a relic from a temple in Tell-el Amarna, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign, Nefertiti is even seen smiting a foreign enemy with a mace. She is often depicted wearing the regal crown. Such depictions were usually reserved for the Pharaoh alone. She did have a title that declared her as the Ruler of the Nile and the Daughter of Gods. But, the question is, &lt;em&gt;was she more than that?&lt;/em&gt; Perhaps, she might even have ruled as a Pharaoh for a while?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions like these are very difficult to answer, especially when it comes to the Amarna period (approximately 1353 to 1336 BCE- Akhenaten’s reign). A lot of events distinguish this particular period in Egyptian history from others. It all starts with Akhenaten’s decision to shift the capital to Tell-el Amarna, in the middle of the desert, in the second year of his roughly 17 year reign. Very soon, Amarna became a modern (for ancient times) city with 50,000 residents. Akhenaten and Nefertiti also started advocating a new monotheistic religion, Atenism. It is the worship of the Sun disc. Monotheism indeed sounds like an Anno Dominic concept. In fact, priests of the time weren’t very happy as the new religion failed to answer important questions about death, something that had been central to their religion for many years. Their successor, Tutankhaten was, however, unable to carry forward the legacy and eventually gave in to the priests. Upon their advice, he changed his name to Tutankhamun and embraced the polytheistic religion that everyone was used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystery surrounding Nefertiti is not just limited to her parentage. She disappears from all records in the 12th year of Akhenaten’s reign and no one seems to know why. Many believe that she died at this point, victimised by a plague that had claimed several lives around that time. Some Egyptologists fail to agree to such an explanation, especially since Nefertiti’s tomb was never found. In 2015, Nicholas Reeves came up with a highly debated and popular alternative theory. While going through some high resolution pictures, he noticed cracks that looked like doors in the northern and eastern walls of Tutankhamun’s burial chamber in the Valley of Kings. Infrared thermography revealed different temperature readings confirming two possible hidden passages. Reeves theorised that Tutankhamun &lt;strong&gt;inherited&lt;/strong&gt; the tomb of Nefertiti. In fact, Tutankhamun’s tomb is rather unusual: it is small and was made in a hurry. Close examinations reveal dripping marks of the paint, impressions of hasty brush strokes and mould, proving that the tomb was closed before the paint dried. A tomb needs to be sealed within 70 days of the Pharaoh’s death. Tutankhamun was only 19 when he passed away. Usually tombs take the entire lifetime of the pharaohs to be built. But Tutankhamun’s tomb decorations couldn’t have taken more than a week to be done with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Reeves, the hidden passage could lead to Nefertiti’s burial chamber. Zahi Hawas, the former Egyptian Minister of Antiquities, rejected this idea stating that Nefertiti was nothing more than a wife to Pharaoh Akhenaten and thus there was no reason for the priest of Amun to honour her by putting her to rest in the Valley of Kings. He further claims that a wall sealing the Queen’s burial chamber would restrict her passage to the afterlife. I, however, find this slightly problematic as all tombs are, in fact, sealed. Recently, however, Italian geophysicists used Ground Penetrating Radar to confirm the absence of a hidden chamber, putting all speculations to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that surprises many is the fact that Nefertiti is portrayed guarding Akhenaten’s granite sarcophagus; a position traditionally reserved for the female deities of Egypt, Isis, Nepthys, Selket and Neith. Her influence remained strong even after her death. Or did it? Did she really die in the 10th year of her residence in Amarna? Many believe that she did not. Right after Nefertiti’s name disappears from the records, a new figure appears; a co-regent with whom Akhenaten actively shared the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is speculated that Nefertiti might even have taken the throne as a female king, following the footsteps of previous female rulers, like Sobekneferu and Hatshepsut. Two such co-regents’ names have been associated with Nefertiti; Neferneferuaten and Smenkhkare. Surprisingly, the latter is male. But, then again, even Hatshepsut had to disguise as a man to rule. In fact, some even go to the extent of saying that Nefertiti took the throne for herself after Akhenaten’s death as Tutankhamun was too young to rule. Tutankhaten changed his name, capital and reverted back to the old religion only in the 3rd year of reign, around the time Nefertiti would have finally died. Nothing, however, is known with certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like a lot of other influential female personalities of the ancient world, Nefertiti’s name and contributions have largely been whitewashed by the future and patriarchy. Not much is known of her today. In fact, what we do know and understand is very little compared to even some of the oldest (male) Pharaohs. This implies that she is unable to boast of the popularity that she deserves. Zoe Saldana once said, “I would love to play Nefertiti or Cleopatra or the Queen of Sheba. We preserve more male history than we do female. We have to preserve [female history]. No more complaining. We have to do it.” We can only hope that one day everyone understands her worth, importance and contribution to our history. A search must start for the lost histories of womankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so special about her?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Will Arsenal’s New Signings Fit In?</title><link href="/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Will Arsenal’s New Signings Fit In?" /><published>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In</id><content type="html" xml:base="/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In">&lt;p&gt;Since the appointment of ex-Arsenal midfielder Edu as the club’s technical
director last month, the Gunners have accelerated their transfer plans after
initially making slow progress towards agreeing deals for the likes of Wilfried
Zaha and Kieran Tierney. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the little-heralded signing of Brazillian youngster Gabriel Martinelli,
the window really kicked off with the double announcement of Dani Ceballos on
loan from Real Madrid and the signing of £27 million William Saliba (who was
subsequently loaned back to Saint Étienne) on July 25th. This was soon trumped
by the surprise signing of Nicolas Pépé from Lille, with Arsenal defying the
reports of their £45 million transfer budget by securing the £72 million Ivorian
forward on a 5 year deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, deadline day saw the defence bolstered by the £25 million signing of
left-back Kieran Tierney from Celtic and the shock arrival of veteran
centre-back David Luiz from London rivals Chelsea for £8M on a two year deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Unai Emery now having added quality at his disposal, the question is how
each of the new boys will fit in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;William Saliba&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick mention of someone Arsenal fans won’t get to see for a while; teenage
defender William Saliba whose former club Saint-Etienne insisted on having him
loaned back to them this season. Despite not having played a game for the club,
he has already endeared himself to the Arsenal faithful after he reportedly
snubbed interest from North London rivals Tottenham before opting to join the
Gunners. Once Arsenal fans do get to see him in action, they will see an
accomplished modern centre-back, capable of surging forward from the back whilst
also being a dependable defender, especially in 1v1 situations. His rangy stride
and 6’3 frame make him a physically excellent prospect and when looking at the
market for the likes of Harry Maguire, £28 million could be a bargain for an 18
year old that was starting for the fourth best team in France.  Saliba, along
with Rob Holding and Calum Chambers, looks set to be the future of Arsenal’s
central defence as Sokratis and David Luiz advance into their 30s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signing of 18 year old Brazillian winger Gabriel Martinelli has
understandably been forgotten about by many after the 5 higher profile signings
that followed. Signed from Brazillian side Ituano for a reported fee of £6
million, Martinelli made his debut in a short cameo against Newcastle last
weekend and, with the sale of Alex Iwobi to Everton, could be in for some
minutes as a rotation player this season. With Pépé and Henrikh Mkhitaryan now
the only established wingers at the club there’s a route to the first team for
Martinelli, but he’ll face fierce competition from fellow teenage wingers Reiss
Nelson, Emile Smith-Rowe and Bukayo Saka. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dani Ceballos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talented midfielder Dani Ceballos played a crucial role in Spain’s triumph at
the European U21 Championship in Italy this summer, and he will now embark on a
short stint in North London before he likely cements himself as a Real Madrid
regular for years to come. A player as gifted as Ceballos is seldom available on
loan and Arsenal should thank the likes of Luka Modric and Toni Kroos for
blocking his path to regular minutes at the Bernabeu, allowing Arsenal to
acquire a player who will slot right into their first XI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Ceballos being the only addition to Arsenal’s midfield this summer, it
would be natural to think he would be tasked with replacing the void left by
Aaron Ramsey’s departure to Juventus. However, Ceballos is more similar to a few
of Ramsey’s former midfield partners: Jack Wilshere and fellow Spaniard Santi
Cazorla. Wilshere and Cazorla both averaged over 2 dribbles a game throughout
their Arsenal careers, but since their departures in 2018 no Arsenal midfielder
averaged more than Mattéo Guendouzi’s 0.7 dribbles a game last season. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ceballos averaged 2.7 dribbles per game in his last league season of regular
football at Real Betis in the 2016/17 season and should contribute to some much
needed technical support in the centre of the park, giving Arsenal a ball
carrying outlet from deep to evade pressure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-01.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-02.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-03.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ceballos’ immense skill set and versatility means he is capable as a deep-lying
playmaker, a tireless box-to-box CM, or in the number 10 role. Given Ramsey’s
departure and Özil’s recent off-the-pitch adversities, Emery is likely to deploy
Ceballos as the furthest forward midfielder. The 23-year old’s outstanding
performance on his home debut against Burnley earned him rave reviews and the
MOTM award, showcasing his masterful ability as he began the game behind the
striker but switched to a deeper role later in the game. Wherever he plays, the
former Real Betis man is a superb addition to Arsenal’s midfield for this
season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicolas Pépé&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£72 million man Nicolas Pépé is the most hyped up of Arsenal’s summer signings
for good reason; the Ivorian was one of only two players in the top 5 European
leagues to score at least 20 times and record over 10 assists, with the other
being Lionel Messi. Only Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang (22) and Alexandre Lacazette
(13) managed more than 6 league goals for Arsenal last season so Pépé’s arrival
should easen the load for the pair while forming a potent 3-pronged attack to
try to match those at Liverpool and Man City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though playing in a weaker league last year, Pépé regularly got into goal
scoring positions and had no hesitation in pulling the trigger, averaging 3.1
shots a game from wide, which is a welcome attribute to a team that had less
shots than Crystal Palace and Southampton last season. Pépé will add value as a
ball carrier and an outlet in the final third, fitting a profile Arsenal have
been missing since the departures of Alex Oxlade-Chamberlain, Theo Walcott and
Alexis Sánchez. Pépé’s dribbling stats last season were comparable to those of
Chamberlain’s and Sánchez’s during their time at the Emirates, and if he can
combine that with Walcott and Sánchez’s goal tallies then Arsenal have found a
real gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, however, questions as to how he will fit into Arsenal’s front line
with the likes of Lacazette, Aubameyang and Özil. Based on Unai Emery’s
pragmatic approach last season, it seems unlikely the 4 will line up together
often, especially away from home. Pépé should nevertheless be a fixture on the
team sheet along with Aubameyang due to their counter attacking potential. With
Pépé being a right sided player and Aubameyang, Özil and Lacazette usually
playing centrally it seems difficult to play them all without one of them being
out of position. Özil prefers to operate on the right rather than the left which
could cause Pépé to be forced to the left in pursuit of playing the two
centre-forwards in their natural positions. Needless to say, this would not be
an ideal situation for a player new to the Premier League so it’ll be up to
Emery to manage his team rotations and come up with a fluid attack to get the
best out of all his star forwards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-11.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-12.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-13.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kieran Tierney&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most important Arsenal signings were made on deadline day as the
Gunners brought in some much needed defensive reinforcements. 22-year-old
Tierney has already captained Celtic and Scotland, fulfilling the criteria of
being a leader, a quality that many pundits, such as Gary Neville, have long
been saying Arsenal miss. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he recovers from his hernia operation, Tierney will be tasked with fighting
off competition from fellow left-backs Nacho Monreal and Sead Kolašinac to make
the position his own. Tierney predominantly featured in a back 4 at Celtic but
has also played on the left of a back 3 for Scotland, with Liverpool’s Andy
Robertson playing as a wing back ahead of him. Whilst this may just have been a
way to shoehorn two of Scotland’s best players into the same XI, it could be an
option for Arsenal going forward with Sead Kolašinac lining up alongside
Tierney. Nacho Monreal has been deployed in a similar way over the last few
years and the benefit of this would be adding another ball playing centre-half
to bring the ball out from the back, as well as ideally having improved
defensive security with 5 defenders playing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should Tierney start in a back 4, he should act as a good counter balance to
Hector Bellerin on the opposite flank, with the Scot being the more reserved,
technically proficient of the pair whilst Bellerin utilises his athleticism to
make off ball runs and try and get in behind the opposition’s defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-21.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Luiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By crossing the divide between West and North London David Luiz followed the
path that several players have trodden in the last 20 years, and if he can
emulate the very reasonable Arsenal career of William Gallas then by all
accounts he should be considered a success. Whilst Gallas was 3 years younger
than Luiz when he left Stamford Bridge for the Emirates, he was a reliable (on
the pitch, at least) performer for the club, playing 142 times for Arsenal and
being named club captain after just one season at the club ahead of established
veterans such as Jens Lehmann and Gilberto Silva. Luiz will likely form an
experienced central defensive partnership with Sokratis, replacing Laurent
Koscielny after the Frenchman’s 9 year residency at the club came to an end. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-31.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luiz entered the Premier League the same year Koscielny did, with both rightly
considered error-prone during their formative years in England before becoming
quality centre-backs. Both are proactive defenders who defend on the front-foot,
frequently stepping up to intercept dangerous passes. They are also both adept
at bringing the ball out of defence and into midfield. However, Luiz is a much
more accomplished passer, completing more through balls than any other Premier
League player last season. If Luiz can replicate that form this season, Pépé and
Aubameyang will thoroughly enjoy themselves in behind opposition backlines.
Luiz’s fine passing repertoire may be best served in a back 3, like in the
2016/17 season where he made the PFA Team of the Year, where he can venture
forward into midfield whilst still having two central defenders to cover for
him. Seeing the Brazillian in an Arsenal shirt will take some getting used to,
but, at £8 million, he could prove to be one of the most astute signings of the
summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal’s window surpassed most people’s expectations and, though nothing is
certain in football, right now has to be tentatively considered a success.
Sanllehi and co. added 5 players ranging from 18-24 years of age along with a 32
year old with years of Premier League experience. Arsenal now have a good mix of
youngsters who can grow together in the next few years whilst also having
several seasoned veterans. The departures of Ramsey, Iwobi, Koscielny and Danny
Welbeck appear to have been well replaced whilst lowering the average squad age
as Arsenal begin a new era. Having said that, we can only review how good a
transfer window has been after seeing how the signings actually perform on the
pitch. There was lots of optimism following Arsenal’s 2016 window in which they
spent around £90 million on Shkodran Mustafi, Granit Xhaka, Lucas Pérez and Rob
Holding though the first 3 have all disappointed to varying degrees. It’s now up
to the team to prove the new signings have brought them back to the level where
Arsenal strive to be. However, fans do have reason for optimism as it seems that
after a few tumultuous years with Sven Mislintat and Ivan Gazidis at the helm,
the new management regime are capable of putting together a squad that looks set
to contend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*pictures are from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot;&gt;www.buildlineup.com&lt;/a&gt; and stats are from
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whoscored.com&quot;&gt;www.whoscored.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Since the appointment of ex-Arsenal midfielder Edu as the club’s technical director last month, the Gunners have accelerated their transfer plans after initially making slow progress towards agreeing deals for the likes of Wilfried Zaha and Kieran Tierney.  After the little-heralded signing of Brazillian youngster Gabriel Martinelli, the window really kicked off with the double announcement of Dani Ceballos on loan from Real Madrid and the signing of £27 million William Saliba (who was subsequently loaned back to Saint Étienne) on July 25th. This was soon trumped by the surprise signing of Nicolas Pépé from Lille, with Arsenal defying the reports of their £45 million transfer budget by securing the £72 million Ivorian forward on a 5 year deal.  Finally, deadline day saw the defence bolstered by the £25 million signing of left-back Kieran Tierney from Celtic and the shock arrival of veteran centre-back David Luiz from London rivals Chelsea for £8M on a two year deal.  With Unai Emery now having added quality at his disposal, the question is how each of the new boys will fit in. William Saliba A quick mention of someone Arsenal fans won’t get to see for a while; teenage defender William Saliba whose former club Saint-Etienne insisted on having him loaned back to them this season. Despite not having played a game for the club, he has already endeared himself to the Arsenal faithful after he reportedly snubbed interest from North London rivals Tottenham before opting to join the Gunners. Once Arsenal fans do get to see him in action, they will see an accomplished modern centre-back, capable of surging forward from the back whilst also being a dependable defender, especially in 1v1 situations. His rangy stride and 6’3 frame make him a physically excellent prospect and when looking at the market for the likes of Harry Maguire, £28 million could be a bargain for an 18 year old that was starting for the fourth best team in France.  Saliba, along with Rob Holding and Calum Chambers, looks set to be the future of Arsenal’s central defence as Sokratis and David Luiz advance into their 30s.  Gabriel Martinelli The signing of 18 year old Brazillian winger Gabriel Martinelli has understandably been forgotten about by many after the 5 higher profile signings that followed. Signed from Brazillian side Ituano for a reported fee of £6 million, Martinelli made his debut in a short cameo against Newcastle last weekend and, with the sale of Alex Iwobi to Everton, could be in for some minutes as a rotation player this season. With Pépé and Henrikh Mkhitaryan now the only established wingers at the club there’s a route to the first team for Martinelli, but he’ll face fierce competition from fellow teenage wingers Reiss Nelson, Emile Smith-Rowe and Bukayo Saka.  Dani Ceballos Talented midfielder Dani Ceballos played a crucial role in Spain’s triumph at the European U21 Championship in Italy this summer, and he will now embark on a short stint in North London before he likely cements himself as a Real Madrid regular for years to come. A player as gifted as Ceballos is seldom available on loan and Arsenal should thank the likes of Luka Modric and Toni Kroos for blocking his path to regular minutes at the Bernabeu, allowing Arsenal to acquire a player who will slot right into their first XI. With Ceballos being the only addition to Arsenal’s midfield this summer, it would be natural to think he would be tasked with replacing the void left by Aaron Ramsey’s departure to Juventus. However, Ceballos is more similar to a few of Ramsey’s former midfield partners: Jack Wilshere and fellow Spaniard Santi Cazorla. Wilshere and Cazorla both averaged over 2 dribbles a game throughout their Arsenal careers, but since their departures in 2018 no Arsenal midfielder averaged more than Mattéo Guendouzi’s 0.7 dribbles a game last season.  Ceballos averaged 2.7 dribbles per game in his last league season of regular football at Real Betis in the 2016/17 season and should contribute to some much needed technical support in the centre of the park, giving Arsenal a ball carrying outlet from deep to evade pressure.  Ceballos’ immense skill set and versatility means he is capable as a deep-lying playmaker, a tireless box-to-box CM, or in the number 10 role. Given Ramsey’s departure and Özil’s recent off-the-pitch adversities, Emery is likely to deploy Ceballos as the furthest forward midfielder. The 23-year old’s outstanding performance on his home debut against Burnley earned him rave reviews and the MOTM award, showcasing his masterful ability as he began the game behind the striker but switched to a deeper role later in the game. Wherever he plays, the former Real Betis man is a superb addition to Arsenal’s midfield for this season. Nicolas Pépé £72 million man Nicolas Pépé is the most hyped up of Arsenal’s summer signings for good reason; the Ivorian was one of only two players in the top 5 European leagues to score at least 20 times and record over 10 assists, with the other being Lionel Messi. Only Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang (22) and Alexandre Lacazette (13) managed more than 6 league goals for Arsenal last season so Pépé’s arrival should easen the load for the pair while forming a potent 3-pronged attack to try to match those at Liverpool and Man City.  Though playing in a weaker league last year, Pépé regularly got into goal scoring positions and had no hesitation in pulling the trigger, averaging 3.1 shots a game from wide, which is a welcome attribute to a team that had less shots than Crystal Palace and Southampton last season. Pépé will add value as a ball carrier and an outlet in the final third, fitting a profile Arsenal have been missing since the departures of Alex Oxlade-Chamberlain, Theo Walcott and Alexis Sánchez. Pépé’s dribbling stats last season were comparable to those of Chamberlain’s and Sánchez’s during their time at the Emirates, and if he can combine that with Walcott and Sánchez’s goal tallies then Arsenal have found a real gem. There are, however, questions as to how he will fit into Arsenal’s front line with the likes of Lacazette, Aubameyang and Özil. Based on Unai Emery’s pragmatic approach last season, it seems unlikely the 4 will line up together often, especially away from home. Pépé should nevertheless be a fixture on the team sheet along with Aubameyang due to their counter attacking potential. With Pépé being a right sided player and Aubameyang, Özil and Lacazette usually playing centrally it seems difficult to play them all without one of them being out of position. Özil prefers to operate on the right rather than the left which could cause Pépé to be forced to the left in pursuit of playing the two centre-forwards in their natural positions. Needless to say, this would not be an ideal situation for a player new to the Premier League so it’ll be up to Emery to manage his team rotations and come up with a fluid attack to get the best out of all his star forwards.  Kieran Tierney Perhaps the most important Arsenal signings were made on deadline day as the Gunners brought in some much needed defensive reinforcements. 22-year-old Tierney has already captained Celtic and Scotland, fulfilling the criteria of being a leader, a quality that many pundits, such as Gary Neville, have long been saying Arsenal miss.  When he recovers from his hernia operation, Tierney will be tasked with fighting off competition from fellow left-backs Nacho Monreal and Sead Kolašinac to make the position his own. Tierney predominantly featured in a back 4 at Celtic but has also played on the left of a back 3 for Scotland, with Liverpool’s Andy Robertson playing as a wing back ahead of him. Whilst this may just have been a way to shoehorn two of Scotland’s best players into the same XI, it could be an option for Arsenal going forward with Sead Kolašinac lining up alongside Tierney. Nacho Monreal has been deployed in a similar way over the last few years and the benefit of this would be adding another ball playing centre-half to bring the ball out from the back, as well as ideally having improved defensive security with 5 defenders playing.  Should Tierney start in a back 4, he should act as a good counter balance to Hector Bellerin on the opposite flank, with the Scot being the more reserved, technically proficient of the pair whilst Bellerin utilises his athleticism to make off ball runs and try and get in behind the opposition’s defence.  David Luiz By crossing the divide between West and North London David Luiz followed the path that several players have trodden in the last 20 years, and if he can emulate the very reasonable Arsenal career of William Gallas then by all accounts he should be considered a success. Whilst Gallas was 3 years younger than Luiz when he left Stamford Bridge for the Emirates, he was a reliable (on the pitch, at least) performer for the club, playing 142 times for Arsenal and being named club captain after just one season at the club ahead of established veterans such as Jens Lehmann and Gilberto Silva. Luiz will likely form an experienced central defensive partnership with Sokratis, replacing Laurent Koscielny after the Frenchman’s 9 year residency at the club came to an end.  Luiz entered the Premier League the same year Koscielny did, with both rightly considered error-prone during their formative years in England before becoming quality centre-backs. Both are proactive defenders who defend on the front-foot, frequently stepping up to intercept dangerous passes. They are also both adept at bringing the ball out of defence and into midfield. However, Luiz is a much more accomplished passer, completing more through balls than any other Premier League player last season. If Luiz can replicate that form this season, Pépé and Aubameyang will thoroughly enjoy themselves in behind opposition backlines. Luiz’s fine passing repertoire may be best served in a back 3, like in the 2016/17 season where he made the PFA Team of the Year, where he can venture forward into midfield whilst still having two central defenders to cover for him. Seeing the Brazillian in an Arsenal shirt will take some getting used to, but, at £8 million, he could prove to be one of the most astute signings of the summer. Summary Arsenal’s window surpassed most people’s expectations and, though nothing is certain in football, right now has to be tentatively considered a success. Sanllehi and co. added 5 players ranging from 18-24 years of age along with a 32 year old with years of Premier League experience. Arsenal now have a good mix of youngsters who can grow together in the next few years whilst also having several seasoned veterans. The departures of Ramsey, Iwobi, Koscielny and Danny Welbeck appear to have been well replaced whilst lowering the average squad age as Arsenal begin a new era. Having said that, we can only review how good a transfer window has been after seeing how the signings actually perform on the pitch. There was lots of optimism following Arsenal’s 2016 window in which they spent around £90 million on Shkodran Mustafi, Granit Xhaka, Lucas Pérez and Rob Holding though the first 3 have all disappointed to varying degrees. It’s now up to the team to prove the new signings have brought them back to the level where Arsenal strive to be. However, fans do have reason for optimism as it seems that after a few tumultuous years with Sven Mislintat and Ivan Gazidis at the helm, the new management regime are capable of putting together a squad that looks set to contend. *pictures are from www.buildlineup.com and stats are from www.whoscored.com</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Houston, Are We Finally Clear for Takeoff?</title><link href="/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Houston, Are We Finally Clear for Takeoff?" /><published>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff">&lt;p&gt;Houston has, perhaps, been one of the most perplexing franchises over the past three seasons because of their seemingly non-existent presence come playoff time. This second installment of breaking down the path to the Larry O’Brien Trophy will discuss the steps the Houston Rockets will need to take in order to finally get over the hump of their recent string of postseason woes, as well as why the Rockets have a strong chance of coming out on top of the 10-team gauntlet that is the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s turn the clock back to the 2016/17 season in which the Rockets went 55-27. Up to this point, James Harden had put up strong performances, however this was the season in which the Rockets finally found their identity: give Harden the ball and allow him to go to work against opposing defenses.With Harden averaging a strong stat line of 29.1/11.2/8.1 (points/assists/rebounds per game), the Rockets were able to secure the third seed in a historic season in which the Golden State Warriors went 67-15. Despite otherworldly offensive talent, Harden was only able to propel the Rockets to the second round of the playoffs, losing a series against the San Antonio Spurs 4-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the second round exit, GM Darly Morey actively pursued several top talents across the NBA that he could pair up with Harden to help carry the load. Out of this search came the (at the time) huge acquisition of Chris Paul. On paper this seemed like a match made in heaven, as Chris Paul is easily one of the top-five passing point guards to have ever played in the association. Having a player of this caliber to accompany Harden causes defenses to draw up on a different defensive scheme, which would, hypothetically, leave players (Eric Gordon, Trevor Ariza, Clint Capela, etc.) open for easier looks, as teams would now have to hone in the Harden/Paul duo out of the backcourt. This trade reaped instant benefits, as the Rockets easily claimed the first seed in the Western Conference, with the Golden State Warriors claiming the second seed 7 games behind the leading Rockets. The year also saw James Harden, once again, astonish the world with his mesmerizing offensive prowess and earn the honor of being crowned the NBA MVP for the 2017/18 regular season. While the Rockets obtained, what was in their eyes, the best possible outcome in the regular season, they again came up short losing to the Golden State Warriors in the Western Conference Finals after being 3-2 up in the series and having the home-court advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This frustration carried over into the 2018/19 season, as the Rockets were unable to consistently stay above the 500 mark into mid-December, largely due to the injury of Chris Paul which sidelined him for roughly half of the season. Despite the slow start, the Rockets saw themselves in the 4th seed, due to the play of James Harden, who seems to have elevated his offensive arsenal to the point that holding him to under 25 points is considered a defensive victory. The Rockets, once again, fell to their foe (the Golden State Warriors) in 6 games in the Western Conference Semifinals, marking yet another early exit. Emotions ran extremely high following the devastating loss, as the Warriors were without Kevin Durant and were expected to lose the series to the Rockets. Soon thereafter, strong disgruntled feelings were reported between James Harden and Chris Paul. Despite the constant dismissal of these reports, this ultimately lead to another blockbuster acquisition by the Rockets this past season, as Harden was reunited with fellow MVP Russell Westbrook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reunification of a backcourt duo of Westbrook and Harden is extremely intriguing given their past playing experience with each other, as well as how their individual playing styles line up very similarly. It is difficult, and misleading, to look at the stats from the three seasons that they were teammates in Oklahoma City because Harden was more of a role-player, and neither had fully reached their offensive potentials that make them top-20 talent players in the current NBA. We, as fans, have learned from the Chris Paul experiment that the success of this acquisition will largely depend on the willingness of James Harden to share the ball. The purpose of the Paul trade in the 2017 offseason was to help take the pressure off of Harden, however, due to injury and ego, Harden put up 1909 field goal attempts, which is nearly 300 more shot attempts than the next highest season, which spans back to times when James Harden was the only offensive power helping the Rockets stay afloat. Harden’s game thrives off of his ability to handle the ball from the second it is inbounded, so the acquisition of another player (especially one that plays the point guard position by nature) that thrives off of holding the ball and making something happen slightly resembles the trade for Paul in the 2017 season, which never came to full fruition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the skepticism, Harden and Westbrook have a different relationship than that of Harden and Paul. Westbrook has the potential to thrive playing off the ball, something that Paul widely struggled with. If Harden and Westbrook are able to create a system in which neither are suffering from not being able to get their shots up, then the Rockets have the potential to bring the Larry O’Brien Trophy back to Houston for the first time since the back-to-back championships in 1994 and 1995. Eric Gordon, PJ Tucker and Clint Capela will most likely round out the rest of the starting five and place their respective starting rotation among the likes of every other top team in the league (Lakers, Clippers, Bucks, 76ers, etc.). With potential contributions off the bench from Tyson Chandler, Austin Rivers, Danuel House and Gerald Green, the Rockets are set-up well to ride the wave when Westbrook and Harden are getting breathers. The talent is definitely present in Houston, as it has been for several seasons. The large looming question is whether the acquisition of Russell Westbrook is more of the same, or if it is the start of a new Warrior-esque dynasty in the West. If good health and cohesion are present in the Rockets locker room, then so will be the Larry O’Brien Trophy come June 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gavin Olson</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="basketball" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">Houston has, perhaps, been one of the most perplexing franchises over the past three seasons because of their seemingly non-existent presence come playoff time. This second installment of breaking down the path to the Larry O’Brien Trophy will discuss the steps the Houston Rockets will need to take in order to finally get over the hump of their recent string of postseason woes, as well as why the Rockets have a strong chance of coming out on top of the 10-team gauntlet that is the Western Conference.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Marvel of Mediocrity</title><link href="/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Marvel of Mediocrity" /><published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A prisoner’s affliction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might contest this by speaking of war-torn Syrians or the muddle of mental health, but Gen Y and Gen Z are sufferers of the worst kind of affliction; the affliction of &lt;em&gt;mediocrity&lt;/em&gt;. What makes this affliction so bad is its non-threatening nature. And I beg your pardon, we are not sufferers of this affliction, we are its prisoners. But what has made us prisoners? And why is this such a big issue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tales from the West&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West has always had an influence, directly or indirectly, over the entire world. We have adopted many of their cultural idiosyncrasies and even live them out everyday, without consciously realising it. One such Western quirk we’ve embraced is &lt;em&gt;individualism&lt;/em&gt;. I am not claiming that the West holds prerogative of it, but they are the ones to have so earnestly sermonised the concept of individualism. Western literature preaches the purpose and value of individual worth; how the world is every individual’s oyster. To permeate the consciousness with a sense of personal worth, they even went a step ahead and materialised it through architecture, giving almost every member of the family a room of their own. Think of the sense of autonomy and powerfulness you feel when you sit in your room, sip coffee or whatever, and ask for nudes. You feel the illusion of having control over your life and that of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Indian subcontinent too, we have had literature that spoke of princes being born with a divine purpose, be it the Tiger King or the Buddha. For a layman back then, however, to have acquired such works was a rarity, and even if he did find himself with one, the stories held little relevance in his life. These factors prevented popularisation and consequentially, realisation of individualism through architecture. As the communal form of existence in families continued through the generations, the concept of individualism never bloomed. We believed in a person’s societal worth rather than personal worth, in caste values rather than personal value, in purpose according to status in society rather than according to an individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A global distress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this changed when globalisation happened. After decades of being hungover on colonialism, once again we got a whiff of the West, and couldn’t get enough of it. Since then, we’ve consumed it like opium until the concept of individualism solidified through material means, i.e. architecture. Today, an average suburban household has separate rooms for almost everyone in the family. This is an embodiment of the privileges which, earlier, we only got to see in films and books of the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how does any of this make us prisoners of mediocrity? The feeling of not being good enough stems from the inability to actualise the personal worth or capability that popular discourse and architecture tell us we’re born with. To begin with, the very sense of personal value gives birth to an ill child called mediocrity. Since birth, we have been taught that we are unique, that we have a purpose to fulfil and that there’s a special place for us in the grand scheme of things. While growing up, we started to realise that perhaps we aren’t as special as we once believed. Right then, along comes someone like Aamir Khan, convincing an entire generation to reinstate their belief in uniqueness. Our existence could exude confidence and hope, once again! Don’t get me wrong, I am not against hope or anything that his films have taught us, in fact, I am most grateful for those films. However, along with everything good comes a bad and possibly, even an ugly. Even though, we are yet to see the ugly one, we very much have seen the bad one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mediocre beginnings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have come too far, the concept is too distilled in our souls to now have an exorcism. We simply have to accept that we aren’t unique geniuses. Maybe, a moderate, uneventful life will be all that we ever get. Maybe, we will never be anyone’s first choice, but there are great benefits to being an average that must not be discounted. To begin with, if you’re mediocre, most people can relate to you. Sure, a genius is looked up to, but up there he’s all alone. A great example of this is the film &lt;em&gt;Green Book&lt;/em&gt;, based on a trip taken to the south of the Mason-Dixon Line by Don Shirley, a famous black classical pianist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a remarkable scene, Mahershala Ali who plays Don Shirley says to his valet, Tony Lip, “Yes, I live in a castle, Tony. Alone! And rich people pay me to play piano for them because it makes them feel cultured, but as soon I step off that step, I go back to being just another n&lt;em&gt;**** to them. Because that is their true culture. But I suffer that slight alone because I am not like by my own people ‘cause I am not like them either.” This is a classic example of the kind of isolation a genius feels and it is common people like Tony Lip, the classic mediocre who lives a more fulfilled life, which is not to say that being a genius is bad and you should avoid it all costs (but if you were one you probably wouldn’t be reading this article right now). Taking a bit more from the example of *Green Book&lt;/em&gt;, Tony Lip lived a life of equilibrium, where he earned sufficiently, had the love of his friends and family, and was well received by the people around him. That kept him happy. At the end of the day, we cannot deny our most basic urge of socialising and wanting to be loved. Being a genius, more often than not, creates a distance between the admirer and the admired. As a mediocre, it is easier to strike a balance in life and to keep a clear and simple vision of it, something most geniuses struggle with. Leaf through the pages of history, and you’ll see that the most revered personalities also suffered the most through their lifetime. Your name living on, hundreds of years after your death, might sound like a golden prospect but what is the point, if your life has been nothing but suffering and despair? Look at it from a different angle, as a genius, you could have been the next Hitler. Hitler was an extremist with strong beliefs and it doesn’t matter if we agree to it or not, he was a genius; a genius too caught up in his own ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The complaisant man&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it is not easy to be a genius, but it also isn’t easy to be mediocre. A genius progresses in life and eventually finds meaninglessness. We, on the other hand, are mostly stagnant, and have to generate and believe in meanings to live by. We need to be ignorant, sometimes knowingly, to our conditions because being aware is not of much help. The genius, however, gets to be enlightened. He is a Sisyphus, aware of the futility of his actions, yet forced to carry the burden of changing the course of history. Whenever history is reshaped, by a single force, there live people who partake in that change and, in a way, make that change possible. They are the average Joes, the mediocres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take no shame in being a mediocre. Unlike a genius, being average requires denying a lot of our basic wants as curious beings and I am willing to trade those curiosities for a more fulfilled life. In the end, we’re all ignorant, what matters is how you exercise your ignorance to live more pleasantly. Just as the world needs the greats, it needs the averages. So, do not fret about not having a personal worth, because you do. Life is not short, as some say, it’s long enough to fill our lives with misery. It is, however, not in the pursuit of excellence but in the pursuit of absolute happiness, which albeit unattainable, that we can find liberation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">A prisoner’s affliction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age</title><link href="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age" /><published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age">&lt;p&gt;The first of The Pangean’s &lt;em&gt;pubcasts&lt;/em&gt; is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirandamowbray/&quot;&gt;Dr Miranda Mowbray&lt;/a&gt;, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/harsh.tiwari/&quot;&gt;Harsh Tiwari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/reuben.pritchard/&quot;&gt;Reuben Pritchard&lt;/a&gt; sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology as a replacement for human interaction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(60)&quot;&gt;01:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology in business and politics&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(1203)&quot;&gt;20:03&lt;/a&gt;), or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The accessibility of technology&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2142)&quot;&gt;35:42&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast1-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-1&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>the.pangean</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The first of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Dr Miranda Mowbray, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data. In this podcast, Harsh Tiwari and Reuben Pritchard sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest: Introduction (00:00), Technology as a replacement for human interaction (01:00), Technology in business and politics (20:03), or The accessibility of technology (35:42). Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Death Penalty: A Contentious Predicament</title><link href="/A-Contentious-Predicament" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Death Penalty: A Contentious Predicament" /><published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Contentious-Predicament</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Contentious-Predicament">&lt;p&gt;In the 1889 short story, &lt;em&gt;The Bet&lt;/em&gt;, Anton Chekhov, a Russian writer, subtly raised one of those deeply divisive questions that has been plaguing humankind since the dawn of civilisation. Through the depiction of an altercation between a young lawyer and a banker, who engage in a fierce battle of wits, he brought forward the motion - whether a lifetime in prison is more befitting than the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both, the nature of criminal activities and the very foundational values of human society, have undergone a significant evolution since Chekhov’s time. It would be myopic to confine the debate to which form of punishment is better or worse. It is only appropriate to subject the variables underlying the statement- which criminal activities deserve the highest of all culpable punishment? The age old debate gained a fresh lease of life with the U.S. Attorney General, William P Barr, clearing way for the federal government of the United States to resume executions of death row convicts after a lapse of nearly two decades. .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Debate raging Worldwide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Oxford English dictionary defines &lt;em&gt;death penalty&lt;/em&gt; as ‘the punishment of being killed that is used in some countries for very serious crimes’. Much to democrat Kamla Harris’s dismay, who regards death penalty as ‘immoral and deeply flawed’, the U.S. President Donald Trump had openly declared his support for capital punishment in 2018, at a rally in New Hampshire by stating that, “Drug dealers should be executed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might perhaps recall what Clive Stafford Smith, author of &lt;em&gt;The Injustice System&lt;/em&gt;,  had portrayed, with conviction, of an American lawyer who spent 28 years of his legal career in a futile attempt to save Kris Maharaj from the gallows. Maharaj, a British national, was subjected to an unfair trial for the death row, in Florida. Smith, through this case, successfully portrayed how often the judicial hierarchy, beginning from law enforcement agencies, often determines the final fate of many cases. He drew upon his own experiences, when he stated that a lawyer representing a private corporation harboured the potential of charging $1000 for an hour while for a death penalty often some of the best criminal lawyers would be payed $1000 for the whole case. The wage disparity invariably tantamounts to the difference in outcomes when it comes to a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the globe, 56 countries retain capital punishment and 106 countries have completely abolished it ‘de jure’. Article 2 of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union prohibits capital punishment. Incidentally (or rather ironically), 60% of the world’s population lives in countries where capital punishment still enjoys a legal stature. Most of the countries of the global south such as Saudi Arabia, Iran, Pakistan, Egypt, Sri Lanka and India fall under this category. With the exception of Belarus, all European countries have abolished the death penalty along with most of the Oceanian states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does death penalty really deter criminal instincts?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely accepted that awarding a death penalty for the commission of a crime sets a precedence for criminal acts of similar nature. In other words, it will serve as a warning for to-be criminals. An idea that can be precipitated is that, in earlier times, public executions were the norm of the day. The complete essence of fear would trickle down to the last man in the crowd, and have a direct psychological impact upon anyone harbouring such criminal instincts. However, with closed-door executions being the norm of the day such impact is no longer exercised. Justice Marshall with regard to the &lt;em&gt;Furman v. Georgia&lt;/em&gt;, in 1972, had clearly pronounced, “Capital punishment cannot be justified on the basis of its deterrent effect.” This was in direct contradiction to then US President Richard Nixon’s perception of capital punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As statistical and hard core factual evidence are necessary for informed policy making, a survey conducted by Thornsten Sellin regarding death penalty in 1959, and later in the data from Ruth Peterson and William Bailey’s paper entitled &lt;em&gt;Murder and Capital Punishment in the Evolving Context of the Post Furman Era&lt;/em&gt;, it was concluded that murder had been more common in states with capital punishment than in those where it’s not used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can death penalty be used solely as a tool of retribution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general notion harboured is “As you sow, so shall you reap.” The guilty deserve to be punished. The question that then arises is with respect to the severity of the punishment. It is absolutely in sync and coherent with our innate sense of morality and conscientious call for justice. However, the delay associated with the period of judicial trial leads to being kept in a condemned cell for a long span of time. This induces severe psychological trauma and stress, known as anticipatory suffering. Many argue life imprisonment truly succeeds in punishing an offender as death often comes as a welcome relief. The closure aspect to the victim’s kith and kin can’t be overlooked either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can the social security mechanism of law and police force be termed as infallible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most widely debated aspect remains whether the one who has extinguished another life deserves the right to live. And here comes the irreversible nature of death penalty. It was noted by former US Vice President, Joseph R Biden Jr, that since 1973, around 160 people who were sentenced to death were later exonerated. In India, a similar predicament was noted in September 2012 when 14 former judges of eminence had written to the then-Indian President Pranab Mukherjee. They had stated that seven of the judgements passed by the Supreme Court were rendered &lt;em&gt;in curium&lt;/em&gt;. Back in 1996 and 1997, as a consequence of flawed judgement, two prisoners- Ravji Rao and Surja Ramhad, were exonerated. These can be termed as nothing less than the most severe of miscarriages of justice- where men who ought to live were ‘killed’. Such is the power of capital punishment, which proves that no human rationale lies beyond human fallibility, and there’s no space for repentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is the verdict upon death penalty selective when it comes to final execution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another widely accepted argument remains that the death penalty is often biased towards individuals belonging to minority segments of the society. The racial, ethnic and geographical prejudice often plays the role of a triggering factor when it comes to ascertaining the final verdict. It usually comes down harsher upon the working class and marginalised groups, perhaps due to lack of resources, or rather to pander to majoritarian populism. In January 2008, the University of Maryland concluded in a study, commissioned by the Governor of Maryland, that defendants were at a greater risk to be sentenced to death if they had killed a white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hugely controversial case revolving around &lt;em&gt;Dhananjay Chatterjee V. The State of West Bengal&lt;/em&gt; (1994) widely spruced up a similar notion in India when the plaintiff himself reportedly stated “Since I’m poor, I’m being falsely accused.” Chatterjee had allegedly raped and murdered a teenager in Calcutta, in 1990. In October 2013, Patna High Court in Bihar, India acquitted 26 accused for the murder of 58 dalits (who in the Indian caste hierarchy are regarded as ‘lower castes’) in the Jehanabad district of Bihar in December, 2007. Thus the question of selective justice arises naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, post the &lt;em&gt;Bachan Singh v. State of Punjab&lt;/em&gt; (1980), the Supreme court clarified that the death penalty is to be awarded only in cases which could be termed as ‘rarest of rare’. Taking appropriate steps, like ensuring the death penalty clause is not used for political gains, death warrants are executed within a stipulated time limit and provision of equal legal aid to the accused regardless of socio-economic stature are some of the measures that will help ensure equity and justice to the charged persons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the title of Earnest Raymonds 1930’s seminal work, &lt;em&gt;We, the Accused&lt;/em&gt;, surprises everyone with its underlying irony where the social political system is the real accused, which breeds a criminal. An Amnesty International report sums it up, “Since Canada stopped executing, the murder rate has dropped by 44%.” However, the geopolitical and socio-economic factors of specific countries too demand significant consideration before taking a radical step such as abolishing capital punishment all together.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In the 1889 short story, The Bet, Anton Chekhov, a Russian writer, subtly raised one of those deeply divisive questions that has been plaguing humankind since the dawn of civilisation. Through the depiction of an altercation between a young lawyer and a banker, who engage in a fierce battle of wits, he brought forward the motion - whether a lifetime in prison is more befitting than the death penalty.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Mind-Numbingness of Black Mirror</title><link href="/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mind-Numbingness of Black Mirror" /><published>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror">&lt;p&gt;I remember being flabbergasted and mesmerised by &lt;em&gt;The National Anthem&lt;/em&gt; - the
very first episode of Charlie Brooker’s surreal and maddening piece of art that
we call &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. It took me a while to understand why it was called that,
and the revelation hit me like a brick. The idea of calling a screen ‘black
mirror’ because it reflects your image is not just genius on the surface but is
also a teaser for the show’s intention: to tell you about yourself through
technology. It is exceedingly difficult to watch the show one episode at a time.
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is discomforting due to the darkness in its content; dark enough
to send any brain on a whirlwind spin. It is potent, razor-sharp, and
brilliantly critical of the ways in which we abuse technology. If I ever had a
horror recommendation for someone, movie or TV show, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was what I
would first go with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t the first time that Charlie Brooker has scathingly criticised
technology. He previously wrote &lt;em&gt;Deadset&lt;/em&gt; - a show where a zombie apocalypse
breaks out in the &lt;em&gt;Big Brother&lt;/em&gt; (or as Indians call it, &lt;em&gt;Bigg Boss&lt;/em&gt;) house. It
is often called a precursor to &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. He’s also hosted &lt;em&gt;How TV Ruined
Your Life&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;TVGoHome&lt;/em&gt; - very self-explanatory titles about his disdain for
reality television’s outlandish premises. That is not to say he hates everything
about mainstream media. He is quite the pop culture and video game buff, having
hosted shows on both. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was the culmination of all of his thought
processes from earlier shows. It was prophetic and innovative, and told us
things about ourselves we did not wish to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not a problem, as long as you do not become the very thing you had hoped
to destroy. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was picked up by Netflix after two seasons and one
Christmas special, and since then, it has run on for three seasons with one
groundbreaking style of narration in the form of the interactive film,
&lt;em&gt;Bandersnatch&lt;/em&gt;. Undoubtedly, it gave us too much to think about again; the power
of technology to affect relationships, rattle politics, reveal sexual subtext,
create near-dystopian scenarios with social credit scores, prove that free will
is a myth, and show how the head of a state can be blackmailed into having sex
with a pig are on full display in this show. Surely, many would agree that, of
late, the episodes have been lacklustre as compared to the first few seasons.
However, that isn’t my concern here, because there is still enough food for
thought in those episodes. I’m concerned with why we find them lacklustre and
the entire culture that has formed around the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Netflix acquired the rights to Channel 4 production, one might have noted
a growing anxiety in people to want the streaming giant to release one more
season of the show. It ends too quickly for viewers, partly because of the
binge-watching culture that has engulfed the experience of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. Irony
kicks in strong here. We are willing to subject ourselves to the control of
technology because it has us hooked like a tight fishing rod. Sure, you get
quite a lot to think about, but you end up not realising the ridiculousness of
what you are doing. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; then becomes a show about how much it can
surprise and shock you, which, in all fairness, it continues to do in cruel and
sometimes gruesome ways. But the real question remains, to what extent have we
been able to grasp what those episodes imply about the future or the present.
This is also where the discomfort attached to the show matters. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;
is not here to spare your feelings, it is unafraid of destroying the lives of
all the protagonists in a single stroke, after around 40 minutes of intense
build up. How does one watch so many episodes of gruesome emotional intensity
and brutal philosophies, all in one go? It contributes to the culture of
incessant, mindless consumption of pop culture, without a pause. Our willingness
to consume such uncomfortable subject matter with such ease and speed is
indicative of how much we have let pop culture consume us, instead of the other
way round. Brooker himself said that bingeing the show is like getting hit by a
car, and that’s just one season worth of episodes. One might even argue that
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;, like all else, is just a show and it isn’t meant to convince or
change status quo vastly. However, it feels really preachy, especially once you
consider Charlie Brooker’s own beliefs. He wants to sell to us why our
increasing reliance on technology won’t get us too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I also find discouraging is the idea of Netflix backing this show. It’s a
terrible idea to pressurise your content creators to churning out further
content. I believe that is, in part, why the show has been declining in quality
lately. Netflix is still trying to find footing in this vast market that has now
been opened up due to the entry of giants like Disney and WarnerBros, not to
mention the existence of Amazon. It’s trying its hardest to keep subscribers
hooked by releasing new series and films continuously. In the midst of companies
taking back their content from Netflix, to host on their own sites, Netflix has
no choice but to create a niche of its own as soon as it can, like HBO, which is
perceived by many as one of the best content producers. A glaring example of
this strategy’s volatility was when Netflix purchased streaming rights to
&lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; for $100 million. Months later, this year, Warner Media took the
rights back when they announced the entry of their own streaming site. Netflix
has progressed in that sphere very well - originals like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New
Black, Narcos, House of Cards,&lt;/em&gt; etc. have carved their own space in the internet
sphere. However, at the end of the day, Netflix is run primarily on data
analytics, and every operation is based on that concept. While it’s the right
way to go about understanding your audience, increasing competition may worsen
the pace at which it wants to expand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does this strategy have such a paramount effect on a show? It’s because of
the resources that Netflix has put in for just this show alone. Before a season
launch, it would release a trailer for every single episode, which isn’t the
usual practice. A heavy marketing campaign will then follow, for engagement with
users on Twitter, YouTube and Facebook; something Netflix is really good at
because it has &lt;em&gt;humanised&lt;/em&gt; itself by replying to comments. Under Channel 4,
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was relatively obscure. Now, it’s Netflix’s marquee signing. More
funds also mean more high-profile celebrities act in the show, some of which
include Miley Cyrus and Jodie Foster. It also means smarter programming, like
the choose-your-own-adventure &lt;em&gt;Bandersnatch&lt;/em&gt;. However, the flip side of this
means that time doesn’t wait for quality, or the overall delivery of the
message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With escalating technological developments, there’s no way to tell whether we
will really use virtual reality or artificial intelligence the way the show
depicts. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is definitely a glimpse of the most vulnerable
tendencies of the human mind, because behind all the gizmo, it’s really a show
about what it means to be human and not about the hi-fi stuff itself.
Unfortunately, in the millennial age, we’re losing our human connections, and
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is just being co-opted into this stream of unconsciousness that
includes being stuck to some form of a screen. The show is prophetic for sure,
but is it going to impact how we approach technology? The use of apps like
FaceApp by a population unaware of the privacy policy or the unwanted potential
of machine learning, does not bode well for this question. We will no doubt have
more seasons of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; in the future, which will be different than the
previous ones. Despite all the meta-level, self-aware marketing Netflix might do
when it parodies itself as being part of the &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; universe, we all
know what it really means. We’ll just absorb more of it with gleeful abandon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we really need another screen to tell us not to be hooked to one?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pranav Manie</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">I remember being flabbergasted and mesmerised by The National Anthem - the very first episode of Charlie Brooker’s surreal and maddening piece of art that we call Black Mirror. It took me a while to understand why it was called that, and the revelation hit me like a brick. The idea of calling a screen ‘black mirror’ because it reflects your image is not just genius on the surface but is also a teaser for the show’s intention: to tell you about yourself through technology. It is exceedingly difficult to watch the show one episode at a time. Black Mirror is discomforting due to the darkness in its content; dark enough to send any brain on a whirlwind spin. It is potent, razor-sharp, and brilliantly critical of the ways in which we abuse technology. If I ever had a horror recommendation for someone, movie or TV show, Black Mirror was what I would first go with. It isn’t the first time that Charlie Brooker has scathingly criticised technology. He previously wrote Deadset - a show where a zombie apocalypse breaks out in the Big Brother (or as Indians call it, Bigg Boss) house. It is often called a precursor to Black Mirror. He’s also hosted How TV Ruined Your Life, and TVGoHome - very self-explanatory titles about his disdain for reality television’s outlandish premises. That is not to say he hates everything about mainstream media. He is quite the pop culture and video game buff, having hosted shows on both. Black Mirror was the culmination of all of his thought processes from earlier shows. It was prophetic and innovative, and told us things about ourselves we did not wish to hear. That is not a problem, as long as you do not become the very thing you had hoped to destroy. Black Mirror was picked up by Netflix after two seasons and one Christmas special, and since then, it has run on for three seasons with one groundbreaking style of narration in the form of the interactive film, Bandersnatch. Undoubtedly, it gave us too much to think about again; the power of technology to affect relationships, rattle politics, reveal sexual subtext, create near-dystopian scenarios with social credit scores, prove that free will is a myth, and show how the head of a state can be blackmailed into having sex with a pig are on full display in this show. Surely, many would agree that, of late, the episodes have been lacklustre as compared to the first few seasons. However, that isn’t my concern here, because there is still enough food for thought in those episodes. I’m concerned with why we find them lacklustre and the entire culture that has formed around the show. Since Netflix acquired the rights to Channel 4 production, one might have noted a growing anxiety in people to want the streaming giant to release one more season of the show. It ends too quickly for viewers, partly because of the binge-watching culture that has engulfed the experience of Black Mirror. Irony kicks in strong here. We are willing to subject ourselves to the control of technology because it has us hooked like a tight fishing rod. Sure, you get quite a lot to think about, but you end up not realising the ridiculousness of what you are doing. Black Mirror then becomes a show about how much it can surprise and shock you, which, in all fairness, it continues to do in cruel and sometimes gruesome ways. But the real question remains, to what extent have we been able to grasp what those episodes imply about the future or the present. This is also where the discomfort attached to the show matters. Black Mirror is not here to spare your feelings, it is unafraid of destroying the lives of all the protagonists in a single stroke, after around 40 minutes of intense build up. How does one watch so many episodes of gruesome emotional intensity and brutal philosophies, all in one go? It contributes to the culture of incessant, mindless consumption of pop culture, without a pause. Our willingness to consume such uncomfortable subject matter with such ease and speed is indicative of how much we have let pop culture consume us, instead of the other way round. Brooker himself said that bingeing the show is like getting hit by a car, and that’s just one season worth of episodes. One might even argue that Black Mirror, like all else, is just a show and it isn’t meant to convince or change status quo vastly. However, it feels really preachy, especially once you consider Charlie Brooker’s own beliefs. He wants to sell to us why our increasing reliance on technology won’t get us too far. What I also find discouraging is the idea of Netflix backing this show. It’s a terrible idea to pressurise your content creators to churning out further content. I believe that is, in part, why the show has been declining in quality lately. Netflix is still trying to find footing in this vast market that has now been opened up due to the entry of giants like Disney and WarnerBros, not to mention the existence of Amazon. It’s trying its hardest to keep subscribers hooked by releasing new series and films continuously. In the midst of companies taking back their content from Netflix, to host on their own sites, Netflix has no choice but to create a niche of its own as soon as it can, like HBO, which is perceived by many as one of the best content producers. A glaring example of this strategy’s volatility was when Netflix purchased streaming rights to Friends for $100 million. Months later, this year, Warner Media took the rights back when they announced the entry of their own streaming site. Netflix has progressed in that sphere very well - originals like Orange Is The New Black, Narcos, House of Cards, etc. have carved their own space in the internet sphere. However, at the end of the day, Netflix is run primarily on data analytics, and every operation is based on that concept. While it’s the right way to go about understanding your audience, increasing competition may worsen the pace at which it wants to expand.  Why does this strategy have such a paramount effect on a show? It’s because of the resources that Netflix has put in for just this show alone. Before a season launch, it would release a trailer for every single episode, which isn’t the usual practice. A heavy marketing campaign will then follow, for engagement with users on Twitter, YouTube and Facebook; something Netflix is really good at because it has humanised itself by replying to comments. Under Channel 4, Black Mirror was relatively obscure. Now, it’s Netflix’s marquee signing. More funds also mean more high-profile celebrities act in the show, some of which include Miley Cyrus and Jodie Foster. It also means smarter programming, like the choose-your-own-adventure Bandersnatch. However, the flip side of this means that time doesn’t wait for quality, or the overall delivery of the message. With escalating technological developments, there’s no way to tell whether we will really use virtual reality or artificial intelligence the way the show depicts. Black Mirror is definitely a glimpse of the most vulnerable tendencies of the human mind, because behind all the gizmo, it’s really a show about what it means to be human and not about the hi-fi stuff itself. Unfortunately, in the millennial age, we’re losing our human connections, and Black Mirror is just being co-opted into this stream of unconsciousness that includes being stuck to some form of a screen. The show is prophetic for sure, but is it going to impact how we approach technology? The use of apps like FaceApp by a population unaware of the privacy policy or the unwanted potential of machine learning, does not bode well for this question. We will no doubt have more seasons of Black Mirror in the future, which will be different than the previous ones. Despite all the meta-level, self-aware marketing Netflix might do when it parodies itself as being part of the Black Mirror universe, we all know what it really means. We’ll just absorb more of it with gleeful abandon. Do we really need another screen to tell us not to be hooked to one?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is it Like to Live in a World of Cyborgs?</title><link href="/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is it Like to Live in a World of Cyborgs?" /><published>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs">&lt;p&gt;At the close of the 19th century, Lord Kelvin, a celebrated scientist, stated
that everything that was meant to be discovered or invented had already been
discovered or invented by man. He and his fellow members of the Royal Society
believed, without a drop of doubt, that they were living in the Golden Age. But,
boy, were they wrong. The 20th century saw some remarkable advancements in
science and technology. Classical Physics gave way to Quantum Physics.
Telescopes gave way to moon missions. Black and white cameras eventually gave
way to DSLRs. And today, a strange new possibility has everyone sitting firmly
in their seats with seat belts on: &lt;em&gt;cyborgs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until a few decades back, robots, androids and cyborgs only thrived in dystopian
sci-fi novels. They, however, grasped the attention of many budding scientists,
and engineers started wondering if, one day, robots and cyborgs could be brought
to reality. Robots have existed for a while now. But possibilities of the future
are well beyond the limits of just mechanical arms used in the factories today,
and this unsurprisingly scares many. Today, bionic limbs are very common.
Amputation hardly frightens or hinders anyone anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one big issue, that is, suppose Mr X has lost his legs to frostbite
and he now has artificial legs, he can run to the grocery on a rainy Wednesday
night to get veggies or even participate in the Paralympics and bring glory to
his country, however, he cannot feel his legs. Cyborgs are not like that at all.
They are partially organic and partly made of artificial parts. The technology
is a part of the cyborg’s human body and maintains a symbiotic relationship with
it. The artificial system, being embedded in the human frame, can feed
information to the nervous system. As a result, this allows sensation. Make no
mistake, the famous Saudi Arabian citizen, Sophia is very different from this.
She is an android: a robot in the form of a human. A cyborg is a human with some
technological parts meant to enhance or repair some of the person’s abilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think that something like this cannot exist beyond the pages of a
fictional novel, then you are wrong. Technology like this already exists. One
example being nanotechnology. This branch of technology has the potential to
revolutionise technology as we know it today. In fact, active research is being
conducted to figure out how it can be used to revolutionise the field of
medicine. Nanobots are robots made of nanomaterials that have the ability to
carry out a specific task. Scientists hope to use this technology to travel down
the blood-stream and kill malignant cells or deliver drugs to a particular
tissue (known as the target tissue). Various other nanotechnological procedures
involve insertion of nano-materials or nano-machines into the human body to
carry out a certain task. Apart from nanotechnology, we also have the developing
fields of neuroscience and neurotechnology. Neuralink is among the pioneers in
this field today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuralink was set up in 2016 by the celebrated engineer and entrepreneur Elon
Musk to develop a device like the ‘neural lace’ from Scottish author Iain M.
Banks’ famous sci-fi novel series &lt;em&gt;The Culture&lt;/em&gt;. Unlike most contemporary sci-fi
novels, this series describes a utopian (and not dystopian) space society. Very
recently, Neuralink was in the news for developing a computer chip that can
enable paralysed people to move a cursor and type words using their brain. The
chip is connected to very thin fibre-like electrodes and the wires are connected
to thought transmitters to accomplish the task. Musk labelled this as a first
step in the path to &lt;em&gt;‘symbiosis with artificial intelligence’,&lt;/em&gt; something that
he believes is necessary for humans to &lt;em&gt;remain relevant&lt;/em&gt; in this era of
technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, so much in science is an ethics and morality debate and neuro and
nanotechnology are no exceptions. It’s easy to see that the ultimate goal is
human enhancement. But just because we are capable of doing something, doesn’t
necessarily mean that it should be done. We have to delineate what kind of human
enhancement should be strived for and what should not be strived for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one end of the spectrum, technology like Nueralink’s chips will definitely
prove beneficial to those who suffer everyday due to some chronic or fatal
disease or some kind of an amputation or genetic disorder. Sufferings due to
health issues would cease to exist completely: no disabilities, no depression,
zero neuro-diversity and of course, no discrimination on the basis of these.
Different companies or universities still do not hire people with heart diseases
or cancer today. Such problems would simply vanish. A new world free of bodily
pain would be born. We would be able to fulfil our utopian vision of a
biologically and socially (to some extent) egalitarian society. While this
sounds like the best thing that could possibly happen to us, closer inspection
reveals other problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the major issues that humans face today is a huge population. In the
past, whenever there was a population boom, some incident or the other, like the
Black Plague, brought it under control. Today, with the help of modern medicine,
such disasters have been effectively averted. In addition, the life span of
humans has increased by a considerable amount in the last few centuries. In a
world where humans do not die of diseases or disabilities, this will become a
much bigger issue. And once humans are replaced by cyborgs, the amount of time
leading up to our doom will only get accelerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, we have seen how dystopian sci-fi novels have eventually come true,
at least to some extent. This includes atom bombs, waterbeds, the nuclear arms
race and so on. Most novels involving cyborgs and robots end with these pieces
of technology taking up arms against humans and replacing them as the most
powerful ‘creatures’ (if I may use this word) on planet Earth. Many companies
are currently conducting research to create robots who express emotions like
humans or those which can be used as war tools. The future is difficult to
predict. But we just cannot ignore the possibility of these novels becoming
reality one day if proper regulations and checks are not put in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem that arises is the problem of unequal distribution of
technology. In the largely capitalist parts of the world, the divide between the
rich and the poor is enormous. The poor are unable to afford a lot of things
that the rich can afford very easily: luxurious housing, expensive sports cars
and, of course, plastic surgery. If the availability of neurotechnology to the
public ends up being anything like plastic surgery, the rich would exploit it to
enhance themselves and eventually modify themselves into an unrecognisable
species. All this while the poor would be unable to afford the simplest of
technologies to even cure diseases. There will be a new divide, this time
between super-humans (or cyborgs) and humans. Even if we consider a scenario
where no human is greater or lesser than the other, it raises some very serious
problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unemployment in Japan is at its peak now. This is because of the fact that too
many people are eligible and qualified for a particular job. Japan has an
astonishing literacy rate of 99% and a population of 126 million. Both of these
contribute to the country’s current condition. In a world of enhanced human
beings, everyone would have eidetic memory and equally exceptional logical
thinking skills. Everyone would be equally capable of everything. Unfortunately,
unless the number of jobs is increased, this would create a very serious
problem. Besides unemployment, there would be an equality crisis: employers
would find it difficult to choose an employee because everyone would more or
less be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture today is highly dependent on human emotion. The best pieces of art are
arguably born out of sadness. Lord Alfred Tennyson wrote &lt;em&gt;In Memoriam&lt;/em&gt; after his
friend, Arthur Henry Hallam who died of a cerebral haemorrhage in 1833. The
&lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, one of the greatest Indian epics, was born after Maharishi Valmiki
witnessed the sad demise of a bird. Van Gogh is famous because of his depression
and the creative expression born out of it. In a world free of pain, sadness, as
we know it, would cease to exist and along with it, all the artistic pieces that
would have otherwise inspired generations to come. The terms- ‘human’, ‘natural’
and ‘biological’, would no longer have a clear and distinct meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For long, humans have wondered where we have come from and where we are headed.
Dan Brown, in his novel &lt;em&gt;Origin,&lt;/em&gt; explained how humans will eventually be
replaced or more accurately evolve into a half-organic, half-artificial species
and that would herald a truly utopian world. In spite of all the possible
negative consequences, scientists continue to conduct research in this field
with an aim to enhance human beings in the near future. Musk’s Neuralink plans
on starting human testing very soon. While some believe that cyborg technology
is ethical and tests on humans should be carried out at the earliest, many fear
a dystopian future instead of the scientist-envisioned utopian one. There are
many concerns surrounding human testing too. While proponents of this debate
argue that it is a necessity for the &lt;em&gt;greater good&lt;/em&gt;, others feel that ‘consent’
from patients who are crippled or terminally ill are born of desperation and
cannot be counted as proper consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At every stage of progress, humans are faced with the dilemma of what is right
and wrong. And at every step, humans have successfully taken a decision to
preserve mankind. But today, we have come a long way, we have done things that
would have been unimaginable a century back, and now, all of humanity is faced
with a choice to alter the very thing that qualifies us as humans. However, it
is up to us, up to our generation to follow a path that would lead us to a
future. And that will determine if we are at all capable of making a right
choice and living on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">At the close of the 19th century, Lord Kelvin, a celebrated scientist, stated that everything that was meant to be discovered or invented had already been discovered or invented by man. He and his fellow members of the Royal Society believed, without a drop of doubt, that they were living in the Golden Age. But, boy, were they wrong. The 20th century saw some remarkable advancements in science and technology. Classical Physics gave way to Quantum Physics. Telescopes gave way to moon missions. Black and white cameras eventually gave way to DSLRs. And today, a strange new possibility has everyone sitting firmly in their seats with seat belts on: cyborgs. Until a few decades back, robots, androids and cyborgs only thrived in dystopian sci-fi novels. They, however, grasped the attention of many budding scientists, and engineers started wondering if, one day, robots and cyborgs could be brought to reality. Robots have existed for a while now. But possibilities of the future are well beyond the limits of just mechanical arms used in the factories today, and this unsurprisingly scares many. Today, bionic limbs are very common. Amputation hardly frightens or hinders anyone anymore. But there is one big issue, that is, suppose Mr X has lost his legs to frostbite and he now has artificial legs, he can run to the grocery on a rainy Wednesday night to get veggies or even participate in the Paralympics and bring glory to his country, however, he cannot feel his legs. Cyborgs are not like that at all. They are partially organic and partly made of artificial parts. The technology is a part of the cyborg’s human body and maintains a symbiotic relationship with it. The artificial system, being embedded in the human frame, can feed information to the nervous system. As a result, this allows sensation. Make no mistake, the famous Saudi Arabian citizen, Sophia is very different from this. She is an android: a robot in the form of a human. A cyborg is a human with some technological parts meant to enhance or repair some of the person’s abilities.  If you think that something like this cannot exist beyond the pages of a fictional novel, then you are wrong. Technology like this already exists. One example being nanotechnology. This branch of technology has the potential to revolutionise technology as we know it today. In fact, active research is being conducted to figure out how it can be used to revolutionise the field of medicine. Nanobots are robots made of nanomaterials that have the ability to carry out a specific task. Scientists hope to use this technology to travel down the blood-stream and kill malignant cells or deliver drugs to a particular tissue (known as the target tissue). Various other nanotechnological procedures involve insertion of nano-materials or nano-machines into the human body to carry out a certain task. Apart from nanotechnology, we also have the developing fields of neuroscience and neurotechnology. Neuralink is among the pioneers in this field today. Neuralink was set up in 2016 by the celebrated engineer and entrepreneur Elon Musk to develop a device like the ‘neural lace’ from Scottish author Iain M. Banks’ famous sci-fi novel series The Culture. Unlike most contemporary sci-fi novels, this series describes a utopian (and not dystopian) space society. Very recently, Neuralink was in the news for developing a computer chip that can enable paralysed people to move a cursor and type words using their brain. The chip is connected to very thin fibre-like electrodes and the wires are connected to thought transmitters to accomplish the task. Musk labelled this as a first step in the path to ‘symbiosis with artificial intelligence’, something that he believes is necessary for humans to remain relevant in this era of technology. Today, so much in science is an ethics and morality debate and neuro and nanotechnology are no exceptions. It’s easy to see that the ultimate goal is human enhancement. But just because we are capable of doing something, doesn’t necessarily mean that it should be done. We have to delineate what kind of human enhancement should be strived for and what should not be strived for.  On one end of the spectrum, technology like Nueralink’s chips will definitely prove beneficial to those who suffer everyday due to some chronic or fatal disease or some kind of an amputation or genetic disorder. Sufferings due to health issues would cease to exist completely: no disabilities, no depression, zero neuro-diversity and of course, no discrimination on the basis of these. Different companies or universities still do not hire people with heart diseases or cancer today. Such problems would simply vanish. A new world free of bodily pain would be born. We would be able to fulfil our utopian vision of a biologically and socially (to some extent) egalitarian society. While this sounds like the best thing that could possibly happen to us, closer inspection reveals other problems. One of the major issues that humans face today is a huge population. In the past, whenever there was a population boom, some incident or the other, like the Black Plague, brought it under control. Today, with the help of modern medicine, such disasters have been effectively averted. In addition, the life span of humans has increased by a considerable amount in the last few centuries. In a world where humans do not die of diseases or disabilities, this will become a much bigger issue. And once humans are replaced by cyborgs, the amount of time leading up to our doom will only get accelerated. In the past, we have seen how dystopian sci-fi novels have eventually come true, at least to some extent. This includes atom bombs, waterbeds, the nuclear arms race and so on. Most novels involving cyborgs and robots end with these pieces of technology taking up arms against humans and replacing them as the most powerful ‘creatures’ (if I may use this word) on planet Earth. Many companies are currently conducting research to create robots who express emotions like humans or those which can be used as war tools. The future is difficult to predict. But we just cannot ignore the possibility of these novels becoming reality one day if proper regulations and checks are not put in place. Another problem that arises is the problem of unequal distribution of technology. In the largely capitalist parts of the world, the divide between the rich and the poor is enormous. The poor are unable to afford a lot of things that the rich can afford very easily: luxurious housing, expensive sports cars and, of course, plastic surgery. If the availability of neurotechnology to the public ends up being anything like plastic surgery, the rich would exploit it to enhance themselves and eventually modify themselves into an unrecognisable species. All this while the poor would be unable to afford the simplest of technologies to even cure diseases. There will be a new divide, this time between super-humans (or cyborgs) and humans. Even if we consider a scenario where no human is greater or lesser than the other, it raises some very serious problems. Unemployment in Japan is at its peak now. This is because of the fact that too many people are eligible and qualified for a particular job. Japan has an astonishing literacy rate of 99% and a population of 126 million. Both of these contribute to the country’s current condition. In a world of enhanced human beings, everyone would have eidetic memory and equally exceptional logical thinking skills. Everyone would be equally capable of everything. Unfortunately, unless the number of jobs is increased, this would create a very serious problem. Besides unemployment, there would be an equality crisis: employers would find it difficult to choose an employee because everyone would more or less be the same. Culture today is highly dependent on human emotion. The best pieces of art are arguably born out of sadness. Lord Alfred Tennyson wrote In Memoriam after his friend, Arthur Henry Hallam who died of a cerebral haemorrhage in 1833. The Ramayana, one of the greatest Indian epics, was born after Maharishi Valmiki witnessed the sad demise of a bird. Van Gogh is famous because of his depression and the creative expression born out of it. In a world free of pain, sadness, as we know it, would cease to exist and along with it, all the artistic pieces that would have otherwise inspired generations to come. The terms- ‘human’, ‘natural’ and ‘biological’, would no longer have a clear and distinct meaning. For long, humans have wondered where we have come from and where we are headed. Dan Brown, in his novel Origin, explained how humans will eventually be replaced or more accurately evolve into a half-organic, half-artificial species and that would herald a truly utopian world. In spite of all the possible negative consequences, scientists continue to conduct research in this field with an aim to enhance human beings in the near future. Musk’s Neuralink plans on starting human testing very soon. While some believe that cyborg technology is ethical and tests on humans should be carried out at the earliest, many fear a dystopian future instead of the scientist-envisioned utopian one. There are many concerns surrounding human testing too. While proponents of this debate argue that it is a necessity for the greater good, others feel that ‘consent’ from patients who are crippled or terminally ill are born of desperation and cannot be counted as proper consent. At every stage of progress, humans are faced with the dilemma of what is right and wrong. And at every step, humans have successfully taken a decision to preserve mankind. But today, we have come a long way, we have done things that would have been unimaginable a century back, and now, all of humanity is faced with a choice to alter the very thing that qualifies us as humans. However, it is up to us, up to our generation to follow a path that would lead us to a future. And that will determine if we are at all capable of making a right choice and living on.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The NBA Runs Through L.A. - Lakers Team to Beat</title><link href="/Lakers-Team-to-Beat" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The NBA Runs Through L.A. - Lakers Team to Beat" /><published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Lakers-Team-to-Beat</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Lakers-Team-to-Beat">&lt;p&gt;The NBA offseason has definitely been one for the books, with foreseeable trades and signings, as well as history-altering pick-ups. Although the Eastern Conference has seemingly stolen the best player in the league (at least up until the Finals - Kevin Durant) and has teams with potentially perennial talents (Giannis Antetokounmpo or the Joel Embiid/Ben Simmons tandem), the power of the NBA will still mostly reside in the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the departure of Kevin Durant and the dreadful injury to Klay Thompson, the Golden State Warriors have seemingly opened the door to the rest of the Western Conference, despite bolstering their roster in the short-term with the sign-and-trade deal with the Brooklyn Nets for D’Angelo Russell. An argument can be made for several teams in the west to pick up the torch (which can be read in my breakdown articles of each team), however this article will focus on the path the Los Angeles Lakers can follow in order to retake the reins of the NBA, which seems to be more open than it has been for the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the 2018/19 season, the Lakers were able to reel in the talents of Lebron James on a four-year deal, with the hopes of luring in another superstar, such as Kawahi Leonard or Paul George, during the offseason. In the short-term, James was tasked with taking an ill-advised, yet somewhat promising, mix of old and new players to the playoffs for the first time since the 2012/13 season. However, early promise shown by youngsters Lonzo Ball, Kyle Kuzma and Brandon Ingram was not enough to prevent the Lakers from their inevitable doom of not reaching the playoffs yet again, as they were frustrated by key injuries and inconsistent contributions from role players across the rotation, with a groin injury to Lebron James on Christmas night being the heaviest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading into this offseason and free agency, the Lakers were drawing a tremendous amount of attention around the NBA circuit, however none of it was pertaining to their plans to sign another big name. The Lakers were bogged down by issues within the front office and ownership, as well as speculation that James wanted out of Los Angeles. This was all silenced when the trade of Anthony Davis, who was previously written off as a potential trade option given the strong opposition from key members within the New Orleans’ front office, was announced. Shortly afterwards, the Lakers were then in the running for the addition of Kawahi Leonard, which would have arguably assembled the most potent big three the league has ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lakers sacrificed the possible signings of several other role players, such as Josh Reddick, so that they would have the financial capability to sign Leonard while still having wiggle room for next season when Anthony Davis will officially become a free agent. In holding out for Leonard, who they ultimately were unable to sign, several players that would have provided much needed shooting support were signed to other teams. Despite the loss of several potential role pieces, the Lakers were still able to benefit by having several contracts with potential bench pieces in place in case their pursuit of Leonard came up short. The same night that Leonard broke the news that he was heading to the other LA-based organization, the Lakers proceeded with this Plan B, and inked deals with Demarcus Cousins, Danny Green, Quinn Cook, Avery Bradley and Jason Dudley. They also resigned Rajon Rondo, JaVale McGee and Kentavious Caldwell-Pope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a potential starting-five of James and Green at the guards, Kuzma and Davis as forwards, and a rotation of Cousins/McGee at the center, the Lakers could replicate the formidable offensive capabilities that the Warriors have been known for with their various starting five line-ups over the past two seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Hamptons Five Lineup was the most dynamic line-up the league has ever seen, the Lakers have set their team up for better success due to the surrounding support of their bench. This past NBA Finals we saw that despite having a star-studded starting rotation, it is still possible to come up short when it matters (although gruesome season-ending injuries to Thompson and Durant did not help the Warriors’ case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James and Davis are proven entities within the NBA, so the Lakers should be in every game that both players are able to suit up and play in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kuzma is the only bright young spot that was not shipped off to New Orleans during the acquisition of Davis, and he has the potential to become a strong third contributor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green is a proven three-point specialist and will have an instant impact on a Lakers team that struggled to shoot from deep last season (33.3%), despite throwing up an average of 31 3-pointers a night. Green will also provide strong defensive support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGee had a strong first season with the Lakers last season. He averaged 12 points and 7.5 rebounds in 22.3 minutes, appearing in 75 games. With the signing of Demarcus Cousins it is probable that McGee will see less minutes, however it will depend largely on the health and conditioning of Cousins. Cousins was unable to land the large, long-term deal that he had anticipated following a cheap one-year deal with the Warriors this past season, largely due to heavy criticism of his lack of conditioning in the back half of the season, as well as the Finals. If Cousins comes to opening night in good shape, he should receive the bulk of minutes at the center position, as he has the potential for a huge bounce-back season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acquisitions of Dudley and Bradley are extremely intriguing, as both have proven their worth in the NBA but neither are more than bodies off the bench. Cook is an interesting back-up guard that has played many minutes as a back-up to Stephen Curry, and Rondo has been a proven dimer since his time in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the NBA Finals it would have been crazy to think that the Lakers would be in the position they are in now. The long-term success of the Lakers is dependent on the health status of James, Davis and Cousins, as well as getting consistent contributions from the bench. If both boxes are checked come the end of the season, and the Lakers head into the playoffs at full health, they will be the toughest team to beat, and should come out of the West on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gavin Olson</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="basketball" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">The NBA offseason has definitely been one for the books, with foreseeable trades and signings, as well as history-altering pick-ups. Although the Eastern Conference has seemingly stolen the best player in the league (at least up until the Finals - Kevin Durant) and has teams with potentially perennial talents (Giannis Antetokounmpo or the Joel Embiid/Ben Simmons tandem), the power of the NBA will still mostly reside in the Western Conference.</summary></entry></feed>