<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-26T18:38:54+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Norway: The Perfect Economy?</title><link href="/The-Perfect-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Norway: The Perfect Economy?" /><published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Perfect-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Perfect-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Norway is a wonderful country that has time and time again been used as the poster child for a socialist-capitalist mixed economy done right. Norway has several times been compared to that child in our school who is absolutely tremendous at each and everything. The country boasts a GDP per capita of $81,995, one of the highest in the world, only falling behind Switzerland and a select group of micronations. The country has a robust trade surplus, exports of $106 billion, compared to imports of $84.8 billion, one of the highest national life expectancies at 81.8 years, an extremely skilled workforce with one of the highest proportion of university graduates at 42% of any country in the world, an extremely low unemployment rate of 0.41%, and international recognition as a place where it is very easy to do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is more remarkable is that Norway has achieved this while also being one of the most economically equal countries in the world. After taxes, a single individual from the bottom 20% of the income earners in Norway still earns on average a quarter of what their top 20% income earners would. Now, this still sounds pretty unfair but compared to the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) average which has top one-fifth earners making an income ten times that of their bottom one-fifth counterparts, this disparity is remarkable. The good news keeps on coming considering working conditions. Norway has workers protections which are commendable, meaning that social issues like working extremely long hours and people needing second jobs to support themselves are very rare. In fact, the OECD better life index notes that only 3% of employees work long hours when compared to the OECD average of 11% or the American average of 33%. All of this contributes to the citizens of Norway being some of the happiest in the entire world despite their country being extremely cold. Norway, by all standards, should be the model that most citizens would want to replicate in their own countries. So why haven’t other countries adopted similar economic policies to those in Norway? Is this country just a lucky outlier or could this success be replicated in other economies around the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that Norway wasn’t always this prosperous. In the 1960’s, it was an economy mainly based on fishing with a GDP similar in size to underdeveloped countries like Bangladesh or Nigeria. Now, in all fairness, Norway’s population was and still is far smaller than these other countries and the average Norwegian back then had a quality of life similar to a person in Spain or Greece. But Norway in the 1960’s was still far out from the economic powerhouse it is today. This all started to change in May of 1963 when the Norwegian government asserted sovereign rights over natural resources in a huge area of the North Sea. This was basically the government saying that this part of the ocean is ours now. If we happen to find any oil here that is ours too. Six years later, in 1969, a ship called the &lt;em&gt;Ocean Viking&lt;/em&gt; struck oil in the North Sea, and from that oil production in the region exploded. This meant that in the mid-1970’s Norway produced more oil per capita than any other country in the world and even today it is only beaten out by Kuwait, UAE, and Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know what you are thinking, but this is not a story about another country that just got rich off oil and now everybody in the country is living like a child handed with a rack of money. It is actually the opposite. Rather than getting drunk off the oil wealth that they had discovered; the Norwegian government was very prudent with the revenue from these finite resources. The oil boom caused Norway’s GDP to grow over five times in the 1970’s growing from $12 billion to $65 billion in this period. But this newfound wealth was not being generated by private companies but rather a publicly run and owned company called &lt;em&gt;Statoil&lt;/em&gt;. All this meant that profits from oil and natural gas sales were not going to the pockets of private shareholders but rather directly to the government. This made the Norwegian government immensely rich meaning that if they wanted, they could have easily gone on a public spending spree, building fancy cities and public infrastructure while also reducing taxes just like many of the countries have done in a similar position. This kind of an approach would have been very popular among citizens because in short term it meant lower taxes and a better quality of life but they didn’t, and even today income and business taxes in Norway are among some of the highest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for Norway, the government had the foresight to realise that oil wealth was not forever and that the citizens of Norway would not be satisfied if they had to go back to fishing in a generations time so the government invested the money into a piggy bank, a very large piggy bank called a ‘sovereign wealth fund’, in fact, this is the largest sovereign wealth fund in the world at $1.002 trillion beating out China’s state investment corporation. This is a fund that belongs to the people of Norway. The rationale is that this oil and these natural resources were originally the property of the Norwegian people and so it is they who should receive from the sale of these resources. This means that every man, woman, and child, who is a citizen of Norway essentially has around $200,000 invested into what is a giant hedge fund. This money is unfortunately not accessible by these citizens to spend on gold plated Ferraris or yachts. The money itself is actually not even accessible to the Norwegian government. In fact, only the profit generated from these investments is used to fund things like education, which explains the very skilled workforce, a very strong welfare system, public infrastructure, and reinvestment into the fund itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, the fund made an incredible $131 billion from investments. This fund is a very diverse portfolio of stocks, bonds, cash, and commodities but what it does invest in is not nearly as interesting as what it does not invest in. The Norwegian government set up an ethical council that oversees investing decisions of all of the fund and it has excluded investing in things like weapons manufacturers, tobacco and alcohol companies, and companies that have caused severe environmental damage or companies that have breached workers rights and labour laws. Additionally, in an effort to diversify where they get their money from, the fund is also forbidden to invest in fossil energy companies. This means that all the investments in this fund are actually in foreign countries’ securities and commodities. Now, despite the massive political power this gives Norway to influence foreign companies, it also means that the fund’s performance is absolutely independent of the situation prevailing in the Norwegian economy. The fund was a fantastic piece of thoughtfulness by the Norwegian government and practically means that Norway is now the national equivalent of the guy that wins the lottery, keeps his day job, and invests the lottery money in a stock portfolio. It certainly is not as cool and it does not get as much attention as blowing all of the money on extravagant displays of wealth, but it does mean that they will be safe and secure for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish it up, it is only fair to look at some of the economic issues that are present in Norway. First and foremost is that it still has an incredibly high cost of living compared to wages. Given the very high taxes, an average Norwegian worker is bringing home about $3,200 a month which is far higher than the American average of $2,730 per month. However, it does not make a considerable difference because Norway is an expensive place. A mid-range restaurant meal in America tends to run about $50, in Norway, it is about $92. A monthly utility bill in the US is expected to be around $130 whereas that same bill in Norway is $176. But the citizens of Norway almost universally agree that they are happy to put up with these high taxes and this incredibly high cost of living because in return they do not have to worry about serious economic hardships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody in Norway is going to go bankrupt because of a medical situation, nobody has to worry about drowning in crippling debt to get an education and they do not have to fear being homeless if they lose their jobs. So, the million-dollar question arises - is Norway really the perfect economy? Well no, not really. Norway is a great example of a planned social-democratic economic system. They have done everything right with the opportunities that have come their way but they were still extremely lucky, and expecting that every country can get to where Norway is today only by copying and pasting their government’s financial policies is absurd but that said I still think Norway is the economy closest to achieve perfection if they haven’t already.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Norway is a wonderful country that has time and time again been used as the poster child for a socialist-capitalist mixed economy done right. Norway has several times been compared to that child in our school who is absolutely tremendous at each and everything. The country boasts a GDP per capita of $81,995, one of the highest in the world, only falling behind Switzerland and a select group of micronations. The country has a robust trade surplus, exports of $106 billion, compared to imports of $84.8 billion, one of the highest national life expectancies at 81.8 years, an extremely skilled workforce with one of the highest proportion of university graduates at 42% of any country in the world, an extremely low unemployment rate of 0.41%, and international recognition as a place where it is very easy to do business.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The IPL Business and the Sponsorship Conundrum</title><link href="/IPL-Sponsorship-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The IPL Business and the Sponsorship Conundrum" /><published>2020-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/IPL-Sponsorship-Conundrum</id><content type="html" xml:base="/IPL-Sponsorship-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;Sports fans comprise one of the most passionate and powerful demographics in the world. From companies like Barilla, to the more well-known ones like Budweiser, all brands consistently bring their A-game to sports sponsorship activities. Sponsors are finding clever ways to bring fans closer to the game, the athletes, and thereby, to their brand. The sponsorship of events represents a significant and growing component of a firm’s overall investment in marketing and promotions. While the marketing literature suggests that sponsorships may be a potential communication tool, relatively little empirical research has been devoted to studying efficiency issues in sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coca-Cola and the Olympics, Rolex and the TED, and PepsiCo and NFL are some of the many long-standing sponsorships that have caught our eyes, have been stuck in our brains, and have managed to hire us as free mouths for applause. In the most memorable episode, during the 1992 Barcelona Olympics, sponsorship was used to fuel comparative advertising campaigns. VISA’s tagline was ‘The Olympics don’t take American Express’, with images of ticket windows being slammed shut in the faces of American Express cardholders. The $20 million that they had paid to the International Olympic Committee (IOC) for their official sponsorship ensured that they received no complaints about the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, American Express responded with more style, pointing out in its own advertisement campaigns that ‘To visit Spain, you don’t need a Visa’. Before UNICEF tied hands with football club Barcelona, it was just a Catalonian football club, but soon after, the football giant became the world’s favourite football club alongside UNICEF as ‘More than a club’. Nike’s close call with Michael Jordan in a commercial &lt;em&gt;“I’ve missed more than 9000 shots in my career….”&lt;/em&gt;, changed the brand forever. The sporting fraternity has seen it all, right from Coca-Cola’s  ‘Taste the feeling’  campaign during the Rio Olympic Games of 2016 with the #thatsgold campaign, to the Arsenal player Nicklas Bendtner proudly lowering his shorts while showcasing his underpants branded with Irish bookmaker Paddy Power’s logo when millions of spectators were glued to their TV sets. Sports has had a love affair with grandstanding sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months down the line Indian cricketers will compete with each other to prove their dominance and for this, they’ll take help from the foreigners too. This will take place as a festival of sorts. People will support their states instead of the country. And, we’ll get to witness a distorted form of the &lt;em&gt;‘Gentleman’s Game’&lt;/em&gt; in the form of an extravaganza. The Indian Premier League (IPL) is set to host its 13th edition in the United Arab Emirates (UAE) this year and the talks around sponsorships have already fuelled. The BCCI and the IPL make money via the auction of broadcasting rights, title and corporate sponsorship, ticket sales, auction of franchise rights, and official umpire sponsorship. Though the IPL has produced ghastly match-fixing incidents, terrible fights among cricketers on the field, mass level gambling, and whatnot, people can be seen binge-watching matches on their phone and simultaneously speculating the outcomes during the 42-day long tournament. Just like the IPL, the history of IPL’s title sponsorship is also muddled with a bit of controversy, confusion and drama. Besides this, the economics of IPL churns in millions and billions of rupees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2008, DLF, India’s largest real estate company, paid a hefty sum of ₹2 billion (around $36.25 million), to own the title rights for the first five years of the tournament. However, after the given period, DLF decided not to renew its contract. This forced Board of Control for Cricket in India (BCCI) to issue a new tender, with a base price of ₹3 billion. In 2013, PepsiCo was the new title sponsor until 2015 when it chose to terminate its contract amid rising concerns of match-fixing, and irregular and untimely blemishes on the face of the IPL. VIVO, the Chinese smartphone company was then roped in for the 2016 and 2017 season. The BCCI had a fresh deal with VIVO in 2018 that saw them earn ₹4.40 billion every year, but the Indo-China face-off across the Line of Actual Control (LAC) as well as the negative publicity of the smartphone brand, has forced VIVO to withdraw its name as IPL sponsor this season. Though VIVO will no longer be a sponsor this year, it has only sought for a one-year moratorium, keeping the door open for a 2021 return. So, the BCCI is in an eager search to find a new short-term replacement sponsor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst the rising cries and steadfast support for home-grown brands, it has been understood that e-commerce companies as well as educational e-portals are keen to get the IPL sponsorship. Others in the race include Patanjali Ayurveda and Jio, besides e-learning platforms Byju’s and Unacademy, and fantasy sports firm Dream11. Though 5 companies have given their Expression of Interest (EOI), Tata Sons are likely to win the race hands down against the others on the back of not only money power but also because of being the biggest home-grown brand. The homegrown FMCG brand, Patanjali was the first brand in the country to openly declare that they would be bidding for the title sponsorship of the IPL but the loudest of the suitors seems to have chickened out. Despite  Patanjali’s antics, the BCCI need not worry as the IPL 2020 is set to get a helping hand from one of the biggest and the most credible business houses of the country. It’s unsure, given the current scenario and sudden exit of VIVO, that the final bid would be anywhere close to what VIVO was offering but it will be interesting to see to what extent the BCCI will manage to cut its losses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, the brand value of IPL stood at $6.8 billion in 2019 up 7% from 2018, according to consultancy firm Duff and Phelps. It is not clear what model the consultants have used to calculate gross value added from the cricketing extravaganza, and a lot depends on this, but cricket administrators have done well to commission such a study. There is a broader lesson here. The contribution of IPL is currently just a drop in the $3 trillion Indian economy, around 0.2%. One can assume from this fact that sports are still a very small part of the economy. Informal studies show that most rich nations have around 1.5-2% of their GDP coming from sports. Indian sports have a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key question which is worthy of consideration is how do you calculate the Return on Investment (ROI) of sponsorship? It is probably the initiative that has the highest budget commitment, so it’s extremely important to ensure that the marketing dollars spent on sponsorship can be traced. There is no Bloomberg Terminal or NASDAQ exchange to provide external benchmarks of the value of sponsorship assets. And there are few accounting standards or valuation models that brands can use to determine the fair financial value of a team, stadium or athlete. There are a few ways to calculate ROI for sponsorship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. By taking into account the change in a brand’s share of ‘voice’ before and after the sports tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. By measuring buyers’ purchase intent using tools like digital surveys or social media audits. Especially if a brand deals in high-value products and purchases such as automobiles, IPL sponsorships cannot immediately skyrocket their sales since generally, a large investment is needed for it. Of course, inquiries can go up, but an immediate ROI would not represent an accurate picture. Purchase intent surveys can help to understand the effectiveness of sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very hard to measure the financial value of sponsorship investments. Chief Finacial Officers (CFOs) fairly argue that they lack the financial vocabulary and Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) to properly measure these complex investments that require a blend of art, science and commercialism to execute. The bigger issue marketers face as they defend their multi-million-dollar sponsorship budgets is that they fail to quantify and communicate how these investments create financial value beyond their equivalent media value. Until these problems are solved, CFOs will continue to treat sponsorship as a discretionary expense rather than a growth asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, the whole of India looks forward to seeing their beloved soap-opera that brings all the emotions on the table. Love, joy, happiness, tears, laughter, sadness, and lots of deceit and intrigue. The white ball going against the night sky like it’s a meteor headed somewhere, bits and pieces of outlandish stump mic conversations, embellished commentary voices, and glitzy song and dance will be a feast to watch. Now attach to it the dollars it deals in, it’s all the way more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mehul Goyal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Sports fans comprise one of the most passionate and powerful demographics in the world. From companies like Barilla, to the more well-known ones like Budweiser, all brands consistently bring their A-game to sports sponsorship activities. Sponsors are finding clever ways to bring fans closer to the game, the athletes, and thereby, to their brand. The sponsorship of events represents a significant and growing component of a firm’s overall investment in marketing and promotions. While the marketing literature suggests that sponsorships may be a potential communication tool, relatively little empirical research has been devoted to studying efficiency issues in sponsorships.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buying Under Influence</title><link href="/Buying-Under-Influence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buying Under Influence" /><published>2020-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Buying-Under-Influence</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Buying-Under-Influence">&lt;p&gt;How many of us have purchased a product simply because it looked pretty in a photo on Instagram? Or maybe some lifestyle blogger mentioned it in their &lt;em&gt;‘August’s Favourites’&lt;/em&gt; video? With the increase in the use of social media, users are daily bombarded with a plethora of content. To avoid getting lost in the sea of information, it is becoming quintessential for the brands to grab the attention of their potential customers by identifying the most relevant and meaningful content. To do so, brands have to constantly think of novel ways to market their products. Accordingly, they have started to increasingly dip their feet in influencer marketing, thereby making the influencers a huge part of their marketing mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Influencer marketing has reinvented the concept of celebrity endorsement, by tapping online influencers for contemporary and content-driven marketing campaigns. With 80% of marketers using influencer marketing, it has become the fastest-growing category within the realm of marketing. The spending in the field is estimated to reach $8 billion this year. According to a 2018 survey conducted by CivicScience, a consumer intelligence research platform, 19% of the American consumers purchased a product or service because a social media influencer recommended it. To successfully generate sales conversions, a brand needs to look for the perfect influencer, the one whose content aligns with the brand’s ideologies, allowing it to target a consumer base that also echoes and understands the brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the surface, influencer-driven marketing offers unique advantages to the brands, which have led to an increase in their demand. Endorsements by influencers are not created as traditional advertisements but, as recommendations, attaching authenticity to them. Additionally, a large audience of followers fosters a belief that the influencer is likeable and popular, and thus, the brand can benefit from their social capital by targeting a large consumer base. The content continues to be picked up during Search Engine Optimisation (SEO) searches, even after the campaign is over, creating a significant long-tail effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, on poking deeper into the issue, various disadvantages have also started coming to light. While the large audience and reach of the influencer are the biggest selling points, however, many are paying people to get fake followers on their social media accounts. This option is becoming increasingly accessible due to its low cost. Social King, a Delhi-based marketing agency offers 100 followers for ₹255 ($3.99). In fact, the Mumbai Police has identified an additional 100 websites in India known to sell ghost followers. However, a large follower count doesn’t necessarily mean that the quality of the content created will be up to the mark and lead to successful conversions. Secondarily, it has been found that an increased follower count, that has been generated by bots leads to a decrease in the engagement, making the Click Through Rate (CTR) fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To bypass the issue of fake followers, brands started paying influencers based on the performance of their posts, assuming a direct correlation between the quality of content and the engagement on the posts. However, this led to the creation of a market for likes and comments, as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of a campaign is contingent on metrics like trending and views. However, when these numbers can be skewed by spending little money, it becomes tough to analyse the actual reach. To prevent artificial inflation of followers and engagement, Jim Tobin, President of Carusele, a marketing agency based out of North Carolina suggests implementing flat-fee compensation or sales-based compensation models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, advertisers tend to run after the same top influencers to partner with them. While this guarantees the quality and reach, the overexposure of paid content for various brands soon leads to saturation, harming the influencers’ following. This is because people follow influencers to keep up with trends and to find inspiration. As a result, if their feed is advertisement dominant, their influence is most likely to plunge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, with it being a novel industry, influencer marketing lacks standard industry practices and regulations. For example, the lack of pricing and measurement standards, and the absence of contracts between agencies and influencers. Generally, small scale operators lack the resources to do the paperwork, failing to sign contracts with influencers. On the flip side, there are also instances of big brands getting small influencers on board, misleading them to sign void/voidable contracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also strong evidence of an ethnicity wage gap wherein the Black, Asian, and Middle Eastern influencers are being paid significantly lesser as compared to their White counterparts. Such wage gaps also exist along the intersections of age, disability, religion, and sexual orientation. Not only are the opportunities available for them far too low, but they are at a double disadvantage in monetary terms too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To release itself from the spiral of doom, influencer marketing needs to reinvent itself by putting in good practices in place. The first becomes a standardised model for pricing and compensation. Second, to formalise the system by putting legal contracts in place. Third, brands must shift their focus from the number of followers or attractive content to the rate of audience engagement, the demographic of the influencers’ followers, the purchasing habits of the followers, and the influence of the influencer to drive sales. It’s not all about reach, but about relevance, resonance and real impact. To this end, harnessing the untapped potential of ‘micro-influencers’ has been known to garner better results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micro-influencers are people who have a more loyal and active follower base, despite a low number of followers. The increased influence is driven by the expertise and specific interest for a particular topic. What distinguishes these micro-influencers from social media celebrities is the personal touch and relationships they have established with their followers. According to a study conducted by Dr Jonah Berger, a marketing professor at the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, micro-influencers have up to 22.2 times more sales conversions each week than an average consumer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the category of influencer marketing adds much value to a brand’s marketing mix, without continuous iteration, it will become tougher for the brands to harness the model to its full potential. The power in the industry lies primarily in the hands of the brands, agencies, and platforms that content curators work with. Thus, both parties need to meet at the negotiation table to develop practices that will lead to a win-win situation for all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">How many of us have purchased a product simply because it looked pretty in a photo on Instagram? Or maybe some lifestyle blogger mentioned it in their ‘August’s Favourites’ video? With the increase in the use of social media, users are daily bombarded with a plethora of content. To avoid getting lost in the sea of information, it is becoming quintessential for the brands to grab the attention of their potential customers by identifying the most relevant and meaningful content. To do so, brands have to constantly think of novel ways to market their products. Accordingly, they have started to increasingly dip their feet in influencer marketing, thereby making the influencers a huge part of their marketing mix.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Narrating The Plodding South-African Economy</title><link href="/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Narrating The Plodding South-African Economy" /><published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy">&lt;p&gt;The second-largest producer of gold in the world is in dire need of its sluggish economic growth to be narrated and analysed. Along with gold, diamond and platinum are the top three exports of South Africa, it is the largest producer of chrome, manganese, platinum, vanadium, and vermiculite; second largest producer of ilmenite, palladium, rutile and zirconium, and most significantly, it is the world’s third-largest exporter of coal. Despite being a king-pin in precious gemstones and minerals, three in every four South Africans live with a constant threat of poverty taking over their daily lives. The most industrialised country of the African continent has not expanded by more than 2.5% a year since 2013, with nearly 50% of the South African population living in the state of poverty. Astoundingly, the swamp isn’t a decade old but has been impending for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Struggling with a mere growth rate of 1.1% per year, the economy cannot absorb the rapidly growing population, leading to a higher rate of deprivation among the people. The cyclical tools which are veiled in monetary and fiscal policies cannot break down the encumbrances of structural weaknesses in the economy. To begin with, even after showcasing improvement, the household saving rate in South Africa is a meagre 0.2% (as per the fourth quarter of 2017). Why is the saving rate a matter of significance? Well, it is the savings that generate capital for investment spending, with no space for investment, the economy can never accelerate due to the lagging infrastructure that has the potential for future growth and provision of high returns to the Gross Domestic Product (GDP). The present rate of household savings is utterly unfavourable when compared to other emerging market countries which usually maintain a rate above 2% and invest rigorously in infrastructural development along with measures to generate and expand the capacity for new capital, unlike the African country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education, the pavement to advancement, has continued to be an issue of concern for South Africa as it was ranked the 75th nation out of 76 in the ‘Table of Education Systems’ drawn by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). The fourth industrial revolution hovers over the globe and calls for a skilled workforce, which has been a clear lag for the African country, the paucity of a skilled workforce arising out of an underdeveloped education system has been ranked as the third-most problematic factor for doing business in South Africa. Revamping the educational structure and enhancing its delivery should be the top-notch priority while restructuring the government policies in order to escalate economic progress, standard of living, ease of doing business, and to attract global as well as domestic investors. The smooth functioning of small and medium-sized enterprises in a developing nation is as cardinal as education to eradicate unemployment and foster a healthy living index. Government bureaucracy, heavy tax burden, and constrictive labour regulations are few of the many unnecessary curtailments for the small and medium enterprises (SMEs). The state-owned enterprises, deployed to generate utility for the public have been relocated to cushion the coffers of a selected few. The public enterprises have capitulated to inefficiency, mismanagement of revenue, bureaucratic lapses, tender rigging, delay in project delivery. This has resulted in a distorted infrastructure, scanty services, and has robbed the national treasure of billions in terms of opportunity cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How disinteresting has it been for the investors? Well, South Africa was ranked 82 out of 190 countries in the ‘Ease of Doing Business Index’ drawn by the World Bank in 2017. It might seem impressive to find a country with numerous economic and financial blemishes to find a spot in the middle of the Index, but the 32nd rank in 2008 is an epiphany to the swift fall. The plethora of monetary policies that have been put into effect will remain ineffective if the grass-root structure of the economic administration is not revamped and paralleled with the fast-paced world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering its 70th month of a downward cycle, the longest since 1945, the economy is stuck in a mire, with rescue looking like a far-fetched dream. A surfeit of sectors felt the tremors of the contracting economy but manufacturing, mining and trade, catering and accommodation, agriculture, and the power sector have been the worst hit. Experts are of the view that low demand, sharp rising fuel prices, and Eskom’s load shedding are the prime factors contributing to the contraction of the economy. Eskom is amongst the top twenty power utilities worldwide, it generates more than 90% of South Africa’s power and 40% of the electricity in the African continent. The surging salary, fuel, and debt-servicing costs along with mismanagement and corruption scandals have led to Eskom having a $30 billion debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of ambitious economic programmes accompanied by the coronavirus pandemic will deepen the crack in the economy. As the nation is in a state of lockdown, hue and cry amongst the public with a lack of essentials and power cuts have worsened the strain on the government. South Africa was one of the few nations to implement the most draconian containment measures to curb the spread of the virus, with an already dwindling economy, a complete shutdown of all the major industries has piled up the heap of debts for the administration. A failure in the political atmosphere, inefficiency of the government to deliver to the public instead of stocking up their coffers, and inviting projects with vested interests have continued to cause a haemorrhage with no defined antidote to the South African economy. Revival seems like a mere dream when the present trends of a global slowdown are observed, the various developed nations which were key importers of the South African minerals and precious gems have curtailed their imports, leaving South Africa with a depleting repository. Failing to engage investors, the government continues to borrow in order to repay its already mounting debts, the matter of concern still remains a part of the vicious cycle as no monetary policy or financial injections can break down the persisting swamp which has driven half of South Africa into poverty.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The second-largest producer of gold in the world is in dire need of its sluggish economic growth to be narrated and analysed. Along with gold, diamond and platinum are the top three exports of South Africa, it is the largest producer of chrome, manganese, platinum, vanadium, and vermiculite; second largest producer of ilmenite, palladium, rutile and zirconium, and most significantly, it is the world’s third-largest exporter of coal. Despite being a king-pin in precious gemstones and minerals, three in every four South Africans live with a constant threat of poverty taking over their daily lives. The most industrialised country of the African continent has not expanded by more than 2.5% a year since 2013, with nearly 50% of the South African population living in the state of poverty. Astoundingly, the swamp isn’t a decade old but has been impending for decades.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Against a Liberal Anti-racism</title><link href="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Against a Liberal Anti-racism" /><published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism">&lt;p&gt;The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s &lt;em&gt;White Fragility&lt;/em&gt;, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DiAngelo’s central premise, that white Americans must reckon with their own implicit biases and engage in rigorous introspection to remedy them, appears less of a repudiation of centuries-old institutional racism than it does an instructional manual for white liberals working in corporate jobs to avoid getting into trouble with HR. It characterises racism merely as an antipathy felt by individuals towards other individuals, leaving untouched the edifice of America’s racist socio-economic structure. It fails to acknowledge that white supremacy is not simply the supremacy of white over black, but also the supremacy of rich whites over poorer whites who can be trusted to vote themselves into economic ruin in return for the illusion of superiority. And even more egregiously, it focuses attention on the self-aggrandising antics of the white liberal, repackaging the fight against racism as a culture war between educated white liberals and less educated whites, many of whom do not view themselves as the beneficiaries of ‘privilege’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the first Africans arrived in Virginia in 1619, there were no ‘white’ people there. It would be another 60 years before colonial records would describe the settlers as ‘white’, as the idea of the ‘white’ race was deliberately constructed by the ruling class as a form of social control, dividing poor European indentured servants and African chattel-bond labourers, assimilating the Europeans into the ‘middle class’, and preventing the likelihood of the reemergence of an event such as Bacon’s Rebellion (1676). Europeans and Africans had jointly demanded the imposition of a land tax and Virginia’s transition from a large plantation economy to a diversified economy of small freeholders, chasing the planter bourgeoisie to the shore and burning Jamestown to the ground. Ira Berlin stated that in the aftermath of Bacon’s Rebellion &lt;em&gt;“they enact laws which say that people of African descent are hereditary slaves. And they increasingly give some power to the independent white farmers and land holders”&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, rather than being simply a form of prejudice on the basis of skin colour, racism can be understood as a complex form of social control. Theodore W Allen’s book &lt;em&gt;The Invention of the White Race&lt;/em&gt; made a similar argument that racism is a “sociogenic” rather than a “phylogenic” phenomenon, analysing how the (phenotypically similar) British used racial oppression against Irish Catholics, later allowing the Irish Catholic bourgeoisie to assimilate into the oppressive structure, accepting the disenfranchisement of the forty-shilling freeholders in return for meagre ‘emancipation’ in 1829.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, liberal anti-racism of the DiAngelo variety, largely devoid of this analysis, becomes an exercise in narcissistic self-indulgence on the part of white liberals, who reframe discussions about race in terms of how they can be better people, and how it is incumbent on all whites to unlearn their white privilege. As this approach to anti-racism fails to acknowledge how racism functions as a tool of socioeconomic disenfranchisement by the ruling class, it assumes that all whites benefit equally from white privilege, ignoring and minimising the plight of working-class whites. A 2019 sociological study by E Cooley, etc. found that learning about white privilege did nothing to increase empathy for people of colour among white liberals, but simply made them less likely to empathise with poorer whites, placing greater personal blame on them on the basis that their privilege outweighed other social factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, reactionary and racist ideology abounds among the white working class, and this article is not intended to downplay such attitudes or pretend that they do not exist. It is to argue that if there is a hope that cross-racial solidarity can be achieved, and these reactionary tendencies extinguished, it will not be accomplished by lecturing working-class whites who are beset by low wages, deindustrialisation, and the opioid epidemic about their ‘privilege’, but by encouraging them to recognise that they have more in common with other races than with elites of the same race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘class reductionist’ is consistently deployed against socialists who recognise that racism and capitalism are intimately connected as if this recognition downplays the significance of racism. But some of the most pernicious forms of American institutional racism, such as redlining and the prison-industrial complex, have explicitly capitalistic imperatives. For example, exclusion from ‘prime’ credit has forced black communities to secure housing through subprime loans and substandard rental accommodation. During the subprime lending boom, predatory loans were five times more likely to be made in black neighbourhoods than in white neighbourhoods, while black Americans were four times as likely as white Americans to be denied loans from the Bank of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations such as the Blackstone Group have conspired to engage in predatory lending practices, buying up houses at cheap prices and selling them on for higher prices or charging exorbitant rents. Invitation Homes, a subsidiary of the Blackstone Group and a prominent lender to black communities, may have broken laws to give tenants loans that maximised profits as they could easily outbid first time buyers. It is issues such as these, the pervasive, material disparities which have concentrated generational wealth in the hands of white communities and generational disadvantage in the hands of black communities that should be the focus of anti-racists, not trivial ideas such as ‘white fragility’. These are not injustices that can be solved simply by more representation of black people within the highest echelons of power, but only through the de-privatisation and de-commodification of housing at a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of viewing racism through a reductive, individualistic lens is the over-medicalisation of the problem, which treats racism as a pathology on the part of its perpetrators. As Kenan Malik writes, &lt;em&gt;“It was not unconscious bias that made a police officer place his knee on George Floyd’s neck”&lt;/em&gt;. A meta-analysis of nearly 500 studies found that unconscious bias training only had a “weak” effect on the behaviour of individuals. Reframing racism as a product of original sin, an aberration that could never be held by ‘normal’ people simply absolves those who are responsible for perpetuating it, as racial bigotry can, and often is, the product of a sound mind. The Nazi war criminals at Nuremberg, for instance, all tested as medically sane, had high IQs, and included a disproportionate number of PhDs. Far from being the irrational judgement of an insane mind, racism is the mendacious, calculated judgement of the elites who perpetuate it, to provide a constant stream of alienated unfree labour from those they impoverish, to divide and conquer and to subjugate. Only an approach that acknowledges the systemic and institutional manifestations of racism can grasp this central point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systemic racism on which the United States was founded, that still exists today, cannot be expunged with ‘unconscious bias training’ or the recognition of white fragility. The injustices will remain, but white corporate consultants such as Robin DiAngelo will become very rich. What is required is not white guilt but white solidarity on a mass scale, such as has been seen in the recent protests, and a recognition that, as Karl Marx stated, &lt;em&gt;“Labour in the white skin cannot emancipate itself where in the black it is branded.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s White Fragility, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Free Market Conundrum</title><link href="/The-Free-Market-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Free Market Conundrum" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Free-Market-Conundrum</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Free-Market-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;The 1980’s was an important era in the history of economics and the world. With the election of President Ronald Regan in the United States and Baroness Thatcher of Kesteven as Prime in the United Kingdom, economic policies in the West underwent a major overhaul. Subsequently, international institutions made these policies a prerequisite for granting loans to the countries that were on the brink of bankruptcy. The policies that I am talking about are the neo-liberal economic policies, and the framework they are built upon is the fundamental assumption of the efficiency of free markets. Every undergraduate economics student is taught that leaving markets to function without any intervention by the State will accrue benefits to the society as a whole. This article is an attempt to look at why free markets are not so free and why they do not always lead to the best of outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every transaction takes place with an implicit assumption that the other party will uphold their end of the bargain. If that does not happen, they are likely to approach the police or courts for justice. This tells us that to function freely, markets depend on some rules and regulations. The rhetoric around the free markets often fails to appreciate these rules because they are taken for granted. In fact, for the markets to function, property rights need to be clearly defined and enforceable. Therefore, it is absolutely correct to say that government laws, rules and regulations create scope for the markets to function and form the basis that drives competition. Then there are patents. Though there are strong arguments as to the requirement of such laws in place, they themselves act as obstacles to market freedom. Patents can lead to situations where the goods are out of reach of those who value (value here is not in terms of the amount paid but in terms of necessity) them the most. &lt;em&gt;Gleevac&lt;/em&gt;, a leukaemia drug, is a case in point. The cost of this drug in the US is $70,000 since Novartis, the company that manufactures the drug has a patent in the US. Thanks to the refusal of the Supreme Court of India to grant a patent, it is available for $2,500 in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem with free markets is that of ‘asymmetric information’. Asymmetric information arises when one party (typically the seller) possesses more information or knowledge about goods or services being sold. One common example that you will come across is about how the buyers of health insurance have an incentive to conceal their health information to get a better insurance deal. This example portrays how the sellers are at a loss. But today, you see almost every insurance company has a physician only from whom you are allowed to take a medical checkup. For a more general example, consider a clothes shop or a tech gadget shop. Old stock is prominently displayed so as to dispose of the stock and in such situations, the seller has more information than the buyer. Of course, there are resources available today that help bridge the information gap, but still the problem is more commonplace than we all think. The economic theory treats this asymmetry of information as an anomaly — one of the three instances of market failure. What it fails to recognise is that this phenomenon is not an exception, but a ubiquitous conundrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inherent characteristic of the free markets, that has hardly ever been a part of the public discourse, is that they are indifferent to human needs and provide only those goods and services that are profitable. Take, for example, the case of Google. Over the years the search engine giant has altered its webpage to show pre-packaged information when we search for something, rather than sending traffic to other websites. This may not affect you or me directly; but will result in the loss of customers to many businesses, whose business models rely on Google sending traffic to their websites. Another example is the pharmaceutical industry. During the initial stages in the coronavirus outbreak in February 2020, Rolf Hilgenfeld, a structural biologist, told the scientific journal &lt;em&gt;Nature, “The total number of people infected, if you combine SARS, MERS [previous related coronavirus outbreaks] and this new virus, is under 12,500 people. That’s not a market. The number of cases is too small. Pharmaceutical companies are not interested”&lt;/em&gt;. Though the trails for a vaccine are underway, one cannot miss the larger point. One more example is the Indian realty market. Despite the requirement of an additional 20 million houses, there is no sign of falling housing prices. This is partly because the developers prevent a fall in price in anticipation of a boost in demand in the future. Sometimes, by delaying construction, they demand higher amounts from the buyers to complete the construction. The end result is, despite a huge population without their own houses and large inventories held by realtors, the market is unable to satisfy the needs of the end-users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time, you might have come to the conclusion that I am a communist; I am not. What I am trying to get across is that while free markets benefit society in many ways, there are also many faults associated with free markets. Even as free markets provide what most people want, they will deceive, manipulate, and tempt us into buying things that might be harmful to us. Renowned economists George Akerlof and Robert Shiller said, &lt;em&gt;“Markets are not benign forces working for the greater good but instead are filled with businesses that ‘phish’ by exploiting our weaknesses to get us to buy their products”&lt;/em&gt;. From the 1980’s, in many countries across the world, the role of the state was cut down, paving ways for the ‘free markets’ to operate. There has been little debate about the flaws in the free market system and economists fail to acknowledge the problem. The failure in understanding the markets will only result in the formulation of bad policies. The failure to rectify the existing problems will tilt the markets to work in favour of a few and will result in wide sections of society being worse off. The capitalist system works well not just because there are free markets but also because there are a wide range of institutional arrangements that act as checks and balances on these markets. It is important to recognise that the state plays as important a role as the markets to bring the economy to equilibrium. Finally, there is nothing wrong with wanting free markets; but to think that they can’t go wrong is a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The 1980’s was an important era in the history of economics and the world. With the election of President Ronald Regan in the United States and Baroness Thatcher of Kesteven as Prime in the United Kingdom, economic policies in the West underwent a major overhaul. Subsequently, international institutions made these policies a prerequisite for granting loans to the countries that were on the brink of bankruptcy. The policies that I am talking about are the neo-liberal economic policies, and the framework they are built upon is the fundamental assumption of the efficiency of free markets. Every undergraduate economics student is taught that leaving markets to function without any intervention by the State will accrue benefits to the society as a whole. This article is an attempt to look at why free markets are not so free and why they do not always lead to the best of outcomes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO</title><link href="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”&lt;/em&gt;, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included &lt;em&gt;“And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”&lt;/em&gt;. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NATO was founded in 1949 with a total of 30 members. The members include nations from North America (Canada and the United States) and 28 of the European countries. Its military nature is profoundly indicated by Article 5 of the treaty which states that in the occurrence of an attack against any one of the member states, it shall be understood to have been an attack against all members. This ensures the assistance of all the other member nations against the common adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) formed what was known as the Warsaw Pact in 1955 that included the Eastern Bloc Socialist Republics of Central and Eastern Europe. It was a collective defence treaty created as a reaction to the integration of West Germany into NATO. After the end of the Cold War and consequent nullification of the Warsaw Pact, NATO added 14 more member nations – 10 of them included in the Warsaw Pact and 4 former Yugoslav Republics. Some of the important operations undertaken by NATO include the defence of Denmark and Norway during September 1952, Exercise Longstep in the Mediterranean sea, Exercise Campaign Reforger which was an annual exercise by NATO states during the Cold War, and Exercise Strikeback which was a naval exercise that took place over a ten-day period in September 1957. The Northern Wedding had been another significant naval military exercise aimed at examining NATOs ability to reinforce Europe militarily during the Cold War in 1978. The latest development arrived in the form of DEFENDER-Europe 20 which was a US-led multinational exercise which included NATO’s participation. Notably, it was the largest deployment of US-based forces to Europe in the last quarter of a century. It included the participation of 20,000 soldiers deployed directly from the US to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Aspersions on NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ascent of Donald Trump in US national politics birthed a characteristic nationalistic, isolationist tendency, popularly termed as the ‘America First Policy’. It has been manifested in his scathing takes on multilateral organisations which include the United Nations (UN), and more recently the World Health Organisation (WHO) in the background of the coronavirus pandemic. Thus it comes as no surprise that he had been a stringent opponent to the very fundamental notions that have contributed to the formation of NATO. The &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; had reported that President Trump had on more than one occasion expressed desires to pull the US out of NATO. There are three primary reasons for his efforts to distance the US from this treaty - nearly 70% of the total spending on defence by NATO governments is accounted for by the US. In terms of the US Gross Domestic Product (GDP), the US spent roughly 3.4% on defence in 2019, while the average in European NATO countries and Canada was 1.55%. Naturally, Trump considers NATO to be an extra drain upon the military budget. NATO is funded by a common funding arrangement determined by each country’s national income. NATO had stated that the civilian and military budget for 2019 was $1.84 billion, out of which the US was paying 22%, France and the UK paid around 10.5% and Germany about 14.76%. The other alliance members contributed for the rest. This had caused bilateral relations between the US and Germany to worsen, as Trump, while referring to the burden shouldered by the US criticised the Germans for being “delinquent” in their payment to NATO. Trump further stated that the US shall move 12,000 troops out of the country. Jens Stoltenberg, the NATO Secretary-General had stated, &lt;em&gt;“We have now agreed (on) a new formula for sharing costs. The US will pay less. Germany will pay more”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem lies in the fact that the US, being a global superpower, has military commitments around the world and is not restricted to the geographical area of Europe and North America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the US deploys tens of thousands of active-duty personnel in Europe including in Turkey. The US diplomatic commitments in Europe also include a missile defence system run by NATO members. This is designed to shield against potential long-range ballistic missile attacks from outside the continent. Thus, the active presence of both men and arms is required on the part of the US. For the US President, all these factors are more of a display of magnanimity than a tool of diplomatic leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is important to note that a Chicago Council Survey in 2014 said that 78% of the American public supports NATO, 66% believed that the US commitment to NATO should remain as it is, as opposed to 7% supporting the possibility of a withdrawal. Thus the question of whether it is time to ring the death knell of NATO has its fair share of nay-sayers and aye-sayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Consequences in a World without NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the possible dissolution of the 71-year-old organisation, there will be a risk of Russian aggression. Many diplomats believe that had the post-Soviet Baltic nations which did not join NATO would have already been occupied by Russian expansionist aims. In the absence of NATO, mutual security interests such as combating ISIS and other global defence attempts emanating from coalition operations would be severely jeopardised. NATO’s retirement has the possibility to exacerbate divisions within Europe, especially in a post-Brexit, weakened European Union. The disappearance of NATO might make America’s Asian partners side with a rising China. Moreover, it will greatly strengthen the Russian Federation, which will reclaim the East European states which were formerly a part of the USSR. The clear political gainers would be Russia and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the question remains: To be or not to be? Amer-Exit from NATO and the consequent dissolution of NATO? Or a fundamental rebuilding exercise is that shall salvage the organisation that has maintained relative stability in the trans-Atlantic region?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included “And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Israel-UAE Deal: History Created?</title><link href="/Israel-UAE-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Israel-UAE Deal: History Created?" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Israel-UAE-Deal</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Israel-UAE-Deal">&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump exemplified his love affair with Twitter as he took to the microblogging platform to break the news of a historic truce between Israel and the United Arab Emirates (UAE). This makes Abu Dhabi the third nation in the Arab world and the first among the Gulf nations to recognise Israel as a nation. The move is touted by many as a game-changer in the geopolitics of the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gulf countries have not, for over a century, officially recognised Israel as a nation because of the ongoing Israel-Palestinian crisis. Trump also brokered an agreement where Israel would suspend its plans to annex the Western Bank — a region of conflict between the Jewish Israelis and the Palestinian Muslims, where the latter has also been subjucted to various atrocities violating human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle East is a precarious region, and its geopolitics is largely influenced by a Cold War-like proxy war between two of its behemoths – Saudi Arabia and Iran. The roots of this complex crosshairs can be traced back to the First World War, which culminated with the fall of the Ottoman Empire. The local Al Saud tribe in the Arabian peninsula fought off everyone who staked a claim in the region, and modern-day Saudi Arabia was officially recognised in 1932. Until 1979, Saudi Arabia was regarded as an undisputed bastion of Muslims across the world, for the progeny of the dynasty were also the custodians of the holy mosques in Mecca and Medina — the two holiest shrines in Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Iranian Revolution in 1979 saw the rise of a theocratic rule stemming from the Shia sect of Islam under Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini. Not only did he envisage Iran as a regional power, but he also challenged a Sunni-dominated Saudi Arabia’s claim to lead the Muslim world. This came as a shock to many for Khomeini’s ascent was first welcomed by then-Saudi ruler King Salman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran, rich in oil reserves, changed its foreign policy to undermine America’s influence in the region. This further fanned its animosity with Saudi, which had been a pro-America state. However, unlike Saudi, Iran wasn’t able to pull in money for its oil reserves and was crippled with the sanctions imposed on it by the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has largely supported rebel groups, some of them are extremists and are categorised as ‘terrorist groups’ in the unrest that has prevailed in the region. Before the US invasion in Iraq, the country served as somewhat of a buffer zone between the two nations. Many diplomatic circles jokingly say that America invaded Iraq only to gift it to Iran, and it is for a good reason that the ISIS occupation in Iraq had been largely supported by the Iraqi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khomeini’s new government also turned hostile towards Israel, it withdrew its decision to recognise Israel as a state and severed all ties with it. Iraq’s policy of supporting rebel groups in conflict-laden areas also meant that it supported opposing extremist groups against Israel — Hezbollah in Lebanon, and Hamas and Palestinian Islamic Jihad in Israel, for it considers the state a Zionist regime. (Zionism was the movement which led to the foundation of Israel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE’s peace agreement (albeit the government in Abu Dhabi calls it a roadmap to a peaceful relationship) has offended the Palestinians, who saw an ally in them. They were also taken by surprise by this announcement since they were not informed about any of this. &lt;em&gt;“May you never be sold out by your ‘friends’”&lt;/em&gt;, Hanan Ashrawi, a senior official, angrily tweeted at the Emirati crown prince.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian Authority has been championing for a separate state, and its President Mahmoud Abbas is disillusioned with the Trump administration for its pro-Israel stance. &lt;em&gt;“The Palestinian leadership rejects and denounces the UAE, Israeli and US trilateral, surprising, announcement”&lt;/em&gt;, said a senior adviser to Abbas and called it a &lt;em&gt;“betrayal of Jerusalem, Al-Aqsa, and the Palestinian cause”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to look at this agreement is a reaffirmation of the fact that UAE doesn’t detest Israel as much as its Arab counterparts do. This is diametrically opposed to the Arab and Muslim viewpoint of the official recognition of Israel in 1948 as a ‘pro-Western’ move, analogous to the erstwhile European colonialism that once existed. Many diplomatic commentators see this as the UAE’s plan for a more liberal and open foreign policy which is evident from the immigrants that throng to the country for work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian cause is, irrefutably, hurt by this agreement. Although the UAE made it clear that the “suspension of plans to annex the Western Bank” was their priority, Palestinians would see it as tokenism if the UAE doesn’t raise the question of Palestinian statehood. There is an opinion that the Emiratis are disenchanted with the Palestinian separatist movement, possibly because they don’t want to see its citizens or its government to be supportive of a separatist movement, especially when dissent is hardly tolerated in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both for US President Donald Trump and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, it is an attempt to save some of the public approval that elected them. The two leaders are receiving flak and opprobrium for their management of the coronavirus pandemic. While Trump is also criticised for his failed diplomatic projects and a US economy that has been bludgeoned by the pandemic, Netanyahu faces a trial of corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the decision in Washington is bipartisan — the Democratic Presidential candidate Joe Biden and presumptive Vice-Presidential candidate Kamala Harris have also welcomed this decision. This also indicates that the government in Abu Dhabi is preparing itself for the fact that Trump might not win a second term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Trump is pinning his hopes on other Arab states to follow suit. However, this agreement also undermines any hopes of a permanent settlement between the Israelis and Palestinians. The further implications of this deal are yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Kant</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">President Donald Trump exemplified his love affair with Twitter as he took to the microblogging platform to break the news of a historic truce between Israel and the United Arab Emirates (UAE). This makes Abu Dhabi the third nation in the Arab world and the first among the Gulf nations to recognise Israel as a nation. The move is touted by many as a game-changer in the geopolitics of the region.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Injudicious Judiciary</title><link href="/Injudicious-Judiciary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Injudicious Judiciary" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Injudicious-Judiciary</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Injudicious-Judiciary">&lt;p&gt;Marquess Acton of Groppoli famously said, &lt;em&gt;“Power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely”&lt;/em&gt;. In order to prevent absolute power from corrupting absolutely, the founding fathers of free India established the Indian judicial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian judicial system has been hailed as the third pillar of democracy. Its primary duty as bestowed by the Constitution of India was to keep a check on the government and to protect the rights of the citizens. Created as a way to balance the powers of the legislature and the executive, and purposely kept out of reach and influence of the aforementioned, the judiciary enjoys the privilege to interfere and overrule the legislature and/or the executive. Vested with the powers of protecting the democratic institutions and championing the rights of the people of India, the judiciary has managed to create for itself an image as a “paragon of justice”, intervening even in matters of public policy to ensure the end of good governance is served.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in the last 18 months, this carefully built facade has been slowly but surely crumbling. It reveals the image of an institution not strong enough to weather the pressure and demands of the public, and an institution apathetic to the innumerable human rights violations that currently encumber the nation. In order to understand how the judiciary has failed to step up and take charge when it needed to, a recounting of its majorly catastrophic judgments and silence in these past few months is imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We begin by recounting the migrant crisis that underscored the disaster wreaked by the coronavirus pandemic. For months, our phones, televisions and newspapers were brimming with stories of resilient men and women travelling hundreds of kilometres to reach home or to seek medical care when the nation went into lockdown. Amidst those stories were also reports of workers and the underprivileged people of India dying on roads because of hunger and thirst, and being killed in accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the country was put under lockdown with barely a 24-hour warning in advance, ration shops, factories, and markets were closed down. The daily wage workers were forced to leave their premises and travel back to their hometown from the big cities when they could neither continue working nor be able to afford rent or food. No modes of transportation or provisions for basic necessities were forthcoming which left these migrant workers and daily wage workers stranded. In the first week of June, the Chief Labour Commissioner estimated that around 2,600,000 migrants were stranded across India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government of India’s failure to account for the millions of underprivileged people in India while formulating the policy of lockdown was not seized upon by the judiciary. At a time when the courts should have taken charge and forced the government to care for the safety and health of the underprivileged citizens, the judiciary’s silence was jarring. Its neglect of the most vulnerable people in the country highlights its egregious failure to uphold the promise of equality in the Indian Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrible human rights violation in the state of Kashmir following the abrogation of Article 370 is yet another failure of the Indian judicial system. 12,500,000 people had to live without access to the internet and were isolated from the rest of the nation under the most stringent military supervision while we heard snippets of the horrors many Kashmiris faced. It took almost a year for the apex Court of India, the Supreme Court to re-establish the privilege of mobile connections in Kashmir. Yet it does not absolve them of their silence and willingness to ignore the hundreds of petitions and Public Interest Litigations (PILs) against the government’s decision regarding Kashmir. The government did not even receive a slap on the wrist from the courts for their actions, underscoring the judiciary’s failure to uphold and protect the fundamental rights of the citizens of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This failure is only aggravated by the superficial response of the courts on the arrest of students, activists, lawyers and journalists by the government for protesting against the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2019. The right to protest and question the government is the key feature of a democracy, and the authorities blatantly violated that right by putting people in jail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varavara Rao, a 79-year-old poet, teacher, and activist, has been diagnosed with COVID-19, yet he suffers in jail for protesting against the government. Sudha Bharadwaj, Hany Babu, and Natasha Narwal are some of the innumerable students and teachers who have been arrested for dissenting. The judiciary’s fear of displeasing the current authorities and holding them accountable for their offence is blatantly emphasised by their inability to protect the democratic principles that uphold the structures of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neglect and lack of concern for extrajudicial killings is yet another characteristic of the Indian judicial system. While it certainly seems extremely heroic for police to take charge, and kill rapists and gang leaders, it undermines the role of a justice system. The glaring misuse of power by the police is a violation of fundamental rights and does not create the deterrence necessary to desist future perpetrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the judiciary fails to perform the duties it was conferred by the Constitution, they excel in performing a role that they should avidly be avoiding: moral policing. The judiciary has a history of passing moral judgments on rape survivors. In a recent rape case, the courts berated the girl for falling asleep after being raped, saying &lt;em&gt;“It is unbecoming of an Indian woman to fall asleep after being ravished”&lt;/em&gt; while in another case, the Court dismissed a sexual assault case by asking the girl to tie a &lt;em&gt;Rakhi&lt;/em&gt; (an amulet tied by sisters around the wrists of brothers, symbolically protecting them) to the person who assaulted her. The courts questioning the moral character of the rape survivors and instances of victim-blaming and shaming form a major chunk of court proceedings. This behaviour is unbecoming of an institution built to protect the dignity of the citizens of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The failure and decay of the judicial system in India is a precursor to receding public trust in justice, lack of accountability of the government, and misuse of power leading to a very dystopian-like future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is justice? What is right and what is wrong? The question of morality and justice has remained unanswered, making the duty of the judiciary difficult. However, we do not expect our courts to answer this question, neither do we expect perfection from our courts, we only expect competence and determination to not purposely violate our freedom and fundamental rights. The role of the judiciary is crucial for the efficient functioning of the country, but during times of rampant fascism led by the government and civil turmoil, it is the duty of the judiciary to keep the country from spiralling into chaos.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Marquess Acton of Groppoli famously said, “Power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely”. In order to prevent absolute power from corrupting absolutely, the founding fathers of free India established the Indian judicial system.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Microsoft’s Satya Nadella: A Catalyst</title><link href="/Satya-Nadella" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microsoft’s Satya Nadella: A Catalyst" /><published>2020-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Satya-Nadella</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Satya-Nadella">&lt;p&gt;Hailing from the Southern part of India which has given birth to leaders of giant companies around the world, Satya Nadella has made Microsoft the largest company in the world, in terms of market capitalisation since he took over 6 years ago. His leadership style has been completely different from what the company had witnessed under its past leaders. From Steve Ballmer’s flashy and supposedly ‘epic’ speeches, Nadella brought a more calming effect to the table. This has certainly worked for the company. Instead of a sideward movement of the stock prices witnessed under Ballmer’s reign, the share prices have only been going up under Nadella’s leadership. Nadella, a proponent of the growth mindset philosophy, believes in the growth of individuals and the team as a whole. Instead of focussing too much on tradition, he convinced the employees that innovation is the only thing that is respected in their industry. Often under the guidance of Ballmer and Gates, Microsoft had begun living off of its past rather than focussing on providing world-class tech to its users. However, tradition is fleeting and the only constant is change in this ever-changing world. This philosophy has helped Nadella in bringing Microsoft where it is today. When Nadella was given charge of Microsoft’s Cloud services, Ballmer had warned Nadella that he would be fired if he doesn’t make it work, and yet again while taking charge as the CEO, he faced a similar do-or-die situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft, by many accounts, was in dire shape before Nadella took over in 2014. Windows 8 had debuted with poor reception, and it was struggling to navigate the smartphone revolution. Although the Surface tablet is a modest success, Microsoft’s smartphones have flopped despite the firm paying more than €5.4 billion ($6.2bn; £4.7bn) for Nokia’s handset business. Apple’s iPhone, and then Google’s Android left Microsoft in the dust. Additionally, ‘Zune’, the company’s iPod lookalike, was considered one of the worst product flops in tech history. There was no doubt that Microsoft had maintained a longstanding legacy in Silicon Valley, but many agreed that it needed a new strategy to compete against its more nimble counterparts like Apple Inc and Alphabet Inc. The major problem was that Microsoft was not dynamic. It had not been changing with time, and was not adapting to the changes that its competitors were creating in the business environment. Where Bill Gates had taken the wind of personal computing, Steve Ballmer failed to do the same with smartphones. However, Satya had no intention of committing the same mistake. He made a pronouncement on day one, &lt;em&gt;“The world is about cloud-first, mobile-first”&lt;/em&gt;, and made clear the direction in which the company would be going for the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Nadella’s leadership, Microsoft has embarked on a major transition towards becoming a cloud computing giant through its Azure platform. The cloud business, growing at a rate of 47%, continues to be the primary driver of the company’s success in recent years. The company’s current flagship business has a 20% market share in the cloud business. Azure is second only to Amazon’s AWS, with 31%. The coevolution of software and hardware will digitise most of the things that we do and experience in business, life and the world. It will be interesting to see who comes out on the top in the cloud competition in this world that is moving towards more sophisticated tech every day. Microsoft surely seems to be on the right path, being one step ahead of the change and not relying too much on its past successes. Nadella has completely shifted the company’s focus from its core business of Windows in the tenure of his leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has also forayed into the world of cloud gaming with Azure. Cloud gaming is like a subscription for games that you can play on any platform (mobile phone, laptop, gaming consoles, etc.). For Microsoft, getting the first-mover advantage would be key as Google too is planning to capture the market with ‘Stadia’. However, it should be easier for Microsoft to establish a strong foothold in this area as it already has experience with its gaming console business ‘Xbox’. The company has been using gamers’ data and constantly improving itself, to give the customers what they want, according to their preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella opposed the decision to purchase Nokia as he could not see why the world needed a third ecosystem in phones. He focussed on more sensible acquisitions, such as that of the job-search portal, LinkedIn. With this acquisition, Microsoft has become the leader in professional data. The Redmond giant plans to integrate the portal and make it available inside Outlook, Office, Skype, and Windows, thereby creating an ecosystem that is inescapable for the customer. Moreover, plans to integrate Cortana with LinkedIn have also been made. If something like this happens, Cortana would be able to assist the users in a much more complex manner by providing intel on customers’ business relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella has also incorporated lessons from his personal life into his leadership style. Talking about his son’s struggle with cerebral palsy in his book &lt;em&gt;Hit Refresh&lt;/em&gt;, he talks about how that experience instilled in him the feeling of empathy. He believes that it is important for people working in an innovation-centric company to be empathetic. In order to find a solution for a problem that your consumer is facing, you need to first be able to put yourself in his shoes and feel the need for innovation. He has repeatedly pressed on the importance of understanding what others are going through in order for a business to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella’s managing style, say those who know him, is akin to cricket’s long-form (a sport of which the CEO is very fond of): slow, deliberative and patient. He makes no snap decisions. He focuses on a handful of the most important issues facing the company and takes a deep dive into each, encouraging serious input from others. Listening, probing, questioning. When he’s satisfied that he has enough information, he makes his decision — not a minute sooner. Nadella and his team know exactly what Microsoft is and what they want it to be: an innovative technology company that exists to help other businesses thrive. This vision is what has kept them growing, and will continue doing so in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Hailing from the Southern part of India which has given birth to leaders of giant companies around the world, Satya Nadella has made Microsoft the largest company in the world, in terms of market capitalisation since he took over 6 years ago. His leadership style has been completely different from what the company had witnessed under its past leaders. From Steve Ballmer’s flashy and supposedly ‘epic’ speeches, Nadella brought a more calming effect to the table. This has certainly worked for the company. Instead of a sideward movement of the stock prices witnessed under Ballmer’s reign, the share prices have only been going up under Nadella’s leadership. Nadella, a proponent of the growth mindset philosophy, believes in the growth of individuals and the team as a whole. Instead of focussing too much on tradition, he convinced the employees that innovation is the only thing that is respected in their industry. Often under the guidance of Ballmer and Gates, Microsoft had begun living off of its past rather than focussing on providing world-class tech to its users. However, tradition is fleeting and the only constant is change in this ever-changing world. This philosophy has helped Nadella in bringing Microsoft where it is today. When Nadella was given charge of Microsoft’s Cloud services, Ballmer had warned Nadella that he would be fired if he doesn’t make it work, and yet again while taking charge as the CEO, he faced a similar do-or-die situation.</summary></entry></feed>