<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-03-22T11:43:34+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti</title><link href="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti" /><published>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti">&lt;p&gt;There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a
step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about
language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when
they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the
degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different
factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and
vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each
other using these mediums or platforms of communication?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest
concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even.
However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about
‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to
realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as
‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around,
like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts
the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It
portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and
non-violent sensibilities. After all, &lt;em&gt;‘bhakti’&lt;/em&gt;(devotion) is not just some
‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some
religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that.
It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human,
and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in
the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we
acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will
be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are
privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you
have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called
‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and
spares none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness
as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and
cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment
with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate
love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does
not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily
centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on
the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists
and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a
better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries
now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has
been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars
of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you
do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious
army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth?
You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations
of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think
is listening to your faint whispers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of
urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of
agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will
be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the
philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation
reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the
profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a
friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its
decency and communion, in its &lt;em&gt;bhaava&lt;/em&gt; (emotion), will one day become something
more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds
can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now
contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the
idea of ‘bhakti’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply &lt;strong&gt;CANNOT&lt;/strong&gt; be denigrated. Far from
mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the
wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more
bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After
all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger
tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to
trivialise language itself the way we do today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this
differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through
language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers
too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some
primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You
need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance
against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with
your criticism, and perhaps yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>swarnima.swastika.tewary</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each other using these mediums or platforms of communication? In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even. However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about ‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as ‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective. The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around, like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and non-violent sensibilities. After all, ‘bhakti’(devotion) is not just some ‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that. It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human, and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called ‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and spares none. The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more. And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth? You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think is listening to your faint whispers? When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its decency and communion, in its bhaava (emotion), will one day become something more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the idea of ‘bhakti’. Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply CANNOT be denigrated. Far from mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to trivialise language itself the way we do today? Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with your criticism, and perhaps yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Cl*t Wants What it Wants</title><link href="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cl*t Wants What it Wants" /><published>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants">&lt;p&gt;Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared
of every &lt;em&gt;flogging&lt;/em&gt; and every &lt;em&gt;caning&lt;/em&gt; or suddenly having no faith in
technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to
avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that
one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or &lt;em&gt;category&lt;/em&gt; of
porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one
feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in
person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk
to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why
do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;,
we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re
scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that &lt;em&gt;these&lt;/em&gt; are our
innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared
of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a
certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how
we think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest
the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s
offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely
a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like &lt;em&gt;choking&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;slapping&lt;/em&gt; cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why
we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s
the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place
where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if
there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is
wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so
dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those
same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because
it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic,
we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense
of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control
what we do or do not &lt;strong&gt;desire&lt;/strong&gt;. We think we can choose to want or not want
something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the
dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are
borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the
‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or
craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet
pussy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to
further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in
role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex,
and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex
for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man.
The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the
one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; by serving only his
needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the
appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for
betraying the rule (women not desiring sex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to
be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its
proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that
most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex
dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your
hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an
average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a
discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into
account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with
submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’.
Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To
claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone
else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to
restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy
or even if only for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you
can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we
are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to
understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to
remember is: &lt;em&gt;desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of
them.&lt;/em&gt; No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has
been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of
life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that
this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be
built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with
these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely
the manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray
you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stuti Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared of every flogging and every caning or suddenly having no faith in technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or category of porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position. The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we want, we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that these are our innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how we think. Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like choking and slapping cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel. It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic, we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control what we do or do not desire. We think we can choose to want or not want something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing. It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the ‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet pussy. It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex, and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man. The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her role by serving only his needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for betraying the rule (women not desiring sex). The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to be? A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’. Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy or even if only for a while. There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to remember is: desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of them. No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely the manifestation. Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“HELICOPTER” MONEY: The Way Ahead?</title><link href="/Helicopter-Money" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“HELICOPTER” MONEY: The Way Ahead?" /><published>2019-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Helicopter-Money</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Helicopter-Money">&lt;p&gt;Suppose, a developed economy is experiencing a period of stagnation coupled with really low-interest rates and the government approaches the central bank to devise a way to spur spending and output in the economy. The central bank tries the conventional way of reducing interest rates to stimulate spending, inflation, growth and output but it falls flat as the interest rates were already very close to zero. Hence, the changes in the interest rates were not substantial enough to bring about a major change in output and spending. Worried, the central bank finds itself in a tough spot with limited monetary options to get out of this fix, none of which are effective. According to Friedman, the only solution would be to fly a helicopter above a community, literally dropping 100 dollar notes out of the sky for the general public to freely spend on commodities and services, therefore stimulating spending, output, and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially developed as a classroom theory, ‘Helicopter Money’ refers to direct money transfers, virtual or cash, from the central bank to the general public with an aim of increasing spending, output, inflation and growth in an economy trapped in stagnation coupled with a liquidity crisis. The tool remained as a textbook chapter for most of the latter part of the 20th century. However, it was brought to light in 2002 by the then Fed governor Ben Bernanke who considered it as a suitable option to revive the US as well as Japan from the deflation which hit most developed countries at the beginning of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, how does ‘Helicopter Money’ succeed when all other monetary methods fail to stimulate expenditure and output in the economy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems with quantitative easing, rate cuts and other monetary methods generally adopted by a central bank fails when the interest rates hover around zero. This is because when the interest rates are near zero, a further rate cut, buying up of government bonds or negative interest rates would not increase the money supply in the economy sufficiently to increase spending. Moreover, most of these traditional financial methods have already been used and proven inefficient in various developed economies at various points in time, such as Japan in the 1990’s and the US in the early 2000’s. Hence, the only method which still remains unused is the Helicopter Drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helicopter Drop has been hypothetically proven to stimulate demand in the economy. As the measure requires a one-time direct cash transfer to the general public, it is sure to stimulate spending. This is because the money supply in the economy increases by the amount of cash transferred by the central bank to the public which then increases the purchasing power of the individual. Naturally, with a higher purchasing power, spending would increase by the MPC (Marginal Propensity to Consume) amount in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prospect of a Helicopter Drop is rather fascinating and sounds too good to be true. Realistically, Helicopter Drops and similar stimulus pose many questions to the central bank, from accounting to distribution. In spite of logistical issues such as how to disperse the amount equitably among the general public, another question which comes up is how will the central bank account for these Helicopter Drops?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the cases of traditional quantitative easing methods, such as open market operations, it is very easy for the central bank to account how much high-powered money has been circulated in the economy. As each accounting transaction has two sides, a debit and a credit, the central bank has to ensure that each accounting debit has its respective credit entry as well. In the case of open market operations, the amount of bonds bought from the market is an increase in the assets of the central bank, which is a debit entry. While the money circulated in the economy is a reduction in the assets of the central bank, hence a credit entry. However, in the case of Helicopter Drop, there is only a reduction in the assets of the central bank. This means that there is only a credit side to this entry, which violates the fundamental principle of accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To counter this, the central bank assumes that it has bought perpetual bonds from the market which have zero interest coupons on it. Basically, this means that The Central Banks assumes that for the money circulated among the general public as helicopter drops, it has bought from the market bonds which are irredeemable for perpetuity and which do not pay interest at all. This ensures that there is a debit side to the accounting entry for Helicopter Drops and that the fundamental principles of accounting are not violated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this solves the issue of accounting, it raises another important question. Nowadays, most economists are concerned with whether a monetary method is reversible or not. In the case of traditional monetary methods such as rate cuts, open market operations, and reserve ratios, all are reversible. Rates and reserve ratios can be increased or decreased as per the situation as the central bank can always buy or sell back government bonds in the market. However, Helicopter Drops are irreversible in nature. That is, once a drop is made, neither its effects on the economy nor the drop itself can be reversed. This limitation makes the economists weary and they argue as a normative proposition, that these drops, if used, should be at most used as a stimulus package to increase one-time spending, output, growth, and inflation in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inconvertible fiat currency is unique in the fact that it has a positive exchange value against commodities as it can be produced at essentially zero cost. Therefore, there is always a potential temptation for central banks to undertake such action by the virtue of printing more and more currency. However, one needs to keep a check on the amount of currency circulated in the economy to ensure that hyperinflation does not occur and the intrinsic value of all commodities do not fall to zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helicopter Drops are dangerous as they conjure up the illusion that monetary magic can whip up real goods and services out of nothing. If this notion holds among those who influence monetary policy, then rational policymaking would become literally impossible. This is because policymakers would become so addicted to Helicopter Money that the overissue of fiat currency would only be dealt with a larger issue of currency until the economy collapses. Therefore, there is a good reason why Helicopter Money has not been used as a monetary policy tool but kept as a classroom experiment. And if Milton Friedman would have been alive today, he would have been horrified at what the Keynesians, the Classicals and the world at large have done to his innocent classroom experiment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhishek Sancheti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Suppose, a developed economy is experiencing a period of stagnation coupled with really low-interest rates and the government approaches the central bank to devise a way to spur spending and output in the economy. The central bank tries the conventional way of reducing interest rates to stimulate spending, inflation, growth and output but it falls flat as the interest rates were already very close to zero. Hence, the changes in the interest rates were not substantial enough to bring about a major change in output and spending. Worried, the central bank finds itself in a tough spot with limited monetary options to get out of this fix, none of which are effective. According to Friedman, the only solution would be to fly a helicopter above a community, literally dropping 100 dollar notes out of the sky for the general public to freely spend on commodities and services, therefore stimulating spending, output, and growth.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Ti Amo Italia”, the EU’s Rhetoric?</title><link href="/the-EU-Rhetoric" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Ti Amo Italia”, the EU's Rhetoric?" /><published>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/the-EU-Rhetoric</id><content type="html" xml:base="/the-EU-Rhetoric">&lt;p&gt;Although the rest of the world may think so, Brexit and Greece are not the only
problems which are troubling the European Union right now. While there is no
denying the fact that the Union has seen many ups-and-downs in its 26-year
history and has averted many crises, it now stands at a juncture where its
future looks bleak, at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From getting the upper-hand in the Brexit negotiations to bailing out Greece,
the European Union saw to it that it tackled both these headaches. On one hand,
it has punished Britain for leaving the Union while on the other hand, it has
somewhat saved the Euro and the Grecian economy from going haywire. At the
moment, however, it is concerned about the third largest economy of the Union
which is at the verge of failure even though it was branded as “too big to
fail”. This economy, called Italy, is marred with high levels of unemployment
and unsustainable levels of debt. If it fails, no matter what measures Paris and
Berlin may take, the European Union would most probably break up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Italy’s condition was not always like that. The economy had been doing
pretty good, growing at a respectable pace of 4% up until the global financial
crisis of 2008. The Italians were taking full advantage of the available cheap
credit and were borrowing freely and heavily from the market to finance their
developmental and infrastructural projects. Before anyone could know, the total
debt of Italy was already more than 100% of the GDP. Even though the situation
was alarming, the banks and investors had confidence in Italy paying off its
debt as its economy was prospering and taking full advantage of the boom.
However, when the financial crisis of 2008 hit the Italians, it hit them hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy was pushed into a recession and since then, Italy has lost 6-7% of
its GDP, the largest loss in the European Union after Greece. When it tried to
recover, the 2011 debt crisis hit back, with the investors losing confidence in
the Euro. What saved Italy from bankruptcy and the European Union from
destruction was Mario Draghi, the Italian President of the European Central
Bank. He famously stated, “I will do whatever it takes me to preserve the Euro.
And believe me, it will be enough.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His decision of printing money to buy up government bonds in the European Union,
reluctantly supported by Germans, is what averted the crisis and pushed it back
further. However, the debt crisis and the lost confidence of investors in the
Euro led to the ousting of the then Prime Minister of Italy, Silvio Berlusconi
in the year 2011. Since then, political instability has also added to the woes
of the Italian economy as the country did not have an elected Prime Minister
till the end of 2018. The present government is being headed by Giuseppe Conte
and is a coalition of the extreme-left Five Star Movement and the extreme-right
League. To add to that instability, the government is currently facing a dilemma
between the European Union and its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real GDP of Italy is still below what it was before the financial crisis of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The per capita GDP is lower than what it was two decades ago. Industrial
production is down by 25%, which has led to massive outbursts of unemployment.
Currently, the official unemployment rate in Italy stands at 10%. However, youth
unemployment is currently between 30-35%. In South Italy, the situation is
absolutely catastrophic with devastating unemployment rates of 60-70%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly speaking, the Italian government does not have money to finance projects
for employment generation. Italy’s sovereign debt stands at $2.1 trillion and
it pays $80 billion as interest each year. Hence, the investors are losing
confidence in Italian government bonds, which is reflected in Moody’s rating of
Baa3, its lowest investment grade above junk status. This has made the cost of
raising debt far too costly for the government of Italy as the difference
between the rate of interest of Italian bonds and German bonds has already
breached the 300-point mark, which is a sign of concern for Italy right now.
This is why foreign investors are selling their Italian bonds like hot cakes in
the market and getting the hell out of the country as they fear Italy to be the
next Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason for the empty pockets of the government is shadow economy and tax
evasion. 30% of the economy is unaccounted for, which leads to the government
losing out on a huge amount of tax revenue. Moreover, low labour productivity
coupled with minimum wages makes Italy unattractive as a manufacturing hub. To
add to this, the population of Italy is ageing. Each woman on an average
produces only 1.3 children which has led to the rapid ageing of the Italian
population. This means a higher expenditure for the government on social
security and lower productivity of the citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of its empty pockets, the left-right government of Italy has proposed
ambitious plans for the restructuring and redevelopment of the economy and
various employment generation programmes for its citizens in its budget of 2019.
This led to the fiscal deficit of the government to rise to 2.4% of the GDP
which is beyond the accepted limits of 2% of the European Union. Hence, the
European Union Commission asked the Italian government to reduce its fiscal
deficit in order to comply with the EU norms or face severe penalties of up to
0.5% of the GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, doing so would mean the government would have to cut out on employment
generation programmes or drop some of its plans for the redevelopment of the
economy. This would lead to its citizens going through at least one more year of
unemployment and low standards of living. It is clear that the Italian
government can choose either of the two. Either its citizens or the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negotiations and talks with the European Union Commission and its President
Jean-Claude Juncker haven’t resulted in any resolutions or compromises from
either side. With both sides in a deadlock, this clash could easily be a recipe
for a disaster. Jean-Claude Juncker has expressed his feelings by voicing his
thoughts, “&lt;em&gt;Ti Amo Italia&lt;/em&gt;” and promising to do something about the situation.
However, this looks more like a crowd-pleasing, fake promise in the form of
rhetoric from the Commission President. Matteo Salvini, Italy’s most powerful
politician, has voiced the government’s anger on the stance of the ECB and the
EU on this matter, stating that “&lt;em&gt;the enemies of Europe are those barricaded in
the bunker of Brussels&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clash between Italy’s populists and the EU’s imperialists could all too
easily set a chain of motions which would lead to far bigger problems for the
EU. This time, the damage would be greater than Brexit or Greece, or both
combined. All that is required is one decision of the government, one investor
losing confidence or one bank failing. With the economists already predicting a
global financial crisis, would Italy be the one to start it all?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhishek Sancheti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Although the rest of the world may think so, Brexit and Greece are not the only problems which are troubling the European Union right now. While there is no denying the fact that the Union has seen many ups-and-downs in its 26-year history and has averted many crises, it now stands at a juncture where its future looks bleak, at best. From getting the upper-hand in the Brexit negotiations to bailing out Greece, the European Union saw to it that it tackled both these headaches. On one hand, it has punished Britain for leaving the Union while on the other hand, it has somewhat saved the Euro and the Grecian economy from going haywire. At the moment, however, it is concerned about the third largest economy of the Union which is at the verge of failure even though it was branded as “too big to fail”. This economy, called Italy, is marred with high levels of unemployment and unsustainable levels of debt. If it fails, no matter what measures Paris and Berlin may take, the European Union would most probably break up. But Italy’s condition was not always like that. The economy had been doing pretty good, growing at a respectable pace of 4% up until the global financial crisis of 2008. The Italians were taking full advantage of the available cheap credit and were borrowing freely and heavily from the market to finance their developmental and infrastructural projects. Before anyone could know, the total debt of Italy was already more than 100% of the GDP. Even though the situation was alarming, the banks and investors had confidence in Italy paying off its debt as its economy was prospering and taking full advantage of the boom. However, when the financial crisis of 2008 hit the Italians, it hit them hard. The economy was pushed into a recession and since then, Italy has lost 6-7% of its GDP, the largest loss in the European Union after Greece. When it tried to recover, the 2011 debt crisis hit back, with the investors losing confidence in the Euro. What saved Italy from bankruptcy and the European Union from destruction was Mario Draghi, the Italian President of the European Central Bank. He famously stated, “I will do whatever it takes me to preserve the Euro. And believe me, it will be enough.” His decision of printing money to buy up government bonds in the European Union, reluctantly supported by Germans, is what averted the crisis and pushed it back further. However, the debt crisis and the lost confidence of investors in the Euro led to the ousting of the then Prime Minister of Italy, Silvio Berlusconi in the year 2011. Since then, political instability has also added to the woes of the Italian economy as the country did not have an elected Prime Minister till the end of 2018. The present government is being headed by Giuseppe Conte and is a coalition of the extreme-left Five Star Movement and the extreme-right League. To add to that instability, the government is currently facing a dilemma between the European Union and its citizens. The real GDP of Italy is still below what it was before the financial crisis of The per capita GDP is lower than what it was two decades ago. Industrial production is down by 25%, which has led to massive outbursts of unemployment. Currently, the official unemployment rate in Italy stands at 10%. However, youth unemployment is currently between 30-35%. In South Italy, the situation is absolutely catastrophic with devastating unemployment rates of 60-70%. Frankly speaking, the Italian government does not have money to finance projects for employment generation. Italy’s sovereign debt stands at $2.1 trillion and it pays $80 billion as interest each year. Hence, the investors are losing confidence in Italian government bonds, which is reflected in Moody’s rating of Baa3, its lowest investment grade above junk status. This has made the cost of raising debt far too costly for the government of Italy as the difference between the rate of interest of Italian bonds and German bonds has already breached the 300-point mark, which is a sign of concern for Italy right now. This is why foreign investors are selling their Italian bonds like hot cakes in the market and getting the hell out of the country as they fear Italy to be the next Greece. Another reason for the empty pockets of the government is shadow economy and tax evasion. 30% of the economy is unaccounted for, which leads to the government losing out on a huge amount of tax revenue. Moreover, low labour productivity coupled with minimum wages makes Italy unattractive as a manufacturing hub. To add to this, the population of Italy is ageing. Each woman on an average produces only 1.3 children which has led to the rapid ageing of the Italian population. This means a higher expenditure for the government on social security and lower productivity of the citizens. In spite of its empty pockets, the left-right government of Italy has proposed ambitious plans for the restructuring and redevelopment of the economy and various employment generation programmes for its citizens in its budget of 2019. This led to the fiscal deficit of the government to rise to 2.4% of the GDP which is beyond the accepted limits of 2% of the European Union. Hence, the European Union Commission asked the Italian government to reduce its fiscal deficit in order to comply with the EU norms or face severe penalties of up to 0.5% of the GDP. However, doing so would mean the government would have to cut out on employment generation programmes or drop some of its plans for the redevelopment of the economy. This would lead to its citizens going through at least one more year of unemployment and low standards of living. It is clear that the Italian government can choose either of the two. Either its citizens or the EU. Negotiations and talks with the European Union Commission and its President Jean-Claude Juncker haven’t resulted in any resolutions or compromises from either side. With both sides in a deadlock, this clash could easily be a recipe for a disaster. Jean-Claude Juncker has expressed his feelings by voicing his thoughts, “Ti Amo Italia” and promising to do something about the situation. However, this looks more like a crowd-pleasing, fake promise in the form of rhetoric from the Commission President. Matteo Salvini, Italy’s most powerful politician, has voiced the government’s anger on the stance of the ECB and the EU on this matter, stating that “the enemies of Europe are those barricaded in the bunker of Brussels.” This clash between Italy’s populists and the EU’s imperialists could all too easily set a chain of motions which would lead to far bigger problems for the EU. This time, the damage would be greater than Brexit or Greece, or both combined. All that is required is one decision of the government, one investor losing confidence or one bank failing. With the economists already predicting a global financial crisis, would Italy be the one to start it all?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding the Great Divergence and the Great Convergence</title><link href="/Understanding-the-Great-Divergence-and-the-Great-Convergence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Great Divergence and the Great Convergence" /><published>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/Understanding-the-Great-Divergence-and-the-Great-Convergence</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-the-Great-Divergence-and-the-Great-Convergence">&lt;p&gt;Prior to the beginning of the 19th century, economies around the world were
highly localised and agrarian. Commerce was seemingly restricted to domestic
production and self-consumption, compelling countries to thrive independently;
transnational trade was underdeveloped at the time. However, with the advent of
the Industrial Revolution in Western Europe around 1760, nations discovered new
methods of production and advanced ways of transportation that employed
inventive machinery and steam power. This facilitated trade by lowering the
costs of moving goods across borders, thus marking the dawn of an age of
globalisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an unprecedented change in the environment for trade gave way to what
scholars term the “Great Divergence”. Between 1820 and 1990, the Great
Divergence is said to have sponsored a rise in the share of global income going
to the Western world from one-fifth of the total to an estimated two-thirds.
Conversely, however, today that share has plunged to where it was in 1900, thus
representing what academics have named the “Great Convergence”. Identified with
reduced communication costs in addition to low trade costs, the Great
Convergence has endorsed the rapid growth of developing and underdeveloped
countries, collectively bringing them almost at par with the share of global GDP
going to the Western world today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the history of humankind, there have been three elaborate phases that
have led to the development of today’s global economy. Phase One, which existed
between 200,000 BCE and 10,000 BCE, was predominantly characterised by the
procurement of food over various seasons and regions. The early man moved around
in search of new locations where he could hunt or cultivate. Food was the
primary good of exchange. Hence, this phase was characterised by
self-locomotion, rather than the movement of goods. In Phase Two, the global
economy progressed towards localisation, and witnessed the exchange of diverse
goods and services between 10,000 BCE and 1820 CE. Revolutions in agriculture
and science triggered population growth, which led to the formation of
civilisations and food surpluses.  Countries termed the &lt;em&gt;Ancient Seven&lt;/em&gt; or the
&lt;em&gt;A7&lt;/em&gt; flourished extensively and witnessed sizeable economic growth. These were
India, China, Egypt, Turkey, Iran, Iraq, and Greece/Italy. It was more
profitable for these countries to manufacture and sell within domestic
territories rather than globally. Local market conditions determined prices,
while international factors had almost no role to play. Although trade did
emerge with the development of the Silk Route and Spice Route among other means,
globalisation in its modern understanding had not yet begun on account of high
trade costs, high communication costs, and high face-to-face costs. It was only
after 1820 that Phase Three witnessed true globalisation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having harnessed steam power, the Industrial Revolution in Western Europe
emphasised the importance of iron and steel in modern manufacturing while
augmenting the establishment of factories and industrial districts. Production
was micro-clustered to gain from economies of scale by channeling
specialisation, division of labour and better allocation of resources. With the
development of railroads and steamships, trade costs dipped, thus enlarging
international trade volumes significantly. Incomes of Western countries
subsequently diverged and marked the beginning of the Great Divergence. Kenneth
Pomeranz’s book, &lt;em&gt;The Great Divergence&lt;/em&gt;, is accredited with making the term
popular among business historians and economists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, why did the incomes of the West and the Rest diverge? Since 1500, India and
China had been enjoying the largest shares of world output with high per capita
incomes and wealthy trade. What caused the sudden divergence of Western incomes
that led to what some have termed the “North-South income gap”? There are three
prominent explanations. The first explanation stresses on &lt;em&gt;cultural factors&lt;/em&gt;.
Niall Ferguson, author of &lt;em&gt;Civilization: West and the Rest&lt;/em&gt;, identifies the
Protestant work ethic as a killer model of capitalist enterprise. The &lt;em&gt;Group of
Seven&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt; countries: United States, Britain, France, Germany, Canada,
Japan, and Italy, underwent rapid industrialization and overtook the &lt;em&gt;A7&lt;/em&gt; in
world dominance and wealth. The West apparently had the ‘right’ culture while
the Rest had the ‘wrong’ culture for sustenance in the international market post
Phase Three&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Unsurprisingly, this explanation is highly contested and lacks
adequate evidence for its validity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second explanation highlights &lt;em&gt;institutional factors&lt;/em&gt;. It is said that the
West had at its disposal, access to better institutions and progressive
political establishments, thus facilitating faster growth in the modern era. On
the contrary, countries like India suffered adverse colonial rule while
countries like China witnessed regular instabilities with changing regimes and
leaders. Similarly, the legal systems in &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt; countries were more advanced and
accountable relative to their &lt;em&gt;A7&lt;/em&gt; counterparts. There is sufficient evidence to
back these claims, however, the Great Divergence was not entirely based on the
foundations of this explanation. And reinforcing this criticism, the final
explanation talks about &lt;em&gt;educational factors&lt;/em&gt; as determinants of global wealth
and poverty.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Claudia Goldin claims in the research paper &lt;em&gt;The Human-Capital Century and
American Leadership:&lt;/em&gt; “the unique egalitarian mass provision of post-elementary
schooling achieved in the United States during the early twentieth century”
validates the educational superiority of the West compared to the Rest. Western
Europe and North America witnessed higher literacy rates and more spending on
education in the modern era, thus augmenting their abilities in trade and
commerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that the harmonisation of all these factors can be said to have led
to the Great Divergence. For most of the modern era, the West outshone the Rest
in all three – cultural, institutional, and educational factors. But then, what
really led to the Great Convergence? Was it the West that lost pace or the Rest
that gathered it? Well, both happened simultaneously…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of the West is said to have slowed down after attaining a certain
degree of development, while growth of the Rest is said to have sped up so as to
attain that certain degree of development. The mutual decrease in trade and
communication costs is what facilitated the Great Convergence. With the advent
of information technology, the cost of moving &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt; across borders, besides
&lt;em&gt;goods&lt;/em&gt;, fell significantly. This made it possible for multinational firms to
shift labour-intensive work to underdeveloped and developing nations, thus
saving private as well as social costs. However, in order to preserve and
maintain the entire production process, in addition to outsourcing jobs, these
firms also had to transfer their technical, managerial, financial, and marketing
know-how to these countries – mainly the currently &lt;em&gt;Industrialising Six&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt;
– China, India, Poland, Korea, Thailand, and Indonesia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West aimed at gaining from the unification of advanced technology and
skilled workers, both of which were easily and economically available in these
countries. While this promoted the industrialisation of the &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt;, it also
triggered the deindustrialisation of the &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt;. Moreover, towards the end of the
20th century, &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt; countries began investing considerably in improving their
institutions and extending education to more citizens. Most exploited countries
were no longer under colonial rule; there was more political stability within
nations and greater international peace after the Second World War. These
factors collectively helped developing countries amplify their growth, and
secure higher incomes with better standards of living for their people.
Therefore, investment brought into developing countries by developed ones, and
self-investment by developing countries themselves, are what mutually led to a
decline in the Western share of global GDP and a convergence of income
inequalities between the global North and South. The stagnated and shrunken
economies of China and India, among others, in the &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt; revived remarkably.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt; countries and &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt; countries enjoy more or less the same share of
global income and output. Although the &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt; might still be richer than the
&lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt;, they no longer treasure the dominance that they once did. Poverty in
developing countries is on the fall owing to an increase in employment and
improved quality of life. Contrastingly, wealth in developed countries is on the
fall owing to debt burdens, reduced employment, brain-drain, and monetary
advances to the rest of the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may affirm that the two final phases in the evolution of globalisation were
responsible for both the Great Divergence and the Great Convergence; only these
two phases differed vastly from one another. The former of the two phases
witnessed the growth of the Asian economies until the 19th century, after which
the European-Atlantic Economy surpassed the income levels and growth rates
prevalent in pre-modern Asia. The latter of the two phases is accredited with
subduing the growth of modern European-Atlantic countries, while elevating Asian
ones to better income levels and improved growth rates. This reversed cycle
confirms that both phases of globalisation are opposite to each other in nature.
Currently, we live in its second phase attributed to advanced information
technology and global income parity. And there is no better way to end this
economic-history article than asking, “&lt;em&gt;What Next?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivang Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Prior to the beginning of the 19th century, economies around the world were highly localised and agrarian. Commerce was seemingly restricted to domestic production and self-consumption, compelling countries to thrive independently; transnational trade was underdeveloped at the time. However, with the advent of the Industrial Revolution in Western Europe around 1760, nations discovered new methods of production and advanced ways of transportation that employed inventive machinery and steam power. This facilitated trade by lowering the costs of moving goods across borders, thus marking the dawn of an age of globalisation. Such an unprecedented change in the environment for trade gave way to what scholars term the “Great Divergence”. Between 1820 and 1990, the Great Divergence is said to have sponsored a rise in the share of global income going to the Western world from one-fifth of the total to an estimated two-thirds. Conversely, however, today that share has plunged to where it was in 1900, thus representing what academics have named the “Great Convergence”. Identified with reduced communication costs in addition to low trade costs, the Great Convergence has endorsed the rapid growth of developing and underdeveloped countries, collectively bringing them almost at par with the share of global GDP going to the Western world today. Throughout the history of humankind, there have been three elaborate phases that have led to the development of today’s global economy. Phase One, which existed between 200,000 BCE and 10,000 BCE, was predominantly characterised by the procurement of food over various seasons and regions. The early man moved around in search of new locations where he could hunt or cultivate. Food was the primary good of exchange. Hence, this phase was characterised by self-locomotion, rather than the movement of goods. In Phase Two, the global economy progressed towards localisation, and witnessed the exchange of diverse goods and services between 10,000 BCE and 1820 CE. Revolutions in agriculture and science triggered population growth, which led to the formation of civilisations and food surpluses.  Countries termed the Ancient Seven or the A7 flourished extensively and witnessed sizeable economic growth. These were India, China, Egypt, Turkey, Iran, Iraq, and Greece/Italy. It was more profitable for these countries to manufacture and sell within domestic territories rather than globally. Local market conditions determined prices, while international factors had almost no role to play. Although trade did emerge with the development of the Silk Route and Spice Route among other means, globalisation in its modern understanding had not yet begun on account of high trade costs, high communication costs, and high face-to-face costs. It was only after 1820 that Phase Three witnessed true globalisation.   Having harnessed steam power, the Industrial Revolution in Western Europe emphasised the importance of iron and steel in modern manufacturing while augmenting the establishment of factories and industrial districts. Production was micro-clustered to gain from economies of scale by channeling specialisation, division of labour and better allocation of resources. With the development of railroads and steamships, trade costs dipped, thus enlarging international trade volumes significantly. Incomes of Western countries subsequently diverged and marked the beginning of the Great Divergence. Kenneth Pomeranz’s book, The Great Divergence, is accredited with making the term popular among business historians and economists. But, why did the incomes of the West and the Rest diverge? Since 1500, India and China had been enjoying the largest shares of world output with high per capita incomes and wealthy trade. What caused the sudden divergence of Western incomes that led to what some have termed the “North-South income gap”? There are three prominent explanations. The first explanation stresses on cultural factors. Niall Ferguson, author of Civilization: West and the Rest, identifies the Protestant work ethic as a killer model of capitalist enterprise. The Group of Seven or G7 countries: United States, Britain, France, Germany, Canada, Japan, and Italy, underwent rapid industrialization and overtook the A7 in world dominance and wealth. The West apparently had the ‘right’ culture while the Rest had the ‘wrong’ culture for sustenance in the international market post Phase Three. Unsurprisingly, this explanation is highly contested and lacks adequate evidence for its validity. The second explanation highlights institutional factors. It is said that the West had at its disposal, access to better institutions and progressive political establishments, thus facilitating faster growth in the modern era. On the contrary, countries like India suffered adverse colonial rule while countries like China witnessed regular instabilities with changing regimes and leaders. Similarly, the legal systems in G7 countries were more advanced and accountable relative to their A7 counterparts. There is sufficient evidence to back these claims, however, the Great Divergence was not entirely based on the foundations of this explanation. And reinforcing this criticism, the final explanation talks about educational factors as determinants of global wealth and poverty.   As Claudia Goldin claims in the research paper The Human-Capital Century and American Leadership: “the unique egalitarian mass provision of post-elementary schooling achieved in the United States during the early twentieth century” validates the educational superiority of the West compared to the Rest. Western Europe and North America witnessed higher literacy rates and more spending on education in the modern era, thus augmenting their abilities in trade and commerce. I would say that the harmonisation of all these factors can be said to have led to the Great Divergence. For most of the modern era, the West outshone the Rest in all three – cultural, institutional, and educational factors. But then, what really led to the Great Convergence? Was it the West that lost pace or the Rest that gathered it? Well, both happened simultaneously… The growth of the West is said to have slowed down after attaining a certain degree of development, while growth of the Rest is said to have sped up so as to attain that certain degree of development. The mutual decrease in trade and communication costs is what facilitated the Great Convergence. With the advent of information technology, the cost of moving ideas across borders, besides goods, fell significantly. This made it possible for multinational firms to shift labour-intensive work to underdeveloped and developing nations, thus saving private as well as social costs. However, in order to preserve and maintain the entire production process, in addition to outsourcing jobs, these firms also had to transfer their technical, managerial, financial, and marketing know-how to these countries – mainly the currently Industrialising Six or I6 – China, India, Poland, Korea, Thailand, and Indonesia.   The West aimed at gaining from the unification of advanced technology and skilled workers, both of which were easily and economically available in these countries. While this promoted the industrialisation of the I6, it also triggered the deindustrialisation of the G7. Moreover, towards the end of the 20th century, I6 countries began investing considerably in improving their institutions and extending education to more citizens. Most exploited countries were no longer under colonial rule; there was more political stability within nations and greater international peace after the Second World War. These factors collectively helped developing countries amplify their growth, and secure higher incomes with better standards of living for their people. Therefore, investment brought into developing countries by developed ones, and self-investment by developing countries themselves, are what mutually led to a decline in the Western share of global GDP and a convergence of income inequalities between the global North and South. The stagnated and shrunken economies of China and India, among others, in the I6 revived remarkably.   Today, I6 countries and G7 countries enjoy more or less the same share of global income and output. Although the G7 might still be richer than the I6, they no longer treasure the dominance that they once did. Poverty in developing countries is on the fall owing to an increase in employment and improved quality of life. Contrastingly, wealth in developed countries is on the fall owing to debt burdens, reduced employment, brain-drain, and monetary advances to the rest of the world.   We may affirm that the two final phases in the evolution of globalisation were responsible for both the Great Divergence and the Great Convergence; only these two phases differed vastly from one another. The former of the two phases witnessed the growth of the Asian economies until the 19th century, after which the European-Atlantic Economy surpassed the income levels and growth rates prevalent in pre-modern Asia. The latter of the two phases is accredited with subduing the growth of modern European-Atlantic countries, while elevating Asian ones to better income levels and improved growth rates. This reversed cycle confirms that both phases of globalisation are opposite to each other in nature. Currently, we live in its second phase attributed to advanced information technology and global income parity. And there is no better way to end this economic-history article than asking, “What Next?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity</title><link href="/Be-a-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity" /><published>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</updated><id>/Be-a-Man</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Be-a-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a
sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right
message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously
for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an
advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products,
not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or
criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply
b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple
advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For
more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that
they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible
for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in
battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and
without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions
about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as
evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being
radically redefined. The question is &lt;em&gt;what should it be redefined into?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer
it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly
socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all
thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we
simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural
construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence
and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and
philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some
grand theory of what it &lt;em&gt;must mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;, we must develop more specific
guidelines on what it &lt;em&gt;should mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but
controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual
couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the
man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use
to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any
independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men
paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies
of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has
changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the
one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an
obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give
a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as
well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not
take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school
values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to
people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of
masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and
responsibility cannot simply say: &lt;em&gt;Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal&lt;/em&gt;.
That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a
psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true
cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that
independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that
people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not
actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place.
But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when
negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern
masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the
patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no
overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and
women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in
dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masculinity is undeniably linked to &lt;em&gt;how good men feel about themselves&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t
know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the
male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about
themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this
problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the
issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is
bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely,
without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears,
they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal
notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things
stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control
of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The
only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of
emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to
skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change,
masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’
or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new
notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not
be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that
crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and
self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to
cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man
enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the
&lt;em&gt;#metoo&lt;/em&gt; movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity
has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in
enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make
women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the
difficult question of &lt;em&gt;why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first
place&lt;/em&gt;. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As
Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the
patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important.
In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two)
male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely
different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile
male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce
human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the
patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the
notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in
relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This
creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers,
husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the
females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of
the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if
they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are
associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether
at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in
the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha
male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have
around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise
all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our
property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure
agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can
combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male
ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be
told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the
women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel
inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a
therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one
crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a
friend, we must remind men that &lt;em&gt;“life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to
die anyway”&lt;/em&gt;. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it
really matters little. The fundamental mortality and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life&quot;&gt;absurdity of life&lt;/a&gt; mean that
our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is
futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we
discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we
are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so
many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project
our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”.
My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those
stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of
masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our
base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from
the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem
or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable
strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep
truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and,
therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a
result of true internal self-belief.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products, not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being radically redefined. The question is what should it be redefined into? One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some grand theory of what it must mean to be a man, we must develop more specific guidelines on what it should mean to be a man.    A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and responsibility cannot simply say: Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal. That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place. But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.      Masculinity is undeniably linked to how good men feel about themselves. I don’t know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely, without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears, they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change, masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’ or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so. With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the #metoo movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the difficult question of why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first place. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important. In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two) male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers, husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right. The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a friend, we must remind men that “life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to die anyway”. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it really matters little. The fundamental mortality and absurdity of life mean that our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with. In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”. My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and, therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a result of true internal self-belief.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can Pak, of All Cards, Help Modi Ace This Next One?</title><link href="/Pak-Modi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Pak, of All Cards, Help Modi Ace This Next One?" /><published>2019-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Pak-Modi</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Pak-Modi">&lt;p&gt;Political opinions today, soaked in fake news and formulated through forwards on WhatsApp, are not too difficult to read and analyse. With each new development in the political scenario of India, endless and unidirectional conversations on social media guide the masses towards a specific perception of reality. One major development, in recent times, that has shaken political narratives across the nation is the Pulwama terror attack and India’s rigorous response towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From removing Pakistan’s status as the “most favoured nation”, to Indian air strikes in the Pakistani territory of Balakot in order to annihilate the terrorist group, Jaish-e-Mohammad (JeM), India has used both soft and hard power to mould international sentiments and domestic opinions in its favour. At the centre of this raging storm stands the “muscular and robust” Prime Minister of India, Narendra Modi. His government has loudly banged on the doors of the Paris-headquartered Financial Action Task Force (FATF) to blacklist Pakistan. This was on done on the grounds of state-sponsored terrorism, and was supported by the United Nations Security Council. Social media was flooded with love and admiration for Prime Minister Modi when the success of the Balakot airstrikes was announced. The following days, replete with cross border fires and violations of the Line of Control—the de facto border between India and Pakistan in Kashmir—were closely watched by the Indian public. Whoever may have won or lost on the battlefield, it seemed that PM Modi emerged victorious. Even though Pakistan extended an olive branch by ensuring the safe return of a captured Indian Air Force pilot, the Indian masses applauded the bravado of Modi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the polar contest dominating the majority of the history of Indo-Pak relations, such a reaction from the general Indian public is hardly surprising. Indians have long felt that their elected leadership shies away from taking a hard stance towards terrorism sponsored by Pakistan and separatist terror outfits in Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir. With PM Modi’s frequent international trips, the “surgical strike” in 2016 and the Balakot air-strikes, India has now positioned itself better in the global community. But the real question is whether such a hard stance on Pakistan will strike a chord with Indian voters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, a distinct feature of the growing hostilities between India and Pakistan is the proximity of this crisis to the Indian general elections of 2019. Historically, foreign policy has not played a very significant role in determining electoral results in India. Economic, political and social issues have a far stronger impact on the minds of voters than foreign policy issues. Nonetheless, election manifestos of political parties have always given great importance to their stances towards Pakistan. For instance, the election manifesto of the Indian National Congress, for 2014, emphasised the improvement of relations with Pakistan while holding it accountable for the 26/11 attacks. Similarly, the BJP committed to addressing the demands of refugees from PoK (Pakistan-occupied Kashmir).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as the next general election draws closer, many expect PM Modi to make national security a plank for his electoral campaign. One can already see gaudy BJP posters showing PM Modi holding guns, flanked by soldiers, fighter jets and orange explosions on billboards and streets. A reputed Indian television journalist and author, Barkha Dutt, even tweeted, “Really uncomfortable with pictures of soldiers on election posters and podiums. This should be banned. Surely, the uniform is sullied by vote gathering in its name.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last year, Modi’s popularity has diminished significantly. In the past, strong “saffron waves” had washed over the nation making it impossible to believe that PM Modi could ever face critical challenges. However, the reports on increasing unemployment numbers, growing farmer distress, policy measures like demonetisation, and a more organised Opposition, is giving the BJP a hard time. The BJP was also defeated in five state elections in 2018. However, the major losses were in Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh, which were a significant part of the “Hindi Belt”—the BJP’s traditional vote base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as Mr Modi is trying to chart a victory dominated by the victories of the armed forces, two alternatives are possible:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The urban and middle-class voters, whose votes greatly hinge on India’s status in the world, are swooned by Modi’s strong stances and decide to vote him back to power.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social and economic issues continue to dominate electoral politics and lead to a genuine battle between the incumbent and the Opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the ideal situation for the saffron party will be the first one. But using national security and the armed forces to further a party’s electoral motives seems lowly. Even then, a BJP leader, Mr BS Yeddyurappa didn’t shy away from saying that the Balakot airstrikes could help BJP win 22 seats in the Indian state of Karnataka. The gaffe by the former Chief Minister of Karnataka was immediately brought into scrutiny by the media and Opposition. Thus, the BJP Federal Minister and former Armed Forces Chief, Mr VK Singh, had to step in with a damage control kit. He issued a statement saying that the government’s decision to carry out air strikes was to “safeguard our nation and ensure the safety of our citizens, and not to win a few seats”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bhanu Joshi, a political scientist at Brown University feels that although foreign policy generally doesn’t drive electoral results in India, Indo-Pak relations have always struck a chord with voters, and the Modi administration can monetise on the image of a vigorous, robust and fearless leader. Milan Vaishnav, a senior fellow and director of the South Asia Program at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, echoes a similar sentiment. However, he also feels that even though the Modi-Shah duo will attempt to change the narrative of their campaign, for the rural constituencies and village communities, tangible economic growth will always play a more important role. If the Indo-Pak strife will swing anyone, it will be in the urban constituencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, the Indian air strikes have made a strong statement. India is refusing to back down. So far, the only beneficiary in this war is the BJP, as it is moulding a renewed jingoistic fervour in the Indian voter. There is still a minor possibility of an escalation of this volatile situation between the nuclear-armed states. Amid an intensifying war of words and action between the two, the BJP hopes that this fervour can help them sway every voter who might have become disillusioned in the last five years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Political opinions today, soaked in fake news and formulated through forwards on WhatsApp, are not too difficult to read and analyse. With each new development in the political scenario of India, endless and unidirectional conversations on social media guide the masses towards a specific perception of reality. One major development, in recent times, that has shaken political narratives across the nation is the Pulwama terror attack and India’s rigorous response towards it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can Minimum Wage Reduce Poverty?</title><link href="/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Minimum Wage Reduce Poverty?" /><published>2019-03-08T23:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-08T23:45:00+00:00</updated><id>/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A guide to its effective implementation…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimum wage in the United Kingdom is considered one of the most successful
government policies ever implemented. It was intricately planned and structured
over a significant length of time. And with one of the lowest unemployment rates
in Europe, Britain, at first sight, appears to illustrate an accurate balance
between executing a minimum wage policy and preserving the uniform availability
of job opportunities (even if Brexit could change that drastically). Apart from
Britain, even Hong Kong has witnessed an upward trend in median monthly wages of
unskilled workers by 43% in money terms and 20% in real terms between 2010 and 2014. Synchronously, the 2014 Report on Annual Earnings and Hours Survey
published by The Census and Statistics Department outlines inputs from the
Minimum Wage Commission that indicate a fall in the unemployment rate for
elementary occupations from 4.4% in 2010 to 3.3% in 2014. Advocates of minimum
wage legislation argue that it can alter the income distribution in favour of
the low-paid labour force by attenuating the bottom tail of the distribution
model. Opponents criticise its “Disemployment Effect” and emphasise that it
might shrink the share of earnings going to the impoverished and destitute
workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A higher minimum wage, evidently, increases costs for firms. This may curtail
them from hiring the exceptionally low-wage, low-skill workers. David Neumark,
an American labour economist, terms this the “Disemployment Effect”. It is
characterised by the loss of jobs, reduction in working hours, automation, or
the struggle to enter into new jobs. The Disemployment Effect, if necessitated
by a minimum wage, invalidates the purpose of bringing in such a policy in the
first place. But this effect can be overcome. Firms can be offered economic
incentives such as subsidies and grants, to compensate for their increased
costs. Lower taxes and excise duties could also serve as economic incentives,
ensuring more cash is available for businesses to absorb the costs of paying a
higher minimum wage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Disemployment Effect is not the only uncertain outcome of a minimum
wage policy, especially in developing countries. As the minimum wage and poverty
lines are closer to each other in developing nations, an increase in minimum
wage could lift workers out of destitution. Yet, several minimum wage workers in
developing countries are young, work part-time, and belong to high-income
households. Correspondingly, most households in poverty seldom have anyone in
the workforce&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Hence, more often than not, a minimum wage ends up helping
the privileged and ignoring the needy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end poverty, a minimum wage should be determined for households and not
individuals. This will facilitate the redistribution of income to poor families
over low-earners of rich families. Simultaneously, governments must increase
spending on education and skill development to build an economy with a speedily
employable workforce, hence fostering growth and development. A minimum wage
policy also needs to tackle the problem of incomplete and irregular legal
coverage. Although minimum wages seem to be extensively applicable, in several
cases the coverage is ineffective and disregards those most in need of social
security, such as domestic workers or homeworkers. By neglecting a few crucial
sectors of the economy, we fail to fully utilise the potential of minimum wage
legislation. Even though legal coverage of the minimum wage developed from the
mid-2000’s to the late 2000’s in India and South Africa, it covered only about
70% of low-paid workers by late 2000’s; in Peru, domestic workers were barred
from the statutory minimum wage&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Research suggests that weak legal coverage
may at times ignore around one-third of all wage earners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may confront this perplexity by undertaking comprehensive legislation that
gratifies all sectors of an economy, and by ensuring that such legislation is
strictly enforced. This, while a herculean task, can be accomplished by the
extensive and intensive consultation of all stakeholders and a thorough analysis
of a variety of socioeconomic and employment data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimum wage is fast becoming a universally adopted policy today and the
principal question is how to operate the system in order to maximise its
benefits. A conscientiously devised minimum wage policy can relegate low pay,
inequalities, and poverty, at little or no adverse cost to employment. Yet, the
minimum wage either continues to be low in many countries, or applies solely to
certain select sectors. But with a little more fine-tuning, as I have suggested,
I believe it is possible to shape an effective minimum wage policy that
successfully reduces poverty and income inequalities across countries without
hurting the job market.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivang Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">A guide to its effective implementation… The minimum wage in the United Kingdom is considered one of the most successful government policies ever implemented. It was intricately planned and structured over a significant length of time. And with one of the lowest unemployment rates in Europe, Britain, at first sight, appears to illustrate an accurate balance between executing a minimum wage policy and preserving the uniform availability of job opportunities (even if Brexit could change that drastically). Apart from Britain, even Hong Kong has witnessed an upward trend in median monthly wages of unskilled workers by 43% in money terms and 20% in real terms between 2010 and 2014. Synchronously, the 2014 Report on Annual Earnings and Hours Survey published by The Census and Statistics Department outlines inputs from the Minimum Wage Commission that indicate a fall in the unemployment rate for elementary occupations from 4.4% in 2010 to 3.3% in 2014. Advocates of minimum wage legislation argue that it can alter the income distribution in favour of the low-paid labour force by attenuating the bottom tail of the distribution model. Opponents criticise its “Disemployment Effect” and emphasise that it might shrink the share of earnings going to the impoverished and destitute workforce. A higher minimum wage, evidently, increases costs for firms. This may curtail them from hiring the exceptionally low-wage, low-skill workers. David Neumark, an American labour economist, terms this the “Disemployment Effect”. It is characterised by the loss of jobs, reduction in working hours, automation, or the struggle to enter into new jobs. The Disemployment Effect, if necessitated by a minimum wage, invalidates the purpose of bringing in such a policy in the first place. But this effect can be overcome. Firms can be offered economic incentives such as subsidies and grants, to compensate for their increased costs. Lower taxes and excise duties could also serve as economic incentives, ensuring more cash is available for businesses to absorb the costs of paying a higher minimum wage. However, the Disemployment Effect is not the only uncertain outcome of a minimum wage policy, especially in developing countries. As the minimum wage and poverty lines are closer to each other in developing nations, an increase in minimum wage could lift workers out of destitution. Yet, several minimum wage workers in developing countries are young, work part-time, and belong to high-income households. Correspondingly, most households in poverty seldom have anyone in the workforce. Hence, more often than not, a minimum wage ends up helping the privileged and ignoring the needy. To end poverty, a minimum wage should be determined for households and not individuals. This will facilitate the redistribution of income to poor families over low-earners of rich families. Simultaneously, governments must increase spending on education and skill development to build an economy with a speedily employable workforce, hence fostering growth and development. A minimum wage policy also needs to tackle the problem of incomplete and irregular legal coverage. Although minimum wages seem to be extensively applicable, in several cases the coverage is ineffective and disregards those most in need of social security, such as domestic workers or homeworkers. By neglecting a few crucial sectors of the economy, we fail to fully utilise the potential of minimum wage legislation. Even though legal coverage of the minimum wage developed from the mid-2000’s to the late 2000’s in India and South Africa, it covered only about 70% of low-paid workers by late 2000’s; in Peru, domestic workers were barred from the statutory minimum wage. Research suggests that weak legal coverage may at times ignore around one-third of all wage earners. We may confront this perplexity by undertaking comprehensive legislation that gratifies all sectors of an economy, and by ensuring that such legislation is strictly enforced. This, while a herculean task, can be accomplished by the extensive and intensive consultation of all stakeholders and a thorough analysis of a variety of socioeconomic and employment data. The minimum wage is fast becoming a universally adopted policy today and the principal question is how to operate the system in order to maximise its benefits. A conscientiously devised minimum wage policy can relegate low pay, inequalities, and poverty, at little or no adverse cost to employment. Yet, the minimum wage either continues to be low in many countries, or applies solely to certain select sectors. But with a little more fine-tuning, as I have suggested, I believe it is possible to shape an effective minimum wage policy that successfully reduces poverty and income inequalities across countries without hurting the job market.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities</title><link href="/Micro-Economies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities" /><published>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/Micro-Economies</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Micro-Economies">&lt;p&gt;Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less
than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce,
University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a
population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present,
there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of
countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are
prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite
their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of
the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic
systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or
island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they
are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as
the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several
countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods
produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports
costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected
to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces
labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work.
Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of
labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face
‘&lt;em&gt;diseconomies of size’&lt;/em&gt; due to low demand and high production costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence,
these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited
range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to
poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact
that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more
than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted
poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low
GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a
GNP per capita of less than $500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It
is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to
providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as
well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge
amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as
well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population.
This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the
case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is
low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on
building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways,
and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign
investment never comes into these countries, creating a &lt;em&gt;chakravyuh&lt;/em&gt; (vicious cycle) of poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies
are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service,
in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population,
the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are
ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over
the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident
from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40%
in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact,
imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these
countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to
international events and shocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering
paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial
crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an
impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two
years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the
standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means
that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as
compared to the world average of 3.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the
parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is
beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African
island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific
depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried
out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as
well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the
fate of these micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their
children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund,
the International Development Association and various other regional and
international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for
developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies
provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these
grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different
micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and
increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains
of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and
the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete
disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is
necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to
look towards the international community and the United Nations for their
sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk
management. &lt;em&gt;Debt bells ringing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as
well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access
to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have
Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant
foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources
from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of
income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on
their territory (China and India are watching closely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and
multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most
prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the
mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by
deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation,
including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax
haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no
exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Alberto Alesina said in his book &lt;em&gt;Size of Nations&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s
degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they
wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single
commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which
have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their
economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers
or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception
than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop,
progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence
of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way
in bringing a change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhishek Sancheti</name></author><category term="economics" /><category term="headline" /><category term="trending" /><summary type="html">Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce, University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present, there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world. These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies. Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work. Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face ‘diseconomies of size’ due to low demand and high production costs. Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence, these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a GNP per capita of less than $500. Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population. This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways, and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign investment never comes into these countries, creating a chakravyuh (vicious cycle) of poverty. With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service, in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population, the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over the rest of the world. Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40% in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact, imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to international events and shocks. Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as compared to the world average of 3.2%. These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the fate of these micro-economies. However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund, the International Development Association and various other regional and international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different micro-economies. One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to look towards the international community and the United Nations for their sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk management. Debt bells ringing. In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on their territory (China and India are watching closely). Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation, including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits. As Alberto Alesina said in his book Size of Nations: “Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.” Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop, progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way in bringing a change.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Corbyn to Podemos, Don’t Forgive Maduro’s Cheerleaders</title><link href="/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Corbyn to Podemos, Don't Forgive Maduro’s Cheerleaders" /><published>2019-03-07T04:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-07T04:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos</id><content type="html" xml:base="/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos">&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is on fire. Two decades of mismanagement by a corrupt regime has left
its people starving, fleeing, and cowering from government death squads. Venezuela,
the world’s most oil-rich state is in ruins. The extent of the spoil has been so
thorough that it now imports more oil from the United States than it produces.
Much of this is because of the severe deficiency of refinement infrastructure.
In addition, hyperinflation has been a major battle for the administration. For
a nation which does not print its own currency, this surely is a cruel fate.
Cash money has become a rare sight. Probably due to the fact that the government
can barely afford to buy new currency. Last Christmas, a plane from Basingstoke
(a quaint Hampshire town) touched down in Caracas, filled with newly printed
Bolivars. The lowest valued note onboard was already worth less than a single US
cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the problems for the Venezuelans weren’t just limited to financial setbacks.
It includes corruption, violence, and extreme disparity within the economic
classes―which fueled tensions. In 2016, the incumbent President, Nicolas Maduro
created a new wing of the police, the Special Action Force or FAES. Various
human rights groups have accused them of acting as Death Squads. They have
allegedly entered low-income neighbourhoods to harass and, sometimes, execute
the rivals and competitors of the regime. Since the beginning of the year,
forty-three protestors have been confirmed to have died in clashes with the
police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicolas Maduro and his predecessor, Hugo Chavez have taken actions that have had
a tragic effect on the lives of ordinary Venezuelans. Over 3.4 million people
now live as refugees, desperately trying to flee poverty. The wealthiest nation
of South America, just a few decades ago, is now a page out of a book and
nothing more. But what makes the Maduro regime so unique is the support it gets
from many useful idiots across the developed world. While dictators like Robert
Mugabe in Zimbabwe and Bashar Al-Assad in Syria have arguably committed far more
heinous crimes against their own people, neither can boast such a committed fan
base in wealthy nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Corbyn, the leader of the UK Labour Party and Her Majesty’s Most Loyal
Opposition is an avid fan of the Chavez-Maduro regime. He has personally called
Maduro to congratulate him on an election victory in 2016. This is the very
election which was decried as unfair by Human Rights Watch. The Labour Party is
the second largest party in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the
largest political movement in Europe by membership. Its prominent members
include Owen Jones who wrote in 2012, “Chavez’s critics in the West are entitled
to passionately disagree with him. But it’s time they stopped pretending he is a
dictator”. That was 4 years after Chavez expelled Human Rights Watch from the
country. In 2014, Corbyn’s top lieutenant John Mcdonnell said, “Here you had the
contrast between capitalism in crisis, and socialism in action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this article isn’t about the asinine debate on whether the Venezuelan
economy can truly be considered socialist or not. I personally doubt a regime as
corrupt as Chavez’s could have ever carried out the necessary reforms to
institute a socialist economy. But we should remember the man who may soon be
the UK Chancellor of The Exchequer (Finance Minister), lauded Venezuela a
‘socialist’ regime, saying it was a nation worth emulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greek Prime Minister, Alexis Tsipras, was the only European head of
government who had attended Hugo Chavez’s funeral, way back in 2012. There he
praised Venezuela as an anti-capitalist model country, and has since remained
friendly with the Venezuelan regime. This has continued over the current crisis.
It should be noted that Tsipras hasn’t instituted the type of authoritarian
reforms of the Chavez and Maduro regimes for his own country. But his fondness
for their government begs the question: what would he have done if Syriza had
achieved a majority in the Greek Parliament or if he didn’t have the European
Union overseeing his administration ready to sanction it for anti-democratic
policies. Jean-Luc Melancon, the leader of the French Left, also in the past,
praised the Chavez regime. In 2013, he described it as a “source of
inspiration”. However, since then, he has changed his mind claiming that he
doesn’t “support dictatorship”, and that he has “never supported dictatorship
anywhere in the world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is Podemos, the Spanish Left-wing party. Since, its foundation, it
has had a special relationship with the Bolivarian regime in Venezuela. Several
of its founders, including its leader Pablo Iglesia, have been economic advisors
to the Venezuelan government. Iglesia once called Venezuela “one of the most
consolidated democracies in the world”. According to a think tank, which is
close to the party, Podemos has received millions in funding from the regime, as
published in the Spanish newspaper ABC. Nevertheless, Iglesia has now u-turned
on his support for the dictatorship. Earlier this year, he was caught on record
saying, “I don’t agree with some of the things I said in the past, and I believe
that the political and economic situation in Venezuela is disastrous. To rectify
in politics is a good thing”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few months, voters all across Europe will have the chance to vote, in free
and fair elections, for who they want as their representatives in the European
Parliament. Voting is a hard-fought privilege held by far less than half of the
world’s population. It was once the right that the people of Venezuela had. If
the European Left’s radical leaders, who supported Chavez and Maduro, win the
elections they are, of course, unlikely to institute the authoritarian policies
as seen in Venezuela. This is because Europe’s civic institutions are strong and
it’s people remember what a dictator looks like. Having said that though, we
must remember that the support of the radical Left for the Venezuelan regime is
a cause for grave concern to the lovers of democracy. It resonates the hard
truth, as to what type of policies all these leaders would like to introduce, if
only they had the power they believe they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reuben Pritchard</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Venezuela is on fire. Two decades of mismanagement by a corrupt regime has left its people starving, fleeing, and cowering from government death squads. Venezuela, the world’s most oil-rich state is in ruins. The extent of the spoil has been so thorough that it now imports more oil from the United States than it produces. Much of this is because of the severe deficiency of refinement infrastructure. In addition, hyperinflation has been a major battle for the administration. For a nation which does not print its own currency, this surely is a cruel fate. Cash money has become a rare sight. Probably due to the fact that the government can barely afford to buy new currency. Last Christmas, a plane from Basingstoke (a quaint Hampshire town) touched down in Caracas, filled with newly printed Bolivars. The lowest valued note onboard was already worth less than a single US cent. But the problems for the Venezuelans weren’t just limited to financial setbacks. It includes corruption, violence, and extreme disparity within the economic classes―which fueled tensions. In 2016, the incumbent President, Nicolas Maduro created a new wing of the police, the Special Action Force or FAES. Various human rights groups have accused them of acting as Death Squads. They have allegedly entered low-income neighbourhoods to harass and, sometimes, execute the rivals and competitors of the regime. Since the beginning of the year, forty-three protestors have been confirmed to have died in clashes with the police. Nicolas Maduro and his predecessor, Hugo Chavez have taken actions that have had a tragic effect on the lives of ordinary Venezuelans. Over 3.4 million people now live as refugees, desperately trying to flee poverty. The wealthiest nation of South America, just a few decades ago, is now a page out of a book and nothing more. But what makes the Maduro regime so unique is the support it gets from many useful idiots across the developed world. While dictators like Robert Mugabe in Zimbabwe and Bashar Al-Assad in Syria have arguably committed far more heinous crimes against their own people, neither can boast such a committed fan base in wealthy nations. Jeremy Corbyn, the leader of the UK Labour Party and Her Majesty’s Most Loyal Opposition is an avid fan of the Chavez-Maduro regime. He has personally called Maduro to congratulate him on an election victory in 2016. This is the very election which was decried as unfair by Human Rights Watch. The Labour Party is the second largest party in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the largest political movement in Europe by membership. Its prominent members include Owen Jones who wrote in 2012, “Chavez’s critics in the West are entitled to passionately disagree with him. But it’s time they stopped pretending he is a dictator”. That was 4 years after Chavez expelled Human Rights Watch from the country. In 2014, Corbyn’s top lieutenant John Mcdonnell said, “Here you had the contrast between capitalism in crisis, and socialism in action.” Now, this article isn’t about the asinine debate on whether the Venezuelan economy can truly be considered socialist or not. I personally doubt a regime as corrupt as Chavez’s could have ever carried out the necessary reforms to institute a socialist economy. But we should remember the man who may soon be the UK Chancellor of The Exchequer (Finance Minister), lauded Venezuela a ‘socialist’ regime, saying it was a nation worth emulating. The Greek Prime Minister, Alexis Tsipras, was the only European head of government who had attended Hugo Chavez’s funeral, way back in 2012. There he praised Venezuela as an anti-capitalist model country, and has since remained friendly with the Venezuelan regime. This has continued over the current crisis. It should be noted that Tsipras hasn’t instituted the type of authoritarian reforms of the Chavez and Maduro regimes for his own country. But his fondness for their government begs the question: what would he have done if Syriza had achieved a majority in the Greek Parliament or if he didn’t have the European Union overseeing his administration ready to sanction it for anti-democratic policies. Jean-Luc Melancon, the leader of the French Left, also in the past, praised the Chavez regime. In 2013, he described it as a “source of inspiration”. However, since then, he has changed his mind claiming that he doesn’t “support dictatorship”, and that he has “never supported dictatorship anywhere in the world”. Then there is Podemos, the Spanish Left-wing party. Since, its foundation, it has had a special relationship with the Bolivarian regime in Venezuela. Several of its founders, including its leader Pablo Iglesia, have been economic advisors to the Venezuelan government. Iglesia once called Venezuela “one of the most consolidated democracies in the world”. According to a think tank, which is close to the party, Podemos has received millions in funding from the regime, as published in the Spanish newspaper ABC. Nevertheless, Iglesia has now u-turned on his support for the dictatorship. Earlier this year, he was caught on record saying, “I don’t agree with some of the things I said in the past, and I believe that the political and economic situation in Venezuela is disastrous. To rectify in politics is a good thing”. In a few months, voters all across Europe will have the chance to vote, in free and fair elections, for who they want as their representatives in the European Parliament. Voting is a hard-fought privilege held by far less than half of the world’s population. It was once the right that the people of Venezuela had. If the European Left’s radical leaders, who supported Chavez and Maduro, win the elections they are, of course, unlikely to institute the authoritarian policies as seen in Venezuela. This is because Europe’s civic institutions are strong and it’s people remember what a dictator looks like. Having said that though, we must remember that the support of the radical Left for the Venezuelan regime is a cause for grave concern to the lovers of democracy. It resonates the hard truth, as to what type of policies all these leaders would like to introduce, if only they had the power they believe they deserve.</summary></entry></feed>