<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-06T19:47:48+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Picture of Dorian Gray</title><link href="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Picture of Dorian Gray" /><published>2019-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray">&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest
compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as
I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of
St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a
composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could
distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s
&lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of
&lt;em&gt;Die Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Figaro&lt;/em&gt; with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker
dramas, &lt;em&gt;The Turn of the Screw&lt;/em&gt; or perhaps &lt;em&gt;Owen Wingrave&lt;/em&gt;. I was mistaken. It
took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking
some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera
into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many
more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s
effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act
show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its
completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the
public by the wonderful people at &lt;em&gt;LoveOpera&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, no small part of me is turned towards retrospection: three years ago,
almost to the day of writing, I was asked by Jay Wolfe of &lt;em&gt;The Wolfian&lt;/em&gt; to write
a small article on the subject of setting about composing something of this
magnitude. I did my best – I had, at that point, only just finished &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;’s
Prologue (the –and-a-half act) and had only vague ideas what the rest of the
opera had in store for me. Nevertheless, I now look back upon that article and
see that there is a compositional thread that stayed with me throughout the
process, even from the pre-Foxian beginnings. I knew then as I know now that
Wilde’s novella brought together the myriad elements of philosophy, dark humour,
and gothic horror. Musically, that meant each of these strands had to be
individually emphasised without any single one dominating the general effect of
the music. Of course, this was no easy task. But I did find a solution, if I can
really claim to have one. I studied closely how the likes of Henry Purcell,
Benjamin Britten, Claude Debussy, and Richard Wagner musically synthesised
various themes in their operas. I also made it a point to follow the man
himself: Oscar Wilde, taking note of how he balanced these themes to create such
a fine piece of art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that there is a fortunate divide between the Prologue of the work and the
two Acts. It is a divide that I touched on in my previous article: much of the
dialogue of the Prologue, taken from the first two chapters of Wilde’s work,
consists of Basil, the painter, philosophising with his friend Lord Henry, the
prime corruptive influence upon young Dorian before the boy actually arrives to
kick-start the drama. This leads to moments of the Prologue that feel somewhat
slower than the rest of the show, a turgid calm before a hopefully more driving
roller-coaster of a storm. And I believe this is as it should be, but I may well
be wrong – I shall have to see after I hear from the audiences in July and
September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as the previous article focussed so heavily upon the Prologue, on
account of the fact that neither of the other two acts actually yet existed, I
feel it may be much more suitable for us now to turn ourselves to a brief
musical guided tour, as it were, through at least some of the show. Therefore,
some introductions must be made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; has a main cast of six – it was quite a task to reduce down the large,
high-society focused drama into six characters, but what else is a chorus for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The characters are, in order of appearance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basil Hallward, (tenor) - the artist who holds Dorian as his muse,
unfortunately;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Henry “Harry” Wotton, (baritone) - a modern-day Mephistopheles with a
heart, somewhere deep down in there;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dorian himself, (mezzo-soprano) - I had this idea when watching Mozart’s
&lt;em&gt;Marriage of Figaro&lt;/em&gt; and realising Dorian and the teenage sex-pest Cherubino,
also a trouser-role, are not so very much alike if you gave the latter money and
immortality;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lady Victoria Wotton, (soprano) - aside from a few witty flashes in the novella,
Henry’s wife is reduced to acting off-screen, as it were. Jamie and I changed
that, as you will see;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sybil Vane, (soprano) – Poor Sybil. To fall in love with an as-yet not fully
corrupted Dorian, only to so quickly jilted after one bad night on the stage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Vane, (bass) – Sybil’s brother arrives in the 2nd Act, and will avenge his
sister… or, at least, he’ll try his utmost, raging best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind these six there comes a host of minor characters that make up our show’s
chorus: the society lords and ladies, the audience of a run-down theatre, the
whores and opium fiends that make up the rich tapestry that is Victorian London
in Oscar’s (and our) minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Act one begins, with Dorian, now in possession of Basil’s masterful
portrait of him, sitting alone in Lord Henry’s living-room, awaiting his friend.
It is here that I can illustrate the first influence of any of the composers
mentioned in my previous article: the act opens with a harp gesture (Fig. 1)
that is at once a textural back-cloth for the scene, and also acts as a
leitmotif, to borrow from Richard Wagner’s vocabulary. The theme, extended by
the strings and later the flute, can be said, therefore to be a genius loci – it
represents the building, musically, suggesting the luxurious, lavish
surroundings of the Wottons’ town-house. When, therefore, it reappears to
introduce use to Dorian’s own house, in both acts one and two, it possibly tells
us something about Dorian’s own following of Henry’s teachings – indeed, this
ability to manipulate melodies is an incredibly useful tool, compositionally, as
melodies are often indelibly linked with the emotion, location or character
alongside which they first appear. Thus, the twisting of a motif by introducing
it to a new context can suggest many things to an audience – watch out for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we hear Henry’s own leitmotif, languorous triplets in the horns, except
this time it isn’t Henry, but his wife, whom neither we nor Dorian are expecting
to see. She has some interesting things to say on the subject of Wagner, too: “I
like Wagner’s music more than anyone’s. It is so loud that one can talk the
whole time without other people hearing what you say!” (I must say, I hope no
one uses &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; to gossip under!) Nevertheless, as Victoria is here only for
some witty repartee and to avoid her husband at this point in the drama, when
Henry does finally show up she departs in short order – it’s not the healthiest
of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry’s real entrance is accompanied by a different sort of music, though. He’s
a little drunk, and announces himself with a lop-sided little fanfare, before
launching in a duettino of banter with Dorian, which again manipulates his own
triplet motif into some fast-paced patter, as Dorian tells us that he has fallen
in rapturously love with an actress, “a rather commonplace debut” as Henry puts
it, named Sybil Vane. This confession leads to the first overtly romantic music
of the evening, as Dorian narrates how he came across his new sweetheart in a
sequence that is, structurally, a reflection of the early-Verdian style of
cantabile-cabaletta, but turned entirely on its head: in Verdi, or indeed,
Donizetti or Bellini, a cantabile-cabaletta consists of (as the name suggests) a
slow, more relaxed section that is very ‘sing-able’ followed by a more
barnstorming or pyrotechnic section. However, here Dorian sings them the wrong
way ‘round: first a fast, rhythmically twisting section (Fig. 2) describing her
beauty, and then two slower sections discussing first her acting ability and
then how lost he is in the romance of it all (Fig. 3), before the scene peters
out, and we transition to the next night, at the theatre&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, the theatre scene. This was a lot of fun to devise – I recall Jamie
gesticulating wildly as he explained to me that this was to be no great work of
Shakespearean spectacle, but a farcical experience, with a wooden, nervous
Juliet and a stout, middle-aged Romeo with a bit too much gut and far too much
Brian Blessed. And in the midst of it all sits Dorian, trying desperately to
convince Henry and Basil that Sybil is, in truth, a wonderful actress and well
worth his love. Therefore, I put my comedy hat on, and have tried to construct a
woeful imitation of Gilbert and Sullivan as an overture to this
play-within-a-play. There is no emotional core to this moment, no attempt to tug
at the heart-strings as one would expect from an overture to a performance of
&lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt;. It’s just dross. As is the acting that follows it, but for
that I had to get more creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I set up a sense of scurrying tension within the on-stage audience by way
of a tiny fragment of melody that, when repeated over and over, becomes an
ostinato-texture which, much like the harp motif of Fig. 1, serves as a backdrop
for the entire scene. Over this, both our trio and the on-stage audience mutter
between each other until the curtain comes up and we see a sequence of three
scenes from the play, each successively worse: steadily, we progress from thin,
dull orchestration and bad singing, add in meandering, meaningless chromaticism
and unstable harmonies, and finally top it all off with some bombastic as the
crowd get steadily more unimpressed with the performance (Fig. 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I write quite good ‘bad’ music, sometimes…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, Basil and Henry resolve to leave before the end of the show and
leave Dorian behind to talk to poor Sybil. Poor Sybil who is, in point of fact,
much more vivacious in real life than she ever was on stage, and so very much in
love with Dorian, as illustrated by her motif, which is itself an extension of
Dorian and the portrait’s own melody (Fig. 5, showing Dorian’s melody on top,
and Sybil’s extension below it), before flourishing into a much more lush
romantic gesture, and finally a re-hashing of one of Dorian’s own earlier
cantabile sections. She is so consumed by what could kindly be called her
infatuation or, worse, obsession with Dorian that she does not create her own
music, merely adopts his. And yet, in his refusal, Dorian himself mimics Henry’s
own more impassioned music from the Prologue; neither of them is, in truth, free
from obsessive thoughts about another person, or the ideals that they represent.
Unfortunately for Sybil, Dorian’s ideals lead him to abandon her, storm out,
have a wild night on the town before returning to his house, alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 5&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cap the act off, Jamie and I had a bit of a predicament: the novella contains
a long time-skip before a certain climactic scene that we both wanted to include
as the finale of Act One. Whilst this reads incredibly well on paper – as the
years pass, Dorian becomes more and more corrupt until he goes beyond the pale –
this does not work near so well on a stage, where the audience is best served by
having a cohesive narrative, at least according to critics as far back as
Aristotle and the classical unities (of action, time and place). Thus, we
conflated several scenes from the book in order to make this finale to Act One
as impactful as can be. As Dorian recovers from his hangover, portrayed by slow,
chromatic triplet descents, his torpor is interrupted by the arrival of Basil,
who has bad news. This is the first change, as Wilde has Henry come to Dorian’s
house to deliver this particular news – that Sybil has committed suicide. Basil
is, therefore, able to finally act more overtly and lovingly towards his muse.
This also sets up a further conflation, as there are two scenes of Basil, in his
moralising fashion, trying to help Dorian. In the one, he asks to see the
portrait and is rebuffed, and on the other, many years later, Dorian crosses a
line. Basil is never seen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we conflated these three scenes into one, I introduced, musically, one last
thing: the poor soprano playing Sybil would otherwise have only two scenes, and,
feeling sorry for her, I wrote her voice into the scene. Dorian, so affected by
the news of her death, can almost hear her calling out to him, turning a duet
into a trio, and having the final action of the scene, and indeed of the first
half of the Opera, become the deaths of two of &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;’s principals (Game of
Thrones style). I don’t believe I know of another opera where both the tenor and
the soprano are killed before we make it half-way. That ought to make an impact
– and hopefully leave the audience as eager to see the conclusion of the drama
as you may well be to read the final instalment of this little-guided tour
through my opera!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Olly Bowes</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s The Picture of Dorian Gray into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of Die Fledermaus or Figaro with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker dramas, The Turn of the Screw or perhaps Owen Wingrave. I was mistaken. It took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the public by the wonderful people at LoveOpera.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues</title><link href="/Self-Censorship" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues" /><published>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Self-Censorship</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Self-Censorship">&lt;p&gt;Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One argument is that this only brings online video streaming platforms at par with movie theatres and cinema halls. In India, all movies and series must be mandatorily certified by the Central Board of Film Certification (CBFC) before they are allowed to be screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, or on TV. The CBFC often orders some scenes to be cut or blurred out, failing which viewership is restricted to an adult audience only, or worse still, the film is not allowed to be screened at all. Scenes which are even remotely “obscene”, substantially against social morality, or which have the potential to create social friction are frequently the target of such restrictions. The CBFC’s ambit, however, does not extend to films streamed online. This attempt at self-censorship, based on general guiding principles which largely reflect how films are censored by the CBFC in practice, will – in theory – bring films streamed online on these platforms at par with those screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, and on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of self-censorship is not new. Advertisers, newspapers, TV channels, and other content publishers and disseminators across the world engage in varying levels of restraint in the content they publish, i.e. self-censorship, in-house or through a common self-regulatory mechanism set by a professional body. For instance, advertisers in India abide by the standards set by the Advertising Standards Council of India, a self-regulatory professional body constituted by advertisers and their representatives themselves. This policy of self-censorship by video streaming platforms is hence not unprecedented in the Indian media industry. However, it does raise its own, unique set of concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the unofficial ‘code’ video streaming platforms have committed themselves to at the moment is too vague, general, and broad. It risks building into the process a large degree of discretion, which may manifest itself as arbitrariness. At worst, it may lead to several versions of the same movie or series airing on different platforms. That will surely have disastrous business implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there is a glaring lack of an appeals process. Video streaming platforms appear to have carte blanche so far as self-censorship is concerned. An appeals process needs to be built in for the same reason courts of appeal exist – as a remedy against fallible human judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, where are the filmmakers? Excluding filmmakers and film professionals from the process of censorship leads to peculiar, laughable results. For a case in example, consider the Amazon Prime Original series, &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;. Mrs. Maisel routinely uses expletives while performing as a comedian – that is part of her unique charm. She even exposed her breasts before a club audience while performing an act. These acts get her arrested twice for public indecency, but she continues with them, largely unchanged. That is her unique charm, and it is a central quirk of the character. Now imagine if these expletives were to be censored, and the scene where Mrs. Maisel exposed her breasts cut out. It would strike at the core of the personality of the central character of a show, and therefore ruin the entire show completely. The persons best qualified to appreciate such artistic and cinematic nuances are film professionals, not tech corporates sitting in the air-conditioned offices of a video streaming platform. Delegating the job of censorship to non-film professionals risks this nuance of filmmaking getting lost in the process of censorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-censorship by online video streaming platforms raises some critical concerns which need to be addressed. It is imperative that online video streaming platforms come up with a clearer, more specific and well-defined code to be guided by while censoring content. An appeals process – both in-house and, at the level of a self-constituted professional body – should be built into such a code. Film professionals must be involved in the entire process of framing a code. Content does not fall on a binary scale of obscene/not obscene. Cinematic nuances, amply illustrated by the example – for instance – of &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;, need to be kept in mind both while framing the code and during self-censorship.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sagnik Sarkar</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?</title><link href="/NBA-Midseason-Awards" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?" /><published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/NBA-Midseason-Awards</id><content type="html" xml:base="/NBA-Midseason-Awards">&lt;p&gt;We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable Player: James Harden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many players putting up great numbers for the season so far, but nobody is even close to James Harden. He is putting up 36.7 points, 8.1 assists, 6.7 rebounds, and 2.1 steals per game. He is literally tearing up teams on a nightly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He even went through a five game stretch where he averaged 52.2 points per game. Its beyond impressive how someone can do that against the world’s best basketball players. The Houston Rockets are a much worse team than last year, but they are still contenders because of what Harden is doing this season. If he keeps it up he might just earn back to back MVP awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rookie of the Year: Luka Doncic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into the NBA, Luka was considered the best international prospect ever. So far he has lived up to the hype. He is averaging 19.0 points per game, 6.7 rebounds per game, 5.1 assists per game, and 1.1 steals per game. He is already competing at a high level as a nineteen year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doncic is a wizard with the ball, making shots you can’t believe and constantly coming up with clutch plays for the Mavericks. It’s a great feeling for a team to know that they have their franchise player, and the Mavericks are probably ecstatic knowing that they have their guy. The sky’s the limit for this young star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defensive Player of the Year: Paul George&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far Paul George is having the best offensive season of his career. It’s pretty extraordinary that his defense has been so impressive as well. He leads the NBA in steals and is third in defensive win shares. This award has typically gone to front court players in recent years, which emphasizes how remarkable Paul George’s defensive game has been. Instead of guarding down low, he has the task of locking down the other team’s best perimeter player every night. The Thunder have the best defensive rating in the NBA and a big reason why is because ‘PG’ is leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixth Man of the Year: Domantas Sabonis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabonis has been a key factor to the Pacers success this season. He is nearly averaging a double-double off the bench with 15.0 points and 9.6 rebounds per game. Sabonis is also pulling his weight in defense with one of the better defensive teams in the NBA. The Pacers are at their best when Sabonis is on the court which says a lot since they are currently third in the eastern conference. Why he’s not starting is a matter of logistics but with Victor Oladipo out for the rest of the year look for Domantas to have an even bigger role for the team going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Improved Player: De’Aaron Fox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sacramento Kings have been one of the big surprises this season. They are currently two and a half games out of the playoffs and a big reason for their unpredictable success is the development of De’Aaron Fox. He made a leap from last season going from 11.6 points, 2.8 rebounds, and 4.4 assist per game to 17.6 points, 3.7 rebounds, and 7.2 assist per game. Fox has stepped up as a leader for a team that hasn’t been this close to the playoffs in over a decade. He will be a key factor for the Kings in their late season push for the postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coach of the Year: Mike Budenholzer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Milwaukee Bucks are in the top seed in the East and Budenholzer is a big reason why. The Bucks have made a couple of tweaks this season which have them one of the best teams in the NBA. Offensively the Bucks have made great strides this season as Milwaukee has the second best offensive ranking in the association. With LeBron no longer playing in the East the conference is wide open and the Bucks are the favorites to win it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the second half of the season underway only time will tell if these players and teams can continue to play at the level they have been since the beginning of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;http://basketball-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Basketball-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Jones</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Friday Night Lights to National Champion, What’s Next for Trevor Lawrence?</title><link href="/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Friday Night Lights to National Champion, What’s Next for Trevor Lawrence?" /><published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion</id><content type="html" xml:base="/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion">&lt;p&gt;Just a little over a year ago, a quarterback in Cartersville, Georgia was the #2 overall ranked high school QB in the nation. A couple weeks later, that same quarterback broke the record for career touchdown passes in Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you might not have known his name a year ago, you most definitely know it now. Trevor Lawrence has proved, as a 19-year-old freshman, that the Clemson Tigers have a new sheriff in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although he did not come into the season as the starting QB, Lawrence took over the job only 3 weeks into the season. He immediately lit up the scoreboards and stats sheets with 5 passing touchdowns in his first two games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading the Clemson Tigers to an undefeated, CFP Championship winning season, Lawrence quickly proved that he is ready for college football. He is the first true freshman quarterback to win the CFP National Championship in over 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some analysts say that Lawrence is already showing NFL level talent despite only being in his freshman year. He had a 30 touchdown season with only 4 interceptions. Along with the big arm, his accuracy was dead-on all season with a completion rate of 65.2 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This young man still has 2 maybe 3 years left in his college career. Also, Clemson have multiple true freshman threats at receiver helping Lawrence out. Coach Dabo Swinney said all season that this team was special, and they proved it in the playoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only wonder what will happen to Trevor Lawrence once his college career is over. Does he have the skills to make it to the NFL? Or will he be another bust like many of the other college quarterback superstars in recent history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on what Trevor Lawrence has done so far, it’s difficult to see him becoming a bust. As previously mentioned, he held the number 2 spot among the nation’s high school quarterbacks in his senior year. Because of this many people knew he would be good but were not sure exactly how he would fare in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He proved that he was ready for a college defense, as he embarrassed the Syracuse defense in his first start with a 97.6 quarterback rating and a 194 passing yard game. And with at least two more years of growth, a coach and teammates with 100% confidence behind him (as well as a brand-new ring) Lawrence’s prime is yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sports-reference.com/cfb/&quot;&gt;https://www.sports-reference.com/cfb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Tanberg</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">Just a little over a year ago, a quarterback in Cartersville, Georgia was the #2 overall ranked high school QB in the nation. A couple weeks later, that same quarterback broke the record for career touchdown passes in Georgia.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bullpen on a Rollercoaster</title><link href="/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bullpen on a Rollercoaster" /><published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster">&lt;p&gt;The convention of projecting the economic rise of the East over the West comes with its own ups and downs. The Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership or RCEP is trying to set up a free (not completely, but not important here) trade area between economies with different levels of openness. Consisting of India, China, Japan, South Korea, Australia, New Zealand, and the 10 ASEAN countries, RCEP (if signed) is set to be a major trading bloc in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASEAN bloc, a major part of RCEP, has itself not been completely integrated despite two decades into its existence. The reasons are numerous and quite technical but I am going to pose a twisted version to the readers: why are they even together? Clearly, it is two things: trade and finance. After the 1990’s, they have understood that they all face the same problem, namely, market sentiments of western countries―the &lt;i&gt;wiseguys&lt;/i&gt; with the greenback. The idea of presenting a united front and avoiding a skewed economy which pulls down the entire region is at the heart of the ASEAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In RCEP, however, different countries are at different places on the development curve, and economists can only ponder what they will prioritize upon reckoning with trouble. This can be extended to a related concern: which country is going to be the engine to which the economies chain themselves in RCEP? The core problem lies in the fact that RCEP is mismatch between developing economies and developed economies. To put it in a light manner, countries like India are the bride behind the veil and economies like Singapore play the groom. The bride is expected to keep the veil on for as long as possible and the groom is expected to act against that. And it is this skewered relationship which creates the confusion. Drawing parallels, the bride’s act of “&lt;i&gt;keeping the veil&lt;/i&gt;” symbolises the act of ‘protectionism’, while the groom’s act of trying to remove it symbolises greater ‘openness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topic where China has the smirk is the power of its political economy. Even though US tariffs have blistered China and the wound is still fresh. As is suspected, China is going into RCEP to expand its influence on the world economy. With the volatility of the Indian rupee (INR), oil prices and other assorted delicacies for a cancerous Current Account Deficit (CAD), Indians are sleeping through the negotiations with one eye open, pondering over the numbers but more importantly, over the political issues which have nothing but negative rents for the current Indian government. India is also in the cross-hairs due to the services-led structure of its economy. As there is no backstopping authority regarding RCEP, running huge trade deficits is not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economics is simple here. It is an election year in India and the fiscal taps are going to open; and countries are sitting with their eyes fixed on this. A market as large as India, with an increased demand due to populist government spending, will be exactly what the ‘hawks’ in a free trade agreement would desire. In simple terms, excessive demand in India means more exports for other countries in RCEP. The cost? India’s CAD.
The moment India nudges on the services sector, labour arbitrage (body shopping) will open itself up. Pharmaceuticals too, are a big thorn in some countries’ beds thanks to India, which is referred to as the “&lt;i&gt;pharmacy of the developing world&lt;/i&gt;” due to the cheap generic medicines it can provide. While exporters might see India (with its young population) as a potential market to tap, India’s services and pharma industry themselves threaten to destroy local competition in many RCEP countries.  Add on to this the fact that India has not been a part of any major free trade agreement like this before, and you can see why India can be a problem for both the bloc and itself. India is both threatened (by an explosion of imports from RCEP) and a threat (thanks to its services and pharmaceuticals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, political stability and a quest for a quasi-hyper globalised trade acting along with inward-looking policy making, cannot go hand-in-hand. This is a serious fault line etching itself into existence. All countries want to cash the dividends but not face rents of such an action. There are various tools, from basic common sense to game theoretic models to prove that, with the potential problems/costs all countries face, the RCEP might lead to policies which are de facto tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may ask why am I being so pessimistic about RCEP? There are two reasons – firstly, I can see the chinks in the contract; and secondly, the winds in global trade have become strong. The world does need a major bloc (in terms of GDP) from the oriental side to put certain perspectives on the global macroeconomic spotlight, ranging from the composition of major international institutions to the skewness sewed into global policy actions. RCEP could be a forum for coordinated action and a backstop to the forceful push of adoption to the western macroeconomic framework. It can also provide an opportunity to end the age of capital imperialism. There are numerous reasons why RCEP should be an opportunity pursued but it doesn’t really look like it could be. To that end, I hope the friends see the milk and cookies after the fight on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Adarsh Agarwal</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The convention of projecting the economic rise of the East over the West comes with its own ups and downs. The Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership or RCEP is trying to set up a free (not completely, but not important here) trade area between economies with different levels of openness. Consisting of India, China, Japan, South Korea, Australia, New Zealand, and the 10 ASEAN countries, RCEP (if signed) is set to be a major trading bloc in the world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Order in Chaos</title><link href="/The-Order-in-Chaos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Order in Chaos" /><published>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Order-in-Chaos</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Order-in-Chaos">&lt;p&gt;What is the most common phenomenon that binds together a seemingly bitter reality that manifests itself in nearly everything present in the universe? The answer, believe it or not, is chaos. Deep down we all know what chaos is, we have all experienced it and that’s why we despise it. From crowded halls to cluttered rooms to the endless traffic on the roads, chaos has been a most fundamental feature deeply woven into the fabric of our lives. It is not just in our day-to-day experiences, where chaos reigns. This miraculous yet notorious concept has also made its way into the most certain discipline of science as the “theory of chaos”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While chaos as a feature of human existence has been a cause of concern since time immemorial, its presence in the sciences as a separate area of study is relatively new. From the outset, the prime objective of science has always been about addressing the questions of uncertainty, and uncovering the underlying pattern in what is seemingly disoriented in nature. It was this pursuit of “pattern recognition” that resulted in the blossoming of Newtonian physics along with the belief that mathematics is the ultimate truth capable of generating precise predictions of the future. The universe was assumed to be a mechanical entity operating in accordance with certain unalterable mathematical principles and norms, making order and harmony almost synonymous with reality and existence. This belief, however, was short-lived. The prescient beauty of Newtonian claims of universal order crumbled into nothingness as Einsteinian theories and New Age Physics shook the scientific world. This advent of the new and the bold provided fertile ground for the recognition of “the chaos” hidden in the complexities of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of chaos was first brought into scientific scrutiny by the French mathematician Henri Poincaré in the 1880’s, during his study of the interaction between the planets, where he noted that even the slightest error or change in the initial conditions can produce enormous consequences in the final phenomenon. Later this took the form of the “butterfly effect” advanced by Edward Lorenz a mathematician and meteorologist in the 1960’s, who in spite of his precise calculations, could not predict the weather accurately. His findings culminated in his famous speech “Does the flutter of a butterfly’s wings in Brazil set up a tornado in Texas?” This speech was a major breakthrough in the history of chaos, establishing uncertainty to be the only certainty in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The butterfly effect is inherently present everywhere, be it in the uncertainty of weather mechanisms or in the most remarkable episodes of human history. After all, it was a rejected application to the Vienna Academy of Fine Art that caused the Holocaust and the Second World War. While this may sound utterly ridiculous, it is true that the Academy of Fine Arts did reject the application letter of the very infamous dictator, Adolf Hitler, which, as his autobiography &lt;i&gt;Mein Kampf&lt;/i&gt; itself tells you, culminated in his anti-Semitic feelings, his enrolment in the German army and much later the Second World War! Imagine how the world would have been had the Academy accepted him. History is replete with examples of how things could have turned out differently if only one tiny event were altered in the slightest way: Had Mughal Emperor Jahangir not been drinking buddies with Sir Thomas Roe―an emissary from England―the East India Company might never really have gained a true foothold in India. The very fact that you are reading this article right now makes the world function in a particular way than it would have otherwise. Who knows! Maybe two minutes of procrastination today may make you question your career choices tomorrow and lead you somewhere you never expected to be in 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is where do we find order? Is it even possible to find order in a world, which is so consumed and immersed in chaos? In a world of chaos, how did we attain our present form endowed with thinking and reasoning abilities, when we are in actuality nothing but a combination of molecules? How do simple cells with no central control system divide and differentiate on their own to form a complex foetus in the womb? This is precisely what the English mathematician Alan Turing discussed in his work, &lt;i&gt;The Chemical Basis of Morphogenesis &lt;/i&gt;, where he underscored the miraculously ingrained patterns of self-organisation observed in living organisms. This spontaneous order stems from the “local interactions” within the disordered system, such as a majestic flock of birds soaring high in the sky, or the schools of fish underwater. While these biological systems may seem chaotic when viewed from the standpoint of an individual constituent within the system (i.e. a bird flying in a flock), they exhibit extraordinary order and exquisite patterns, when analysed as a whole from a third person’s perspective (a human observing the flock of birds). It is self-organisation that leads to grains of sands being unconsciously assembled such that they create magnificent sand dunes. Trees, rivers and blood vessels branching into stunning patterns of self-similarity, all beautifully demonstrate this paradox of order in disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that we, in our petty human lives, fail to understand that chaos is nothing but a masked form of order and the key lies not in evading it but embracing it. While chaos may cause momentary frustration, it enables man to see the greater truth, showing him how his pathetic attempts to control everything around him may verily be the cause of his misery. In the words of the Buddha, “&lt;i&gt;Chaos is inherent in all compounded things. Strive on with diligence&lt;/i&gt;”. The beauty of life lies in the perfect blend of both the systems and not merely escaping from one. Embrace the chaos, rise every morning in the expectation of being surprised and learning something new, let life teach you how to have peace in all this turmoil that you cannot control.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">What is the most common phenomenon that binds together a seemingly bitter reality that manifests itself in nearly everything present in the universe? The answer, believe it or not, is chaos. Deep down we all know what chaos is, we have all experienced it and that’s why we despise it. From crowded halls to cluttered rooms to the endless traffic on the roads, chaos has been a most fundamental feature deeply woven into the fabric of our lives. It is not just in our day-to-day experiences, where chaos reigns. This miraculous yet notorious concept has also made its way into the most certain discipline of science as the “theory of chaos”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Oil Trickled Through the Decade</title><link href="/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Oil Trickled Through the Decade" /><published>2019-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade</id><content type="html" xml:base="/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; It all started with the oil. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 20, 2010, the &lt;i&gt;Deepwater Horizon&lt;/i&gt;, an oil drilling rig owned by British Petroleum in the Gulf of Mexico, exploded. It was the largest marine oil spill in the history of the petroleum industry; an estimated 4.9 million barrels of crude oil in over 87 days was supposed to have been spilled. At the time, 126 crew members were on board and eleven workers were never found despite multiple US Coast Guard search operations. The &lt;i&gt;Deepwater Horizon&lt;/i&gt; sank two days later. Official reports say the oil spill has likely harmed or killed approximately 82,000 birds of 102 species, and approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20160130231923/http://news.discovery.com/animals/whales-dolphins/record-dolphin-sea-turtle-deaths-since-gulf-spill-130402.htm&quot;&gt;6,165 sea turtles, and up to 25,900 marine mammals.&lt;/a&gt; The entire rescue, response and cleanup operations took 4 months, 4 weeks and 2 days. British Petroleum paid more than $20 billion in fines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Obama Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;i&gt;The consequences of our inaction are now in plain sight. Countries like China are investing in clean energy jobs and industries that should be here in America. Each day, we send nearly $1 billion of our wealth to foreign countries for their oil. We cannot consign our children to this future. The tragedy unfolding on our coast is the most painful and powerful reminder yet. The time to embrace a clean energy future is now.&lt;/i&gt; “– Barack Obama, June 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 44th President of the United States had just been in office for over a year and yet he had already done the unimaginable. Pulling the economy out of The Great Recession, Obama became a symbol of hope to the post-crash America. &lt;i&gt;Hope&lt;/i&gt;. The most important word on his campaign trail; something he hoped to carry on with him into the White House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on this June morning, addressing the Mississippi crowd, he focused on two things: clean energy and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barack Obama’s struggle towards clean energy has been tough and why shouldn’t it be? When you have an unresponsive Congress who won’t budge because of a Republican majority; when the Congress won’t lend an ear to clean energy because their donors are rich oil magnates; when nobody in your government seems to be rooting for you, what do you do? You look outside. It was at the 2009 United Nations Climate Change Conference at Copenhagen, where he championed the cause of alternative sources of energy for a cleaner environment before member nations of the UNFCCC. It was called the COP15 but they called it ‘&lt;i&gt;Hope&lt;/i&gt;nhagen’.  Unfortunately, things were ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://unfccc.int/resource/docs/2009/cop15/eng/l07.pdf&quot;&gt;taken note of&lt;/a&gt;’ and not ‘adopted’. Things would remain the same in coming years. Obama had the intentions, but people questioned his execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chinese Production or Possibilities?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, China’s economy was on the rise. Just look at the number of billionaires shoot up post-2000:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the turn of the decade, China had a GDP growth rate bordering on 10% with investors high about the potential that the Chinese market had. Even the US markets were looking at the Far East manufacturing powerhouse as a likely rival in the coming future, with experts predicting their economic output to be at par by 2018. China was not only becoming a force to be reckoned with but also a major consumer of oil which was expected to lead a huge boost in global oil demand. But &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/yuwahedrickwong/2018/08/23/the-reality-of-chinas-economic-slowdown/#2c7990464d86&quot;&gt;predictions do not always come true, do they?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring in the Arab Desert&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early years of the decade, just as the world was reeling from the financial disaster that was, the markets were shaken by another catastrophic series of events. A revolution broke out in Tunisia, powered majorly by the newfound abilities of social media. All of a sudden, one country after another started falling to popular uprisings, social violence and major protests with regimes being overthrown in at least five other countries in the Middle East and North Africa region. This time, again, it was the oil markets which faced the brunt of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy and Middle East scholar at Oxford, &lt;a href=&quot;http://rebeleconomy.com/economy/how-the-arab-spring-shook-up-oil-markets/&quot;&gt;Justin Dargin&lt;/a&gt; put it this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Global investors speculated that in the beginning months of the Arab Spring, there could be oil production disruption in the oil-producing Gulf countries. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;

There was the fear that perhaps several important sea-lanes and canals, such as the Strait of Hormuz or the Suez Canal, could be blocked. Furthermore, a bit later on during the Arab Spring, terrorism fears grew and it was thought that the regional power vacuum could encourage militant groups to launch attacks on MENA energy infrastructure.”&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;‘fear premium&lt;/i&gt;’(price rise due to speculations about significant events that will negatively affect markets) caused a surge that the world was definitely not prepared for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sheikh Vs. Shale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2015, Crude oil prices ended &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=13&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiZrMawhvLfAhUQfSsKHdylDWEQFjAMegQIBBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washingtonpost.com%2Fopinions%2Frobert-samuelson-key-facts-about-the-great-oil-crash-of-2014%2F2014%2F12%2F03%2Fa1e2fd94-7b0f-11e4-b821-503cc7efed9e_story.html&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3vc-XO8xnUKemMPPF_GwR9&quot;&gt;below $40 per barrel&lt;/a&gt;, the lowest level since 2009. Prices were above $100 just a year ago, only to be met by an inconceivable bust to the oil markets. Lower crude oil prices in 2015 reflected the sustained excess of crude oil supply over global demand. There had been a major supply gut which caused global crude oil inventories to increase steadily through the year. With China facing a gradual slowdown in its economy, the hopes for higher crude oil demand looked slim. What had happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most surprising fact of all was the conflict in the Middle East, including the Syrian Crisis, had little to no effect on the oil markets. If these forces did not affect the markets, then who did? OPEC? Saudi Arabia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, and No. The Saudis were partially to blame. But they were completely responsible for one of the &lt;i&gt;greatest tricks pulled in economic history&lt;/i&gt;. Since 2008, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ihsmarkit.com/press-release/energy-power/tight-oil-test-us-production-growth-remains-resilient-amid-lower-crude-oi&quot;&gt;US had been steadily increasing&lt;/a&gt; their production of ‘shale’ oil, obtained from organic-rich sedimentary rock found primarily in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2018/11/23/669198912/after-struggles-north-dakota-grows-into-its-ongoing-oil-boom&quot;&gt;Texas and North Dakota&lt;/a&gt;. By 2014, they had shaved off 50% of their imports from OPEC while expanding production by a hefty 70 percent. This boost to supply caused oil prices to drop globally and at a frenetic pace, unchecked by the OPEC disagreeing on whether to lower their production. So Saudi Arabia held out, their Oil Minister saying he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwipvYmKjfLfAhWCXSsKHc33CJcQFjAAegQIAxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.businessinsider.com%2Fr-saudis-naimi-says-opec-will-not-cut-output-however-far-oil-falls-mees-2014-12&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2O8qH49yL33uAaNlFrEgoY&quot;&gt;doesn’t care&lt;/a&gt; even if prices fell to $20 a barrel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon the outwitted Americans realised that the oil prices were falling far too low to maintain production at a sustainable (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiE4Z7FjfLfAhUGbo8KHWIgAiEQFjAAegQICBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Foilprice.com%2FEnergy%2FCrude-Oil%2FThe-Struggle-Continues-For-Bankrupt-Shale-Drillers.html&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1L4UlPPBvNj8c_0HHOwo42&quot;&gt;let alone profitable&lt;/a&gt;) pace. Even at $60-$80 a barrel, shale oil was going for a loss, and a toss. The OPEC had won again, this time, thanks to the clever Saudi Arabians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volatile shifts and the Trump Era&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slump had caused economic contractions in oil-producing countries like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/e1c89278-c33c-3fbe-83ae-985497365cf6&quot;&gt;Brazil&lt;/a&gt; and Venezuela, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-venezuela-economy/venezuelas-economy-shrank-16-5-percent-in-2016-government-idUSKBN1EG06V&quot;&gt;whose economy shrunk by 16.5%&lt;/a&gt;. Even Saudi Arabia took on austerity measures, dropping capital spending by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/saudi-arabia-capital-spending-drop-71-per-cent-2016-amid-cheaper-oil-austerity-a7357666.html&quot;&gt;whopping 71 percent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prayers were finally heard in 2016. The OPEC cut its production in November, which hadn’t happened since the global crisis of ‘08. The cut, which was joined by the likes of Russia, helped push oil costs sharply higher. Crude oil jumped at least five per cent when the OPEC decided to limit production to thirty-three million barrels daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As things seem to be moving towards a period of stability by the end of the year, Donald Trump wins the elections and is ushered into the White House, sailing on a campaign of lambasting the Obama administration and in particular the Iran Deal (JCPOA):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;“John Kerry can’t get over the fact that he had his chance and blew it!”&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/993815373190492160&quot;&gt;Trump wrote&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;“Stay away from negotiations John, you are hurting your country!”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Venezuela whose economy was (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2018/12/15/having-wrecked-the-economy-venezuelas-rulers-see-no-reason-to-change&quot;&gt;and still is&lt;/a&gt;) reeling from Nicholas Maduro’s autocracy, had their production declining so much that they could no longer satisfy their domestic needs, let alone foreign customers. Then they went out and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/venezuela-bolivar-cryptocurrency-economy-crisis-collapse-petro-bitcoin-a8499266.html&quot;&gt;pegged their failing currency to their almost failing oil market&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back in the global oil markets, things were looking better. Prices were rising steadily for the latter half of 2017 and most of 2018, which prompted Trump to tweet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;“Oil prices are too high, OPEC is at it again. Not good!”—US President Donald Trump in June 2018&lt;/i&gt;
This prompted the 23rd June meeting of OPEC ministers in Vienna where they decided to boost production by 1 million barrels/day. Unfortunately, it was soon overshadowed by Trump’s announcement of US withdrawal from the JCPOA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/realdonaldtrump/status/1021234525626609666?lang=en&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action, as the market expected, would result in a greater loss of supply than the initial estimates of 500,000 bl/d. As a result, the market began &lt;a href=&quot;https://oilprice.com/Energy/Crude-Oil/Iran-Claims-Its-Oil-Revenues-Surged-Despite-Sanctions.html&quot;&gt;preparing for the worst&lt;/a&gt;(even overestimating shortages) and sources reveal that OPEC had started to hike its production way before the June 2018 meeting.
Contrary to economic understanding, when November 4th approached, the day the sanctions on Iran would be enforced again, the price of crude oil &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/why-oil-prices-are-plunging-despite-us-sanctions-on-irans-energy-sector-2018-11-01&quot;&gt;dropped like a rock&lt;/a&gt;.Factor in the growing fears of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/chinas-coming-recession-has-pushed-oil-below-60-2018-11-13&quot;&gt;oncoming recession in China&lt;/a&gt; (the world’s largest importer of oil) and the ensuing fall in demand, and we have another spectacular swing again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Year may bring new sentiments but much remains to be seen. Only Oil can affect geopolitics so greatly. Or is it the other way around? At least for the past century, one thing’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It all started with the oil.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shohan Mukherjee</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">It all started with the oil.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Super Bowl LIII: Old School vs. The New Age</title><link href="/Super-Bowl-LIII" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Super Bowl LIII: Old School vs. The New Age" /><published>2019-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Super-Bowl-LIII</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Super-Bowl-LIII">&lt;p&gt;It all comes down to this. 266 games played in the NFL to decide one matchup. It’s the game in which legacies are built, legends are made, and cities are given hope. It’s the Super Bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey to this game could not of been more opposite for these two teams. A team that is trying to build on their incredible dynasty vs. a team that is trying to start one of their own. The best coach in NFL history vs. the best young coach football has ever seen. The best quarterback to ever set foot on a field vs. a young buck that wants to show the world that he’s the next big thing at the quarterback position. The classic David vs. Goliath story. Its experience vs. youth, East Coast vs. West Coast, Belichick vs. McVay, Brady vs. Goff, The New England Patriots vs. The Los Angeles Rams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 3rd these two teams will meet up in Atlanta to battle for the Lombardi Trophy and the right to call themselves World Champions. Playing in Football’s most coveted game isn’t new to the Patriots. This will be Tom Brady’s and Bill Belichick’s ninth Super Bowl together in which they have a previous record of 5-3. For the Rams this will be their first Super Bowl appearance since 2002 when they lost to the Patriots, which actually kick started the Brady and Belichick Patriots dynasty. Like most players on this team this will be the first time Goff and McVay have played on football’s biggest stage. So, the experience factor definitely goes toward the Patriots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about the past, let’s look at the current teams. Both of these teams are stacked on the offensive side of things. The Los Angeles Rams have the third ranked offense in the NFL putting up 32.9 points per game and averaging 421.1 total yards per game. They have dynamic playmakers in running back Todd Gurley (1,251 rushing yards and 17 touchdowns) and wide receiver Brandin Cooks (1,204 receiving yards and 5 touchdowns). At QB they have Jared Goff who is an incredible young quarterback posting a 101.1 QB rating for the season. The man behind the play calling is the best offensive mind football has ever seen, head coach Sean McVay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Patriots aren’t too far behind the Rams offensively. New England has the fourth ranked offense in the NFL racking up 27.2 points per game and a steady 393.4 yards per game. The Patriots have a veteran receiving core lead by future Hall of Famer Rob Gronkowski and the elusive wide receiver Julian Edelman. Both were huge factors in the AFC championship helping Brady convert on many key third downs. The Patriots also have a great running back committee led by Sony Michel who is having a fantastic postseason finding the end zone 5 times already and racking up 242 yards in just two games. And of course, this team is led by arguably the greatest quarterback of all time, Tom Brady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensively these teams aren’t as strong. The Rams have the nineteenth ranked defense in the NFL (358.6 yards per game) and the Patriots have the twenty first (359.1 yards per game). But the difference between the two teams’ defenses are the playmakers that the Rams possess. They got straight dudes on the defensive side. LA has two great interior linemen in Ndamukong Suh and the defensive player of the year Aaron Donald (led the NFL with 20.5 sacks). To complement their front seven, they have Aqib Talib and Marcus Peters, two veteran cornerbacks who have come up big in this postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like every Super Bowl that the Patriots have played in, we are bound to have a very competitive and entertaining game. Looking at the rosters the Rams have by far the best team. But the Patriots aren’t built on having a team full of stars, they never have been. They play brilliantly as a team rather than individuals. They have the richest history in the NFL and the system that Belichick has created makes it impossible not to succeed. They have more experience than anybody in NFL history. That’s why Tom Brady should get his sixth ring. The New England Patriots are the safer bet to repeat history and defeat the Rams in the Super Bowl again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats via &lt;a href=&quot;http://pro-football-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Pro-football-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Jones</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">It all comes down to this. 266 games played in the NFL to decide one matchup. It’s the game in which legacies are built, legends are made, and cities are given hope. It’s the Super Bowl.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Golden Era Continues with The Warriors</title><link href="/The-Golden-Era-Continues" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Golden Era Continues with The Warriors" /><published>2019-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Golden-Era-Continues</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Golden-Era-Continues">&lt;p&gt;Year in, year out, winning is the goal at the beginning of the season. And every season the reigning champion is celebrated for conquering the beast that is a playoff run. Unless that team is the Golden State Warriors. For them it’s just another day (or season rather) at the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past four years in the NBA The Warriors have created a dynasty like no other. They have made four consecutive trips to the NBA finals, winning three of them and solidifying their team’s place in the record books forever. This current run of dominance in the NBA seems to be slowing down no time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DeMarcus Cousins Finally Joins the Splash Family&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors quickly jumped into the spotlight and became one of the best, if not the best team ever. They dominate opponents with their ability to heat up like no team in history. They are virtually unbeatable with their four All Stars Steph Curry, Kevin Durant, Klay Thompson and Draymond Green. Let it be known that the Warriors are the first team in 40 years to have four All Stars on a roster, and now they’ve added their fifth. What does this team have left to improve on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the off season after the 2018 NBA Finals, Warriors General Manager Bob Myers made the move to acquire six-time All Star DeMarcus Cousins to fill the role as the Center for the 2018-2019 season. Cousins signed a 1 year, 5.4 million-dollar deal with the Warriors after tearing his achilles with the New Orleans Pelicans last January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cousins has been on the Injured Reserve all season, but on Friday he was fully cleared to play in his first game with Golden State. It was a good run, but the season might be over for the rest of the competition in the National Basketball Association. Cousins is a great physical presence down low in the post and will force teams to crash down, which ultimately spreads the floor open for teammate sharpshooters Steph Curry and Klay Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Men Can Shoot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors are respected for their three-point excellence and have many players with the ability to shoot from anywhere on the court. DeMarcus Cousins is one of the best shooting big men in the league, shooting a career 33.8 percent from behind the arc. His addition to the team now allows the Warriors to be even more deadly from beyond the three-point line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors’ dominance over the past few years came out of nowhere and they have no doubt planted themselves in the history books. The addition of DeMarcus Cousins should strike fear in the rest of the NBA, and who knows who else the Warriors could acquire? With three championship titles in four seasons (winning back-to-back in 2017 and 2018), this team shows no signs of slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tyler Pesavento</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">Year in, year out, winning is the goal at the beginning of the season. And every season the reigning champion is celebrated for conquering the beast that is a playoff run. Unless that team is the Golden State Warriors. For them it’s just another day (or season rather) at the office.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Surplus Transfers between Central Banks and Governments</title><link href="/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Surplus Transfers between Central Banks and Governments" /><published>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers">&lt;p&gt;The trend over the last few decades for greater independence of central banks has raised the question of their financial independence. There has been increasing discussion on whether central banks require capital and if so, how much? The central bank (CB) mainly has two functions: print currency notes that are held by the public, and issue deposits to commercial banks. These are liabilities for which it does not have to pay any interest. At the same time, it purchases financial assets in the form of domestic and foreign government bonds on which it gets interest. As the cost of printing currency is on average 1/7th of the net interest income, the result is a large net interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any time the CB issues currency, undertakes foreign exchange operations, investments, conducts monetary policy operations, or provides liquidity assistance, its net worth is impacted. For central banks, much like commercial banks, the capital buffer or net worth on balance sheets allows them to absorb any potential losses. This means that it’s net worth impacts its ability to achieve monetary policy objectives, which include keeping the inflation rate within the set target. But there are no rules that dictate the amount of capital a central bank must possess. And different countries have taken different approaches based on their unique circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; Up until the 1980’s, CBs in most countries weren’t as independent as we know them to be today. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CBs usually served under the government. They had myriad roles like financing government expenditure, maintaining financial stability, ensuring stability of prices and stimulating economic activity. But they did not have independence. The 90’s and 2000’s saw a trend in favour of independence for central banks to improve long run economic performance. This resulted from a consensus that a central bank independent from the government would be more capable of conducting a credible monetary policy. Market expectations that are more responsive to its actions will make it easier to achieve the monetary policy objectives. The main role of the CBs became the maintenance of price stability, although it was still expected to safeguard financial stability in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When central banks served as an arm of the Ministry of Finance/Treasury, the level of CB capital and rules for distribution of profits to governments weren’t of consequence. As and when CBs across countries were allowed to set a monetary policy without interference from the government, these questions came under contention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When capital becomes sufficiently negative, there are two ways for the central bank to move forward: it has to either be recapitalised; or it has to cover losses on a cash-flow basis from the government. In latter case, which is most common, the government can insist it have discretion over the time and magnitude of the transfer, which effectively places the monetary policy in its hands. Now, the former case may seem more appealing. However, in countries that have negative capital as well as budget deficits, concerns for government interference resurface with recapitalisation as well. A government that is cash-strapped itself would not be able to render a large amount of capital to a CB in need. This was seen in the case of Argentina, where CB losses were 23.5% of the GDP in 1989 and in Jamaica, where losses were 53% of the GDP from 1988 to 1991. Financing these losses implied abandonment of monetary policy objectives that were conflicting with the government’s objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to all these issues plaguing banks with negative capital, central banks with positive amounts of capital and legal independence have been able to resist such pressures. Moreover, it is during banking crises that the CB’s demonstration of its ability to maintain financial stability becomes of utmost importance. A market that believes the central bank may change its policy to avoid losses undermines its credibility. This deters investors and delays restructuring of distressed assets, suppressing fiscal revenue and growth in the process. Indeed, in cases like Peru, Bolivia, and Chile, recapitalisation has led to a gradual improvement in financial position. But it is important to note that in these case studies, recapitalisation was brought about in conjunction with new central bank laws and economic reforms that sought to restore the public’s faith. So, it appears that if credibility is important for success of the monetary policy, the central bank must be financially strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The next question that arises is how much capital do CBs need?&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Peter Stella in a paper written in 2005 identified four different ways that central banks have determined their level of capital:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An absolute nominal value of capital. (e.g. Bank of Canada)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A target ratio of capital to another central bank balance sheet item. (e.g. Bank of Japan)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A target ratio of capital to a macroeconomic variable. (e.g. US Federal Reserve)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on the perceived risks to the solvency of the bank.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the optimal level of capital depends on a large number of factors, such as the macroeconomic environment, how vulnerable the CB is to large financial shocks, its historical legacy, policy obligations (like a fixed or pegged exchange rate) and the volatility of profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(e.g. Reserve Bank of India, Reserve Bank of New Zealand)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also follows that in developing countries and countries with narrow capital markets, the CB should have larger capital. Countries where governments have frequent or constant budget deficits and those with fixed or pegged exchange rates should pursue the same path. It is only after taking into consideration policy objectives, such as price or exchange rate stability, can an ideal level of capital be determined. The determination of the minimum financial strength should also take into account the exposure to risk. Finally, a mechanism and sufficient resources must to be available to absorb the risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the determination of an ideal level of capital, profit in excess of what is required by the central bank has to be transferred to the government. This is another source of discord. Usually the amount to be transferred is decided by both the parties before the budget for the year is set. In some cases, such as Japan, the government decides the quantum. Governments want a higher surplus in order to reduce fiscal deficit or provide assistance to distressed financial institutions, while CBs want to be cautious and keep reserves from profits for unforeseen risk. A debate follows on whether the CB is holding more capital than it requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is little doubt that clear rules for allocation of profits would alleviate some of the strain between the CB and the government. Since the amount is subject to much fluctuation, it is also advisable to have a committee that reviews the surplus distribution policy. The rules should also contain contingencies for cases in which CB capital becomes negative. Clearly specified and transparent principles will safeguard the bank’s independence in the event that CB capital is seriously depleted. Most important of all, it would enhance the credibility of commitment to price stability on the part of both the government and the CB in the public eye.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reema Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The trend over the last few decades for greater independence of central banks has raised the question of their financial independence. There has been increasing discussion on whether central banks require capital and if so, how much? The central bank (CB) mainly has two functions: print currency notes that are held by the public, and issue deposits to commercial banks. These are liabilities for which it does not have to pay any interest. At the same time, it purchases financial assets in the form of domestic and foreign government bonds on which it gets interest. As the cost of printing currency is on average 1/7th of the net interest income, the result is a large net interest.</summary></entry></feed>