<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-04T01:20:25+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Bye, Bye Pinochet: Chile’s Journey Towards a New Constitution</title><link href="/Bye-Bye-Pinochet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bye, Bye Pinochet: Chile’s Journey Towards a New Constitution" /><published>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bye-Bye-Pinochet</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bye-Bye-Pinochet">&lt;p&gt;In 1990, Chile saw the end of President Pinochet’s dictatorship. Yet, they carried his legacy forward for the next three decades. Finally, on October 25, 2020, Chileans voted to get rid of his most prominent legacy: the Constitution formulated during his rule. This change was essential and long overdue and it was a consequence of a year-long protest, the second state of emergency since Pinochet’s rule and mass protests and destruction of public property. Chile had amended its Constitution more than 40 times, yet the fundamental principles of the book remained the same. In essence, the old Constitution had two major issues: &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt;, it favoured the private sector at the cost of public welfare and &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt;, it gave too much power to the President over the proceedings of the Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests were sparked by a rise of 30 pesos in the price of the peak-hour metro fare. While it may seem like a trivial issue for the world, for the people of Chile it was a move that tipped the scales against the government. The pre-referendum system of governance in Chile favoured the market and private sector. The private sector controlled major public services and the government played second fiddle.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile has a two-level healthcare structure, wherein the public chooses between a private healthcare system (called Isapres) and a publicly funded one. The public healthcare system is mired with troubles: they have long queues, and poor staff and medical resources, whereas the private healthcare facilities offer the finest services in a fraction of the time that the public healthcare system takes. Unsurprisingly, the private system is also exorbitantly priced and largely unaffordable for a majority of people in Chile. The government offered no intervention or made zero effort to improve the circumstances. The education system followed a similar track of poorly funded state schools and expensive private universities. The schools are poorly staffed and so resource-starved that parents often have no choice but to take out loans and send their child to a private school if they want proper education for their offspring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poor state of healthcare and education; two of the most important components of a decent standard of living fueled the fire of the revolution in Chile, another catalyst, that perhaps led the protests was the pension scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One of the trademarks of Pinochet’s model was a pension system of individual savings account in private funds known as AFPS, with no contributions by employers or governments” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2020/03/12/can-chile-reinvent-itself&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Santiago, 2020&lt;/a&gt;) The pension system was based on the idea that private savings should have a “70% of final salary” of payout, however, the actual payout was less than the minimum wage in the country. The military did not have a private fund based pension system, which meant that the government was spending more on military pensions than for the rest of the country. This was a force point of contention between the government and the protestors, partly because the AFPS was a pro-market scheme which gave more power to private insurers and consequently aligned perfectly with the right-wing regime’s agendas. However, for the rest of the country, this scheme was a deadly noose. Almost 60% of the country’s population lie in the middle-lower income bracket. This group had to take massive loans to access basic healthcare and education services, and the pension scheme was a beacon of light for these people to be able to pay back those loans to the private companies. However, due to the low payout, the pension scheme created a debt trap.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile has the widest income inequality gap in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), an elite group of countries that Chile became a part of in 2010. It was the first country in Latin America to have joined OECD owing to its rapidly growing economy. However, this economic progress slowed down significantly in 2014. Yet, economic growth was one of the major arguments of pro-Pinochet-era constitution groups.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these arguments may have some merit, it does not negate the fact that there are huge gaps in the distributions of economic gains within the country. The policies and laws favour the elite and rich community. There existed a trade-off between economic growth and basic human needs when there was no need for such a binary. The public has very little trust in the democratic institutions of the country. The revolution was against inequality, it was a revolt against the elite and it has finally come to fruition in the form of a new Constitution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the new Constitution is to make Chile socially-democratic. A committee formed under it will have women forming half its total strength and will focus on improving economic and social equality. The laws would likely amend the structure of important facilities: education, healthcare, housing and pension. It will also aim to reduce the influence of the private sector in the public services sphere and install greater checks and balances on the powers accorded to the President, who until now had powers to prioritise bills debated in the Parliament and be one of the few people in the Congress with the power to introduce fiscal policy bills. The people have high hopes of this change in Chilean political structure, and so far it seems as legitimate a chance as it can be. The people will decide the committee that will make the new Constitution, and there are little chances of the elite in the parliament bull-dozing the proceedings because any new convention would require a minimum of 67% approval in the committee. The focus, now, would shift towards creating an ecosystem where equality and economic growth will sustain together. The new Constitution of Chile is expected to make a decent and healthy standard of life in Chile affordable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In times of heavy anti-democracy movements and governance across the globe, this revolution in Chile is a silver lining in the otherwise dark cloud of global governance and one congratulates the people of Chile on this hard-earned victory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 1990, Chile saw the end of President Pinochet’s dictatorship. Yet, they carried his legacy forward for the next three decades. Finally, on October 25, 2020, Chileans voted to get rid of his most prominent legacy: the Constitution formulated during his rule. This change was essential and long overdue and it was a consequence of a year-long protest, the second state of emergency since Pinochet’s rule and mass protests and destruction of public property. Chile had amended its Constitution more than 40 times, yet the fundamental principles of the book remained the same. In essence, the old Constitution had two major issues: one, it favoured the private sector at the cost of public welfare and two, it gave too much power to the President over the proceedings of the Parliament. The protests were sparked by a rise of 30 pesos in the price of the peak-hour metro fare. While it may seem like a trivial issue for the world, for the people of Chile it was a move that tipped the scales against the government. The pre-referendum system of governance in Chile favoured the market and private sector. The private sector controlled major public services and the government played second fiddle.&amp;nbsp; Chile has a two-level healthcare structure, wherein the public chooses between a private healthcare system (called Isapres) and a publicly funded one. The public healthcare system is mired with troubles: they have long queues, and poor staff and medical resources, whereas the private healthcare facilities offer the finest services in a fraction of the time that the public healthcare system takes. Unsurprisingly, the private system is also exorbitantly priced and largely unaffordable for a majority of people in Chile. The government offered no intervention or made zero effort to improve the circumstances. The education system followed a similar track of poorly funded state schools and expensive private universities. The schools are poorly staffed and so resource-starved that parents often have no choice but to take out loans and send their child to a private school if they want proper education for their offspring.&amp;nbsp; The poor state of healthcare and education; two of the most important components of a decent standard of living fueled the fire of the revolution in Chile, another catalyst, that perhaps led the protests was the pension scheme. “One of the trademarks of Pinochet’s model was a pension system of individual savings account in private funds known as AFPS, with no contributions by employers or governments” (Santiago, 2020) The pension system was based on the idea that private savings should have a “70% of final salary” of payout, however, the actual payout was less than the minimum wage in the country. The military did not have a private fund based pension system, which meant that the government was spending more on military pensions than for the rest of the country. This was a force point of contention between the government and the protestors, partly because the AFPS was a pro-market scheme which gave more power to private insurers and consequently aligned perfectly with the right-wing regime’s agendas. However, for the rest of the country, this scheme was a deadly noose. Almost 60% of the country’s population lie in the middle-lower income bracket. This group had to take massive loans to access basic healthcare and education services, and the pension scheme was a beacon of light for these people to be able to pay back those loans to the private companies. However, due to the low payout, the pension scheme created a debt trap.&amp;nbsp; Chile has the widest income inequality gap in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), an elite group of countries that Chile became a part of in 2010. It was the first country in Latin America to have joined OECD owing to its rapidly growing economy. However, this economic progress slowed down significantly in 2014. Yet, economic growth was one of the major arguments of pro-Pinochet-era constitution groups.&amp;nbsp; While these arguments may have some merit, it does not negate the fact that there are huge gaps in the distributions of economic gains within the country. The policies and laws favour the elite and rich community. There existed a trade-off between economic growth and basic human needs when there was no need for such a binary. The public has very little trust in the democratic institutions of the country. The revolution was against inequality, it was a revolt against the elite and it has finally come to fruition in the form of a new Constitution.&amp;nbsp; The aim of the new Constitution is to make Chile socially-democratic. A committee formed under it will have women forming half its total strength and will focus on improving economic and social equality. The laws would likely amend the structure of important facilities: education, healthcare, housing and pension. It will also aim to reduce the influence of the private sector in the public services sphere and install greater checks and balances on the powers accorded to the President, who until now had powers to prioritise bills debated in the Parliament and be one of the few people in the Congress with the power to introduce fiscal policy bills. The people have high hopes of this change in Chilean political structure, and so far it seems as legitimate a chance as it can be. The people will decide the committee that will make the new Constitution, and there are little chances of the elite in the parliament bull-dozing the proceedings because any new convention would require a minimum of 67% approval in the committee. The focus, now, would shift towards creating an ecosystem where equality and economic growth will sustain together. The new Constitution of Chile is expected to make a decent and healthy standard of life in Chile affordable.&amp;nbsp; In times of heavy anti-democracy movements and governance across the globe, this revolution in Chile is a silver lining in the otherwise dark cloud of global governance and one congratulates the people of Chile on this hard-earned victory.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Conundrum of Crackers: A Deeper Look into Religious Reform</title><link href="/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Conundrum of Crackers: A Deeper Look into Religious Reform" /><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers">&lt;p&gt;The deafening sound of crackers bursting left, right and centre on Diwali&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;often gag the factions who are vociferously at loggerheads with each other. One faction who believes in burning crackers under the garb of ‘Hindu traditions’ and upholding the ‘Hindu way of life’. The other dons a more ‘reformist’ stance of making Hindu practices and traditions amend to the times we live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the Indian government has started to take cognisance of how a night of burning crackers recklessly exacerbates the already alarming rate of air pollution. It did earn the ire of the traditionalists; who, infuriated, got onto primetime slots on news channels and denouncing the move, calling it Hinduphobic and a threat to Hindu practices. Populist Indian anchors such as Arnab Goswami engaged in expected whataboutery by asking Muslim clerics if &lt;em&gt;aazan&lt;/em&gt; doesn't amount to noise pollution every day—with cultural icons like Sonu Nigam further normalising it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration banning firecrackers indeed brings up a rather pertinent question — whether religious reforms should be done by the legislature, or those who practice the faith itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right-wing organisations in India currently promote a more radical form of Hinduism, which often clobbers Hindus with memories of the tumultuous history of Islamic conquest in India — rifling the narrative with the sight of blemished or razed temples, on which many mosques built in that period purportedly stand today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is from this radical branch of Hinduism where the recalcitrancy of refusing to give up firecrackers stems from. Twitter is mostly bombarded with whataboutery whenever and wherever this debate rises; where Muslims sacrificing goats every year doesn't account for slaughter and Christmas trees don't account for &quot;deforestation&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more liberal argument from the same branch has a clarion call to ban crackers indefinitely and not do so only on Diwali as the rationale behind a more &quot;progressive&quot; decision is religionism, not environmentalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing the damage by burning crackers to the aforementioned practices in Islam or Christianity sets regressive precedence — for it doesn't leave room for reform at all. For time immemorial, Hinduism has evolved to fit societal paradigms. Although the precarious issues of caste and Brahminical hegemony show that Hinduism is a far cry away from major reform, Hindus should strive to constantly reform the tenets of the religion, irrespective of how other religions around the world function.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extremists deserve credit for coming up with this ruse where Hindus bear the brunt of being righteous. To its bare-bones, it is analogous to a near-anarchistic milieu — where people refuse to conform to a righteous path because others around them are diabolical.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, accusing the administration of using religionism as an impetus to ban crackers is reflective of yet another trope of the extremist narrative — to live with an inherent 'insecurity' that Hinduism is under a constant threat from monotheism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an insecure demeanour for an ancient religion is a deterrent to an egalitarian and equivocal India, which is set-in-stone in the Constitution. This insecurity is what the right-wing extremists stand for — making people believe in a false, internal enemy who is alleged to be constantly at loggerheads with Hindus and make conniving plots to attack Hinduism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The far-right ruling party’s fervent and Islamophobic attack on ‘love jihad’ — a term promoted by far-right organisations to discredit inter-faith relationships and marriages, is another way that they convolute harmony by victimising Hindu women who ‘fall’ for traps set by ‘well-groomed, handsome’ Muslim men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the country is rifled with intolerance to an extent where there is institutionalised normalisation of coercive endogamy, Hindus should introspect the tenets of the faith that exists in the mainstream narrative. Legislative measures won’t suffice reforms in Hinduism as long as it is in tandem with the resolute of Hindus to seek reform. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Kant</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The deafening sound of crackers bursting left, right and centre on Diwali often gag the factions who are vociferously at loggerheads with each other. One faction who believes in burning crackers under the garb of ‘Hindu traditions’ and upholding the ‘Hindu way of life’. The other dons a more ‘reformist’ stance of making Hindu practices and traditions amend to the times we live in. Lately, the Indian government has started to take cognisance of how a night of burning crackers recklessly exacerbates the already alarming rate of air pollution. It did earn the ire of the traditionalists; who, infuriated, got onto primetime slots on news channels and denouncing the move, calling it Hinduphobic and a threat to Hindu practices. Populist Indian anchors such as Arnab Goswami engaged in expected whataboutery by asking Muslim clerics if aazan doesn't amount to noise pollution every day—with cultural icons like Sonu Nigam further normalising it. The administration banning firecrackers indeed brings up a rather pertinent question — whether religious reforms should be done by the legislature, or those who practice the faith itself.&amp;nbsp; Right-wing organisations in India currently promote a more radical form of Hinduism, which often clobbers Hindus with memories of the tumultuous history of Islamic conquest in India — rifling the narrative with the sight of blemished or razed temples, on which many mosques built in that period purportedly stand today.&amp;nbsp; It is from this radical branch of Hinduism where the recalcitrancy of refusing to give up firecrackers stems from. Twitter is mostly bombarded with whataboutery whenever and wherever this debate rises; where Muslims sacrificing goats every year doesn't account for slaughter and Christmas trees don't account for &quot;deforestation&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A more liberal argument from the same branch has a clarion call to ban crackers indefinitely and not do so only on Diwali as the rationale behind a more &quot;progressive&quot; decision is religionism, not environmentalism.&amp;nbsp; Comparing the damage by burning crackers to the aforementioned practices in Islam or Christianity sets regressive precedence — for it doesn't leave room for reform at all. For time immemorial, Hinduism has evolved to fit societal paradigms. Although the precarious issues of caste and Brahminical hegemony show that Hinduism is a far cry away from major reform, Hindus should strive to constantly reform the tenets of the religion, irrespective of how other religions around the world function.&amp;nbsp; The extremists deserve credit for coming up with this ruse where Hindus bear the brunt of being righteous. To its bare-bones, it is analogous to a near-anarchistic milieu — where people refuse to conform to a righteous path because others around them are diabolical.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, accusing the administration of using religionism as an impetus to ban crackers is reflective of yet another trope of the extremist narrative — to live with an inherent 'insecurity' that Hinduism is under a constant threat from monotheism.&amp;nbsp; Such an insecure demeanour for an ancient religion is a deterrent to an egalitarian and equivocal India, which is set-in-stone in the Constitution. This insecurity is what the right-wing extremists stand for — making people believe in a false, internal enemy who is alleged to be constantly at loggerheads with Hindus and make conniving plots to attack Hinduism. The far-right ruling party’s fervent and Islamophobic attack on ‘love jihad’ — a term promoted by far-right organisations to discredit inter-faith relationships and marriages, is another way that they convolute harmony by victimising Hindu women who ‘fall’ for traps set by ‘well-groomed, handsome’ Muslim men. When the country is rifled with intolerance to an extent where there is institutionalised normalisation of coercive endogamy, Hindus should introspect the tenets of the faith that exists in the mainstream narrative. Legislative measures won’t suffice reforms in Hinduism as long as it is in tandem with the resolute of Hindus to seek reform.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Retail Binge for the Mental Twinge</title><link href="/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Retail Binge for the Mental Twinge" /><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;They say, “When the going gets tough, the tough go shopping.” This is more commonly known as &lt;em&gt;Retail Therapy&lt;/em&gt;. It is a phenomenon where people shop to improve one’s disposition and raise spirits. People in distress often resort to this as a source of solace. A study published in the journal &lt;em&gt;Psychology and Marketing&lt;/em&gt; states that retail therapy has a lasting positive effect on mood. While its findings pointed out that these are impulsive purchases, the survey suggested that feelings of guilt or regret were not associated among the respondents.&amp;nbsp;The name in itself is ironic. Shopping is a concept deeply rooted in materialism. As its positive impact is temporary, it does not qualify as a ‘therapy’ in the medical sense. However, it is a fairly popular phrase used around the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In a 2001 survey conducted by the European Union, it was found that 33% of the shoppers surveyed had a “high level of addiction to rash buying”. The study also revealed that ‘binge purchasing’ was most common among the Scottish youth. Another study of 1,000 American adults, conducted in 2013, detected that more than half of the respondents indulged in retail therapy. It also threw light on the gender aspect of the practice, stating that it is more common among women than men. It was found that 64.9% of women and 38.9% of men binge purchased while women mostly bought clothing, men indulged in ‘comfort food’. This was further reinforced by the Youngstown State University with similar male-female percentages, showing that relief from stress was the most common reason behind the practice. A more adverse extension of retail therapy is Oniomania or Compulsive Buying Disorder, which is an obsession with shopping, resulting in serious financial and mental consequences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Whys behind the Comfort Buys&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While stress, anxiety and sadness are a part of daily life, they can be tackled through other means such as reaching out to others, practicing yoga, mindfulness and meditation, journaling, exercising and consulting experts in more severe cases. Despite there being these solutions, which on an average are cheaper than shopping, why do people indulge in purchasing things to boost their mood? To understand the causes behind retail therapy, the behavioral aspect of individuals needs to be analysed in a twofold manner. Even though, at first glance, these reasons seem simple — associated with daily life, a deeper analysis suggests that the root cause can be traced back to psychological theory.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Firstly, we examine the relatively straightforward causes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;When everything goes wrong and nothing falls into place as you imagined it to, how do you feel? Out of control, right? Thus, one of the reasons people indulge in retail therapy is that shopping is a coping mechanism that helps people feel more in control. From deciding where to shop, to choosing what to purchase, it allows people to exercise autonomy and make decisions. In my personal opinion, shopping can also make one feel a sense of achievement. Utilising good offers and deals, applying coupons to get discounts and sometimes even getting goods for free certainly makes one feel happier as they ‘save’ along with fulfilling a guilty pleasure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Secondly, retail therapy can be a useful mechanism for smooth transitions of life as it enables people to envisage their lives post such changes. For instance, people often shop excessively before they are going to live alone for the first time, shifting to a new house, getting married or having a baby. Shopping may ease anxiety by making people feel more in control by helping them to prepare themselves for such huge transitions through the process of ‘visualisation’, which is a process that boosts performance, confidence and reduces anxiety.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another way in which retail therapy boosts mood is through a pleasant gush of creativity. Specifically, clothing of various kinds of colors and textures, accessories like jewelry, footwear, bags, sunglasses, etc, home decor items may induce a positive breeze of art and aesthetics. For example, the arrival of a new outfit may stir your creative juices in thinking about what shoes, jewelry and bag to pair it up with. This may certainly bring about a calmness in a way similar to art therapy, a well-known method of healing and reducing stress.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Some people treat shopping, both online and offline as a source of refreshment from the humdrum of daily life. Being a mindless activity, it enables people to relax and take some time off from their sources of stress. This form may vary from window shopping to scrolling on an online website or going to a shopping-mall for a break.&amp;nbsp;Yet another reason behind binge-purchasing may be the need to ‘feel connected’. For instance, one may shop for a sweater with a snowman or bells, candies and wreaths for decoration during Christmas, to feel more socially connected to the festival. Or someone may shop for a beret before visiting Paris to feel a part of the culture of the fashion capital. Thus, retail therapy may help individuals to feel closer to society and culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An extensive scrutiny of the idea suggests that the root cause lies in Sigmund Freud’s Pleasure Principle of psychology. The principle claims that individuals instinctively seek immediate pleasure to avoid experiencing feelings of stress, pain and sadness. In the context of impulsive purchasing, the principle fits well, as it is only a short term coping mechanism rooted in instant relief from stress. As compared to the Freudian Reality Principle, the Pleasure Principle is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inability of individuals to defer immediate gratification of certain desires and wants that rationality and reality may disallow.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sadness Cycle&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even though retail therapy eases the anxiety and pain in people’s lives, such a positive impact may be short-lived. While retail therapy can be supported by psychological reasoning, Economics does not go hand-in-hand with the concept due to its assumption of rationality among all individuals. From the point of view of rationality, the problems of running out of budget and debts arise due to limited financial resources. Impulsive overspending may lead people to become even more anxious and distressed due to the inability of paying bills and lacking a sound financial base, in the long run. A rough patch after having run out of budget may seem more dramatic and difficult to handle, due to a lack of finance to purchase something to feel better. In desperate times like these, individuals addicted to the method, may resort to desperate measures like taking loans from others or stealing. This might be complemented with feelings of guilt due to unrealistically high expenditure patterns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, retail therapy, to an obsessive degree can lead to reverse effects by introducing a cycle of stress and anxiety for an individual rather than helping one fight the tough times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ‘Viral’ Remedy&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With the Coronavirus pandemic hitting the world, people across the globe felt paralysed due to being restricted homes all the time. While this altered the work culture among people, the norms of schooling among students and put a halt to dining out, it had an impact on the shoppers. Research suggests that elements appealing to an individual’s senses, like aroma, music, a creative arrangement of products in a store, temperature contribute to the experience of shoppers. Unfortunately, with the lockdown implemented across the world, this ‘sensory’ experience was no longer available. As a result of this, one would expect sales to fall. However, the online retail industry led to a different turn of events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to &lt;em&gt;Forbes&lt;/em&gt;, as of March 2020, several online retail categories experienced a 74% year over year increase in sales, as compared to March 2018. Some of the top categories that saw a surge in the sale are home goods like furniture and home decor items and athletic and loungewear. While it may be argued that these categories resonate more with individuals in the current scenario due to the need to stay home, it must be noted that none of these items are essentials. Thus, it can be suggested that individuals binge purchased during the pandemic to escape the fears and stress of the situation and its uncertainty, thereby serving as a recent instance of retail therapy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact of retail therapy on an individual’s life depends upon the degree of engagement. On one hand, retail therapy in the form of window shopping, purchasing with adherence to one’s budget or buying pre-planned things can help to reduce stress and sadness both in the short term and long run. On the other hand, if the simple habit intensifies to become an addiction, it results in adverse problems which in turn brings more distress, thereby defeating the purpose of the ‘therapy’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">They say, “When the going gets tough, the tough go shopping.” This is more commonly known as Retail Therapy. It is a phenomenon where people shop to improve one’s disposition and raise spirits. People in distress often resort to this as a source of solace. A study published in the journal Psychology and Marketing states that retail therapy has a lasting positive effect on mood. While its findings pointed out that these are impulsive purchases, the survey suggested that feelings of guilt or regret were not associated among the respondents.&amp;nbsp;The name in itself is ironic. Shopping is a concept deeply rooted in materialism. As its positive impact is temporary, it does not qualify as a ‘therapy’ in the medical sense. However, it is a fairly popular phrase used around the world.&amp;nbsp; In a 2001 survey conducted by the European Union, it was found that 33% of the shoppers surveyed had a “high level of addiction to rash buying”. The study also revealed that ‘binge purchasing’ was most common among the Scottish youth. Another study of 1,000 American adults, conducted in 2013, detected that more than half of the respondents indulged in retail therapy. It also threw light on the gender aspect of the practice, stating that it is more common among women than men. It was found that 64.9% of women and 38.9% of men binge purchased while women mostly bought clothing, men indulged in ‘comfort food’. This was further reinforced by the Youngstown State University with similar male-female percentages, showing that relief from stress was the most common reason behind the practice. A more adverse extension of retail therapy is Oniomania or Compulsive Buying Disorder, which is an obsession with shopping, resulting in serious financial and mental consequences.&amp;nbsp; The Whys behind the Comfort Buys&amp;nbsp; While stress, anxiety and sadness are a part of daily life, they can be tackled through other means such as reaching out to others, practicing yoga, mindfulness and meditation, journaling, exercising and consulting experts in more severe cases. Despite there being these solutions, which on an average are cheaper than shopping, why do people indulge in purchasing things to boost their mood? To understand the causes behind retail therapy, the behavioral aspect of individuals needs to be analysed in a twofold manner. Even though, at first glance, these reasons seem simple — associated with daily life, a deeper analysis suggests that the root cause can be traced back to psychological theory.&amp;nbsp; Firstly, we examine the relatively straightforward causes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;When everything goes wrong and nothing falls into place as you imagined it to, how do you feel? Out of control, right? Thus, one of the reasons people indulge in retail therapy is that shopping is a coping mechanism that helps people feel more in control. From deciding where to shop, to choosing what to purchase, it allows people to exercise autonomy and make decisions. In my personal opinion, shopping can also make one feel a sense of achievement. Utilising good offers and deals, applying coupons to get discounts and sometimes even getting goods for free certainly makes one feel happier as they ‘save’ along with fulfilling a guilty pleasure.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, retail therapy can be a useful mechanism for smooth transitions of life as it enables people to envisage their lives post such changes. For instance, people often shop excessively before they are going to live alone for the first time, shifting to a new house, getting married or having a baby. Shopping may ease anxiety by making people feel more in control by helping them to prepare themselves for such huge transitions through the process of ‘visualisation’, which is a process that boosts performance, confidence and reduces anxiety.&amp;nbsp; Another way in which retail therapy boosts mood is through a pleasant gush of creativity. Specifically, clothing of various kinds of colors and textures, accessories like jewelry, footwear, bags, sunglasses, etc, home decor items may induce a positive breeze of art and aesthetics. For example, the arrival of a new outfit may stir your creative juices in thinking about what shoes, jewelry and bag to pair it up with. This may certainly bring about a calmness in a way similar to art therapy, a well-known method of healing and reducing stress.&amp;nbsp; Some people treat shopping, both online and offline as a source of refreshment from the humdrum of daily life. Being a mindless activity, it enables people to relax and take some time off from their sources of stress. This form may vary from window shopping to scrolling on an online website or going to a shopping-mall for a break.&amp;nbsp;Yet another reason behind binge-purchasing may be the need to ‘feel connected’. For instance, one may shop for a sweater with a snowman or bells, candies and wreaths for decoration during Christmas, to feel more socially connected to the festival. Or someone may shop for a beret before visiting Paris to feel a part of the culture of the fashion capital. Thus, retail therapy may help individuals to feel closer to society and culture.&amp;nbsp; An extensive scrutiny of the idea suggests that the root cause lies in Sigmund Freud’s Pleasure Principle of psychology. The principle claims that individuals instinctively seek immediate pleasure to avoid experiencing feelings of stress, pain and sadness. In the context of impulsive purchasing, the principle fits well, as it is only a short term coping mechanism rooted in instant relief from stress. As compared to the Freudian Reality Principle, the Pleasure Principle is the inability of individuals to defer immediate gratification of certain desires and wants that rationality and reality may disallow.&amp;nbsp; The Sadness Cycle&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Even though retail therapy eases the anxiety and pain in people’s lives, such a positive impact may be short-lived. While retail therapy can be supported by psychological reasoning, Economics does not go hand-in-hand with the concept due to its assumption of rationality among all individuals. From the point of view of rationality, the problems of running out of budget and debts arise due to limited financial resources. Impulsive overspending may lead people to become even more anxious and distressed due to the inability of paying bills and lacking a sound financial base, in the long run. A rough patch after having run out of budget may seem more dramatic and difficult to handle, due to a lack of finance to purchase something to feel better. In desperate times like these, individuals addicted to the method, may resort to desperate measures like taking loans from others or stealing. This might be complemented with feelings of guilt due to unrealistically high expenditure patterns.&amp;nbsp; Thus, retail therapy, to an obsessive degree can lead to reverse effects by introducing a cycle of stress and anxiety for an individual rather than helping one fight the tough times.&amp;nbsp; The ‘Viral’ Remedy&amp;nbsp; With the Coronavirus pandemic hitting the world, people across the globe felt paralysed due to being restricted homes all the time. While this altered the work culture among people, the norms of schooling among students and put a halt to dining out, it had an impact on the shoppers. Research suggests that elements appealing to an individual’s senses, like aroma, music, a creative arrangement of products in a store, temperature contribute to the experience of shoppers. Unfortunately, with the lockdown implemented across the world, this ‘sensory’ experience was no longer available. As a result of this, one would expect sales to fall. However, the online retail industry led to a different turn of events. According to Forbes, as of March 2020, several online retail categories experienced a 74% year over year increase in sales, as compared to March 2018. Some of the top categories that saw a surge in the sale are home goods like furniture and home decor items and athletic and loungewear. While it may be argued that these categories resonate more with individuals in the current scenario due to the need to stay home, it must be noted that none of these items are essentials. Thus, it can be suggested that individuals binge purchased during the pandemic to escape the fears and stress of the situation and its uncertainty, thereby serving as a recent instance of retail therapy.&amp;nbsp; The impact of retail therapy on an individual’s life depends upon the degree of engagement. On one hand, retail therapy in the form of window shopping, purchasing with adherence to one’s budget or buying pre-planned things can help to reduce stress and sadness both in the short term and long run. On the other hand, if the simple habit intensifies to become an addiction, it results in adverse problems which in turn brings more distress, thereby defeating the purpose of the ‘therapy’.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">11.11 - The Singles’ Date</title><link href="/11-11-The-Singles-Date" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="11.11 - The Singles’ Date" /><published>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/11-11-The-Singles-Date</id><content type="html" xml:base="/11-11-The-Singles-Date">&lt;p&gt;China is one of the world’s biggest powerhouses in innovation and technology. While the country has its own set of laws, it has a holiday that not many people around the globe know about- the &lt;em&gt;Singles’ Day&lt;/em&gt;! It might sound peculiar, but it is a huge part of modern Chinese culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Singles’ Day&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Double 11&lt;/em&gt;, originally called&lt;em&gt; Bachelors’ Day&lt;/em&gt;, is celebrated on November 11. It is a Chinese commercial holiday to celebrate being romantically unattached and paradoxically, turns out to be the largest physical retail and online shopping day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative behind the Singles’ Day is pretty nice. It originated at Nanjing University in 1993. A group of lonely, yet positive students decided that instead of lamenting their lack of a significant other, they would celebrate being single. The reasoning? 11.11 looks like four, single sticks, strung together trying to make the most out of their time. The anti-Valentine’s Day celebration of singledom caught on and spread across universities throughout China, generally characterised by fun and harmless events. With the widespread use of social media, the day has become increasingly popular within contemporary Chinese culture and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alibaba’s Blockbuster Growth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alibaba’s co-founder Jack Ma instituted the first Singles’ Day sale in 2009, laying the foundation for the highest-grossing shopping day of the year in the world. In 2012, the e-commerce company officially trademarked ‘Double 11’. Next in 2017, Alibaba’s mobile wallet app Alipay broke the record for the greatest number of transactions per second, whoa!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not be Singles’ Day without Alibaba having some great deals available. This year, the company’s annual sales frenzy broke records again by raking in roughly $75 billion. The total includes an earlier three-day period that was added to boost post-pandemic sales. The company claimed that, compared to the same timeframe as last year, this year’s haul represents an increase of 26%. Chinese consumers, who already buy about 30% of the nation’s retail purchase online, have become more reliant on e-commerce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, Alibaba also held a ‘Go Global 11.11 Pitch Fest’ aimed at small and medium-sized US brands, offering them a chance to be spotlighted during the event. Besides that, the company has been trying to involve more foreign brands globally. In 2019, Americans commanded the second-highest sales among importers, behind Japan but ahead of South Korea, Australia, and Germany.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, Alibaba makes stupendous efforts to hype up Double 11 with its extravagant, rather over-the-top countdown gala. It featured appearances from celebrities such as Nicole Kidman, Kobe Bryant, Scarlett Johansson, Mariah Carey, Pharrell Williams, Miranda Kerr, Jessie J, Lionel Messi, and Taylor Swift in the preceding years. Pop star Katy Perry, who has performed at the event before, made an appearance at the company’s gala this season, albeit via a live stream, as travel restrictions on outside visitors remain in place in China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though many other online platforms and stores take part in Singles’ Day, it is still closely tied to Alibaba.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crazy Sale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For brands and retailers scrambling to recover from months of shuttered shops and consumers hunkered down indoors, the profitable Chinese shopper is a much-needed bright spot. It is estimated that the participation of luxury brands has doubled on Singles’ Day, as millions of Chinese who have been unable to travel overseas on shopping trips go online for what experts are dubbing ‘revenge spending’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the buzz of Singles’ Day led the retailers worldwide to opt for special promotions to boost sales. &lt;em&gt;Uniqlo&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Foot Locker&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Best Buy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Steam&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Target&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Expedia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Topman&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Brooklinen&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Levi’s&lt;/em&gt;, and numerous other companies offered massive deals and discounts, orbiting the holiday. Three million workers, aided by 4,000 planes and ships got ready for the world’s biggest online sale in the current year- with ‘revenge spending’ tipping to be one of this year’s biggest trends.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey by market research firm &lt;em&gt;Oliver Wyman&lt;/em&gt; found out that 86% of Chinese consumers were willing to spend the same as or more than what they did during last year’s Singles’ Day. The remaining 14% of survey respondents said that they had spent less on Singles’ Day, because of the unprecedented times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On The Outside&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singles’ Day has become the most lucrative shopping holiday in several places outside China as well. The holiday has particularly grown in Southeast Asia, with customers in Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam, who are the recipient of the huge discounts offered by Alibaba’s subsidiary Lazada. In the United Kingdom, Singles’ Day is marked on March 11. It was initiated by a group of internationally recognised dating experts to help singles embrace themselves. Furthermore, Swedish Electronic retailer &lt;em&gt;Elgiganten&lt;/em&gt; promoted a Singles’ Day campaign in Norway before implementing it in the other Nordic countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MediaMarkt&lt;/em&gt;, a German Company, also promotes this day in its stores. Conversely, Belgian &lt;em&gt;MediaMarkt&lt;/em&gt; also participates but the reactions have been negative. It is because November 11 is the anniversary of the Armistice of 1918 that ended the First World War.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, awareness of Singles’ Day in New Zealand is still relatively low. According to a survey by &lt;em&gt;PriceSpy&lt;/em&gt;, around 73% of Kiwis have never heard of this day, with just 12% of Kiwis reporting to have brought something during the world’s biggest shopping bonanza.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singles’ Day will continue to grow in importance for retailers outside of China, particularly in the United Kingdom, which last year grew their discounting assortment to mirror the United States. In the light of the pandemic and feel of 2020, upbeat marketing angles that touch on celebrating and treating yourself are drawing attention globally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Antidote to Valentine’s Day&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally on Singles’ Day, people buy things, take themselves out for dinner, watch movies, sheepishly ruin dates, hang out with their other single friends and delve into the gratifying embrace of self-love. This phenomenon of retail therapy has resulted in oodles of sales, easily surpassing Black Friday and Cyber Monday combined.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, it is fun getting gifts on your birthday, Christmas and on other occasions- but how can people know what you actually want? On this day, you get to shop for yourself. I’m not just talking about buying yourself flowers or a decent meal. It is the day to show yourself some real love and appreciation. Go on, indulge. Splurge on those jeans you have been eying, or fancy wine club membership- you have earned it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retailers all over the world are instigating exclusive, singles-oriented deals in Alibaba’s footsteps. Grab the benefit of special promotions- ticket for 1 to Fiji? Yes, please.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samakshi Garg</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">China is one of the world’s biggest powerhouses in innovation and technology. While the country has its own set of laws, it has a holiday that not many people around the globe know about- the Singles’ Day! It might sound peculiar, but it is a huge part of modern Chinese culture.&amp;nbsp; The Singles’ Day or Double 11, originally called Bachelors’ Day, is celebrated on November 11. It is a Chinese commercial holiday to celebrate being romantically unattached and paradoxically, turns out to be the largest physical retail and online shopping day of the year. Genesis The narrative behind the Singles’ Day is pretty nice. It originated at Nanjing University in 1993. A group of lonely, yet positive students decided that instead of lamenting their lack of a significant other, they would celebrate being single. The reasoning? 11.11 looks like four, single sticks, strung together trying to make the most out of their time. The anti-Valentine’s Day celebration of singledom caught on and spread across universities throughout China, generally characterised by fun and harmless events. With the widespread use of social media, the day has become increasingly popular within contemporary Chinese culture and society.&amp;nbsp; Alibaba’s Blockbuster Growth Alibaba’s co-founder Jack Ma instituted the first Singles’ Day sale in 2009, laying the foundation for the highest-grossing shopping day of the year in the world. In 2012, the e-commerce company officially trademarked ‘Double 11’. Next in 2017, Alibaba’s mobile wallet app Alipay broke the record for the greatest number of transactions per second, whoa!&amp;nbsp; It would not be Singles’ Day without Alibaba having some great deals available. This year, the company’s annual sales frenzy broke records again by raking in roughly $75 billion. The total includes an earlier three-day period that was added to boost post-pandemic sales. The company claimed that, compared to the same timeframe as last year, this year’s haul represents an increase of 26%. Chinese consumers, who already buy about 30% of the nation’s retail purchase online, have become more reliant on e-commerce.&amp;nbsp; This year, Alibaba also held a ‘Go Global 11.11 Pitch Fest’ aimed at small and medium-sized US brands, offering them a chance to be spotlighted during the event. Besides that, the company has been trying to involve more foreign brands globally. In 2019, Americans commanded the second-highest sales among importers, behind Japan but ahead of South Korea, Australia, and Germany.&amp;nbsp; Undoubtedly, Alibaba makes stupendous efforts to hype up Double 11 with its extravagant, rather over-the-top countdown gala. It featured appearances from celebrities such as Nicole Kidman, Kobe Bryant, Scarlett Johansson, Mariah Carey, Pharrell Williams, Miranda Kerr, Jessie J, Lionel Messi, and Taylor Swift in the preceding years. Pop star Katy Perry, who has performed at the event before, made an appearance at the company’s gala this season, albeit via a live stream, as travel restrictions on outside visitors remain in place in China.&amp;nbsp; Even though many other online platforms and stores take part in Singles’ Day, it is still closely tied to Alibaba.&amp;nbsp; Crazy Sale For brands and retailers scrambling to recover from months of shuttered shops and consumers hunkered down indoors, the profitable Chinese shopper is a much-needed bright spot. It is estimated that the participation of luxury brands has doubled on Singles’ Day, as millions of Chinese who have been unable to travel overseas on shopping trips go online for what experts are dubbing ‘revenge spending’.&amp;nbsp; Unsurprisingly, the buzz of Singles’ Day led the retailers worldwide to opt for special promotions to boost sales. Uniqlo, Foot Locker, Best Buy, Steam, Target, Alibaba, Expedia, Topman, Brooklinen, Levi’s, and numerous other companies offered massive deals and discounts, orbiting the holiday. Three million workers, aided by 4,000 planes and ships got ready for the world’s biggest online sale in the current year- with ‘revenge spending’ tipping to be one of this year’s biggest trends.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A survey by market research firm Oliver Wyman found out that 86% of Chinese consumers were willing to spend the same as or more than what they did during last year’s Singles’ Day. The remaining 14% of survey respondents said that they had spent less on Singles’ Day, because of the unprecedented times.&amp;nbsp; On The Outside Singles’ Day has become the most lucrative shopping holiday in several places outside China as well. The holiday has particularly grown in Southeast Asia, with customers in Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam, who are the recipient of the huge discounts offered by Alibaba’s subsidiary Lazada. In the United Kingdom, Singles’ Day is marked on March 11. It was initiated by a group of internationally recognised dating experts to help singles embrace themselves. Furthermore, Swedish Electronic retailer Elgiganten promoted a Singles’ Day campaign in Norway before implementing it in the other Nordic countries.&amp;nbsp; MediaMarkt, a German Company, also promotes this day in its stores. Conversely, Belgian MediaMarkt also participates but the reactions have been negative. It is because November 11 is the anniversary of the Armistice of 1918 that ended the First World War.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, awareness of Singles’ Day in New Zealand is still relatively low. According to a survey by PriceSpy, around 73% of Kiwis have never heard of this day, with just 12% of Kiwis reporting to have brought something during the world’s biggest shopping bonanza.&amp;nbsp; Singles’ Day will continue to grow in importance for retailers outside of China, particularly in the United Kingdom, which last year grew their discounting assortment to mirror the United States. In the light of the pandemic and feel of 2020, upbeat marketing angles that touch on celebrating and treating yourself are drawing attention globally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; An Antidote to Valentine’s Day&amp;nbsp; Traditionally on Singles’ Day, people buy things, take themselves out for dinner, watch movies, sheepishly ruin dates, hang out with their other single friends and delve into the gratifying embrace of self-love. This phenomenon of retail therapy has resulted in oodles of sales, easily surpassing Black Friday and Cyber Monday combined.&amp;nbsp; Certainly, it is fun getting gifts on your birthday, Christmas and on other occasions- but how can people know what you actually want? On this day, you get to shop for yourself. I’m not just talking about buying yourself flowers or a decent meal. It is the day to show yourself some real love and appreciation. Go on, indulge. Splurge on those jeans you have been eying, or fancy wine club membership- you have earned it.&amp;nbsp; Retailers all over the world are instigating exclusive, singles-oriented deals in Alibaba’s footsteps. Grab the benefit of special promotions- ticket for 1 to Fiji? Yes, please.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge</title><link href="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge" /><published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge">&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan. The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF. India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp; This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma. However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere</title><link href="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere" /><published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere">&lt;p&gt;Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “&lt;em&gt;America First!&lt;/em&gt;”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp; Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp; From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond. But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp; In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “America First!”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp; In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp; Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War. What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modern Monetary Theory: The Solution to Developing Countries’ Problems?</title><link href="/Modern-Monetary-Theory" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Monetary Theory: The Solution to Developing Countries’ Problems?" /><published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Modern-Monetary-Theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Modern-Monetary-Theory">&lt;p&gt;Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is increasingly gaining traction in today’s public discourse. While there is huge literature available regarding MMT, it is often ridiculed by statements claiming to explain the theory, such as “&lt;em&gt;money printer gone brrrr&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; It is important to know that MMT doesn’t advocate for money printing. To borrow from L Randall Wray, a pioneer of the field, MMT argues that a sovereign government that issues its own “nonconvertible” currency cannot become insolvent (in terms of its own currency). It cannot be forced into involuntary default on its obligations denominated in its own currency. It can “afford” to buy anything for sale that is priced in its own currency. Here sovereignty is defined in monetary terms in that a state has monetary sovereignty when it issues its own currency, taxes its people in that currency, accepts that currency in payment of the imposed obligations, and issues debt in its own currency. Along with this, a fifth consideration, according to Wray, is to have a floating exchange rate regime (which is what “nonconvertible” currency means); so that it provides more fiscal space for the government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MMTers argue that their descriptions and prescriptions equally hold for the developing nations as for the developed nations. While this is largely true, there are however some constraints with regard to the developing countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first such constraint is the need for a developing country to accumulate foreign currency, especially the international reserve currency - the dollar. One major factor that leads to this accumulation is the necessity to import various types of goods (which could be for various reasons). So, with the accumulation of external debt, the demand for foreign currency also increases because it leads to higher debt service obligations and also because it increases risk perception as there is greater exposure to currency mismatch. The accumulation of foreign debt means that the balance of payments becomes a major limitation on the policy front for a developing country. In the current account of the balance of payments, a trade deficit (imports &amp;gt; exports) is compensated by positive capital inflows (which leads to a surplus in the capital account). That is, a current account deficit must be balanced by the sum of the capital account. Randal Wray once wrote that “&lt;em&gt;MMT makes no claim that floating rates eliminate current account deficits, indeed, MMT does not argue that elimination of current account deficits is even desirable”&lt;/em&gt;. But, the said balancing does not mean that a country can sustain any level of the current account deficit, over time. There is ample evidence available that the higher the current account deficit, the less likely that it can be sustained. What all this means is that the current account deficit chips away the monetary sovereignty of developing countries and thus the validity of MMT in such countries becomes uncertain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second issue, which is related here is that Wray suggests that in a floating exchange regime a government does not need to fear that it will run out of foreign currency reserves (or gold reserves) for the simple reason that it does not convert its domestic currency to foreign currency at a fixed exchange rate. Indeed, the government does not have to promise to make any conversions at all. But a developing country necessarily concerns itself with the capital flows not because of the issue of convertibility of currency, but because it needs to pay for its imports (or some sort of short-term obligation). All this is to say that a developing country may very well face the risk of foreign debt default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fadhel Kaboub, another MMT economist, identifies three broad areas from where a trade deficit arises. It arises because the developing country lacks food sovereignty, energy sovereignty and they essentially export low-value goods and import high-value goods. He says that this is a trap, in that a trade deficit leads a country to accumulate foreign currency. To do this, domestic resources are diverted from the areas of the government’s priority to areas that earn foreign exchange for the country. For instance, a government may prioritise the needs of foreign tourists as they spend the foreign currency or the government may announce tax concessions with the hope to attract foreign investors and end up losing revenue which could otherwise be used to develop local government. So, his advice to developing countries is to invest in sustainable agriculture to reach a level of self-sufficiency, to invest in renewable energy production that allows the countries to set their priorities, to invest in education, and to prepare an industrial strategy to move up the value chain from producing low-value-added goods to high-value-added goods. All these will provide resilience for a country from external shocks that a country may face.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third important constraint is inflation. MMT argues that while a sovereign can never default, there are limits as to how much it can spend; that is, there are certain limits on the fiscal deficit a sovereign runs. These limits are in the form of constraints on the part of real resources in an economy. If a government spends more than what these real resources could absorb, it risks the possibility of price hikes, i.e. inflation. MMT’s prescription to this problem is that the government could increase tax rates so that the purchasing power of the economy as a whole falls and thus inflation could be arrested (note that MMT also says tax revenue does not pay for anything but gives several other reasons for justifying the taxes). Now, in developing countries, there are two main problems with this. First, the tax base is lower in developing countries. Therefore, even when taxes are increased there might not be the desired effect of reducing purchasing power and thus controlling inflation. The prevalence of the informal economy on a large scale is also a constraint in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that developing economies face certain constraints that the MMT approach has not fully gauged. For instance, a developed country might not have constraints of fiscal space due to the current account of the balance of payments (and due to implications thereof). However, it can also be argued that it is precisely the understanding and the implementation of MMT that is required for the developing countries to overcome these constraints. The primary focus of MMT on real resources can be an important takeaway for developing economies because the development of real resources (in part) entails huge investments in developing human capital, green resources, and health resources. Despite many constraints, MMT also opens many doors for the developing economies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is increasingly gaining traction in today’s public discourse. While there is huge literature available regarding MMT, it is often ridiculed by statements claiming to explain the theory, such as “money printer gone brrrr”. It is important to know that MMT doesn’t advocate for money printing. To borrow from L Randall Wray, a pioneer of the field, MMT argues that a sovereign government that issues its own “nonconvertible” currency cannot become insolvent (in terms of its own currency). It cannot be forced into involuntary default on its obligations denominated in its own currency. It can “afford” to buy anything for sale that is priced in its own currency. Here sovereignty is defined in monetary terms in that a state has monetary sovereignty when it issues its own currency, taxes its people in that currency, accepts that currency in payment of the imposed obligations, and issues debt in its own currency. Along with this, a fifth consideration, according to Wray, is to have a floating exchange rate regime (which is what “nonconvertible” currency means); so that it provides more fiscal space for the government.&amp;nbsp; MMTers argue that their descriptions and prescriptions equally hold for the developing nations as for the developed nations. While this is largely true, there are however some constraints with regard to the developing countries.&amp;nbsp; The first such constraint is the need for a developing country to accumulate foreign currency, especially the international reserve currency - the dollar. One major factor that leads to this accumulation is the necessity to import various types of goods (which could be for various reasons). So, with the accumulation of external debt, the demand for foreign currency also increases because it leads to higher debt service obligations and also because it increases risk perception as there is greater exposure to currency mismatch. The accumulation of foreign debt means that the balance of payments becomes a major limitation on the policy front for a developing country. In the current account of the balance of payments, a trade deficit (imports &amp;gt; exports) is compensated by positive capital inflows (which leads to a surplus in the capital account). That is, a current account deficit must be balanced by the sum of the capital account. Randal Wray once wrote that “MMT makes no claim that floating rates eliminate current account deficits, indeed, MMT does not argue that elimination of current account deficits is even desirable”. But, the said balancing does not mean that a country can sustain any level of the current account deficit, over time. There is ample evidence available that the higher the current account deficit, the less likely that it can be sustained. What all this means is that the current account deficit chips away the monetary sovereignty of developing countries and thus the validity of MMT in such countries becomes uncertain.&amp;nbsp; A second issue, which is related here is that Wray suggests that in a floating exchange regime a government does not need to fear that it will run out of foreign currency reserves (or gold reserves) for the simple reason that it does not convert its domestic currency to foreign currency at a fixed exchange rate. Indeed, the government does not have to promise to make any conversions at all. But a developing country necessarily concerns itself with the capital flows not because of the issue of convertibility of currency, but because it needs to pay for its imports (or some sort of short-term obligation). All this is to say that a developing country may very well face the risk of foreign debt default. Fadhel Kaboub, another MMT economist, identifies three broad areas from where a trade deficit arises. It arises because the developing country lacks food sovereignty, energy sovereignty and they essentially export low-value goods and import high-value goods. He says that this is a trap, in that a trade deficit leads a country to accumulate foreign currency. To do this, domestic resources are diverted from the areas of the government’s priority to areas that earn foreign exchange for the country. For instance, a government may prioritise the needs of foreign tourists as they spend the foreign currency or the government may announce tax concessions with the hope to attract foreign investors and end up losing revenue which could otherwise be used to develop local government. So, his advice to developing countries is to invest in sustainable agriculture to reach a level of self-sufficiency, to invest in renewable energy production that allows the countries to set their priorities, to invest in education, and to prepare an industrial strategy to move up the value chain from producing low-value-added goods to high-value-added goods. All these will provide resilience for a country from external shocks that a country may face.&amp;nbsp; A third important constraint is inflation. MMT argues that while a sovereign can never default, there are limits as to how much it can spend; that is, there are certain limits on the fiscal deficit a sovereign runs. These limits are in the form of constraints on the part of real resources in an economy. If a government spends more than what these real resources could absorb, it risks the possibility of price hikes, i.e. inflation. MMT’s prescription to this problem is that the government could increase tax rates so that the purchasing power of the economy as a whole falls and thus inflation could be arrested (note that MMT also says tax revenue does not pay for anything but gives several other reasons for justifying the taxes). Now, in developing countries, there are two main problems with this. First, the tax base is lower in developing countries. Therefore, even when taxes are increased there might not be the desired effect of reducing purchasing power and thus controlling inflation. The prevalence of the informal economy on a large scale is also a constraint in this context. It is true that developing economies face certain constraints that the MMT approach has not fully gauged. For instance, a developed country might not have constraints of fiscal space due to the current account of the balance of payments (and due to implications thereof). However, it can also be argued that it is precisely the understanding and the implementation of MMT that is required for the developing countries to overcome these constraints. The primary focus of MMT on real resources can be an important takeaway for developing economies because the development of real resources (in part) entails huge investments in developing human capital, green resources, and health resources. Despite many constraints, MMT also opens many doors for the developing economies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scams &amp;amp; Frauds: Serial Killers of the Economy</title><link href="/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scams &amp; Frauds: Serial Killers of the Economy" /><published>2020-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy">&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy has been growing at an unprecedented rate in recent times. Various factors have culminated together to lead to such growth. No doubt, financial institutions are one of the most important aspects and thus referred to as the ‘backbones of the economy’. Banks, co-operatives, and other financial institutions look into the monetary affairs of a state, thus making their efficient functioning essential for an economy’s healthy growth. However, in recent times, these holy institutes have been marred by impious activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do face errors and issues due to a number of reasons but it is of no serious concern until it is taken care of. There have been times when these issues and errors slipped out of hand and created chaos among the public. These major errors can also be termed as ‘banking frauds’. Banking frauds are referred to the illegal and unethical means used by one party to extract or misuse funds, assets or even property owned by a financial institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India has seen a spike in these frauds recently and the reasons are still unknown. The cases of Vijay Mallya and Nirav Modi are two major examples of such frauds. Mallya is accused of fraud and money laundering and owes an estimated ₹90 billion to 17 Indian banks. The Nirav Modi-PNB scam is one of the largest in India’s banking history. It involves undertaking an estimated amount of ₹110 billion from the Punjab National Bank, Brady House branch located in Mumbai. Both accused escaped the country and the cases are still under trial. The money has not been returned yet and thus the banks had to lose out on such a huge amount that belongs to their account holders in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frauds are usually done by individuals for petty self-gains but the involvement of people within the banks is definite. It is possible to plan and execute a crime so huge only when you play around with the loopholes existing in the policies and thereby messing the entire functioning of the system. This usually requires help from the people working within the institution and in most cases of frauds, employees are involved. The advent of technology can also be one reason which facilitates these frauds. Other reasons can be concentration of power at certain levels or giving leeway during legal procedures. Ideally, accounts with huge exposures and capital need to be checked frequently with the use of forensic due diligence infrastructure. The decision making regarding huge loans should be done by a committee rather than a single person. Monitoring the trail of money will also reduce the risk of laundering cases.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question still remains: how do these frauds impact the public or even the economy?&amp;nbsp; They cause a slowdown in the growth of the economy which weakens the economy and discourages foreign investments. The money being stolen or laundered in these cases is the public fund. The minute public loses trust in a bank, it leads to even greater losses for the banks, and the bank might even go bankrupt. Banks play an important and integral part of the monetary system. They affect the cash flow, money demand, and various other factors. The moment their functioning is disturbed by these frauds, it definitely trickles down to other areas as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frauds and scams can surely be avoided at various levels and it is important that even governments provide guidelines to minimise the risks. Strict action against the offenders should be taken to set a precedence for the public. It is a huge task to maintain transparency at every step but at the same time, banks should come forward and take responsibility and accountability for the mishaps. The trust between the public and these financial institutions has to be maintained for the smooth functioning of the economy. Banking institutions are vital and thus a step towards more secure functioning needs to be taken to avoid these circumstances. It is tedious but definitely not impossible. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Indian economy has been growing at an unprecedented rate in recent times. Various factors have culminated together to lead to such growth. No doubt, financial institutions are one of the most important aspects and thus referred to as the ‘backbones of the economy’. Banks, co-operatives, and other financial institutions look into the monetary affairs of a state, thus making their efficient functioning essential for an economy’s healthy growth. However, in recent times, these holy institutes have been marred by impious activities. They do face errors and issues due to a number of reasons but it is of no serious concern until it is taken care of. There have been times when these issues and errors slipped out of hand and created chaos among the public. These major errors can also be termed as ‘banking frauds’. Banking frauds are referred to the illegal and unethical means used by one party to extract or misuse funds, assets or even property owned by a financial institution.&amp;nbsp; India has seen a spike in these frauds recently and the reasons are still unknown. The cases of Vijay Mallya and Nirav Modi are two major examples of such frauds. Mallya is accused of fraud and money laundering and owes an estimated ₹90 billion to 17 Indian banks. The Nirav Modi-PNB scam is one of the largest in India’s banking history. It involves undertaking an estimated amount of ₹110 billion from the Punjab National Bank, Brady House branch located in Mumbai. Both accused escaped the country and the cases are still under trial. The money has not been returned yet and thus the banks had to lose out on such a huge amount that belongs to their account holders in the first place. Frauds are usually done by individuals for petty self-gains but the involvement of people within the banks is definite. It is possible to plan and execute a crime so huge only when you play around with the loopholes existing in the policies and thereby messing the entire functioning of the system. This usually requires help from the people working within the institution and in most cases of frauds, employees are involved. The advent of technology can also be one reason which facilitates these frauds. Other reasons can be concentration of power at certain levels or giving leeway during legal procedures. Ideally, accounts with huge exposures and capital need to be checked frequently with the use of forensic due diligence infrastructure. The decision making regarding huge loans should be done by a committee rather than a single person. Monitoring the trail of money will also reduce the risk of laundering cases.&amp;nbsp; The question still remains: how do these frauds impact the public or even the economy?&amp;nbsp; They cause a slowdown in the growth of the economy which weakens the economy and discourages foreign investments. The money being stolen or laundered in these cases is the public fund. The minute public loses trust in a bank, it leads to even greater losses for the banks, and the bank might even go bankrupt. Banks play an important and integral part of the monetary system. They affect the cash flow, money demand, and various other factors. The moment their functioning is disturbed by these frauds, it definitely trickles down to other areas as well.&amp;nbsp; Frauds and scams can surely be avoided at various levels and it is important that even governments provide guidelines to minimise the risks. Strict action against the offenders should be taken to set a precedence for the public. It is a huge task to maintain transparency at every step but at the same time, banks should come forward and take responsibility and accountability for the mishaps. The trust between the public and these financial institutions has to be maintained for the smooth functioning of the economy. Banking institutions are vital and thus a step towards more secure functioning needs to be taken to avoid these circumstances. It is tedious but definitely not impossible.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Present Bias: Focus on the Now but maybe Not Always</title><link href="/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Present Bias: Focus on the Now but maybe Not Always" /><published>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always">&lt;p&gt;Many times we wonder, what is it that makes us procrastinate? Why do we spend the whole day scrolling through Instagram instead of finishing the assignment that is due tomorrow? Apart from the fact that social media is designed to distract us, procrastinating isn't as simple as just being lazy. It isn't only about not wanting to do the task at hand, but more about how we humans are wired.&amp;nbsp; Procrastination is in fact related to a cognitive bias called the &lt;em&gt;present bias&lt;/em&gt;. As the name in itself suggests, it is the tendency of humans to be biased towards the present. This means that we tend to go for short-term rewards that provide us instant gratification rather than choosing long-term benefits. Thus, even though the benefit of finishing that assignment is clearly more than simply being on Instagram, the sense of gratification is achieved faster in the latter. Therefore, our brain might as well trick us into choosing the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand why humans are actually biased towards the present. The answer lies in how our ancestors lived their lives. The times they lived in, it only made sense that they focused on the present. With the uncertainty of the future and the environment they lived in, they had no other option but to be short-sighted in their decision making. This present bias allowed them to survive and deal with the immediate threats that existed around them. Over the centuries, this outlook of theirs seems to have been so well engraved in our brains that even today we have a similar mindset. Despite us having a far more stable lifestyle and a future to actually look forward to, our brain still makes us biased towards our present. It still makes us believe that the future is a scary avenue that one shouldn't be focusing much on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of the present bias has been studied by many researchers over the years, in order to understand to what extent such a bias can affect the lives of individuals. An interesting experiment in this field was conducted by Walter Mischel. This experiment that goes by the name of &lt;em&gt;Marshmallow Test &lt;/em&gt;is a famous experiment which involved finding out whether children delayed gratification. It involved children being asked to either choose a marshmallow now or wait for 15-20 minutes to get two of them. This experiment, however, did not end here only. After a few years, these very children, who were by then adolescents, were traced and it was seen that the children who delayed gratification at a younger age were able to be more successful in the later period of their lives. Thus, shedding light on the connection between small decisions turning into a lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect of present bias is that it is not just limited to the field of psychology but also equally important for economics. Take for an example, if you were to choose between getting a job of ₹15,000/month now, or interning for free for a year and getting a job of ₹30,000/month. You are more likely to choose the former. But if you were asked to either complete your 3 years of Bachelor's and get a job starting at ₹15,000/month or to choose an integrated programme of 4 years that would allow you to get a package starting at ₹30,000/month, then you are most likely to choose the second option. Even though there isn’t a difference between these two cases other than the time periods, your choice would potentially differ. This is because our brain can only distinguish between the present and the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the future is three or four years down the lane, our brain fails to distinguish between them, because both are considered as far-sighted. Since our mind takes the future as uncertain it wants to make decisions for now, even though they might not be as beneficial. In economics, present bias is used when we talk about time inconsistency and discounting. Time inconsistency refers to the fact that individuals are inconsistent over time. That is, for instance, you decide to hit the gym next month, but when next month arrives, you are more likely to postpone it to another month. Thus, meaning that people aren't as rational in making decisions, but there are various social and psychological factors that govern their decisions. People have the tendency to change their choices, over different time periods even though the benefits remain the same. Richard H Thaler (a Nobel Prize Winner for his work in the field of behavioural economics) has conducted researches that show that economics and psychology are far more closely related than one can imagine, thus expanding the scope and importance of behavioural economics. He along with H M Shefrin wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;An Economic Theory of Self-control&lt;/em&gt; that introduced an economic model of self-control. This model explains that people aren't only lacking self-control when it comes to not buying new clothes, or when it comes to stopping with just another episode. But the lack of self-control can also be seen towards how people handle their finances, especially saving for their retirements before it gets late. To us, saving money seems more like a loss now even though it’ll benefit us in future, and thus people tend to postpone saving money. In fact, this research has led to various social policies to emerge to help people with saving their money from early days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it is wired into our system to focus on what could harm us immediately, rather than what could harm us in the long-term, present bias manifests itself in many of our actions. The concept of present bias explains why we humans tend to make self-harming choices that provide us instant gratification but clearly have harmful consequences in the future. It also explains why we tend to ignore the importance of climate change, since it doesn't seem like an instant harm to our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in the present is important, but it isn't all we should be focused on. In reality, our lives are a combination of the past, present and future and therefore it becomes equally important to realise that the present is only a small piece in the puzzle of life. Understanding what present bias is, and how strongly it can control our decision making, allows us to be more aware of our own selves. It makes us realise that our brains aren't always thinking what's best for us and can quite a few times make impulsive decisions that might not seem so right in the years to come. Clearly, our brains are guided by the fear of the future, because of all the uncertainty it brings. So it only makes sense that we continue to ignore the future, and be in a more comfortable zone, the present. And honestly, instant gratification, no matter for how little of a time, does feel good. But it also feels fulfilling to make decisions that'll help our future selves. This is the dilemma that present bias poses. Whether to choose the time that we know of or to choose the time that'll come. It isn't easy to break away from our habits, especially the ones that are so well engraved in our nerves. Self-control and will power aren't as easily attained as we are likely to believe. But what we can do is to be more aware of how our brains have a tendency of fooling our own selves, and maybe for once not trust whatever our brain has to say.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Priyanshi Mehra</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Many times we wonder, what is it that makes us procrastinate? Why do we spend the whole day scrolling through Instagram instead of finishing the assignment that is due tomorrow? Apart from the fact that social media is designed to distract us, procrastinating isn't as simple as just being lazy. It isn't only about not wanting to do the task at hand, but more about how we humans are wired.&amp;nbsp; Procrastination is in fact related to a cognitive bias called the present bias. As the name in itself suggests, it is the tendency of humans to be biased towards the present. This means that we tend to go for short-term rewards that provide us instant gratification rather than choosing long-term benefits. Thus, even though the benefit of finishing that assignment is clearly more than simply being on Instagram, the sense of gratification is achieved faster in the latter. Therefore, our brain might as well trick us into choosing the latter. It is important to understand why humans are actually biased towards the present. The answer lies in how our ancestors lived their lives. The times they lived in, it only made sense that they focused on the present. With the uncertainty of the future and the environment they lived in, they had no other option but to be short-sighted in their decision making. This present bias allowed them to survive and deal with the immediate threats that existed around them. Over the centuries, this outlook of theirs seems to have been so well engraved in our brains that even today we have a similar mindset. Despite us having a far more stable lifestyle and a future to actually look forward to, our brain still makes us biased towards our present. It still makes us believe that the future is a scary avenue that one shouldn't be focusing much on it. The idea of the present bias has been studied by many researchers over the years, in order to understand to what extent such a bias can affect the lives of individuals. An interesting experiment in this field was conducted by Walter Mischel. This experiment that goes by the name of Marshmallow Test is a famous experiment which involved finding out whether children delayed gratification. It involved children being asked to either choose a marshmallow now or wait for 15-20 minutes to get two of them. This experiment, however, did not end here only. After a few years, these very children, who were by then adolescents, were traced and it was seen that the children who delayed gratification at a younger age were able to be more successful in the later period of their lives. Thus, shedding light on the connection between small decisions turning into a lifestyle. An interesting aspect of present bias is that it is not just limited to the field of psychology but also equally important for economics. Take for an example, if you were to choose between getting a job of ₹15,000/month now, or interning for free for a year and getting a job of ₹30,000/month. You are more likely to choose the former. But if you were asked to either complete your 3 years of Bachelor's and get a job starting at ₹15,000/month or to choose an integrated programme of 4 years that would allow you to get a package starting at ₹30,000/month, then you are most likely to choose the second option. Even though there isn’t a difference between these two cases other than the time periods, your choice would potentially differ. This is because our brain can only distinguish between the present and the future. Whether the future is three or four years down the lane, our brain fails to distinguish between them, because both are considered as far-sighted. Since our mind takes the future as uncertain it wants to make decisions for now, even though they might not be as beneficial. In economics, present bias is used when we talk about time inconsistency and discounting. Time inconsistency refers to the fact that individuals are inconsistent over time. That is, for instance, you decide to hit the gym next month, but when next month arrives, you are more likely to postpone it to another month. Thus, meaning that people aren't as rational in making decisions, but there are various social and psychological factors that govern their decisions. People have the tendency to change their choices, over different time periods even though the benefits remain the same. Richard H Thaler (a Nobel Prize Winner for his work in the field of behavioural economics) has conducted researches that show that economics and psychology are far more closely related than one can imagine, thus expanding the scope and importance of behavioural economics. He along with H M Shefrin wrote a paper titled An Economic Theory of Self-control that introduced an economic model of self-control. This model explains that people aren't only lacking self-control when it comes to not buying new clothes, or when it comes to stopping with just another episode. But the lack of self-control can also be seen towards how people handle their finances, especially saving for their retirements before it gets late. To us, saving money seems more like a loss now even though it’ll benefit us in future, and thus people tend to postpone saving money. In fact, this research has led to various social policies to emerge to help people with saving their money from early days. Since it is wired into our system to focus on what could harm us immediately, rather than what could harm us in the long-term, present bias manifests itself in many of our actions. The concept of present bias explains why we humans tend to make self-harming choices that provide us instant gratification but clearly have harmful consequences in the future. It also explains why we tend to ignore the importance of climate change, since it doesn't seem like an instant harm to our minds. Living in the present is important, but it isn't all we should be focused on. In reality, our lives are a combination of the past, present and future and therefore it becomes equally important to realise that the present is only a small piece in the puzzle of life. Understanding what present bias is, and how strongly it can control our decision making, allows us to be more aware of our own selves. It makes us realise that our brains aren't always thinking what's best for us and can quite a few times make impulsive decisions that might not seem so right in the years to come. Clearly, our brains are guided by the fear of the future, because of all the uncertainty it brings. So it only makes sense that we continue to ignore the future, and be in a more comfortable zone, the present. And honestly, instant gratification, no matter for how little of a time, does feel good. But it also feels fulfilling to make decisions that'll help our future selves. This is the dilemma that present bias poses. Whether to choose the time that we know of or to choose the time that'll come. It isn't easy to break away from our habits, especially the ones that are so well engraved in our nerves. Self-control and will power aren't as easily attained as we are likely to believe. But what we can do is to be more aware of how our brains have a tendency of fooling our own selves, and maybe for once not trust whatever our brain has to say.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meraki and More</title><link href="/Meraki-and-More" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meraki and More" /><published>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Meraki-and-More</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Meraki-and-More">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;I’ve recently had the opportunity to travel to the city where my freedom lies and be back in all of 30 minus 1 hour, and let me tell you- the thrill of running away from an ill-fashioned mask wearer, who is munching on chips as he coughs, and to look at Starbucks with nostalgia, and think of times when you didn’t have to worry about how many people might have touched that straw? Mind-blowing. The question of my sanity lies in if the risk, the multiple masks, the shield, the gloves, the chaos, all of it was worth a total of 40 minutes spent in ecstasy garnered from a bubble tea and nachos, a well-lit room and comfy hotel bed, oh, and well, a well-timed fight with your may-be/may-not-be boyfriend. Well, so was it? I wouldn’t know, might have to come back to that.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the world that we live now, not much seems to be as it was, most of all, the things that are. Every stressor is either exaggerated or it exasperates you to think of your stressor in the face of others’ much bigger ones. No problem is big enough to hold in the face of a pandemic, and that is known - but every problem is definitely magnified in the face of a pandemic and if that’s not the truth, I don’t know what is. The other day, I got my results back from an entrance that I barely prepared for and upon announcing my failure to my friend, you know what I received? “&lt;em&gt;It is the pandemic, no one expects better.&lt;/em&gt;” Pure empathy, pure justification, pure ‘hello, new issue causing other issues’. I’ve rationalised most things in the last 7 months to be external, and that maybe the fundamental attribution at play but I’m not to be blamed. Am I trying to shroud the pain the world has been due to this hazard? Absolutely not. I couldn’t if I wanted to, know that.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Last time I sat down to write, Kanye was in his first phase of the breakdown and today, Biden has bagged the highest votes in Pennsylvania. No amount of stimulus has been able to stimulate me enough to go back to my Googling days, oh! The blessed days of me finding a new word and reaching out to it every chance I could get, complete Icarus to the sun. Which reminds me, (in my most moving voice) they say when you do something with all your creativity, love and passion - you do it with Meraki. A word I’m extremely fond and am slightly terrified of. Like every other beautiful, soul-filling word (well, in this case, soul shedding, (you’ll see)), it belongs to the Greeks and implies that &lt;em&gt;“every time one works on something one really loves, they put a part of themselves into it&lt;/em&gt;”. While the concept is beautiful and has no English counterpart, there lies enough truth in it to make it completely sound. In my little to no knowledge of the ‘worldly’ affairs, I could only bring myself to compare it to Cathexis - the psychic energy one puts into people, objects, things, a gift given to us by my all-time favourite, Mr Freud. A close second could be ardour, or well, ardour. Ah, here I am again, stuck in words, when what I need to do is be stressed by my stressors, and subsequently, others’ stressors, too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Is this the time to get back to the drama that folds in from my may-be/may-be-not boyfriend? How about my (n)ever engaged and lengthy enough to go around the sun once (maybe, twice) to-do list? Ah, the joys. All I hope for is that if and when you read this, if and when you are in a position where it seems that you’re not working with Meraki anymore, this could work as a reinforcement, perhaps an aversive one. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><summary type="html">I’ve recently had the opportunity to travel to the city where my freedom lies and be back in all of 30 minus 1 hour, and let me tell you- the thrill of running away from an ill-fashioned mask wearer, who is munching on chips as he coughs, and to look at Starbucks with nostalgia, and think of times when you didn’t have to worry about how many people might have touched that straw? Mind-blowing. The question of my sanity lies in if the risk, the multiple masks, the shield, the gloves, the chaos, all of it was worth a total of 40 minutes spent in ecstasy garnered from a bubble tea and nachos, a well-lit room and comfy hotel bed, oh, and well, a well-timed fight with your may-be/may-not-be boyfriend. Well, so was it? I wouldn’t know, might have to come back to that.&amp;nbsp; In the world that we live now, not much seems to be as it was, most of all, the things that are. Every stressor is either exaggerated or it exasperates you to think of your stressor in the face of others’ much bigger ones. No problem is big enough to hold in the face of a pandemic, and that is known - but every problem is definitely magnified in the face of a pandemic and if that’s not the truth, I don’t know what is. The other day, I got my results back from an entrance that I barely prepared for and upon announcing my failure to my friend, you know what I received? “It is the pandemic, no one expects better.” Pure empathy, pure justification, pure ‘hello, new issue causing other issues’. I’ve rationalised most things in the last 7 months to be external, and that maybe the fundamental attribution at play but I’m not to be blamed. Am I trying to shroud the pain the world has been due to this hazard? Absolutely not. I couldn’t if I wanted to, know that.&amp;nbsp; Last time I sat down to write, Kanye was in his first phase of the breakdown and today, Biden has bagged the highest votes in Pennsylvania. No amount of stimulus has been able to stimulate me enough to go back to my Googling days, oh! The blessed days of me finding a new word and reaching out to it every chance I could get, complete Icarus to the sun. Which reminds me, (in my most moving voice) they say when you do something with all your creativity, love and passion - you do it with Meraki. A word I’m extremely fond and am slightly terrified of. Like every other beautiful, soul-filling word (well, in this case, soul shedding, (you’ll see)), it belongs to the Greeks and implies that “every time one works on something one really loves, they put a part of themselves into it”. While the concept is beautiful and has no English counterpart, there lies enough truth in it to make it completely sound. In my little to no knowledge of the ‘worldly’ affairs, I could only bring myself to compare it to Cathexis - the psychic energy one puts into people, objects, things, a gift given to us by my all-time favourite, Mr Freud. A close second could be ardour, or well, ardour. Ah, here I am again, stuck in words, when what I need to do is be stressed by my stressors, and subsequently, others’ stressors, too.&amp;nbsp; Is this the time to get back to the drama that folds in from my may-be/may-be-not boyfriend? How about my (n)ever engaged and lengthy enough to go around the sun once (maybe, twice) to-do list? Ah, the joys. All I hope for is that if and when you read this, if and when you are in a position where it seems that you’re not working with Meraki anymore, this could work as a reinforcement, perhaps an aversive one.</summary></entry></feed>