<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-26T18:45:13+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture</title><link href="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely
an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as
Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw
boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or
raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the
millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation
of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with
little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or
people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of
these problems, it made sure that they were heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies
like &lt;em&gt;Forrest Gump&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Platoon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse Now&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Deer Hunter&lt;/em&gt; surely
gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the
protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed
‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps
finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a movie like &lt;em&gt;Driving Miss Daisy&lt;/em&gt;, for example. It won the Best Picture
Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart
from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about
Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know
what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation
won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are
scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a
post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of &lt;em&gt;James Bond&lt;/em&gt; has
evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional
womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation
effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a
man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. &lt;em&gt;Get Out&lt;/em&gt; was a pivotal
movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would
solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald
Glover show &lt;em&gt;Atlanta&lt;/em&gt;, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true
portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans.
This trend extends to a lot of shows, like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New Black&lt;/em&gt;, that
eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most
inclusive shows in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for
masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more
recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities
and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused
of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been
much more open about the same throughout their discography.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like
Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear
candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global
influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been
considered too taboo to even be talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the
millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely
sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want
tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about
people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because
a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority,
has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar
bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life,
are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do
not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to
tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who
are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see
any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it
means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking
something &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and
human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is
seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows
like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily
because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental
health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that
already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about
combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end
surreal art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need
more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To
be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a
global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem,
if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success.
During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit
song &lt;em&gt;Alright&lt;/em&gt;. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for
some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good
about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better
people, if at all we really need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a
much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on
diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share
of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of
people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the
same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the
Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various
cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only
like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values
on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to
personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing
to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the
millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class
and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it
sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is
slowly but surely influencing content around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the
calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a
circle that was &lt;em&gt;woke just for show&lt;/em&gt;, female comedians have been earning what’s
due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience,
quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In
another example, TVF’s &lt;em&gt;Kota Factory&lt;/em&gt; created ripples across the student
community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering
students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw
their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold
content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the
millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms
such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially
charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a
generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a
generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view
life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own
troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans
in our cinema.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pranav Manie</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of these problems, it made sure that they were heard. This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies like Forrest Gump, Platoon, Apocalypse Now and The Deer Hunter surely gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed ‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.   Take a movie like Driving Miss Daisy, for example. It won the Best Picture Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories. The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of James Bond has evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies. Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. Get Out was a pivotal movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald Glover show Atlanta, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans. This trend extends to a lot of shows, like Orange Is The New Black, that eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most inclusive shows in recent times. Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been much more open about the same throughout their discography. Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been considered too taboo to even be talked about. But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority, has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life, are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender. One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking something real in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end surreal art. There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem, if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success. During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit song Alright. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better people, if at all we really need it. The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18. Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is slowly but surely influencing content around us.   Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a circle that was woke just for show, female comedians have been earning what’s due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience, quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In another example, TVF’s Kota Factory created ripples across the student community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold content. Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans in our cinema.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Secrets of Sorcery</title><link href="/Secrets-of-Sorcery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Secrets of Sorcery" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Secrets-of-Sorcery</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Secrets-of-Sorcery">&lt;p&gt;The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now,
that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon
heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long
crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from &lt;em&gt;The Vampire Diaries&lt;/em&gt;. But have you
ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is,
however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it.
Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda
behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This
historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly
enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past.
In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and
subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been
abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every
Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot
witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many
women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch
hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly
lending legitimacy to witch doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people
have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact,
witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them
as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current
government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government
recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just
by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak,
depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian
witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident
that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it
is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under
Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret
societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of
the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa,
commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt;.
While &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; practice natural medicine, &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt; practice magic, predict the
future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out
their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who
consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass
hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were
established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the
locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice
of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the
fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The
followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are
self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in
magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community
is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However,
contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches
too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in
worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.”
Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their
poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena
like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities.
Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named &lt;em&gt;The Book of
Shadows&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the
witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever
actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of
the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and
disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions
were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several
females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t
made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various
conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were
convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some
were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary
to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places,
male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches
stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. &lt;em&gt;Malleus Maleficarum&lt;/em&gt; was
published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the
Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot,
interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to
come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you
are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many
secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they
also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position
of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through
generations. &lt;em&gt;The Book of the Dead&lt;/em&gt; famously contains various spells to aid one
in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt
often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no
written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a
cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that
potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever
condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans
continued as long as the great civilisation thrived. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of
magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s
go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of
Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb,
George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation
team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11
deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly
attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is
believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s
occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between
robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard
Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies
have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the
masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in
different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have
only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to
solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold
beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated
with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to
decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have
assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we
rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more
complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly
enough, paganism is on the rise too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft
still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced
witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations
hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is
about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s
intriguing is the existence of the human &lt;strong&gt;urge&lt;/strong&gt; to look for magic in a world
that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world
desperation to cling to rationale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now, that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from The Vampire Diaries. But have you ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice? To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is, however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it. Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past. In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly lending legitimacy to witch doctors. Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact, witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches.  In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak, depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society. Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa, commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: Inyanga and Sangoma. While Inyanga practice natural medicine, Sangoma practice magic, predict the future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them. Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches. In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However, contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.” Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities. Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named The Book of Shadows. The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places, male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. Malleus Maleficarum was published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot, interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to come. If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through generations. The Book of the Dead famously contains various spells to aid one in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans continued as long as the great civilisation thrived.  With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb, George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11 deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action. Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly enough, paganism is on the rise too. While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s intriguing is the existence of the human urge to look for magic in a world that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world desperation to cling to rationale.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rise of the Screen Thriller</title><link href="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the Screen Thriller" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer">&lt;p&gt;Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided
useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of
writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a
subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider
these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the BBC masterpiece, &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt;, for example. Sherlock is quite often in
contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message
bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously
observe Sherlock’s expressions. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; portrays the internet the best -
take an episode like &lt;em&gt;Nosedive&lt;/em&gt;; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if
we introduce a social credit rating for humans or &lt;em&gt;Shut Up And Dance&lt;/em&gt;; an
episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the
aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of
being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online.
The need to harness and depict that is what led to the &lt;em&gt;computer screen
thriller&lt;/em&gt; being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the
film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or
television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt;, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching
for his missing daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first
documented screen-only movie was &lt;em&gt;The Collingswood Story&lt;/em&gt;, which is about an
online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams.
The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie
&lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It
made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian
director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to
this subgenre that he calls &lt;em&gt;Screen Life&lt;/em&gt;. He produced a sequel to the movie, as
well as &lt;em&gt;Searching,&lt;/em&gt; and directed one of his own called &lt;em&gt;Profile.&lt;/em&gt; There were
other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show
&lt;em&gt;Modern Family&lt;/em&gt; to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by
many as one of the best episodes of the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the
Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the
information can be revealed without using screens throughout. &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt; was
able to demonstrate it well. The TV show &lt;em&gt;American Vandal&lt;/em&gt; was themed around
internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Why&lt;/em&gt; could be
credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards
millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern
film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it
for us to simultaneously consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense.
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt; made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;
made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little.
Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but
also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story
gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and
texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not
reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the
characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny
things are indicators of something large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder
in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find
out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen
thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to
show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the
audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on
cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not
exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often
shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life
and online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The
screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and
windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the
viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always
waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter
how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is
wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human
desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David
Fincher, the director of &lt;em&gt;The Social Network&lt;/em&gt; says, “People are perverts.” They
want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless,
they will love it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pranav Manie</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold. Take the BBC masterpiece, Sherlock, for example. Sherlock is quite often in contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously observe Sherlock’s expressions. Black Mirror portrays the internet the best - take an episode like Nosedive; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if we introduce a social credit rating for humans or Shut Up And Dance; an episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape. These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online. The need to harness and depict that is what led to the computer screen thriller being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of Searching, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching for his missing daughter. However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first documented screen-only movie was The Collingswood Story, which is about an online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams. The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie Unfriended, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to this subgenre that he calls Screen Life. He produced a sequel to the movie, as well as Searching, and directed one of his own called Profile. There were other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show Modern Family to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by many as one of the best episodes of the show. The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the information can be revealed without using screens throughout. Sherlock was able to demonstrate it well. The TV show American Vandal was themed around internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even 13 Reasons Why could be credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it for us to simultaneously consume. These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense. Searching made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and Unfriended made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye? At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little. Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny things are indicators of something large. If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life and online. These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David Fincher, the director of The Social Network says, “People are perverts.” They want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless, they will love it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building the Abode of Gods…From Scratch</title><link href="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building the Abode of Gods...From Scratch" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘&lt;em&gt;Amaravati&lt;/em&gt;’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2014 Assembly elections, N Chandrababu Naidu of India’s Telugu Desam Party became the Chief Minister of the state. Soon, the government set up committees to finalise the area for capital construction. Amaravati was chosen by the end of 2014. There are many reasons for this selection. First, the proposed region is at the centre and is equidistant from every corner of the state. The second reason is the availability of water. The proposed capital city is situated on the banks of the river Krishna. It also has a barrage constructed which could hold up to 1 TMC of water. The third is the ease of connectivity. Amaravati is not more than 400 km from Hyderabad, Chennai and Bengaluru, capital cities of states that neighbour Andhra Pradesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon deciding the capital, the government constituted the Andhra Pradesh Capital Region Development Authority (APCRDA) in 2014 for planning, supervising, executing, financing and developing the capital region of Andhra Pradesh. Its tasks include finalising designs, calling for tenders and administering capital construction. Right from the beginning, the state drew its inspiration from Singapore to build a world-class city. Mr Naidu always talked about how Singapore too had developed from scratch and Andhra Pradesh was in the same position. APCRDA even signed an MoU with the Singapore government for the development of a master plan for Amaravati, which was finalised recently in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing to be noted here is that land for the capital was pooled rather than acquired. This was done to avoid the financial burden that would arise in the form of compensations against land acquisitions. Under this land pooling scheme, the landowners (mostly farmers) who surrendered their lands to the government would get a portion of the developed plots in the capital city after a period of 10 years. A huge 33,000 acres (133.5 square kilometers) was pooled for the construction of the capital city. It is a commendable achievement because the land was pooled in a very short period, that too without a single court case. Mr Naidu played a key role in assuring the fearful farmers that they would lose nothing by sacrificing their lands. To attract investments into the capital (and the state), the Andhra Pradesh government introduced a slew of measures. It eased its industrial policy by introducing a ‘single window clearance’ for industries, under which one can easily obtain all the necessary approvals for the setting up of a business, and avoid red tape thereof. Not only did this place Andhra Pradesh at the number 1 spot in the ‘Ease of Doing Business’ index of India but also helped the state in signing a $500 million deal with the World Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a city from scratch is an uphill task. For a state with finances like Andhra Pradesh, it is an economic nightmare. The state is so deep in a financial crisis that a recent White Paper released by the government stated that the state has to go for an overdraft almost every month! Yet, there seems to be non-cooperation from India’s central government. When the  Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Bill was up for discussion in the Rajya Sabha, the upper house of the Indian Parliament, the then Prime Minister Dr Manmohan Singh said “for the purpose of central assistance, Special Category Status (SCS) will be extended to the State of Andhra Pradesh for a period of five years. This will put the state finances on a firmer footing.” What SCS means is that the state would get preferential treatment in the transfer of funds from the central government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, SCS money never seems to come. It is estimated that construction of the new capital would require a massive sum of ₹330 billion. Out of this, a mere ₹25 billion has been allocated by India’s central government, and only ₹10.5 billion has been released till date. The administrative help from the Indian central government has been delayed too. One example of the central government’s neglect is worth mentioning here. Emirates, a world-renowned airline, sought to fly from Andhra Pradesh and establish a training facility there. It requested the state to provide the requisite land. As aviation is regulated by the central government according to India’s Constitution, this required the centre’s approval. Unfortunately, that approval never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all these troubles, wouldn’t it have been more feasible for Andhra Pradesh to select an already existing city rather than build a capital from scratch? All this said, building a new capital boosts aggregate demand. A huge amount of money is invested and employment opportunities are generated. However, the government needs to take appropriate steps to invite private investment into the state. Given the high fiscal deficit of the state, 4.5% of the GSDP or Gross State Domestic Product, it is imperative that the state goes hand-in-hand with the private sector because a further increase in fiscal deficit would put the state in a financially critical position. Infrastructural development needs huge investments with a generally long gestation period. It would be burdensome for the crippled economy of Andhra Pradesh to finance such investments. Private investments would ensure that there is no stoppage in the fund flow and the projects are completed duly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the erstwhile Andhra Pradesh, excessive economic centralisation took place in and around Hyderabad. Even today, a lion’s share of Telangana’s (the newly formed state) revenue is generated by Hyderabad. It is because all major developmental activities were planned in Hyderabad and less emphasis was placed on the development of other cities and towns. Bearing this experience in mind, the new Andhra Pradesh should be diversified in its development trajectory. Single-city centric development will cost the state dearly (like it did during its bifurcation). The capital should be restricted to administrative uses. Necessary infrastructure should be built in other cities to transform them into major centres in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Visakhapatnam, or Vizag, in its anglicised form, is a happening port city with a notable presence of the software industry. It has the potential to emerge as a major IT hub and the government should take steps to harness the said potential. Rayalaseema, the southern part of Andhra Pradesh, receives scarce rainfall and is not as feasible for agriculture as the other regions are. On the other hand, southern India is not a manufacturing power in the country. Andhra Pradesh could fill this gap by developing the Rayalaseema region into a major industrial and manufacturing hub. Like the existing Sri City Special Economic Zone (SEZ), a rising industrial hub in the southern part of the state, more of such initiatives can be taken up for the same purpose. The lawmakers should learn from their earlier experiences. They should make plans in such a way that development is spread throughout the state rather than being concentrated in Amaravati. Andhra Pradesh should not repeat its mistakes. And using its scarce funds to create a grand city of Amaravati would be doing so, in fact, one could say it’s already doing so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘Amaravati’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Great (Millennial) Depression</title><link href="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great (Millennial) Depression" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Great-Millennial-Depression</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression">&lt;p&gt;If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the WHO, about 300 million people around the world are affected by depression. Nearly 800,000 people commit suicide every year. Suicide is second on the list of leading causes of deaths in 15 to 29 year-olds today. In spite of this, only 1 in every 5 depressed people receives treatment consistent with modern practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous TV series and films have been made, aimed at tackling this. Their failure, however, has been appalling. Season 1 of the TV series &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Wh&lt;/em&gt;y features a series of tapes left behind by a girl who commits suicide while in high school. In these tapes, she explains the 13 reasons behind her drastic step. No wonder this series became very popular; it was not just relatable to the very core but the drama of listening to a dead girl’s tapes, explaining why she committed suicide, was scintillating. Besides the wave of awareness, the series left behind one adverse impact. The number of suicides increased by almost a third, instead of going down, ever since the series aired. Within three weeks of being aired, searches about suicides increased by a staggering 20%. Many blame it on the very graphic depiction of how Hannah Baker, the protagonist, took her life by slitting her wrists at the very end of the series. This is not something that audiences have witnessed before on television, certainly not in programmes aimed at teenagers. The popularity of the series earned it two more seasons in the years that followed. However, amidst all the concerns, Netflix altered the 3-minute sequence, although convinced that the series had nothing to do with the increase in suicide rates in the USA, over 2 years after its initial release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has, however, been a decline in the stigma surrounding mental health. People do seek to talk about and actively treat depression and other mental health problems. Various online portals and helplines are active to give help to those seeking it. Earlier, they failed to recognise depression as a disease that needed treatment. Instead, they saw it as inadequacy or incompetence. Certain old asylums are often considered to be haunted because of the unspoken torture within its walls in the past. Hundreds have died in various such locations around the world, after being shunned by society for being mentally ill. Shock therapy, invented in the Italy of the 1930s, was commonly practiced to treat ‘madness’. Many, even today, believe in the effectiveness of electroconvulsive therapy, although it has been repeatedly tagged as medical abuse by different organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are convinced that they are but &lt;strong&gt;doomed&lt;/strong&gt;. And this conviction comes from a place of hyperawareness. There is near-constant exposure to news of thousands being beheaded in the name of religion or people committing suicide by bringing down an entire airbus full of people along with themselves. Or, maybe, that people are capable of democratically electing a person who doesn’t believe that Global Warming, which, by the way, can facilitate the extinction of humanity, is real, as the Leader of the Free World. We are always talking and making memes about Trump’s tweets, the melting ice caps or India’s water crisis. We see the expendability of human life in the deaths of our beloved Cameron Boyce, Stan Lee, Avicii, Stephen Hawking, Dolores O’Riordan, David Cassidy, Chester Bennington, Bill Paxton, Carrie Fisher, Harper Lee, and Alan Rickman. In fact, most Millennials do not even conform to the term ‘Millennial’, tagging it as &lt;em&gt;overly optimistic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media and its ultra-fast nature have made it clear to the Millennials that humans are irrevocable. Millennials are &lt;strong&gt;aware&lt;/strong&gt; that the Zodiac Killer was never caught, MH-370 was never found and that France experienced its highest ever temperature in recorded history, earlier this year. They are aware of students shooting down hundreds in schools, abortion being banned and trees being cut. We know how this is affecting us all as a species and yet, there seems to be nothing that we can do about it. The news of bad incidents looms over us every day along with the knowledge that it can happen to any of us too. The incredibly talented and very dead singer Kurt Cobain did tell us, “Just because you are paranoid, does not mean they are not after you.” Millennials are the first generation to grow up in an era of both overwhelming awareness and paralysing feeling of our incapability to be able to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know what is expected of us, the perfect job and the perfect partner, and we are aware of how it is just a pipe dream. They tell us it is social media reinforcements of everyone else living the perfect life that is making our generation depressed. That we are trying to reach for standards we will never attain. But I think there is more to the Great Millennial Depression than just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that you are Einstein-smart, devilishly beautiful and incredibly funny. Are you among the top 10 something? If you are not, well then, you do not matter. Let us assume that you are among the world’s top 10 most hilarious people. Will you hold the position forever? What happens next year? What if you face a decade-long writer’s block and go bankrupt? Perhaps you &lt;em&gt;succeed&lt;/em&gt; and go on a cruise with your soulmate and drown in your bathtub? We all will die one day and there will be nothing left of us in a few decades. No one will remember our sacrifices, pain, hard work or the embarrassing moments that we have shared with our crushes. The question is, are we important? Are our actions significant? Why is it that humans have had the privilege to even exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have asked these for long and today, Millennials are convinced that nothing has an explanation. There is nowhere a certain someone is meant to be or something they are meant to do. They just exist. The stars were not specially created to dazzle us. Neither are we at the centre of the solar system, the universe or Creation in general. Things just exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think I am right, well then, congratulations, you are a nihilist. It is highly likely that you are a Millennial too. Turns out, the term nihilism has a very simple meaning. It is the rejection of all religious and moral principles. Nihilists believe that life has absolutely no meaning and yet humans keep seeking a way to give it some meaning, some purpose, but eventually die and are forgotten. In Tyler Durden’s &lt;em&gt;immortal&lt;/em&gt; words: “We are the middle children of history, man. No purpose or place. We have no Great War, No Great Depression. Our Great War’s a spiritual war… Our Great Depression is our Lives.” Nihilism is hot today. The great success of Bojack Horseman, Rick and Morty, Hazel’s response to Augustus’ confession of the fear of oblivion and so on bear testimony to this very fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that depression and the popularity of nihilistic ideas have increased exponentially about the same time makes me wonder if they share some sort of a symbiotic relationship. If someone is depressed, the consolation that nothing really matters must help, surely? In fact, Optimistic Nihilism emphasises the notion that no one will ever remember one’s ill actions or embarrassing moments. Not all people who are depressed believe in nihilism though. But all nihilists may to some extent be sad. Everything productive that people do today is because they believe that it has meaning and life has a purpose. Nihilists dismiss this idea as nonsense. To them nothing has meaning and thus, there is no use doing anything. And the depressed do feel this way. Besides, I am sure you might have noticed the surge of suicidal and nihilistic memes’ pages on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilists do not care about anything because nothing makes sense or has any significance. And thus, nothing can make them sad. Embarrassing moments do not matter and so there is no need to overthink them. Mistakes and bad deeds do not matter and so, they can move on and do something better. Of course, life has no meaning. But we can try to give it one or at least try and be happy for the little time that we have on our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilism, however, contrary to popular opinion, is not the lack of hope. Life has no meaning. But, that does not mean that you cannot give it some purpose. Moreover, your failures do not count in anyone’s book and so, one should not be held back by them. Whether or not nihilism has been helping the depressed generation is up for debate. But, then again, there is no point in arguing. Alan Moore in &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; did very accurately say- “Why do we argue? Life is so fragile, a successful virus clinging to a speck of mud, suspended in endless nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a generation trapped in the growing realisation that they must face and solve the environmental, social and political crises of the day while lodged in the belief that nothing really matters. The same thing that causes our depression is also the source of our respite; how &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; it all matters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime</title><link href="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime">&lt;p&gt;When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When determining what is preventing Arsenal from progressing as a club, it is now clear that there can no longer be a single scapegoat and accountability must be shared across different departments of the club. Wenger had an almost autocratic reign for 2 decades and it was going to take more than 1 man to replace him. Have Arsenal hired the right men?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural place to start is with Wenger’s direct successor, Unai Emery. When Arsenal announced the appointment of the Spaniard, the press release described his role as ‘head coach’, perhaps indicating that he wouldn’t have the same influence on matters such as transfers as his predecessor did and his role would be more focused towards on-pitch matters. From a results point of view, Emery improved Arsenal’s points total and league position by 7 points and 1 place respectively, although it wasn’t hard to improve on a season in which Arsenal lost a staggering 11 away league games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 2 difficult games to open the season, Arsenal had a strong first few months in terms of results, although the performances weren’t on par and stars Aaron Ramsey and Mesut Özil were noticeably less influential than they were during the Wenger years. As of yet, Emery has failed to maximise Özil’s ability. Since he moved to north London in 2013, the German world champion has regularly topped the stats for assists and chances created as he operated as the fulcrum of Wenger’s side, however there was a sharp decline in his output last season. Whilst Özil himself must shoulder most of the blame, he was sometimes bypassed by Emery’s system which saw a more direct way of chance creation. This was often through long passes to Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang and Alexandre Lacazette up front or through Bosnian wing-back Sead Kolašinac getting in behind the back-line, though his end product was often found wanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the reliance on Kolašinac as an attacking outlet caused problems at the back as Arsenal’s left side of the defence was often left exposed by his attacking charges. This contributed to a season where Arsenal conceded just as many league goals as they had the season prior, ending up with a worse defensive record than the likes of Newcastle and Everton despite Emery’s reputation as a pragmatic, defensive minded coach. After years of attractive attacking football under Wenger, it did seem as though a lot of the Arsenal fanbase were more than prepared to trade that off for a more conservative style if it yielded better results. Diego Simeone and Massimiliano Allegri were often (optimistically) touted as possible Wenger replacements, both men having league titles from the top 5 European leagues and multiple Champions League finals under their belts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was Unai Emery who eventually filled Wenger’s boots. The Spaniard came with a reputation as a Europa League specialist and as impressive as his 3 successive tournament victories with Sevilla were, they themselves are a sign of what an uninspiring appointment he was. Sevilla only had the chance to participate in the Europa League by virtue of not being good enough to get into the last 16 of the Champions League. Emery’s Sevilla won the Europa League in 2014 but finished 5th in La Liga, missing out on Champions League qualification and allowing them to win the Europa League the following year. That 2015 triumph guaranteed them qualification for the following season’s Champions League due to a new rule whereby the Europa League winners automatically qualified for Europe’s premier club competition the next season. However, Sevilla could only scrape 3rd in Group D, dropping down back into the EL and winning the competition again, beating Liverpool in the final. Emery was firmly established as a quality second tier manager, cemented further by a mediocre spell with a star-studded Paris Saint Germain team, making him a questionable choice. He was a known quantity; he wouldn’t be a disaster, but neither would he get more out of the squad than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a transfer policy that doesn’t seem to be prioritising youth, the club have signed experienced players such as Aubameyang, Sokratis, Henrikh Mkhitaryan and Stefan Lichsteiner in recent years. Arsenal are currently stagnating with little sign of improvement unless drastic changes are made. Having said all of that, the outlook on Arsenal as a whole would be vastly different if the club had managed to secure a top 4 place over a heavily criticised Maurizio Sarri-led Chelsea or Tottenham, who were distracted by their European run but still managed to stumble over the finishing line. In the end, Arsenal finished just 1 point behind Chelsea and 2 behind Tottenham. Arsenal’s failure to win any of their 4 games against Brighton, Leicester, Wolves and Crystal Palace in the final run-in proved to be the sticking point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seemingly prioritised the Europa League, Emery’s chance at salvaging the season went up in smoke as he was outclassed by Sarri and Chelsea in a humiliating defeat to the London rivals in Baku. With Unai Emery at the helm Arsenal are seemingly treading water and for that reason serious questions have to be asked about whether he is the man to take the club forward or whether a change is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of Emery’s faults, the majority of the blame has to lie within the higher echelons of the club. If we rewind a year (give or take), back to when it was announced Arsène Wenger’s tenure in north London would be coming to an end, Chief Executive Ivan Gazidis and Head of Recruitment Sven Mislintat were primed to be the figureheads of Arsenal’s rebuilding process. Gazidis made himself vocal around this time and spearheaded the search for a new manager, reportedly considering former Arsenal captain Mikel Arteta before settling on Emery. However, he departed for A.C Milan in September 2018, a puzzling decision that was soon followed by Mislintat leaving after barely 12 months in his role, having recruited the likes of Aubameyang, Matteo Guendouzi, Lucas Torreira and Bernd Leno.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal felt Gazidis was so influential that he couldn’t be replaced by one man, thus Vinai Venkatesham and Raul Sanllehi were brought in. The pair featured in a lengthy interview conducted on Arsenal’s social media platforms, a PR exercise in which they looked to assert their positions as the key directors at the club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mislintat, meanwhile, has been replaced by former Arsenal midfielder, Edu. The invincible left his role as general coordinator of the Brazilian national team following their Copa America triumph, being brought in as Arsenal’s first ever technical director with less than a month of the transfer window left. Arsenal’s window, so far, has been disappointing; pursuits of the likes of Kieran Tierney, William Saliba and Wilfried Zaha have been unsuccessful as of now. Once news broke that Arsenal reportedly had a transfer budget of just £45 million, expectations were lowered. With the season fast approaching, Edu will have to quickly re-accustom himself to his old surroundings and set off bargain hunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal owner Stan Kroenke has been extensively criticised for his frugality which, along with Arsenal’s high wage bill and their inability to maximise their assets, has led to this paltry budget. In recent years, the club has let key players such as Mesut Özil, Alexis Sanchez, Aaron Ramsey, Danny Welbeck, Jack Wilshere and Santi Cazorla run their contracts down to the final 6 months, with the latter four having left for free meaning Arsenal did not receive any money to help with finding replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite those inconveniences, the most crippling examples of poor asset management came with Arsenal’s 2 star players as they swapped Alexis Sanchez for (then 29 year old) Manchester United flop Henrikh Mkhitaryan in an attempt to extract some kind of value for the Chilean, reportedly giving Mkhitaryan a 4 year, £180,000 a week contract. Meanwhile, Arsenal retained the services of Özil for the small price of £350,000 a week over 4 years, with the club desperately trying to dump him just 18 months later. Furthermore, with big contract extensions reportedly being lined up for 30-year old Aubameyang and 28-year-old Lacazette, the club must decide whether they want to risk a situation where they again overpay players as they exit their prime. Conversely, the alternative could be to have a repeat of the Sanchez and Ramsey situations if they choose to let the attackers run down the remainder of their contracts, which expire in 2021 and 2022 respectively. It is a somewhat unenviable position for Arsenal management to be in as it must also be considered that any decision to sell either of these two fan favourites will be widely lambasted by the Arsenal faithful, not to mention the impact selling a star player would have on the team’s success. Signings such as 18-year-old forward Gabriel Martinelli represent the player profile that Arsenal should be targeting; young players with potential to improve and be sold for profit. This was the approach Arsenal took following their move to the Emirates Stadium when funds were restricted. Players such as Cesc Fabregas, Emmanuel Adebayor, Robin Van Persie and Alex Song put in years of good service before recouping high transfer fees. Arsenal are currently not in a position to contend for the Premier League or Champions League but could be in 5-8 years if they are patient and have a long-term plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a club has undergone such drastic change in such a short period of time, it is important that it has a clear vision about how to achieve its goals. When a club’s Chief Executive and Head of Recruitment leave in the same season, it makes said club look like an aimless mess. Arsenal’s transfer plans look to be uncreative to say the least. When former Borussia Dortmund scout Sven Mislintat was at the club, Arsenal signed 3 former players that he knew from his time at the German club in Aubameyang, Mkhitaryan and Sokratis. Interestingly, despite this, he was reportedly ‘dismayed’ when Unai Emery requested the signing of one of his former players, Denis Suarez, with the German leaving shortly after. There seems to be a worrying pattern here with several former Emery players such as Ever Banega, Christopher Nkunku and Thomas Meunier also being linked with a move to the Emirates. Furthermore, widely reported targets Kieran Tierney and Wilfried Zaha come with a premium added to their price due to their home grown statuses which isn’t optimal for a club with limited funds. The future looks bleak and will continue to look so until the club commits to a full scale rebuild where they prioritise the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal should be hiring a young manager that has a clear footballing philosophy with the potential to win major honours; Julian Nagelsmann and Mikel Arteta are possible options. The club must come to terms with the fact that the current squad is not close to being good enough to challenge for the league title and youngsters like Reiss Nelson, Hector Bellerin, Ainsley Maitland-Niles, Alex Iwobi, Guendouzi and Torreira should be considered the key to future success, along with any signings that have potential to grow into quality players. This is likely to be a slow process, but, due to the mess the club has gotten itself into, it is a necessary one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do Millennials Fetishise Productivity?</title><link href="/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Millennials Fetishise Productivity?" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity">&lt;p&gt;There’s always that one favorite cousin in the family, who wakes up at 5 AM to meditate and revise the previous day’s lessons, pays attention during all lectures, is up to date with social media and is going to intern at Microsoft for the coming summer. And then, there’s every other Millennial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials; who manage to sleep through eight alarms in a span of ten minutes, we are not eating healthy and we are definitely not performing well in college. But we are still quite there. Last I remember, we were thriving on self-deprivation, grinding through work and pulling off all-nighters just to submit that one assignment on time. We are most definitely not the ‘ungrateful, lazy, unambitious generation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obsession with maximising the resources at hand (case in point: time) goes beyond just textbooks on neoclassical economists’ theories of optimisation. It runs in our blood. Internalised capitalism or a fetish for productivity, call it what you want. We feel we must work hard all the time and rest should bring on a bout of guilt. We are relentless in the act of pursuing something, to the point that the fixation with pursuance takes precedence over asking ourselves what we truly want. We take ourselves too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our days are intricately scheduled because how else will we be content? The Starbucks way of life has inspired us to grind through the week to be able to enjoy the weekend. But that happy weekend never arrives. We work hard every weekend to better the next one. The drive to the movies is reserved for making calls, emails are catered to while waiting on a dinner date, backlog and future plans are left for vacations. All this with the hope of this professional development turning into essentially, what we call, a good life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anti-capitalism, social justice flag-waving, trying to embody ‘wokeness’ generation finds itself in a state of inner turmoil. Corporate lifestyles leave no time for leisure, ‘the basis of culture’ (courtesy: Josef Pieper, German philosopher). The normalisation of dissatisfaction with the existing work environment and of constant struggle is dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pervading uncertainty in our lives contributes to our anxiety. The rapid development of technology has added to the fear of being automated out, more so now than ever before, and adapting to the highly dynamic work environments in different sectors is not easy either. Moreover, with the dwindling employment rates, it is safe to say the economy has not particularly been a friend. The apprehensions cultivating from the need to pay off student debt means we cannot switch jobs in this exceedingly competitive job market. The Millennials have, therefore, resigned to working excruciatingly hard in college and grad school to avail, at least, a job with decent pay. As long as we need the money and real estate, we will learn to live with the misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just a mundane 9 AM to 5 PM job. There is also passion. Passion, because what is life without it? A reason to be fiercely alive, a way to be ferociously happy. Millennials spend a huge amount of their lives looking for a passion to offset the effect of stress. We love being unique, to do something different from the rest. So, we go the extra mile to stand out and outdo our peers. It is not called a hobby anymore, it is a skill. It is something we can have on our resume while being equally fascinating to qualify as something to post about on our social media. We attend galas, watch theatre, immerse ourselves in poetry, visit exhibitions and try extremely hard to keep up with pop culture. Even art is not for the sake of art anymore, it is something to be done; a territory waiting to be embarked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invasion of technology has wiped away the distinction between our personal and work lives in a way it had not happened for previous generations. With the convenience of always being able to send and receive emails, documenting at all times, we have brought the office back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are part of a society which has taught us that stagnancy is acceptable, but quitting is not. The romanticisation of stability has made us layout an entire plan for our life. Being the generation that has inherited soaring housing, education, and living costs, settling down becomes the ultimate goal. It is not something that has come to us as a matter of personal choice. Our childhoods were meticulously supervised. Regular homework, summer classes to learn a new hobby, timely school assessments, yada yada. Things that do not eventually lead to a bigger goal do not belong in our lives, which is why we are always expected to know what we want. What to study, where to get a job, which job after the current one. Moreover, there is a sense of finality in every decision; the first decision needs to be the right one, otherwise, everything goes downhill. Quitting jobs we do not like is a sign of ‘impulsiveness’ and ‘weakness’. We all wish to achieve stability, what we end up getting is monotonicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do life in bits and pieces. When we seek thrill, we resort to extreme sports (ah, passion). Finding a little bit of happiness to thrive on, in between life. In the fear of being left behind, we have reached so far ahead that we are blinded to all the life that’s happening outside of our work-home space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we hustle because we are uncomfortable. The discomfort arriving from the feeling of losing out on time; the same time we spend watching inspirational videos on YouTube and scrolling through Instagram feeds, constantly reiterating feelings of inadequacy and of not being ‘good enough’. And for the rest, we know the drill. The drill of the hustle. Panic, dissatisfaction, failure. Rather, the fear of failure. As a generation, we were built to not be akin to failure. We tell ourselves these marks matter the most, this social gathering I cannot miss, if I do not get this job…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The break down of the journey has vanished, there is an origin and destiny. A far fetched destiny that is so flawless, we tend to make the path longer and more and more dreadful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hrishita Sharma</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">There’s always that one favorite cousin in the family, who wakes up at 5 AM to meditate and revise the previous day’s lessons, pays attention during all lectures, is up to date with social media and is going to intern at Microsoft for the coming summer. And then, there’s every other Millennial.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Did We Let the World Down?</title><link href="/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Did We Let the World Down?" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is fascinating to see how quickly we have moved from a phase of ultra-optimism about our future to, as Henry Kissinger described in his latest book, a state of disorder not seen since World War II.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990’s, it was the end of all negative ‘&lt;em&gt;isms’&lt;/em&gt;. Like the climax of a typical Bollywood movie, &lt;em&gt;Good&lt;/em&gt; was slowly prevailing over &lt;em&gt;Evil&lt;/em&gt;. The days of Communism and Colonialism were gone. Former authoritarian regimes had been gripped by democratic fever. Walls that divided us were being struck down. Half the world was developed, and the countries in the other half were accepting the ideals of globalisation, opening their economies to a more prosperous future. It finally looked that the world will be rich together. Francis Fukuyama called it the ‘End of History’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who was going to lead the world into this much-awaited future: a new, progressive-thinking generation, the millennials, for whom war was confined to history textbooks. They were already calling the world a &lt;em&gt;Global Village&lt;/em&gt; and themselves &lt;em&gt;International Citizens&lt;/em&gt;. Instead of declaring war on each other, humans started declaring war against terrorism and poverty. The chorus of the song, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GFGPSx6cPN0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Love&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” by Blue, seemed to sum up the mood of the times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the same song starts with the lines, “&lt;em&gt;It is kind of funny, how life can change. Can flip 180, in a matter of days!&lt;/em&gt;”. And so it did. Try time-travelling to the beginning of the 21st century and telling one of the many optimists of the era that come 2019, protectionism will be trumping globalisation, a major migrant crisis, ethnic conflict, and civil war will still be the call of the day, that a ‘rules-based international order’ will be a hope rather than a reality, that countries will choose conflict over co-operation, that international trade will slow as tariffs rise, and anti-establishment leaders will be coming to power across nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question: &lt;em&gt;how did everyone f*ck up everything?&lt;/em&gt; A synopsis of the Arab Spring might be a good parallel to draw. There was a social movement for political change, optimism was sky-high, some progress was made, and just when all pieces of the puzzle seemed to be coming together, due to &lt;em&gt;someone’s&lt;/em&gt; self-interest, everything went back to square one. That is where the world stands today: back to square one. It was much ado about nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we now rename the millennials as the “Lost Generation”? The ones who had the golden opportunity to firmly establish human civility but could not. Should the rest of this article be an apology letter on behalf of all millennials, for screwing it all up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming the driver for losing control of the car makes sense. Except, the millennial was never in the driver’s seat! Instead of making a scapegoat out of a whole generation (who also suffer from the same problems as the rest), it is time we ask some uncomfortable questions and come up with solutions which might disgruntle a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the millennials may not have united the world, one area where the world seems united against the millennials is denying them political participation. The global average age of an MP (Member of Parliament) is 53, and the global median age is 29. This means, there is a gap of 24 years (almost one whole generation) between the policymakers and the people affected by the policy. In other words, we live in a young world run by old ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 2.2% of MPs around the world are under 30. A staggering 76% of upper chambers of parliament have no MPs under the age of 30. The most absurd status quo in global democracy is the ‘waiting time’ between the eligible voting age and eligible participation age. On average, an eligible voter needs to wait for 5 years to become eligible for running for office. For example, in India, a person aged 18 can vote but cannot run for the lower house until he is 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more in-depth study reveals that, barring some honourable exceptions like Ecuador and Bhutan, every country, irrespective of region, has inadequate youth political representation. Remember, this is a generation whose idealistic bubble burst along with the housing bubble of 2008. Millennials caught themselves day-dreaming amid the worst economic crisis in 75 years. Coming at a time when most millennials were seeking jobs, the financial crisis ensured that they became the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019&quot;&gt;first generation to be earning less than their parents&lt;/a&gt;, despite having more qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While millennials around the world were kept busy by unemployment and underemployment, their representatives kept getting older. For instance, the average age of the US Congress has jumped from 49 in 1981 to 61 in 2014 (thankfully, the latest Congress is an exception to the trend, with the average age dropping by 10 years). Nigeria, with a median age of just 18, has never seen a leader less than 50 years old. No wonder, the potential African economic powerhouse witnessed a popular &lt;em&gt;#NotTooYoungToRun&lt;/em&gt; campaign before the 2019 elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair to our old politicians, millennials cannot expect to be politically represented if they do not turn up for voting in the first place! Globally, the average turnout amongst the youth is 30%, much lesser than the overall turnout. The theory on electoral participation suggests, with some credible research, that voting is habitual. If you vote once, you will likely vote again. As a corollary, if you do not vote, it is unlikely you will participate the next time. If millennials miss out early on, many of them will likely not participate ever. As per some estimates, the average youth turnout in mid-terms in the USA over the last 2 decades is a meagre 21.66%. Millennials in ageing societies are further dissuaded from voting, as they feel their vote ‘hardly matters’ when they form a small part of the electorate. In European elections, less than one-third of young voters participated in 2014 (in Finland, turnout was 10.4%). Japan, another ageing society, has been facing similar problems and had to lower its voting age to 16 to fight this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break these structural barriers, a few conventional and innovative ideas exist. The most common solution is reservation. Having youth quotas sounds reasonable enough (of course, subject to other socio-political considerations), given that empirical data suggests that they are politically marginalised. These quotas can also reduce inter-generational conflict in policymaking, as recent examples of ideological clashes on climate change and immigration suggest. Simply, if we are making policies for the future, the part of the population having the highest stake in it should be involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small but growing number of countries like Kenya, Egypt and Kyrgyzstan have youth quotas in their parliaments. Some of these countries also require a certain percentage of the youth getting elected through these quotas to be women. Having gender parity in youth quotas helps solve another problem in representational politics: women make up only 24% of parliamentarians worldwide. This imbalance is less pronounced amongst the young MPs, with a 60:40 ratio. Let’s not let another opportunity pass us by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other ideas around reservation include reserving seats in local elections (like Sri Lanka, Uganda and Peru) and political parties (like Vietnam, Sweden and Turkey). All forms have their benefits but progress can only be made when youth is defined as someone under the age of 30. Many countries introducing the youth quota have set the bar ‘too high’ at 35 or 40. Empirical research by the Inter-Parliamentary Union tells us that such policies do help in greater representation for people below 40, but the millennials are left out again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from reducing the eligible age to run in elections (as discussed above), another electoral reform can be the promotion of the Proportional Representation (PR) system. A PR system induces political parties to put up candidates from various backgrounds unlike a First-Past-the-Post system, where candidates are usually majoritarian, populist, and in most cases, NOT in their 20s. The share of young MPs is significantly higher in PR systems or a mix of the two systems. This is particularly useful in ageing societies where the young, aspiring politicians fail to get enough votes as their core support base is insignificant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next and a major step forward will be to check political funding in elections. In countries where political campaigning is influenced by private donations and limitless spending, the youth find themselves unable to raise such resources with little political and business contacts and self-worth (unless they are themselves heir to a political dynasty). Money cannot buy you happiness but as long as it can buy you power, do not expect youth political participation to go up. At the least, countries can set up recognized Youth Parliaments and integrate it with the national parliament (most “Youth Parliaments” that function today are currently through NGOs and private initiatives). This gives the youth a legitimate forum to express their opinions. Politics is not a science, it takes practice. Hence, promotion and mainstreaming of Youth Parliaments will prepare a larger number of youngsters with varied backgrounds for politics than any other means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be sure, age is not the only factor which makes people not want to participate politically. Education, unemployment, immigration background, marital status, and income are some other important influencing factors. However, it is the Millennial which is facing the brunt of a combination of these factors. In South Africa, where democracy is as old as a millennial, &lt;em&gt;#IWantToVoteBut&lt;/em&gt; trended hours before the polls opened, and was accompanied by reasons like limited job prospects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a millennial, I can guarantee that we are much more than a bunch of people who do not care about the larger good, as we are often made out to be. And there are positive signs around. The number of millennials in the recent US House of Representatives is up by 420%. Green parties in the EU are becoming a political force to reckon with, in large part because of rising millennial support. In Indonesia, the Indonesian Solidarity Party (PSI) has been formed to represent the millennial voice. Not bad for a country where 15 years ago, youth would shy away from public political participation as they were slowly transitioning to a democracy. Recent elections around the world have seen more MPs below 45 being elected. This article started by laughing off the 21st-century optimists, but a little hope of change from the most educated generation ever does not hurt, does it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidyarthi</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">It is fascinating to see how quickly we have moved from a phase of ultra-optimism about our future to, as Henry Kissinger described in his latest book, a state of disorder not seen since World War II.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree</title><link href="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree" /><published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree">&lt;p&gt;The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some millennials, burdened by low-income jobs and debt obligations, living from paycheck to paycheck, are genuinely unable to finance stock purchases, the statistics tell us how even better-off millennials are straying away from investing and are preferring to save instead. Unfortunately, their risk-averse tendencies are miscalculated and are costing them precious returns, since the S&amp;amp;P 500 (adjusted for inflation and dividends reinvested) averaged a 7.92% return between 2007 to 2017, while the money market bank accounts averaged a 0.3% return during the same period. Nearly 42% of millennials are conservative investors, as opposed to 38% of GenXers and 23% of the Boomers. They are unwilling to fully embrace the financial markets, and when they do, it is only through a safer, less costly mechanism such as that of an Exchange Traded Fund (ETF), which is a type of fund that holds multiple underlying assets rather than a single stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worth noting is that their caution seems selective. Millennials’ risk-aversion appears to be more about scepticism when one realises how they have stayed away only from what they personally saw fail - the stock markets. They are still the ones responsible for inflating the crypto-market, despite its lack of intrinsic value or any ‘faith’ backing. The only argument in defense of their wild investment choice is perhaps the sophisticated distributed ledger technology used in the asset which makes the case for fostering technological innovation in the stock markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the politically correct environment, with encouragement from Hollywood, has put capitalism out of style for many. The ones still willing to invest have raised the bar over mere profitability when making an investment decision. Company ethics and transparency are a primary consideration for millennials when they choose to invest, and these additional filters reduce the overall amount invested. The rate of investment for women is in an even poorer state. The Harris Poll survey revealed that a staggering 79% of women do not invest at all, with 70% of them stating that the process is confusing to them, while 60% of them believing how they felt investing was ‘an old-white man’s game’. Clearly, the Millennials need a better education when it comes to managing their finances and getting over &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture is clear: Millennials are savers and not investors. 71% of Millennial workers are saving for retirement, and begin saving at the median age of 24, which puts the GenX’s median saving age of 30 to shame. And while they rely on the banks for saving, they try to keep away from availing any of the other services. A three year study from Scratch, an in-house unit of Viacom, as a part of the &lt;em&gt;Millennial Disruption Study&lt;/em&gt;, found that not only were banks among the ‘Most Hated’ brands, but a third of this demographic cohort believed that they’d be better off without them. This is a major concern for banks, who are now resorting to appeasement techniques. Providing special discounts on credit card bills and easing out the enrollment mechanism for loans are a few examples. This has also partially fueled the rise of fintech in the formal banking system and is encouraging the development of such technologies. Developing a system with a user-friendly interface and greater transparency by incorporation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning is an obvious solution to this issue. For instance,  a ZeroHedge survey revealed that one in three Millennials would rather invest in Bitcoin than in the stock market, simply because of the unconventional and futuristic technology involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that in traditional economics, the West had never been considered the saver’s economy, and this pattern is shifting for the better. The situation is quite akin to the rise in savings post the hyperinflationary periods in Germany after World War I, which incidentally was also a result of the psychological impact of the crisis. At the macro level, greater savings would imply lesser dependence on foreign investment. Lesser inflow of USD denominated investment in the USA implies lesser demand for the dollar. The consequent decline in appreciation of the USD is great for recovering the Current Account Deficit, which has been a primary long-term concern for the nation. But this advantage is dwarfed when growth concerns step in, as slowdowns are the projected case for the next few years. Additionally, with the rise of protectionist, right-wing governments around the globe, millennials are increasingly inclining towards what they think is socialism, which implies increased disinterest towards the financial markets. And that is a terrible prospect for growth. Hence, even though this demographic cohort has been through quite a lot at an impressionable age, they must put their concerns aside and take up a more rational approach. They have made a wise decision to save, considering the depleting ability of the burgeoning federal balance sheet to finance their post-retirement expenses. But they must learn to be comfortable with the idea of some risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Millennials and Meme Culture</title><link href="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials and Meme Culture" /><published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and the intent behind it shape the adaptability of art. Art can be used as a mouthpiece for personal vexation, for political propaganda, as a romantic sonnet, a rebellious speech, or even as satire. The possibilities are endless and the means to propagate them have a few malleable forms. The very beginning of art was through illustrations, statuettes, and fictional stories. As our ancestors developed their faculties, so did art. It has since then taken several forms, namely illustration, text, sculpting, acting, dance, song, cinema and now, memes. Like innumerable developments in the field of art, memes too betray a thing or two about the period to which they are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;meme&lt;/em&gt; originally comes from the Greek word ‘&lt;em&gt;mimema&lt;/em&gt;’, meaning imitation. The term was coined by Richard Dawkins in his book &lt;em&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;/em&gt; in 1976. Back then, however, the word didn’t gain a lot of recognition. A few decades later, after the emergence of the Internet, memes have surged to be an art form most characteristic of the millennials or Gen Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how a meme is a form of art, we need to understand other art forms. The key idea behind any art is to freeze or compress a particular thought or vision, a whole infinity into a finite space. It confronts our consciousness with matters that we miss out on due to activities essential to survival. If rendered well enough, it takes hold of our spirits and colonises it with whatever it wanted to. Consuming art is a conscious effort and has always been, until the arrival of memes. Memes have gone astray from this principle of art. Memes are consumed in an unstudied manner, seldom requiring cognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes are symbolic of millennials. They symbolise the hyperactive lifestyle of our generation. They betray the cultural degradation we are going through. A degradation that makes us ponder and say less and less and passively consume more and more. Our vocabulary is riddled with buzzwords which lose meaning with every passing day. Abundance has made us fall out of our practice of thinking. Time has shortened itself relatively, and we constantly seek to escape reality. On average, in a single day, a person goes through a hundred different thoughts, which are &lt;em&gt;not his own&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are losing the originality of thought, the creativity that we are born with. It is in the nature of words and of our human selves to make it difficult to say just about anything. It is momentous to experience the bittersweetness of struggling for words to express how we feel, to lose words just as they are clawing at the base of one’s throat. But with meme culture we lose that. My broken expression and my efforts give way to tagging my friends in memes and to what Buzzfeed tells me describes me and the culture of my generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The erosion of human cognition is alarming and evermore because of the manner of consumption. As mentioned before, memes are consumed quite absently not requiring a conscious effort. This leaves us unguarded, vulnerable to what the memes represent. And, as the practice of conscious thinking ebbs away, so does our consciousness towards life. We are gradually turning apathetic, normalising things that should evoke deep concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Phil Kaye tells us, “If you repeat something over and over again it loses its meaning.” The words ‘climate change’ turn into a category of memes you share, people’s mental traumas become a ‘&lt;em&gt;mood&lt;/em&gt;’ to us and bashing capitalist exploitation just something we do for the kick of feeling edgy. The outrageous loses the ability to outrage us anymore. We think we feel so much that we end up feeling very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A generation distinguished by a mental health crisis, an existential crisis, a crisis of faith, and a crisis of belief requires, above all, empathy and a careful understanding of the self to counter all our crises. But with the emergence of memes, the probability of countering them is plummeting. Memes that represent cultures and societies, on both micro and macro levels, qualify as phenomenal and path-breaking. Memes have helped us understand our kind better, they’ve taken away the alienation we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, memes have ended up normalising, without us realising, a lot that is worrisome. The apathy we feel towards ourselves and our actions is of grave concern. The manifestation of this apathy is seen in the increasing streak of nihilism in our generation. Memes are blurring the lines and lies constructed through fiction over the ages and slowly lifting our trust from certain systems of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough about the villainy of memes. Memes are an extension of postmodernism. One can’t discount all of the good that memes have brought. They’ve made us aware of things we otherwise would have remained oblivious of: culture, people, politics, ideologies, sports, our favourite celebrities. Memes are reaching to form a global culture, unparalleled by any art form before. Millennials understand diversity better than any of our previous generations. Millennials are aware of and understand the climate crisis, the water crisis and in general the humanitarian crisis breathing heavily down our necks. With the hyperactivity and the pace of things, it is difficult to take time out to be aware, to seek information, but with memes, it is no longer an arduous task. The simplicity of it is probably its greatest feature. It psychologically functions on the need to remain simple. Perhaps why we keep returning to memes in the face of rising complexities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes represent a milestone in the evolution of art, a point at which human art has transcended from a confrontation of our inner consciousness to an unguarded passive intake of what lies before one. For better or for worse, meme culture has a sinister ability to both reveal and shape the people who consume it the most, namely the Millennials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.</summary></entry></feed>