<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-07T10:00:51+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age</title><link href="/Pubcast-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age" /><published>2019-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Pubcast-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-1">&lt;p&gt;The first of The Pangean’s &lt;em&gt;pubcasts&lt;/em&gt; is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirandamowbray/&quot;&gt;Dr Miranda Mowbray&lt;/a&gt;, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/harsh.tiwari/&quot;&gt;Harsh Tiwari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/reuben.pritchard/&quot;&gt;Reuben Pritchard&lt;/a&gt; sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology as a replacement for human interaction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(40)&quot;&gt;00:40&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology in the army and the workplace&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(1183)&quot;&gt;19:43&lt;/a&gt;), or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The accessibility of technology&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2127)&quot;&gt;35:27&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast1-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-1&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>the.pangean</name></author><summary type="html">The first of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Dr Miranda Mowbray, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data. In this podcast, Harsh Tiwari and Reuben Pritchard sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest: Introduction (00:00), Technology as a replacement for human interaction (00:40), Technology in the army and the workplace (19:43), or The accessibility of technology (35:27). Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why So Bad *rse?</title><link href="/Why-So-Bad-Arse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why So Bad *rse?" /><published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Why-So-Bad-Arse</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Why-So-Bad-Arse">&lt;p&gt;Raise your hand if you remember the &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt; fever that gripped Hollywood - and
pretty much the rest of the world too - in the fall of 2013. If you remember the
glittering reviews and the innumerable times ‘&lt;em&gt;shattered the glass ceiling&lt;/em&gt;’,
‘&lt;em&gt;badass princesses&lt;/em&gt;’ or ‘&lt;em&gt;Oscar worthy&lt;/em&gt;’ flashed before your eyes, till you
were made certain that all of life was meaningless unless you booked first-day,
deluxe seat tickets. If you remember how Disney Renaissance enthusiasts, across
the globe, made sure you knew that Anna and Elsa were &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt;, unlike the
&lt;em&gt;girly-girls&lt;/em&gt; you see in other princess movies. They are &lt;em&gt;empowered,&lt;/em&gt; with their
M-slit gowns and absence of a romantic wedding for an ending, jot that down. If
you remember how you found yourself at the theatre, semi-guilt tripped into
watching the movie, and finally realised that Jennifer Lee’s retelling of &lt;em&gt;The
Snow Queen&lt;/em&gt; to be, at most, a well-intentioned but weak tea nod as to what made
a woman ‘badass’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s funny, actually, because when one sits down to look back upon this legacy
of retconning traditionally feminine roles as &lt;em&gt;weak&lt;/em&gt;, so as to prop up
tomboyish, often desensitised heroines, it’s not just the creators, critics and
audience of present day showbiz media who are to blame. Even adored and revered
works like those of C S Lewis and Rowling, &lt;em&gt;yes, Rowling&lt;/em&gt;, have often sought to
perpetuate this trope, often under a carefully arranged veneer of offering
simple didactic messages in children’s literature. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s talk about &lt;em&gt;these girly-girls&lt;/em&gt;. Not just the predecessor Disney
princesses, no, but the so-called wimpy girls in the media, the featherbrained
airheads, the wet blankets. The ones who can’t and won’t punch assassins, knife
through captors or ride horses into sandstorms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For as long as I can remember, it was a struggle for me to find feminine,
unapologetically girly characters in literature and media, who were not
dismissed as prissy, uppity damsels or useless, shivering waifs whose plethora
of interests - sewing, fashion, painting, music, and so forth - were not
dismissed as completely decorative and impractical in the general context of the
storyline. Worse still, if I did manage to find a rare favourite, it was quite
the feat to avoid the barrage of snide remarks from acquaintances, friends, and
even more terrible - overenthusiastic vloggers and literary dissenters who were
sure to hammer home the fact that Sansa Stark and Amy March are, in fact,
horrible sinners doomed to burn in eternal hellfire for their crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sansa Stark, from George R R Martin’s &lt;em&gt;A Song of Ice and Fire,&lt;/em&gt; is a textbook
example of the stern fact that a non-tomboyish, non-sexualised female lead can
do nothing without being written off as a wimp. A young, naive lady of merely
eleven&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; when the series begins, Sansa is held captive, forced to endure the
slaughter of her family and shoulders through being a political pawn and a
hostage with kindness, bravery and resilience. She has no dragons and no swords,
she loves lemon cakes, ballads and handsome knights, and is therefore, by
default, painted by the &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; fandom as a wet blanket airhead. She’s
even seen as a veritable ableist demon for not feeling sexually attracted
towards a man thrice her age (and he hails from the house that murdered her
family, no less). She only manages to garner some sympathy after she is violated
in the TV adaptation, a scene that doesn’t even exist in the books. It is hardly
surprising that many male characters in the series, who do much worse, get away
with their misdeeds way easily. &lt;em&gt;Thrones’&lt;/em&gt; treatment of non-warrior women is
particularly repulsive. Sansa is made to mouth lines showing stoic gratitude
towards her assaulters for teaching her strength, and another female character,
who is often praised for being the snarky cool kid, demurely announces that she
doesn’t plan to be useless during battle, namely ‘sit knitting by the fire’.
Non-canonical lines, inserted because of the directors’ knowledge that they
specifically pander to the audience’s needs and explicit scenes where women
condemn softness and acts of ‘predictable’ ladyship, thereby metamorphosing into
&lt;em&gt;badasses,&lt;/em&gt; are aplenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is alarming that such scenes, in books and films, are often revered and
portrayed as a sort of phoenix-from-the-ashes-moment, worthy of wolf-whistles
and printed merchandise. Even more alarming is how the notion of empowerment has
grown so utterly distorted that nothing, save for panning people who do not go
against the grain, can properly qualify as a wholesome depiction of strong
women. Why, after all, is knitting by the fire, or working in the kitchen so
problematic? Do soldiers magically grow their uniforms? Does food come to us
without the contribution of those who make it? Demeaning the choice of a woman
to do as she pleases or act as she wants, is but an elaborately twisted route,
ultimately ending in degrading womanhood itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When C S Lewis published &lt;em&gt;The Last Battle&lt;/em&gt; in 1956 the final instalment of his
Narnia series, there was quite a bit of hue and outcry over his decision to
close the gates of Narnia upon Susan Pevensie, the older, calmer, more beautiful
and ladylike of the Pevensie sisters. After her family is killed in a car
accident and the souls of her siblings find eternal refuge in Narnia, (a clear
metaphor of an Eden-like realm) Susan is left alone, literally and figuratively
locked out of heaven, her dismissal most summarily executed by Lewis in a couple
of lines: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;My sister Susan,” answered Peter shortly and gravely, “is no longer a friend
of Narnia.&lt;/em&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem? Because it’s not so much a question of &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; her fate
was, as it is of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; she deserved such a peremptory conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Oh Susan!” said Jill. “She’s interested in nothing nowadays except nylons and
lipsticks and invitations. She always was a jolly sight too keen on being
grown-up&lt;/em&gt;…” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, of course. Dresses and makeup, wanting to socialise and have peers;
what could be more heinous a crime for an adolescent? Surely, a crime worthy of
being unpardonable, in a book replete with Biblical imagery and repeated
emphasis on the need to keep the innocence in children untainted, with a fervour
that would make Blake proud. If you are shaking your head at this, slightly
unconvinced, here’s a snippet from Lewis himself, where he makes it clear that
our lipstick-wearing, nylon-loving lady is not enjoying the fruits of the
Promised Land anytime soon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The books don’t tell us what happened to Susan. She is left alive in this
world at the end, having by then turned into a rather silly, conceited young
woman. But there’s plenty of time for her to mend and perhaps she will get to
Aslan’s country in the end… in her own way&lt;/em&gt;…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even while he offers us a glimmer of hope, one can’t help but wince at the last
lines. ‘Plenty of time for her to mend’ what, exactly? What is so indisputably
repulsive about Susan craving extremely normal things, for a girl of her age?
Why is there an immediate need to demonise a female character who chooses to
beautify herself with makeup and pretty clothes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, Susan’s crisis has attracted plenty of sympathetic voices from the
literary community: Philip Pullman, Neil Gaiman, J K Rowling - to name a few,
with Gaiman even creating a sort of spinoff short story with a very Susan-esque
protagonist, giving her a much-needed voice and agency. Still, the older
Pevensie sister remains an outcast of Narnia, a scarring reminder of what
happens to girls who dare to be…well, just be. The ugly implications of
girlish existence in Lewis’ ramrod world of old laws and deep magic are proof
enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Rowling, an interesting and somewhat ironic fact is that while the
&lt;em&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; series, on the forefront, seems chock-full of strong,
three-dimensional female characters, there is something slightly problematic in
the way she treats any character that teeters dangerously into &lt;em&gt;girly-girl&lt;/em&gt;
territory. Two classic examples are Cho Chang, Harry’s first girlfriend, who is
constantly vilified for being ‘too emotional’ and too mopey over her dead
boyfriend, and Fleur Delacour, who while she gets a much better conclusion, is
still written off as the shallow dumb blonde, with a subpar performance in the
Triwizard tournament where she’s the only female competitor. Cho is eventually
cast aside for Ginny, whom Harry considers wonderful because she is ‘rarely
weepy’. Constant misogynistic and slightly racist jabs are directed at Fleur by
none other than Molly and Ginny Weasley, two of the most glorified and
celebrated women in Harry’s life. Not even the minor characters escape
judgement: the Patil twins and Lavender Brown, bubblier and more extroverted
classmates of Hermione, are often reduced to nothing but cartoonish caricatures
vying for Harry and Ron’s affections in the movies. Besides the evocation of
unpleasant racial overtones, it’s something to think about, really. Where does
mild, school cliché-centric humour end and perpetual bracketing-and-bashing of
softness and &lt;em&gt;generic&lt;/em&gt; girlishness begin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal favourite though, is the much-hated Amy March from &lt;em&gt;Little Women&lt;/em&gt;.
Amy’s case is particularly interesting because Alcott never meant to malign her,
no, it’s the audience, unable to look past their ‘JO x LAURIE ENDGAME’ stupor,
who miss the whole point of Amy’s arc - the resourcefulness in her choice to
work within the conventions of traditional femininity instead of rebelling
against it, the raw honesty in her desire as an impoverished girl to enjoy
pretty material pleasures, the flaws and petty mistakes she succumbs to, because
she is not written to be liked, she is written to be &lt;em&gt;real.&lt;/em&gt; Jo’s struggles are
very earthy and very honest, and her staunch refusal to fit in and fulfil
societal expectations is admirable, but Amy’s willingness to maintain a sort of
harmony with her community and work towards self-fulfilment…how is that, in
any way, less gratifying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for that matter, what do all these endless debates actually uncover? What
does this hollow classification system of girls into &lt;em&gt;badasses&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;girly-girls&lt;/em&gt; entail?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is uncertain, but it’s surely not an easy one. One cannot simply go
for a shallow deconstruction of the &lt;em&gt;not-like-other-girls syndrome&lt;/em&gt; without
looking into why this syndrome had to arise at all. And then one finds that the
root of this bizarre phenomenon lies in square one: the &lt;em&gt;trivialisation&lt;/em&gt; of
tenderness in girls and women, leading many to think that female voices and
characters might not be taken seriously unless they are stripped away of all
that could possibly hint at compassion and clemency. While Katniss Everdeen,
Merida and the warrior heroines of some of the later Young Adult franchises may
have arrived at exactly the right moment to prevent oversaturation of the market
by the same kind of feminine representation, the boomerang effect that arose out
of this is girls, in the younger demographic, seeking validation by rejecting
and loudly denouncing traits that could possibly mark them as girly. This
denunciation shows an almost vitriolic hatred in harmless things, marked out as
extremely feminine motifs: anything pink and/or coded as &lt;em&gt;princessy&lt;/em&gt; being the
commonest examples. It’s alarming, it’s potentially harmful that the psyche of
girls is shaped by what they &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; be as opposed to what they prefer to
be, it leans towards the patriarchy having the last laugh at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, as hackneyed as this sounds, there is nothing more
reproachable than the actions and behaviour of one woman being tainted so as to
glorify another. Feminism and badassery don’t spring &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; from elaborate fight
sequences or by being completely stone-cold or perpetually displeased and in a
fighting stance. Yes, female characters so portrayed are valid, beautiful, even
necessary. But they are not the beginning and end of all that’s marvellous and
awe-inspiring about women. It’s definitely heartening to see a much more
positive and varied portrayal of sharp and brilliant women in contemporary
media, who don’t always depend on brawn or magic to achieve unanimous approval,
take the famous Elle Woods (&lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde)&lt;/em&gt; for example, a wonderful
subversion of the dumb blonde stereotype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while we praise Arya for knifing through her tormentors, we cannot forget
Sansa, who comforts children and women with songs during a battle; we can
celebrate angry, rebellious spirits without coming for gentle, tranquil hearts.
We can cherish both sides of the spectrum. We can appreciate that some
rebellions happen quietly, in utter tranquillity, glossed with pink and flowers.
We can, for once, not let the patriarchy win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe, just maybe at the end, Susan, the outcast of Narnia, no longer a
powerful queen but just gloriously and heartbreakingly a human girl, will have
the last laugh.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sritama Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Raise your hand if you remember the Frozen fever that gripped Hollywood - and pretty much the rest of the world too - in the fall of 2013. If you remember the glittering reviews and the innumerable times ‘shattered the glass ceiling’, ‘badass princesses’ or ‘Oscar worthy’ flashed before your eyes, till you were made certain that all of life was meaningless unless you booked first-day, deluxe seat tickets. If you remember how Disney Renaissance enthusiasts, across the globe, made sure you knew that Anna and Elsa were different, unlike the girly-girls you see in other princess movies. They are empowered, with their M-slit gowns and absence of a romantic wedding for an ending, jot that down. If you remember how you found yourself at the theatre, semi-guilt tripped into watching the movie, and finally realised that Jennifer Lee’s retelling of The Snow Queen to be, at most, a well-intentioned but weak tea nod as to what made a woman ‘badass’. It’s funny, actually, because when one sits down to look back upon this legacy of retconning traditionally feminine roles as weak, so as to prop up tomboyish, often desensitised heroines, it’s not just the creators, critics and audience of present day showbiz media who are to blame. Even adored and revered works like those of C S Lewis and Rowling, yes, Rowling, have often sought to perpetuate this trope, often under a carefully arranged veneer of offering simple didactic messages in children’s literature.  So, let’s talk about these girly-girls. Not just the predecessor Disney princesses, no, but the so-called wimpy girls in the media, the featherbrained airheads, the wet blankets. The ones who can’t and won’t punch assassins, knife through captors or ride horses into sandstorms.  For as long as I can remember, it was a struggle for me to find feminine, unapologetically girly characters in literature and media, who were not dismissed as prissy, uppity damsels or useless, shivering waifs whose plethora of interests - sewing, fashion, painting, music, and so forth - were not dismissed as completely decorative and impractical in the general context of the storyline. Worse still, if I did manage to find a rare favourite, it was quite the feat to avoid the barrage of snide remarks from acquaintances, friends, and even more terrible - overenthusiastic vloggers and literary dissenters who were sure to hammer home the fact that Sansa Stark and Amy March are, in fact, horrible sinners doomed to burn in eternal hellfire for their crimes. Sansa Stark, from George R R Martin’s A Song of Ice and Fire, is a textbook example of the stern fact that a non-tomboyish, non-sexualised female lead can do nothing without being written off as a wimp. A young, naive lady of merely eleven, when the series begins, Sansa is held captive, forced to endure the slaughter of her family and shoulders through being a political pawn and a hostage with kindness, bravery and resilience. She has no dragons and no swords, she loves lemon cakes, ballads and handsome knights, and is therefore, by default, painted by the Game of Thrones fandom as a wet blanket airhead. She’s even seen as a veritable ableist demon for not feeling sexually attracted towards a man thrice her age (and he hails from the house that murdered her family, no less). She only manages to garner some sympathy after she is violated in the TV adaptation, a scene that doesn’t even exist in the books. It is hardly surprising that many male characters in the series, who do much worse, get away with their misdeeds way easily. Thrones’ treatment of non-warrior women is particularly repulsive. Sansa is made to mouth lines showing stoic gratitude towards her assaulters for teaching her strength, and another female character, who is often praised for being the snarky cool kid, demurely announces that she doesn’t plan to be useless during battle, namely ‘sit knitting by the fire’. Non-canonical lines, inserted because of the directors’ knowledge that they specifically pander to the audience’s needs and explicit scenes where women condemn softness and acts of ‘predictable’ ladyship, thereby metamorphosing into badasses, are aplenty. It is alarming that such scenes, in books and films, are often revered and portrayed as a sort of phoenix-from-the-ashes-moment, worthy of wolf-whistles and printed merchandise. Even more alarming is how the notion of empowerment has grown so utterly distorted that nothing, save for panning people who do not go against the grain, can properly qualify as a wholesome depiction of strong women. Why, after all, is knitting by the fire, or working in the kitchen so problematic? Do soldiers magically grow their uniforms? Does food come to us without the contribution of those who make it? Demeaning the choice of a woman to do as she pleases or act as she wants, is but an elaborately twisted route, ultimately ending in degrading womanhood itself. When C S Lewis published The Last Battle in 1956 the final instalment of his Narnia series, there was quite a bit of hue and outcry over his decision to close the gates of Narnia upon Susan Pevensie, the older, calmer, more beautiful and ladylike of the Pevensie sisters. After her family is killed in a car accident and the souls of her siblings find eternal refuge in Narnia, (a clear metaphor of an Eden-like realm) Susan is left alone, literally and figuratively locked out of heaven, her dismissal most summarily executed by Lewis in a couple of lines:  “My sister Susan,” answered Peter shortly and gravely, “is no longer a friend of Narnia.”  Why is this a problem? Because it’s not so much a question of what her fate was, as it is of why she deserved such a peremptory conclusion: “Oh Susan!” said Jill. “She’s interested in nothing nowadays except nylons and lipsticks and invitations. She always was a jolly sight too keen on being grown-up…”  Ah, yes, of course. Dresses and makeup, wanting to socialise and have peers; what could be more heinous a crime for an adolescent? Surely, a crime worthy of being unpardonable, in a book replete with Biblical imagery and repeated emphasis on the need to keep the innocence in children untainted, with a fervour that would make Blake proud. If you are shaking your head at this, slightly unconvinced, here’s a snippet from Lewis himself, where he makes it clear that our lipstick-wearing, nylon-loving lady is not enjoying the fruits of the Promised Land anytime soon: “The books don’t tell us what happened to Susan. She is left alive in this world at the end, having by then turned into a rather silly, conceited young woman. But there’s plenty of time for her to mend and perhaps she will get to Aslan’s country in the end… in her own way…” Even while he offers us a glimmer of hope, one can’t help but wince at the last lines. ‘Plenty of time for her to mend’ what, exactly? What is so indisputably repulsive about Susan craving extremely normal things, for a girl of her age? Why is there an immediate need to demonise a female character who chooses to beautify herself with makeup and pretty clothes? Since then, Susan’s crisis has attracted plenty of sympathetic voices from the literary community: Philip Pullman, Neil Gaiman, J K Rowling - to name a few, with Gaiman even creating a sort of spinoff short story with a very Susan-esque protagonist, giving her a much-needed voice and agency. Still, the older Pevensie sister remains an outcast of Narnia, a scarring reminder of what happens to girls who dare to be…well, just be. The ugly implications of girlish existence in Lewis’ ramrod world of old laws and deep magic are proof enough. Speaking of Rowling, an interesting and somewhat ironic fact is that while the Harry Potter series, on the forefront, seems chock-full of strong, three-dimensional female characters, there is something slightly problematic in the way she treats any character that teeters dangerously into girly-girl territory. Two classic examples are Cho Chang, Harry’s first girlfriend, who is constantly vilified for being ‘too emotional’ and too mopey over her dead boyfriend, and Fleur Delacour, who while she gets a much better conclusion, is still written off as the shallow dumb blonde, with a subpar performance in the Triwizard tournament where she’s the only female competitor. Cho is eventually cast aside for Ginny, whom Harry considers wonderful because she is ‘rarely weepy’. Constant misogynistic and slightly racist jabs are directed at Fleur by none other than Molly and Ginny Weasley, two of the most glorified and celebrated women in Harry’s life. Not even the minor characters escape judgement: the Patil twins and Lavender Brown, bubblier and more extroverted classmates of Hermione, are often reduced to nothing but cartoonish caricatures vying for Harry and Ron’s affections in the movies. Besides the evocation of unpleasant racial overtones, it’s something to think about, really. Where does mild, school cliché-centric humour end and perpetual bracketing-and-bashing of softness and generic girlishness begin? My personal favourite though, is the much-hated Amy March from Little Women. Amy’s case is particularly interesting because Alcott never meant to malign her, no, it’s the audience, unable to look past their ‘JO x LAURIE ENDGAME’ stupor, who miss the whole point of Amy’s arc - the resourcefulness in her choice to work within the conventions of traditional femininity instead of rebelling against it, the raw honesty in her desire as an impoverished girl to enjoy pretty material pleasures, the flaws and petty mistakes she succumbs to, because she is not written to be liked, she is written to be real. Jo’s struggles are very earthy and very honest, and her staunch refusal to fit in and fulfil societal expectations is admirable, but Amy’s willingness to maintain a sort of harmony with her community and work towards self-fulfilment…how is that, in any way, less gratifying? And for that matter, what do all these endless debates actually uncover? What does this hollow classification system of girls into badasses and girly-girls entail? The answer is uncertain, but it’s surely not an easy one. One cannot simply go for a shallow deconstruction of the not-like-other-girls syndrome without looking into why this syndrome had to arise at all. And then one finds that the root of this bizarre phenomenon lies in square one: the trivialisation of tenderness in girls and women, leading many to think that female voices and characters might not be taken seriously unless they are stripped away of all that could possibly hint at compassion and clemency. While Katniss Everdeen, Merida and the warrior heroines of some of the later Young Adult franchises may have arrived at exactly the right moment to prevent oversaturation of the market by the same kind of feminine representation, the boomerang effect that arose out of this is girls, in the younger demographic, seeking validation by rejecting and loudly denouncing traits that could possibly mark them as girly. This denunciation shows an almost vitriolic hatred in harmless things, marked out as extremely feminine motifs: anything pink and/or coded as princessy being the commonest examples. It’s alarming, it’s potentially harmful that the psyche of girls is shaped by what they shouldn’t be as opposed to what they prefer to be, it leans towards the patriarchy having the last laugh at the end. Most importantly, as hackneyed as this sounds, there is nothing more reproachable than the actions and behaviour of one woman being tainted so as to glorify another. Feminism and badassery don’t spring just from elaborate fight sequences or by being completely stone-cold or perpetually displeased and in a fighting stance. Yes, female characters so portrayed are valid, beautiful, even necessary. But they are not the beginning and end of all that’s marvellous and awe-inspiring about women. It’s definitely heartening to see a much more positive and varied portrayal of sharp and brilliant women in contemporary media, who don’t always depend on brawn or magic to achieve unanimous approval, take the famous Elle Woods (Legally Blonde) for example, a wonderful subversion of the dumb blonde stereotype. So while we praise Arya for knifing through her tormentors, we cannot forget Sansa, who comforts children and women with songs during a battle; we can celebrate angry, rebellious spirits without coming for gentle, tranquil hearts. We can cherish both sides of the spectrum. We can appreciate that some rebellions happen quietly, in utter tranquillity, glossed with pink and flowers. We can, for once, not let the patriarchy win. And maybe, just maybe at the end, Susan, the outcast of Narnia, no longer a powerful queen but just gloriously and heartbreakingly a human girl, will have the last laugh.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Capitalist Realism</title><link href="/Capitalist-Realism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalist Realism" /><published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Capitalist-Realism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Capitalist-Realism">&lt;p&gt;The Mayan calendar had prophesied that the world would end in 2012. Various
scientists have predicted that life on Earth will end after an asteroid hits the
planet. All these forecasts seem more or less acceptable to the general
populace. But will communism ever be the next world order? Not a chance. If one
were to inspect carefully, it is easier for us to imagine the end of the world
than to think that an alternative to capitalism exists. It is precisely this
phenomenon that Mark Fisher wrote about in his book, &lt;em&gt;Capitalist Realism - Is
There No Alternative?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalist Realism is the acceptance that “not only is capitalism the only
viable political and economic system but also that it is now impossible even to
imagine a coherent alternative to it.” While there is an acceptance of the many
faults in capitalism, the ramifications of those faults are often neglected or
undermined. Capitalist realism exists because it has managed to become
irreplaceable to us and has killed any sort of hope for a new system to take its
place. The narrative says that though we may not live in a condition of perfect
‘Goodness’, we must be grateful that we are saved from the ultimate ‘Evil’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is vehement in the criticism of any alternatives that may be present&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;while things may not be ideal, the alternatives are much worse. Here, it draws
power by painting contrasts between democracies and dictatorships, between civil
liberties and stark inequality - where one is shown to be a lesser evil, even if
reality may speak differently. The bombing of thousands of innocents in Syria is
justified, as long as it does not imitate the ruthless persecution or ethnic
cleansing that happened in countries like Rwanda. By characterising itself as a
hail-Mary from the disaster that any other alternative would lead to, capitalism
poses as a protector and gives way to capitalist realism - the foregone
conclusion that what persists is the best out there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even for those who realise the problem, there is a severe lack of action. What
could be an explanation for this? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea theorised is that the repetition of history has saturated us. In the
time and age we are in, it seems that every action we take has already been
taken in the past. Imagine the despondency of a generation that has come after
history, “whose every move is anticipated, tracked, bought and sold before it
had even happened.” Every act of ours is an experienced cliche, already noted in
the accounts of the past. No protest is novel. The realisation is in itself a
cliche. When all our attempts to create history are old and uninspired, it
eventually leads to a detached witnessing of events instead of active
involvement and engagement. There is a saturation of history, which inspires a
sense of cultural and political exhaustion - almost sterility - into old and
young minds alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger threat of the indoctrination of capitalism is that it has penetrated
our unconscious. Our unconscious shapes our desires, hopes and aspirations. If
one introspects, he/she would realise that our ambitions are driven by a
capitalist narrative - the image of success for us is a rich, privileged
businessman, who enjoys a position of social, economic and political capital in
society. Even while mentally accepting that money is tokenistic and “cannot buy
happiness,” we fetishise money. This acceptance of capitalist aims by society as
a whole and the subsequent trickle down to an individual level further solidify
its existence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengthening the Roots of Capitalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to think of Stalin, Hitler or Mussolini succeeding without
propaganda - their rallies were charged with nationalist sentiment and were
publicised to the extent that the idea of a Great Reich was almost shoved down
people’s throats. But the way that capitalism promotes itself is more nuanced -
the anti-capitalist sentiment is co-opted into capitalism. In a majority of
Hollywood movies, the villain turns out to be the CEO of an evil corporation or
a wealthy fanatic in retirement. Capitalist realism, therefore, is dangerous as
it gets away with including critique within its structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We accept that capitalism has problems - but the way we perceive the solution to
these problems is problematic in itself. Poverty and income inequality are
accepted faults of capitalism. Ask yourself - can we have a world without
poverty? Can we have one where there is income equity? Can an egalitarian
society exist? The answer will be no. Sure, we are striving towards these goals,
but their actual achievement is &lt;em&gt;utopian&lt;/em&gt;. Capitalist realism allows the
acceptance of a state of crisis in a continuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to challenge this idea is to identify how capitalist realism
escapes our notice on a day-to-day basis. Fisher gives three simple examples for
us to understand this: climate change, bureaucracy, and mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is built on the idea of consumerism. A capitalist state aims to grow
and expand markets continuously. A system that wants to be on its feet
constantly, that is principally in support of bulldozing through time for
profits, can never simultaneously aim for sustenance and stability. This
dichotomy in the theory of capitalism itself is something that often gets
unnoticed. Instead of saying that institutionalised inequalities are a result of
consumerism, the narrative is spun on its head by saying that what we buy is
going to change the principle of the political theory. For example, we are told
to consume alternatives instead of questioning the practicality of usage and
reducing our consumption. Buying the right thing, from the right place is
projected as a long term solution - but it still feeds into a structure that
advocates for consumerism. Climate change can never be solved or dealt with in a
capitalist construct because expansion is the ultimate goal and usage of
resources is a way to achieve the ‘target’. We will always, despite our best
efforts, hold resources secondary to this manic need for material progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberal and neo-liberal societies, while criticising socialism and communism,
highlight the problem with giving excess power to bureaucratic structures.
Bureaucrats often exploit their power and it leads to corruption and
inefficiency in the economy. The winning pitch for capitalism to be accepted
originally was to promise that bureaucracy would vanish. Except, what is the
status quo like? Even in late capitalism, bureaucracy still exists. The
difference is that it is morphed into a different kind of bureaucracy - one that
is allowed to penetrate all forms of structures through things like demanding
memos and answering to superiors. This bureaucracy is enforced at all levels of
management, establishing its place in the micro-levels of the economy.
Capitalist realism further reinforces that we cannot ‘practically’ do without
this culture of constantly answering to someone and being monitored, making the
control of societies a self-enforcing reality. Essentially, capitalism has
failed to differentiate itself from its alternatives on this metric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism, in its want to create overachievers and socially acceptable success
stories, has created ‘hustle culture’ - one that essentially relies on the idea
that &lt;em&gt;one mustn’t stop&lt;/em&gt;. If one chooses to listen to music instead of a podcast
on the way home, he/she is actively choosing to not add to his/her productivity.
If one does not succeed, the burden of the failure is wholly individualistic -
one must work harder or do things a particular way because regardless of the
kind of burdens one faces (for instance sociological burdens like racism),
anyone who strives enough &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; succeed. As a society, we have
pressurised people to the extent that mental health issues are on the rise among
young people - and no one ties it back to the inherent dysfunction in
capitalism. Instead of taking responsibility for this mass pressurisation, we
have privatised stress to be caused by individual chemical imbalances. By
placing the onus of a healthy state of mind exclusively on the individual
instead of accepting how society has failed him/her, we have allowed capitalist
realism to become our inevitable reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we establish capitalist realism’s claim to fame, one must wonder how it
sustains itself. Lacan argues that the concept of the ‘big Other’ in this
regard. The PR image that capitalism creates is sustained by those who are
willing to buy into this marketing. The Other is simply one who experiences life
differently even after knowing what the truth may be. The difference between
what one chooses to accept and what exists primarily sustains the ordinary
interactions we have daily. When the Other accepts reality as it is and chooses
to ignore the narrative that is set out, it creates an abnormality. When
Khrushchev’s speech in 1965 accepted the faults in the Soviet Union, it caused
an uproar. It was not as if people did not know of the kind of human rights
violations and corruption that was happening - the declaration just ensured that
‘the Other’ could not ignore it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, unlike Khrushchev in the Soviet Union, there is no incentive for anyone
with legitimacy in the Other’s eye to inform the Other of the kind of abominable
structure it is living in. The persons considered by the Other as leaders enjoy
the power that they hold and acceptance of truth by the masses will threaten
their hold over being able to control narratives. Thus, when people who can make
a difference choose not to, it serves to further crystallise capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Playing the Blame Game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with capitalism is accountability. While, in principle, corporations
are supposed to be the drivers of growth, they do not take responsibility as
they aren’t supposed to look after the welfare of every citizen operating within
the ambit of the care of the government. But the government does not take
responsibility either because it says that its role is minimised and unwanted.
So, any anger towards the system is directed towards an abstraction that is,
thus, unresponsive - someone did something wrong and we are now left with the
burden of cleaning up the mess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to hold collective responsibility for issues that plague all of us -
like climate change needs to be addressed by each one of us to get any tangible
change. The genius of capitalism is especially evident here - it protects itself
while making individuals scapegoats. For any scandal that happens, we tend to
burden the individual and ask for a more ‘morally upright’ replacement. However,
countless examples of upright individuals succumbing to the pressures and power
of a particular appointment and ending up corrupt are a testament to the fact
that vices are engendered in and by the system - as long as the system persists,
these vices will continue to sustain themselves. Therefore, Žižek argues that
placing individual responsibility due to the need for “ethical immediacy” lets
the system shirk the responsibility of cleaning itself up. He uses the example
of the 2008 credit crisis, wherein the blame was put on those ‘horrible people’
who abused the system rather than on the system that encouraged this culture of
abuse itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the acceptance of the possibility of an alternative to capitalism, none
of these problems will be effectively tackled and capitalist realism will
continue to dominate - perhaps as an unconscious undertone, but with immense
power over our economic, social and political interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Road Ahead &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may be a glimmer of hope for the world yet. Neoliberal capitalism is no
longer secure in its throne as the days of democratic socialism are on the
horizon. As the study of late capitalism and its critique increases, protesting
voices have emerged.  There is an increasing acceptance of left leaders like
Jeremy Corbyn, Alexandria Cortez, Bernie Sanders, and their policies in states
that have been the poster-children for capitalism. Healthcare for all, free
education and opportunity for the underprivileged are being accepted by a vast
majority of people - especially those who have been victims of capitalist
structures. The gravity of the stark income inequality is being acknowledged and
called out. Corporates and the wealthy are under increasing pressure and
scrutiny to pay higher taxes and fulfil any responsibility they have towards the
less privileged. While capitalist realism paints a bleak picture of us as a
civilisation, perhaps it is time for the sleeping phoenix to rise from the ashes
and take us to a better tomorrow. The cracks in the existing system are more
prominent and visible today than ever before - the responsibility of analysing
them and creating a new order is now on us to fulfil.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aanandi Arjun</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The Mayan calendar had prophesied that the world would end in 2012. Various scientists have predicted that life on Earth will end after an asteroid hits the planet. All these forecasts seem more or less acceptable to the general populace. But will communism ever be the next world order? Not a chance. If one were to inspect carefully, it is easier for us to imagine the end of the world than to think that an alternative to capitalism exists. It is precisely this phenomenon that Mark Fisher wrote about in his book, Capitalist Realism - Is There No Alternative? Capitalist Realism is the acceptance that “not only is capitalism the only viable political and economic system but also that it is now impossible even to imagine a coherent alternative to it.” While there is an acceptance of the many faults in capitalism, the ramifications of those faults are often neglected or undermined. Capitalist realism exists because it has managed to become irreplaceable to us and has killed any sort of hope for a new system to take its place. The narrative says that though we may not live in a condition of perfect ‘Goodness’, we must be grateful that we are saved from the ultimate ‘Evil’.  Capitalism is vehement in the criticism of any alternatives that may be present while things may not be ideal, the alternatives are much worse. Here, it draws power by painting contrasts between democracies and dictatorships, between civil liberties and stark inequality - where one is shown to be a lesser evil, even if reality may speak differently. The bombing of thousands of innocents in Syria is justified, as long as it does not imitate the ruthless persecution or ethnic cleansing that happened in countries like Rwanda. By characterising itself as a hail-Mary from the disaster that any other alternative would lead to, capitalism poses as a protector and gives way to capitalist realism - the foregone conclusion that what persists is the best out there. Even for those who realise the problem, there is a severe lack of action. What could be an explanation for this?  One idea theorised is that the repetition of history has saturated us. In the time and age we are in, it seems that every action we take has already been taken in the past. Imagine the despondency of a generation that has come after history, “whose every move is anticipated, tracked, bought and sold before it had even happened.” Every act of ours is an experienced cliche, already noted in the accounts of the past. No protest is novel. The realisation is in itself a cliche. When all our attempts to create history are old and uninspired, it eventually leads to a detached witnessing of events instead of active involvement and engagement. There is a saturation of history, which inspires a sense of cultural and political exhaustion - almost sterility - into old and young minds alike. The bigger threat of the indoctrination of capitalism is that it has penetrated our unconscious. Our unconscious shapes our desires, hopes and aspirations. If one introspects, he/she would realise that our ambitions are driven by a capitalist narrative - the image of success for us is a rich, privileged businessman, who enjoys a position of social, economic and political capital in society. Even while mentally accepting that money is tokenistic and “cannot buy happiness,” we fetishise money. This acceptance of capitalist aims by society as a whole and the subsequent trickle down to an individual level further solidify its existence.  Strengthening the Roots of Capitalism It is impossible to think of Stalin, Hitler or Mussolini succeeding without propaganda - their rallies were charged with nationalist sentiment and were publicised to the extent that the idea of a Great Reich was almost shoved down people’s throats. But the way that capitalism promotes itself is more nuanced - the anti-capitalist sentiment is co-opted into capitalism. In a majority of Hollywood movies, the villain turns out to be the CEO of an evil corporation or a wealthy fanatic in retirement. Capitalist realism, therefore, is dangerous as it gets away with including critique within its structure. We accept that capitalism has problems - but the way we perceive the solution to these problems is problematic in itself. Poverty and income inequality are accepted faults of capitalism. Ask yourself - can we have a world without poverty? Can we have one where there is income equity? Can an egalitarian society exist? The answer will be no. Sure, we are striving towards these goals, but their actual achievement is utopian. Capitalist realism allows the acceptance of a state of crisis in a continuum. The only way to challenge this idea is to identify how capitalist realism escapes our notice on a day-to-day basis. Fisher gives three simple examples for us to understand this: climate change, bureaucracy, and mental health. Capitalism is built on the idea of consumerism. A capitalist state aims to grow and expand markets continuously. A system that wants to be on its feet constantly, that is principally in support of bulldozing through time for profits, can never simultaneously aim for sustenance and stability. This dichotomy in the theory of capitalism itself is something that often gets unnoticed. Instead of saying that institutionalised inequalities are a result of consumerism, the narrative is spun on its head by saying that what we buy is going to change the principle of the political theory. For example, we are told to consume alternatives instead of questioning the practicality of usage and reducing our consumption. Buying the right thing, from the right place is projected as a long term solution - but it still feeds into a structure that advocates for consumerism. Climate change can never be solved or dealt with in a capitalist construct because expansion is the ultimate goal and usage of resources is a way to achieve the ‘target’. We will always, despite our best efforts, hold resources secondary to this manic need for material progress. Liberal and neo-liberal societies, while criticising socialism and communism, highlight the problem with giving excess power to bureaucratic structures. Bureaucrats often exploit their power and it leads to corruption and inefficiency in the economy. The winning pitch for capitalism to be accepted originally was to promise that bureaucracy would vanish. Except, what is the status quo like? Even in late capitalism, bureaucracy still exists. The difference is that it is morphed into a different kind of bureaucracy - one that is allowed to penetrate all forms of structures through things like demanding memos and answering to superiors. This bureaucracy is enforced at all levels of management, establishing its place in the micro-levels of the economy. Capitalist realism further reinforces that we cannot ‘practically’ do without this culture of constantly answering to someone and being monitored, making the control of societies a self-enforcing reality. Essentially, capitalism has failed to differentiate itself from its alternatives on this metric. Capitalism, in its want to create overachievers and socially acceptable success stories, has created ‘hustle culture’ - one that essentially relies on the idea that one mustn’t stop. If one chooses to listen to music instead of a podcast on the way home, he/she is actively choosing to not add to his/her productivity. If one does not succeed, the burden of the failure is wholly individualistic - one must work harder or do things a particular way because regardless of the kind of burdens one faces (for instance sociological burdens like racism), anyone who strives enough can and must succeed. As a society, we have pressurised people to the extent that mental health issues are on the rise among young people - and no one ties it back to the inherent dysfunction in capitalism. Instead of taking responsibility for this mass pressurisation, we have privatised stress to be caused by individual chemical imbalances. By placing the onus of a healthy state of mind exclusively on the individual instead of accepting how society has failed him/her, we have allowed capitalist realism to become our inevitable reality.  Once we establish capitalist realism’s claim to fame, one must wonder how it sustains itself. Lacan argues that the concept of the ‘big Other’ in this regard. The PR image that capitalism creates is sustained by those who are willing to buy into this marketing. The Other is simply one who experiences life differently even after knowing what the truth may be. The difference between what one chooses to accept and what exists primarily sustains the ordinary interactions we have daily. When the Other accepts reality as it is and chooses to ignore the narrative that is set out, it creates an abnormality. When Khrushchev’s speech in 1965 accepted the faults in the Soviet Union, it caused an uproar. It was not as if people did not know of the kind of human rights violations and corruption that was happening - the declaration just ensured that ‘the Other’ could not ignore it anymore. However, unlike Khrushchev in the Soviet Union, there is no incentive for anyone with legitimacy in the Other’s eye to inform the Other of the kind of abominable structure it is living in. The persons considered by the Other as leaders enjoy the power that they hold and acceptance of truth by the masses will threaten their hold over being able to control narratives. Thus, when people who can make a difference choose not to, it serves to further crystallise capitalism. Playing the Blame Game The problem with capitalism is accountability. While, in principle, corporations are supposed to be the drivers of growth, they do not take responsibility as they aren’t supposed to look after the welfare of every citizen operating within the ambit of the care of the government. But the government does not take responsibility either because it says that its role is minimised and unwanted. So, any anger towards the system is directed towards an abstraction that is, thus, unresponsive - someone did something wrong and we are now left with the burden of cleaning up the mess.  We need to hold collective responsibility for issues that plague all of us - like climate change needs to be addressed by each one of us to get any tangible change. The genius of capitalism is especially evident here - it protects itself while making individuals scapegoats. For any scandal that happens, we tend to burden the individual and ask for a more ‘morally upright’ replacement. However, countless examples of upright individuals succumbing to the pressures and power of a particular appointment and ending up corrupt are a testament to the fact that vices are engendered in and by the system - as long as the system persists, these vices will continue to sustain themselves. Therefore, Žižek argues that placing individual responsibility due to the need for “ethical immediacy” lets the system shirk the responsibility of cleaning itself up. He uses the example of the 2008 credit crisis, wherein the blame was put on those ‘horrible people’ who abused the system rather than on the system that encouraged this culture of abuse itself. Without the acceptance of the possibility of an alternative to capitalism, none of these problems will be effectively tackled and capitalist realism will continue to dominate - perhaps as an unconscious undertone, but with immense power over our economic, social and political interactions. The Road Ahead  There may be a glimmer of hope for the world yet. Neoliberal capitalism is no longer secure in its throne as the days of democratic socialism are on the horizon. As the study of late capitalism and its critique increases, protesting voices have emerged.  There is an increasing acceptance of left leaders like Jeremy Corbyn, Alexandria Cortez, Bernie Sanders, and their policies in states that have been the poster-children for capitalism. Healthcare for all, free education and opportunity for the underprivileged are being accepted by a vast majority of people - especially those who have been victims of capitalist structures. The gravity of the stark income inequality is being acknowledged and called out. Corporates and the wealthy are under increasing pressure and scrutiny to pay higher taxes and fulfil any responsibility they have towards the less privileged. While capitalist realism paints a bleak picture of us as a civilisation, perhaps it is time for the sleeping phoenix to rise from the ashes and take us to a better tomorrow. The cracks in the existing system are more prominent and visible today than ever before - the responsibility of analysing them and creating a new order is now on us to fulfil.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk</title><link href="/Beauty-and-Brazen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk" /><published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Beauty-and-Brazen</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-and-Brazen">&lt;p&gt;“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his
humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in
&lt;em&gt;Berserk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of
other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the
least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an
adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his
life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close
to the &lt;strong&gt;Truth&lt;/strong&gt; and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more
interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he
know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to
script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche
refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered
to be, the future of humanity, &lt;em&gt;Ubermensch&lt;/em&gt;, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’.
Thus begins the journey of &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; and its protagonist, the most bad*rse
anime/manga character in history, &lt;em&gt;Guts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the
very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story
is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate
&lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; overtake him and he &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be entwined with his future, with what is
already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not
always free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in
&lt;em&gt;Twilight of the Idols&lt;/em&gt;, where he referred to causality as the cause of
humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning
to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause
behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to
support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; that free
will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians
exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche
thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a
protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it,
at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been
hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him.
When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him.
Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to
survive in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary
group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He
falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and
the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith
sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as &lt;em&gt;Eclipse&lt;/em&gt;, is a momentous image
of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get
killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get
violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He
does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining
several scars of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably
his most interesting piece of work, &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; introduced the
concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and
philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is
an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps:
The Camel, The Lion and The Child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the
knowledge of the &lt;em&gt;Dragon&lt;/em&gt; (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore
listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself.
As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told
to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’
demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a
Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system
in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The
Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of
the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the
system himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to
Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being
who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to
struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’
transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to
integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who
defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very
epitome of the Overman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the
Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company,
unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a
society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man.
Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the
other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of
this ambition. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in the same manner, brings about the reference of
Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not
understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand
the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the
light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all
their goals and dreams as one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of
Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to
resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true
goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs
and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been
highlighted in &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, where we are informed of the existence of a
monotheistic religion, termed as the &lt;em&gt;Holy See&lt;/em&gt;, whose ideals bear similarity to
Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who
could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro
Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all
odds, through Guts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is
all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit
of a fighter. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and
deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled
under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher
Man’, despite not being from the nobility. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in Berserk. Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close to the Truth and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered to be, the future of humanity, Ubermensch, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’. Thus begins the journey of Berserk and its protagonist, the most bad*rse anime/manga character in history, Guts. Berserk is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate will overtake him and he will be entwined with his future, with what is already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not always free. Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in Twilight of the Idols, where he referred to causality as the cause of humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in Twilight that free will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge. Berserk challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it, at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him. When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him. Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to survive in the wild. Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power. The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as Eclipse, is a momentous image of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining several scars of his own. Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably his most interesting piece of work, Thus Spoke Zarathustra introduced the concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps: The Camel, The Lion and The Child. The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the knowledge of the Dragon (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself. As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel. When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’ demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the system himself. That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’ transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very epitome of the Overman. A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company, unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man. Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of this ambition. Berserk, in the same manner, brings about the reference of Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all their goals and dreams as one.” Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been highlighted in Berserk, where we are informed of the existence of a monotheistic religion, termed as the Holy See, whose ideals bear similarity to Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all odds, through Guts. Berserk has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit of a fighter. Berserk, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher Man’, despite not being from the nobility. </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Only I Exist</title><link href="/Only-I-Exist" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only I Exist" /><published>2019-08-01T11:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-01T11:45:00+00:00</updated><id>/Only-I-Exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Only-I-Exist">&lt;p&gt;Questions have been the very heart and soul of philosophy and, unlike any other
discipline, it has raised more questions than it has answered. The dire
intellectual need to discern the abstract, in the form of reality and truth,
consumes all thinkers alike. They all seek answers that spring from an objective
source to bring an end to the seemingly perpetual quest for knowledge. However,
it is not that simple. Philosophy, over the years, has gotten mired down in
countless irrefutable hypotheses, thriving on the body of possibilities and
reason. This is especially true of metaphysical discussions, which have resulted
in the blossoming of unconventional, at times, bizarre theories to explain
reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;? One way to grasp reality amounts to the way you understand the
world external to you. But what if that understanding is faulty? Take, for
instance, the understanding of the earth as a flat disc. Today we can ‘claim to
know’ that the earth is spherical, yet in those times the supposed axiom of the
earth being flat was the foundational truth on which the early peoples developed
an understanding of other concepts and ideas. This is disconcerting, because
there’s a pretty high possibility of us assuming a false belief as an
irrefutable fact, because although there are proofs to make claims, science per
se isn’t perfect, just workable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now go even further to understand the concept of matter that we &lt;em&gt;assume&lt;/em&gt;
to be real. As Bertrand Russell discussed in his &lt;em&gt;Problems of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;,
whatever we perceive is the mere appearance of an object, as opposed to its
reality. The surface of an apple that is seen with the naked eye is very
different when viewed under the microscope, its colour varies with the changing
source of light too. In short, what your perception leads you into believing is
real is actually nothing but the appearance of the apple, in varying degrees of
magnification. If this is the case, then the existence of the apple becomes
questionable. Does an &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; apple exist at all? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some, it does not. A philosopher named Bishop Berkeley, for instance, argued
in favour of &lt;em&gt;immaterialism&lt;/em&gt; – that rather than being a form of matter, an apple
in actuality is the amalgamation of several qualities which cannot exist
independent of the mind. You can test this, try defining an apple devoid of its
qualities and properties. It is almost impossible to do so. So are the qualities
(of the objects) that we perceive in the universe, are they created by our
imagination or do they exist as a comprehensive whole contained in an underlying
substratum called matter? This is the starting point of the idea of ‘solipsism.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solipsism revolves around the idea that only I exist and weave the fabric of my
reality. The &lt;em&gt;certainty&lt;/em&gt; I can ascribe to my experience is limited to my &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt;
existence and thoughts, everything else in this world, including the existence
of this article, is doubtable. This may seem very absurd to hear, at first, but
it’s a possibility that is hard to deny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The empirical experiences one goes through forms an essential part of their own
subjective reality. One can, in no way validate the experience of anybody else
(egocentric predicament). One’s understanding of the apple is theirs alone and
cannot be grasped by anyone else. The comprehension of all that is external to
their consciousness is beyond their ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, your thoughts and ideas are the only undisputed and obvious entities that
exist. This is to say that all humans have their own psychological conceptions
whose understanding is forbidden to others. And so, we cannot be certain of the
independent existence of other bodies and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of solipsism has subtly remained embedded in other philosophical
ideas. One such idea was propounded by Rene Descartes’ principle of “&lt;em&gt;Cogito,
ergo sum&lt;/em&gt;” (I think, therefore I am). Descartes was convinced that he was being
deceived, by an evil genius, into believing some essentially flawed concepts as
true. Maintaining that every thought is dubitable, he cleansed his mind of all
distortions and came up with the most irrefutable, indubitable truth (as the
basic frame of reference to understand all the other truths)- “I think therefore
I am.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solipsism takes this idea of &lt;em&gt;Cogito&lt;/em&gt; way too seriously. Nothing but the mind is
true for the solipsist. While Descartes did believe in rationality and
mathematics as a means to search for truth, for the solipsist (metaphysically
and epistemologically) such conceptions are your own inventions, something you
make up in your head, bereft of any independent existence (here your
consciousness shall assume the place of Descartes’ demon). One can understand it
as a perpetual state of hallucination, characterised by vivid details. If you
are a solipsist, then whatever you experience, this article, your friends,
family, nature, all the coolest things in the world are actually an invention of
your own! An understanding of the world devoid of the ego is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However fascinating it may sound, solipsism has some dire outcomes, when
accepted as a lifestyle choice. It possesses the potential to throw the world
into utter chaos. Since everything that one sees around them is a creation of
their imagination, they would have all the power of calling the shots and
asserting their dominance over the entire world around them. Morality and ethics
would lose their credibility and an individual’s will would determine the fate
of all that is around them. Or else, it could make a person abnegate everything,
despairing about the loneliness they experience every second of their existence,
since they have no proof of the existence of any other. Either way, solipsism
could inflict more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult to refute, solipsism continues to haunt the imagination of humankind.
However, rejecting the theory altogether wouldn’t be right either, given the
crucial questions it raises on reality and the foundations of epistemological
speculations. The question of solipsism has stirred minds and propelled
philosophy from a state of certainty to that of unpredictability, thereby adding
profundity and beauty to the subject. And as long as such ingenious thoughts
continue to flow in the body of philosophy, the answer to this problem, along
with all problems, I believe, is not too far away.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Questions have been the very heart and soul of philosophy and, unlike any other discipline, it has raised more questions than it has answered. The dire intellectual need to discern the abstract, in the form of reality and truth, consumes all thinkers alike. They all seek answers that spring from an objective source to bring an end to the seemingly perpetual quest for knowledge. However, it is not that simple. Philosophy, over the years, has gotten mired down in countless irrefutable hypotheses, thriving on the body of possibilities and reason. This is especially true of metaphysical discussions, which have resulted in the blossoming of unconventional, at times, bizarre theories to explain reality. What is real? One way to grasp reality amounts to the way you understand the world external to you. But what if that understanding is faulty? Take, for instance, the understanding of the earth as a flat disc. Today we can ‘claim to know’ that the earth is spherical, yet in those times the supposed axiom of the earth being flat was the foundational truth on which the early peoples developed an understanding of other concepts and ideas. This is disconcerting, because there’s a pretty high possibility of us assuming a false belief as an irrefutable fact, because although there are proofs to make claims, science per se isn’t perfect, just workable.  Let us now go even further to understand the concept of matter that we assume to be real. As Bertrand Russell discussed in his Problems of Philosophy, whatever we perceive is the mere appearance of an object, as opposed to its reality. The surface of an apple that is seen with the naked eye is very different when viewed under the microscope, its colour varies with the changing source of light too. In short, what your perception leads you into believing is real is actually nothing but the appearance of the apple, in varying degrees of magnification. If this is the case, then the existence of the apple becomes questionable. Does an actual apple exist at all?  For some, it does not. A philosopher named Bishop Berkeley, for instance, argued in favour of immaterialism – that rather than being a form of matter, an apple in actuality is the amalgamation of several qualities which cannot exist independent of the mind. You can test this, try defining an apple devoid of its qualities and properties. It is almost impossible to do so. So are the qualities (of the objects) that we perceive in the universe, are they created by our imagination or do they exist as a comprehensive whole contained in an underlying substratum called matter? This is the starting point of the idea of ‘solipsism.’ Solipsism revolves around the idea that only I exist and weave the fabric of my reality. The certainty I can ascribe to my experience is limited to my own existence and thoughts, everything else in this world, including the existence of this article, is doubtable. This may seem very absurd to hear, at first, but it’s a possibility that is hard to deny. The empirical experiences one goes through forms an essential part of their own subjective reality. One can, in no way validate the experience of anybody else (egocentric predicament). One’s understanding of the apple is theirs alone and cannot be grasped by anyone else. The comprehension of all that is external to their consciousness is beyond their ability. Thus, your thoughts and ideas are the only undisputed and obvious entities that exist. This is to say that all humans have their own psychological conceptions whose understanding is forbidden to others. And so, we cannot be certain of the independent existence of other bodies and minds. The theory of solipsism has subtly remained embedded in other philosophical ideas. One such idea was propounded by Rene Descartes’ principle of “Cogito, ergo sum” (I think, therefore I am). Descartes was convinced that he was being deceived, by an evil genius, into believing some essentially flawed concepts as true. Maintaining that every thought is dubitable, he cleansed his mind of all distortions and came up with the most irrefutable, indubitable truth (as the basic frame of reference to understand all the other truths)- “I think therefore I am.”  Solipsism takes this idea of Cogito way too seriously. Nothing but the mind is true for the solipsist. While Descartes did believe in rationality and mathematics as a means to search for truth, for the solipsist (metaphysically and epistemologically) such conceptions are your own inventions, something you make up in your head, bereft of any independent existence (here your consciousness shall assume the place of Descartes’ demon). One can understand it as a perpetual state of hallucination, characterised by vivid details. If you are a solipsist, then whatever you experience, this article, your friends, family, nature, all the coolest things in the world are actually an invention of your own! An understanding of the world devoid of the ego is impossible. However fascinating it may sound, solipsism has some dire outcomes, when accepted as a lifestyle choice. It possesses the potential to throw the world into utter chaos. Since everything that one sees around them is a creation of their imagination, they would have all the power of calling the shots and asserting their dominance over the entire world around them. Morality and ethics would lose their credibility and an individual’s will would determine the fate of all that is around them. Or else, it could make a person abnegate everything, despairing about the loneliness they experience every second of their existence, since they have no proof of the existence of any other. Either way, solipsism could inflict more harm than good. Difficult to refute, solipsism continues to haunt the imagination of humankind. However, rejecting the theory altogether wouldn’t be right either, given the crucial questions it raises on reality and the foundations of epistemological speculations. The question of solipsism has stirred minds and propelled philosophy from a state of certainty to that of unpredictability, thereby adding profundity and beauty to the subject. And as long as such ingenious thoughts continue to flow in the body of philosophy, the answer to this problem, along with all problems, I believe, is not too far away.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture</title><link href="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely
an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as
Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw
boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or
raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the
millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation
of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with
little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or
people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of
these problems, it made sure that they were heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies
like &lt;em&gt;Forrest Gump&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Platoon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse Now&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Deer Hunter&lt;/em&gt; surely
gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the
protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed
‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps
finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a movie like &lt;em&gt;Driving Miss Daisy&lt;/em&gt;, for example. It won the Best Picture
Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart
from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about
Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know
what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation
won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are
scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a
post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of &lt;em&gt;James Bond&lt;/em&gt; has
evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional
womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation
effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a
man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. &lt;em&gt;Get Out&lt;/em&gt; was a pivotal
movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would
solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald
Glover show &lt;em&gt;Atlanta&lt;/em&gt;, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true
portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans.
This trend extends to a lot of shows, like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New Black&lt;/em&gt;, that
eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most
inclusive shows in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for
masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more
recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities
and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused
of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been
much more open about the same throughout their discography.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like
Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear
candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global
influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been
considered too taboo to even be talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the
millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely
sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want
tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about
people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because
a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority,
has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar
bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life,
are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do
not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to
tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who
are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see
any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it
means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking
something &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and
human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is
seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows
like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily
because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental
health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that
already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about
combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end
surreal art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need
more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To
be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a
global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem,
if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success.
During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit
song &lt;em&gt;Alright&lt;/em&gt;. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for
some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good
about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better
people, if at all we really need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a
much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on
diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share
of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of
people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the
same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the
Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various
cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only
like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values
on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to
personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing
to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the
millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class
and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it
sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is
slowly but surely influencing content around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the
calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a
circle that was &lt;em&gt;woke just for show&lt;/em&gt;, female comedians have been earning what’s
due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience,
quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In
another example, TVF’s &lt;em&gt;Kota Factory&lt;/em&gt; created ripples across the student
community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering
students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw
their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold
content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the
millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms
such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially
charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a
generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a
generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view
life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own
troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans
in our cinema.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pranav Manie</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of these problems, it made sure that they were heard. This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies like Forrest Gump, Platoon, Apocalypse Now and The Deer Hunter surely gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed ‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.   Take a movie like Driving Miss Daisy, for example. It won the Best Picture Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories. The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of James Bond has evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies. Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. Get Out was a pivotal movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald Glover show Atlanta, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans. This trend extends to a lot of shows, like Orange Is The New Black, that eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most inclusive shows in recent times. Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been much more open about the same throughout their discography. Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been considered too taboo to even be talked about. But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority, has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life, are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender. One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking something real in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end surreal art. There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem, if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success. During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit song Alright. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better people, if at all we really need it. The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18. Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is slowly but surely influencing content around us.   Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a circle that was woke just for show, female comedians have been earning what’s due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience, quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In another example, TVF’s Kota Factory created ripples across the student community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold content. Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans in our cinema.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Secrets of Sorcery</title><link href="/Secrets-of-Sorcery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Secrets of Sorcery" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Secrets-of-Sorcery</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Secrets-of-Sorcery">&lt;p&gt;The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now,
that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon
heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long
crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from &lt;em&gt;The Vampire Diaries&lt;/em&gt;. But have you
ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is,
however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it.
Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda
behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This
historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly
enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past.
In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and
subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been
abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every
Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot
witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many
women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch
hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly
lending legitimacy to witch doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people
have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact,
witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them
as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current
government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government
recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just
by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak,
depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian
witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident
that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it
is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under
Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret
societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of
the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa,
commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt;.
While &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; practice natural medicine, &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt; practice magic, predict the
future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out
their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who
consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass
hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were
established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the
locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice
of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the
fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The
followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are
self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in
magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community
is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However,
contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches
too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in
worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.”
Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their
poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena
like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities.
Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named &lt;em&gt;The Book of
Shadows&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the
witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever
actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of
the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and
disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions
were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several
females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t
made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various
conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were
convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some
were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary
to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places,
male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches
stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. &lt;em&gt;Malleus Maleficarum&lt;/em&gt; was
published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the
Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot,
interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to
come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you
are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many
secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they
also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position
of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through
generations. &lt;em&gt;The Book of the Dead&lt;/em&gt; famously contains various spells to aid one
in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt
often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no
written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a
cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that
potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever
condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans
continued as long as the great civilisation thrived. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of
magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s
go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of
Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb,
George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation
team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11
deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly
attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is
believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s
occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between
robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard
Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies
have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the
masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in
different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have
only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to
solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold
beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated
with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to
decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have
assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we
rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more
complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly
enough, paganism is on the rise too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft
still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced
witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations
hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is
about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s
intriguing is the existence of the human &lt;strong&gt;urge&lt;/strong&gt; to look for magic in a world
that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world
desperation to cling to rationale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now, that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from The Vampire Diaries. But have you ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice? To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is, however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it. Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past. In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly lending legitimacy to witch doctors. Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact, witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches.  In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak, depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society. Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa, commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: Inyanga and Sangoma. While Inyanga practice natural medicine, Sangoma practice magic, predict the future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them. Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches. In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However, contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.” Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities. Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named The Book of Shadows. The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places, male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. Malleus Maleficarum was published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot, interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to come. If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through generations. The Book of the Dead famously contains various spells to aid one in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans continued as long as the great civilisation thrived.  With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb, George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11 deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action. Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly enough, paganism is on the rise too. While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s intriguing is the existence of the human urge to look for magic in a world that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world desperation to cling to rationale.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rise of the Screen Thriller</title><link href="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the Screen Thriller" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer">&lt;p&gt;Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided
useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of
writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a
subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider
these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the BBC masterpiece, &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt;, for example. Sherlock is quite often in
contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message
bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously
observe Sherlock’s expressions. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; portrays the internet the best -
take an episode like &lt;em&gt;Nosedive&lt;/em&gt;; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if
we introduce a social credit rating for humans or &lt;em&gt;Shut Up And Dance&lt;/em&gt;; an
episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the
aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of
being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online.
The need to harness and depict that is what led to the &lt;em&gt;computer screen
thriller&lt;/em&gt; being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the
film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or
television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt;, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching
for his missing daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first
documented screen-only movie was &lt;em&gt;The Collingswood Story&lt;/em&gt;, which is about an
online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams.
The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie
&lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It
made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian
director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to
this subgenre that he calls &lt;em&gt;Screen Life&lt;/em&gt;. He produced a sequel to the movie, as
well as &lt;em&gt;Searching,&lt;/em&gt; and directed one of his own called &lt;em&gt;Profile.&lt;/em&gt; There were
other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show
&lt;em&gt;Modern Family&lt;/em&gt; to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by
many as one of the best episodes of the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the
Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the
information can be revealed without using screens throughout. &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt; was
able to demonstrate it well. The TV show &lt;em&gt;American Vandal&lt;/em&gt; was themed around
internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Why&lt;/em&gt; could be
credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards
millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern
film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it
for us to simultaneously consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense.
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt; made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;
made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little.
Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but
also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story
gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and
texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not
reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the
characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny
things are indicators of something large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder
in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find
out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen
thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to
show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the
audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on
cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not
exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often
shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life
and online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The
screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and
windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the
viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always
waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter
how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is
wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human
desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David
Fincher, the director of &lt;em&gt;The Social Network&lt;/em&gt; says, “People are perverts.” They
want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless,
they will love it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pranav Manie</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold. Take the BBC masterpiece, Sherlock, for example. Sherlock is quite often in contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously observe Sherlock’s expressions. Black Mirror portrays the internet the best - take an episode like Nosedive; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if we introduce a social credit rating for humans or Shut Up And Dance; an episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape. These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online. The need to harness and depict that is what led to the computer screen thriller being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of Searching, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching for his missing daughter. However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first documented screen-only movie was The Collingswood Story, which is about an online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams. The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie Unfriended, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to this subgenre that he calls Screen Life. He produced a sequel to the movie, as well as Searching, and directed one of his own called Profile. There were other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show Modern Family to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by many as one of the best episodes of the show. The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the information can be revealed without using screens throughout. Sherlock was able to demonstrate it well. The TV show American Vandal was themed around internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even 13 Reasons Why could be credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it for us to simultaneously consume. These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense. Searching made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and Unfriended made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye? At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little. Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny things are indicators of something large. If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life and online. These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David Fincher, the director of The Social Network says, “People are perverts.” They want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless, they will love it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building the Abode of Gods…From Scratch</title><link href="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building the Abode of Gods...From Scratch" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘&lt;em&gt;Amaravati&lt;/em&gt;’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2014 Assembly elections, N Chandrababu Naidu of India’s Telugu Desam Party became the Chief Minister of the state. Soon, the government set up committees to finalise the area for capital construction. Amaravati was chosen by the end of 2014. There are many reasons for this selection. First, the proposed region is at the centre and is equidistant from every corner of the state. The second reason is the availability of water. The proposed capital city is situated on the banks of the river Krishna. It also has a barrage constructed which could hold up to 1 TMC of water. The third is the ease of connectivity. Amaravati is not more than 400 km from Hyderabad, Chennai and Bengaluru, capital cities of states that neighbour Andhra Pradesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon deciding the capital, the government constituted the Andhra Pradesh Capital Region Development Authority (APCRDA) in 2014 for planning, supervising, executing, financing and developing the capital region of Andhra Pradesh. Its tasks include finalising designs, calling for tenders and administering capital construction. Right from the beginning, the state drew its inspiration from Singapore to build a world-class city. Mr Naidu always talked about how Singapore too had developed from scratch and Andhra Pradesh was in the same position. APCRDA even signed an MoU with the Singapore government for the development of a master plan for Amaravati, which was finalised recently in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing to be noted here is that land for the capital was pooled rather than acquired. This was done to avoid the financial burden that would arise in the form of compensations against land acquisitions. Under this land pooling scheme, the landowners (mostly farmers) who surrendered their lands to the government would get a portion of the developed plots in the capital city after a period of 10 years. A huge 33,000 acres (133.5 square kilometers) was pooled for the construction of the capital city. It is a commendable achievement because the land was pooled in a very short period, that too without a single court case. Mr Naidu played a key role in assuring the fearful farmers that they would lose nothing by sacrificing their lands. To attract investments into the capital (and the state), the Andhra Pradesh government introduced a slew of measures. It eased its industrial policy by introducing a ‘single window clearance’ for industries, under which one can easily obtain all the necessary approvals for the setting up of a business, and avoid red tape thereof. Not only did this place Andhra Pradesh at the number 1 spot in the ‘Ease of Doing Business’ index of India but also helped the state in signing a $500 million deal with the World Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a city from scratch is an uphill task. For a state with finances like Andhra Pradesh, it is an economic nightmare. The state is so deep in a financial crisis that a recent White Paper released by the government stated that the state has to go for an overdraft almost every month! Yet, there seems to be non-cooperation from India’s central government. When the  Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Bill was up for discussion in the Rajya Sabha, the upper house of the Indian Parliament, the then Prime Minister Dr Manmohan Singh said “for the purpose of central assistance, Special Category Status (SCS) will be extended to the State of Andhra Pradesh for a period of five years. This will put the state finances on a firmer footing.” What SCS means is that the state would get preferential treatment in the transfer of funds from the central government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, SCS money never seems to come. It is estimated that construction of the new capital would require a massive sum of ₹330 billion. Out of this, a mere ₹25 billion has been allocated by India’s central government, and only ₹10.5 billion has been released till date. The administrative help from the Indian central government has been delayed too. One example of the central government’s neglect is worth mentioning here. Emirates, a world-renowned airline, sought to fly from Andhra Pradesh and establish a training facility there. It requested the state to provide the requisite land. As aviation is regulated by the central government according to India’s Constitution, this required the centre’s approval. Unfortunately, that approval never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all these troubles, wouldn’t it have been more feasible for Andhra Pradesh to select an already existing city rather than build a capital from scratch? All this said, building a new capital boosts aggregate demand. A huge amount of money is invested and employment opportunities are generated. However, the government needs to take appropriate steps to invite private investment into the state. Given the high fiscal deficit of the state, 4.5% of the GSDP or Gross State Domestic Product, it is imperative that the state goes hand-in-hand with the private sector because a further increase in fiscal deficit would put the state in a financially critical position. Infrastructural development needs huge investments with a generally long gestation period. It would be burdensome for the crippled economy of Andhra Pradesh to finance such investments. Private investments would ensure that there is no stoppage in the fund flow and the projects are completed duly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the erstwhile Andhra Pradesh, excessive economic centralisation took place in and around Hyderabad. Even today, a lion’s share of Telangana’s (the newly formed state) revenue is generated by Hyderabad. It is because all major developmental activities were planned in Hyderabad and less emphasis was placed on the development of other cities and towns. Bearing this experience in mind, the new Andhra Pradesh should be diversified in its development trajectory. Single-city centric development will cost the state dearly (like it did during its bifurcation). The capital should be restricted to administrative uses. Necessary infrastructure should be built in other cities to transform them into major centres in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Visakhapatnam, or Vizag, in its anglicised form, is a happening port city with a notable presence of the software industry. It has the potential to emerge as a major IT hub and the government should take steps to harness the said potential. Rayalaseema, the southern part of Andhra Pradesh, receives scarce rainfall and is not as feasible for agriculture as the other regions are. On the other hand, southern India is not a manufacturing power in the country. Andhra Pradesh could fill this gap by developing the Rayalaseema region into a major industrial and manufacturing hub. Like the existing Sri City Special Economic Zone (SEZ), a rising industrial hub in the southern part of the state, more of such initiatives can be taken up for the same purpose. The lawmakers should learn from their earlier experiences. They should make plans in such a way that development is spread throughout the state rather than being concentrated in Amaravati. Andhra Pradesh should not repeat its mistakes. And using its scarce funds to create a grand city of Amaravati would be doing so, in fact, one could say it’s already doing so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘Amaravati’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Great (Millennial) Depression</title><link href="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great (Millennial) Depression" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Great-Millennial-Depression</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression">&lt;p&gt;If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the WHO, about 300 million people around the world are affected by depression. Nearly 800,000 people commit suicide every year. Suicide is second on the list of leading causes of deaths in 15 to 29 year-olds today. In spite of this, only 1 in every 5 depressed people receives treatment consistent with modern practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous TV series and films have been made, aimed at tackling this. Their failure, however, has been appalling. Season 1 of the TV series &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Wh&lt;/em&gt;y features a series of tapes left behind by a girl who commits suicide while in high school. In these tapes, she explains the 13 reasons behind her drastic step. No wonder this series became very popular; it was not just relatable to the very core but the drama of listening to a dead girl’s tapes, explaining why she committed suicide, was scintillating. Besides the wave of awareness, the series left behind one adverse impact. The number of suicides increased by almost a third, instead of going down, ever since the series aired. Within three weeks of being aired, searches about suicides increased by a staggering 20%. Many blame it on the very graphic depiction of how Hannah Baker, the protagonist, took her life by slitting her wrists at the very end of the series. This is not something that audiences have witnessed before on television, certainly not in programmes aimed at teenagers. The popularity of the series earned it two more seasons in the years that followed. However, amidst all the concerns, Netflix altered the 3-minute sequence, although convinced that the series had nothing to do with the increase in suicide rates in the USA, over 2 years after its initial release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has, however, been a decline in the stigma surrounding mental health. People do seek to talk about and actively treat depression and other mental health problems. Various online portals and helplines are active to give help to those seeking it. Earlier, they failed to recognise depression as a disease that needed treatment. Instead, they saw it as inadequacy or incompetence. Certain old asylums are often considered to be haunted because of the unspoken torture within its walls in the past. Hundreds have died in various such locations around the world, after being shunned by society for being mentally ill. Shock therapy, invented in the Italy of the 1930s, was commonly practiced to treat ‘madness’. Many, even today, believe in the effectiveness of electroconvulsive therapy, although it has been repeatedly tagged as medical abuse by different organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are convinced that they are but &lt;strong&gt;doomed&lt;/strong&gt;. And this conviction comes from a place of hyperawareness. There is near-constant exposure to news of thousands being beheaded in the name of religion or people committing suicide by bringing down an entire airbus full of people along with themselves. Or, maybe, that people are capable of democratically electing a person who doesn’t believe that Global Warming, which, by the way, can facilitate the extinction of humanity, is real, as the Leader of the Free World. We are always talking and making memes about Trump’s tweets, the melting ice caps or India’s water crisis. We see the expendability of human life in the deaths of our beloved Cameron Boyce, Stan Lee, Avicii, Stephen Hawking, Dolores O’Riordan, David Cassidy, Chester Bennington, Bill Paxton, Carrie Fisher, Harper Lee, and Alan Rickman. In fact, most Millennials do not even conform to the term ‘Millennial’, tagging it as &lt;em&gt;overly optimistic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media and its ultra-fast nature have made it clear to the Millennials that humans are irrevocable. Millennials are &lt;strong&gt;aware&lt;/strong&gt; that the Zodiac Killer was never caught, MH-370 was never found and that France experienced its highest ever temperature in recorded history, earlier this year. They are aware of students shooting down hundreds in schools, abortion being banned and trees being cut. We know how this is affecting us all as a species and yet, there seems to be nothing that we can do about it. The news of bad incidents looms over us every day along with the knowledge that it can happen to any of us too. The incredibly talented and very dead singer Kurt Cobain did tell us, “Just because you are paranoid, does not mean they are not after you.” Millennials are the first generation to grow up in an era of both overwhelming awareness and paralysing feeling of our incapability to be able to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know what is expected of us, the perfect job and the perfect partner, and we are aware of how it is just a pipe dream. They tell us it is social media reinforcements of everyone else living the perfect life that is making our generation depressed. That we are trying to reach for standards we will never attain. But I think there is more to the Great Millennial Depression than just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that you are Einstein-smart, devilishly beautiful and incredibly funny. Are you among the top 10 something? If you are not, well then, you do not matter. Let us assume that you are among the world’s top 10 most hilarious people. Will you hold the position forever? What happens next year? What if you face a decade-long writer’s block and go bankrupt? Perhaps you &lt;em&gt;succeed&lt;/em&gt; and go on a cruise with your soulmate and drown in your bathtub? We all will die one day and there will be nothing left of us in a few decades. No one will remember our sacrifices, pain, hard work or the embarrassing moments that we have shared with our crushes. The question is, are we important? Are our actions significant? Why is it that humans have had the privilege to even exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have asked these for long and today, Millennials are convinced that nothing has an explanation. There is nowhere a certain someone is meant to be or something they are meant to do. They just exist. The stars were not specially created to dazzle us. Neither are we at the centre of the solar system, the universe or Creation in general. Things just exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think I am right, well then, congratulations, you are a nihilist. It is highly likely that you are a Millennial too. Turns out, the term nihilism has a very simple meaning. It is the rejection of all religious and moral principles. Nihilists believe that life has absolutely no meaning and yet humans keep seeking a way to give it some meaning, some purpose, but eventually die and are forgotten. In Tyler Durden’s &lt;em&gt;immortal&lt;/em&gt; words: “We are the middle children of history, man. No purpose or place. We have no Great War, No Great Depression. Our Great War’s a spiritual war… Our Great Depression is our Lives.” Nihilism is hot today. The great success of &lt;em&gt;BoJack Horseman, Rick and Morty, Hazel’s response to Augustus’ confession of the fear of oblivion&lt;/em&gt; and so on bear testimony to this very fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that depression and the popularity of nihilistic ideas have increased exponentially about the same time makes me wonder if they share some sort of a symbiotic relationship. If someone is depressed, the consolation that nothing really matters must help, surely? In fact, Optimistic Nihilism emphasises the notion that no one will ever remember one’s ill actions or embarrassing moments. Not all people who are depressed believe in nihilism though. But all nihilists may to some extent be sad. Everything productive that people do today is because they believe that it has meaning and life has a purpose. Nihilists dismiss this idea as nonsense. To them nothing has meaning and thus, there is no use doing anything. And the depressed do feel this way. Besides, I am sure you might have noticed the surge of suicidal and nihilistic memes’ pages on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilists do not care about anything because nothing makes sense or has any significance. And thus, nothing can make them sad. Embarrassing moments do not matter and so there is no need to overthink them. Mistakes and bad deeds do not matter and so, they can move on and do something better. Of course, life has no meaning. But we can try to give it one or at least try and be happy for the little time that we have on our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilism, however, contrary to popular opinion, is not the lack of hope. Life has no meaning. But, that does not mean that you cannot give it some purpose. Moreover, your failures do not count in anyone’s book and so, one should not be held back by them. Whether or not nihilism has been helping the depressed generation is up for debate. But, then again, there is no point in arguing. Alan Moore in &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; did very accurately say- “Why do we argue? Life is so fragile, a successful virus clinging to a speck of mud, suspended in endless nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a generation trapped in the growing realisation that they must face and solve the environmental, social and political crises of the day while lodged in the belief that nothing really matters. The same thing that causes our depression is also the source of our respite; how &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; it all matters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.</summary></entry></feed>