<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-29T22:04:06+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Love Jihad: U.P. Government’s Fallout with Freedom and Liberty</title><link href="/Love-Jihad" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love Jihad: U.P. Government’s Fallout with Freedom and Liberty" /><published>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Love-Jihad</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Love-Jihad">&lt;p&gt;A young, Muslim man — a &lt;em&gt;Macaulayputra&lt;/em&gt; (a term to describe covenanted, elitist English-speaking Indians; named after Lord Macaulay, who pioneered English-medium, Anglicised education in India), working a white-collar job, is sitting in an upmarket café in Uttar Pradesh with a Hindu woman of the ilk. The meeting is going well, until suddenly, a group of men, wearing saffron bandanas and carrying sticks, bats — with bellicose eyes and an intimidating demeanour, start policing unmarried couples. The 'features' of the Muslim man arise suspicion and after coercively rounding him up, his identity is confirmed. No one dares to dissuade them as they nab the man and take him away; with the words “love &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;” echoing in different decibels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This abhorring picture is how the Uttar Pradesh Prohibition of Unlawful Conversion of Religion Ordinance of 2020 — colloquially and contemptuously known as the “love &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;” law, is taking shape and will continue to take shape. This law touts to curb the forceful conversion of Hindu women to other religions (a caveat here is that the law does not speak much, if nothing at all, about Muslim or Christian women) under the false pretext of marriage. If booked under this law, the perpetrator can be imprisoned for up to ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving things some context, the firebrand Chief Minister of Uttar Pradesh, Yogi Adityanath — a Hindu monk from the Hindu nationalist Bhartiya Janata Party (BJP), has, on multiple occasions in his political career, addressed crowds with the clarion call of retorting violently to Muslims hostile towards Hindus. His narrative is also infamous for stoking fears among Hindus of Muslim domination; often citing convoluted historical anecdotes of Aurangzeb’s and Mahmud of Ghazni’s invasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since the BJP won a landslide majority in the state in 2017, the Yogi Adityanath government’s rule has been marred by increasing instances of violent attacks on minorities and cow vigilantism after the government banned illegal slaughterhouses on top of banning the sale and export of beef. Early on in his tenure, Yogi went on a spree of moral policing under the garb of stepping up measures for women safety by introducing 'Anti-Romeo squads' — law enforcement officers dressed in civilian clothes, policing anywhere and everywhere, given a free-hand to persecute those unmarried couples, who according to them, arouse suspicion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The love &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; ordinance (the use of the word ‘ordinance’ here carries a lot of legislative significance here because ordinances are laws passed on an ‘urgent’ basis and are not open to debate and discussions in the State Assembly) in its essence, deters all interfaith relationships to get the much needed legal approval in a society which is hitherto apprehensive of such courtships — especially one between Hindus and Muslims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This law, being passed as an ordinance and not going through the democratic process, raises questions about what it espouses— whether it legitimises Adityanath’s authoritarian rule which places state over the individual. Furthermore, this legislation also gives legal precedence to Hindu vigilante groups such as Bajrang Dal to prosecute all interfaith relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest points of contention is the cumbersome bureaucratic process that is required to gain legal approval of interfaith marriages in the state. The law mandates people involved in such a marital union to fill out paperwork and seek approval from the district magistrate. Consequently, they will end up exposing information about their private lives to an entire office of &lt;em&gt;babus &lt;/em&gt;— colloquial lexicon for bureaucrats and clerks, often describing their lax and recalcitrant demeanour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As laborious as getting through all the paperwork sounds, what makes it even more problematic is that anyone who knows the girl – a relative, neighbour, for instance, can object to the union and thereby deter the marriage from happening. Given how precarious interfaith unions are, especially a Hindu-Muslim one, it wouldn’t be incredulous to find a person in every union who would object to it, making the process almost improbable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is only logical to think that with such intricacies and nuances, the law would be equally comprehensive in persecuting those violating this law. In its application, especially the recent incarcerations under this law, it could be opined that the law has been “blatant” and “arbitrary”. An interfaith wedding in the state’s capital, Lucknow, was stopped mid-way by members of The Akhil Bharat Hindu Mahasabha — despite the bride’s father confirming to &lt;em&gt;Newslaundry&lt;/em&gt; that his daughter was not pressured to convert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the more riveting cases of this draconian legislation being applied was seen in Moradabad in western Uttar Pradesh. An interfaith couple was confronted by the Bajrang Dal — a vigilante group hitherto nefarious for moral policing unmarried couples on Valentine’s Day. What prevailed was a horrific tale of a miscarriage which exposed gaping holes in the administration which executes the law and the subsequent, incalculable human cost of “love &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forceful conversions, ones under undue influence or allurement — literally what the legislation espouses to protect Hindu women from, does indeed exist. However, those should be treated as isolated incidents and not precedence to plot a conspiracy against all Muslim men who purportedly 'lure' women into converting into Islam, as part of an 'Islamic invasion' in India. There should be stringent laws to punish those who indeed trick people into abandoning their faith, but not at the cost of all interfaith unions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recalcitrance of the Yogi Adityanath government to continue persecuting couples despite it drawing flak for violating the right to profess any religion further embellishes an authoritarian rule which borrows its doctrines from the Hindutva ideology. What is even more worrisome is that this rule also makes men strong patriarchs in families and restricts women’s freedom and liberty. This is further cemented by the Lucknow Police’s decision of installing AR-powered CCTV cameras in public places, which would identify “a woman’s facial expression when in distress” to curb attacks on women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fictional narrative quoted in the beginning highlights that the rich — who often get away with persecution in somewhat of a closeted plutocracy, might not also be able to use their privilege to save themselves. The government, henceforth, should tread carefully — the palpable air of tensions simmering in the state during the 2013 Muzzafarnagar riots — a communal clash between Hindus and Muslims, is still too recent to be forgotten. Anything igniting that flame could be detrimental for the whole populace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Kant</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">A young, Muslim man — a Macaulayputra (a term to describe covenanted, elitist English-speaking Indians; named after Lord Macaulay, who pioneered English-medium, Anglicised education in India), working a white-collar job, is sitting in an upmarket café in Uttar Pradesh with a Hindu woman of the ilk. The meeting is going well, until suddenly, a group of men, wearing saffron bandanas and carrying sticks, bats — with bellicose eyes and an intimidating demeanour, start policing unmarried couples. The 'features' of the Muslim man arise suspicion and after coercively rounding him up, his identity is confirmed. No one dares to dissuade them as they nab the man and take him away; with the words “love jihad” echoing in different decibels. This abhorring picture is how the Uttar Pradesh Prohibition of Unlawful Conversion of Religion Ordinance of 2020 — colloquially and contemptuously known as the “love jihad” law, is taking shape and will continue to take shape. This law touts to curb the forceful conversion of Hindu women to other religions (a caveat here is that the law does not speak much, if nothing at all, about Muslim or Christian women) under the false pretext of marriage. If booked under this law, the perpetrator can be imprisoned for up to ten years. Giving things some context, the firebrand Chief Minister of Uttar Pradesh, Yogi Adityanath — a Hindu monk from the Hindu nationalist Bhartiya Janata Party (BJP), has, on multiple occasions in his political career, addressed crowds with the clarion call of retorting violently to Muslims hostile towards Hindus. His narrative is also infamous for stoking fears among Hindus of Muslim domination; often citing convoluted historical anecdotes of Aurangzeb’s and Mahmud of Ghazni’s invasions. Ever since the BJP won a landslide majority in the state in 2017, the Yogi Adityanath government’s rule has been marred by increasing instances of violent attacks on minorities and cow vigilantism after the government banned illegal slaughterhouses on top of banning the sale and export of beef. Early on in his tenure, Yogi went on a spree of moral policing under the garb of stepping up measures for women safety by introducing 'Anti-Romeo squads' — law enforcement officers dressed in civilian clothes, policing anywhere and everywhere, given a free-hand to persecute those unmarried couples, who according to them, arouse suspicion. The love jihad ordinance (the use of the word ‘ordinance’ here carries a lot of legislative significance here because ordinances are laws passed on an ‘urgent’ basis and are not open to debate and discussions in the State Assembly) in its essence, deters all interfaith relationships to get the much needed legal approval in a society which is hitherto apprehensive of such courtships — especially one between Hindus and Muslims. This law, being passed as an ordinance and not going through the democratic process, raises questions about what it espouses— whether it legitimises Adityanath’s authoritarian rule which places state over the individual. Furthermore, this legislation also gives legal precedence to Hindu vigilante groups such as Bajrang Dal to prosecute all interfaith relationships. One of the biggest points of contention is the cumbersome bureaucratic process that is required to gain legal approval of interfaith marriages in the state. The law mandates people involved in such a marital union to fill out paperwork and seek approval from the district magistrate. Consequently, they will end up exposing information about their private lives to an entire office of babus — colloquial lexicon for bureaucrats and clerks, often describing their lax and recalcitrant demeanour. As laborious as getting through all the paperwork sounds, what makes it even more problematic is that anyone who knows the girl – a relative, neighbour, for instance, can object to the union and thereby deter the marriage from happening. Given how precarious interfaith unions are, especially a Hindu-Muslim one, it wouldn’t be incredulous to find a person in every union who would object to it, making the process almost improbable. It is only logical to think that with such intricacies and nuances, the law would be equally comprehensive in persecuting those violating this law. In its application, especially the recent incarcerations under this law, it could be opined that the law has been “blatant” and “arbitrary”. An interfaith wedding in the state’s capital, Lucknow, was stopped mid-way by members of The Akhil Bharat Hindu Mahasabha — despite the bride’s father confirming to Newslaundry that his daughter was not pressured to convert. One of the more riveting cases of this draconian legislation being applied was seen in Moradabad in western Uttar Pradesh. An interfaith couple was confronted by the Bajrang Dal — a vigilante group hitherto nefarious for moral policing unmarried couples on Valentine’s Day. What prevailed was a horrific tale of a miscarriage which exposed gaping holes in the administration which executes the law and the subsequent, incalculable human cost of “love jihad”. Forceful conversions, ones under undue influence or allurement — literally what the legislation espouses to protect Hindu women from, does indeed exist. However, those should be treated as isolated incidents and not precedence to plot a conspiracy against all Muslim men who purportedly 'lure' women into converting into Islam, as part of an 'Islamic invasion' in India. There should be stringent laws to punish those who indeed trick people into abandoning their faith, but not at the cost of all interfaith unions. The recalcitrance of the Yogi Adityanath government to continue persecuting couples despite it drawing flak for violating the right to profess any religion further embellishes an authoritarian rule which borrows its doctrines from the Hindutva ideology. What is even more worrisome is that this rule also makes men strong patriarchs in families and restricts women’s freedom and liberty. This is further cemented by the Lucknow Police’s decision of installing AR-powered CCTV cameras in public places, which would identify “a woman’s facial expression when in distress” to curb attacks on women. The fictional narrative quoted in the beginning highlights that the rich — who often get away with persecution in somewhat of a closeted plutocracy, might not also be able to use their privilege to save themselves. The government, henceforth, should tread carefully — the palpable air of tensions simmering in the state during the 2013 Muzzafarnagar riots — a communal clash between Hindus and Muslims, is still too recent to be forgotten. Anything igniting that flame could be detrimental for the whole populace.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Egyptian Mummies: A Story of the Colonial Abuse of History</title><link href="/Egyptian-Mummies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Egyptian Mummies: A Story of the Colonial Abuse of History" /><published>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Egyptian-Mummies</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Egyptian-Mummies">&lt;p&gt;Mummies are probably among the most 'Egyptian' things to exist in our history books in spite of the fact that mummification is neither unique to ancient Egypt nor is it always man-made. The main reason behind the popularisation of mummification as a part of ancient Egyptian culture, apart from the academic fascination with the extraordinary methods employed in the process to mummify a dead body by ancient Egyptians, is the endless number of stories that exist about them. Very unsurprisingly, most of them are distorted and sometimes outright lies regarding the culture. Most, if not all of these, are rooted in absolute ignorance about history and sometimes, they exist due to a veiled effort to profit off of an exotic ancient African civilisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a believer in science and as a passionate reader of history, the process of mummification is rather interesting to me. The Egyptians were, however, not the first to mummify their dead. At least 2,000 years before them, the Chinchorro people of Southern American descent were already practising mummification. Of course, the methods employed vary from civilisation to civilisation. In addition, based on how well the bodies were preserved and other factors, it can be inferred that the procedure changed with time. Unfortunately, climate change has not been kind to mummies. The rising humidity levels have contributed to the spread of flesh-eating microbes, which are detrimental to the preservation of mummies. This makes studying them all the more difficult. Apart from this, the procedure employed for the poor was less extensive compared to that employed for the Pharaohs. Unfortunately, there are no proper accounts of how the mummification was done in ancient Egypt left behind by the Egyptians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only two ancient texts that lay out the mummification techniques are the accounts of Diodorus and Herodotus from when they travelled to Egypt. The famous &lt;em&gt;Book of the Dead&lt;/em&gt;, which has made appearances in various cult classics, does not extensively talk about the methods employed. Instead, it provides various spells and rituals that could potentially help the dead enter the afterlife. In 1994, two scientists used the ancient Egyptian mummification methods on a victim of heart attack successfully, in order to get a greater depth of understanding of the procedure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of mummification is very elaborate. It began with removing the internal organs, with the exception of the heart. The ancient Egyptian religion propagated a belief that the dead were judged by their heart on entering the underworld, before proceeding on to the afterlife. They would thus use an amulet, commonly referred to as the heart scarab, to protect it. The overall mummification process took about 40 days. The Egyptians did not limit this practice to humans - they mummified various animals like cats, ibises, hawks, crocodiles, rats and lizards, primarily for religious reasons.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice of mummification in Egypt died out between the 4th and 7th century AD, which is around the time when many of the Egyptians converted to Christianity. It has been estimated that over a period of about 3,000 years over 70 million mummies were made in Egypt. The Egyptian civilisation existed for much longer than this. It is believed that anthropogenic mummification was introduced into practice around 2,600 BC, that is, during the Fourth or Fifth Dynasties. There are older mummies available but these have been preserved naturally, especially owing to the fact that Egypt has zero measurable rainfall.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Egyptian mummies have always fascinated people. While today we are aware of the psyche behind the process and the procedure involved in mummifying the remains of humans, the same cannot be said about those who came much before us and after the decline of ancient Egypt. Scholars of the 18th century were interested in knowing what lay under the wrappings of a mummy. Soon 'Mummy Unwrapping Parties' were popularised by those who could afford them, in their private homes. Later, such unwrapping ceremonies would also be organised in public theatres. Many of these people, who conducted these events, had no knowledge of medical sciences. It was simply a source of entertainment, a way to feed the public’s fascination with mummies and of course, as a symbol of wealth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Mummy dust' makes appearances throughout history in the most absurd places and manners. King Charles II believed that mummy dust could potentially contribute to his greatness and so, he was known to rub it onto his skin. King Francis I of France had a similar belief - he thought that it would make him stronger and so he took a pinch of mummy every day with rhubarb. An abstract published in the &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Royal Society of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; journal of 1927 puts forward the idea that between the 12th and the 17th centuries, medicines were prepared from powdered mummies. In fact, 'mummy medicine' was actually very popular around this time and an unrecorded number of mummies were disentombed and burned to prepare the medication. People at the time believed that bitumen had medicinal properties and it was thought that mummification involved embalming the body with bitumen. However, this was actually very uncommon - most mummies were embalmed with resins.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most commonly encountered occurrence of the Egyptian mummy in popular culture is the undead mummy. Going by Egyptian mythology, this is a rather weird concept. Their religious beliefs encouraged the idea that living beings move on to the after-life after death. A walking mummy in that context is simply absurd. How then was this trope born?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mummy genre has its origins in the 19th century. This was when Egypt was first colonised by France and then by Victorian Britain. The colonial romanticisation of the East resulted in most of these early stories, which presented mummies as mostly female and more often than not, the love interest of the protagonist. This is one of the numerous examples of sexualised orientalism born during the age of colonialism. Some of the greatest writers of the age delved into this new genre: &lt;em&gt;The Jewel of the Seven Stars&lt;/em&gt; by Bram Stoker and Sir Arthur Canon Doyle’s &lt;em&gt;The Ring of Thoth&lt;/em&gt; are two such examples. In H D Everett’s &lt;em&gt;Iras: A Mystery&lt;/em&gt;, the protagonist ends up marrying a mummy, which turns into a beautiful woman. In 1845, Edgar Allan Poe wrote &lt;em&gt;Some Words with a Mummy&lt;/em&gt;. This piece was a satire unlike most of the stories about mummies written at the time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1892 novel &lt;em&gt;Lot No. 249&lt;/em&gt;, written by Sir. Doyle is believed to be the first to portray a mummy as a dangerous creature. It was only in the 1930's that the 'monster mummy' started making frequent appearances. The 'romantic mummy' would make a comeback only in the late 20th century with Anne Rice’s 1989 novel, &lt;em&gt;The Mummy, or Ramses the Damned&lt;/em&gt;. This novel, unlike most of the 19th century ones, involved a sexual relationship between a male mummy (instead of a female) and a female archaeologist.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Romanticised and dangerous undead mummies would increasingly dominate books and screens from this point on, in the form of novellas, TV series, video games and so on and so forth. The &lt;em&gt;Goosebumps&lt;/em&gt; series by R L Stine has quite a few of them as monsters. Marvel Comics has its own mummies like N’Kantu. In the very popular &lt;em&gt;Ben 10&lt;/em&gt; franchise, Thep Khufans is a race of alien mummies. The lead character Ben Tennyson has ten alien forms, one of which is Snare-oh, previously named Benmummy, which is a Thep Khufan. In video games, mummies make notable appearances as hostile creatures thriving in deserts in &lt;em&gt;Terraria &lt;/em&gt;and as an immortal creature named Kan-Ra in&lt;em&gt; Killer Instinct&lt;/em&gt;, among others. In several editions of &lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/em&gt;, mummies have found a place in the form of Bog Mummies, Hunefers, Mummy Lords, etc. Various films also have Egyptian mummies as characters like Ahkmenrah from the &lt;em&gt;Night at the Museum &lt;/em&gt;and Murray the Mummy from &lt;em&gt;Hotel Transylvania.&lt;/em&gt; Almost nothing in any of these depictions has any similarity with the ancient Egyptian ideas or understanding of mummies and they are simply a result of colonial fascination with oriental culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While walking undead mummies are a creation of the West and have no Egyptian origins, modern science has been trying to make this a reality, at least in a way. DNA capable of being analysed was found in mummies dating back to 2,012 BC by scientists who wish to clone mummies. A group of researchers recreated the voice of a 3,000-year-old mummy of an ancient Egyptian priest, Nesyamun using 3-D printing and body-scanning technology, effectively bringing him to life in 2020. Of course, none of these actually have the effect that the various stories perpetuate - a monster or a lover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common plot in many Egyptian mummy-centric stories of today involves the 'Mummy’s Curse' or the 'Pharaoh’s Curse'. Now the question is, did ancient Egyptians believe in such a curse? The people of ancient Egypt were very particular about protecting tombs and mummies. Many of the pharaohs were entombed in a spot in the famous Valley of the Kings. According to the ancient Egyptian myths, Meretseger, a goddess who took the form of a cobra, protects the Valley of the Kings by blinding or poisoning tomb robbers. There were various punishments put in place to prevent tomb robbery in ancient times. Tomb raiders, who were caught, had the soles of their feet beaten before being publicly impaled on a sharp wooden stick.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various deaths have been attributed to the Pharaoh’s Curse in the more recent past. The most famous among them is possibly the so-called Curse of Tutankhamun, which is popularly believed to have claimed over six lives in the years following the discovery of the tomb of the boy king in 1922. One of the victims is Lord Carnarvon, the sponsor of the expedition, who died six weeks after the historic event due to supposed blood poisoning. However, Howard Carter, the seemingly prime target of the supposed curses because of the fact that he was responsible for the discovery, died only in 1939, almost 17 years after the opening of the tomb. Only six of the 23 people present during the opening died in a decade following the discovery. With statistics like these, many refuse to believe that a curse was involved in the deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people have tried to explain these deaths. It is commonly believed to be biological in nature. Egyptian tombs have various items intended to help on the dead’s journey to the afterlife, alongside the sarcophagus. This includes food. It is possible that pathogens thrive in such sealed tombs. Investigations into this matter revealed that some tombs have mould-like &lt;em&gt;Aspergillus niger&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Aspergillus flavus&lt;/em&gt;, and bacteria like &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/em&gt;. These are capable of causing various lung ailments. However, most scientists agree that these are not very dangerous. F DeWolfe Miller, Emeritus Professor of Epidemiology at the University of Hawaii at Manoa, agrees with this. He has been quoted as saying that he knows of no archaeologist or tourist who has suffered the adverse effects of tomb toxins.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Howard Carter believed that taking the conditions of Upper Egypt of the 1920's into consideration, Lord Carnarvon was probably safer inside the tomb, a statement that many scientists agree with. In this context, Miller was quoted saying, “The idea that an underground tomb, after 3,000 years, would have some kind of bizarre microorganism in it that's going to kill somebody six weeks later and make it look exactly like [blood poisoning] is very hard to believe”. The cause of the deaths is thus still up for debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The belief in the curses as being the cause has been around for a while now but did they exist back during the ancient times? Late egyptologist Dominic Montserrat was quoted by &lt;em&gt;The Independent&lt;/em&gt; at the conclusion of extensive research into the matter as follows: “My research has not only confirmed that there is, of course, no ancient Egyptian origin of the mummy's curse concept, but, more importantly, it also reveals that it didn't originate in the 1923 press publicity about the discovery of Tutankhamen's tomb either”. The mummy’s curse concept is also not a contribution of Hollywood. In fact, it dates back to the 1800's. One of the earliest examples of this is Louisa May Alcott’s &lt;em&gt;Lost in a Pyramid &lt;/em&gt;or &lt;em&gt;The Mummy’s Curse&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all egyptologists agree with this though. Salima Ikram, who is an Egyptologist at the American University of Cairo believes that a form of curses did in fact exist in ancient Egyptian times as a primitive security system against the desecration of the tomb or any form of tomb robbery. According to Ikram, some of the mastaba (early Egyptian non-pyramidal tomb) walls located at Saqqara and Giza have curses inscribed on them. She has been quoted saying, “They tend to threaten desecrators with divine retribution by the council of the gods or a death by crocodiles, or lions, or scorpions, or snakes”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the expansive availability of various stories regarding the ancient Egyptians, it is difficult to know what among these is actually historically accurate. These stories have had the impact of this ancient civilisation is widely viewed as a land of extremely religious people who practised magic, making it difficult for many, including Elon Musk, to believe that these people built the magnificent pyramids, among other similar astonishing accomplishments. Of course, this is not the first time that Westerners have questioned the capabilities of the people of ancient Asian, South American or African civilisations. Quite frankly, much of what we know today through stories are solely a result of the colonial world’s unhealthy fascination with the exotic cultures and are not rooted in real history. The idea of undead mummies causing devastation or the fact that there are people who are actively seeking to hunt down specific mummies and disentomb them (archaeologists), would probably scandalise the ancient Egyptians. At the end of the day, 'disturbing' the dead in any culture is considered disrespectful. However, people have made exceptions for the ancient Egyptians in the name of gaining knowledge, preparing medicines and sometimes, for the riches enclosed within the walls of the tombs, for a very long time now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Mummies are probably among the most 'Egyptian' things to exist in our history books in spite of the fact that mummification is neither unique to ancient Egypt nor is it always man-made. The main reason behind the popularisation of mummification as a part of ancient Egyptian culture, apart from the academic fascination with the extraordinary methods employed in the process to mummify a dead body by ancient Egyptians, is the endless number of stories that exist about them. Very unsurprisingly, most of them are distorted and sometimes outright lies regarding the culture. Most, if not all of these, are rooted in absolute ignorance about history and sometimes, they exist due to a veiled effort to profit off of an exotic ancient African civilisation.&amp;nbsp; As a believer in science and as a passionate reader of history, the process of mummification is rather interesting to me. The Egyptians were, however, not the first to mummify their dead. At least 2,000 years before them, the Chinchorro people of Southern American descent were already practising mummification. Of course, the methods employed vary from civilisation to civilisation. In addition, based on how well the bodies were preserved and other factors, it can be inferred that the procedure changed with time. Unfortunately, climate change has not been kind to mummies. The rising humidity levels have contributed to the spread of flesh-eating microbes, which are detrimental to the preservation of mummies. This makes studying them all the more difficult. Apart from this, the procedure employed for the poor was less extensive compared to that employed for the Pharaohs. Unfortunately, there are no proper accounts of how the mummification was done in ancient Egypt left behind by the Egyptians. The only two ancient texts that lay out the mummification techniques are the accounts of Diodorus and Herodotus from when they travelled to Egypt. The famous Book of the Dead, which has made appearances in various cult classics, does not extensively talk about the methods employed. Instead, it provides various spells and rituals that could potentially help the dead enter the afterlife. In 1994, two scientists used the ancient Egyptian mummification methods on a victim of heart attack successfully, in order to get a greater depth of understanding of the procedure.&amp;nbsp; The process of mummification is very elaborate. It began with removing the internal organs, with the exception of the heart. The ancient Egyptian religion propagated a belief that the dead were judged by their heart on entering the underworld, before proceeding on to the afterlife. They would thus use an amulet, commonly referred to as the heart scarab, to protect it. The overall mummification process took about 40 days. The Egyptians did not limit this practice to humans - they mummified various animals like cats, ibises, hawks, crocodiles, rats and lizards, primarily for religious reasons.&amp;nbsp; The practice of mummification in Egypt died out between the 4th and 7th century AD, which is around the time when many of the Egyptians converted to Christianity. It has been estimated that over a period of about 3,000 years over 70 million mummies were made in Egypt. The Egyptian civilisation existed for much longer than this. It is believed that anthropogenic mummification was introduced into practice around 2,600 BC, that is, during the Fourth or Fifth Dynasties. There are older mummies available but these have been preserved naturally, especially owing to the fact that Egypt has zero measurable rainfall.&amp;nbsp; Egyptian mummies have always fascinated people. While today we are aware of the psyche behind the process and the procedure involved in mummifying the remains of humans, the same cannot be said about those who came much before us and after the decline of ancient Egypt. Scholars of the 18th century were interested in knowing what lay under the wrappings of a mummy. Soon 'Mummy Unwrapping Parties' were popularised by those who could afford them, in their private homes. Later, such unwrapping ceremonies would also be organised in public theatres. Many of these people, who conducted these events, had no knowledge of medical sciences. It was simply a source of entertainment, a way to feed the public’s fascination with mummies and of course, as a symbol of wealth.&amp;nbsp; 'Mummy dust' makes appearances throughout history in the most absurd places and manners. King Charles II believed that mummy dust could potentially contribute to his greatness and so, he was known to rub it onto his skin. King Francis I of France had a similar belief - he thought that it would make him stronger and so he took a pinch of mummy every day with rhubarb. An abstract published in the Proceedings of the Royal Society of Medicine journal of 1927 puts forward the idea that between the 12th and the 17th centuries, medicines were prepared from powdered mummies. In fact, 'mummy medicine' was actually very popular around this time and an unrecorded number of mummies were disentombed and burned to prepare the medication. People at the time believed that bitumen had medicinal properties and it was thought that mummification involved embalming the body with bitumen. However, this was actually very uncommon - most mummies were embalmed with resins.&amp;nbsp; The most commonly encountered occurrence of the Egyptian mummy in popular culture is the undead mummy. Going by Egyptian mythology, this is a rather weird concept. Their religious beliefs encouraged the idea that living beings move on to the after-life after death. A walking mummy in that context is simply absurd. How then was this trope born?&amp;nbsp; The mummy genre has its origins in the 19th century. This was when Egypt was first colonised by France and then by Victorian Britain. The colonial romanticisation of the East resulted in most of these early stories, which presented mummies as mostly female and more often than not, the love interest of the protagonist. This is one of the numerous examples of sexualised orientalism born during the age of colonialism. Some of the greatest writers of the age delved into this new genre: The Jewel of the Seven Stars by Bram Stoker and Sir Arthur Canon Doyle’s The Ring of Thoth are two such examples. In H D Everett’s Iras: A Mystery, the protagonist ends up marrying a mummy, which turns into a beautiful woman. In 1845, Edgar Allan Poe wrote Some Words with a Mummy. This piece was a satire unlike most of the stories about mummies written at the time.&amp;nbsp; The 1892 novel Lot No. 249, written by Sir. Doyle is believed to be the first to portray a mummy as a dangerous creature. It was only in the 1930's that the 'monster mummy' started making frequent appearances. The 'romantic mummy' would make a comeback only in the late 20th century with Anne Rice’s 1989 novel, The Mummy, or Ramses the Damned. This novel, unlike most of the 19th century ones, involved a sexual relationship between a male mummy (instead of a female) and a female archaeologist.&amp;nbsp; Romanticised and dangerous undead mummies would increasingly dominate books and screens from this point on, in the form of novellas, TV series, video games and so on and so forth. The Goosebumps series by R L Stine has quite a few of them as monsters. Marvel Comics has its own mummies like N’Kantu. In the very popular Ben 10 franchise, Thep Khufans is a race of alien mummies. The lead character Ben Tennyson has ten alien forms, one of which is Snare-oh, previously named Benmummy, which is a Thep Khufan. In video games, mummies make notable appearances as hostile creatures thriving in deserts in Terraria and as an immortal creature named Kan-Ra in Killer Instinct, among others. In several editions of Dungeons and Dragons, mummies have found a place in the form of Bog Mummies, Hunefers, Mummy Lords, etc. Various films also have Egyptian mummies as characters like Ahkmenrah from the Night at the Museum and Murray the Mummy from Hotel Transylvania. Almost nothing in any of these depictions has any similarity with the ancient Egyptian ideas or understanding of mummies and they are simply a result of colonial fascination with oriental culture. While walking undead mummies are a creation of the West and have no Egyptian origins, modern science has been trying to make this a reality, at least in a way. DNA capable of being analysed was found in mummies dating back to 2,012 BC by scientists who wish to clone mummies. A group of researchers recreated the voice of a 3,000-year-old mummy of an ancient Egyptian priest, Nesyamun using 3-D printing and body-scanning technology, effectively bringing him to life in 2020. Of course, none of these actually have the effect that the various stories perpetuate - a monster or a lover. A common plot in many Egyptian mummy-centric stories of today involves the 'Mummy’s Curse' or the 'Pharaoh’s Curse'. Now the question is, did ancient Egyptians believe in such a curse? The people of ancient Egypt were very particular about protecting tombs and mummies. Many of the pharaohs were entombed in a spot in the famous Valley of the Kings. According to the ancient Egyptian myths, Meretseger, a goddess who took the form of a cobra, protects the Valley of the Kings by blinding or poisoning tomb robbers. There were various punishments put in place to prevent tomb robbery in ancient times. Tomb raiders, who were caught, had the soles of their feet beaten before being publicly impaled on a sharp wooden stick.&amp;nbsp; Various deaths have been attributed to the Pharaoh’s Curse in the more recent past. The most famous among them is possibly the so-called Curse of Tutankhamun, which is popularly believed to have claimed over six lives in the years following the discovery of the tomb of the boy king in 1922. One of the victims is Lord Carnarvon, the sponsor of the expedition, who died six weeks after the historic event due to supposed blood poisoning. However, Howard Carter, the seemingly prime target of the supposed curses because of the fact that he was responsible for the discovery, died only in 1939, almost 17 years after the opening of the tomb. Only six of the 23 people present during the opening died in a decade following the discovery. With statistics like these, many refuse to believe that a curse was involved in the deaths. Many people have tried to explain these deaths. It is commonly believed to be biological in nature. Egyptian tombs have various items intended to help on the dead’s journey to the afterlife, alongside the sarcophagus. This includes food. It is possible that pathogens thrive in such sealed tombs. Investigations into this matter revealed that some tombs have mould-like Aspergillus niger and Aspergillus flavus, and bacteria like Pseudomonas and Staphylococcus. These are capable of causing various lung ailments. However, most scientists agree that these are not very dangerous. F DeWolfe Miller, Emeritus Professor of Epidemiology at the University of Hawaii at Manoa, agrees with this. He has been quoted as saying that he knows of no archaeologist or tourist who has suffered the adverse effects of tomb toxins.&amp;nbsp; Howard Carter believed that taking the conditions of Upper Egypt of the 1920's into consideration, Lord Carnarvon was probably safer inside the tomb, a statement that many scientists agree with. In this context, Miller was quoted saying, “The idea that an underground tomb, after 3,000 years, would have some kind of bizarre microorganism in it that's going to kill somebody six weeks later and make it look exactly like [blood poisoning] is very hard to believe”. The cause of the deaths is thus still up for debate. The belief in the curses as being the cause has been around for a while now but did they exist back during the ancient times? Late egyptologist Dominic Montserrat was quoted by The Independent at the conclusion of extensive research into the matter as follows: “My research has not only confirmed that there is, of course, no ancient Egyptian origin of the mummy's curse concept, but, more importantly, it also reveals that it didn't originate in the 1923 press publicity about the discovery of Tutankhamen's tomb either”. The mummy’s curse concept is also not a contribution of Hollywood. In fact, it dates back to the 1800's. One of the earliest examples of this is Louisa May Alcott’s Lost in a Pyramid or The Mummy’s Curse. Not all egyptologists agree with this though. Salima Ikram, who is an Egyptologist at the American University of Cairo believes that a form of curses did in fact exist in ancient Egyptian times as a primitive security system against the desecration of the tomb or any form of tomb robbery. According to Ikram, some of the mastaba (early Egyptian non-pyramidal tomb) walls located at Saqqara and Giza have curses inscribed on them. She has been quoted saying, “They tend to threaten desecrators with divine retribution by the council of the gods or a death by crocodiles, or lions, or scorpions, or snakes”.&amp;nbsp; Due to the expansive availability of various stories regarding the ancient Egyptians, it is difficult to know what among these is actually historically accurate. These stories have had the impact of this ancient civilisation is widely viewed as a land of extremely religious people who practised magic, making it difficult for many, including Elon Musk, to believe that these people built the magnificent pyramids, among other similar astonishing accomplishments. Of course, this is not the first time that Westerners have questioned the capabilities of the people of ancient Asian, South American or African civilisations. Quite frankly, much of what we know today through stories are solely a result of the colonial world’s unhealthy fascination with the exotic cultures and are not rooted in real history. The idea of undead mummies causing devastation or the fact that there are people who are actively seeking to hunt down specific mummies and disentomb them (archaeologists), would probably scandalise the ancient Egyptians. At the end of the day, 'disturbing' the dead in any culture is considered disrespectful. However, people have made exceptions for the ancient Egyptians in the name of gaining knowledge, preparing medicines and sometimes, for the riches enclosed within the walls of the tombs, for a very long time now.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond Clapping: How to Really Appreciate the NHS</title><link href="/Beyond-Clapping" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Clapping: How to Really Appreciate the NHS" /><published>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Beyond-Clapping</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Beyond-Clapping">&lt;p&gt;How many times have you heard the National Health Service (NHS) described as modern Britain’s closest thing to a national religion? This is a cliché almost impossible to avoid when reading about healthcare in Britain. In writing the sentences you have just read, it looks like I, too, have failed in putting this rather trite observation to bed. But I reference it because, however much I tire of hearing it, it’s truer than ever.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No other organ in the country commands the same reverence as the NHS. Nevertheless, when I work in the NHS as an administrator, I don’t feel much pride, or emotional attachment, or anything approaching religious fervour. Instead, what swamps me is incredulity that what we call the NHS has survived for as long as it has. The pandemic really hammered that home, but it was a nagging feeling that had begun to rise in me before the empty football stands or momentary amusement caused by watching someone talk into a muted microphone became depressingly routine. Many are perennially dissatisfied with the state of our health service. Given the herculean responsibilities placed upon it, by the state and by the people, it’s doing about as well as can reasonably be expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the operative word here is “reasonably”. Every economy should endeavour to deliver the best quality of healthcare to the largest number of people, at the lowest possible cost. If the state can bring the country closer towards fulfilling that ambition, then it should do so. But we must not lose sight of how difficult a task this is, because no matter how many nurses, doctor’s appointments and hospital beds there are, demand for these things will always outstrip supply.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demand for healthcare has no limits. What we can limit, and must, are our expectations. The number of freebies people expect from the NHS is ridiculous. Making healthcare “free at the point of use”- the mantra of Attlee’s post-War Labour government - is a noble principle. However, if large swathes of the public do not accept that this principle is, at best, very difficult to reach, then they will be forever disappointed. Can all surgery be free if nobody pays for prescriptions or spectacles? It is possible that, in order to receive the really big healthcare procedures for free, we might just have to accept paying for the smaller ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially amid the current crisis, this shouldn’t need spelling out. Expecting a bureaucratic organisation to bring about an undeliverable no-fee nirvana and inhalers when thousands of people are dying every day from a novel virus is maddening. And the creators of the NHS knew it, too. In 1951, amid economic calamity, Labour’s Chancellor Hugh Gaitskell introduced charges on dental and eye appointments, doing so against public opinion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a shame that the current political establishment lacks Gaitskell’s gall to stare down its constituents. Instead of levelling with people about the state of the NHS, both political parties endlessly pander to them, outbidding each other to pledge more and more money to the health service in a pathetic game of chicken. No minister ever stops to consider the possibility that the problem with the NHS might not be that its budget, which swells year on year, is too small, but that no amount of money could ever bring reality into line with people’s sky-high ideals. Until Labour and the Tories face up to this, little will change for the better.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point in most conversations that people assume that I am anti-NHS, and support some sort of American-style insurance system. This is incorrect; as I said earlier, there is a place for the state in healthcare. As for the US, even describing healthcare there as a “system” would be overly charitable. Its disorganised and overlapping mandates fail to constrain costs, and for all the libertarian claims that Americans will never accept “socialised medicine”, the US Federal Government spends about twice as much of its budget on healthcare as most European countries. In so many respects, America fails to realise its small government aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some in Britain support a transition towards the more comprehensive insurance-based systems found in France and Germany. These systems do have better controls on costs, but I suspect that they would also come with their own unintended consequences. People don’t like seeing a doctor, even when they aren’t asked to reach for their insurance papers afterwards. Under these circumstances, people may avoid going to see their GP, thus waiting for minor health issues to spiral out of control. There is no way of knowing how Britain, where the concept of healthcare free at the point of use is so ingrained, would fare with an insurance system, and people on the right of politics don’t spend enough time considering the potential flaws of alternative systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the fact that there is no debate over fundamental reforms to the NHS is a travesty. In an era where people are getting older, fatter, and more numerous, the expectation that every service the NHS provides can be free, from top to bottom, is unsustainable. There must be a middle-ground between expecting to pay for nothing, and turning to insurance to cover nearly everything. I fear that if the state does not take the issue of reform seriously, it will have reform imposed upon it by a total breakdown of the system. The current predicament should serve as a warning to the government that a breakdown might not be far away.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to avoid such a crisis or insurance-style reform, we, the British people, must reform our own attitude towards the health service. When the NHS is required to do so much, not everything it does can be free. The next time you have to pay for a prescription, or a dental appointment, realise that somebody else less fortunate than you isn’t paying for their chemotherapy as a result. Coughing up would do more for the NHS than clapping ever could. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">How many times have you heard the National Health Service (NHS) described as modern Britain’s closest thing to a national religion? This is a cliché almost impossible to avoid when reading about healthcare in Britain. In writing the sentences you have just read, it looks like I, too, have failed in putting this rather trite observation to bed. But I reference it because, however much I tire of hearing it, it’s truer than ever.&amp;nbsp; No other organ in the country commands the same reverence as the NHS. Nevertheless, when I work in the NHS as an administrator, I don’t feel much pride, or emotional attachment, or anything approaching religious fervour. Instead, what swamps me is incredulity that what we call the NHS has survived for as long as it has. The pandemic really hammered that home, but it was a nagging feeling that had begun to rise in me before the empty football stands or momentary amusement caused by watching someone talk into a muted microphone became depressingly routine. Many are perennially dissatisfied with the state of our health service. Given the herculean responsibilities placed upon it, by the state and by the people, it’s doing about as well as can reasonably be expected. Of course, the operative word here is “reasonably”. Every economy should endeavour to deliver the best quality of healthcare to the largest number of people, at the lowest possible cost. If the state can bring the country closer towards fulfilling that ambition, then it should do so. But we must not lose sight of how difficult a task this is, because no matter how many nurses, doctor’s appointments and hospital beds there are, demand for these things will always outstrip supply.&amp;nbsp; Demand for healthcare has no limits. What we can limit, and must, are our expectations. The number of freebies people expect from the NHS is ridiculous. Making healthcare “free at the point of use”- the mantra of Attlee’s post-War Labour government - is a noble principle. However, if large swathes of the public do not accept that this principle is, at best, very difficult to reach, then they will be forever disappointed. Can all surgery be free if nobody pays for prescriptions or spectacles? It is possible that, in order to receive the really big healthcare procedures for free, we might just have to accept paying for the smaller ones. Especially amid the current crisis, this shouldn’t need spelling out. Expecting a bureaucratic organisation to bring about an undeliverable no-fee nirvana and inhalers when thousands of people are dying every day from a novel virus is maddening. And the creators of the NHS knew it, too. In 1951, amid economic calamity, Labour’s Chancellor Hugh Gaitskell introduced charges on dental and eye appointments, doing so against public opinion.&amp;nbsp; It’s a shame that the current political establishment lacks Gaitskell’s gall to stare down its constituents. Instead of levelling with people about the state of the NHS, both political parties endlessly pander to them, outbidding each other to pledge more and more money to the health service in a pathetic game of chicken. No minister ever stops to consider the possibility that the problem with the NHS might not be that its budget, which swells year on year, is too small, but that no amount of money could ever bring reality into line with people’s sky-high ideals. Until Labour and the Tories face up to this, little will change for the better.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It is at this point in most conversations that people assume that I am anti-NHS, and support some sort of American-style insurance system. This is incorrect; as I said earlier, there is a place for the state in healthcare. As for the US, even describing healthcare there as a “system” would be overly charitable. Its disorganised and overlapping mandates fail to constrain costs, and for all the libertarian claims that Americans will never accept “socialised medicine”, the US Federal Government spends about twice as much of its budget on healthcare as most European countries. In so many respects, America fails to realise its small government aspirations. Some in Britain support a transition towards the more comprehensive insurance-based systems found in France and Germany. These systems do have better controls on costs, but I suspect that they would also come with their own unintended consequences. People don’t like seeing a doctor, even when they aren’t asked to reach for their insurance papers afterwards. Under these circumstances, people may avoid going to see their GP, thus waiting for minor health issues to spiral out of control. There is no way of knowing how Britain, where the concept of healthcare free at the point of use is so ingrained, would fare with an insurance system, and people on the right of politics don’t spend enough time considering the potential flaws of alternative systems.&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, the fact that there is no debate over fundamental reforms to the NHS is a travesty. In an era where people are getting older, fatter, and more numerous, the expectation that every service the NHS provides can be free, from top to bottom, is unsustainable. There must be a middle-ground between expecting to pay for nothing, and turning to insurance to cover nearly everything. I fear that if the state does not take the issue of reform seriously, it will have reform imposed upon it by a total breakdown of the system. The current predicament should serve as a warning to the government that a breakdown might not be far away.&amp;nbsp; If we want to avoid such a crisis or insurance-style reform, we, the British people, must reform our own attitude towards the health service. When the NHS is required to do so much, not everything it does can be free. The next time you have to pay for a prescription, or a dental appointment, realise that somebody else less fortunate than you isn’t paying for their chemotherapy as a result. Coughing up would do more for the NHS than clapping ever could.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beat The Casinos</title><link href="/Beat-The-Casinos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beat The Casinos" /><published>2021-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Beat-The-Casinos</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Beat-The-Casinos">&lt;p&gt;Being a huge &lt;em&gt;Hangover&lt;/em&gt; fan, there is something that I have always wanted to do in my life and that is, gambling all night at a casino in Las Vegas for once. Within the walls of the 51 licensed casinos of the Las Vegas Strip, there are 2,879 gaming tables collectively bringing in $3.1 billion in revenue annually, or over a million dollars in each table. In addition, there are some 38,864 slot machines bringing in another $3.4 billion dollars. A single large Las Vegas casino, like the Bellagio, makes more than some small countries, annually.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because the casino business model is pretty much bulletproof. Overall, the odds are always in the casino’s favour. If this weren’t true, casinos would fail - so these floors just print money. MGM International, for example, one of the world’s largest multinational gaming companies, has about 2.5 million square feet of casino floor worldwide meaning it makes, on average, $1,038 per square foot. With the money their casinos bring in, they could line every inch of every foot of their casino floor worldwide with a brand-new iPad and still have money left over. This is all to say, casinos make a lot of money, but to do so, they need a lot more money coming through their doors. You see, the casino business model all revolves around risk. With every game they have, the odds are in their favour, but doesn’t mean the house will always win. Their advantage varies from game to game - in Roulette, it is about 5.25%, in Poker, it is about 3.35%, and in Blackjack, it is about 0.5%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, given how tight these margins are, there’s natural variability, so casinos can come out behind or lose money on a given table on a given night but overall, with enough tables and enough nights, they average out these odds. However, in order to do so, they need an immense amount of money running through their casinos. Blackjack, for example, is one of the games with the lowest house edge so if the casino wants to earn $1 billion in a given year from the game, they would need $200 billion changing hands within their doors each year. That’s pretty much the entire GDP of New Zealand. When you have such a rapid throughput of money, very slight changes in the odds can make a huge variation in the gaming company’s earnings. If, for example, the house edge in the Blackjack changed from 0.5% to 0.4%, they would lose $200 million, assuming $200 billion in annual play. This is why making sure these odds stay in their favour is so important to the casinos. It could quite literally be the difference between millions of dollars in profit or filing for bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite what the movie culture might portray, a casino’s biggest problem is not robbers or hackers or even technically cheaters, because each of those is relatively easy to prevent and detect. Rather, their biggest problem is people who are able to turn the odds in their favour without robbing, hacking or even cheating. Cheating in a casino is generally illegal, however, it’s possible for a player to consistently win without cheating. The best-known example of this is card counting, a type of advantage play used in the Blackjack family of games which is not illegal and in some cases is even legally protected. This play technique takes the basic principles of the game of Blackjack and uses them against the casino, and these principles are fairly simple.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start a game, each player bets an amount of money and then six decks of cards are shuffled together to form what’s called the Shoe. Each player is dealt two cards face-up while the dealer gets one face-up and one face-down card. The goal for all the participants is simple, it’s to get their cards to total as close to 21 without going above 21. Starting from the left, each player will either decide to stick with the total they have or to take another card to add to it. Of course, the player doesn’t know what the next card will be worth in between one to 11, so it’s a gamble on whether it’ll make the total go over 21 – in which case their bet is lost.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The higher the original sum, the riskier it is to take another card but there is in fact a mathematically optimal choice for every scenario called the 'basic strategy'. Once every player is done taking cards, the dealer reveals the face-down card and automatically if their total is below 17, they take additional cards until it isn’t over 17. If it's 17 or higher, they leave it as it is. There are then 3 scenarios. If the dealer goes above 21, all players’ bets are doubled, as long as they didn’t go above 21 first. If the player’s total is higher than the dealer’s then the player's bet is doubled, however, if the player's total is lower, they lose their bet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this explanation skipped over plenty of smaller rules and less likely edge-cases, but it is these fundamental elements of game-play that tie into why card counting works. Now, without getting too much into the math, on average, in Blackjack, higher value cards benefit the player, while the lower value cards benefit the dealers. While the explanation for the higher cards is more complex, lower card benefit is based on the fact that the dealer is required to take additional cards when their total is less than 17 and so a greater density of lower cards makes it less likely that they will go over 21 – in which case each player’s bet is doubled. Therefore, if you know that a bunch of low cards are coming, you know that the odds are against you and so you should reduce your bet or not play but the question is how do you know what’s coming in a randomly shuffled deck. Well, you perform the process of elimination or even more simply you count the cards you see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are hundreds of different forms of card counting that work in hundreds of different ways, but all are more or less based on what’s known as the 'Hi-Lo' system. With this, each card is assigned a value. Cards ranging from two to six are assigned 'one', cards from seven to nine are assigned 'zero', and card 10 and ace and all the face cards are assigned 'minus one'. This is based on the fact that every time a high-value card is dealt there are fewer of them left in the deck, which means the odds get worse for the player considering that high-value cards are better for them and vice versa. With every card a player sees, they add up its assigned value. So, if there are three players and they are dealt the cards in &lt;em&gt;figure 1&lt;/em&gt;, the running count would be two.&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/cardlayouteuan.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 1: Cards dealt to three players and their running count - Euan Decourt, 23/01/2020&lt;/div&gt;As the play goes on and they get deeper into the deck, the running count will generally increase in one direction or the other giving the player more confidence on where the odds stand. So, for example, if the running count equals 20, the player would know that the odds are greatly in their favour and therefore that they should bet big on the next round as they have a greater than 50% chance of winning. This is how people can reliably make money in Blackjack. If a player changes their bet by a factor of 15 depending on the odds, and the dealer waits until they’re through five of the six decks before shuffling, a player, following a perfect Blackjack strategy, could earn an advantage of about 1.182% over the house. That means that if assuming a table completes a round of play every minute and an average bet is around $200, a card counter could profit on average about $110 an hour - enough that some people can and do make a living by sitting at Blackjack tables, counting cards. However, how simple and reliable this advantage play method is, casinos go to great lengths to stop it which is very, very difficult. That’s because the advantage is all in the mind—there’s no good way to fully prove that a person is counting cards. Sometimes, people are just lucky and it is quite a bad look for casinos to kick people out just because they are winning. That’s why instead of trying to prove it, most casinos implement rules to try and stop card counting from working as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that, generally, the running count will get further into positive or negative the further into the game one goes because the card counter would have seen more cards that are now in the discard pile, and therefore cannot be dealt. While a few rounds in the running count might be in the single digits positive or negative, further on, it will get into the double digits which gives the counter great confidence whether they should bet big or not. It is towards the end of the Shoes, when card counters really make their money, so to make it less profitable, casinos can just have their dealers shuffle earlier on. If they shuffle 4 decks deep into a six-deck show rather than five, that decreases the player’s advantage from 1.182 to just 0.568%. However, shuffling earlier and more often also cuts into the casino’s profits because, anytime the dealer is shuffling the non-advantaged players aren’t playing and losing money, which is how the casino makes its money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option for casinos is to increase the number of decks they shuffle together to make a show. Back before card-counting first became a widespread issue for casinos, they would play Blackjack with just a single deck of cards but if they did this today, it would only be a matter of minutes before a card counter would have high confidence about the odds. Therefore, they typically now play with six decks shuffled together, which increases the time it takes to get to high confidence and since time is money for a card counter, this decreases their profits. Some casinos take this a step further by using a continuous shuffling machine. With no discard piles, there is no increase or decrease in the beneficial cards in the shoe, so card counting is completely ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these methods deal with stopping or reducing a player’s ability to actually know what the odds are at a given moment, the other method involves stopping a player’s ability to respond to this knowledge by changing the size of their bets. Essentially, if a dealer or a pit boss suspects someone might be counting cards, they’ll change the rules on them and require flat betting which means making a player choose one bet size for all rounds and not allowing them to change the bet in future rounds when the count is in their favour. However, that poses the question, how do you spot a card counter? Well, one of the signs is if a player changes their bet from 100 to 1000 right before a series of wins or as the Shoe is close to finish, that’s a good sign that they know what the odds are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end, the casinos aren’t much affected by card counters as they make a very small proportion of all the players and they consider it as a cost of running the business. Till this time these games continue to exist, players will always try to find new ways to shift the odds in their favour and this causes a never-ending cycle, but what we must know is that if we use basic math we can outwit some of these casinos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about Blackjack, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blackjackapprenticeship.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Being a huge Hangover fan, there is something that I have always wanted to do in my life and that is, gambling all night at a casino in Las Vegas for once. Within the walls of the 51 licensed casinos of the Las Vegas Strip, there are 2,879 gaming tables collectively bringing in $3.1 billion in revenue annually, or over a million dollars in each table. In addition, there are some 38,864 slot machines bringing in another $3.4 billion dollars. A single large Las Vegas casino, like the Bellagio, makes more than some small countries, annually.&amp;nbsp; This is because the casino business model is pretty much bulletproof. Overall, the odds are always in the casino’s favour. If this weren’t true, casinos would fail - so these floors just print money. MGM International, for example, one of the world’s largest multinational gaming companies, has about 2.5 million square feet of casino floor worldwide meaning it makes, on average, $1,038 per square foot. With the money their casinos bring in, they could line every inch of every foot of their casino floor worldwide with a brand-new iPad and still have money left over. This is all to say, casinos make a lot of money, but to do so, they need a lot more money coming through their doors. You see, the casino business model all revolves around risk. With every game they have, the odds are in their favour, but doesn’t mean the house will always win. Their advantage varies from game to game - in Roulette, it is about 5.25%, in Poker, it is about 3.35%, and in Blackjack, it is about 0.5%.&amp;nbsp; Of course, given how tight these margins are, there’s natural variability, so casinos can come out behind or lose money on a given table on a given night but overall, with enough tables and enough nights, they average out these odds. However, in order to do so, they need an immense amount of money running through their casinos. Blackjack, for example, is one of the games with the lowest house edge so if the casino wants to earn $1 billion in a given year from the game, they would need $200 billion changing hands within their doors each year. That’s pretty much the entire GDP of New Zealand. When you have such a rapid throughput of money, very slight changes in the odds can make a huge variation in the gaming company’s earnings. If, for example, the house edge in the Blackjack changed from 0.5% to 0.4%, they would lose $200 million, assuming $200 billion in annual play. This is why making sure these odds stay in their favour is so important to the casinos. It could quite literally be the difference between millions of dollars in profit or filing for bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; Despite what the movie culture might portray, a casino’s biggest problem is not robbers or hackers or even technically cheaters, because each of those is relatively easy to prevent and detect. Rather, their biggest problem is people who are able to turn the odds in their favour without robbing, hacking or even cheating. Cheating in a casino is generally illegal, however, it’s possible for a player to consistently win without cheating. The best-known example of this is card counting, a type of advantage play used in the Blackjack family of games which is not illegal and in some cases is even legally protected. This play technique takes the basic principles of the game of Blackjack and uses them against the casino, and these principles are fairly simple.&amp;nbsp; To start a game, each player bets an amount of money and then six decks of cards are shuffled together to form what’s called the Shoe. Each player is dealt two cards face-up while the dealer gets one face-up and one face-down card. The goal for all the participants is simple, it’s to get their cards to total as close to 21 without going above 21. Starting from the left, each player will either decide to stick with the total they have or to take another card to add to it. Of course, the player doesn’t know what the next card will be worth in between one to 11, so it’s a gamble on whether it’ll make the total go over 21 – in which case their bet is lost.&amp;nbsp; The higher the original sum, the riskier it is to take another card but there is in fact a mathematically optimal choice for every scenario called the 'basic strategy'. Once every player is done taking cards, the dealer reveals the face-down card and automatically if their total is below 17, they take additional cards until it isn’t over 17. If it's 17 or higher, they leave it as it is. There are then 3 scenarios. If the dealer goes above 21, all players’ bets are doubled, as long as they didn’t go above 21 first. If the player’s total is higher than the dealer’s then the player's bet is doubled, however, if the player's total is lower, they lose their bet.&amp;nbsp; Of course, this explanation skipped over plenty of smaller rules and less likely edge-cases, but it is these fundamental elements of game-play that tie into why card counting works. Now, without getting too much into the math, on average, in Blackjack, higher value cards benefit the player, while the lower value cards benefit the dealers. While the explanation for the higher cards is more complex, lower card benefit is based on the fact that the dealer is required to take additional cards when their total is less than 17 and so a greater density of lower cards makes it less likely that they will go over 21 – in which case each player’s bet is doubled. Therefore, if you know that a bunch of low cards are coming, you know that the odds are against you and so you should reduce your bet or not play but the question is how do you know what’s coming in a randomly shuffled deck. Well, you perform the process of elimination or even more simply you count the cards you see. There are hundreds of different forms of card counting that work in hundreds of different ways, but all are more or less based on what’s known as the 'Hi-Lo' system. With this, each card is assigned a value. Cards ranging from two to six are assigned 'one', cards from seven to nine are assigned 'zero', and card 10 and ace and all the face cards are assigned 'minus one'. This is based on the fact that every time a high-value card is dealt there are fewer of them left in the deck, which means the odds get worse for the player considering that high-value cards are better for them and vice versa. With every card a player sees, they add up its assigned value. So, if there are three players and they are dealt the cards in figure 1, the running count would be two.Figure 1: Cards dealt to three players and their running count - Euan Decourt, 23/01/2020As the play goes on and they get deeper into the deck, the running count will generally increase in one direction or the other giving the player more confidence on where the odds stand. So, for example, if the running count equals 20, the player would know that the odds are greatly in their favour and therefore that they should bet big on the next round as they have a greater than 50% chance of winning. This is how people can reliably make money in Blackjack. If a player changes their bet by a factor of 15 depending on the odds, and the dealer waits until they’re through five of the six decks before shuffling, a player, following a perfect Blackjack strategy, could earn an advantage of about 1.182% over the house. That means that if assuming a table completes a round of play every minute and an average bet is around $200, a card counter could profit on average about $110 an hour - enough that some people can and do make a living by sitting at Blackjack tables, counting cards. However, how simple and reliable this advantage play method is, casinos go to great lengths to stop it which is very, very difficult. That’s because the advantage is all in the mind—there’s no good way to fully prove that a person is counting cards. Sometimes, people are just lucky and it is quite a bad look for casinos to kick people out just because they are winning. That’s why instead of trying to prove it, most casinos implement rules to try and stop card counting from working as well.&amp;nbsp; Remember that, generally, the running count will get further into positive or negative the further into the game one goes because the card counter would have seen more cards that are now in the discard pile, and therefore cannot be dealt. While a few rounds in the running count might be in the single digits positive or negative, further on, it will get into the double digits which gives the counter great confidence whether they should bet big or not. It is towards the end of the Shoes, when card counters really make their money, so to make it less profitable, casinos can just have their dealers shuffle earlier on. If they shuffle 4 decks deep into a six-deck show rather than five, that decreases the player’s advantage from 1.182 to just 0.568%. However, shuffling earlier and more often also cuts into the casino’s profits because, anytime the dealer is shuffling the non-advantaged players aren’t playing and losing money, which is how the casino makes its money. Another option for casinos is to increase the number of decks they shuffle together to make a show. Back before card-counting first became a widespread issue for casinos, they would play Blackjack with just a single deck of cards but if they did this today, it would only be a matter of minutes before a card counter would have high confidence about the odds. Therefore, they typically now play with six decks shuffled together, which increases the time it takes to get to high confidence and since time is money for a card counter, this decreases their profits. Some casinos take this a step further by using a continuous shuffling machine. With no discard piles, there is no increase or decrease in the beneficial cards in the shoe, so card counting is completely ineffective. While these methods deal with stopping or reducing a player’s ability to actually know what the odds are at a given moment, the other method involves stopping a player’s ability to respond to this knowledge by changing the size of their bets. Essentially, if a dealer or a pit boss suspects someone might be counting cards, they’ll change the rules on them and require flat betting which means making a player choose one bet size for all rounds and not allowing them to change the bet in future rounds when the count is in their favour. However, that poses the question, how do you spot a card counter? Well, one of the signs is if a player changes their bet from 100 to 1000 right before a series of wins or as the Shoe is close to finish, that’s a good sign that they know what the odds are. At the end, the casinos aren’t much affected by card counters as they make a very small proportion of all the players and they consider it as a cost of running the business. Till this time these games continue to exist, players will always try to find new ways to shift the odds in their favour and this causes a never-ending cycle, but what we must know is that if we use basic math we can outwit some of these casinos. If you want to learn more about Blackjack, click here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Pandemic of Inequality</title><link href="/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pandemic of Inequality" /><published>2021-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality">&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus outbreak has plunged the entire globe into a deep ‘shock’ with simultaneous disruptions to both the demand and supply side in a highly interdependent and interconnected world economy. The increased incidence of infections has led to a large reduction in labour supply and the initial period of lockdowns have led to a loss of income for several households. Yet, there has been one section of people that have been worst hit by the pandemic - ‘the poor’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a general view that crises and pandemics like this often lead to the redistribution of resources among the masses, as the spread of the virus sees no caste, class and gender differences. However, this couldn’t be further away from reality. The COVID-19 has had a uniform impact on the entire world when it comes to the possibilities of being infected, but the social and economic impacts have been the most on the vulnerable sections of the society. In a recent study by the World Bank, “&lt;em&gt;Global extreme poverty is expected to rise in 2020 for the first time in over 20 years. The COVID-19 pandemic is estimated to push an additional 88 million to 115 million people into extreme poverty this year, with the total rising to as many as 150 million by 2021.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is thus an attempt to shed light on how the pandemic transformed into a pandemic of inequality using various arguments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past Experiences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A comparative analysis of the novel coronavirus and other past epidemics is often made to understand the relationship between the pandemics and inequalities caused across countries. The first example that comes into the mind is that of the 14th century Black Death which suggested that pandemics seem to reduce inequality in the long run. According to various studies conducted, the Black Death re-balanced the population, and available resources led to a useful reorganisation of agrarian production and triggered significant increases in real wages across the European continent. But the pandemics in recent history seem to have defied this theory. If recent episodes of pandemics are included, ranging from plagues to cholera pandemic &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, they fail to prove the substantial reduction in inequality levels. Instead, the levels have been observed to be increasing substantially, coinciding with the occurrence of these events. Therefore the impact of Black Death turns out to be an ‘exception’ in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Uneven Playing Field&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we begin analysing this relationship between a pandemic and inequality, have a look at the rising income trend in the figure given below and keep it in mind. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/#:~:text=The%20world%20population%20increased%20from,to%201.05%25%20per%20year%20today.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldbank1.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 1. Source: World Bank &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, economic inequality refers to the unequal distribution of income and opportunity between different groups in society. According to Tony Atkinson, a renowned British economist, “&lt;em&gt;Inequality of outcome among today’s generation is the source of the unfair advantage received by the next generation. If we are concerned about equality of opportunity tomorrow, we need to be concerned about inequality of outcome today.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s world, inequality is a pressing concern transforming into a situation of emergency. The figure below visualises the inequality in living conditions between the world’s best-off and worst-off countries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/#:~:text=The%20world%20population%20increased%20from,to%201.05%25%20per%20year%20today.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldbank2.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 2. Source: World Bank&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Income and wealth inequality have particularly witnessed an upward trend in all major advanced economies while for the emerging ones, the income distribution trends have been mixed but most of them are experiencing an upward trend too, led by major emerging economies such as China and India. In this scenario, the increase in inequality due to the current pandemic is quite worrisome.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a study conducted Oxfam, a non-profit operating across the world, it is estimated that there are as much as 121 million more people on the brink of starvation today due to mass unemployment, disruption to food production and supplies. “&lt;em&gt;As many as 12,000 people could die every day from COVID-linked hunger&lt;/em&gt;,” stated Oxfam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the wake of these figures, it becomes imperative to understand the two-way relationship between pandemics and inequality, i.e. inequality is not just an impact of the pandemic, it is the cause of the outbreak itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no doubt that it is the extreme socio-economic inequalities and the lack of access to public healthcare facilities that have led to stark ill-proportioned costs being borne by these downtrodden individuals, both in terms of infection incidences as well as the economic well-being. But how exactly does this play out?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, the countries facing a sustained rise in population levels also experience an increasing population density, which therefore leads to a rise in the ability of the disease to reproduce and spread. At the same time, due to an increase in the labour force, the wages are driven down due to an excess supply of labour. On the other hand, the richer and affluent sections of the society become richer and richer, on account of declining labour wages. These sections are generally the ones having major wealth in the form of capital holdings.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of the stark differences in the income levels, the poor people face a major problem of poverty and undernutrition, the cause of which can be broken down into three aspects: Parental Resources (low awareness and education among the poor, high morbidity), Household Resources (income levels of households) and Community Resources (unavailability of safe drinking water and sanitation). This leads to higher susceptibility to infections making them less capable to fight the pathogens. And when it comes to being tested positive for the virus, these individuals are likely to face higher mortality due to lack of access to public health services. Apart from this, we also observe large scale migration of poor from rural to urban areas in search of employment opportunities, which leads to increased population density in cities and makes them breeding ground for diseases again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly, the outbreak of novel coronavirus has led to an emergence of the ‘new normal’- work from home (WFH), since it is the only option to continue working and minimising the risk of virus exposure. Even though recent studies have shown an increase in average labour incomes because of this positive shift to work from home, the potential benefit will be highly asymmetrical,&amp;nbsp; favouring highly-educated and high-paid employees. Also, there are numerous jobs which cannot come under the ambit of this new normal, and individuals in these sectors have been rendered unemployed, worsening the income distribution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IMF, in its recent study, has analysed the aggregate decrease in income levels using its GDP growth projections for 2020. It has been found that the estimated effect of COVID-19 will be larger than that caused by the past pandemics and that gains achieved since the global financial crisis (2008) might be reversed. The analysis shows that the average &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gini_coefficient&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gini coefficient&lt;/a&gt; for emerging markets and developing economies will rise to 42.7, which is comparable to the level in 2008. The impact would be larger for low-income developing countries despite slower progress since 2008. The pandemic could also possibly reduce welfare by about 8% in emerging economies and developing nations with more than 50% change coming from the increase in inequality due to WFH feasibility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/WEO#:~:text=Description%3A%20Global%20growth%20is%20projected,Economic%20Outlook%20(WEO)%20forecast.&amp;amp;text=In%202021%20global%20growth%20is,19%20projections%20of%20January%202020.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldecon1.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 2. Source: World Bank&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems don’t end here. When the vaccines for the virus come out, the market mechanism comes into play to dictate the distribution over and within the countries. The poor countries are very likely to be crowded out of the markets as they receive the vaccines at the very end, as these countries are plagued with poor health infrastructure. Within countries, the most vulnerable sections will find themselves unable to access the necessary medical aid. Even if in the end they are able to administer the vaccine, the damage would have been done. The pathogens might have been rendered ineffective. And therefore, the future generation is bound to face the ripples of the pandemic too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way the generation is doomed is the asymmetries in access to health and education services. With the mode of teaching being shifted online, children belonging to poor households face an amplified barrier to schooling and education.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the social inequalities will create ‘avenues for development of unrest and discontentment among the people’ which in the long run leads to political upheavals and the rise of populist leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the pandemic proves to be perilous to the society in a multitude of ways that go over and above health risks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned impact is on a global level. Now let’s analyse the impact of the pandemic so far on India, to understand how it is particularly bad.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August 2020, Mukesh Ambani became the 4th richest person in the world. On the same day, a man reportedly committed suicide and killed his family because of job loss induced by the pandemic. The above case exactly represents the tale of two Indias and how badly this pandemic has affected the already high inequality in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last 20 years, the increase in inequality has been the highest in India except Russia. As the rich get richer even amidst a pandemic, nearly 400 million workers are at the cusp of falling into abject poverty, as reported by the International Labour Organisation (ILO).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is often said that epidemics are true mirrors of society, and the COVID-19 outbreak has effectively mirrored the broken public healthcare system in India. In India, there exists significant inter-state and intra-state disparities. When it comes to distribution of doctors in urban and rural areas, there is a huge skewness observable. In terms of availability of hospital beds, states like Bihar are well below the national average of 0.55 beds in the public sector per 1,000 population while others like West Bengal (2.25 beds/1000) and Sikkim (2.34 beds/1000) have considerably more. The pandemic hit the country at a time when the country was facing an economic slowdown, and the public health crisis of this magnitude is going to have a further negative impact on the Indian economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of inequality is with respect to gender. With many companies enforcing strict social distancing guidelines and WFH policy, women even with full-time paid employment are facing reduced efficiency because of the additional and disproportionate share of the workload. Additionally, the concerns of rising domestic violence and sexual abuse paints a grim picture of state of women currently.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the line with the foregoing discussion, the first and foremost task is to secure the livelihoods of the most vulnerable sections of the society. The empowerment and growth of the global community is linked to the socio-economic well-being of each individual. While the impact of the pandemic can never be ascertained 100%, the policy measure taken today will be responsible for the outcomes for the future generations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rajsi Sah</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The coronavirus outbreak has plunged the entire globe into a deep ‘shock’ with simultaneous disruptions to both the demand and supply side in a highly interdependent and interconnected world economy. The increased incidence of infections has led to a large reduction in labour supply and the initial period of lockdowns have led to a loss of income for several households. Yet, there has been one section of people that have been worst hit by the pandemic - ‘the poor’.&amp;nbsp; It is a general view that crises and pandemics like this often lead to the redistribution of resources among the masses, as the spread of the virus sees no caste, class and gender differences. However, this couldn’t be further away from reality. The COVID-19 has had a uniform impact on the entire world when it comes to the possibilities of being infected, but the social and economic impacts have been the most on the vulnerable sections of the society. In a recent study by the World Bank, “Global extreme poverty is expected to rise in 2020 for the first time in over 20 years. The COVID-19 pandemic is estimated to push an additional 88 million to 115 million people into extreme poverty this year, with the total rising to as many as 150 million by 2021.” The article is thus an attempt to shed light on how the pandemic transformed into a pandemic of inequality using various arguments.&amp;nbsp; Past Experiences A comparative analysis of the novel coronavirus and other past epidemics is often made to understand the relationship between the pandemics and inequalities caused across countries. The first example that comes into the mind is that of the 14th century Black Death which suggested that pandemics seem to reduce inequality in the long run. According to various studies conducted, the Black Death re-balanced the population, and available resources led to a useful reorganisation of agrarian production and triggered significant increases in real wages across the European continent. But the pandemics in recent history seem to have defied this theory. If recent episodes of pandemics are included, ranging from plagues to cholera pandemic et al, they fail to prove the substantial reduction in inequality levels. Instead, the levels have been observed to be increasing substantially, coinciding with the occurrence of these events. Therefore the impact of Black Death turns out to be an ‘exception’ in this case. An Uneven Playing Field Before we begin analysing this relationship between a pandemic and inequality, have a look at the rising income trend in the figure given below and keep it in mind. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Figure 1. Source: World Bank Fundamentally, economic inequality refers to the unequal distribution of income and opportunity between different groups in society. According to Tony Atkinson, a renowned British economist, “Inequality of outcome among today’s generation is the source of the unfair advantage received by the next generation. If we are concerned about equality of opportunity tomorrow, we need to be concerned about inequality of outcome today.” In today’s world, inequality is a pressing concern transforming into a situation of emergency. The figure below visualises the inequality in living conditions between the world’s best-off and worst-off countries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Figure 2. Source: World Bank&amp;nbsp; Income and wealth inequality have particularly witnessed an upward trend in all major advanced economies while for the emerging ones, the income distribution trends have been mixed but most of them are experiencing an upward trend too, led by major emerging economies such as China and India. In this scenario, the increase in inequality due to the current pandemic is quite worrisome.&amp;nbsp; In a study conducted Oxfam, a non-profit operating across the world, it is estimated that there are as much as 121 million more people on the brink of starvation today due to mass unemployment, disruption to food production and supplies. “As many as 12,000 people could die every day from COVID-linked hunger,” stated Oxfam. In the wake of these figures, it becomes imperative to understand the two-way relationship between pandemics and inequality, i.e. inequality is not just an impact of the pandemic, it is the cause of the outbreak itself.&amp;nbsp; It is no doubt that it is the extreme socio-economic inequalities and the lack of access to public healthcare facilities that have led to stark ill-proportioned costs being borne by these downtrodden individuals, both in terms of infection incidences as well as the economic well-being. But how exactly does this play out?&amp;nbsp; To begin with, the countries facing a sustained rise in population levels also experience an increasing population density, which therefore leads to a rise in the ability of the disease to reproduce and spread. At the same time, due to an increase in the labour force, the wages are driven down due to an excess supply of labour. On the other hand, the richer and affluent sections of the society become richer and richer, on account of declining labour wages. These sections are generally the ones having major wealth in the form of capital holdings.&amp;nbsp; As a result of the stark differences in the income levels, the poor people face a major problem of poverty and undernutrition, the cause of which can be broken down into three aspects: Parental Resources (low awareness and education among the poor, high morbidity), Household Resources (income levels of households) and Community Resources (unavailability of safe drinking water and sanitation). This leads to higher susceptibility to infections making them less capable to fight the pathogens. And when it comes to being tested positive for the virus, these individuals are likely to face higher mortality due to lack of access to public health services. Apart from this, we also observe large scale migration of poor from rural to urban areas in search of employment opportunities, which leads to increased population density in cities and makes them breeding ground for diseases again.&amp;nbsp; Particularly, the outbreak of novel coronavirus has led to an emergence of the ‘new normal’- work from home (WFH), since it is the only option to continue working and minimising the risk of virus exposure. Even though recent studies have shown an increase in average labour incomes because of this positive shift to work from home, the potential benefit will be highly asymmetrical,&amp;nbsp; favouring highly-educated and high-paid employees. Also, there are numerous jobs which cannot come under the ambit of this new normal, and individuals in these sectors have been rendered unemployed, worsening the income distribution.&amp;nbsp; The IMF, in its recent study, has analysed the aggregate decrease in income levels using its GDP growth projections for 2020. It has been found that the estimated effect of COVID-19 will be larger than that caused by the past pandemics and that gains achieved since the global financial crisis (2008) might be reversed. The analysis shows that the average Gini coefficient for emerging markets and developing economies will rise to 42.7, which is comparable to the level in 2008. The impact would be larger for low-income developing countries despite slower progress since 2008. The pandemic could also possibly reduce welfare by about 8% in emerging economies and developing nations with more than 50% change coming from the increase in inequality due to WFH feasibility.&amp;nbsp; Figure 2. Source: World Bank The problems don’t end here. When the vaccines for the virus come out, the market mechanism comes into play to dictate the distribution over and within the countries. The poor countries are very likely to be crowded out of the markets as they receive the vaccines at the very end, as these countries are plagued with poor health infrastructure. Within countries, the most vulnerable sections will find themselves unable to access the necessary medical aid. Even if in the end they are able to administer the vaccine, the damage would have been done. The pathogens might have been rendered ineffective. And therefore, the future generation is bound to face the ripples of the pandemic too.&amp;nbsp; Another way the generation is doomed is the asymmetries in access to health and education services. With the mode of teaching being shifted online, children belonging to poor households face an amplified barrier to schooling and education.&amp;nbsp; And lastly, the social inequalities will create ‘avenues for development of unrest and discontentment among the people’ which in the long run leads to political upheavals and the rise of populist leaders.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the pandemic proves to be perilous to the society in a multitude of ways that go over and above health risks.&amp;nbsp; The above-mentioned impact is on a global level. Now let’s analyse the impact of the pandemic so far on India, to understand how it is particularly bad.&amp;nbsp; In August 2020, Mukesh Ambani became the 4th richest person in the world. On the same day, a man reportedly committed suicide and killed his family because of job loss induced by the pandemic. The above case exactly represents the tale of two Indias and how badly this pandemic has affected the already high inequality in the country.&amp;nbsp; In the last 20 years, the increase in inequality has been the highest in India except Russia. As the rich get richer even amidst a pandemic, nearly 400 million workers are at the cusp of falling into abject poverty, as reported by the International Labour Organisation (ILO). It is often said that epidemics are true mirrors of society, and the COVID-19 outbreak has effectively mirrored the broken public healthcare system in India. In India, there exists significant inter-state and intra-state disparities. When it comes to distribution of doctors in urban and rural areas, there is a huge skewness observable. In terms of availability of hospital beds, states like Bihar are well below the national average of 0.55 beds in the public sector per 1,000 population while others like West Bengal (2.25 beds/1000) and Sikkim (2.34 beds/1000) have considerably more. The pandemic hit the country at a time when the country was facing an economic slowdown, and the public health crisis of this magnitude is going to have a further negative impact on the Indian economy.&amp;nbsp; Another aspect of inequality is with respect to gender. With many companies enforcing strict social distancing guidelines and WFH policy, women even with full-time paid employment are facing reduced efficiency because of the additional and disproportionate share of the workload. Additionally, the concerns of rising domestic violence and sexual abuse paints a grim picture of state of women currently.&amp;nbsp; In the line with the foregoing discussion, the first and foremost task is to secure the livelihoods of the most vulnerable sections of the society. The empowerment and growth of the global community is linked to the socio-economic well-being of each individual. While the impact of the pandemic can never be ascertained 100%, the policy measure taken today will be responsible for the outcomes for the future generations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Love Letter to Fellow Scapegoats</title><link href="/A-Love-Letter-to-Fellow-Scapegoats" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Love Letter to Fellow Scapegoats" /><published>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Love-Letter-to-Fellow-Scapegoats</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Love-Letter-to-Fellow-Scapegoats">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This is a love letter, let me begin with that. It's Christmas today, and no, I don’t have a glass of wine on me, nor do I have a roaring fireplace beside me. I’m definitely not surrounded by a loved one’s arms, and I most definitely don’t have a black Persian cat with heterochromia fast asleep on my lap. What I’m trying to say here is, Santa put me in the naughty-people list and nothing I wanted has been afforded to me. Not even the Post-Grad admission I had bribed (may I add, heavily) God for. You must wonder why am I writing words of amore when not a lot of what I wanted has been given to me. Or is that wishful thinking on my part?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;I wonder in what words I could explain that I might be grateful for all of my turmoil-induced-emotions. I wonder if my fervour for these emotions has anything to do with the mindless novelty of them, or perhaps, it is due to their unrestricted nature. I’m not a Godless person, but neither am I someone who completely believes in God’s idealistic characters. Yet, in recent times, I’ve found charm in begging, bribing and accepting the Higher Presence. With not one thing in my hand, I enjoy the idea of having left the utter discourse of my life on the One higher-up. I may not have what I want, not even what I possibly deserve, but who’s to blame? Not me. I wish I were one of those who felt ‘touched’ by The Presence, or the ones who believe only the good is destined, and maybe I’m paving a path towards that, but I’m not there, yet (most likely, I never will be). But, I must accept, I’ve felt much better about coursing the blame through someone else. There’s less to it than devotion and yet, it’s pristine enough to maybe be beyond it. It may be called a defence mechanism, or maybe it’s simply just a change of tact, a diversion, if you will. Either way, it has saved me quite a lot of tears and several hours of self-loathing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;If one were to search ‘God is a micromanager?’, the likeness of a treasure trove may be found. My favourite answers (very obviously) belong to Quora. Jim Whitehead, Former Subatomic whisperer answered ‘&lt;em&gt;No we do!&lt;/em&gt;’ and, I’m here for it, his answer is eloquent and metaphorical and everything I wanted from a Quora answer. However, after much deliberation, I decided to forego further research, mostly because of Jim, and partially because I wasn’t in the mood to give up on the blame game, yet. The feeling of guilt I tried not to feel, or even the remorse, I suppose, caught up to me. The &lt;em&gt;7 Laws of Magical Thinking&lt;/em&gt; by Matthew Hutson gives a purview into why we do what we do - it speaks quite a lot about God’s Plan (not the fun Drake kind) and about negative agency bias (my favourite kind of bias). What it suggests is that acts of consequence, particularly unfavourable consequence, arouse feelings of divine authorship. The negative agency bias also results from the fact that we like to take credit for positive outcomes and blame failures on someone else. But I’ve spoken about that before, many times, if I recall correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I would say I was simply looking for a scapegoat, one who doesn’t retort back. They don’t unfollow you, or tweet you back, or worse, block you. Or do they? Ah, I’ll try not to give myself a scare. I’m sure you’re screaming at me to just take responsibility, fess up and get on with the ‘real’ world. Believe me, Sir Louis Cohen, off-of-Quora’s answer, “&lt;em&gt;The only gods are fictional characters in fairy tales. You’re in charge so don’t try to pass the buck&lt;/em&gt;” really tried to do a number on me. But it’s Christmas, in the middle of a pandemic with new mutant versions popping out each day, and don’t you remember? My cat is not here for support. And like I said, this is a love letter, to fellow scapegoats, whose presence are sometimes questioned, always appreciated and very well monetised. If this pity party of mine has managed to affront you, I heartily apologise, I’m open to new learnings (mostly, because I’m Uni-less at the moment) and will like, follow and subscribe if you put a good word for me to the One Above. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><summary type="html">This is a love letter, let me begin with that. It's Christmas today, and no, I don’t have a glass of wine on me, nor do I have a roaring fireplace beside me. I’m definitely not surrounded by a loved one’s arms, and I most definitely don’t have a black Persian cat with heterochromia fast asleep on my lap. What I’m trying to say here is, Santa put me in the naughty-people list and nothing I wanted has been afforded to me. Not even the Post-Grad admission I had bribed (may I add, heavily) God for. You must wonder why am I writing words of amore when not a lot of what I wanted has been given to me. Or is that wishful thinking on my part? I wonder in what words I could explain that I might be grateful for all of my turmoil-induced-emotions. I wonder if my fervour for these emotions has anything to do with the mindless novelty of them, or perhaps, it is due to their unrestricted nature. I’m not a Godless person, but neither am I someone who completely believes in God’s idealistic characters. Yet, in recent times, I’ve found charm in begging, bribing and accepting the Higher Presence. With not one thing in my hand, I enjoy the idea of having left the utter discourse of my life on the One higher-up. I may not have what I want, not even what I possibly deserve, but who’s to blame? Not me. I wish I were one of those who felt ‘touched’ by The Presence, or the ones who believe only the good is destined, and maybe I’m paving a path towards that, but I’m not there, yet (most likely, I never will be). But, I must accept, I’ve felt much better about coursing the blame through someone else. There’s less to it than devotion and yet, it’s pristine enough to maybe be beyond it. It may be called a defence mechanism, or maybe it’s simply just a change of tact, a diversion, if you will. Either way, it has saved me quite a lot of tears and several hours of self-loathing.&amp;nbsp; If one were to search ‘God is a micromanager?’, the likeness of a treasure trove may be found. My favourite answers (very obviously) belong to Quora. Jim Whitehead, Former Subatomic whisperer answered ‘No we do!’ and, I’m here for it, his answer is eloquent and metaphorical and everything I wanted from a Quora answer. However, after much deliberation, I decided to forego further research, mostly because of Jim, and partially because I wasn’t in the mood to give up on the blame game, yet. The feeling of guilt I tried not to feel, or even the remorse, I suppose, caught up to me. The 7 Laws of Magical Thinking by Matthew Hutson gives a purview into why we do what we do - it speaks quite a lot about God’s Plan (not the fun Drake kind) and about negative agency bias (my favourite kind of bias). What it suggests is that acts of consequence, particularly unfavourable consequence, arouse feelings of divine authorship. The negative agency bias also results from the fact that we like to take credit for positive outcomes and blame failures on someone else. But I’ve spoken about that before, many times, if I recall correctly. At this point, I would say I was simply looking for a scapegoat, one who doesn’t retort back. They don’t unfollow you, or tweet you back, or worse, block you. Or do they? Ah, I’ll try not to give myself a scare. I’m sure you’re screaming at me to just take responsibility, fess up and get on with the ‘real’ world. Believe me, Sir Louis Cohen, off-of-Quora’s answer, “The only gods are fictional characters in fairy tales. You’re in charge so don’t try to pass the buck” really tried to do a number on me. But it’s Christmas, in the middle of a pandemic with new mutant versions popping out each day, and don’t you remember? My cat is not here for support. And like I said, this is a love letter, to fellow scapegoats, whose presence are sometimes questioned, always appreciated and very well monetised. If this pity party of mine has managed to affront you, I heartily apologise, I’m open to new learnings (mostly, because I’m Uni-less at the moment) and will like, follow and subscribe if you put a good word for me to the One Above.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yemen: A Pawn in the Game of Middle Eastern Checkers?</title><link href="/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yemen: A Pawn in the Game of Middle Eastern Checkers?" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers">&lt;p&gt;On December 31, 22 people were killed and 50 others injured in an attack at the Aden airport in South Yemen. The attack was directed at the Saudi-backed cabinet of the new Unity Government which had landed in the same airport at that time. A second explosion was reported from Aden's Maasheq presidential palace which housed the cabinet members including the Yemeni Prime Minister Maeen Abdulmalik and the Saudi ambassador to Yemen. The Yemeni government had been sworn in on December 26, 2020, days prior to the incident, comprising 24 ministers representing the major political powers of the nation including the Southern Transitional Council. The government placed the responsibility of the attack upon the Houthis. This even should not be interpreted in isolation but in the context of a diplomatic and military crisis that goes back years into the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yemen's Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roots of the long-drawn conflict can be traced back to the multi-sided war between the Abrabbuh Mansur Hadi led Yemeni government in the South and the Houthi rebels who have seized control of Northern Yemen including the capital city of Sana'a, adjoining the Saudi border. The civil war started in 2014 and is largely attributed to the religious angle. The Zaidis, a sect of Shias, faced discrimination during the rule of Muhammad al-Shawkani, who propounded Sunnification as the means to consolidate a unified Yemen. This was in defiance to Zaidi Shi'ism. The Houthis trace their ancestry from a Zaidi group located at the Sa'dah governorate on the Northern borders of Yemen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of the Houthi rebellion was seen in 2004, when Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi, a former member of the Yemeni Parliament was killed by government military forces following his protests against governmental regulations. The political situation escalated following the 2011 Yemeni Revolution of Dignity, an offshoot of the broader Arab Spring revolution. Abdul- Malik al-Houthi supported the rebel organisations' demand for the resignation of the Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh and its siege of the Salafi village of Dammaj in Northern Yemen, boycotting the 2012 single-candidate elections aimed at making Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi the President of Yemen (a post which he still holds).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2014, the Sunni-Houthi conflict engulfed the rest of Yemen including the Sana'a Governorate by August 2014. The civil war was marked by several military milestones including the Battle of Taiz, at Yemen's third-largest city. The Houthis employed a Tochka missile (ballistic) against the Saudi-led coalition. At the battle of Aden in 2015, Hadi escaped to Riyadh, seeking assistance from Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman Al Saud, the Saudi heir apparent. The war no longer remained confined within Yemeni borders and was immediately internationalised. A Saudi-led coalition including UAE attempted at restoring the previous Yemeni Government. Sudanese and Egyptian troops had also cooperated against the Houthi advances. Amidst a geopolitical crisis, the ISIS too had been actively involved, conducting a series of suicide bombings that resulted in the death of 15 soldiers affiliated with the Saudi coalition. They, however, didn't side with the Houthi rebels either - exhorting their followers to kill the Zaidis as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the Saudi led coalition launched a major offensive mission to regain control of the city of Hudaydah, adjoining the Red Sea, in spite of warnings by the UN that the port's destruction would serve as a “crossing of Rubicon” moment. Basically, it was a point of no return as it would be impossible to avert massive loss of life due to the famine conditions that would ensue due to the disastrous effects on the shipping of food supplies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;In August 2019, there was a rift in Southern Yemen between the government forces backed by the Saudi government and the Southern Transitional Council (STC) which enjoyed UAE support. Following the failure of the Kuwait initiative seeking a political solution, the 2019 Riyadh agreement was brokered as a power-sharing deal between the Yemeni government and the Southern separatists aimed at transcending this difference between the friends turned foes. However, the conflict resumed on January 7, 2020, when the Houthi rebels shot down a Saudi coalition drone at Jawf.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the COVID-19 outbreak, an air raid ceasefire had been declared while 10,000 people had been displaced, and 13 million civilians denied access to clean and safe drinking water. Yemen had previously faced a cholera epidemic in 2017 affecting 20 out of the 22 Yemeni provinces. As of July 2020, the UNHCR estimated that 3.6 million people had been displaced and 24 million await urgent aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geopolitical ramifications&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The civil war has been at the heart of a much larger international political equation. Despite the fact that United States spokesperson Bernadette Meehan has openly stated: “&lt;em&gt;It remains our assessment that Iran does not exert command and control over the Houthis in Yemen”,&lt;/em&gt; many have viewed this as a larger Iranian proxy war. Iran and Yemen are composed of Shia Islamist, albeit with minor differences - the Iranians are followers of the Twelve Imam Shias while the Houthis are Zaidi Shias. This is in contrast to the Saudi Arabia-led coalition that largely comprises Sunni-majority nations. Ali Khamenei has even explicitly stated that he shall provide “spiritual support&quot; to the movement of the Houthis in 2019. Eritrea too has been accused of providing Iranian ammunition to the Houthis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni government on the other hand has received military as well as financial aid from the United States, which conducted drone strikes in Sana’a aiming to neutralise Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP). Reports published by Amnesty International in 2019 also indicate logistical assistance from the UK in the form of laser-guided bombs and other weaponry. Interestingly, the US Arms Export Control Act was believed to have been violated by the United States Department while ratifying arms sales to the Gulf states of Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates in August 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The launch of the ballistic missile by Houthis aimed at Saudi Arabia in 2017 led to a further strengthening of the Yemen blockade by the Saudi coalition under the pretext of preventing weapon smuggling by Iranian rebels, an accusation Tehran vehemently denies. In hindsight, this led to a hike in the price of food and fuel, adding a food security dimension to the military conflict.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yemen continues to suffer from the world's worst humanitarian crisis. The crisis is not only a concern to the Middle Eastern neighbours of Yemen but fuels the threat perception pertaining to that of the West's War on Terror against terrorism at large, particularly Al-Qaeda and ISIS. Yemen enjoys superior strategic significance, located as it is geographically on the strait linking the Red Sea with the Gulf of Aden which constitutes the zone from which most of the world's oil cargo travels. Many had blamed Saudi Arabia for its lack of security provisions on the day of the Aden airport blast, yet this might be considered as the tip of the iceberg of a deep-seated problem concerning the 'unity government.' What needs to be understood is that in more ways than one, Yemen has become a pawn in the clutches of the broader strategic dynamics of the Arab world and Uncle Sam’s War on Terror.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">On December 31, 22 people were killed and 50 others injured in an attack at the Aden airport in South Yemen. The attack was directed at the Saudi-backed cabinet of the new Unity Government which had landed in the same airport at that time. A second explosion was reported from Aden's Maasheq presidential palace which housed the cabinet members including the Yemeni Prime Minister Maeen Abdulmalik and the Saudi ambassador to Yemen. The Yemeni government had been sworn in on December 26, 2020, days prior to the incident, comprising 24 ministers representing the major political powers of the nation including the Southern Transitional Council. The government placed the responsibility of the attack upon the Houthis. This even should not be interpreted in isolation but in the context of a diplomatic and military crisis that goes back years into the past. Yemen's Civil War The roots of the long-drawn conflict can be traced back to the multi-sided war between the Abrabbuh Mansur Hadi led Yemeni government in the South and the Houthi rebels who have seized control of Northern Yemen including the capital city of Sana'a, adjoining the Saudi border. The civil war started in 2014 and is largely attributed to the religious angle. The Zaidis, a sect of Shias, faced discrimination during the rule of Muhammad al-Shawkani, who propounded Sunnification as the means to consolidate a unified Yemen. This was in defiance to Zaidi Shi'ism. The Houthis trace their ancestry from a Zaidi group located at the Sa'dah governorate on the Northern borders of Yemen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The first of the Houthi rebellion was seen in 2004, when Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi, a former member of the Yemeni Parliament was killed by government military forces following his protests against governmental regulations. The political situation escalated following the 2011 Yemeni Revolution of Dignity, an offshoot of the broader Arab Spring revolution. Abdul- Malik al-Houthi supported the rebel organisations' demand for the resignation of the Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh and its siege of the Salafi village of Dammaj in Northern Yemen, boycotting the 2012 single-candidate elections aimed at making Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi the President of Yemen (a post which he still holds). By 2014, the Sunni-Houthi conflict engulfed the rest of Yemen including the Sana'a Governorate by August 2014. The civil war was marked by several military milestones including the Battle of Taiz, at Yemen's third-largest city. The Houthis employed a Tochka missile (ballistic) against the Saudi-led coalition. At the battle of Aden in 2015, Hadi escaped to Riyadh, seeking assistance from Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman Al Saud, the Saudi heir apparent. The war no longer remained confined within Yemeni borders and was immediately internationalised. A Saudi-led coalition including UAE attempted at restoring the previous Yemeni Government. Sudanese and Egyptian troops had also cooperated against the Houthi advances. Amidst a geopolitical crisis, the ISIS too had been actively involved, conducting a series of suicide bombings that resulted in the death of 15 soldiers affiliated with the Saudi coalition. They, however, didn't side with the Houthi rebels either - exhorting their followers to kill the Zaidis as well.&amp;nbsp; In 2018, the Saudi led coalition launched a major offensive mission to regain control of the city of Hudaydah, adjoining the Red Sea, in spite of warnings by the UN that the port's destruction would serve as a “crossing of Rubicon” moment. Basically, it was a point of no return as it would be impossible to avert massive loss of life due to the famine conditions that would ensue due to the disastrous effects on the shipping of food supplies.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;In August 2019, there was a rift in Southern Yemen between the government forces backed by the Saudi government and the Southern Transitional Council (STC) which enjoyed UAE support. Following the failure of the Kuwait initiative seeking a political solution, the 2019 Riyadh agreement was brokered as a power-sharing deal between the Yemeni government and the Southern separatists aimed at transcending this difference between the friends turned foes. However, the conflict resumed on January 7, 2020, when the Houthi rebels shot down a Saudi coalition drone at Jawf.&amp;nbsp; Following the COVID-19 outbreak, an air raid ceasefire had been declared while 10,000 people had been displaced, and 13 million civilians denied access to clean and safe drinking water. Yemen had previously faced a cholera epidemic in 2017 affecting 20 out of the 22 Yemeni provinces. As of July 2020, the UNHCR estimated that 3.6 million people had been displaced and 24 million await urgent aid. Geopolitical ramifications&amp;nbsp; The civil war has been at the heart of a much larger international political equation. Despite the fact that United States spokesperson Bernadette Meehan has openly stated: “It remains our assessment that Iran does not exert command and control over the Houthis in Yemen”, many have viewed this as a larger Iranian proxy war. Iran and Yemen are composed of Shia Islamist, albeit with minor differences - the Iranians are followers of the Twelve Imam Shias while the Houthis are Zaidi Shias. This is in contrast to the Saudi Arabia-led coalition that largely comprises Sunni-majority nations. Ali Khamenei has even explicitly stated that he shall provide “spiritual support&quot; to the movement of the Houthis in 2019. Eritrea too has been accused of providing Iranian ammunition to the Houthis.&amp;nbsp; The Yemeni government on the other hand has received military as well as financial aid from the United States, which conducted drone strikes in Sana’a aiming to neutralise Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP). Reports published by Amnesty International in 2019 also indicate logistical assistance from the UK in the form of laser-guided bombs and other weaponry. Interestingly, the US Arms Export Control Act was believed to have been violated by the United States Department while ratifying arms sales to the Gulf states of Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates in August 2020.&amp;nbsp; The launch of the ballistic missile by Houthis aimed at Saudi Arabia in 2017 led to a further strengthening of the Yemen blockade by the Saudi coalition under the pretext of preventing weapon smuggling by Iranian rebels, an accusation Tehran vehemently denies. In hindsight, this led to a hike in the price of food and fuel, adding a food security dimension to the military conflict.&amp;nbsp; The way forward Yemen continues to suffer from the world's worst humanitarian crisis. The crisis is not only a concern to the Middle Eastern neighbours of Yemen but fuels the threat perception pertaining to that of the West's War on Terror against terrorism at large, particularly Al-Qaeda and ISIS. Yemen enjoys superior strategic significance, located as it is geographically on the strait linking the Red Sea with the Gulf of Aden which constitutes the zone from which most of the world's oil cargo travels. Many had blamed Saudi Arabia for its lack of security provisions on the day of the Aden airport blast, yet this might be considered as the tip of the iceberg of a deep-seated problem concerning the 'unity government.' What needs to be understood is that in more ways than one, Yemen has become a pawn in the clutches of the broader strategic dynamics of the Arab world and Uncle Sam’s War on Terror.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Intangible Behind the Pink</title><link href="/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Intangible Behind the Pink" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink">&lt;p&gt;Lydia Michaels in her book, &lt;em&gt;La Vie En Rose: Life in Pink&lt;/em&gt;, gives readers Emma Sanders, a seemingly ordinary girl who wound up being the strongest woman Riley Lockhart (the protagonist, if you may) had ever known. Below is an excerpt from the erotic, intellectual, and haunting journey of the deceptive pink bow that shines on its cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Emma shut her laptop and scowled at them. “I’m pink.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She wasn’t sure when her opinion of the colour changed or why, but she now took offence to outsiders putting down the pink as much as she took offence to corporations abusing the colour. What she once criticized she now understood. Despite all the exploitation, there was something intangible behind the pink, a sense of connectedness, and she wanted to embrace that camaraderie.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am certain that pink reminded her of her love for dance. The innocence of being young. Tutus. Strawberry frosting on a vanilla cake. And lipstick (I bet she loves a good lipstick). Perhaps, it reminds her that she should take pride in her feminine traits, in being a woman. There is nothing remotely wrong with enjoying femininity. Curves. Hips. Lips. Empathy. Vulnerability. Sensuality. Patience. Intuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knew capitalists would take her intangible behind the pink quite so literally. Have you ever wondered why there exists a price difference for male and female shoppers’ while buying similar products? Masculine products come in dark-coloured packages while female products come in packages of pink and purple, coated with fruity and floral fragrance. And while colour and scent are the notable elements that distinguish one from the other, there is another yet indistinct facet that is costing those who buy women-based products more – the infamous “pink tax”&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;pink tax&lt;/strong&gt;, also known as an episode of gender-based price discrimination, is an invisible cost that women have to pay for products and services designed for them, while the male constituent of the same is priced less, more often than not.&amp;nbsp;There is a rambling tendency for products marketed specifically toward women to be pricier than those marketed for men, despite either gender's preference to purchase either product. And this tax is not confined to the wealthiest nations of the world, women in developing nations too pay a higher price for feminine products.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Weiss-Wolf, a lawyer, Vice President for the Brennan School of Justice at NYU School of Law, and co-founder of Period Equity says that from a technical standpoint, it isn’t really a tax, rather an income-generating scenario for private corporations who found a money minting technique. Part of the reason why products that are considered ‘pink’ are priced more is that society typically places women to a higher standard when it comes to appearance, providing big business houses with a window of opportunity to push women from all backgrounds to spend more on their appearance. Then, pricing products higher becomes part of the marketing strategy and companies are happy to rake in a bit more from women. So, razors for women cost more than the razors for men. And just because they &lt;em&gt;can &lt;/em&gt;explicitly make money off of pink tax, they think that they should, a classic capital stance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pink tax coupled with wage discrimination makes even basic hygiene products for women unaffordable. The Consumer Reports of California, Florida, Connecticut and South Dakota reveal that women pay as much as 50% more than men do for similar products. However, women and men are not even completely aware of the existence of a pink tax or gender tax. In a survey conducted with a small sample size in the age group of 18-25, 67% of the respondents had never heard either of the terms.&amp;nbsp;However, interestingly, 93%&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;of the respondents felt that similar consumer products were charged at a higher price for women than for&amp;nbsp;men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Surbhi Singh, a practising gynaecologist and founder and president of the menstrual awareness NGO 'Sacchi Saheli', says that in general, most of our choices in life are determined by marketing and advertising. With this in mind, we are drawn towards products that are marketed to make us feel prettier or fairer, etc. For this, women certainly pay the “extra price”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fashion industry, a matrix to look into is the bridal segment. Retailers and designers lay a great deal of emphasis on the bridal apparel or jewellery or all those accessories that go into making a bride (like Emma Sanders), versus all those that go into making a groom (like Riley Lockhart). There is clearly an extensive disparity. A chunk of it is certainly developed by branding, marketing and a push from the marketers; rest is gender stereotyping. A study on shoppers and their buying habits vouchsafed that women consumers are more at the mercy of this kind of marketing because it appeals to their ‘lower’ self-esteem and self-pride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2018, Mrs Indra Nooyi, the then chief executive of PepsiCo went over the board with ‘Lady’ Doritos in a podcast. The masses didn’t take it well, obviously. Mrs Nooyi told the interviewer that women did not eat Doritos the same way men did. “They don’t like to crunch too loudly in public,” she said. “And they don’t lick their fingers generously, and they don’t like to pour the little broken pieces and the flavouring into their mouth.” She further suggested that “snacks for women can be designed and packaged differently,” or in other words, PepsiCo was planning “a male and female version of chips.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women want equal pay for equal work and an end to sex discrimination in the workplace, and all our society has to offer is a bag of Lady Doritos so they won’t have to crunch too loudly in front of their male colleagues. What most people believed and I’m sure still would, if Lady Doritos actually becomes a thing, is that Lady Doritos are just regular Doritos but when a woman buys a bag, she only gets 70% of the chips a guy would. Funny how mysteriously our pink tax finds its way to things as ordinary as a packet of chips.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet gender tax is not an issue that infuriates women, even educated and gender-sensitive ones. Gender tax would be visible, perhaps, if we all knew that it exists. However, consumers are getting aware of it gradually. And hence, strategies and policies are bound to change in future. Companies like Burger King have staged their campaign against pink pricing. Hopefully, a time shall come where women may not have to pay more for products just because they are considered pink or feminine. If we think about the enduring and complex history of the color pink, it was considered masculine by virtue of being a diminutive of red, before it was considered girlish or feminine. It wasn’t until the 19th century, that it became coded as female, while blue became an indicator of masculinity. Perhaps, the problem that we’re trying to solve would ask us, society as a whole, to change the very definition of what does and doesn’t qualify as a gender specific notion, &lt;em&gt;vox populi&lt;/em&gt;. And a lot of work needs to be done to make it happen but as Lily Pulitzer, one of the greatest American fashion designers, says, &lt;em&gt;“anything is possible with sunshine and a little pink”&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anjali Harjani</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Lydia Michaels in her book, La Vie En Rose: Life in Pink, gives readers Emma Sanders, a seemingly ordinary girl who wound up being the strongest woman Riley Lockhart (the protagonist, if you may) had ever known. Below is an excerpt from the erotic, intellectual, and haunting journey of the deceptive pink bow that shines on its cover. 'Emma shut her laptop and scowled at them. “I’m pink.” She wasn’t sure when her opinion of the colour changed or why, but she now took offence to outsiders putting down the pink as much as she took offence to corporations abusing the colour. What she once criticized she now understood. Despite all the exploitation, there was something intangible behind the pink, a sense of connectedness, and she wanted to embrace that camaraderie.” I am certain that pink reminded her of her love for dance. The innocence of being young. Tutus. Strawberry frosting on a vanilla cake. And lipstick (I bet she loves a good lipstick). Perhaps, it reminds her that she should take pride in her feminine traits, in being a woman. There is nothing remotely wrong with enjoying femininity. Curves. Hips. Lips. Empathy. Vulnerability. Sensuality. Patience. Intuition. Who knew capitalists would take her intangible behind the pink quite so literally. Have you ever wondered why there exists a price difference for male and female shoppers’ while buying similar products? Masculine products come in dark-coloured packages while female products come in packages of pink and purple, coated with fruity and floral fragrance. And while colour and scent are the notable elements that distinguish one from the other, there is another yet indistinct facet that is costing those who buy women-based products more – the infamous “pink tax”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The&amp;nbsp;pink tax, also known as an episode of gender-based price discrimination, is an invisible cost that women have to pay for products and services designed for them, while the male constituent of the same is priced less, more often than not.&amp;nbsp;There is a rambling tendency for products marketed specifically toward women to be pricier than those marketed for men, despite either gender's preference to purchase either product. And this tax is not confined to the wealthiest nations of the world, women in developing nations too pay a higher price for feminine products.&amp;nbsp; Jennifer Weiss-Wolf, a lawyer, Vice President for the Brennan School of Justice at NYU School of Law, and co-founder of Period Equity says that from a technical standpoint, it isn’t really a tax, rather an income-generating scenario for private corporations who found a money minting technique. Part of the reason why products that are considered ‘pink’ are priced more is that society typically places women to a higher standard when it comes to appearance, providing big business houses with a window of opportunity to push women from all backgrounds to spend more on their appearance. Then, pricing products higher becomes part of the marketing strategy and companies are happy to rake in a bit more from women. So, razors for women cost more than the razors for men. And just because they can explicitly make money off of pink tax, they think that they should, a classic capital stance. Pink tax coupled with wage discrimination makes even basic hygiene products for women unaffordable. The Consumer Reports of California, Florida, Connecticut and South Dakota reveal that women pay as much as 50% more than men do for similar products. However, women and men are not even completely aware of the existence of a pink tax or gender tax. In a survey conducted with a small sample size in the age group of 18-25, 67% of the respondents had never heard either of the terms.&amp;nbsp;However, interestingly, 93% of the respondents felt that similar consumer products were charged at a higher price for women than for&amp;nbsp;men.&amp;nbsp; Dr Surbhi Singh, a practising gynaecologist and founder and president of the menstrual awareness NGO 'Sacchi Saheli', says that in general, most of our choices in life are determined by marketing and advertising. With this in mind, we are drawn towards products that are marketed to make us feel prettier or fairer, etc. For this, women certainly pay the “extra price”.&amp;nbsp; In the fashion industry, a matrix to look into is the bridal segment. Retailers and designers lay a great deal of emphasis on the bridal apparel or jewellery or all those accessories that go into making a bride (like Emma Sanders), versus all those that go into making a groom (like Riley Lockhart). There is clearly an extensive disparity. A chunk of it is certainly developed by branding, marketing and a push from the marketers; rest is gender stereotyping. A study on shoppers and their buying habits vouchsafed that women consumers are more at the mercy of this kind of marketing because it appeals to their ‘lower’ self-esteem and self-pride. Back in 2018, Mrs Indra Nooyi, the then chief executive of PepsiCo went over the board with ‘Lady’ Doritos in a podcast. The masses didn’t take it well, obviously. Mrs Nooyi told the interviewer that women did not eat Doritos the same way men did. “They don’t like to crunch too loudly in public,” she said. “And they don’t lick their fingers generously, and they don’t like to pour the little broken pieces and the flavouring into their mouth.” She further suggested that “snacks for women can be designed and packaged differently,” or in other words, PepsiCo was planning “a male and female version of chips.” Women want equal pay for equal work and an end to sex discrimination in the workplace, and all our society has to offer is a bag of Lady Doritos so they won’t have to crunch too loudly in front of their male colleagues. What most people believed and I’m sure still would, if Lady Doritos actually becomes a thing, is that Lady Doritos are just regular Doritos but when a woman buys a bag, she only gets 70% of the chips a guy would. Funny how mysteriously our pink tax finds its way to things as ordinary as a packet of chips.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; And yet gender tax is not an issue that infuriates women, even educated and gender-sensitive ones. Gender tax would be visible, perhaps, if we all knew that it exists. However, consumers are getting aware of it gradually. And hence, strategies and policies are bound to change in future. Companies like Burger King have staged their campaign against pink pricing. Hopefully, a time shall come where women may not have to pay more for products just because they are considered pink or feminine. If we think about the enduring and complex history of the color pink, it was considered masculine by virtue of being a diminutive of red, before it was considered girlish or feminine. It wasn’t until the 19th century, that it became coded as female, while blue became an indicator of masculinity. Perhaps, the problem that we’re trying to solve would ask us, society as a whole, to change the very definition of what does and doesn’t qualify as a gender specific notion, vox populi. And a lot of work needs to be done to make it happen but as Lily Pulitzer, one of the greatest American fashion designers, says, “anything is possible with sunshine and a little pink”.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper</title><link href="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 5: Connecting the Dots&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “&lt;em&gt;it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge&lt;/em&gt;.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samakshi Garg</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp; Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp; Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp; With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp; Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people. The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes. Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp; Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp; Part 5: Connecting the Dots Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp; Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive. Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sign the Deal and Bob’s your Uncle!</title><link href="/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sign the Deal and Bob’s your Uncle!" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle">&lt;p&gt;The tortuous ordeal of Britain’s divorce from the European Union finally came to a rather anticlimactic conclusion on January 24, 2020. Teetering from the raging pandemic on shaky ground, Britain will now have to learn to navigate the tumultuous seas of global trade, defence and foreign alliances without the backing of 27 European nations. The journey forward is difficult. Leadership suffers from a lack of confidence. There is a lot that could go wrong, but there are things to look forward too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and the resulting double-dip recession, triggered Britain’s scepticism of the European Union. But their reasons for holding a referendum for Brexit were largely entrenched in the anti-immigrant sentiments and “burdensome” economic regulations. While the new deal may assuage the fear of many Brits of “immigrants from the European countries stealing their jobs,” Britain’s quest to leave behind the troublesome and meddling economic regulations may cause a slightly bigger problem.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a positive note, this is an opportunity for Britain to redefine its role in the global arena. International leadership is undergoing a major structural change. The United States of America has replaced their 74-year-old President with a 78 year old one although this one is far-more saner and far-less fascist. China is becoming a dangerous superpower. An increasing number of Scandinavian and European nations are formulating plans to become clean-energy spaces with zero fossil fuel usage.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain can choose to redefine itself. It holds a prominent position on the negotiation table when it comes to defence and trade. It has a permanent position in the defence and security tables in the form of its position in the United Nations Security Council and membership of North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.&amp;nbsp; Britain would be chairing the G7 summit in 2021 and consequently has an opportunity to shape trade and defence policies to its advantage. However, with the current leadership and an overwhelming public distrust because of COVID-19, there is a bleak possibility of the aforementioned. Britain has also suffered from a blow to its reputation in the international arena because of its poor response to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada has not been a fan of Boris Johnson’s friendship with Donald Trump, and it would not be looked upon favourably by the Biden administration either. Considering the broken ties with the EU members, the UK better make plans for mending the bridges with these two immediate neighbours. Britain can use this time to build stronger alliances with Asian countries. India, China and now Bangladesh are becoming active participants in global trade and security. It would be beneficial for Britain to look for alternate market channels because the likelihood of the EU countries looking favourably upon trade from Britain is very low. Alternatively, trade with the EU was a major source of income for Britain, and they would need to move fast to fill the gaping hole left from Brexit. However, Boris Johnson’s cancellation of his visit to India as the chief guest for India's Republic Day celebration marks an inauspicious start to their decision to build a stronger alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calls for a united Ireland and Scottish independence have also been making waves in Britain. This has been a contentious issue for Britain for a long time. The possibility of rising waves of separatist movements in the midst of Britain’s shaky future in the global sphere is not a situation that Britain could possibly endure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal signed has left Britain and the EU worse off, though it did its best to leave Britain the worst off. British citizens lost more than just their right to live and work in 27 European countries. British goods would now face tariffs and restrictions at EU borders, and the deal has not managed to finalise negotiations for foreign policy, external security and defence. Foreign investors fear an economic decline and their confidence has been an all-time low, consequently foreign investments have dropped. The only sweet spot in this deal has been Britain’s success in securing a greater portion of fishes in the UK waters.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The small traders and business owners in the UK would suffer the most. They were the worst affected by the lockdown and the COVID-19 pandemic. The Brexit deal would ensure they lose the market channels and international avenues for trade and a major chunk of their profits. While the members of the EU would too lose access to British markets, they would still have the remaining 27 member countries to satisfy themselves with. Unsurprisingly, British citizens are unhappy with the government’s inability to negotiate a profitable deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major source of income for Britain is the influx of foreign students. The year-long pandemic and now the new strain of COVID-19 has already resulted in substantial loss of revenue for the country. Universities fear that this scenario, compounded by the anti-immigrant sentiments that triggered Brexit in the first place and the on-going global recession would be the catalyst for a downward spiral of the British economy. The offer for a two-year tier-4 work visa is a step in the right direction. Hopefully, this would incentivise students from abroad, and the year 2021 would revive the revenue influx.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain now has to determine the path that it would take regarding the pandemic, foreign policy, security, defence and international development. It needs to formulate plans to revive the demand for domestic goods and investor confidence. The political and public dissatisfaction and a weakening social fabric of the country await the current government. The economy is slowing and the growth trajectory is moving south. The list is long. The stakes are high. Britain has more to lose than just economic prosperity. Political turmoil, a changing social fabric, and safe transitions should also be on the British government’s vision for 2021. No one would want to be in Boris Johnsons’s shoes right now, but perhaps the citizens of Britain would be more sympathetic to his plight, had he not been the orchestrator of this terrible political opera.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The tortuous ordeal of Britain’s divorce from the European Union finally came to a rather anticlimactic conclusion on January 24, 2020. Teetering from the raging pandemic on shaky ground, Britain will now have to learn to navigate the tumultuous seas of global trade, defence and foreign alliances without the backing of 27 European nations. The journey forward is difficult. Leadership suffers from a lack of confidence. There is a lot that could go wrong, but there are things to look forward too.&amp;nbsp; The aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and the resulting double-dip recession, triggered Britain’s scepticism of the European Union. But their reasons for holding a referendum for Brexit were largely entrenched in the anti-immigrant sentiments and “burdensome” economic regulations. While the new deal may assuage the fear of many Brits of “immigrants from the European countries stealing their jobs,” Britain’s quest to leave behind the troublesome and meddling economic regulations may cause a slightly bigger problem.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; On a positive note, this is an opportunity for Britain to redefine its role in the global arena. International leadership is undergoing a major structural change. The United States of America has replaced their 74-year-old President with a 78 year old one although this one is far-more saner and far-less fascist. China is becoming a dangerous superpower. An increasing number of Scandinavian and European nations are formulating plans to become clean-energy spaces with zero fossil fuel usage.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Britain can choose to redefine itself. It holds a prominent position on the negotiation table when it comes to defence and trade. It has a permanent position in the defence and security tables in the form of its position in the United Nations Security Council and membership of North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.&amp;nbsp; Britain would be chairing the G7 summit in 2021 and consequently has an opportunity to shape trade and defence policies to its advantage. However, with the current leadership and an overwhelming public distrust because of COVID-19, there is a bleak possibility of the aforementioned. Britain has also suffered from a blow to its reputation in the international arena because of its poor response to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Canada has not been a fan of Boris Johnson’s friendship with Donald Trump, and it would not be looked upon favourably by the Biden administration either. Considering the broken ties with the EU members, the UK better make plans for mending the bridges with these two immediate neighbours. Britain can use this time to build stronger alliances with Asian countries. India, China and now Bangladesh are becoming active participants in global trade and security. It would be beneficial for Britain to look for alternate market channels because the likelihood of the EU countries looking favourably upon trade from Britain is very low. Alternatively, trade with the EU was a major source of income for Britain, and they would need to move fast to fill the gaping hole left from Brexit. However, Boris Johnson’s cancellation of his visit to India as the chief guest for India's Republic Day celebration marks an inauspicious start to their decision to build a stronger alliance. Calls for a united Ireland and Scottish independence have also been making waves in Britain. This has been a contentious issue for Britain for a long time. The possibility of rising waves of separatist movements in the midst of Britain’s shaky future in the global sphere is not a situation that Britain could possibly endure.&amp;nbsp; The deal signed has left Britain and the EU worse off, though it did its best to leave Britain the worst off. British citizens lost more than just their right to live and work in 27 European countries. British goods would now face tariffs and restrictions at EU borders, and the deal has not managed to finalise negotiations for foreign policy, external security and defence. Foreign investors fear an economic decline and their confidence has been an all-time low, consequently foreign investments have dropped. The only sweet spot in this deal has been Britain’s success in securing a greater portion of fishes in the UK waters.&amp;nbsp; The small traders and business owners in the UK would suffer the most. They were the worst affected by the lockdown and the COVID-19 pandemic. The Brexit deal would ensure they lose the market channels and international avenues for trade and a major chunk of their profits. While the members of the EU would too lose access to British markets, they would still have the remaining 27 member countries to satisfy themselves with. Unsurprisingly, British citizens are unhappy with the government’s inability to negotiate a profitable deal. Another major source of income for Britain is the influx of foreign students. The year-long pandemic and now the new strain of COVID-19 has already resulted in substantial loss of revenue for the country. Universities fear that this scenario, compounded by the anti-immigrant sentiments that triggered Brexit in the first place and the on-going global recession would be the catalyst for a downward spiral of the British economy. The offer for a two-year tier-4 work visa is a step in the right direction. Hopefully, this would incentivise students from abroad, and the year 2021 would revive the revenue influx.&amp;nbsp; Britain now has to determine the path that it would take regarding the pandemic, foreign policy, security, defence and international development. It needs to formulate plans to revive the demand for domestic goods and investor confidence. The political and public dissatisfaction and a weakening social fabric of the country await the current government. The economy is slowing and the growth trajectory is moving south. The list is long. The stakes are high. Britain has more to lose than just economic prosperity. Political turmoil, a changing social fabric, and safe transitions should also be on the British government’s vision for 2021. No one would want to be in Boris Johnsons’s shoes right now, but perhaps the citizens of Britain would be more sympathetic to his plight, had he not been the orchestrator of this terrible political opera.</summary></entry></feed>