<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-27T14:28:17+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Art, the Artist and the Investor</title><link href="/Art-Artisan-Investor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art, the Artist and the Investor" /><published>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Art-Artisan-Investor</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Art-Artisan-Investor">&lt;p&gt;Creativity has its own timeline, and art can only blossom through experience and patience. It takes its own sweet time getting through to people letting the art ripen naturally, instead of spoon-feeding its patrons, and is usually a mark of the artist’s authenticity. Take Van Gogh or Kafka, for instance, with both dying in ignorance of the ingenuity of their works. Their patience, or rather underconfidence, eventually led to the posthumous recognition, capitalised on by whoever could claim to ignite the inspiration, rendering their lives analogous to a sad art film, that yet still, managed to inspire people further. But not every artist wants to make a sad art film of their lives. It isn’t simply about the lack of patience or existence of confidence to market their work, it is, quite often, about &lt;em&gt;survival&lt;/em&gt;. Putting all stakes in an industry that isn’t entirely welcoming to new works due to their abstract nature is certainly a dicey choice for one’s career. Looking for popular platforms that can get you eyeballs is only natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These platforms are the ones that claim to ‘discover’ the artists, and subsequently, capitalise on the lifetime of earnings through their artwork. Take the music industry, for example. Artists still make their music, but that is not exactly how they make their money. The commercialisation of the records by label companies has been in place for decades now. Singers would only get a proportion of the sales revenue generated when new music would be released, which is only fair. Associating a famous record label’s name with the music of a new artist is a high-risk position to take business-wise, and hence it’s only natural to expect higher returns. Labels own master recordings, the copyrights associated and the back catalogues of artists. These assets are owned to compensate them in exchange for the risks taken by the platform in financing the artists’ careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in the 80’s &amp;amp; 90’s, the transparency of record deals wasn’t exactly crystal clear, both record labels and the singers managed to make good money because their primary source of revenue was the literal sale of the songs via CDs, vinyl records, etc. Currently, the music sales revenue, though growing, in absolute terms, by nearly $1 billion per year, is only about 60% of what it was in 1999. The industry took its major hit post the year 2000 when internet services began illegally offering easy access to the free download of music. The advent of pirated downloading of music drove down the record sales and seemingly marked a Malthusian-style prophecy of the end of the commercialised and profitable era. That was until the streaming platforms stepped in. Although a third of the global music listeners still pirate their music (as per a report by the International Federation of Phonographic Industry), a massive rise in legal streaming platforms like Spotify, Apple Music and Tidal seems to have curbed the illegal consumption of music. And while the revenues and the contract transparency is on the rise, the monetary credit accrued to the actual artists has fallen with the steepening of the industry’s growth trajectory. Private equity (PE) players have stepped in to invest in the record labels, adding complicated layers to the revenue distribution model, and thus, leaving even lower residual amount that goes to the singers. Now, how do these big-money investors in PE corporates that, at the very least, expect consistency in their returns, align themselves with an industry that has its own volatile timeline? They &lt;em&gt;undershare&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The labels now provide to the artists a platform, and that’s nearly all. An estimate suggests that an average artist gets around one-tenth of a cent per play of an associated song on Spotify. The streaming platform generally takes up 15-30% of the revenue generated, and then a major chunk is instantly slashed off in the name of the record label. At this point, less than 40% of the revenue remains before singers, songwriters or publishers. The final average payout is dependent on how much ownership of the master recordings and the compositions the artists can exert. To put it into perspective, a star as big as Beyoncé makes only 10% of her money through music sales. One would think that music tours and concerts ought to make up for the deficiencies, but they’re simply a marketing programme, an attempt to keep the artists relevant, which becomes evident once you realise that rarely do any of the global or national level tour revenues ever break-even. The artists are paid only a proportional royalty of any other public performance not financed by the label, but by talk-shows or award shows. The payment structure often leaves the singers earning off of advertisements and endorsements, robbing them of their ‘authenticity’ tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the highest-paid pop-artist in 2017, Diddy, who made the money from his Cirac vodka deal, hadn’t even released an album in over 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while the streaming platforms aren’t exactly killing the music industry, they’re still skewed in favour of the private equity players, and hence are the primary drivers of the aggregate growth recorded in the revenues, dwarfing the ability of the actual artists to exert any influence. However, some of the bigger names are now coming out against the unregulated PE influence in the industry. Recently Big Machine Records, which owned the rights to the music catalogue of all of Taylor Swift’s past albums, except for &lt;em&gt;Lover&lt;/em&gt;, was sold out for $300-$350 Million, to Scooter Braun’s Ithaca Holdings, disallowing Swift to perform her own songs at the AMAs, and leading to a highly publicised feud between the two. The sale was backed by the renowned Carlyle Group, that was already facing backlash for its indirect stake in defence contractors who had actively supplied weapons to fund the bombings in Yemen by Saudi Arabia, and now came under the heat of the fans as well as Alexandria Ocasio Cortez and Elizabeth Warren. While the matter remains unresolved, it is likely that this time the artist might register a victory, since Swift has threatened to re-record her past albums. The victory would put her in the rare company of the few major-label artists like Metallica, Janet Jackson and Jay-Z to gain control of the assets associated with their music. The outcome of the lawsuit pursued by EDM artist Martin Garrix against the label Spinnin’ Records has also brought some good news, with Garrix being given the rights and masters to some of his biggest hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investors are constantly innovating to capitalise on the gains of the music industry, with some even experimenting with removal of ownership exclusivity and opening song rights for public offerings. An Initial Song Offering (ISO) was made for Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Jodeci Freestyle&lt;/em&gt;, wherein 10% of the copyright stake was available for public purchase to the top 100 subscribers, with Ethereum based payments. While such innovations are in the interest of the public and allow them to channelise their savings towards better investment options, it needs to be realised that the lack of tangibility of both the output and most of the inputs of this industry is an important consideration in the face of the financial innovations that should follow. Therefore, the battle between rights and arts will continue for an indefinite period, as long as we, as a corporate, wouldn’t stop patronising the creative skills of the people involved in this field.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Creativity has its own timeline, and art can only blossom through experience and patience. It takes its own sweet time getting through to people letting the art ripen naturally, instead of spoon-feeding its patrons, and is usually a mark of the artist’s authenticity. Take Van Gogh or Kafka, for instance, with both dying in ignorance of the ingenuity of their works. Their patience, or rather underconfidence, eventually led to the posthumous recognition, capitalised on by whoever could claim to ignite the inspiration, rendering their lives analogous to a sad art film, that yet still, managed to inspire people further. But not every artist wants to make a sad art film of their lives. It isn’t simply about the lack of patience or existence of confidence to market their work, it is, quite often, about survival. Putting all stakes in an industry that isn’t entirely welcoming to new works due to their abstract nature is certainly a dicey choice for one’s career. Looking for popular platforms that can get you eyeballs is only natural.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beer, anyone? Levity in a Time of Crisis</title><link href="/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beer, anyone? Levity in a Time of Crisis" /><published>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;If one were to tell me that I’d be receiving an impromptu holiday which may last anywhere between 10 days to the end of time (my personal time, friends) - I’d be elated, ecstatic, even. However, the very backing of the same would be resulting in deaths around the world and would be the reason for self-quarantining? Not as idealistic. While COVID-19 is no secret, and there is plenty known as well as unknown about this global pandemic, what has increasingly caught on like wildfire is the machinery related to the meme-making and the subsequent jokes that have flown in. While everyone is apprehensive about the unknown, the at-homeness has led to coping with the situation in any fashion we can. But, why humour? And what version of it is deemed appropriate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that something that was born along one side of the world and has followed around the entirety of it has led to a strong sense of levity, at this dire time? What room do we have in our heads that makes us condone a business supposedly so corroded? And if not supposedly as corroded as it is supposed to be- what conception of this humour makes the cut?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From making fun of Trump and his infallible speeches (and more importantly, wigs) to now, suggesting how Bollywood star Ranveer Singh dresses like Coronavirus - believe you me, the latter tickled me about as much as it shocked me. The memes have hit like the plague, itself (no pun, intended) - quite unavoidable and with no cure. Just this morning, Snapchat informed me that a proficient actress was being ‘cancelled’ for making less of this pandemic. If she is at fault, aren’t we all? If Tom Hanks can tweet out that he’s lost 216 bouts of rummy with his wife due to the posited isolation of his positive-to-the-virus-self, we laugh, don’t we? It is ‘absolutely amazing’ how well he’s handling the issue at hand. However, if another individual so much as suggest that this pandemic is God’s gift to students- Ma’am, you have a #cancelled on your hands. I, a mere human, only ask for the boundary - where to build the wall, you know? (Please forgive me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do what I can do best, right about now. I ask. People, Google, one and all. My friend tells me memes are the medicine to this pandemic, at least until you test positive, while a research published in ​Harvard Business Review explains that “laughter relieves stress and boredom, boosts engagement and well-being, and spurs not only creativity and collaboration but also analytic precision and productivity.” It’s the manna from heaven, my friends. All that has troubled us: stress, boredom- cured. One article went ahead and suggested that humour can be and is, very well a form of self-care when experiencing burnout and compassion fatigue. Finding a humorous angle together can serve as a doorway to a deeper connection with other individuals, acting as a buffer. Could it be that a sense of belonging is what we seek, it is this that makes these jokes and memes as popular as they are - our need for affiliation! ​Malchiodi, one of the greatest researchers of ‘the funnies’ has vastly discussed the positive mental and physical results of laughter and/or humour. “Since the late 1980s, a number of studies support the idea that laughter stimulates the immune system and counteracts the effects of stress ​hormones, although results are mixed about exactly how,” she said. “In brief, there’s agreement that it’s another way to arrive at the relaxation response.” ​We’ve got it, people - an explanation as to why there has been a surge in the circulation of COVID-19 memes, parodies and videos aiming to get a laugh out of people. It could be that for certain people, making light of things is more of a coping mechanism than it is a chance at fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and what fame to give up, too. Please afford me another moment of pondering and I shall be done. In the extensive research that this phenomenon took - what became extremely apparent to me was the cultural difference. While Singapore is busy with how other countries are copying their way of work, or may I suggest, homework; the USA was busy with toilet paper memes (or, better yet, buttcoin, the new currency crowned after the infamous bitcoin.) India, out here, is confused about which issue to put higher up on the hierarchy - the failure of it as a democracy, the communal riots, the pandemic that is barely being considered as one or just the sheer amount of Whatsapp forwards that suggest you drink ‘gau mutra’ (cow urine) and get vaccinated towards Corona. Hitherto, the reigning queen, (and this I say with much bias) has to be the Corona Beer memes and the expected aversion to the same by the sages of the world. The economy is down the drain for most countries, the population - more so. But, I really do think Corona with/without lime deserves better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, and this may be of interest to one and all, the place where Rapunzel isolated herself? Corona. In more ways than one, the world is coming full circle- and while it may be really difficult to go through, it is nonetheless entertaining to watch the unfolding. Just this morning, another friend and I had a long conversation about the conspiracy theories involved with the awakening of COVID-19. Oh, and if you weren’t aware CoronaVirus Disorder- 2019 getting abbreviated has very much to do with the memes, you can ask WHO, they’d attest. While I’m no meme connoisseur, conspiracy theories really get me going but that’s for another day, another time, another beer. Done with my rambling, I warrant my answer to my aforementioned question - why humour? Why this very coping mechanism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I think? It is non-violent resistance to any form of oppression. A successful one at that. It facilitates a culture of resistance, tries to bring levity, sure - but with it, interest and awareness. It’s the pink colour to cough syrups - the pretty packaging to venomous bottles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as ​at a personal level, self-irony and joking about one’s own shortcomings are considered to have the greatest impact on self-liberation through humour, dare I suggest that may be true at the social level, irrespective of cultural and individual differences? Now, what does mere me know? While I ride back home in an airplane where no individual is without a mask or sanitizer - while I go home because my mother would rather I be sick with her than without - while there’s panic and apprehension on almost possible levels of conscious awareness, I wonder if you’d like that Corona with lime or without.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><category term="trending" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">If one were to tell me that I’d be receiving an impromptu holiday which may last anywhere between 10 days to the end of time (my personal time, friends) - I’d be elated, ecstatic, even. However, the very backing of the same would be resulting in deaths around the world and would be the reason for self-quarantining? Not as idealistic. While COVID-19 is no secret, and there is plenty known as well as unknown about this global pandemic, what has increasingly caught on like wildfire is the machinery related to the meme-making and the subsequent jokes that have flown in. While everyone is apprehensive about the unknown, the at-homeness has led to coping with the situation in any fashion we can. But, why humour? And what version of it is deemed appropriate?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Indo-US Relations in the Second Decade of the 21st Century: The Way Ahead</title><link href="/Indo-US-Relations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indo-US Relations in the Second Decade of the 21st Century: The Way Ahead" /><published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Indo-US-Relations</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Indo-US-Relations">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump, the President of the United States undertook his first official trip to India since he assumed the Presidency in 2016. His 36-hour trip was marked by activities which ranged from travelling across Ahmedabad to Agra, to culminate his trip to Delhi. In the words of Trump himself, “Nobody else got the reception that I got yesterday. We had thousands of people. That was an incredible scene.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His trip, which took place in the last week of February, may be considered to be an extremely significant political gesture ahead of the United States presidential election due for November this year. This had been the fifth meeting between the two global leaders in the last eight months, indicating a maturity of the two nations’ diplomatic ties. The reception accorded to Trump may be reminiscent of the crowd gathered to welcome Dwight D Eisenhower, the United States President in 1959.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indo-US Ties Down the Ages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indo-US relations can be traced from the time prior to the independence of India in 1947. Prominent leaders of the national movement including M N Roy (one of the leaders of the Indo-German conspiracy), had settled in the US. However, in the initial decades of the Cold War, when the US had made Pakistan a CENTO ally (Central Treaty Organization), India had developed a strategic alliance with the Soviet Union. Yet, with the crystallisation of the Non-Aligned Movement in 1961 at the Bandung Conference, India embarked on an attempt to distance itself from the prevalent Cold War power politics. And there was a gradual deterioration in the relationship between India and the US, with Richard Nixon’s administration extending its support to Pakistan during the Bangladesh Liberation War of 1971 (in which India was an ally of Bangladesh). Moreover, India signed a 20-year Treaty of Friendship with the Soviet Union in 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indo-US ties soured further in 1974 when India detonated its first nuclear device. This strategic move ensured two decades of estrangement between the two nations. However, in 1982, the then US president Ronald Reagan did meet with the then Indian Prime Minister Indira Gandhi where the latter proclaimed, “We should find a common area, however so small.” The thaw in relations was prevalent till 1991, the year which marked the dissolution of the Soviet Union. With the adoption of India’s new economic policy in 1991, under Prime Minister Narasimha Rao and with Manmohan Singh as the Finance Minister, Indian foreign policy adapted itself to the unipolar world with the US as the champion of capitalist global domination. The adoption of the policies of Liberalisation, Privatisation and Globalisation cemented the economic ties of the two nations. Bilateral trade and investments increased, and one saw the strengthening of India’s decision-making powers in global governance via its introduction of India into multilateral export control regimes such as the Australia Group, The Missile Technology Control Regime (2016), the Wassenaar Arrangement and so on. In fact, the US offered assistance to India in joining the Nuclear Suppliers Group and in July 2006, the US Congress had amended the US law to accommodate civilian nuclear trade with India. Indo-US relations reached a zenith when India was declared a major defence partner of the US in 2016, under the Presidency of Barack Obama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Matters of Military and Economic Development Post The 1990’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 11, 1998, the Indian government had declared the successful completion of a series of underground nuclear tests at Pokhran, Rajasthan- close to the North-Western border shared by the two nations. The act drew widespread international criticism with Bill Clinton, the then US President, recalling the US ambassador to India and further imposing economic sanctions, leading to severe diplomatic tensions escalating between the two nations. However, in an amazing turn of events, in March 2000, Clinton became the first US President to visit India since 1978. With a fledgeling global economy, Clinton’s visit signalled a US foreign policy shifting its priorities from its Cold War ally Pakistan to India. In the areas of energy security, the 2005 visit of Condoleezza Rice, the United States Secretary of State initiated a dialogue on this primary core economic sector. This step had gained international significance as there had been mounting tensions over the US sale of fighter jets to Pakistan. Further, the signing of the Civil Nuclear Deal ensured a clear demarcation between India’s civil and military nuclear facilities, leading to India’s civil resources being placed under International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of economic developments, out of India’s largest direct investors, the US ranks number 1. India’s major exports are in the manufacturing sector, closely followed by non-financial services, which predominantly includes the software development industry. The US Department of State mentions that the major American items that have been imported by India include aircraft, fertilisers, computer hardware, scrap metal and medical equipment. The US accounts for a direct investment of $10 billion to India annually. Yet, the hindrance posed by tariff and non-tariff barriers includes agreement on the insecticides manufactured by US companies that may be sold throughout India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Donald Trump’s Presidential Visit and its Diplomatic Repercussions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The population of the Indian diaspora living in the US accounts to 4 million, which constitute slightly over 1% of the US population. Considering the US election due for November 2020, many international observers have regarded this visit as an attempt to secure the vote bank of the Indo-Americans. India and the US have issued a joint statement by proclaiming the US-India ties to the level of “comprehensive global strategic partnership.” An attempt to make defence manufacturers part of each other’s supply chains and an assurance to strengthen homeland security to resist global terrorism was made. A twin arms deal amounting to $3.5 billion for 6 Apache attack helicopters and 24 Seahawk anti-submarine warfare helicopters have been inked. Further, a $1.9 billion for missile defence system awaits in the pipeline. There have been talks to revitalise the Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (US, India, Australia and Japan) initiative on areas such as counter-terrorism and maritime security. Moreover, a collaboration for the Blue Dot Network and escalating tensions over China’s Belt and Road initiative has strengthened collaboration on regional infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Affairs Survey conducted by Gallup (US Analytics and Advisory company) in 2015 states that “Americans perceive India as their 6th favourite nation in the world.” 74% of Americans viewed India favourably in 2017 and 72% in 2019. While all aspects of the economic relations between the two countries are improving, the people-to-people relationship is also getting better. In the words of the Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi, “Relations between India and US aren’t just between two governments, but are people-centric and people-driven.” The bonhomie between the two nations may become stronger if besides military and energy, other areas of cooperation are explored. Much may depend upon the US election results.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Donald Trump, the President of the United States undertook his first official trip to India since he assumed the Presidency in 2016. His 36-hour trip was marked by activities which ranged from travelling across Ahmedabad to Agra, to culminate his trip to Delhi. In the words of Trump himself, “Nobody else got the reception that I got yesterday. We had thousands of people. That was an incredible scene.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Farewell Uncle Sam?</title><link href="/Farewell-Uncle-Sam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Farewell Uncle Sam?" /><published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Farewell-Uncle-Sam</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Farewell-Uncle-Sam">&lt;p&gt;Hollywood, Statue of Liberty, Oprah, Abraham Lincoln, The Empire State Building and Trump’s tweets aren’t the only things the United States of America is famous for. The Big Brother Energytm and invasions are also what makes America Great (again), and the most prominent example of the aforementioned would be the US invasion of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US invaded Afghanistan in October 2001 in response to the September 11, 2001 terror attacks carried out by Al-Qaeda. Taliban, which controlled Afghanistan in 2001 refused to hand over Osama Bin Laden, the man responsible for orchestrating the attacks, resulting in the US invasion of Afghanistan and consequently, an 18-year-long war. In 2004, the US and its allies were successful in removing the Taliban from power, however, as soon as the allies backed out, the Taliban grew again. So despite having a US-backed government in Afghanistan, the Taliban controlled over 70% of the country. Following which, the then-in-power Bush administration established US troops and military bases in Afghanistan to fight the Taliban and prevent the country from becoming a terrorist base of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US-Taliban war is one of the most gruesome and costly wars fought by the US, leaving behind innumerable casualties and war-aggrieved families. Its cost exceeds over $2 trillion, excluding post-war care for veterans and injured soldiers. Thousands of Afghans were displaced and killed, and Afghanistan currently retains the largest refugee population in the world. Yet the war was internationally recognised as a necessary evil because the US’s withdrawal would engender a Taliban-ruled Afghanistan, and Taliban has made no attempts to hide its inclination towards harbouring and creating terrorist organisations. The Trump administration, however, does not agree to the US’s presence in Afghanistan as necessary. They asserted that the war was a drain on the US’s resources and that the US had ‘no need’ to fight a war for someone else. These statements, no matter how contrary to past US dealings with other countries (Vietnam and Syria to name a few) resonated with the masses. And President Trump’s penchant for power-moves and ‘businessman-like’ deals consequently paved the way for a ‘peace accord’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negotiations began in 2019, and finally, on 29 February 2020, the US signed the peace accord with the Taliban. Under the accord, in exchange for the withdrawal of the US troops, Taliban agreed to not associate with terrorist organisations such as ISIS, Al-Qaeda or any other militant group. It agreed to not allow the use of Afghan territory to plot, organise or launch attacks on the US and its allies. The US troops are expected to evacuate within 14 months for the agreement to hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terms further negotiated for a peaceful power-sharing agreement to be agreed upon between the Afghanistan government and Taliban within the 14-month withdrawal period. This clause claims the protection of the US-backed Afghan government from the Taliban during the negotiation. Furthermore, the US has agreed to release 5,000 Taliban prisoners held by the Afghani forces in return for the 1,000 members of the Afghan forces. The US has also promised to facilitate the removal of penalties and sanctions imposed by the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem arises, however, due to the ‘secret annexes’ in the peace accord. The members and MPs who were made abreast with the two classified annexes have claimed them to be nebulous and are sceptical of the success of the peace accord. They feel that the terms in the annex are insufficient and unlikely to hold the Taliban accountable to its terms. The Afghan government officials fear that the Taliban would not adhere to the stipulations of the accord, reports and recent tweets by the Taliban have also provided little relief. News reports of the Taliban violating the week-old peace accord have surfaced. A recent report by &lt;em&gt;NBC News&lt;/em&gt; claims to have intel that the Taliban does not intend to abide by the contract, and US allies and the public are now wary of the peace accord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary stakeholders in this deal, the Afghanistan government and the civilians, were largely kept on the periphery of the agreement. The government fears that the US troops will withdraw regardless of the Taliban’s defection. Afghani officials and governments have become reliant on the USA’s protection and financial assistance, rendering them unequipped to deal with the troop’s withdrawal in the face of an incoming onslaught by the Taliban. The most vulnerable to this treaty would be the Afghani women and children, who, in a very likely scenario of the Taliban regaining control, have the most to lose under their oppressive regime. Public flogging and execution, no rights and being denied their education and freedom are some of their most common fears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peace accord is not expected to sustain itself once the troops depart, leaving Afghanistan vulnerable to the Taliban. Policymakers and diplomats augur a Taliban regime being established shortly after. A direct consequence of the same would be upon the neighbouring countries of Pakistan, Iran, India and even China. With no US troops to fight, their focus would lie on gaining more power and territory. Perhaps, the most ludicrous aspect of this treaty is that, by the virtue of entering into an agreement with the Taliban to prevent terrorism, they have also entered into an agreement with an officially listed terrorist group, the Haqqani Network. This network is known for its campaign of suicide bombings. The network’s leader, Sirajuddin Haqqani, is the Taliban’s deputy leader and military commander, hence, further reducing the likelihood of any success in this endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fragility of this peace accord has not escaped the US government, Secretary of the State, Mike Pompeo has even acknowledged that they ‘expected the road to be difficult’. Taliban has attacked the Afghan government more than 70 times since February 29, in direct violation of the agreement, and the US government hasn’t done much besides issuing slight rebukes and warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seen the toll this war has taken on the US, no one can fault them for withdrawing, however, a pertinent point of contention remains as to why should the US fight and ensure that the peace accord holds before leaving? The answer to this, perhaps, lies in the historical precedent set by the US itself. The US has often claimed itself to be the ‘Harbinger of Democracy’, having fought wars and invaded countries to secure freedom and sovereignty. Similarly, upon entering Afghanistan in 2001 and subsequently establishing troops and beginning a decade-long tussle, the United States made peace its primary aim in Afghanistan. One cannot also ignore the harmful and potentially disastrous consequences of the troops backing out without a stable arrangement in place. The Land of Liberty promised help against the Taliban to the people and the government of Afghanistan, it now remains to be seen whether they fulfill this promise or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Hollywood, Statue of Liberty, Oprah, Abraham Lincoln, The Empire State Building and Trump’s tweets aren’t the only things the United States of America is famous for. The Big Brother Energytm and invasions are also what makes America Great (again), and the most prominent example of the aforementioned would be the US invasion of Afghanistan.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Bukayo Saka Should Be In England’s Euro 2020 Squad</title><link href="/Bukayo-Saka-2020-Squad" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Bukayo Saka Should Be In England’s Euro 2020 Squad" /><published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bukayo-Saka-2020-Squad</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bukayo-Saka-2020-Squad">&lt;p&gt;During a difficult season for Arsenal, one of the major positives has been the rise of 18-year-old Bukayo Saka. The Hale End graduate started the season off with impressive performances on the left-wing, notably away at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sKrmDr0d6_0&quot;&gt;Eintracht Frankfurt&lt;/a&gt; and Manchester United, but it has been at left-back where Saka has really caught the eye in the last few months. With England’s dearth of talent at left-back, relative to their options on the right, it is worth considering whether Bukayo Saka should be in the Three Lions’ squad for Euro 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering he was only known as a tricky, slight, teenage winger a few months ago, it is difficult to overstate how impressive Saka has been since his move into defence following injuries to Kieran Tierney and Sead Kolasinac. He has held his own in the Premier League against more experienced and physical right-wingers, showing himself to be adept in 1v1 duels. What’s more is that Saka has also rarely been caught out positionally for someone who has such little experience of the position. This ability to learn on the fly bodes well for his progression for England and Arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with his solid defensive play, he has still managed to flourish as an attacking force; the 18-year-old is frequently being used as one of the focal points of Arsenal’s attack. Slick combination play with the likes of Mesut Ozil and Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang results in Saka often finding himself in threatening positions where he can whip in a quality left-footed cross to the Arsenal striker, as he did for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mom_VOTUxmk&quot;&gt;Eddie Nketiah’s equaliser vs Everton&lt;/a&gt;. Should he make the England squad, then the likes of Harry Kane and Tammy Abraham will be licking their lips over the prospect of feasting off of his crosses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned, England’s current crop of left-backs are distinctly average, with there being no one on the level of Kyle Walker, Aaron Wan-Bissaka or Trent Alexander-Arnold. Ben Chilwell is currently manager Gareth Southgate’s first choice and, despite some patchy form this season, seems virtually assured of his place in the Euros squad. Danny Rose has joined Chilwell in the last five England squads, but this season has been a disappointing one for Rose after having been dropped at Tottenham by Jose Mourinho. He is trying to resurrect his career at Newcastle but still looks some way off the player he was a few years ago and he certainly won’t be assured of his place in the Three Lions’ squad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the World Cup in Russia two years ago, it was Ashley Young who was the starter at left-wing-back, however, the veteran hasn’t added to his 39 caps since, despite recently establishing himself in the XI of title-challenging Inter Milan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teenager Brandon Williams has looked solid, if unspectacular, since taking Young’s place in the Manchester United side. However, like Young, his propensity to cut inside onto his prefered right foot isn’t ideal when trying to build fluid attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2014, the thought of Luke Shaw being an afterthought for Euro 2020 would have been laughable, but a rough five and a half year stint at Old Trafford has meant he is currently just that. Shaw has featured just twice for England in the last four years but still represents a solid option for Southgate, especially since having proven himself to be competent in a back-three in recent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Tackles/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Key Passes/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Interceptions/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Passes Completed/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dribbles Completed/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dribbled Past/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;England Caps&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Ben Chilwell&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;58.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Danny Rose&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;45.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Bukayo Saka&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:bold&quot;&gt;2.1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;36.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Luke Shaw&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;60.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Brandon Williams&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;49.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Ashley Young&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;49.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Stats from all competitions in the 2019/20 season (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whoscored.com/&quot;&gt;www.whoscored.com/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking someone of Bukayo Saka’s age and inexperience to a major tournament wouldn’t be unprecedented for England with the likes of Michael Owen and Wayne Rooney famously capturing the world’s attention as 18-year-olds in 1998 and 2004 respectively. Whilst it would be outlandish to claim Saka is on par with those two, Marcus Rashford, Theo Walcott and Shaw have also gone to major tournaments as teenagers and even though they didn’t make a significant impact it provided the (then) youngsters with a great experience moving forward. Rashford looks on his way to becoming a key-player for England and this would have likely been the case for Walcott and Shaw had injuries not derailed their progress. Walcott’s hat-trick as a 19-year-old in Zagreb against a tricky Croatia side serves as an example of how getting youngsters integrated into the international set-up can benefit their progress on the big stage in the following years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst he may be deserving of a place in the England squad by the summer, it is important to bear in mind that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football/50886874&quot;&gt;Saka has still not committed his international allegiance to the country of his birth&lt;/a&gt;. Born in East London to Nigerian parents, Saka hasn’t ruled out playing for the Super Eagles and, if they don’t act fast, England could find themselves losing out on a precocious talent in similar circumstances to how they let Wilfried Zaha slip through their grasp and into an Ivory Coast shirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be understandable if Gareth Southgate elects not to take Saka to the Euros in favour of a safer choice, especially considering the England squad is already relatively young and inexperienced. With that being said, Bukayo Saka could be the perfect wildcard addition to fill a problem position and there’s no reason to think he isn’t capable of making the squad should he continue his good form.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">During a difficult season for Arsenal, one of the major positives has been the rise of 18-year-old Bukayo Saka. The Hale End graduate started the season off with impressive performances on the left-wing, notably away at Eintracht Frankfurt and Manchester United, but it has been at left-back where Saka has really caught the eye in the last few months. With England’s dearth of talent at left-back, relative to their options on the right, it is worth considering whether Bukayo Saka should be in the Three Lions’ squad for Euro 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">HER: A Tale of Blurred Lines of Love</title><link href="/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HER: A Tale of Blurred Lines of Love" /><published>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love</id><content type="html" xml:base="/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; What are you doing? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; I'm just sitting here, looking at the world and writing a new piece of music. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; Can I hear it? What's this one about?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; Well, I was thinking, we don't really have any photographs of us. And I thought this song could be like a photo that captures us at this moment in our life together.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; Aw, I like our photograph. I can see you in it.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; I am.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t watched this movie yet, you need to figure out the most mundane and ordinary day to sit and binge through this cinematic work of art because you’ll need a good two hours later to stare at the wall and think about it. &lt;em&gt;A little later in the week and in all the still and noiseless moments of your life too&lt;/em&gt;. But why are we talking about a six-year-old movie? Primarily because &lt;em&gt;Her&lt;/em&gt; is a movie that stands more relevant today than ever and it will remain so for the next century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story spins around a fairly simple and reclusive guy, Theodore Twombly who writes heartwarming letters for a living at a company called (BeautifulHandwrittenLetters.com)[BeautifulHandwrittenLetters.com], letters that’ll make you feel a tingling sensation in your back and curl your toes. He’s your everyday Joe with a sweet and simple appearance, but if you look closely, he has a broken heart from his ex-wife that he is seen trying to mend throughout the movie. &lt;em&gt;Her&lt;/em&gt; is set in an undisclosed time in the future, where technology has taken over the human life threefold than it does now, trickling down human interaction to its least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it’s completely normal for us to meet somebody via the internet or social media, talk to them, laugh with them, and maybe even fall in love with them in the process. Meeting the old fashioned way isn’t what you get to see very often- a café, two corner booths and eyes meeting over the same order of Irish coffee from across the room. Instead, it starts with a follow request or a right swipe. If that’s our cultural identity, then it’s not going too far to say that you can fall in love with an operating system; as shown in this ensemble by Spike Jonze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you gulped a little too hard at that, then sit tight because this story is all about the struggle of the self, about thinning the boundaries of the real and the unreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an adventure of the protagonist Theodore Twombly, who purchases a new operating system to better his life, exclusively designed for the personal needs of each individual. This operating system names herself Samantha, who is an ever-evolving device, learning from humans and picking up on their habits. He carries her around, shares the little and larger things about his day and most importantly- laughs wholeheartedly with her. He befriends her over their shared humour and easiness of being together which ultimately leads to falling in love with her, so much so that he isn’t afraid to accept it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound ridiculous to think of someone loving an inanimate object such as an OS but the intricacy with which Spike Jonze has written it and Joaquin Phoenix has flawlessly personified the character would take you on a roller coaster of emotions throughout the two hours of this movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A light banter over the phone becomes their everyday routine and Samantha feels more like a human with every passing minute, and so does their relationship. This delusion is conjured skillfully by the writer through the seclusion of characters from the world and the empathising nature of Theodore’s loneliness. The lightness in him and the calming effect of his presence gives a nice contrast to the brazenly out-there idea of the movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only point of human contact that Theodore has is his neighbour and college best friend, Amy who provides him with little bits of sanity now and then, as most of our friends do for us. Telling them your innermost thoughts that sound beyond normal in your head, somehow begin to gain a sense of sanity as you voice it out to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Amy tells him that she has become best friends with her OS since she left her husband, Theodore gathers the courage to say it out loud for the first time: that he is dating an operating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He somewhere feels that this is insane but Amy senses that and sympathises with him telling him that, “Falling in love is kind of like a form of socially acceptable insanity”. This one line ties together the essence of the movie and the argument of what is acceptable and what isn’t. As long as you can accommodate and accept an idea in your head and heart, nothing is too far fetched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, you start to believe in their relationship and the genuineness of Samantha; which is the beauty of the screenplay and the one man tussle of Joaquin Phoenix, who carries us with him throughout the movie, never letting us go off the wagon even for a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this misty canvas of emotions comes washing down when one day he wakes up and calls Samantha, only to find out that she’s not there at the other end of the line. He tries in vain to connect to her repeatedly but it’s as if she vanished from his phone, his life. And in that brief second, their entire relationship flashes before his eyes, he’s panting and almost subliminal. Even though she’s back in the next moment, he realizes how fleetingly real this relationship was. One minute it was everything, and the next there was no trace of it in the world- it fizzled into thin air. For a spectator, this instance was like a snap out of a daydream as a huge underlying reality of the story hits you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, Theodore’s ex-wife, whom he has always had unresolved feelings for, learns about his relationship with an operating system, Samantha, and blatantly tells him that he is crazy to pursue such a relationship just because he cannot handle ‘real emotions.’ She even goes on to say that he had always wanted a wife without the challenges of actually dealing with something real. Her reaction gives us an insight into Theodore’s deepest insecurities and a more clear view of why his relationship with Samantha worked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes into a dour state of introspection and starts developing issues with Samantha. They fight, they cry and emotionalise, consummating the final step of their relationship and making it as human as it could have been. But the reality once slipped away, only drifts farther and farther in his mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What finally happens to Samantha and Theodore is something I’d leave up to you to comprehend for yourself. I’d urge you to go and watch the movie, for the feeling that it ends with is not something any writer can pen down in a review, let alone myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I can comment on is the complex and mind-twisting path chosen by Spike Jonze to portray modern love, the paradox of solipsism and its untwined relationship with technology in the 21st century. It makes us question the boundaries of love? The line that separates the real and the unreal is no more clear to one. This movie toys with the questions we’re too afraid to ask ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the tangled beauty of this story - it leaves you with an unfamiliar feeling in the pit of your stomach towards the end because we humans like to know the why and how of everything, and that is something that this movie does not promise.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Theodore Twombly: What are you doing? Samantha: I'm just sitting here, looking at the world and writing a new piece of music. Theodore Twombly: Can I hear it? What's this one about? Samantha: Well, I was thinking, we don't really have any photographs of us. And I thought this song could be like a photo that captures us at this moment in our life together. Theodore Twombly: Aw, I like our photograph. I can see you in it. Samantha: I am.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Regret in The American Dream</title><link href="/The-Regret-in-The-American-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Regret in The American Dream" /><published>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Regret-in-The-American-Dream</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Regret-in-The-American-Dream">&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream&quot;&gt;first article&lt;/a&gt; for The Pangean was on how Martin Scorsese felt about the ‘American Dream’ and expressed the same through the medium of his movies. In 2019, he took another attempt at revising that same theme with &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt;. It feels like a full-circle moment when I was asked to write on it because the first thing that I thought of when I watched this 3-hour epic was that this was Scorsese looking back introspectively on his own career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right off the bat, I want to note that* The Irishman* has very little similarity to &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt;, or The &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Mean Streets&lt;/em&gt;, apart from style. The first shot of the movie shows a heavily made-up Robert De Niro, playing an old, wheelchair-ridden Frank Sheeran, narrating his story in flashback-style. If I had known better, this was indication enough that &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; is not going to be the type of borderline glorification that Martin Scorsese has been accused of throughout his career. His movies generally start with the energy of youth - Jordan Belfort’s infectious but immature energy to be a bull, Henry Hill with an iconic line about how he always wanted to be a gangster or even the excitement of running casinos mixed with all the sins you can think of in &lt;em&gt;Casino&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; progresses with showing how Frank Sheeran, an American of Irish descent, started off as a meat truck driver after leaving army service, a possibly traumatic experience where he may have killed unarmed Germans who were willing to surrender, just as a revenge statement. He shows no qualms in joining the Bufalino crime family and doing questionable things for money and, hence, a more stable family life. He would do as he was told, no questions asked. Loyalty took first place above all other ambitions. The violence in the movie was subtle, there was nothing flashy about the editing of the movie in terms of it making the movie more frenetic, and everyone who was killed in the movie was just done off without a lot of hullabaloos, unlike Scorsese’s other films. Mind you,* The Irishman* has lots of killings. The difference was that most of them were hardly shown visually, but merely explained. In stark contrast, &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; has an entire montage showing how wiseguys Tommy, Jimmy and Henry eliminated people that could have troubled them. In &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt;, every person who died before Sheeran was accompanied by a text infographic showing their name, date of death and cause of death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It speaks volumes about what Scorsese wants to achieve through the movie. Is it to make the mob life more interesting, and show what attracts people to that side of life? If that was the case, there would really be nothing separating &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Casino&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Mean Streets&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;. Rather, &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; has more in common with &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; than any of his other films. &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; starts very similarly - after a celebrated, but incredibly rough boxing career marred by relationship issues, anger, abuse, a prison sentence, and a run with the Mafia, Jake LaMotta becomes a stand-up comedian. He looks at himself in the mirror, and monologues about the point of his life. He’s become much fatter compared to his boxer days and looks withered out. Scorsese may often be accused of having extremely stock female characters that aren’t well fleshed out. However, to his credit, he doesn’t spare anything in ripping the character of his male leads to shreds, to the extent that they may be unlikeable. At the same time, the world that they live in draws you, and you can’t resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; is not that world. The second hour of the movie focuses on Sheeran’s relationship with Jimmy Hoffa, the leader of the Teamsters Union of workers, and thereby a hugely-respected man. All of the problematic things Hoffa does is for the betterment of his workers. Otherwise, he has a joyful code of conduct in life. He loves his family and turns out to be a better father figure to Sheeran’s younger daughter, Peggy, than Sheeran himself. This hour of the movie is extremely wholesome - Sheeran discovers that you can form personal, endearing relationships with the people you work for. For him, that person was Hoffa. This friendship sounds hardly like any of the partnerships that were present in Scorsese’s filmography. They were based on a code of brotherhood: friendly enough that neither would screw the other over, but professional enough that each knows his boundaries. Sheeran helped Hoffa build his American Dream, where the workers feel empowered and have maximum bargaining power. It wouldn’t take Hoffa one day to shut down operations across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoffa was jailed for jury tampering in 1963 by the Kennedy administration. According to the movie, he wanted to come back to power in the Union. His replacement, Frank Fitzsimmons, was handing out interest-free loans to the Bufalino family. Hoffa was barred by Nixon from interacting with any labour organisation in any capacity. He also had a prison spat with Anthony Provenzano, former vice-president of the Union and New Jersey mob leader. The Mafia was wary of Hoffa’s rise to power, which may have disrupted their arrangements with the Union. Soon enough, Russell Bufalino called for his head, and ordered Frank Sheeran to do it, at least, according to the movie’s stance: nobody can actually confirm who was involved in Hoffa’s disappearance. The book written by Charles Brandt is vocal about Sheeran’s direct involvement, and hence, the movie as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next 30 minutes are spent in patience, waiting up to the moment where Sheeran shoots Hoffa. The 30 minutes after are spent in Sheeran trying to process the emotion of regret, but possibly failing, or being unable to move on. He goes to confession, brags about Jimmy Hoffa to his hospice care with pride as if he were a rockstar in his time, all the while trying to grapple with what he had truly done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One look at a summary of the movie tells you that it plays about the classic elements of a standard mob movie very subtly. The idea that you could bend your moral code just a little each day so that you could achieve your ideal of the American Dream, got tested with each questionable act, or each emotion that Sheeran was unable to process. The code of loyalty, brotherhood and business, that so tightly binds mobs in gangster movies was broken down in the most emotional way possible. What Scorsese may have done before is show downfall in terms of a sentence served, a physical manifestation of Icarus flying too close to the sun. Nobody was shown to be eaten from the insides, unlike Frank Sheeran here. It wasn’t the prison sentence he served later that was his penance; it was the fact that he had to live with being unable to truly feel for Hoffa, despite wanting to so badly because he loved him. One may argue that the American Dream doesn’t care about how you feel: in a race to consume everything by growing to be the best version of yourself financially, you forget about your mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, mob movies are tied by familial bonds, which become another foundation for the American Dream as defined by the mafioso, or the genre of movies. Your actions are justified to a fair extent as long as you’re extending the benefits to your family and giving them a happy life. &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; indulged in that idea for the longest time. In &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt;, it hardly mattered. Peggy, Sheeran’s youngest daughter, never looked at him as a father. For all the money and stature that he may have earned, he could never gain the trust of someone who arguably mattered more. What is worse was that Sheeran never truly found out why his daughter was so quiet around him. He never figured out it was a resentment of the violence he perpetrated or the fact that his name was in the papers for all the wrong reasons. He didn’t spend too much time with her either. His being around for her was restricted to financial concern and physical protection, or so says the movie. And &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; then elaborates on why that in itself is so preposterous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like the movie, rather fittingly, this piece feels like an extended epilogue to the first article I wrote for The Pangean. I had no idea &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; would be this entire flip from what old man Marty had done before. I remember laughing so much when I first saw &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas. *I rewatch *The Departed *every time I’m free, *Hugo&lt;/em&gt; was nice too and &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; is also a riot with every viewing. &lt;em&gt;Taxi Driver&lt;/em&gt; is jarring and &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; is wondrous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then who’s cutting these onions? &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; is easily one of the best movies of last year (second-best in this author’s humble opinion) because it does exactly what no one expected: get you teary-eyed for the life of nonagenarian Irish mobster, based on a story that, while unconfirmed, is most likely true, and was heralded by a boomer that has changed the face of cinema as we have known it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pranav Manie</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">My first article for The Pangean was on how Martin Scorsese felt about the ‘American Dream’ and expressed the same through the medium of his movies. In 2019, he took another attempt at revising that same theme with The Irishman. It feels like a full-circle moment when I was asked to write on it because the first thing that I thought of when I watched this 3-hour epic was that this was Scorsese looking back introspectively on his own career.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pole Dancing: Road to the Olympics</title><link href="/Pole-Dancing-Road-to-the-Olympics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pole Dancing: Road to the Olympics" /><published>2020-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Pole-Dancing-Road-to-the-Olympics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Pole-Dancing-Road-to-the-Olympics">&lt;p&gt;Let’s be real, the title sounds interesting to you because at first glance it seems to be an oxymoron. Most of us do not really associate pole dancing with sports. It reminds us of strip clubs and excessively raunchy moves in skimpy clothing. The truth, however, is that the very sexualised act of dancing on a pole requires immense muscle strength and is inherently very artistic: two things that characterise many mainstream sports including gymnastics and diving. Nevertheless, for the longest time, pole dancing in the Western world has been performed only by strippers and none of them were very proud of their work. The stigma surrounding sex work kept the hidden potential of pole dancing under covers for a very long time. But the last two decades has seen some extreme transition in terms of how pole dancing is perceived and practiced; and today, it dreams to be a part of the Olympic programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early 2000s turned people’s heads, as pole dancing began its roller coaster ride to mainstream popularity as a fitness routine. After all, pole dancing undeniably involves intense upper body strength. Many also argue that pole dancing is a form of art. It involves expressing and finding oneself, which is basically what art is for. Besides, who can deny that pole dancing is extremely aesthetically pleasing. More recently, pole dancing has also started on its journey as a move of female empowerment. The first time I came across something like this was when I watched one of my favourite youtubers Devin of the channel Ladylike share her sexual assault story. Her rape had left her in a dark place and she was desperately trying to get back her confidence, and pole dancing helped her find her way out. She talked about S Factor, a pole dancing academy aimed at empowering women and encouraging them to be sexy for themselves rather than someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The S Factor is the brainchild of Sheila Kelley who has been featured in various talk shows including that of Oprah Winfrey. She has also been a speaker at TEDx American Riviera. In her roughly 20 minute long talk titled ‘Lets Get Naked’ she hits on various feminist issues like female objectification and talks about the sexual reclamation of the female body. Kelley was only a young actress when she ended paying a strip club an unwanted visit, and the experience made her fall in love with the art of pole dancing. She went on to write and produce a film where she played a stripper called “Dancing at the Blue Iguana”. She learnt the art of pole dancing and as she reiterates throughout the talk, found herself during the process. She realised that pole dancing is not just about stripping for men, it is a lot more than that. By the end of it all, she knew she had to share her revelation and the art with women across the world. In no time, she gained a massive fan following among women across borders. Her conviction that finding one’s sensual identity had a major positive psychological impact led her to start her own pole dancing company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As pole dancing continued on its ambitious path to get rid of the stigma associated with it, #NotAStripper started trending on Twitter. However, it is difficult to claim that it was well received. Twitterati attacked pole dancers, claiming that their routines were not even half as pleasing as those performed by strippers or that their story was not as important as the multitude of other issues that the modern woman faces. Besides the fact that these people clearly did not get the memo that pole dancers were not really indulging in the art to please others, they also failed to recognise that the aim was to dissociate the art or sport of pole dancing from the stigma associated with stripping. However, many also claimed that the hashtag was a blatant proof of whorephobia that it is deep rooted in the belief that sex work is not really ‘work’. Very soon, stripper and activist Elle Stanger created the #YesAStripper in response. She was once quoted saying “…#NotAStripper and I am like, OK, why is that important? Why do you feel the need to differentiate?” Her hashtag had a significantly larger number of tags than the former and it seemed like a great social media win within a very short span of time. Stanger has also repeatedly said that it was necessary in order to let recreational pole dancers respect and embrace their professions at the fullest. While all these were going on, many even argued that modern pole dancing is the brainchild of strippers and thus, #NotAStripper was borderline disrespectful. However, it seems that pole dance has much older roots than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese Pole is an ancient form of acrobatics born during the Qin and Han dynasties of China between 221 BC and 230 AD. While one can easily spot several similarities between Chinese Pole and Pole Dance, there are some very important divergences. The pole used in the former is much taller, often extending upto 30 feet. The length gave it a necessary wobble during the acrobatic performances. Besides, pole dancing adds dancing, calisthenics and gymnastics to make it more erotic or aesthetically pleasing, depending on the audience and requirement. Another form of exercise bearing close resemblance to the modern day pole dance is Mallakhamba, an ancient Indian sport. This sport involves gymnasts performing aerial yoga postures on a pole or a vertical rope. However, it is undeniable that modern day pole dance is very different from these ancient forms of ‘sport’ and in fact, was born in the strip clubs. Clearly, Chinese Pole and Mallakhamba were performed as sports in the past, in stark contrast to the conventional pole dancing in gentlemen’s clubs. However, some pole dancers have actually practiced the art as a sport for a while now and envision a future where pole dancing is a regular at the Olympics. Various figures across the world have advocated for this cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years many have backed the inclusion of various sports, which were fast-tracking their way to their main-stream acceptance as a legitimate sport, in the Olympics. The non-existent formal and popular definition of the term ‘sport’ makes it easy to accept or deny the status to various activities by the general public. Case in point, cheerleading. Often appreciated for the very enthusiastic and artistic moves alongside the incredibly difficult jumps and gymnastics, cheerleading is often dismissed easily in sports discussions. Many consider sports to be an activity that is inherently competitive in nature and follows certain rules. Cheerleading, however, is popularly seen as an activity solely meant to entertain the crowd during various sporting events. Many also believe that there is no proper mechanism by which cheerleading competitions can be judged. Proponents of the debate argue that cheerleading requires at least, if not more, as much effort, practice and dedication as mainstream gymnastics. Besides, they claim that the problems associated with judging cheerleading tournaments are encountered in sports like figure skating, synchronised swimming and gymnastics too and thus, the argument is, in the mildest terms, frail. However, after the immense success of having breakdancing in the 2018 Youth Olympics, ‘Breaking’ was added to the program of the 2024 Games to be held at Paris. This came in response to the IOC’s aim to make the Olympics “more urban” and “more artistic”. Climbing, skateboarding and surfing were also added to the programme after a unanimous vote by the IOC’s session in Lausanne, Switzerland on June 25, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various sports federations and commissions have come up with varying definitions of the term  ‘sports’. The Global Association of International Sports Federation’s definition of a sport has many requirements. Besides the fact that the proposed ‘sport’ must have an element of competition and should not rely on any element of luck, it should also not pose any risks to the health or safety of the participants. In addition, the equipment used cannot be provided by a single supplier. Going by this definition and the fact that the IOC is eager to revolutionise the Games to be more “artistic” and “urban”, I see no reason why the process of inclusion of pole dancing in the Olympics is being delayed. This ‘process’ involves various steps, many of which have already been achieved by the sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katie Coates, the woman behind the International Pole Sports Federation (IPSF) and pole dancing’s 11 year struggle to be recognised as a professional sport, always dreamt of seeing pole dancing in the Olympics. In 2006, Coates conducted a survey to review the public’s opinion on pole dancing as a sport and over 10,000 people voted in the favour of it being included in the Olympics. In 2008, she collaborated with Tim Trautman and started working on the IPSF and coined the term ‘pole sports’. Soon, various federations across the world cropped up and competitive pole sports started gaining attention. However, this was not easy especially for Coates. Abuses were hurled at her as many didn’t appreciate her efforts to reinvent pole dancing as a serious sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It cannot be denied that the art of pole dancing is dominated by women, thanks to its exploitative history. In fact, a startling majority of pole sports federations across the world are run by women. Over the years, pole dancing has been harshly criticised as an antithesis to movements of female empowerment. Ariel Levy’s book* Female Chauvinist Pigs: Women and the Rise of Raunch Culture* is one such literature. In the book she writes, “spinning greasily around a pole… is more of a parody of female sexual power than an expression of it. How is resurrecting every stereotype of female sexuality that feminism endeavoured to banish for good for women?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many women who actually practice pole dancing vehemently criticise this view. Third wave feminists argue that women should have control over their lives and their decisions. The ability to choose a career path, manner of expression, dressing and so on is integral to the feminist movement. Therefore, the choice to be a pole dancer and or or a stripper is empowering as long as the woman concerned retains control over her decisions. However, the stigma against pole dancing perpetuates even among the most liberal-minded of people. An incident that bears testimony to the same took place back in September, 2016. An event aimed at ending violence against women and the popular culture of victim blaming called the “Take Back the Night” march was going to be organised, and London Abused Women’s Centre (LAWC) was due to participate in the same. However, on finding out that a pole fitness studio would be in attendance, they immediately withdrew their participation. The programme manager for LAWC was quoted saying, “we will not solve women’s oppression by dancing on a pole”. In countries like China, Russia and several South and Central American countries, however, pole dance never existed in the heavily sexualised form that people in other countries popularly know of today. In fact, in Mexico, pole sports is funded alongside other Olympic sports. This includes provisions for sports science testing and youth programmes. Although pole sports found it easy to establish itself as a serious sport in these countries, the stigma of sex work continues to haunt athletes in the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major set back came in 2011 when it came to light that an estimated 95% of all Pole Sports athletes were women, something that the IOC did not appreciate. However, this did little to discourage Coates and 2012 witnessed the inaugural edition of the World Pole Sports Championship with the humble participation count of 38 women and 5 men. By the following year, the youth category was introduced and the first year saw the participation of only 7 athletes. As the athletes continued to fight to establish pole sports as a serious sport, the need for a rulebook became very apparent. Very soon a rulebook was devised that lists down the compulsory moves and categories of skills required for ranking each routine. Initially the book comprised only 20 moves but by 2018, it was already 170 pages long. New techniques are invented and added every year. After hiccuping its way through the years, 2017 brought in great news for pole sports enthusiasts. The male and novice categories were introduced in the World Pole Sports Championship which increased male participation by 70% and an 80% increase in participation in the youth category was observed. A total of a staggering 229 athletes from 36 countries across the globe competed in the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in spite of all this, Katie Coates’ goal of making pole sports an Olympic event remained unfulfilled. She reached her first milestone in the direction of the same in 2017 when GAISF announced its recognition of pole dancing as a professional sport. Coates was quoted saying, “In the early 2000’s people started doing it as fitness routine and taking away the sex stigma, so no high heels and making it accessible for average people. Pole dancing is not like everyone thinks it is, you need to actually watch it to understand.” The IPSF continues to emphasise that pole sports is all about “athleticism and technical merit” and that it is in line with “other Olympic standard sports such as gymnastics, diving and ice skating.” They argue that even though the act of pole dancing is popularly associated with strip clubs, a performance does not have to contain an erotic element. By extension, the IPSF deems pole sports appropriate for all ages and audiences and thus, runs competitions for athletes between the ages of 10 and 65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three basic criteria that a particular sport needs to meet in order for it to be eligible for Olympic consideration. Firstly, it needs to be signed to the World Anti-Doping Agency. It also must be a full member of GAISF and finally, it must have at least 50 national federations. Pole sports currently fulfills only the first criteria. In February, 2020, GAISF awarded Observer Status for a further 2 years to pole sports. However, there is still a long way to go before we probably actually see pole sports in the Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that pole dancing has come a long way from its days of being a profession that required women to strip for men in exchange for money while society continued to look down upon them to a sport that is fast gaining attention and support to be featured in the Olympics. A little more than two decades ago pole dancers were afraid of even acknowledging their profession in fear of being seen as ‘too easy’ and harassed. Today, women are using the art of pole dancing for their sensual awakening and learning how to be sexy for themselves. A large number of people across the world have incorporated pole dancing into their fitness routines. Many others, irrespective of their gender and age, are embracing pole dancing as a form of expression and sport. Presently, it is fast turning into a symbol of feminism much the same way the mini skirt has become the symbol of women’s liberation over the years. However, whether or not pole dancing will be able to make space for itself in the Olympics is a question only time can answer. For now, that continues to be the goal that athletes have in mind as they fight for recognition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Let’s be real, the title sounds interesting to you because at first glance it seems to be an oxymoron. Most of us do not really associate pole dancing with sports. It reminds us of strip clubs and excessively raunchy moves in skimpy clothing. The truth, however, is that the very sexualised act of dancing on a pole requires immense muscle strength and is inherently very artistic: two things that characterise many mainstream sports including gymnastics and diving. Nevertheless, for the longest time, pole dancing in the Western world has been performed only by strippers and none of them were very proud of their work. The stigma surrounding sex work kept the hidden potential of pole dancing under covers for a very long time. But the last two decades has seen some extreme transition in terms of how pole dancing is perceived and practiced; and today, it dreams to be a part of the Olympic programme.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thailand’s UCS: How A Middle Income Country Achieved Universal Health Coverage</title><link href="/Thailand-s-UCS" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thailand’s UCS: How A Middle Income Country Achieved Universal Health Coverage" /><published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Thailand-s-UCS</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Thailand-s-UCS">&lt;p&gt;In 2000, Thailand was in the midst of a healthcare crisis. The year marked the death of more than 17,000 children under the age of five, of which two-thirds were suffering from easily preventable communicable diseases. 20% of the poorest households in the country also slipped Below Poverty Line due to hefty payments on healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2001, massive reforms were undertaken by the winning party, Thai Rak Thai, which led to the introduction of Thailand’s Universal Coverage Scheme (UCS). The UCS, which spread to all provinces the following year, provides outpatient, inpatient and emergency care, which is available to all according to need. Within a decade, the program covered 48 million citizens or 98% of the Thais.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of their achievement must not be understated. Even today, developed, high-income countries such as the US struggle with schemes like universal health insurance coverage. But Thailand, a developing country, with its meagre per capita income of $1900 (in 2001, at the time of the initiation of this policy) achieved astounding improvement in access and quality of healthcare without putting too much pressure on the fiscal vaults. So, how did Thailand achieve the near-impossible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;history-of-thailands-uhc&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History of Thailand’s UHC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning three decades ago, Thailand’s health care policy first covered the poor, then the near-poor, the formal sector employees, and finally the children and the elderly, through various publicly funded and contributory schemes until it reached 71% of the entire population in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1975, Thailand launched its ‘first medical care programme.’ The starting population coverage was 30%, but the service coverage, although comprehensive, was not deep. It then, gradually, covered the near-poor in 1985, based on a voluntary, publicly subsidised healthcare scheme. From 1982 to 1986, despite the economic crisis, the government decided to freeze all capital investment in the urban hospitals and shifted the limited resources to build rural district hospitals and health centres with extensive training of community-level health professionals and rural doctors. This resulted in the rapid, nationwide expansion of rural health services and broadened access to 15 essential health services at the community level. Around one million village health volunteers were recruited and trained to assist health personnel in providing basic healthcare and health education to their communities. The volunteers helped distribute essential drugs and get children vaccinated; they also built sanitary latrines and clean-water reservoirs and implemented nutrition programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal sector employees were covered by the contributory Social Security Health Insurance in 1992. Across developing countries, assurance of the quality of healthcare continues to be the most persistent challenge of government-funded schemes. But programs initiated in the 1970’s helped Thailand invest heavily in infrastructure, build hospitals and clinics and train medical personnel to support universal coverage. After the implementation of the Universal Coverage Scheme, this long-term investment in the sector finally paid off as relationships between doctors and patients transformed completely. Before, patients paid a fee to their doctors when they visited the hospital. After 2001, the government paid hospitals, including salaries for staff, and financially incentivised medical professionals to serve unpopular rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country’s health scheme is primarily funded by general income tax and costs only $80 billion annually (2011). The system has successfully reduced infant mortality, decreased workers’ sick days and lightened families’ financial burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;policy-implementation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy Implementation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy provides a benefits package that encompasses a comprehensive set of health interventions stipulated in a contract with the National Health Security Office and the providers, at every level of health service. Further, it is made up of two different components: the health promotion and disease preventive package, and the treatment and care package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For budgeting of the programme, it was decided in 2001 that the UCS would use a capitation payment method. In a capitated contract, the physician, hospital or clinic receives fixed, pre-determined monthly payments per patient enrolled in a health plan. The expenses of the UCS are budgeted under an annual close-ended capitation system that includes each facility’s labour costs to ensure tight budget control. The rate of capitation budget of the UCS increased gradually in the first few years, and, more rapidly, since the fiscal year 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unique feature of Thailand’s healthcare system has been its encouragement of active involvement of CSOs (civil society organisations). These have provided volunteers to the government and have also assisted in policy formulation by providing data on healthcare and in implementation through direct intervention in underdeveloped areas of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time where the just and equitable distribution of healthcare services is becoming an increasingly contentious issue around the world, Thailand has shown that even a middle-income developing country can attain fiscally-responsible universal healthcare. Thailand has cut child mortality rates alongside saving adult lives by providing treatments like antiretroviral therapies and renal replacement therapy. Catastrophic health spending that tends to push people into poverty has been significantly slashed. The correlation between poverty and infant mortality has disappeared and an improvement in the number of people that were prevented from going to work through illness, particularly at the older end of the workforce has been observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 400 million people across the globe still lacking access to healthcare, Thailand’s universal coverage scheme emphasises on focusing on primary health care units by employing methods that are fair, efficient and sustainable. Governments must show immense political commitment, and accountability must be introduced at multiple stages through the creation of several stakeholders and involvement of CSOs to create a system that is fast, effective and equitable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 2000, Thailand was in the midst of a healthcare crisis. The year marked the death of more than 17,000 children under the age of five, of which two-thirds were suffering from easily preventable communicable diseases. 20% of the poorest households in the country also slipped Below Poverty Line due to hefty payments on healthcare.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)</title><link href="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)" /><published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West">&lt;p&gt;I have written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood, dirt, and money — or a combination of the three — are responsible for virtually all conflicts. Of course, the Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception, but on a fundamental level, the radicals on both sides see this as a religious struggle. In the current generation, we tend to secularise everything so that we can pretend to scientifically map out a solution. But with conflict as complicated as the Arab-Israeli conflict, it’s easy to wrap ourselves with the blanket of self-pity and proclaim “Oh! It’s just so complicated. So many different perspectives and feelings. I’ll just never understand it!” It is true that we will never solve the conflict with the systematic precisions given to us by science because not every societal problem can be solved in such a manner. If we want to progress, we have to move beyond the fact no one will completely understand everything about the conflict. However, we must still strive to understand it. Even if religion seems strange or difficult to understand for some, it is essential for one to recognise the control it has over people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going any further, I must highlight my shortcomings. One popular saying I encountered while travelling to Israel was “two Jews have five opinions.” By this, the saying means that there are a lot of internal disagreements within the Jewish community. So when I write “The Jews believe this…” or “Muslims have faith that…”, I implore you to take it with a grain of salt. Every religion is filled with people who dissent on virtually every aspect. There are very few dogmas or beliefs completely agreed upon by an entire religion. Even among radicals, the interpretations of those dogmas are bitterly disputed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask any religious person, even those who have spent decades training and study, if they understand their own religion. I anxiously await to hear back from you. Until you find that person, the world will keep on rotating while the Israeli and Palestinian children die. We will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; understand even just one perspective of this conflict, however, we can (and must) strive to at least understand where both sides are coming from. The Arab-Israel conflict is very much religious conflict. Not just between Jews and Muslims, but also between the different factions within those faiths, in addition to many other religions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Israel and Palestine have religious sites sacred to Christians and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldheritagesite.org/list/Bah%C3%A1%E2%80%99i+Holy+Places&quot;&gt;Baha’i&lt;/a&gt; (and probably more religions), the local population is mostly made up of Jews in Israel and Muslims in Palestine. Although the minorities play a role in the history and international relations, the chief actors — Israel and Palestine — have undeniable ties to the religion of their majorities. Therefore, if one does not understand religion, they will never understand this conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my dear secular readers, religion may superficially seem like a way of life or a set of traditions, but if that is the extent of your view of religion, then allow me to correct your course. This may be true for a casual religious observer, but we are not solely dealing with casual observers, we are dealing with hardliners and fundamentalists. Now I consider myself to be a Christian fundamentalist, so allow me to explain what ‘fundamentalism’ means. Essentially when one is seeking to get to the fundamentals of one’s religion, they are a fundamentalist. For some, it means pursuing a message of peace and love, for others, their perception of the fundamentals of their religion is to rid themselves (and others) of impurity by any means necessary. Again, even within fundamentalists, you can see a wide range of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a person may arrange their day-to-day schedule or diet around their religion. Perhaps take special holidays and be extra motivated to spend time with their family. But any serious or dedicated religious person will tell you, it is also a philosophy. It’s a framework for understanding how the world works and how you must act every day. Both Jews and Muslims may agree to pray often, not eat pork, celebrate certain holidays, or go to a special building for worship, but if you think that makes them essentially the same, you’re a fool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, they are both Abrahamic religions, they both admire similar people (such as Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Elijah to name a few), and they both love a good falafel. But these are all superficial things. Muslims believe the Jewish sacred law books (the Torah) have been corrupted, and their holy book (the Quran), which was completed over a thousand years later, is the true word of God. The fundamentalist Jewish zionists believe God has given them all of the land held by the Palestinians. These are two &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different religions. To expect them to put aside years of bloodshed is one thing, but to expect them to live without resentment for the other’s disrespect for their texts is not an expectation to be taken lightly. Nevertheless, if there is to be peace between Jews and Muslims, what should be the extent of our hopes? And how do we get there? Do we ask them both to just put aside their history? Their faith? Or we ask both of them to search for the fundamentals of their religion. What is the most fundamental aspect of religion? To look after the widows and orphans. Be you a Jew, Muslim, Chrisitan, Buddist, or Scientologist, if this act is not being done, how can you be so sure your religion — or your interpretation of your religion — is being fundamentally carried out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are voices of wisdom and charity on both sides. But because this conflict is so frustrating, people are giving ear to the voices of violence and hatred. In order to preserve peace, we must seek to give a stronger platform to the radicals. Not the radicals for their own religion, but the radicals for peace, justice and love. The radicals for those fundamental virtues all humans strive to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Madajian</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">I have written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.</summary></entry></feed>