<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-03T20:32:30+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Earth to the Robots: Fourth Industrial Revolution</title><link href="/Earth-to-the-robots" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Earth to the Robots: Fourth Industrial Revolution" /><published>2019-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Earth-to-the-robots</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Earth-to-the-robots">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you book something from your favourite food outlet online. A robot cooks the food and it is then delivered by a driverless van or a drone. A world where humans are being replaced by robots no longer seems to be a scene from a Sci-Fi film. Recently, a British online supermarket, ‘Ocado,’ successfully developed a completely automatic system of picking up grocery items for its customers. This is representative of the fact that we are moving towards a &lt;em&gt;Digital Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, which is generally termed as the ‘Fourth Industrial Revolution’ (IR 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to policy makers, the world economy has been on a continuous decline for the last three-four years and a revolution seems to be imperative. In the past, a phase of substantial growth has always been preceded by a revolution. The first such instance dates back to the 1760’s, when Industrial Revolution 1.0 began and was called a &lt;em&gt;Mechanical Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. It revolved around the production of machines that were powered and driven by water and steam. The &lt;em&gt;Technological Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, which was the Second Industrial Revolution, entailed the usage of electrical energy in the manufacturing process, helping in voluminous production. The launch of the internet was the third revolution, which was termed the &lt;em&gt;Virtual Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. The information technology sector had a boom, which promoted the use of electronics to automate the production line and achieve economies of scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry Revolution 4.0 and its impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What sets IR 4.0 apart from the earlier revolutions is the speed at which the revolution is approaching the world, and how its effects will be intangible. Industrial Revolution 4.0 is where the lines between the physical, digital and biological spheres get merged. Production, management and governance systems are likely to be revamped. And policies aligning Artificial intelligence (AI), drones and blockchain technology are already being implemented. Taking up AI technology helps in reducing the operational costs that are involved in the production process, increasing not only efficiency but also revenue. Improvement in the customer experience is also a benefit AI brings with itself. Only 15% of the enterprises in the world are using AI as of today, but 31% are expected to start making use of it in the coming 12 months, according to Adobe. The Fourth Industrial Revolution will allow hyper-connection. This will help connect not only one person to another person, but also machines to people. Amazon’s Alexa works using this technology and is representative of the hyper-connectivity between devices and humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will have an impact on a lot of sectors. The recruitment industry will be impacted in multiple ways. Firstly, less people will be required to be employed as robots will be prevalent. Secondly, the time taken to screen all CVs will get drastically reduced due to the invention of AI softwares, like Ideal, which will help recruiters. Increased automation is already phasing out the role of humans in the manufacturing industry and agriculture sector. It might even affect the pharmaceutical industry by replacing doctors with applications, and chemist with robots. Thirdly, the transportation sector will flourish with applications which help people to track their cab and ensure safety. The retail sector will also receive a lot of traffic as AI technology advances, where these online stores will already know what you want before you even place the order. With cashlessness taking over the globe, the banking sector will face a setback as everything will be online. With a substantial impact on each of these sectors, it surely will lead to digitising the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenges posed to policy makers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data forms the base of the revolution, and for a digital economy, exchange of data holds utmost significance. Facebook’s data breach took everybody by surprise. Security of the IT sector, privacy of data, maintenance of the integrity of the production process and excessive investment are few of the challenges associated with the transformation. Another challenge is the availability of AI talent. These people are in high demand, and the demand-supply ratio is quite skewed. The skill set required by the companies isn’t readily available in the job seekers currently. The maximum supply gap is at the middle-level. If these professionals get lured by high salaries being offered by companies in the developed world, it would not help to bridge the technological gap between developing and developed nations. Further, cities across the world are already grappling with parking space issues. The situation is likely to get worsened as by the end of the next decade, large fleets of drones will be very common and would need parking space. Policy makers have to equip themselves to solve these issues, both big and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are we moving towards a “jobless future”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dystopian future where robots are ubiquitous and humans are merely power sources may be the norm in the coming decades. It is important for humans to change the complexion of the job market. A recent research by McKinsey says that 45% of the current jobs can be automated. Few beginnings have already been made in this direction. Japan has already taken the first step towards this advancement and there are companies that are in the business of “saying sorry.” They hire people to apologise on behalf of others. Not far behind, in China, one can hire boyfriends who can help ladies with shopping and take perfect selfies. Robots that have been created to help humans, may become job creators for humans in future. They will require an entire ecosystem of support staff to optimise their performance and to avail services such as robot maintenance and robot monitoring. Robot ethicists may also be in great demand. But what we need to understand is that AI as whole could be a big benefit to entire humanity if used in the proper direction. What a lot of experts believe is that to make a productive future, it is pertinent for humans to work alongside robots to make the process faster. Therefore, it wouldn’t be a surprise to see robots doing the work which requires mindless skills whilst humans work on managing the system and adding a creative touch to the process. Their jobs would transform, and re-skilling themselves and expanding their skill set is the need of the hour. This goes on to prove that jobs are changing, but not going away, humans simply need to change and keep evolving to fit in society better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manya Manushi</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Imagine you book something from your favourite food outlet online. A robot cooks the food and it is then delivered by a driverless van or a drone. A world where humans are being replaced by robots no longer seems to be a scene from a Sci-Fi film. Recently, a British online supermarket, ‘Ocado,’ successfully developed a completely automatic system of picking up grocery items for its customers. This is representative of the fact that we are moving towards a Digital Revolution, which is generally termed as the ‘Fourth Industrial Revolution’ (IR 4).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Apple’s China problems ft. Future Apple and the Coase Conjecture</title><link href="/Apple-China-Problems" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple’s China problems ft. Future Apple and the Coase Conjecture" /><published>2019-03-28T02:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-28T02:03:00+00:00</updated><id>/Apple-China-Problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Apple-China-Problems">&lt;p&gt;The Apple craze in China is officially over a decade old. During my days in
China, more often than not, I would take the early bus to Tianjin, along with 20
people glued to the glare of their phone screens. Take a walk across a busy
intersection on a weekday morning and you will find dozens of people marching to
work, busy on their smartphones. Not just any smartphones―the Apple iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/lb38KXlz1F2TllikTfKpV3QKflZ14w92D3AnAwq8xIDHYLYtaELdYAwVWzngy9CZL74x2d-m5T_5E5xvwu8CCnNjQQZdB_1EhYWv6BH0lrHxWevAoriAgQAx-uvdWf0jM9KdcirH&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/1509730264519.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why I did not specify which models are most popular is that the
iPhone craze in China is more about class than tech specs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“The people don’t bother which generation it is, as long as it’s an iPhone”--
Mobile store owner, Tianjin, China
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 4th Generation all the way to the latest models, the Chinese make a big
deal out of the iPhone, even if they are not the ones to show it. Despite this,
Apple’s returns for the holiday quarter have not been good. One may attribute
this to the slowing Chinese economy but there are other factors at play. Things
have turned so bad that Apple has had to scale down its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investors.com/news/apple-chinese-iphones-demand-revenue/&quot;&gt;revenue forecasts by an
estimated $5 billion- $9
billion&lt;/a&gt;.
The announcement (made way back in January) sent its stock
&lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/aapl/&quot;&gt;(AAPL)&lt;/a&gt; tumbling, falling by about 10
percentage points, though it has managed to recover since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The struggle for Apple in the Chinese market was real and people were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apnews.com/e0a2c907669c4821814763035b562c55&quot;&gt;simply
not buying iPhones&lt;/a&gt; as
they found the price tag too demanding. What seemed to be the problem? Was there
a new competitor on the block? If so, who was causing the disruption?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is pretty simple, it was Apple - yes, Apple from the Future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break this down, we have to take a look at the Cupertino smartphone giant and
its position in the Chinese market. Yes, they make smartphones, but not just any
smartphone. They are makers of the most sought-after digital product in China.
No, not the BlackBerry. With an iPhone comes class, finesse, style, elegance,
efficiency, exclusivity and a burning hole in the pocket. This is where Apple
separates itself from the Huaweis and the Xiaomis of the market. To be honest,
Apple is a monopoly, with no competition in the foreseeable future. But wait,
our good friend Ronald Coase, a Nobel-winning economist, has something important
to say…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“[A]s soon as the consumers who are willing to pay the monopoly price make
their purchases, the monopolist has an incentive to lower his price and sell to
some of the remaining consumers. Immediately after the next round of sales, the
monopolist would find it worthwhile to lower his price yet again. This process
would continue until all buyers with reservation prices above marginal cost are
served. But rational consumers would anticipate this rapid fall of prices and
wait until the market price reaches its ultimate level before making any
purchases”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that went over your head, do not panic. What he means to say is that in a
market for a durable good (whose resale is not possible) with only one primary
seller (monopoly), once the first lot of goods is sold at a particular price,
the remaining goods are sold at a lower price. Now of the further remaining
goods, some are sold at an even lower price than before and those still
remaining shall be sold even cheaper and this goes on. If a rational buyer
anticipates this and waits for the price to keep falling, he can nab the good at
a much lower price than before. This is what we call the Coase Conjecture. In
effect, the Coase Conjecture holds that a monopolist faces competition from
future incarnations of himself, even though he is the only producer in the
market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we take an iPhone (any generation) to be a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bgr.com/2018/05/28/iphone-x-vs-iphone-7-case-screen-scratches/&quot;&gt;durable&lt;/a&gt;
good, as most of the Chinese market prefers it to be, and Apple as the
monopolist, there will be competition faced by Apple. From whom one may ask?
From the Apple of tomorrow, its future self. And as a result, Apple will be
forced to drive down prices to encourage purchases. Oh, look, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notebookcheck.net/Apple-cuts-iPhone-8-and-XR-prices-in-China-by-20-percent.394146.0.html&quot;&gt;it’s already
taking
place&lt;/a&gt;.
Time to get yourself an iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/ZTgkOCzIQP3kJpWuDzoY5rOmUl3jCg11OTrIRKWgguK_Qc8JXos7VycoRldaD2_HHOTOFTtfklC5r8vT2j8JDSeOcyM1IPjIfgIDQmCm78DiUmHKLevdmnuwMw2le3Yx_MSrDOTk&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/gettyimages-93081350.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people in China know this well enough and this is why they keep sitting on
the iPhones, waiting for prices to drop. That, ladies and gentlemen, is exactly
how most of the Chinese middle class enjoys an excess of iPhones. Nevermind them
showing off models released six years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that there is little Apple can do to rid themselves of such a
predicament. They could try introducing a new spec of such a high quality that
people simply &lt;em&gt;have to have&lt;/em&gt; the new model. Or, as an alternative, they could
simply refuse to lower the price of new models for such a period of time that
people are practically forced into a purchase. But neither of these seem like
realistic solutions. The former will likely fail due to the notional loyalty to
&lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; iPhone. The latter will fall short also, as long as older models continue
to function. The question is then, what next for Apple in the Chinese market? Is
there an unexploited strategy waiting to lure the Chinese public into parting
with their hard earned cash, or is Apple destined to be a fashion item?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shohan Mukherjee</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The Apple craze in China is officially over a decade old. During my days in China, more often than not, I would take the early bus to Tianjin, along with 20 people glued to the glare of their phone screens. Take a walk across a busy intersection on a weekday morning and you will find dozens of people marching to work, busy on their smartphones. Not just any smartphones―the Apple iPhone. The reason why I did not specify which models are most popular is that the iPhone craze in China is more about class than tech specs. “The people don’t bother which generation it is, as long as it’s an iPhone”-- Mobile store owner, Tianjin, China From 4th Generation all the way to the latest models, the Chinese make a big deal out of the iPhone, even if they are not the ones to show it. Despite this, Apple’s returns for the holiday quarter have not been good. One may attribute this to the slowing Chinese economy but there are other factors at play. Things have turned so bad that Apple has had to scale down its revenue forecasts by an estimated $5 billion- $9 billion. The announcement (made way back in January) sent its stock (AAPL) tumbling, falling by about 10 percentage points, though it has managed to recover since. The struggle for Apple in the Chinese market was real and people were simply not buying iPhones as they found the price tag too demanding. What seemed to be the problem? Was there a new competitor on the block? If so, who was causing the disruption? The answer is pretty simple, it was Apple - yes, Apple from the Future. To break this down, we have to take a look at the Cupertino smartphone giant and its position in the Chinese market. Yes, they make smartphones, but not just any smartphone. They are makers of the most sought-after digital product in China. No, not the BlackBerry. With an iPhone comes class, finesse, style, elegance, efficiency, exclusivity and a burning hole in the pocket. This is where Apple separates itself from the Huaweis and the Xiaomis of the market. To be honest, Apple is a monopoly, with no competition in the foreseeable future. But wait, our good friend Ronald Coase, a Nobel-winning economist, has something important to say… “[A]s soon as the consumers who are willing to pay the monopoly price make their purchases, the monopolist has an incentive to lower his price and sell to some of the remaining consumers. Immediately after the next round of sales, the monopolist would find it worthwhile to lower his price yet again. This process would continue until all buyers with reservation prices above marginal cost are served. But rational consumers would anticipate this rapid fall of prices and wait until the market price reaches its ultimate level before making any purchases” If that went over your head, do not panic. What he means to say is that in a market for a durable good (whose resale is not possible) with only one primary seller (monopoly), once the first lot of goods is sold at a particular price, the remaining goods are sold at a lower price. Now of the further remaining goods, some are sold at an even lower price than before and those still remaining shall be sold even cheaper and this goes on. If a rational buyer anticipates this and waits for the price to keep falling, he can nab the good at a much lower price than before. This is what we call the Coase Conjecture. In effect, the Coase Conjecture holds that a monopolist faces competition from future incarnations of himself, even though he is the only producer in the market. Now, if we take an iPhone (any generation) to be a durable good, as most of the Chinese market prefers it to be, and Apple as the monopolist, there will be competition faced by Apple. From whom one may ask? From the Apple of tomorrow, its future self. And as a result, Apple will be forced to drive down prices to encourage purchases. Oh, look, it’s already taking place. Time to get yourself an iPhone. The people in China know this well enough and this is why they keep sitting on the iPhones, waiting for prices to drop. That, ladies and gentlemen, is exactly how most of the Chinese middle class enjoys an excess of iPhones. Nevermind them showing off models released six years ago. It appears that there is little Apple can do to rid themselves of such a predicament. They could try introducing a new spec of such a high quality that people simply have to have the new model. Or, as an alternative, they could simply refuse to lower the price of new models for such a period of time that people are practically forced into a purchase. But neither of these seem like realistic solutions. The former will likely fail due to the notional loyalty to any iPhone. The latter will fall short also, as long as older models continue to function. The question is then, what next for Apple in the Chinese market? Is there an unexploited strategy waiting to lure the Chinese public into parting with their hard earned cash, or is Apple destined to be a fashion item?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Dialectic on Cultural Relativism</title><link href="/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dialectic on Cultural Relativism" /><published>2019-03-28T01:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-28T01:45:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism">&lt;p&gt;In this kaleidoscopic world, cultural diversity is a phenomenon that is standard
to every institution and organisation. Adorned with a plethora of societies and
people dressed in almost every colour on the palette, communicating in different
languages, and following all sorts of customs and traditions, the world
certainly is a beautiful place to live in. Wherever you go, whatever you do, you
are bound to encounter differences and unfamiliarity in the form of people and
the cultures they manifest. With every nook and corner characterised by its own
uniqueness, diversity has certainly become an undeniable reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are always taught to appreciate and embrace this diversity, we must
also be cautious of its potential to cause morally problematic situations.
Consider for instance, how would you feel if someone sticks out their tongue at
you? I am sure humiliated would be the answer. But, what if I tell you that it’s
the way people greet each other in Tibet. This would certainly change things a
little bit, however, still, the whole idea of sticking out your tongue to greet
others would seem unnatural or rather weird to you, something you’ll never dare
to do to out of fear of embarrassment, unless you’re from Tibet of course! This
becomes very troubling. With divergent practices exclusive to each culture,
often questions pertaining to the “ideal conduct” are raised. One may, in fact,
be inclined to ask “Is there an ideal way at all?” And this is where the theory
of cultural relativism steps in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have always been very intimately linked with the culture they’re brought
up in, to the extent that their choices, tastes and behaviours resonate with the
spirit and essence of their culture. Especially with respect to actions and
demeanours, culture is believed to exercise a profound influence on the lives of
people. Therefore, it is quite natural for them to cling onto their own cultural
standards and view other cultures with suspicion. Activities like the
recreational use of cemeteries in Denmark, or the Greek practice of pretending
to spit on a married couple for good luck, or the exhuming of dead bodies by
Trojan tribes, long-ringed necks in Thailand, foot binding in China, etc. might
seem a little strange to hear at first and even impel us to pass a negative
judgement. But, according to the idea of cultural relativism, such judgements
would be wrong and irrational, as they are evaluated on the basis of our own
cultural sense and sensibilities, which fail to cover the moral codes of other
cultures. According to the theory of cultural relativism, the conception of good
and evil, right and wrong, is relative to cultures and so there can never be any
universal moral code of judgment. In other words, we can’t asses other cultures
by employing our own cultural standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes immensely important, given the phenomenal rise in ethnocentrism and
intolerance. With culture assuming supremacy over our lives in governing our
views and judgements, often acceptance of others becomes a little challenging.
In the face of such strict cultural conditioning, it would seem the theory of
cultural relativism is our only way out to advance towards a world characterised
by harmony and brotherhood. This seems to make cultural relativism an impeccable
theory. But is it so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a world with strict cultural relativism. Here, there shall be no
cross-cultural judgements; humanity would function on the principle of
tolerance, almost to the extent that everything would be approved. All cultures,
with their boons and banes, would be embraced blindly, without any reservation.
As a result, if a culture commands its male members to rape women as a
traditional custom, then cultural relativism would be able to do very little
about it. And this is where the theory takes a problematic turn. Blind
acceptance of practices paves way for certain evil tendencies to proliferate,
and since no culture is immune to defects, the theory would essentially place
the entire humanity under a grave threat. For example, women in parts of Africa
are robbed of sexual pleasure by the age-old barbaric custom of female
circumcision. But, because of cultural relativism, it becomes almost impossible
to eradicate this ill practice. While the theory does leave some scope for
intra-cultural judgements, very seldom are people seen raising voices of dissent
against their own cultures, given it is something that pulsates through their
veins. Like any other theory, cultural relativism is not a viable solution for
all situations. However, before rejecting the theory completely, it’s also
important to appreciate certain aspects of it, so that one can find a more
nuanced version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution here could be perhaps to design a new relativism altogether, one
which is based on respect, not just for the culture as a whole, but also for
individual subjects belonging to the culture. This new relativism can have a
separate mechanism to address the issues of members, who get victimised in the
name of cultural customs. With people’s participation (and not interference) in
a peaceful, rational dialogue, the seeds of change can be sown in any culture to
do away with the inherent ferocity in it. Whatever be the case, it is difficult
to deny that cultural relativism promotes an atmosphere of tolerance and amity.
By eliminating the views of dogmatism surrounding one’s culture, it makes a
person more grounded and open to greater acceptance by others. Further, it
strengthens the intercultural relationships and builds a world based on the
principles of universal brotherhood. With communities being able to understand
and empathise with each other, the world certainly becomes a better place. Of
course, cultural relativism like any theory is harmful at its logical extreme,
but so long as it is caveated with a spirit of earnest dialogue, critique, and
individual respect, it works as a theory that makes a better world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">In this kaleidoscopic world, cultural diversity is a phenomenon that is standard to every institution and organisation. Adorned with a plethora of societies and people dressed in almost every colour on the palette, communicating in different languages, and following all sorts of customs and traditions, the world certainly is a beautiful place to live in. Wherever you go, whatever you do, you are bound to encounter differences and unfamiliarity in the form of people and the cultures they manifest. With every nook and corner characterised by its own uniqueness, diversity has certainly become an undeniable reality. While we are always taught to appreciate and embrace this diversity, we must also be cautious of its potential to cause morally problematic situations. Consider for instance, how would you feel if someone sticks out their tongue at you? I am sure humiliated would be the answer. But, what if I tell you that it’s the way people greet each other in Tibet. This would certainly change things a little bit, however, still, the whole idea of sticking out your tongue to greet others would seem unnatural or rather weird to you, something you’ll never dare to do to out of fear of embarrassment, unless you’re from Tibet of course! This becomes very troubling. With divergent practices exclusive to each culture, often questions pertaining to the “ideal conduct” are raised. One may, in fact, be inclined to ask “Is there an ideal way at all?” And this is where the theory of cultural relativism steps in. Humans have always been very intimately linked with the culture they’re brought up in, to the extent that their choices, tastes and behaviours resonate with the spirit and essence of their culture. Especially with respect to actions and demeanours, culture is believed to exercise a profound influence on the lives of people. Therefore, it is quite natural for them to cling onto their own cultural standards and view other cultures with suspicion. Activities like the recreational use of cemeteries in Denmark, or the Greek practice of pretending to spit on a married couple for good luck, or the exhuming of dead bodies by Trojan tribes, long-ringed necks in Thailand, foot binding in China, etc. might seem a little strange to hear at first and even impel us to pass a negative judgement. But, according to the idea of cultural relativism, such judgements would be wrong and irrational, as they are evaluated on the basis of our own cultural sense and sensibilities, which fail to cover the moral codes of other cultures. According to the theory of cultural relativism, the conception of good and evil, right and wrong, is relative to cultures and so there can never be any universal moral code of judgment. In other words, we can’t asses other cultures by employing our own cultural standards. This becomes immensely important, given the phenomenal rise in ethnocentrism and intolerance. With culture assuming supremacy over our lives in governing our views and judgements, often acceptance of others becomes a little challenging. In the face of such strict cultural conditioning, it would seem the theory of cultural relativism is our only way out to advance towards a world characterised by harmony and brotherhood. This seems to make cultural relativism an impeccable theory. But is it so? Consider a world with strict cultural relativism. Here, there shall be no cross-cultural judgements; humanity would function on the principle of tolerance, almost to the extent that everything would be approved. All cultures, with their boons and banes, would be embraced blindly, without any reservation. As a result, if a culture commands its male members to rape women as a traditional custom, then cultural relativism would be able to do very little about it. And this is where the theory takes a problematic turn. Blind acceptance of practices paves way for certain evil tendencies to proliferate, and since no culture is immune to defects, the theory would essentially place the entire humanity under a grave threat. For example, women in parts of Africa are robbed of sexual pleasure by the age-old barbaric custom of female circumcision. But, because of cultural relativism, it becomes almost impossible to eradicate this ill practice. While the theory does leave some scope for intra-cultural judgements, very seldom are people seen raising voices of dissent against their own cultures, given it is something that pulsates through their veins. Like any other theory, cultural relativism is not a viable solution for all situations. However, before rejecting the theory completely, it’s also important to appreciate certain aspects of it, so that one can find a more nuanced version. The solution here could be perhaps to design a new relativism altogether, one which is based on respect, not just for the culture as a whole, but also for individual subjects belonging to the culture. This new relativism can have a separate mechanism to address the issues of members, who get victimised in the name of cultural customs. With people’s participation (and not interference) in a peaceful, rational dialogue, the seeds of change can be sown in any culture to do away with the inherent ferocity in it. Whatever be the case, it is difficult to deny that cultural relativism promotes an atmosphere of tolerance and amity. By eliminating the views of dogmatism surrounding one’s culture, it makes a person more grounded and open to greater acceptance by others. Further, it strengthens the intercultural relationships and builds a world based on the principles of universal brotherhood. With communities being able to understand and empathise with each other, the world certainly becomes a better place. Of course, cultural relativism like any theory is harmful at its logical extreme, but so long as it is caveated with a spirit of earnest dialogue, critique, and individual respect, it works as a theory that makes a better world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feminist? No, of course not.</title><link href="/Feminist-No-of-course-not" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feminist? No, of course not." /><published>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</updated><id>/Feminist-No-of-course-not</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Feminist-No-of-course-not">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism
to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words
to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous
rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet
into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed
feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my
opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or
not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why
someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market
that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not
believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd,
right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women?
I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This
is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned
conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do
some women not want to be ‘feminists’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office,
with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural
relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural
discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not
everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The
&lt;em&gt;Oxford Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on
the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the
English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or
character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th
century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings.
Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with
the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave
belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a
way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of
feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave
of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history
of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first
sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for
women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second
wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women.
The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in
society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about
racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image
of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the
second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we
talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the
third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk
with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what
the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion
surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar
Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave
activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and
working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of
people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an
online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have
begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour.
It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to
target women with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then,
would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement?
Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as
feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my
interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and
not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off
as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is
verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating,
lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner,
it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist
has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This
viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and
speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds
sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to
understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might
as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women
wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress,
while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be
a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not
wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women
and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my
acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On
this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes
out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and
fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m
aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our
physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings
included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic
genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in
all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like
that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the
Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from
what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared
of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the
reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make
sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a
position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in
this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very
small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr,
you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded,
even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of
women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman
is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the
drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been
taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a
while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men
will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all
of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist
really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called
one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace
out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not
of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if
feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement
for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still
provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the
mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the
feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you
don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.” Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd, right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women? I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do some women not want to be ‘feminists’? As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office, with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The Oxford Dictionary suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings. Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict. Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women. The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour. It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to target women with impunity. Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then, would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement? Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.   A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating, lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner, it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress, while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist. There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.     Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr, you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags. Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded, even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression. All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rwanda the Real Wakanda?</title><link href="/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rwanda the Real Wakanda?" /><published>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda">&lt;p&gt;Last year, the film &lt;em&gt;Black Panther&lt;/em&gt; broke box office records and challenged the Hollywood consensus. For the first time ever, an ‘all black’ cast had headlined a major motion picture. One which made over a billion dollars worldwide and more in the United States than &lt;em&gt;Avengers Infinity War&lt;/em&gt;. The film imagined a world, home to the advanced African nation of Wakanda, which thanks to its monopoly over the unique resource of Vibranium, had managed to avoid the horrors of colonialism and become a prosperous, independent African nation. As an economics student, I believe that this premise seems to be painfully false. There is an African nation blessed with unique natural resources, so important that every person reading this article will have it in their pocket. It’s the Democratic Republic of the Congo, which is home to more than half of the world’s supply of cobalt. A mineral used to create smartphones’ rechargeable batteries. But the Democratic Republic of the Congo remains one of the world’s poorest nations, despite having rich resources of cobalt as well as copper, diamonds, tantalum, and tin. In reality Wakanda, just like the DRC, would suffer from a nasty case of “Dutch disease”, inhibiting industrialisation and a diversified economy. The real vibranium, as economists will tell you, is the “World Bank’s’ Ease of Doing Business Index”. Score higher than your neighbours in this, and your economy will soar through an influx in that magical blessing of foreign direct investment (FDI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what makes Rwanda the real Wakanda? For starters, Rwanda is a small landlocked nation within the African interior with far higher living standards than all of its neighbours. Also, just like the fictional Wakanda, it owes its wealth to a warrior king. While Rwanda’s president Paul Kagame isn’t a superhero, he is quite possibly the world’s greatest living general. At the age of twenty-eight, he helped overthrow the Ugandan regime, and at thirty-six, he toppled the Rwandan regime and ended the genocide. But his journey of martial brilliance didn’t stop here. He further went on to oust the government of the DRC, at the age of thirty-nine. Since 2000 he has ruled Rwanda as a warrior king, the rare autocrat who proved his martial credentials in a total war. After eighteen years of leading his nation, he has dramatically increased its GDP per capita from $200 to over $750. In 2000, the foreign direct investment into Rwanda was less than US$20 million. However, today it averages $232 million a year. The Kagame regime is a peaceful one with only 2.5 murders per thousand residents per year, much less than the United States, and far lower than its neighbour, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, with 13.5 murders per thousand people a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the mandatory question is how has Rwanda’s despot achieved so much. It is not through democracy or liberalism. Rwanda has severe limitations on freedom of speech and assembly. It’s a police state, with opposition leaders frequently being harassed and jailed. Former intelligence leaders have been mysteriously strangled to death in a South African hotel, and strangely, a former Interior Minister was shot dead in Kenya. In the most recent presidential election in 2017, Kagame won over 98% of the popular vote, a number even Stalin would blush at. It should be noted that the Rwandan population is over 85% Hutu, while Kagame hails from the market-dominant minority Tutsi ethnic group. It’s a little unlikely that a member of an unpopular minority could receive such overwhelming support in free elections. However, Kagame’s authoritarian tendencies are in keeping with the &lt;em&gt;Black Panther&lt;/em&gt; comparison. Like King T’Challa from the film, Kagame gained his throne through martial prowess (while not in quite as grand a personal challenge as the film version). He also maintains his throne for the good of his people without actually asking for their input on his rule. The film is notable both for its stereotype breaking all-black cast and for its status as the rare Hollywood film which advocates for an absolute monarchical government instead of one based on the ideals of American liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon his election, Kagame declared he would turn Rwanda into the “Singapore of Africa” and that the country would be the business and financial hub of the world’s developing continent. Just as Singapore had once gone from a small city on the edge of a Royal Navy base to the business hub of Asia in less than 50 years. Under Kagame, Rwanda has adopted English as its’ ‘lingua franca’ and become the second nation not associated with the British Empire to join the ‘Commonwealth of Nations’. Since 2000, Rwanda has liberalised its economy, cutting regulations and opening the markets to foreign businesses. The result of this is that now Rwanda ranks 29th in the ‘World Bank’s Ease of Doing Business Index’, by far the highest in Africa and higher than nations such as the Netherlands, Japan, and Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is Rwanda the real-life Wakanda? If you accept that in the real world resource wealth almost never leads to sustained national wealth, and instead view vibranium as perhaps a metaphor for a liberal economic policy and uncorrupt courts and institutions, then Rwanda becomes the most obvious example of a real-world African nation which has achieved economic success, in spite of European colonialism in the past. Of course, through a policy of austere economic exceptionalism under the leadership of a great warrior monarch. However, while the fictional Wakanda was ruled by a benign dynasty, the very real Rwanda isn’t so lucky. In 2005, Kagame said that if by 2017 he hadn’t found a successor and made “a post me Rwanda possible”, then he would deem himself a failed leader. Contrary to that, in 2017, Kagame bullied the supreme court into allowing him to run for a third term. With the strict regulations and life-threatening challenges, to this day no possible successor has emerged. Today Rwanda sits at a crossroads. Its success has been remarkable, but if it can’t find a solution to the terrifying question of succession then its golden age might be a short-lived one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wakanda forever and we hope Rwanda too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reuben Pritchard</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Last year, the film Black Panther broke box office records and challenged the Hollywood consensus. For the first time ever, an ‘all black’ cast had headlined a major motion picture. One which made over a billion dollars worldwide and more in the United States than Avengers Infinity War. The film imagined a world, home to the advanced African nation of Wakanda, which thanks to its monopoly over the unique resource of Vibranium, had managed to avoid the horrors of colonialism and become a prosperous, independent African nation. As an economics student, I believe that this premise seems to be painfully false. There is an African nation blessed with unique natural resources, so important that every person reading this article will have it in their pocket. It’s the Democratic Republic of the Congo, which is home to more than half of the world’s supply of cobalt. A mineral used to create smartphones’ rechargeable batteries. But the Democratic Republic of the Congo remains one of the world’s poorest nations, despite having rich resources of cobalt as well as copper, diamonds, tantalum, and tin. In reality Wakanda, just like the DRC, would suffer from a nasty case of “Dutch disease”, inhibiting industrialisation and a diversified economy. The real vibranium, as economists will tell you, is the “World Bank’s’ Ease of Doing Business Index”. Score higher than your neighbours in this, and your economy will soar through an influx in that magical blessing of foreign direct investment (FDI).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crimea and Iraq: A Lesson in Economic Sanctions</title><link href="/Crimea-and-Iraq" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crimea and Iraq: A Lesson in Economic Sanctions" /><published>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Crimea-and-Iraq</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Crimea-and-Iraq">&lt;p&gt;In an increasingly globalised world, nations are often called upon to intervene in situations thousands of miles from their own borders. This may be in the response to atrocities such as genocide, as happened in Rwanda in 1994. Or, it may be needed to prevent a hostile escalation, such as the one which occurred when Russia annexed Crimea in 2014. It is often the case that the oppressed group is far smaller than its attacker and therefore needs outside assistance. As a result, often through public pressure, countries are forced into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to such events, the powers-that-be have several tools at their disposal. A more mellow approach could come in the form of a political warning such as a leader’s speech, in the hope that actual, costly action would not be required. The other extreme is military intervention. This, however, has obvious drawbacks such as huge financial costs, loss of life and the risk of civilian casualties. A commonly argued alternative comes in the form of economic sanctions, often seen as an effective, peaceful form of coercion with a lesser risk to human life. However, these beliefs are often unfounded, and evidence would suggest its utility as a form of coercion is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prevailing view is that economic sanctions provide the optimal middle-ground between a peaceful approach and military warfare. The former is often viewed as weak, ineffective and more often than not, pointless. Leaders who take this avenue are viewed to be doing so simply to please their audience, possibly responding to public calls for crisis response. Leaders’ statements often serve the purpose of audience appeasement, amid fear of a backlash to inaction. Of course, there are possible arguments in favour of this approach. A powerful country may be able to impose some authority merely through an ultimatum if their reputation precedes them. Furthermore, if successful, it provides a completely costless solution. The targeted country will concede with no cost to the demanding nation. The positives are there, it’s just a shame that words are rarely enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is economic sanctions. These too are a varied tool and can range from action against individuals, such as business leaders, or the political elite, or broader blanket-sanctions on nations as a whole. The underlying logic is that the sanctions will over time cripple a country into submission, forcing them to concede to demands. Although this may cost the sanctioning nation in lost trade, it is usually far cheaper than troop mobilisation or air warfare. However, in the modern world, this is much easier said than done. Most countries are no longer dependant on a single commodity or links to a handful of trading partners. To have any significant impact, sanctions often need to be multilateral, often requiring the support of not just several countries, but from international bodies such as the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of the many stumbling blocks with the Crimean crisis. Sanctions primarily came from the United States and Europe. Although together they accounted for a substantial portion of Russia’s trade, they failed to gain the support of crucial Asian states, as a result failing to eradicate their trade links. Russia was able to ease any economic suffering by strengthening ties with China and North Korea. The costs to Russia needed to be severe enough that it would have little choice but to modify its behaviour. As Russia was able to partially circumvent the sanctions and relieve some of the damage, the chance of sanction success drastically decreased. Cooperation from North Korea and China would have resulted in much more severe economic damage, and therefore a higher chance of Russia modifying its behaviour and sanction success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second crucial factor when evaluating the probability of sanction success is the presence of domestic audience pressure. The leader in question, in this case Putin, needs to be accountable to his people, who should have the ability and motivation to remove him should the economy start to suffer. It is clear that a democratic audience has the opportunity, via elections, to remove a leader or force him into policy change. However, a common misconception is that this scenario only exists within a democracy. Work by Jessica Weeks demonstrates that this may also occur in dictatorships, albeit in a different fashion. In a country with a political make-up akin to Russia, a political elite may choose to overthrow a leader if they stand to benefit and have the capacity to do so. This may occur if the elite stand to gain more through a coup than maintaining the status quo, as may be the case during a sanctions-induced economic crisis. In Russia, this was not the case. No democratic audience exists, and Putin has established an elite whose fate is tied to his. So, Putin’s approval rating soared when the sanctions hit, creating an anti-western “rally around the flag” effect as the economic suffering was blamed on Europe and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empirical studies have shown these two influences, multilateral sanctions, and audience pressure, to be the most important factors. But even then, the success rate is weak. The ground-breaking HSE study into sanction success found only a third of 120 cases to be a success. Even more damning is further work by Robert Pape which showed only 5 of these cases to be successful. In the Crimean case, the sanctions ultimately failed in their objective to remove Russia from Crimea, and given their generally appalling success rate it begs the question, why even bother?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong answer is that sanctions can be ‘smart’ and limit civilian suffering. A common objection to military action is that they often result in accidental civilian casualties, and if we instead use economic sanctions this will reduce the likelihood of such consequences. But again, this has not always gone to plan. As was the case with Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a response to Iraq’s invasion of Kuwait in August 1990, the United Nations enforced economic sanctions. The initial aim was to pressure Iraq into withdrawing from Kuwait, and a demand to give up any weapons of mass destruction was soon added. Although the sanctions may have been relatively effective, more noticeable was the alarming impact on child mortality. The economic impacts were severe which, whilst admittedly being the aim, had devastating effects on innocent civilians, particularly children. Some estimates place the number of deaths attributable to sanctions between half-a-million and a million, although there is much controversy surrounding these claims. Further surveys by UNICEF in 1999 concluded that in certain areas, children under five were dying at more than twice the rate they were ten years before, clean water and medical supplies were particular issues. This sheds some harsh reality on the potential cost to civilian life under economic sanctions, to a degree comparable with warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The saving grace for world leaders is that they may simply have no other choice. Threats are often deemed empty and fall on deaf ears. To save face, action is required, yet military action is often opposed by the public. As a result, some form of economic sanction is required. However, with a success rate between 5% and 36%, this seems futile. The next question, then, is how do we respond to such events? It would be wrong to stand by as a spectator, yet no response seems suitable. Of course, as many scholars have pointed out, long-term solutions provide the best answer. Preventing such disasters from ever occurring is the desired outcome. But until then, a preferable alternative to economic sanctions must be sought.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stephen McAndrew</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">In an increasingly globalised world, nations are often called upon to intervene in situations thousands of miles from their own borders. This may be in the response to atrocities such as genocide, as happened in Rwanda in 1994. Or, it may be needed to prevent a hostile escalation, such as the one which occurred when Russia annexed Crimea in 2014. It is often the case that the oppressed group is far smaller than its attacker and therefore needs outside assistance. As a result, often through public pressure, countries are forced into action.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">And the Academy Award goes to…Mexico?</title><link href="/Academy-Award-Mexico" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And the Academy Award goes to…Mexico?" /><published>2019-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Academy-Award-Mexico</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Academy-Award-Mexico">&lt;p&gt;I love the Oscars. I acknowledge this without a hint of shame and I’m more than happy to admit it. With the television ratings slumping to 26.6 million in 2018 (a 39% decrease from 2014), and remaining below 30 million for this year’s broadcast, it’s safe to say that I am part of a rare breed – a young person still interested in the Academy Awards. However, the caveat is that I watch the show ‘almost completely ironically’. Every year for the past four years, myself and another film buff nit-pick the entirety of the marathon show. We do have a few reasons for it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, to make the near 240-minute programme bearable, you have to do something a bit more exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, if you think that the Academy Awards are merely a ‘celebration of cinematic excellence’, then you are truly mistaken. There are many different film festivals and ceremonies that take place during the awards season, and there is definitely a debate to be had over which is the most prestigious or important. Whether the Oscars will admit it or not, they feast on the grand spectacle as much as, or perhaps even more than, simply rewarding genuine talent. From #oscarssowhite, to &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; winning by mistake, to this year’s host debacle. It is these controversies which make people watch the Oscars. So, by critiquing it, we subconsciously embrace the farce and fanfare of the show. Thus, we make the whole experience of watching it far more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly and finally, predicting the Oscars is an artform and each year we have just one opportunity to test our skills. I highly recommend Insider’s Youtube Video: “Are the Oscars Rigged?” if you’ve never thought about the logistics of winning Best Picture, or any Academy Award for that matter. To state the obvious, it doesn’t just simply happen on merit. There are tried and tested formulas on how the system works, with each critic or film buff having their own method of guessing the winners. As the great film critic Roger Ebert wrote in 2005:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Shhhhhh. Don’t tell a soul. Close Oscar-watchers (and Academy insiders) know that what you are about to read is true but few like to talk about these things. When it comes to picking Oscar winners, you can study the statistics of the past Oscars in search of patterns and clues, but there are certain influential paradigms that defy and transcend conventional statistical analysis.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to give a few examples, all of which are worth a read, but my favourite is definitely the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;Having a Period&lt;/strong&gt;: The showiest way to flaunt your budget (besides spending it on astronomical marquee names) is to set your movie in the past, so you can see all the departments – costumes, production design, cinematography, makeup – working hard all the time. It’s astonishing, but the only Best Picture winners in the last 20 years to be set in contemporary times (real or fantasy) were “Rain Man,” “The Silence of the Lambs,” and “American Beauty” – which are also among the few that weren’t historical biographies.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know (or think you know) the formula, guessing all of the 24 awards is simple…or so it seems. As Ebert notes, “&lt;em&gt;count on at least one surprise, off-the-wall winner&lt;/em&gt;”, and in my experience it is not usually the obscure categories that trip you up, usually it is one of the big ones, such as Best Supporting Actor/Actress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cynic might say that by watching the Oscars, in this manner, we are just making a mockery of the Academy Awards; and, despite its over-exuberance, by ridiculing the show we are also ridiculing the pieces of art that the show is rewarding. Now, I do partially agree with this; the Oscars will, for a lot of people, always be the watermark of good cinema. Moreover, in recent years the Oscars have helped promote smaller indie films that without the Best Picture nomination or win, would never have achieved such success. Indeed, in a world where five films made over US$1 billion in 2018, the past six Best Picture Winners all grossed under US$100 million in the United States. To cite some prime examples, films such as &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; (2014) and the &lt;em&gt;Shape of Water&lt;/em&gt; (2017) would never have gotten the exposure that they did, without the Academy Awards, or more specifically, the Academy’s reputation as representing prestigious cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that I watch the Oscars “almost completely ironically” and it is time to address the ‘almost’ part of that statement. There is one part of the annual broadcast that I do take seriously, namely the meteoric rise of ‘New Mexican Cinema’ that surely would have gone largely unnoticed by the general public, but for the Oscars. Now, if you’re thinking, “I am an average film-goer, and I have literally no idea what New Mexican Cinema is”, that’s fine. In fact, I think this is the beauty of this movement; it has quietly infiltrated Hollywood, and apart from film buffs and industry experts, nobody was even aware it was happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I deliberately listed the examples of &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; (2014) and the &lt;em&gt;Shape of Water&lt;/em&gt; (2017) earlier, and both of these have Mexican directors: Alejandro González Iñárritu and Guillermo Del Toro, who along with Alfonso Cuarón make ‘Los Tres Amigos’, the leading lights of the second wave of this movement. Incredibly, between the three of them they have won five of the past six Academy Awards for Best Director. They have an astonishing ten Academy Awards between them and show no signs of slowing down. Yet, perhaps what is more impressive is how they have been able to blend this critical success with commercial “Hollywood” box office hits. Remember, these are the very same directors that made &lt;em&gt;Hellboy&lt;/em&gt; (2004), &lt;em&gt;Pacific Rim&lt;/em&gt; (2013), &lt;em&gt;Children of Men&lt;/em&gt; (2006), &lt;em&gt;The Revenant&lt;/em&gt; (2015) and &lt;em&gt;*Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; and the Prisoner of Azkaban* (2004). Yet, the three have stayed true to their roots as well. They continue to make Spanish language films, with the best and most recent example being Cuarón’s &lt;em&gt;Roma&lt;/em&gt; (2018), winner of three Oscars this year and, in my opinion, robbed of Best Picture. It is available to view on Netflix, and whilst a black and white Spanish language drama about a maid for a middle-class Mexican family might not be everybody’s cup of tea, it is definitely my favourite film of the past few months and worth a watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as a Spanish and Portuguese student, foreign language films have always been more accessible to me than they might be for the average viewer. I know that subtitles can be a little unpalatable for some people, and it is usually easier to relate to something if you have shared culture or understanding. That said, despite all I may critique about the Oscars, they have actually taken note of the genuine movement of foreign cinematic talent that has hijacked the awards over the past few years. By recognising these directors, it validates the movement as a whole, bringing respect and recognition from a global audience. Films such as &lt;em&gt;Y tu Mamá También&lt;/em&gt; (2001), &lt;em&gt;El Laberinto del Fauno&lt;/em&gt; (2006) and &lt;em&gt;Amores Perros&lt;/em&gt; (2001) were all nominated for Oscars in various categories; they were just the first indication of what was to come. Moreover, it is not just directors that are receiving recognition. The cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki won Best Achievement in Cinematography, three years running from 2013 to 2015, and actors such as Gael García Bernal (&lt;em&gt;Coco&lt;/em&gt;, 2017) and Diego Luna (&lt;em&gt;Rogue One&lt;/em&gt;, 2016) are stepping into the spotlight of Western cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I do make fun of the Academy, perhaps a little too much. However, I am somewhat part of the snobbery that make the Oscars what it is; I love the inside jokes, the awards scandals, the predicting of formulas. Even if I critique the ridiculous nature of it, that in and of itself just contributes to the grand annual spectacle. With all the said, what brings me back to the Academy is the small belief that it still does do what it should do; reward some of the best cinema that the world has to offer. And maybe the success of New Mexican Cinema is a sign that the Academy is getting back on track.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Daniel Harris</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">I love the Oscars. I acknowledge this without a hint of shame and I’m more than happy to admit it. With the television ratings slumping to 26.6 million in 2018 (a 39% decrease from 2014), and remaining below 30 million for this year’s broadcast, it’s safe to say that I am part of a rare breed – a young person still interested in the Academy Awards. However, the caveat is that I watch the show ‘almost completely ironically’. Every year for the past four years, myself and another film buff nit-pick the entirety of the marathon show. We do have a few reasons for it:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">There is No Going Back on Brexit</title><link href="/No-Going-Back" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="There is No Going Back on Brexit" /><published>2019-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/No-Going-Back</id><content type="html" xml:base="/No-Going-Back">&lt;p&gt;Dear Bremainers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Julius Caesar crossed the Rubicon with his armies, in defiance of the Senate and to start a civil war against Pompey, he is supposed to have said: “Alea Iacta Est” or “The die is cast”. Of course, politicians like Nigel Farage or Boris Johnson or Jacob Rees-Mogg (despite his Latin) are far from being Caesar, but they may have led Britain on a path of no return. British Prime Minister Theresa May’s consistent ability to disappoint but not surprise, whether it be in negotiating a deal with the EU, getting Brexit legislation through Parliament, or actually holding on to office, has destroyed all the fantasies Brexiteers sold and upheld all the nightmares Bremainers dreaded. So much so, that a petition to effectively stop Brexit has reportedly reached three million signatures whilst hilariously causing the government website to crash too! The big question is: should Britain really implement that referendum vote, especially after seeing the absolute chimera that has already emerged? Or has the die truly been cast?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments made by those in favour of this petition or those demanding a second referendum are very compelling: The Irish border issue is simply too complicated to be resolvable after two years of worthless back-and-forth. Even notional agreement on a future relationship with the EU is hard to find, whether in Parliament or in government. The consequences of a no-deal Brexit will be severe and, with a weak government, it is bound to be more so. Clearly, staying on or asking the people again seem to be the least worst ways out of this mess. Moreover, Parliament is not technically bound by the referendum results. It is a Sovereign institution, as the UK Supreme Court so recently affirmed in the Miller case, and it can certainly choose to not make an Act of Parliament to implement Brexit plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as a patriotic foreign national having lived in this wet, grim, sad yet hauntingly beautiful country, I find this defeatist attitude hard to accept. Britain was once an Empire on which the sun never set, it was the country that ruled mine. This country has survived two World Wars and assisted in unleashing hell on Iraq and Afghanistan (read the Chilcot Report), it has a history of being aggressive and not backing down from a fight. So, sure, I may smile a little when I see its ignominious decline, but as someone who can’t help but love this country, I feel saddened too. How can Britain’s Parliament, which has been described as the “Mother of all Parliaments” ever seek to ignore the results of a referendum? How can a country that was once ready to find “Victory! Victory, at all costs” at the bidding of a drunk now find itself so easily losing? Have things really gotten so out of hand that even democracy finds itself being questioned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the British Parliament can certainly accept the demands of those who want another referendum or those who want Brexit stopped altogether, it would completely violate the ethos of what can be called Britain’s Constitution. Britain’s Constitution is ultimately political, it rests on tradition and time-tested conventions, and not on “Constitutional Acts” or the opinions of judges. The British Constitution reveals its core tenets through rituals and crowns and maces. It shows its fundamentally democratic nature through peculiar rituals like the House of Commons closing the door on the Black Rod’s face, when he (an official of the House of Lords) approaches the Commons to invite them for the Queen’s Speech every year at the first sitting of Parliament. Britain’s Constitution, in some senses, is an evolving agreement between its aristocracy and masses, from the Magna Carta, to the Petition of Right 1628, to the Bill of Rights 1688, and to the European Union Act 2011―which requires all big EU decisions to be put to a referendum. It is these ‘agreements’ that ensure the replacement of imperial authority with the rule of law and it is these agreements which ensure that Parliament simply does not “make or unmake any law whatever”. Through its age-old traditions and expensive rituals, the British Constitution ensures that the voice of the people is never ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, one may contend here, and do so not in futility, that the people spoke in favour of Brexit due to severe misinformation and propaganda, (arguably) electoral malpractice and racism. One may also say that ignoring the 48% would be undemocratic too. But all of this simply ignores something very important about democracy: it is not supposed to give us the right answer all the time.Vox Populi Vox Dei (the voice of the people is the voice of God) does not mean God gets it right all the time, otherwise he would have made Eden snake-proof and without the Tree of Knowledge. But the fact still remains that when God commands you leave Eden (and the EU is far from Eden), you have to leave Eden. The nature of democracy is such that a popular vote on something can very well lead to bad decision-making. But one can do very little about that, this is a systemic flaw of democracy itself. One can seek to prevent misinformation or hateful propaganda before people step into the ballot box, but once the votes are counted and sorted according to all legal strictures, and the results declared, Caesar’s horse crosses the Rubicon. To try and go back is to threaten the ‘agreement’ on which British Constitutional Democracy rests, it is to say democracy shall only be sacrosanct when it is ‘right’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit of the EU Act 2011 was to ensure the public had the ultimate say in matters that majorly concerned the European Union. While it did not mandate Parliament be bound by what the public said, it seems nonsensical to assume it wanted umpteen referendums conducted in futility till the time those in power had the results they think they wanted. The EU Act does not imply anywhere that referendum results can ever be trivialised. Democracy has to be upheld. The referendum result has to be accepted. Britain has to leave the EU. Or else, it will tear itself apart, with chaos and anarchy―exactly the way in which it would fall apart in the event of no-deal. Those seeking to sabotage Brexit now will find themselves going from the frying pan and into the fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A student whose country fought the British in order to have democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Dear Bremainers,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti</title><link href="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti" /><published>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti">&lt;p&gt;There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a
step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about
language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when
they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the
degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different
factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and
vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each
other using these mediums or platforms of communication?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest
concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even.
However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about
‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to
realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as
‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around,
like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts
the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It
portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and
non-violent sensibilities. After all, &lt;em&gt;‘bhakti’&lt;/em&gt;(devotion) is not just some
‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some
religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that.
It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human,
and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in
the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we
acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will
be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are
privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you
have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called
‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and
spares none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness
as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and
cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment
with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate
love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does
not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily
centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on
the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists
and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a
better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries
now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has
been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars
of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you
do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious
army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth?
You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations
of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think
is listening to your faint whispers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of
urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of
agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will
be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the
philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation
reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the
profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a
friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its
decency and communion, in its &lt;em&gt;bhaava&lt;/em&gt; (emotion), will one day become something
more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds
can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now
contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the
idea of ‘bhakti’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply &lt;strong&gt;CANNOT&lt;/strong&gt; be denigrated. Far from
mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the
wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more
bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After
all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger
tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to
trivialise language itself the way we do today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this
differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through
language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers
too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some
primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You
need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance
against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with
your criticism, and perhaps yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each other using these mediums or platforms of communication? In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even. However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about ‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as ‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective. The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around, like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and non-violent sensibilities. After all, ‘bhakti’(devotion) is not just some ‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that. It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human, and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called ‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and spares none. The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more. And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth? You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think is listening to your faint whispers? When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its decency and communion, in its bhaava (emotion), will one day become something more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the idea of ‘bhakti’. Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply CANNOT be denigrated. Far from mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to trivialise language itself the way we do today? Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with your criticism, and perhaps yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Cl*t Wants What it Wants</title><link href="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cl*t Wants What it Wants" /><published>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants">&lt;p&gt;Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared
of every &lt;em&gt;flogging&lt;/em&gt; and every &lt;em&gt;caning&lt;/em&gt; or suddenly having no faith in
technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to
avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that
one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or &lt;em&gt;category&lt;/em&gt; of
porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one
feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in
person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk
to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why
do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;,
we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re
scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that &lt;em&gt;these&lt;/em&gt; are our
innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared
of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a
certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how
we think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest
the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s
offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely
a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like &lt;em&gt;choking&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;slapping&lt;/em&gt; cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why
we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s
the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place
where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if
there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is
wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so
dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those
same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because
it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic,
we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense
of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control
what we do or do not &lt;strong&gt;desire&lt;/strong&gt;. We think we can choose to want or not want
something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the
dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are
borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the
‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or
craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet
pussy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to
further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in
role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex,
and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex
for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man.
The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the
one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; by serving only his
needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the
appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for
betraying the rule (women not desiring sex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to
be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its
proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that
most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex
dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your
hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an
average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a
discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into
account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with
submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’.
Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To
claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone
else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to
restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy
or even if only for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you
can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we
are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to
understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to
remember is: &lt;em&gt;desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of
them.&lt;/em&gt; No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has
been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of
life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that
this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be
built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with
these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely
the manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray
you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stuti Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared of every flogging and every caning or suddenly having no faith in technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or category of porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position. The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we want, we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that these are our innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how we think. Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like choking and slapping cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel. It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic, we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control what we do or do not desire. We think we can choose to want or not want something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing. It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the ‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet pussy. It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex, and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man. The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her role by serving only his needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for betraying the rule (women not desiring sex). The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to be? A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’. Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy or even if only for a while. There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to remember is: desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of them. No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely the manifestation. Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray you.</summary></entry></feed>