<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-11T01:46:27+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Post-COVID World Economy</title><link href="/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Post-COVID World Economy" /><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The history of the world economy demonstrates a trend of economic shocks emerging in every generation. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19 as a global pandemic on March 11, 2020; and since then, almost every human endeavour has been disrupted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact on the global economy is particularly worrying. We witnessed global supply chains being severely disrupted and strained, financial markets unsettled, resulting in a cross-border economic disaster. Border closures and lockdowns shattered the core sustaining pillars of modern world economies, with the economic shock due to these measures still being weighed across the globe. The ramifications of these disruptions are more far-reaching than anticipated, and the legacies of COVID-19 will shape global growth for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even though economies are recovering at different paces throughout the world, the world economy is well on the way to recovery from a slump the likes of which none of its 7.7 billion inhabitants has seen in their lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The new paradigms enforced in the COVID-19 era have led to an unprecedented acceleration in automation and digitisation of operations whilst highlighting the importance of upskilling the workforce. Turbulent labour markets provide additional challenges to professionals as the pace of technology adoption remains unabated while automation, in tandem with the COVID-19 recession, is creating a 'double-disruption' scenario for the labour force. There is more inequality between and within countries, and governments are playing a larger role in the lives of citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Looking at historical precedents, the World Economic Forum postulates that the pandemic is about three times as bad as the global financial crisis of 2008 in terms of GDP decline on an annual basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/09/an-economist-explains-what-covid-19-has-done-to-the-global-economy/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/IHS-Markit-gdp-growth.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economists surmise that adopting a circular economy would be the best way for the world's economy to recover, whilst enabling the transition to an essentially low-carbon economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pandemic also catalysed the rise of the digital economy, with the influx of digital behaviour such as remote working and learning, telemedicine, and delivery services. Due to this rapid digitisation, other structural changes can also be anticipated, including regionalisation of supply chains and a further explosion of cross-border data flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The future of work has arrived faster, along with its myriad challenges such as worker vulnerability, income polarisation, more gig work, and the need for workers to adapt to occupational transitions multiplied in potential. This acceleration is the result not only of technological advances and recession, but also of new considerations for health and safety, and economies and labour markets will take time to recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The quantum of the amplification of these trends and the realities of this crisis have also triggered a reconsideration of several beliefs, with implicit and long-lasting effects on the economy and society and attitudes about efficiency versus resilience, the future of capitalism, densification of economic activity and peoples’ lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pandemic has also accelerated some of the key geopolitical trends that will shape our next world order - de-globalisation and nationalism, for instance, along with debilitating China’s hegemony in the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the quantitative disruptions in the economy, structured finance and credit facilities are quite explicit, the more permanent changes are perhaps the ones considered from humanitarian perspectives. The most prominent qualities that were on display during this time of distress were the adaptability and versatility of people, which caused the cataclysmic shift of buying patterns to the online medium and helped to keep it afloat while intensifying the focus on the triple bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Over the past two decades, in advancing economies, the onus of security has generally shifted from institutions to individuals. Healthcare systems are being tested and often found wanting, while benefits from paid sick leave to universal basic income are getting reviewed. There is potential for a long-term shift in how institutions offer support, through safety nets, and a more inclusive social contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;History bears witness that choices made during crises can shape the world for decades to come. What remains critical is the need for collective action to build economies that deliver inclusive economic growth, prosperity, and safety for all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Maanya Oberoi</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The history of the world economy demonstrates a trend of economic shocks emerging in every generation. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19 as a global pandemic on March 11, 2020; and since then, almost every human endeavour has been disrupted.&amp;nbsp; The impact on the global economy is particularly worrying. We witnessed global supply chains being severely disrupted and strained, financial markets unsettled, resulting in a cross-border economic disaster. Border closures and lockdowns shattered the core sustaining pillars of modern world economies, with the economic shock due to these measures still being weighed across the globe. The ramifications of these disruptions are more far-reaching than anticipated, and the legacies of COVID-19 will shape global growth for years to come. Even though economies are recovering at different paces throughout the world, the world economy is well on the way to recovery from a slump the likes of which none of its 7.7 billion inhabitants has seen in their lifetimes. The new paradigms enforced in the COVID-19 era have led to an unprecedented acceleration in automation and digitisation of operations whilst highlighting the importance of upskilling the workforce. Turbulent labour markets provide additional challenges to professionals as the pace of technology adoption remains unabated while automation, in tandem with the COVID-19 recession, is creating a 'double-disruption' scenario for the labour force. There is more inequality between and within countries, and governments are playing a larger role in the lives of citizens. Looking at historical precedents, the World Economic Forum postulates that the pandemic is about three times as bad as the global financial crisis of 2008 in terms of GDP decline on an annual basis. Economists surmise that adopting a circular economy would be the best way for the world's economy to recover, whilst enabling the transition to an essentially low-carbon economy. The pandemic also catalysed the rise of the digital economy, with the influx of digital behaviour such as remote working and learning, telemedicine, and delivery services. Due to this rapid digitisation, other structural changes can also be anticipated, including regionalisation of supply chains and a further explosion of cross-border data flows. The future of work has arrived faster, along with its myriad challenges such as worker vulnerability, income polarisation, more gig work, and the need for workers to adapt to occupational transitions multiplied in potential. This acceleration is the result not only of technological advances and recession, but also of new considerations for health and safety, and economies and labour markets will take time to recover. The quantum of the amplification of these trends and the realities of this crisis have also triggered a reconsideration of several beliefs, with implicit and long-lasting effects on the economy and society and attitudes about efficiency versus resilience, the future of capitalism, densification of economic activity and peoples’ lifestyles. The pandemic has also accelerated some of the key geopolitical trends that will shape our next world order - de-globalisation and nationalism, for instance, along with debilitating China’s hegemony in the supply chain. While the quantitative disruptions in the economy, structured finance and credit facilities are quite explicit, the more permanent changes are perhaps the ones considered from humanitarian perspectives. The most prominent qualities that were on display during this time of distress were the adaptability and versatility of people, which caused the cataclysmic shift of buying patterns to the online medium and helped to keep it afloat while intensifying the focus on the triple bottom line. Over the past two decades, in advancing economies, the onus of security has generally shifted from institutions to individuals. Healthcare systems are being tested and often found wanting, while benefits from paid sick leave to universal basic income are getting reviewed. There is potential for a long-term shift in how institutions offer support, through safety nets, and a more inclusive social contract. History bears witness that choices made during crises can shape the world for decades to come. What remains critical is the need for collective action to build economies that deliver inclusive economic growth, prosperity, and safety for all.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decoding Cryptic Cryptos</title><link href="/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding Cryptic Cryptos" /><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos">&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrencies have yet again gone through one of the many roller coaster rides in the past few months. They can synonymously be used for volatility – they are that highly erratic. In this article, we will try to decode the entire episode and present it to you from scratch.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, cryptocurrency is a digital asset or a form that is secured by cryptography. Cryptography refers to the process of converting legible information into an almost uncrackable code. The first-ever cryptocurrency, Bitcoin, was introduced in 2009 by a mysterious individual (or a group of people) with the pseudonym Satoshi Nakamoto. The creator's objective was to eliminate the intermediaries (eg, banks) in the backdrop of the 2008 debacle, also known as The Great Recession. Therefore, it did not want any third party's involvement, which raises the transaction cost (by way of transaction fees) and risk via exposure to mortgage lending. Additionally, the value of fiat currency is dependent on money circulation in the economy, which can fluctuate depending on the monetary authority. These interventions, per se, are not wrong; however, the component of uncertainty and dependence on third-party necessitated the absence of intermediaries in the eyes of Nakamoto.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next big question arises: if no intermediary involvement is present, then who develops and verifies these digital currencies? Through the process of mining, these digital coins are created and verified by way of blockchain networks. Simply put, blockchains are digital ledgers where the transactional data are stored in an encrypted, decentralised format such that no person can own, control or manipulate the particulars.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mining is a laborious procedure involving solving complex computational puzzles. Nonetheless, it still appeals to various individuals (known as miners) because of its reward in terms of ownership of the new crypto tokens. Initially, mining could be done with basic devices. When crypto participants and engagement increased, the activity became further complicated. It can no longer be solved by basic computers and instead requires supercomputers. Cryptos have a fixed supply; hence, unlike government-backed fiat money, their supply cannot go up suddenly. The disadvantageous element of this process is the carbon footprint it accounts for.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A University of Cambridge study has stated that mining of the largest cryptocurrency by market capitalisation – Bitcoins, consumes more than 120 Terawatt Hours (Twh) each year, using more electricity annually than countries like Malaysia or Sweden. Furthermore, studies claim that mining should follow the adoption rate of other broadly adopted technologies, and Bitcoin could alone produce enough carbon dioxide emissions to push global warming above 2°C within less than three decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes without saying that other much smaller cryptocurrencies have a far lower energy footprint due to their much smaller scale. However, if scaled up, they are equally carbon-heavy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, proponents of cryptos say that mining is increasingly being done with electricity generated from renewable sources. Nevertheless, environmentalists continue to decry mining since miners will keep up consuming coal (it is the cheapest source) for electricity generation, thus giving us its ecological aftermath.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from environment lovers, government and monetary officials view these digital assets as potential threats due to their operation outside government control, which can potentially overturn an economy if not supervised.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several risks are associated with cryptocurrencies. Firstly, a high degree of market manipulation due to the lack of backing by any tangible assets questions their intrinsic value, marking their price discovery in uncharted territory.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, asymmetrical information raises the likelihood of money laundering, hacking, cyber extortion, and more, damaging consumer protection and systemic stability.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some risks are familiar with other financial products; however, crypto's information opacity disrupts the adjustment. For example, as per a &lt;em&gt;Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal &lt;/em&gt;finding, Hamas, the Palestinian militant group, saw a spike in Bitcoin donations during the violence between Israel and Palestine in mid-May. Hamas, which rules the Gaza Strip, is designated as a terrorist entity by the US, the European Union (EU) and other Western nations and has sanctions imposed upon it. Nonetheless, its funding remained unaffected due to anonymous digital transactions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another such instance, according to the analytics firm Elliptic, DarkSide, a hacking group, shut down a critical US oil pipeline in May and collected over $90 million in hard-to-trace Bitcoin from 47 victims. That hack ended after Colonial Pipeline paid nearly $5 million as ransom to regain control of systems needed to supply gasoline to the Eastern US.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these complications, cryptocurrencies are seeing huge public acceptance. There are multiple reasons for broader acceptance of these digital assets, owing to their higher yields on the back of low-interest rates, hedging against inflation, or their growing acceptance by corporate leaders. For example, digital assets are pretty popular in Argentina as a way for locals to hedge against cyclical economic crises, including repeat currency devaluations, defaults and hyperinflation, with the recent imposition of foreign exchange controls and now a three-year recession made worse by the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The massive monthly rally of cryptos in early 2021 and the big sell-off in mid-May, as per market observers, was caused by Elon Musk's tweets. The American electric car maker, Tesla, announced in its February, 2021 filing to the market regulator that it had bought $1.5 billion worth of Bitcoins and would soon start accepting the digital currency for payments. A few weeks back, its CEO Musk hinted as much by adding '#bitcoin' to his Twitter bio. Followers and the general public went into a frenzy, and the market price surged. However, the plunge in crypto prices in mid-May was sparked when the Tesla chief tweeted the company’s u-turn on Bitcoin acceptance and criticised it for the environmental hazard posed by aggressive power mining.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk has a track record of influencing the market price of asset classes. Back in 2018, Musk and Tesla, each paid $20 million to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) to settle fraud charges for tweeting about a potential buyout of the car-making company, leading to a spike in share prices followed by a fall when the buyout could not be negotiated. Many regulators are worried about the concentration of social power among a few individuals and organisations to influence prices of various asset classes, which can hamper price stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key reason for slumping prices of crypto in the early morning of May 19 in Wall Street was attributed to China, after the country barred its financial institutions from dealing in cryptocurrencies.&amp;nbsp;China accounts for more than 70% of all bitcoin mining in the world. Due to its cheap energy, the country's Inner Mongolia Autonomous region accounts for around 8% globally, a more significant share than the US. The move is part of the government's target of achieving carbon neutrality by 2060.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China had such a ban in 2017, but the 2021 ban has a broader scope. The ban prohibits institutions from accepting or settling payments in crypto or providing exchange services to convert crypto to fiat currencies, including the Chinese yuan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, are cryptocurrency banned? No, they are not 100% legal, so it is all right for us to trade in crypto exchanges like WazirX or CoinDCX. However, they are not legal tender of money, so you cannot purchase any goods or services and make payments in these digitised currencies. Back in 2018, the Indian central bank had issued a circular to refrain financial institutions from having any relation with any crypto assets or crypto organisations; however, the ban was lifted by an Indian Supreme Court decision in the very same year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court in March 2020 said the central bank could notify cryptocurrencies as ‘other similar instruments’ under the definition of the term 'currency' in the Indian Foreign Exchange Management Act (FEMA). Therefore, the trading in crypto can fall within the purview of the central bank. In May 2021, the central bank came out with a circular reiterating its commitment to upholding the Court's decision. However, it did ask institutions and other entities to carry out due diligence processes in line with customer protection and economic stability as per the FEMA Act. The Indian Finance Minister in her 2021-22 budget hinted that the government would take a ‘calibrated approach’ towards digital assets. Hence, some regulation or oversight by the government is expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will get to know whether these computerised assets are the future of payments in years to come. However, administrations need to acknowledge the public involvement and bridge the loopholes these instruments carry with themselves as soon as possible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Cryptocurrencies have yet again gone through one of the many roller coaster rides in the past few months. They can synonymously be used for volatility – they are that highly erratic. In this article, we will try to decode the entire episode and present it to you from scratch.&amp;nbsp; To begin with, cryptocurrency is a digital asset or a form that is secured by cryptography. Cryptography refers to the process of converting legible information into an almost uncrackable code. The first-ever cryptocurrency, Bitcoin, was introduced in 2009 by a mysterious individual (or a group of people) with the pseudonym Satoshi Nakamoto. The creator's objective was to eliminate the intermediaries (eg, banks) in the backdrop of the 2008 debacle, also known as The Great Recession. Therefore, it did not want any third party's involvement, which raises the transaction cost (by way of transaction fees) and risk via exposure to mortgage lending. Additionally, the value of fiat currency is dependent on money circulation in the economy, which can fluctuate depending on the monetary authority. These interventions, per se, are not wrong; however, the component of uncertainty and dependence on third-party necessitated the absence of intermediaries in the eyes of Nakamoto.&amp;nbsp; The next big question arises: if no intermediary involvement is present, then who develops and verifies these digital currencies? Through the process of mining, these digital coins are created and verified by way of blockchain networks. Simply put, blockchains are digital ledgers where the transactional data are stored in an encrypted, decentralised format such that no person can own, control or manipulate the particulars.&amp;nbsp; Mining is a laborious procedure involving solving complex computational puzzles. Nonetheless, it still appeals to various individuals (known as miners) because of its reward in terms of ownership of the new crypto tokens. Initially, mining could be done with basic devices. When crypto participants and engagement increased, the activity became further complicated. It can no longer be solved by basic computers and instead requires supercomputers. Cryptos have a fixed supply; hence, unlike government-backed fiat money, their supply cannot go up suddenly. The disadvantageous element of this process is the carbon footprint it accounts for.&amp;nbsp; A University of Cambridge study has stated that mining of the largest cryptocurrency by market capitalisation – Bitcoins, consumes more than 120 Terawatt Hours (Twh) each year, using more electricity annually than countries like Malaysia or Sweden. Furthermore, studies claim that mining should follow the adoption rate of other broadly adopted technologies, and Bitcoin could alone produce enough carbon dioxide emissions to push global warming above 2°C within less than three decades. It goes without saying that other much smaller cryptocurrencies have a far lower energy footprint due to their much smaller scale. However, if scaled up, they are equally carbon-heavy.&amp;nbsp; However, proponents of cryptos say that mining is increasingly being done with electricity generated from renewable sources. Nevertheless, environmentalists continue to decry mining since miners will keep up consuming coal (it is the cheapest source) for electricity generation, thus giving us its ecological aftermath.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Apart from environment lovers, government and monetary officials view these digital assets as potential threats due to their operation outside government control, which can potentially overturn an economy if not supervised.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Several risks are associated with cryptocurrencies. Firstly, a high degree of market manipulation due to the lack of backing by any tangible assets questions their intrinsic value, marking their price discovery in uncharted territory.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, asymmetrical information raises the likelihood of money laundering, hacking, cyber extortion, and more, damaging consumer protection and systemic stability.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Some risks are familiar with other financial products; however, crypto's information opacity disrupts the adjustment. For example, as per a Wall Street Journal finding, Hamas, the Palestinian militant group, saw a spike in Bitcoin donations during the violence between Israel and Palestine in mid-May. Hamas, which rules the Gaza Strip, is designated as a terrorist entity by the US, the European Union (EU) and other Western nations and has sanctions imposed upon it. Nonetheless, its funding remained unaffected due to anonymous digital transactions.&amp;nbsp; In another such instance, according to the analytics firm Elliptic, DarkSide, a hacking group, shut down a critical US oil pipeline in May and collected over $90 million in hard-to-trace Bitcoin from 47 victims. That hack ended after Colonial Pipeline paid nearly $5 million as ransom to regain control of systems needed to supply gasoline to the Eastern US.&amp;nbsp; Despite these complications, cryptocurrencies are seeing huge public acceptance. There are multiple reasons for broader acceptance of these digital assets, owing to their higher yields on the back of low-interest rates, hedging against inflation, or their growing acceptance by corporate leaders. For example, digital assets are pretty popular in Argentina as a way for locals to hedge against cyclical economic crises, including repeat currency devaluations, defaults and hyperinflation, with the recent imposition of foreign exchange controls and now a three-year recession made worse by the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The massive monthly rally of cryptos in early 2021 and the big sell-off in mid-May, as per market observers, was caused by Elon Musk's tweets. The American electric car maker, Tesla, announced in its February, 2021 filing to the market regulator that it had bought $1.5 billion worth of Bitcoins and would soon start accepting the digital currency for payments. A few weeks back, its CEO Musk hinted as much by adding '#bitcoin' to his Twitter bio. Followers and the general public went into a frenzy, and the market price surged. However, the plunge in crypto prices in mid-May was sparked when the Tesla chief tweeted the company’s u-turn on Bitcoin acceptance and criticised it for the environmental hazard posed by aggressive power mining.&amp;nbsp; Elon Musk has a track record of influencing the market price of asset classes. Back in 2018, Musk and Tesla, each paid $20 million to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) to settle fraud charges for tweeting about a potential buyout of the car-making company, leading to a spike in share prices followed by a fall when the buyout could not be negotiated. Many regulators are worried about the concentration of social power among a few individuals and organisations to influence prices of various asset classes, which can hamper price stability. Another key reason for slumping prices of crypto in the early morning of May 19 in Wall Street was attributed to China, after the country barred its financial institutions from dealing in cryptocurrencies.&amp;nbsp;China accounts for more than 70% of all bitcoin mining in the world. Due to its cheap energy, the country's Inner Mongolia Autonomous region accounts for around 8% globally, a more significant share than the US. The move is part of the government's target of achieving carbon neutrality by 2060. China had such a ban in 2017, but the 2021 ban has a broader scope. The ban prohibits institutions from accepting or settling payments in crypto or providing exchange services to convert crypto to fiat currencies, including the Chinese yuan.&amp;nbsp; In India, are cryptocurrency banned? No, they are not 100% legal, so it is all right for us to trade in crypto exchanges like WazirX or CoinDCX. However, they are not legal tender of money, so you cannot purchase any goods or services and make payments in these digitised currencies. Back in 2018, the Indian central bank had issued a circular to refrain financial institutions from having any relation with any crypto assets or crypto organisations; however, the ban was lifted by an Indian Supreme Court decision in the very same year. The Supreme Court in March 2020 said the central bank could notify cryptocurrencies as ‘other similar instruments’ under the definition of the term 'currency' in the Indian Foreign Exchange Management Act (FEMA). Therefore, the trading in crypto can fall within the purview of the central bank. In May 2021, the central bank came out with a circular reiterating its commitment to upholding the Court's decision. However, it did ask institutions and other entities to carry out due diligence processes in line with customer protection and economic stability as per the FEMA Act. The Indian Finance Minister in her 2021-22 budget hinted that the government would take a ‘calibrated approach’ towards digital assets. Hence, some regulation or oversight by the government is expected. We will get to know whether these computerised assets are the future of payments in years to come. However, administrations need to acknowledge the public involvement and bridge the loopholes these instruments carry with themselves as soon as possible.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Critical Look at Female Representation in the Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton</title><link href="/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Critical Look at Female Representation in the Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton" /><published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton">&lt;p&gt;Female representation in cinema has been an area of contention for a while now. One of the most popular measures used to look for equality in representation of the sexes in movies is the Bechdel-Wallace test. To pass the test, the film under consideration has to have at least two female characters that have names and who converse with each other about anything other than men. It sounds very simple but unfortunately, a surprisingly large number of productions fail, even today. My time in quarantine over the past year gave me an opportunity to explore a variety of films and TV series; and in doing so, another issue made itself very prominent amongst countless others - misrepresentation of women and the relationships among them. In this article, I’ll be pointing out the absurd depiction and storylines involving female characters in &lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga a&lt;/em&gt;nd &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Queen’s Gambit is probably one of the best TV series that I have watched over the past year. However, it does have a glaring problem, one that is common in many modern day movies - the male gaze. “Male gaze” is a phrase coined by feminist thinker Laura Mulvey and in the context of cinema, it refers to the depiction of women as seen through a heterosexual male lens. The most commonly used example of this is the portrayal of female superheroes in unrealistic hypersexualised and non-functional costumes, such as the Black Widow or Wonder Woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A girlboss character is one who is seen as a feminist, with talents and powers at par with or more than her male counterparts, yet still are characterised by the male gaze. For example, while Black Widow is a fan-favourite character with unparalleled combat skills and iconic one-liners, she is still a hypersexualised girlboss character, waiting to be elevated beyond her almost side-kick like status by her individual movie to be released next month after a decade of being a part of the MCU.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise Elizabeth “Beth” Harmon in &lt;em&gt;The Queen’s&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Gambit&lt;/em&gt; is a girlboss character. Depictions of “rock bottom” faced by women in cinema have been criticised for being sexist, eroticised and, overall, unrealistic throughout history. Beth is shown struggling with addiction and her past trauma throughout the miniseries. In one scene she is dancing around in her underwear, with perfectly shaved legs and with the camera following her rear end; apart from her indulging in alcoholic drinks or smoking cigarettes in order to showcase her version of “rock bottom”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to remember that mental health issues manifest in a spectrum of different ways in different people and this can be used to justify the artistic choices involved in the depiction of Beth’s struggles. However, it is easy to note that a man’s struggles with alcoholism or any other form of addiction would probably not have been portrayed similarly, and a conscious choice was involved in trying to make Harmon and her mental illness sexy - a gorgeous damsel in distress. In terms of entertainment, hyperbole and embellishment are common. But, unrealistic depictions of struggles of characters meant to be reflections of reality over and over again makes real people question their own struggles, and this often isolates them. Accurate representation is important, especially in a world where so many struggle with mental illnesses.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is a Netflix remake of the beloved Italian animated TV series &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;. The original series was extremely popular because of its colour palette, the fashion sense of the characters, the diversity and, of course, the friendship between the titular characters, all of whom were female.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; was meant to cater to the now 20+ year olds who grew up watching the iconic show as kids. However, as soon as the trailer dropped, fans of the original series were more than disappointed. It featured a very “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'aged' sense of fashion, one that many described as far too old for fashionable teenagers of 2020/21. In addition, blatant whitewashing of the beloved characters like Musa (originally, East Asian coded) and Flora (originally, Latin coded but replaced in the new series with a white character named Terra) left viewers disappointed. There were various other issues with the trailer too like the lack of wings in spite of the characters being fairies, the absence of one of the lead characters, Tecna and so on.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the series finally aired early this year, the audience was left divided - some enjoyed the series while most others, who grew up watching the original, were not satisfied with the Netflix show. There are many reasons why I personally did not enjoy the series, but in this article I shall confine myself to discussions regarding the portrayal of women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original series portrayed female characters as fairies or witches; and male characters as warriors designated as the “specialists”. These three categories of magical creatures attended three different schools located in Magix. The new TV series makes it abundantly clear right from the start that anyone can be a fairy or a specialist (witches don’t find a place in the franchise), which is a welcome change. However, my approval of the series probably ends here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series tries to portray itself as a story of very woke characters but fails at every step in actually living up to the claim. For example, in the very first scene, the protagonist Bloom, who is from Earth and is visiting the 'Other World' (where the school for fairies and specialists known as &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt; is located for the first time), comes face to face with Sky, a specialist, who is Bloom’s love interest in both the original and the Netflix adaptation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sky offers help after noticing that Bloom is new to the school and is facing difficulty in finding her way around. Bloom tags this as 'mansplaining'. The choice of words sound almost like someone who is attempting to make fun of feminism by trying to give terms like mansplaining a meaning very different from what it really is in a way to undermine women’s experiences. Had Bloom known what she was doing, was aware of what Sky said about the school beforehand and didn't actually need help, then the use of the phrase 'mansplaining' would make sense. But she did in fact need help as Bloom was in a world that she admittedly didn't know existed up until a few months ago.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One striking difference between the original and &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is the relationship between the lead characters: Bloom, Stella, Aisha, Terra and Musa. In &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;, they are shown to be mean to each other before even getting to know each other. Their hurtful comments make no sense. They are seen trying to avoid being friends with each other and even crossing paths, again, without a reason. In the original, they enjoyed each other’s company, appreciated their individualities and supported each other through everything that life threw at them. In fact, the 'Winx Club' is what they named their friend group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;, however, Winx is simply the name of the suite that they unfortunately had to share. Real life interactions between women (or anyone for that matter) who are meeting for the first time are rarely ever the way &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; describes it and is definitely much closer to the animation, except when internalised misogyny plays a role. &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;’s version of a broken relationship between all female characters is unfortunately not uncommon in cinema. Animosity between women, shown to be a result of jealousy, is used as a plot line, even the main plot line, in shows very often. The lack of friendship and the chaotic energy that the audience of the original series so loved was painfully apparent and a punch in the face of those who were looking forward to the adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stella, clearly, absolutely despised Bloom. The show would let us know eventually that it is because Sky, who is now interested in Bloom, is Stella’s ex boyfriend - a standard love triangle trope. This trope is not only tired but also is solely created to cause friction between the female characters and reduce all their interactions. This, however, did not exist in the original. In &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;, Stella was the one to discover Bloom on Earth and take her to &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt;. The two were the closest of friends.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best friend’s position in &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is taken up by Aisha, the only person of colour in the show. She is stripped of her extremely celebrated original storyline, much like all of the other characters, and reduced to an overachieving mother-like character to Bloom - serving yet another common and tired trope - the ‘Black best friend’. All of the characters were stripped of their individualities - their style, their backgrounds, their struggles and their personalities; in a weak attempt to make Bloom look like an interesting character. Unfortunately, the original &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt; was celebrated because of the diversity and extensive storyline, which the creators of &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; obviously failed to realise.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series does make a feeble effort to overcome the biggest criticism of the original series: the lack of diversity in body shapes as each female character was portrayed with an unattainable hourglass figure while simultaneously being extremely thin. On the other hand, the male characters were tall, built and had very broad shoulders. There were very few exceptions to this. &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; introduced a singular plus size character through Terra - a token plus size character.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that the extras were also very thin made her standout. In addition, her entire storyline was reduced to a young girl always conscious and embarrassed of her size and as a result, always opting to cover up. Winx was a perfect opportunity to have a confident plus sized character with an incredible fashion sense and not make everything in her story revolve around her size, in contrast to almost all of the stories told by movies today that involve a curvy character.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final criticism is about &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;’s protagonist, Bloom and her unbearably annoying personality that again, is in stark contrast to the original Bloom. She comes across as a “I am not like the other girls'' type of female protagonist as she herself makes it clear to the show's audience by repeatedly mentioning how she is not very social or in any way like a cheerleader from Earth; and somehow that is indicative of her fairy ancestry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even while she is at &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt;, her antics, attitude and sharp words make her come across as a, for the lack of a better phrase, self-important brat. She certainly doesn’t know how to treat those around herself including her suite mates well, and often makes rather dumb choices inspite of having Aisha always trying to babysit her. She however does realise this herself, only after she has caused more than enough trouble and the series has shown her to be indeed different from the others in the sense that she, someone who has been unaware of magic her entire life and has a meagre few months of training, is the most powerful fairy in the realm and has wings! Everyone loves a chosen one trope, but this particular instance has been handled terribly. Being rude does not make anyone cool or dark and mysterious, it just makes them super annoying.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, this entire series was a weak amalgamation of tired, problematic tropes that did not exist in the original series resulting in an absolute train wreck of a show that many were looking forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bridgerton has amassed an almost cult-like following with both commoners and celebrities repeatedly expressing their love for the show since its release in December, 2020. The series is based on the 2000 book &lt;em&gt;The Duke and I &lt;/em&gt;written by Julia Quinn. There have been a variety of critiques that have come up over the past few months, and rightfully so. Most of these are about how the show was marketed as one with a diverse cast but 'diverse', for the showrunners of &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;, meant having only white and black characters. The show's queer baiting (due to gay sex scene in the trailer but a lack of a queer storyline in the actual show) and tone deaf handling of race as an issue (addressed only once in the series through an interaction between the Duke and Lady Danbury) has also been criticised.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rarely does it happen that Black characters are played by those of full black heritage. This is very evident in the case of &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; too. Marina Thompson and Simon Basset who are to be perceived as desirable are light skinned while the Duke’s late abusive father, Lady Danbury (a much older woman) and Will Mondrich (who fights for a living) are dark-skinned. Colourism, although not as highly discussed or debated as racism, is a very important issue, even within individual minority communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main criticism of the show is how the series is seen as empowering to women when in fact, it glamourises sexual assault. The titular female character, Daphne Bridgerton rapes her husband as she tries to get impregnated by him without his consent and in spite of him repeatedly asking her to stop. The following scenes make it look like Simon is at fault for lying when, in fact, he had been very clear in his intentions right from the beginning about not wanting to have kids. Whether it is that he cannot or does not want to have children is immaterial and Daphne should have respected his choice.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show fails to call out Daphne for her act and she is shown to be mad at the Duke for “lying” to her. The scenes are set in a way that the audience is meant to take her side and view Simon’s anger at his wife as unjustified. It was a missed opportunity to actually call Daphne out and acknowledge that men can be victims of rape, women can rape men and marital rape is just as prevalent and unforgiveable. None of these discussions take place and when the Duke explains to Daphne about the abuse he experienced at the hands of his father, she simply sees it as not sufficient a reason to “lie” to her. The relationship between the two is very toxic and everything seems to be rectified by the two simply reiterating their love for each other and deciding that if they have a child, “nothing else will matter”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this is problematic enough in itself but the series takes it a step further by drawing a parallel between Daphne’s situation and that of Marina, a Black woman who at this point in the story believes that she has been abandoned by her lover and the father of her unborn child. Daphne offers to help her out - the, unfortunately, very common white saviour trope wherein white characters are portrayed as selfless saviours of characters of colour, an idea deep rooted in white supremacy. When Daphne comes to know that her efforts did not bear any fruit, she is seen crying. At no point in the series whatsoever is Simon’s position as a survivor of abuse and a victim of sexual assault viewed with sympathy and the show ends without Daphne apologising.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another women-related issue with the series is the treatment of period health. The portrayal might be true to the Regency era but frankly it is difficult to keep up with what is or isn’t meant to be accurate or morally right as per the Regency era in the show. Throughout the season Daphne and Marina are shown to check their bedsheets for bloodstains that would indicate periods. This, in their knowledge, would suggest that they are not pregnant. However, biologically, this is not the best way to check for pregnancy. Spotting or light bleeding during the first trimester, that is, implantation bleeding, is very common.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, implantation bleeding is a definitive proof of pregnancy contrary to what the characters believed. In addition, when the Duke talks to Daphne about self pleasure, he asks her to touch in between her legs. This in itself is a very vague instruction and seems to be made under an assumption that vaginal penetration is the only way, all or at least most, women experience orgasm. However, only 18% of women actually experience orgasm through vaginal penetration alone and thus, it is an abject misrepresentation of female pleasure. Of course, this has been an issue with video based media for a long time now. Pornography too is often criticised for being inaccurate when it comes to female pleasure and for setting unrealistic standards for women. Again, such notions were justified under the mask of the Regency era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, many of the issues discussed above can be easily done away with without affecting the main storyline too much. Errors associated with representation of women can be avoided to a large extent by ensuring that women tell women’s stories (&lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt; have male showrunners and &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; has female showrunners). Most widely used tropes that have been discussed here are deeply-rooted in sexism, racism and homophobia. These tropes are tired and do not have a place in a world undergoing radical changes through the MeToo movement, the Black Lives Matter movement, Pride and so on and so forth. It is important that TV series and movies not only pass the Bechdel-Wallace test, which is the most basic requirement, but also accurately represent women, their problems, aspirations, desires and relationships.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Female representation in cinema has been an area of contention for a while now. One of the most popular measures used to look for equality in representation of the sexes in movies is the Bechdel-Wallace test. To pass the test, the film under consideration has to have at least two female characters that have names and who converse with each other about anything other than men. It sounds very simple but unfortunately, a surprisingly large number of productions fail, even today. My time in quarantine over the past year gave me an opportunity to explore a variety of films and TV series; and in doing so, another issue made itself very prominent amongst countless others - misrepresentation of women and the relationships among them. In this article, I’ll be pointing out the absurd depiction and storylines involving female characters in The Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton.&amp;nbsp; The Queen’s Gambit The Queen’s Gambit is probably one of the best TV series that I have watched over the past year. However, it does have a glaring problem, one that is common in many modern day movies - the male gaze. “Male gaze” is a phrase coined by feminist thinker Laura Mulvey and in the context of cinema, it refers to the depiction of women as seen through a heterosexual male lens. The most commonly used example of this is the portrayal of female superheroes in unrealistic hypersexualised and non-functional costumes, such as the Black Widow or Wonder Woman. A girlboss character is one who is seen as a feminist, with talents and powers at par with or more than her male counterparts, yet still are characterised by the male gaze. For example, while Black Widow is a fan-favourite character with unparalleled combat skills and iconic one-liners, she is still a hypersexualised girlboss character, waiting to be elevated beyond her almost side-kick like status by her individual movie to be released next month after a decade of being a part of the MCU.&amp;nbsp; Likewise Elizabeth “Beth” Harmon in The Queen’s Gambit is a girlboss character. Depictions of “rock bottom” faced by women in cinema have been criticised for being sexist, eroticised and, overall, unrealistic throughout history. Beth is shown struggling with addiction and her past trauma throughout the miniseries. In one scene she is dancing around in her underwear, with perfectly shaved legs and with the camera following her rear end; apart from her indulging in alcoholic drinks or smoking cigarettes in order to showcase her version of “rock bottom”.&amp;nbsp; It is important to remember that mental health issues manifest in a spectrum of different ways in different people and this can be used to justify the artistic choices involved in the depiction of Beth’s struggles. However, it is easy to note that a man’s struggles with alcoholism or any other form of addiction would probably not have been portrayed similarly, and a conscious choice was involved in trying to make Harmon and her mental illness sexy - a gorgeous damsel in distress. In terms of entertainment, hyperbole and embellishment are common. But, unrealistic depictions of struggles of characters meant to be reflections of reality over and over again makes real people question their own struggles, and this often isolates them. Accurate representation is important, especially in a world where so many struggle with mental illnesses.&amp;nbsp; Fate: The Winx Saga Fate is a Netflix remake of the beloved Italian animated TV series Winx Club. The original series was extremely popular because of its colour palette, the fashion sense of the characters, the diversity and, of course, the friendship between the titular characters, all of whom were female.&amp;nbsp; Fate was meant to cater to the now 20+ year olds who grew up watching the iconic show as kids. However, as soon as the trailer dropped, fans of the original series were more than disappointed. It featured a very “ 'aged' sense of fashion, one that many described as far too old for fashionable teenagers of 2020/21. In addition, blatant whitewashing of the beloved characters like Musa (originally, East Asian coded) and Flora (originally, Latin coded but replaced in the new series with a white character named Terra) left viewers disappointed. There were various other issues with the trailer too like the lack of wings in spite of the characters being fairies, the absence of one of the lead characters, Tecna and so on.&amp;nbsp; When the series finally aired early this year, the audience was left divided - some enjoyed the series while most others, who grew up watching the original, were not satisfied with the Netflix show. There are many reasons why I personally did not enjoy the series, but in this article I shall confine myself to discussions regarding the portrayal of women.&amp;nbsp; The original series portrayed female characters as fairies or witches; and male characters as warriors designated as the “specialists”. These three categories of magical creatures attended three different schools located in Magix. The new TV series makes it abundantly clear right from the start that anyone can be a fairy or a specialist (witches don’t find a place in the franchise), which is a welcome change. However, my approval of the series probably ends here.&amp;nbsp; The series tries to portray itself as a story of very woke characters but fails at every step in actually living up to the claim. For example, in the very first scene, the protagonist Bloom, who is from Earth and is visiting the 'Other World' (where the school for fairies and specialists known as Alfea is located for the first time), comes face to face with Sky, a specialist, who is Bloom’s love interest in both the original and the Netflix adaptation.&amp;nbsp; Sky offers help after noticing that Bloom is new to the school and is facing difficulty in finding her way around. Bloom tags this as 'mansplaining'. The choice of words sound almost like someone who is attempting to make fun of feminism by trying to give terms like mansplaining a meaning very different from what it really is in a way to undermine women’s experiences. Had Bloom known what she was doing, was aware of what Sky said about the school beforehand and didn't actually need help, then the use of the phrase 'mansplaining' would make sense. But she did in fact need help as Bloom was in a world that she admittedly didn't know existed up until a few months ago.&amp;nbsp; One striking difference between the original and Fate is the relationship between the lead characters: Bloom, Stella, Aisha, Terra and Musa. In Fate, they are shown to be mean to each other before even getting to know each other. Their hurtful comments make no sense. They are seen trying to avoid being friends with each other and even crossing paths, again, without a reason. In the original, they enjoyed each other’s company, appreciated their individualities and supported each other through everything that life threw at them. In fact, the 'Winx Club' is what they named their friend group. In Fate, however, Winx is simply the name of the suite that they unfortunately had to share. Real life interactions between women (or anyone for that matter) who are meeting for the first time are rarely ever the way Fate describes it and is definitely much closer to the animation, except when internalised misogyny plays a role. Fate’s version of a broken relationship between all female characters is unfortunately not uncommon in cinema. Animosity between women, shown to be a result of jealousy, is used as a plot line, even the main plot line, in shows very often. The lack of friendship and the chaotic energy that the audience of the original series so loved was painfully apparent and a punch in the face of those who were looking forward to the adaptation. Stella, clearly, absolutely despised Bloom. The show would let us know eventually that it is because Sky, who is now interested in Bloom, is Stella’s ex boyfriend - a standard love triangle trope. This trope is not only tired but also is solely created to cause friction between the female characters and reduce all their interactions. This, however, did not exist in the original. In Winx Club, Stella was the one to discover Bloom on Earth and take her to Alfea. The two were the closest of friends.&amp;nbsp; The best friend’s position in Fate is taken up by Aisha, the only person of colour in the show. She is stripped of her extremely celebrated original storyline, much like all of the other characters, and reduced to an overachieving mother-like character to Bloom - serving yet another common and tired trope - the ‘Black best friend’. All of the characters were stripped of their individualities - their style, their backgrounds, their struggles and their personalities; in a weak attempt to make Bloom look like an interesting character. Unfortunately, the original Winx Club was celebrated because of the diversity and extensive storyline, which the creators of Fate obviously failed to realise.&amp;nbsp; The series does make a feeble effort to overcome the biggest criticism of the original series: the lack of diversity in body shapes as each female character was portrayed with an unattainable hourglass figure while simultaneously being extremely thin. On the other hand, the male characters were tall, built and had very broad shoulders. There were very few exceptions to this. Fate introduced a singular plus size character through Terra - a token plus size character.&amp;nbsp; The fact that the extras were also very thin made her standout. In addition, her entire storyline was reduced to a young girl always conscious and embarrassed of her size and as a result, always opting to cover up. Winx was a perfect opportunity to have a confident plus sized character with an incredible fashion sense and not make everything in her story revolve around her size, in contrast to almost all of the stories told by movies today that involve a curvy character.&amp;nbsp; My final criticism is about Fate’s protagonist, Bloom and her unbearably annoying personality that again, is in stark contrast to the original Bloom. She comes across as a “I am not like the other girls'' type of female protagonist as she herself makes it clear to the show's audience by repeatedly mentioning how she is not very social or in any way like a cheerleader from Earth; and somehow that is indicative of her fairy ancestry.&amp;nbsp; However, even while she is at Alfea, her antics, attitude and sharp words make her come across as a, for the lack of a better phrase, self-important brat. She certainly doesn’t know how to treat those around herself including her suite mates well, and often makes rather dumb choices inspite of having Aisha always trying to babysit her. She however does realise this herself, only after she has caused more than enough trouble and the series has shown her to be indeed different from the others in the sense that she, someone who has been unaware of magic her entire life and has a meagre few months of training, is the most powerful fairy in the realm and has wings! Everyone loves a chosen one trope, but this particular instance has been handled terribly. Being rude does not make anyone cool or dark and mysterious, it just makes them super annoying.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, this entire series was a weak amalgamation of tired, problematic tropes that did not exist in the original series resulting in an absolute train wreck of a show that many were looking forward to. Bridgerton Bridgerton has amassed an almost cult-like following with both commoners and celebrities repeatedly expressing their love for the show since its release in December, 2020. The series is based on the 2000 book The Duke and I written by Julia Quinn. There have been a variety of critiques that have come up over the past few months, and rightfully so. Most of these are about how the show was marketed as one with a diverse cast but 'diverse', for the showrunners of Bridgerton, meant having only white and black characters. The show's queer baiting (due to gay sex scene in the trailer but a lack of a queer storyline in the actual show) and tone deaf handling of race as an issue (addressed only once in the series through an interaction between the Duke and Lady Danbury) has also been criticised.&amp;nbsp; Rarely does it happen that Black characters are played by those of full black heritage. This is very evident in the case of Bridgerton too. Marina Thompson and Simon Basset who are to be perceived as desirable are light skinned while the Duke’s late abusive father, Lady Danbury (a much older woman) and Will Mondrich (who fights for a living) are dark-skinned. Colourism, although not as highly discussed or debated as racism, is a very important issue, even within individual minority communities.&amp;nbsp; My main criticism of the show is how the series is seen as empowering to women when in fact, it glamourises sexual assault. The titular female character, Daphne Bridgerton rapes her husband as she tries to get impregnated by him without his consent and in spite of him repeatedly asking her to stop. The following scenes make it look like Simon is at fault for lying when, in fact, he had been very clear in his intentions right from the beginning about not wanting to have kids. Whether it is that he cannot or does not want to have children is immaterial and Daphne should have respected his choice.&amp;nbsp; The show fails to call out Daphne for her act and she is shown to be mad at the Duke for “lying” to her. The scenes are set in a way that the audience is meant to take her side and view Simon’s anger at his wife as unjustified. It was a missed opportunity to actually call Daphne out and acknowledge that men can be victims of rape, women can rape men and marital rape is just as prevalent and unforgiveable. None of these discussions take place and when the Duke explains to Daphne about the abuse he experienced at the hands of his father, she simply sees it as not sufficient a reason to “lie” to her. The relationship between the two is very toxic and everything seems to be rectified by the two simply reiterating their love for each other and deciding that if they have a child, “nothing else will matter”.&amp;nbsp; All this is problematic enough in itself but the series takes it a step further by drawing a parallel between Daphne’s situation and that of Marina, a Black woman who at this point in the story believes that she has been abandoned by her lover and the father of her unborn child. Daphne offers to help her out - the, unfortunately, very common white saviour trope wherein white characters are portrayed as selfless saviours of characters of colour, an idea deep rooted in white supremacy. When Daphne comes to know that her efforts did not bear any fruit, she is seen crying. At no point in the series whatsoever is Simon’s position as a survivor of abuse and a victim of sexual assault viewed with sympathy and the show ends without Daphne apologising.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another women-related issue with the series is the treatment of period health. The portrayal might be true to the Regency era but frankly it is difficult to keep up with what is or isn’t meant to be accurate or morally right as per the Regency era in the show. Throughout the season Daphne and Marina are shown to check their bedsheets for bloodstains that would indicate periods. This, in their knowledge, would suggest that they are not pregnant. However, biologically, this is not the best way to check for pregnancy. Spotting or light bleeding during the first trimester, that is, implantation bleeding, is very common.&amp;nbsp; In fact, implantation bleeding is a definitive proof of pregnancy contrary to what the characters believed. In addition, when the Duke talks to Daphne about self pleasure, he asks her to touch in between her legs. This in itself is a very vague instruction and seems to be made under an assumption that vaginal penetration is the only way, all or at least most, women experience orgasm. However, only 18% of women actually experience orgasm through vaginal penetration alone and thus, it is an abject misrepresentation of female pleasure. Of course, this has been an issue with video based media for a long time now. Pornography too is often criticised for being inaccurate when it comes to female pleasure and for setting unrealistic standards for women. Again, such notions were justified under the mask of the Regency era. Clearly, many of the issues discussed above can be easily done away with without affecting the main storyline too much. Errors associated with representation of women can be avoided to a large extent by ensuring that women tell women’s stories (The Queen’s Gambit and Fate: The Winx Saga have male showrunners and Bridgerton has female showrunners). Most widely used tropes that have been discussed here are deeply-rooted in sexism, racism and homophobia. These tropes are tired and do not have a place in a world undergoing radical changes through the MeToo movement, the Black Lives Matter movement, Pride and so on and so forth. It is important that TV series and movies not only pass the Bechdel-Wallace test, which is the most basic requirement, but also accurately represent women, their problems, aspirations, desires and relationships.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unlimited Vacation: A Relief or A Stressor?</title><link href="/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlimited Vacation: A Relief or A Stressor?" /><published>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor">&lt;p&gt;Last year around March, most of the countries went into a lockdown. Everything, including education and work, shifted to an online mode and the phrase 'work from home' (WFH) became popular.&amp;nbsp; It felt like a relief at first, as working from home in the comfort of pyjamas seemed like a dream come true. After a few months, the internet got flooded with articles claiming how WFH increases stress among young adults as the boundaries between professional and personal lives get blurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings and zoom calls picked up the pace and continued even after the office hours. The nine-to-five rule was discarded by this new normal of working, which demanded people work round the clock. Work-life balance seemed like a distant reality as both were accessible throughout the day. All these factors acted as stressors for the working adults. Vacation and leaves were not the best options as everyone was stuck at home with no other place to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many employees might have thought about the 'No-Vacation Policy' followed by many organisations during these times. The policy was first initiated by Netflix several years ago. It promotes unlimited vacation for its employees. There won't be any check on the number of days a person has taken off in a year. In the beginning, it was seen as a 'controversial policy' which won't stay in place for long. People argued in favour of as well as against the policy. Several diverse viewpoints came forward, but none of them could prove themselves as the absolute right. Even after all this time, Netflix has continued with the policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emerging startups and other companies have also started to follow the 'No Vacation Policy'. In the US, 1% of all the companies have abandoned the existing vacation and leave policies. Employees are trusted to complete their work and tasks at scheduled times and given the freedom to take leaves and go for holidays at their convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The critics of the policy claim that 'no rules and regulations' might not work in the firm's best interests. They believe that the employees will take advantage of it and not turn up for important meetings or meet deadlines. Thus, it will impact the output and efficiency of any company in a negative manner. Human behaviour is unpredictable and varies from person to person. Not all employees will behave similarly. Some might avail themselves of working while being on vacation while others might never take a holiday because they do not want others to think they work less!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advocates of the policy have given various arguments in its defence. They believe that the foundation of any such approach is based on mutual trust between the employees and the employer. With freedom comes responsibility! Every employee will be responsible for fulfilling their work on time and keeping other members in the loop with their vacation plans. Team leaders will have the responsibility to set examples for their employees to maintain a perfect work-life balance. They also believe that the existing holiday calendar doesn't serve all employees. Not every employee in Netflix celebrates Christmas or Hanukkah, thus giving them the freedom to take off is justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the US, 35% of the workforce is millennials. Their way of doing things and perceiving the world is way too different from the previous generation. They don't want to prioritise work at the cost of personal life. They want a flexible work-life that allows them to live and enjoy as per their convenience. They believe that there's no point in working hard if one does not have enough time to enjoy and relax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, the millennials have a strong opinion on equality among the genders. Demand for paternity leaves has been a priority for the employees in the past few years. The no vacation policy works in favour of the millennial way of thinking. It allows them to maintain a work-life balance that suits their needs. Working parents now have the liberty to spend more time with their kids and family. The concept of period leave does not come up in these organisations because one has the freedom to take an off whenever they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hustle culture has increased productivity but at the cost of mental health. Young adults suffer from anxiety, stress and even depression because of the overly competitive atmosphere at the workplace. Half of Millennials, along with 75% of Gen-Zers, have left a job for mental health reasons. WHO (World Health Organisation) has classified 'burnout' as an occupational phenomenon. The race to be better and more productive never ends. People end up working extra to achieve the next target or deadline. Leisure and relaxation are not encouraged in hustle culture. It is believed that working all the time without breaks is entirely normal and every individual should aspire to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With increased awareness of mental health, companies are taking measures to reduce the burden on the employees. In some ways, the no vacation policy will lead to reduced stress. The reason being, it allows people to work at their own pace. Employees have the liberty to take leaves whenever they are stressed. They can rejuvenate themselves and get back to work at their convenience. This helps increase efficiency as employees work with a fresh and relaxed mind. Each individual has a different way to cope with stress, and thus the policy gives them the freedom to choose what they want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than this, there are other aspects as well which make this policy favourable for all! New startups can recruit people from far off cities. The approach makes it possible for these people to work from wherever they are. These companies are giving more weightage to the amount and quality of work rather than the place and time at which they are done. This also encourages diversity in the workplace, as people from different cities join and work in one team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unlimited vacation policy might allow people to work at their own pace and in the comfort of their own home. It could also help them to think better, which would reflect in the quality of work. Not everyone will agree, but then every human behaves and perceives differently! This policy tries to accommodate all the employees under one frame. It gives freedom but not at the cost of work. Work has to be prioritised, but the time and place should depend on the employee and his preferences. After all, it harms no one to relax a bit and sing, &quot;&lt;em&gt;A-a-aye, I'm on vacation, every single day 'cause I love my occupation!&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Last year around March, most of the countries went into a lockdown. Everything, including education and work, shifted to an online mode and the phrase 'work from home' (WFH) became popular.&amp;nbsp; It felt like a relief at first, as working from home in the comfort of pyjamas seemed like a dream come true. After a few months, the internet got flooded with articles claiming how WFH increases stress among young adults as the boundaries between professional and personal lives get blurred. Meetings and zoom calls picked up the pace and continued even after the office hours. The nine-to-five rule was discarded by this new normal of working, which demanded people work round the clock. Work-life balance seemed like a distant reality as both were accessible throughout the day. All these factors acted as stressors for the working adults. Vacation and leaves were not the best options as everyone was stuck at home with no other place to go. Many employees might have thought about the 'No-Vacation Policy' followed by many organisations during these times. The policy was first initiated by Netflix several years ago. It promotes unlimited vacation for its employees. There won't be any check on the number of days a person has taken off in a year. In the beginning, it was seen as a 'controversial policy' which won't stay in place for long. People argued in favour of as well as against the policy. Several diverse viewpoints came forward, but none of them could prove themselves as the absolute right. Even after all this time, Netflix has continued with the policy. Emerging startups and other companies have also started to follow the 'No Vacation Policy'. In the US, 1% of all the companies have abandoned the existing vacation and leave policies. Employees are trusted to complete their work and tasks at scheduled times and given the freedom to take leaves and go for holidays at their convenience. The critics of the policy claim that 'no rules and regulations' might not work in the firm's best interests. They believe that the employees will take advantage of it and not turn up for important meetings or meet deadlines. Thus, it will impact the output and efficiency of any company in a negative manner. Human behaviour is unpredictable and varies from person to person. Not all employees will behave similarly. Some might avail themselves of working while being on vacation while others might never take a holiday because they do not want others to think they work less! The advocates of the policy have given various arguments in its defence. They believe that the foundation of any such approach is based on mutual trust between the employees and the employer. With freedom comes responsibility! Every employee will be responsible for fulfilling their work on time and keeping other members in the loop with their vacation plans. Team leaders will have the responsibility to set examples for their employees to maintain a perfect work-life balance. They also believe that the existing holiday calendar doesn't serve all employees. Not every employee in Netflix celebrates Christmas or Hanukkah, thus giving them the freedom to take off is justified. In the US, 35% of the workforce is millennials. Their way of doing things and perceiving the world is way too different from the previous generation. They don't want to prioritise work at the cost of personal life. They want a flexible work-life that allows them to live and enjoy as per their convenience. They believe that there's no point in working hard if one does not have enough time to enjoy and relax. Apart from this, the millennials have a strong opinion on equality among the genders. Demand for paternity leaves has been a priority for the employees in the past few years. The no vacation policy works in favour of the millennial way of thinking. It allows them to maintain a work-life balance that suits their needs. Working parents now have the liberty to spend more time with their kids and family. The concept of period leave does not come up in these organisations because one has the freedom to take an off whenever they want. The hustle culture has increased productivity but at the cost of mental health. Young adults suffer from anxiety, stress and even depression because of the overly competitive atmosphere at the workplace. Half of Millennials, along with 75% of Gen-Zers, have left a job for mental health reasons. WHO (World Health Organisation) has classified 'burnout' as an occupational phenomenon. The race to be better and more productive never ends. People end up working extra to achieve the next target or deadline. Leisure and relaxation are not encouraged in hustle culture. It is believed that working all the time without breaks is entirely normal and every individual should aspire to do that. With increased awareness of mental health, companies are taking measures to reduce the burden on the employees. In some ways, the no vacation policy will lead to reduced stress. The reason being, it allows people to work at their own pace. Employees have the liberty to take leaves whenever they are stressed. They can rejuvenate themselves and get back to work at their convenience. This helps increase efficiency as employees work with a fresh and relaxed mind. Each individual has a different way to cope with stress, and thus the policy gives them the freedom to choose what they want to do. Other than this, there are other aspects as well which make this policy favourable for all! New startups can recruit people from far off cities. The approach makes it possible for these people to work from wherever they are. These companies are giving more weightage to the amount and quality of work rather than the place and time at which they are done. This also encourages diversity in the workplace, as people from different cities join and work in one team. An unlimited vacation policy might allow people to work at their own pace and in the comfort of their own home. It could also help them to think better, which would reflect in the quality of work. Not everyone will agree, but then every human behaves and perceives differently! This policy tries to accommodate all the employees under one frame. It gives freedom but not at the cost of work. Work has to be prioritised, but the time and place should depend on the employee and his preferences. After all, it harms no one to relax a bit and sing, &quot;A-a-aye, I'm on vacation, every single day 'cause I love my occupation!&quot;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Tyranny of Trends</title><link href="/The-Tyranny-of-Trends" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Tyranny of Trends" /><published>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Tyranny-of-Trends</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Tyranny-of-Trends">&lt;p&gt;Where does your clothing go when it's not needed anymore?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every second, a truck full of clothes is burned or dumped in a landfill. Every year, 92 million tonnes of fast fashion items are thrown away. Every year, 79 trillion litres of water is consumed by the fashion industry. Consequently, every year, more than $500 billion of value is lost due to clothing underutilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were just a few of the many facts illustrating the case of ‘TYRANNY OF TRENDS’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With new trends taking over the market everyday, fast fashion is blooming like never before, leading to excessive carbon emissions, imprudent waste generation, giving birth to a new water crisis and to top it all, the lack of recycling is worsening the existing situation of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is imperative for the world to know that it takes more than just a piece of cloth and a few designers to design the trendsetting high-on-bling clothes that influencers wear, the head-turning long trails that brides want to wear or the gorgeous Italian-cut tuxedos that men wish to wear. The essence of sustainability lies in finding plausible alternatives to the existing resources being used because soon there will be a time when we won’t be left with any. It’s high time that we buckle up and start working in the direction to find new resources in order to keep the existing ones available for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we wrap our heads around finding implementable solutions to the problem of fast fashion, let’s get into the nitty gritties of the concept of fast fashion. As a consequence of the fickle trends, which seem to change while you are reading this article, there exists a never ending demand for affordable, high-in-fashion garments to fulfil the quest of the masses to be in-trend. Which in turn compels and gives fashion brands and garment manufacturers a new avenue to mint money by producing cheap, in-trend fashion to keep up with the demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast fashion is a by-product of trends, so let's take a look at how this frenzy around trends is created? Saying that trends come and go like seasons would be wrong in this day and age as these trends are way more volatile to be able to stay for a full season. The real question is how are these trends set in the first place, compelling people to be in trend all the time. The following are a few ways in which trends are introduced to the world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Runway Trends - Many-a-times certain runway looks created by designers catch the eyes of people and the next thing we know is every other brand starts incorporating those elements in their collection to be able to fill their pockets by pushing trends and fast fashion forward.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Celebrities - Trends are fuelled by celebrities the minute they are spotted wearing something which no one has seen before. People who idolise celebrities are always on a hunt for similar pieces eventually paving a way for a new trend to enter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Social media and influencers -&amp;nbsp; The impact social media has on one’s life is immense so much so that everyone wants to follow and replicate the well-fabricated lives portrayed by influencers on their well-curated handles. To top it all, designers and brands approach influencers just as they approach celebrities to make new trends enter the market.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem which fast fashion brings with itself is the problem of disposal. Once a piece of clothing goes out of trend, both the consumers and the fashion labels do not think twice before dumping huge heaps of clothes which no longer continues to quench their thirst for trends so much so that every second, enough clothes&amp;nbsp;to fill a garbage truck full are either burned or sent to a landfill. Extortion of environmental resources, excessive waste generation, carbon emissions are all consequences of a choice that we have opted for, a choice to simply wear clothes for a shorter span of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the aforementioned heinous consequences of fast fashion pose one question to mankind, should we stop buying clothes at all? The answer is NO! You can still stand out and manage to be a trendsetter just by being a little mindful of your actions and choices.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most efficient way of tackling the problem at hand is by adopting sustainable fashion in order to achieve a circular fashion economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circular fashion economy proposes a progressive system of circulating a piece of clothing in the economy till the time its maximum value gets exhausted and the cycle is completed by safely disposing off the no-longer-in-use piece back to the environment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainability is a two-way stream, brands and consumers are the two main players who can pave the way for circular and sustainable fashion. Before looking at how long is the road ahead, let’s see how far we have come on this long journey of achieving sustainability in its true sense. On the manufacturer’s side we have brands like H&amp;amp;M, which is now planning to deviate from the well-trodden path of fast fashion to reduce their environmental footprint by introducing sustainable collections made of organic cotton and recycled polyester.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a brand which has now stepped up its game in circular fashion by accepting and recycling unwanted garments from customers, H&amp;amp;M has set a benchmark for brands in the similar line. Levi’s, on the other hand, has been trying to reduce the notorious amounts of water required to make a pair of jeans by 96% which is a huge step towards making judicial use of existing resources. Like H&amp;amp;M and Levi’s there are many more brands which are working in the same direction but there is still a lot to be done. On the other hand, consumers of fashion can adopt the following steps with a motive to convert their vision for the fashion industry into reality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Keep and wear the clothes for a longer span of time.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Think twice before dumping clothes which no longer please you. Instead, upcycle, alter, repair or donate them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Buy sustainable fashion, go for upcycled, thrifted pieces.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bigger question is, can sustainability and profitability ever go hand-in-hand? It’s the demand which can make or break a brand’s fate. With more and more consumers becoming environmentally conscious, the demand for sustainable fashion has hiked up over the course of the years, which has led to brands supplying more and more sustainable garments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aware and conscious customers, especially Gen Z and millennials are ready to buy sustainable clothing even if they have to shell out more money for it, which makes it profitable for brands to go sustainable. And the ones whose pockets are holding them back from supporting the cause, they tend to take another route by turning to thrift stores which are sustainable and pocket friendly too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These small measures are just a few steps on the ladder towards achieving our goal of a sustainable and circular fashion economy which is all about covering one full circle from growing, designing, wearing, thrifting to finally passing the cloth to the biosphere by safely composting it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Agrawal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Where does your clothing go when it's not needed anymore? Every second, a truck full of clothes is burned or dumped in a landfill. Every year, 92 million tonnes of fast fashion items are thrown away. Every year, 79 trillion litres of water is consumed by the fashion industry. Consequently, every year, more than $500 billion of value is lost due to clothing underutilisation. These were just a few of the many facts illustrating the case of ‘TYRANNY OF TRENDS’. With new trends taking over the market everyday, fast fashion is blooming like never before, leading to excessive carbon emissions, imprudent waste generation, giving birth to a new water crisis and to top it all, the lack of recycling is worsening the existing situation of climate change. It is imperative for the world to know that it takes more than just a piece of cloth and a few designers to design the trendsetting high-on-bling clothes that influencers wear, the head-turning long trails that brides want to wear or the gorgeous Italian-cut tuxedos that men wish to wear. The essence of sustainability lies in finding plausible alternatives to the existing resources being used because soon there will be a time when we won’t be left with any. It’s high time that we buckle up and start working in the direction to find new resources in order to keep the existing ones available for generations to come. Before we wrap our heads around finding implementable solutions to the problem of fast fashion, let’s get into the nitty gritties of the concept of fast fashion. As a consequence of the fickle trends, which seem to change while you are reading this article, there exists a never ending demand for affordable, high-in-fashion garments to fulfil the quest of the masses to be in-trend. Which in turn compels and gives fashion brands and garment manufacturers a new avenue to mint money by producing cheap, in-trend fashion to keep up with the demand. Fast fashion is a by-product of trends, so let's take a look at how this frenzy around trends is created? Saying that trends come and go like seasons would be wrong in this day and age as these trends are way more volatile to be able to stay for a full season. The real question is how are these trends set in the first place, compelling people to be in trend all the time. The following are a few ways in which trends are introduced to the world: Runway Trends - Many-a-times certain runway looks created by designers catch the eyes of people and the next thing we know is every other brand starts incorporating those elements in their collection to be able to fill their pockets by pushing trends and fast fashion forward. Celebrities - Trends are fuelled by celebrities the minute they are spotted wearing something which no one has seen before. People who idolise celebrities are always on a hunt for similar pieces eventually paving a way for a new trend to enter.&amp;nbsp; Social media and influencers -&amp;nbsp; The impact social media has on one’s life is immense so much so that everyone wants to follow and replicate the well-fabricated lives portrayed by influencers on their well-curated handles. To top it all, designers and brands approach influencers just as they approach celebrities to make new trends enter the market. The main problem which fast fashion brings with itself is the problem of disposal. Once a piece of clothing goes out of trend, both the consumers and the fashion labels do not think twice before dumping huge heaps of clothes which no longer continues to quench their thirst for trends so much so that every second, enough clothes&amp;nbsp;to fill a garbage truck full are either burned or sent to a landfill. Extortion of environmental resources, excessive waste generation, carbon emissions are all consequences of a choice that we have opted for, a choice to simply wear clothes for a shorter span of time. All the aforementioned heinous consequences of fast fashion pose one question to mankind, should we stop buying clothes at all? The answer is NO! You can still stand out and manage to be a trendsetter just by being a little mindful of your actions and choices.&amp;nbsp; The most efficient way of tackling the problem at hand is by adopting sustainable fashion in order to achieve a circular fashion economy.&amp;nbsp; Circular fashion economy proposes a progressive system of circulating a piece of clothing in the economy till the time its maximum value gets exhausted and the cycle is completed by safely disposing off the no-longer-in-use piece back to the environment.&amp;nbsp; Sustainability is a two-way stream, brands and consumers are the two main players who can pave the way for circular and sustainable fashion. Before looking at how long is the road ahead, let’s see how far we have come on this long journey of achieving sustainability in its true sense. On the manufacturer’s side we have brands like H&amp;amp;M, which is now planning to deviate from the well-trodden path of fast fashion to reduce their environmental footprint by introducing sustainable collections made of organic cotton and recycled polyester.&amp;nbsp; As a brand which has now stepped up its game in circular fashion by accepting and recycling unwanted garments from customers, H&amp;amp;M has set a benchmark for brands in the similar line. Levi’s, on the other hand, has been trying to reduce the notorious amounts of water required to make a pair of jeans by 96% which is a huge step towards making judicial use of existing resources. Like H&amp;amp;M and Levi’s there are many more brands which are working in the same direction but there is still a lot to be done. On the other hand, consumers of fashion can adopt the following steps with a motive to convert their vision for the fashion industry into reality: Keep and wear the clothes for a longer span of time.Think twice before dumping clothes which no longer please you. Instead, upcycle, alter, repair or donate them.&amp;nbsp;Buy sustainable fashion, go for upcycled, thrifted pieces. The bigger question is, can sustainability and profitability ever go hand-in-hand? It’s the demand which can make or break a brand’s fate. With more and more consumers becoming environmentally conscious, the demand for sustainable fashion has hiked up over the course of the years, which has led to brands supplying more and more sustainable garments.&amp;nbsp; Aware and conscious customers, especially Gen Z and millennials are ready to buy sustainable clothing even if they have to shell out more money for it, which makes it profitable for brands to go sustainable. And the ones whose pockets are holding them back from supporting the cause, they tend to take another route by turning to thrift stores which are sustainable and pocket friendly too.&amp;nbsp; These small measures are just a few steps on the ladder towards achieving our goal of a sustainable and circular fashion economy which is all about covering one full circle from growing, designing, wearing, thrifting to finally passing the cloth to the biosphere by safely composting it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Work Hard, Pay Hard</title><link href="/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Work Hard, Pay Hard" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard">&lt;p&gt;On my way to university, I heard two women chatting beside me on the train and I couldn't help but eavesdrop at the horrors exchanged in their dialogue. They were engrossed in discussing or rather denouncing the daughter-in-law of one of their acquaintances for her values and time devoted to her family. From what I heard, they believed that she doesn't contribute much to the household chores as she continues to work after marriage (a heinous crime apparently) and comes home late. One of them said that this is bound to happen when women study too much.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made me spiral into thinking about what most women, both married or unmarried, but mostly married, living with huge families and kids go through. They work from 9-5 or more I assume, complete their chores, handle their kids and still are not compensated enough for the same, be it the remuneration at their jobs in terms of money or the healthcare and safety provisions, and, on top of that, they are conveniently expected to undertake relentless unpaid work at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after all the effort that women put in every sphere of life, they still earn less respect and salary than their male counterparts for the same job, irrespective of their qualification and experience, contingent merely on their gender. &lt;em&gt;Because women are child-bearers and menstruators who expect the bare minimum of maternity and period leaves as an employee. Because women can't lead teams as capably as their male counterparts, since they aren't dominant by birth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led me to realise that the gender-pay-gap is one of the most exploitative and discriminative features of our economic systems staring us in the face. One would expect a better system of rewards based on one’s merit and calibre, but even in the 21st century only six countries in the world, namely, Belgium, Denmark, France, Latvia, Luxembourg and Sweden grant men and women equal legal work rights, which is a concept as old as only a decade, according to a report by &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, bringing about legal changes does not translate into effective actions. In Sweden, women still earn about 5% less than their male counterparts and, globally, women earn 79 cents for every dollar paid to a man - which might not sound like a huge gap in theory but again, this is just a statistic which might not even reflect the actual situation flailing about in our system. It might not even consider the many women who are employed in the informal sectors of developing countries or are labouring away in the agricultural-sector without reaping any significant benefits out of it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wage gap exists for women of all educational backgrounds - from high school graduates to women with advanced degrees. According to a report by the Economic Policy Institute, this gap ranges from three dollars for women having an education level of less than high school to twelve dollars for women with advanced degrees. This is the opposite of what one would expect and a strong argument against how gender-wage-gap stems from the lower education levels of women. The gap only widens as the level of education increases, which is testament to the fact that the more literate and intelligent the woman, the more of a threat she is made out to be.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this bias is not limited to merely the pecuniary aspect of the work culture; it is deeply embedded in how women are treated in offices, always put on a rung lower than men, listened to but never heard or appreciated. From bearing the ‘motherhood penalty’ to being biologically ‘complicated’, women around the world are stifled at every step of their way to success. A recent American study deduced the average by which women’s future wages fall—at 4% per child, and 10% for the highest-earning, most skilled white women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women are considered assets as long as they do not ask for anything that lies outside the zone of anyone's convenience - be it providing maternity leaves or transportation for late work hours. And are also looked at like a nuisance for any lawsuits and uncomfortable conversations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the famous #MeToo movement, many companies and men in position suggested that hiring a woman nowadays can prove to be a risky investment because everything these days leads to lawsuits. Blaming the MeToo movement, many men claim that they are afraid to be alone with women in the workspace or hesitant to be around in their close vicinity - which is a complete rationalisation of the actions that are not okay in any workspace. And these men flagrantly choose to ignore that the issue doesn’t lie in women’s capability to live by the rules created by men but in men’s inability to treat them like human beings with boundaries that are to be respected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zomato, a food-delivery service was one of the first major-league companies in India to grant paid period leaves - an action heavily slated by men. Even so, only bringing a policy in place doesn't seem enough to provoke a change because most women might be hesitant to take those leaves due to the pronounced stigma around menstruation and being considered weak and fragile for going through with it. Menstruation is not given enough medical importance, contingent on how potent its symptoms can be- from nausea and backache to stomach cramps that can invalidate any healthy and strong person. The hope is that with policies like these there is wider acceptance towards the gravity of this issue without it being used as a pretext for inequality or inferiority in the workplace.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though women are more substantially employed now, occupying more positions in the workspace than before especially in developed countries, the proportion of women in managerial and top executive positions still remains abysmally low and according to the Enterprise Survey by the World Bank, only 18% of businesses had a female CEO. On the other hand in legislatures, the proportion of women is approximately 24%. Women, in their entirety, comprise less than one-fourth of the major domains of the working world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is not just gender-based discrimination but also discrimination against occupations that are majorly dominated by women. Professions of nurses, teachers, secretaries, child-care workers are found to be respected less and paid less too. According to a report by &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, Primary teachers in the OECD countries earn 81% of the average for graduate jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue leads to a polarity in the jobs pursued by men and women and thus demotivates and intimidates women to take up jobs in the field of law and litigation, engineering and the police force. It is found that only 3.5% of women are firefighters, which is one of the most heavily male-dominated industries next to male technicians and mechanics who dominate 99.19% of the industry. Even something as universal as religion is dominated by men, according to &lt;em&gt;the Insider&lt;/em&gt;, only 17.6% of the clergy is female. And I am pretty sure this is not pertinent only to America but most of the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, an important solution to gender-wage-gap is the migration of genders from female-dominated sectors to the male-dominated sectors and vice-versa. As important as it is for women to pursue fields that are considered too ambitious for them, it is equally imperative for men to be accepted in industries that are primarily governed by women. It is also important for the parental-care axle to shift from mothers, who drop out of the workforce or shift to less-intensive jobs to take care of their children to fathers, with a higher emphasis on the implementation of paternity leaves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While discussing gender-based discrimination, to not consider the prejudice faced by trans people and other non-binary genders in the workplace would be unjust to the cause of equal wages for all. Trans people have even lesser representation and provisions to fall back on than women in the workplace and face persistent abuse and hiring-discrimination throughout the world, but more so in third-world and developing countries. Let alone provisions in the workplace, third-world countries like Kenya, Uganda, Senegal and Haiti do not even have basic anti-discriminatory laws for trans people. The transgender social acceptance rate, according to a report by Kimberly Tower is -2 whereas, in countries like India, Nepal and Argentina, it is positive yet wretchedly low, that is, 3, 2 and 1.5 respectively. Thus, there is still a long way to go for other genders to have equal remuneration and dignity as our &lt;em&gt;patriarchal lords&lt;/em&gt; in the workplace.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These statistics and facts only substantiate the actuality of domination of men in most sectors of the world, which leads to the gender-wage-gap. This majority that men enjoy in legislation, business or the sciences, is what propagates ideas, policies and products fabricated by men, which more often than not are not gender-friendly. Representation is salient as it leads to better targeted economic and social policies which will help bridge this widening gap and actualise acceptance - thus ameliorating the social and economic status of minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">On my way to university, I heard two women chatting beside me on the train and I couldn't help but eavesdrop at the horrors exchanged in their dialogue. They were engrossed in discussing or rather denouncing the daughter-in-law of one of their acquaintances for her values and time devoted to her family. From what I heard, they believed that she doesn't contribute much to the household chores as she continues to work after marriage (a heinous crime apparently) and comes home late. One of them said that this is bound to happen when women study too much.&amp;nbsp; This made me spiral into thinking about what most women, both married or unmarried, but mostly married, living with huge families and kids go through. They work from 9-5 or more I assume, complete their chores, handle their kids and still are not compensated enough for the same, be it the remuneration at their jobs in terms of money or the healthcare and safety provisions, and, on top of that, they are conveniently expected to undertake relentless unpaid work at home.&amp;nbsp; Even after all the effort that women put in every sphere of life, they still earn less respect and salary than their male counterparts for the same job, irrespective of their qualification and experience, contingent merely on their gender. Because women are child-bearers and menstruators who expect the bare minimum of maternity and period leaves as an employee. Because women can't lead teams as capably as their male counterparts, since they aren't dominant by birth.&amp;nbsp; This led me to realise that the gender-pay-gap is one of the most exploitative and discriminative features of our economic systems staring us in the face. One would expect a better system of rewards based on one’s merit and calibre, but even in the 21st century only six countries in the world, namely, Belgium, Denmark, France, Latvia, Luxembourg and Sweden grant men and women equal legal work rights, which is a concept as old as only a decade, according to a report by The Guardian.&amp;nbsp; Even so, bringing about legal changes does not translate into effective actions. In Sweden, women still earn about 5% less than their male counterparts and, globally, women earn 79 cents for every dollar paid to a man - which might not sound like a huge gap in theory but again, this is just a statistic which might not even reflect the actual situation flailing about in our system. It might not even consider the many women who are employed in the informal sectors of developing countries or are labouring away in the agricultural-sector without reaping any significant benefits out of it.&amp;nbsp; The wage gap exists for women of all educational backgrounds - from high school graduates to women with advanced degrees. According to a report by the Economic Policy Institute, this gap ranges from three dollars for women having an education level of less than high school to twelve dollars for women with advanced degrees. This is the opposite of what one would expect and a strong argument against how gender-wage-gap stems from the lower education levels of women. The gap only widens as the level of education increases, which is testament to the fact that the more literate and intelligent the woman, the more of a threat she is made out to be.&amp;nbsp; However, this bias is not limited to merely the pecuniary aspect of the work culture; it is deeply embedded in how women are treated in offices, always put on a rung lower than men, listened to but never heard or appreciated. From bearing the ‘motherhood penalty’ to being biologically ‘complicated’, women around the world are stifled at every step of their way to success. A recent American study deduced the average by which women’s future wages fall—at 4% per child, and 10% for the highest-earning, most skilled white women.&amp;nbsp; Women are considered assets as long as they do not ask for anything that lies outside the zone of anyone's convenience - be it providing maternity leaves or transportation for late work hours. And are also looked at like a nuisance for any lawsuits and uncomfortable conversations.&amp;nbsp; After the famous #MeToo movement, many companies and men in position suggested that hiring a woman nowadays can prove to be a risky investment because everything these days leads to lawsuits. Blaming the MeToo movement, many men claim that they are afraid to be alone with women in the workspace or hesitant to be around in their close vicinity - which is a complete rationalisation of the actions that are not okay in any workspace. And these men flagrantly choose to ignore that the issue doesn’t lie in women’s capability to live by the rules created by men but in men’s inability to treat them like human beings with boundaries that are to be respected.&amp;nbsp; Zomato, a food-delivery service was one of the first major-league companies in India to grant paid period leaves - an action heavily slated by men. Even so, only bringing a policy in place doesn't seem enough to provoke a change because most women might be hesitant to take those leaves due to the pronounced stigma around menstruation and being considered weak and fragile for going through with it. Menstruation is not given enough medical importance, contingent on how potent its symptoms can be- from nausea and backache to stomach cramps that can invalidate any healthy and strong person. The hope is that with policies like these there is wider acceptance towards the gravity of this issue without it being used as a pretext for inequality or inferiority in the workplace.&amp;nbsp; Even though women are more substantially employed now, occupying more positions in the workspace than before especially in developed countries, the proportion of women in managerial and top executive positions still remains abysmally low and according to the Enterprise Survey by the World Bank, only 18% of businesses had a female CEO. On the other hand in legislatures, the proportion of women is approximately 24%. Women, in their entirety, comprise less than one-fourth of the major domains of the working world.&amp;nbsp; The issue is not just gender-based discrimination but also discrimination against occupations that are majorly dominated by women. Professions of nurses, teachers, secretaries, child-care workers are found to be respected less and paid less too. According to a report by The Economist, Primary teachers in the OECD countries earn 81% of the average for graduate jobs. This issue leads to a polarity in the jobs pursued by men and women and thus demotivates and intimidates women to take up jobs in the field of law and litigation, engineering and the police force. It is found that only 3.5% of women are firefighters, which is one of the most heavily male-dominated industries next to male technicians and mechanics who dominate 99.19% of the industry. Even something as universal as religion is dominated by men, according to the Insider, only 17.6% of the clergy is female. And I am pretty sure this is not pertinent only to America but most of the world.&amp;nbsp; Thus, an important solution to gender-wage-gap is the migration of genders from female-dominated sectors to the male-dominated sectors and vice-versa. As important as it is for women to pursue fields that are considered too ambitious for them, it is equally imperative for men to be accepted in industries that are primarily governed by women. It is also important for the parental-care axle to shift from mothers, who drop out of the workforce or shift to less-intensive jobs to take care of their children to fathers, with a higher emphasis on the implementation of paternity leaves.&amp;nbsp; While discussing gender-based discrimination, to not consider the prejudice faced by trans people and other non-binary genders in the workplace would be unjust to the cause of equal wages for all. Trans people have even lesser representation and provisions to fall back on than women in the workplace and face persistent abuse and hiring-discrimination throughout the world, but more so in third-world and developing countries. Let alone provisions in the workplace, third-world countries like Kenya, Uganda, Senegal and Haiti do not even have basic anti-discriminatory laws for trans people. The transgender social acceptance rate, according to a report by Kimberly Tower is -2 whereas, in countries like India, Nepal and Argentina, it is positive yet wretchedly low, that is, 3, 2 and 1.5 respectively. Thus, there is still a long way to go for other genders to have equal remuneration and dignity as our patriarchal lords in the workplace.&amp;nbsp; These statistics and facts only substantiate the actuality of domination of men in most sectors of the world, which leads to the gender-wage-gap. This majority that men enjoy in legislation, business or the sciences, is what propagates ideas, policies and products fabricated by men, which more often than not are not gender-friendly. Representation is salient as it leads to better targeted economic and social policies which will help bridge this widening gap and actualise acceptance - thus ameliorating the social and economic status of minority genders.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?</title><link href="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, &lt;em&gt;during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with &lt;em&gt;rocks, &lt;/em&gt;we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: &lt;em&gt;“The world is watching, but will it do anything?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer. The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows. The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp; When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with rocks, we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp; The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp; Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: “The world is watching, but will it do anything?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Makeup Conundrum</title><link href="/The-Makeup-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Makeup Conundrum" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Makeup-Conundrum</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Makeup-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;Makeup is a very fascinating mode of self-expression. It is also a central part of many cultures across the globe. It is beautiful and is respected, but only within certain unspoken limits that are decided by the society in question.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often judge one’s personality by the amount and kind of makeup they are wearing. It can be either 'feminine’ and beautiful or unprofessional and frivolous. Not to mention, this is applicable only to one gender and everyone else is expected to not understand anything about it. In fact, they are expected to stay away from makeup, and when they do not follow this rule, they are seen as “unnatural”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Indians, like many other cultures, makeup is auspicious. A specific kind of makeup is reserved for each occasion or milestone in one’s life like engagement or wedding and of course, this varies from culture to culture. If you have, by any chance, come across an Indian TV serial or movie, you will know that more often than not, makeup is used to express certain character traits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, the female protagonist, who is shown to be a rather innocent and naive person, characteristics that we see being appreciated in female characters almost globally, has natural makeup on. On the other hand, the female antagonist tends to have very heavy makeup on, often playing with darker shades of red and black. This results in and is born out of an unconscious association of heavy or dark makeup with being promiscuous or a bad person.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moral policing in schools, especially in India, where I am from, is not rare. The administration and teachers often question the character of female students who choose to express themselves through different hairstyles or even just a simple eyeliner. It has been so ingrained in our psyche that most of us never even questioned it and in fact, were, to a large extent, in agreement with the policing. Makeup is simply a form of expression and associating it with not being serious about education is simply baseless and a way to control women. If a simple eyeliner is 'disruptive', we are definitely going wrong somewhere in our education system.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extension of this is the idea that women wear makeup solely to attract men. In fact, this is often used to shame girls in schools (at least, in India) who are found wearing anything that can be remotely associated with makeup. Honestly, if a little makeup distracts boys and men, they need to be taught to not sexualise anything and everything that is considered 'feminine' by society. Instead, school girls face punishment, sometimes to the extent of getting suspended.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When someone with authority suspends someone over wearing makeup, with the reason that it deviates attention from what is the main purpose of school, that is education, and more importantly, that it distracts the 'boys', it is a clear proclamation that they are unwilling to put an effort to teach boys to be respectful and are more satisfied with sending the person wearing makeup home, because their education is simply not as important as that of the boys.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of the matter is that makeup is simply a form of art. Neither should it be gendered nor should it be associated with a certain intention or personality trait. Some people wear makeup because of insecurities, some wear it because they enjoy it, some do it as a form of art and expression, some do it because it makes them feel confident - there is a myriad of reasons for wearing makeup.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This association of makeup with being frivolous or in other words, 'girly', a trait usually seen as negative and associated with not being serious, hardworking or trustworthy, has been around for a while now. In fact, many women who are victims of internalised misogyny fail to notice the problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, a young graphic designer, Katherine Young re-created the cover of &lt;em&gt;Girls’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum - articles on fashion and makeup, as well as other career choices?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and a fashion-forward outfit as less accomplished or not symbolic of an empowered woman, than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cultures, women are expected to wear heavy makeup to conform to a very restrictive standard of beauty. This is, more often than not, influenced by Western ideals: sharp nose, fair skin, straight hair, oval face, etc. Women face societal pressure to use makeup to live up to these standards, lest they be misunderstood as not being serious or worth listening to or, worst of all, ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cultures, women’s worth is defined by how easy it is to “marry her off” and being conventionally pretty helps the process. Yet, when they post their own pictures on social media looking absolutely gorgeous with makeup on, they are swarmed with messages about how she would look prettier without makeup or how a certain person prefers women who don't wear makeup. In male-dominated office spaces, women who dress up or wear makeup often find it difficult to be taken seriously and are repeatedly sexualised - makeup is seen as unprofessional. Yet, when they don’t, they are not seen as well put together or are questioned if they are sick. The double standards are quite frankly, astonishing and hilarious.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of Hollywood’s beloved movies with 'ugly duckling transformation' sequences continue to propagate the idea that someone who isn't wearing makeup, is not really taking care of themselves and so, is not taken seriously. Until of course, the transformation sequence takes place and suddenly, everything she says makes sense and is worth listening to. Yet, the same movie has a jealous female character, portrayed as someone who understands only clothes and makeup, hell-bent upon making the protagonist’s life miserable for no apparent reason. The amount of knowledge concerning makeup makes all the difference in the personalities in these movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In South Korea, beauty standards are very strict and this often pushes youngsters to opt for plastic surgery simply to make their lives easier by being able to conform to the unrealistic Korean beauty standards. Over the last couple of years, K-beauty has made a mark on the Western world. However, it is now facing backlash from within Korea’s borders. Influencers and commoners alike want to see a shift in the standards that pressurise women to go to extreme lengths to attain an unrealistic youthful look appreciated by society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Escape the Corset, #metoo and other similar feminist movements have seen Korean women openly expressing their dissatisfaction with the highly unequal and unfair societal norms through demonstrations like cutting their hair short and destroying makeup, among others. In June of 2018, Lina Bae, a former beauty Youtuber, posted a video titled 'I am not pretty'. The video concludes with her asking her audience to not compare themselves to what the media portrays as beautiful because they are special just the way they are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This message was appreciated by a large audience and the video went viral and was watched several million times. However, Korean media continues to worship a very specific look, a look that Korean idols continue to feel pressured to starve themselves and go under the knife to achieve. There are very few popular exceptions like Hwasa and Jessi, and they are treated as just that, exceptions in their place because idols are meant to be thin, tall and fair.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is more interesting is that society sometimes tends to have different expectations, in terms of beauty, from people of different races or ethnic backgrounds. For example, big lips and dark skin is not appreciated on black girls and yet, that seems to be the most appreciated 'look' on white women. Kim Kardashian and Kylie Jenner are frequently called out for their choices that are best described as blackfishing or black faces. However, the impact is short lived and the same mistakes are made over and over again. Blackface was a popular form of makeup used by white actors to portray a caricature of a black person for a long time. The portrayals were nowhere near accurate and were primarily meant to dehumanise and make fun of black people. So, you can see why people are not fond of such trends and rightfully so.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox eyes are all the rage right now, with Bella Hadid making several magazine covers and fashion shows with the look, while East Asians, with monolids and natural fox eyes are frequently attacked and criticised for their looks. The 'migraine pose' that these models often use to pull the eyes up to give a fox eye effect is identical to the racially charged gesture made to make fun of East Asians. It is important to remember that this is not a recent issue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1930's, Cecil Holland, a Hollywood makeup artist used various techniques to simulate East Asian fox eyes on white actors to portray Asian characters, often villains. This was practised for a very long time and gave us characters like Fu Manchu and I Y Yunioshi (&lt;em&gt;Breakfast at Tiffany’s&lt;/em&gt;), both played by white actors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to genders other than cis-females, makeup is treated very differently. It's very clear from Candance Owen’s remarks on Harry Styles’ &lt;em&gt;Vogue&lt;/em&gt; cover wearing traditionally feminine garments: “Bring back manly men”, that the conservative world is not very appreciative of makeup on men. They are often victims of homophobic slurs, when love for creative expression through makeup has absolutely nothing to do with one’s sexuality. Drag makeup is often criticised too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disagreement often comes in the form of a claim that makeup was meant to be feminine and thus, should be reserved for women. This is actually objectively false, because it was only in the mid-1800's when makeup started to be associated with a particular gender. Queen Victoria I of Britain and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination” resulting in a widespread and long-standing association of it with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”. These ideas were exported with imperialism and colonialism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, prior to that, men were often seen dawning makeup. In ancient Egypt, makeup was an integral part of the culture and had various religious connotations and so, makeup was worn, irrespective of gender. In ancient Rome, men often used makeup to cover up bald spots, lightened their skin using white powder, applied red pigment on their cheeks and so on and so forth. Even in Elizabethan England, makeup was popular among men. The influence of the Victorian age would start dying out only when Hollywood started using makeup on actors. However, they were still not mainstream. In the late 20th century, rock and roll artists started expressing themselves through makeup. Even today, as multiple male makeup gurus dominate the internet, many are wary of men wearing makeup in everyday life. However, this gendered aspect of makeup is clearly very new and for thousands of years, starting around 4000 BC to the mid-1800's, makeup was very common among men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, a lot of associations, often negative, made with makeup are baseless and are only an attempt to control women and demean those who do not agree with the modern societal interpretations of 'femininity' and 'masculinity'. Most of these are a result of internalised misogyny and perception of anything “girly” as frivolous and not serious. These have long-standing consequences in terms of forcing women to opt for extreme measures to adhere to beauty standards and to escape the constant scrutiny based on their looks, and alternatively, toning it down to be taken seriously in certain male-dominated spaces. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Makeup is a very fascinating mode of self-expression. It is also a central part of many cultures across the globe. It is beautiful and is respected, but only within certain unspoken limits that are decided by the society in question.&amp;nbsp; People often judge one’s personality by the amount and kind of makeup they are wearing. It can be either 'feminine’ and beautiful or unprofessional and frivolous. Not to mention, this is applicable only to one gender and everyone else is expected to not understand anything about it. In fact, they are expected to stay away from makeup, and when they do not follow this rule, they are seen as “unnatural”.&amp;nbsp; For Indians, like many other cultures, makeup is auspicious. A specific kind of makeup is reserved for each occasion or milestone in one’s life like engagement or wedding and of course, this varies from culture to culture. If you have, by any chance, come across an Indian TV serial or movie, you will know that more often than not, makeup is used to express certain character traits.&amp;nbsp; Generally, the female protagonist, who is shown to be a rather innocent and naive person, characteristics that we see being appreciated in female characters almost globally, has natural makeup on. On the other hand, the female antagonist tends to have very heavy makeup on, often playing with darker shades of red and black. This results in and is born out of an unconscious association of heavy or dark makeup with being promiscuous or a bad person.&amp;nbsp; Moral policing in schools, especially in India, where I am from, is not rare. The administration and teachers often question the character of female students who choose to express themselves through different hairstyles or even just a simple eyeliner. It has been so ingrained in our psyche that most of us never even questioned it and in fact, were, to a large extent, in agreement with the policing. Makeup is simply a form of expression and associating it with not being serious about education is simply baseless and a way to control women. If a simple eyeliner is 'disruptive', we are definitely going wrong somewhere in our education system.&amp;nbsp; An extension of this is the idea that women wear makeup solely to attract men. In fact, this is often used to shame girls in schools (at least, in India) who are found wearing anything that can be remotely associated with makeup. Honestly, if a little makeup distracts boys and men, they need to be taught to not sexualise anything and everything that is considered 'feminine' by society. Instead, school girls face punishment, sometimes to the extent of getting suspended.&amp;nbsp; When someone with authority suspends someone over wearing makeup, with the reason that it deviates attention from what is the main purpose of school, that is education, and more importantly, that it distracts the 'boys', it is a clear proclamation that they are unwilling to put an effort to teach boys to be respectful and are more satisfied with sending the person wearing makeup home, because their education is simply not as important as that of the boys.&amp;nbsp; The point of the matter is that makeup is simply a form of art. Neither should it be gendered nor should it be associated with a certain intention or personality trait. Some people wear makeup because of insecurities, some wear it because they enjoy it, some do it as a form of art and expression, some do it because it makes them feel confident - there is a myriad of reasons for wearing makeup.&amp;nbsp; This association of makeup with being frivolous or in other words, 'girly', a trait usually seen as negative and associated with not being serious, hardworking or trustworthy, has been around for a while now. In fact, many women who are victims of internalised misogyny fail to notice the problem.&amp;nbsp; In 2016, a young graphic designer, Katherine Young re-created the cover of Girls’ Life magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum - articles on fashion and makeup, as well as other career choices?&amp;nbsp; Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and a fashion-forward outfit as less accomplished or not symbolic of an empowered woman, than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated.&amp;nbsp; In some cultures, women are expected to wear heavy makeup to conform to a very restrictive standard of beauty. This is, more often than not, influenced by Western ideals: sharp nose, fair skin, straight hair, oval face, etc. Women face societal pressure to use makeup to live up to these standards, lest they be misunderstood as not being serious or worth listening to or, worst of all, ugly. In many cultures, women’s worth is defined by how easy it is to “marry her off” and being conventionally pretty helps the process. Yet, when they post their own pictures on social media looking absolutely gorgeous with makeup on, they are swarmed with messages about how she would look prettier without makeup or how a certain person prefers women who don't wear makeup. In male-dominated office spaces, women who dress up or wear makeup often find it difficult to be taken seriously and are repeatedly sexualised - makeup is seen as unprofessional. Yet, when they don’t, they are not seen as well put together or are questioned if they are sick. The double standards are quite frankly, astonishing and hilarious.&amp;nbsp; Many of Hollywood’s beloved movies with 'ugly duckling transformation' sequences continue to propagate the idea that someone who isn't wearing makeup, is not really taking care of themselves and so, is not taken seriously. Until of course, the transformation sequence takes place and suddenly, everything she says makes sense and is worth listening to. Yet, the same movie has a jealous female character, portrayed as someone who understands only clothes and makeup, hell-bent upon making the protagonist’s life miserable for no apparent reason. The amount of knowledge concerning makeup makes all the difference in the personalities in these movies. In South Korea, beauty standards are very strict and this often pushes youngsters to opt for plastic surgery simply to make their lives easier by being able to conform to the unrealistic Korean beauty standards. Over the last couple of years, K-beauty has made a mark on the Western world. However, it is now facing backlash from within Korea’s borders. Influencers and commoners alike want to see a shift in the standards that pressurise women to go to extreme lengths to attain an unrealistic youthful look appreciated by society.&amp;nbsp; The Escape the Corset, #metoo and other similar feminist movements have seen Korean women openly expressing their dissatisfaction with the highly unequal and unfair societal norms through demonstrations like cutting their hair short and destroying makeup, among others. In June of 2018, Lina Bae, a former beauty Youtuber, posted a video titled 'I am not pretty'. The video concludes with her asking her audience to not compare themselves to what the media portrays as beautiful because they are special just the way they are.&amp;nbsp; This message was appreciated by a large audience and the video went viral and was watched several million times. However, Korean media continues to worship a very specific look, a look that Korean idols continue to feel pressured to starve themselves and go under the knife to achieve. There are very few popular exceptions like Hwasa and Jessi, and they are treated as just that, exceptions in their place because idols are meant to be thin, tall and fair.&amp;nbsp; What is more interesting is that society sometimes tends to have different expectations, in terms of beauty, from people of different races or ethnic backgrounds. For example, big lips and dark skin is not appreciated on black girls and yet, that seems to be the most appreciated 'look' on white women. Kim Kardashian and Kylie Jenner are frequently called out for their choices that are best described as blackfishing or black faces. However, the impact is short lived and the same mistakes are made over and over again. Blackface was a popular form of makeup used by white actors to portray a caricature of a black person for a long time. The portrayals were nowhere near accurate and were primarily meant to dehumanise and make fun of black people. So, you can see why people are not fond of such trends and rightfully so.&amp;nbsp; Fox eyes are all the rage right now, with Bella Hadid making several magazine covers and fashion shows with the look, while East Asians, with monolids and natural fox eyes are frequently attacked and criticised for their looks. The 'migraine pose' that these models often use to pull the eyes up to give a fox eye effect is identical to the racially charged gesture made to make fun of East Asians. It is important to remember that this is not a recent issue.&amp;nbsp; In the 1930's, Cecil Holland, a Hollywood makeup artist used various techniques to simulate East Asian fox eyes on white actors to portray Asian characters, often villains. This was practised for a very long time and gave us characters like Fu Manchu and I Y Yunioshi (Breakfast at Tiffany’s), both played by white actors.&amp;nbsp; When it comes to genders other than cis-females, makeup is treated very differently. It's very clear from Candance Owen’s remarks on Harry Styles’ Vogue cover wearing traditionally feminine garments: “Bring back manly men”, that the conservative world is not very appreciative of makeup on men. They are often victims of homophobic slurs, when love for creative expression through makeup has absolutely nothing to do with one’s sexuality. Drag makeup is often criticised too.&amp;nbsp; The disagreement often comes in the form of a claim that makeup was meant to be feminine and thus, should be reserved for women. This is actually objectively false, because it was only in the mid-1800's when makeup started to be associated with a particular gender. Queen Victoria I of Britain and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination” resulting in a widespread and long-standing association of it with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”. These ideas were exported with imperialism and colonialism.&amp;nbsp; However, prior to that, men were often seen dawning makeup. In ancient Egypt, makeup was an integral part of the culture and had various religious connotations and so, makeup was worn, irrespective of gender. In ancient Rome, men often used makeup to cover up bald spots, lightened their skin using white powder, applied red pigment on their cheeks and so on and so forth. Even in Elizabethan England, makeup was popular among men. The influence of the Victorian age would start dying out only when Hollywood started using makeup on actors. However, they were still not mainstream. In the late 20th century, rock and roll artists started expressing themselves through makeup. Even today, as multiple male makeup gurus dominate the internet, many are wary of men wearing makeup in everyday life. However, this gendered aspect of makeup is clearly very new and for thousands of years, starting around 4000 BC to the mid-1800's, makeup was very common among men.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, a lot of associations, often negative, made with makeup are baseless and are only an attempt to control women and demean those who do not agree with the modern societal interpretations of 'femininity' and 'masculinity'. Most of these are a result of internalised misogyny and perception of anything “girly” as frivolous and not serious. These have long-standing consequences in terms of forcing women to opt for extreme measures to adhere to beauty standards and to escape the constant scrutiny based on their looks, and alternatively, toning it down to be taken seriously in certain male-dominated spaces.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital Yuan: The Start of the End for the US Dollar?</title><link href="/Digital-Yuan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Yuan: The Start of the End for the US Dollar?" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Digital-Yuan</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Digital-Yuan">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Crypto currency mania has gripped the world, as increasing acceptance of blockchain technology by major financial institutions has propelled the likes of Bitcoin into the mainstream. Whether you believe in crypto or not, the emergence of crypto currencies threatens to usurp fiat money. The Chinese government has identified the threat early, and has taken significant steps to ensure they have a meaningful head start on digitising their commercial sector and money supply. China’s long anticipated and recently released digital Yuan threatens to undermine the US dollar’s (USD) supremacy as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;China’s digital Yuan project is the first of its kind for any major global economy. It is a version of normal Chinese currency, deployed on a blockchain; the highly encrypted and secure online ledger technology that underpins digital coins like Bitcoin and Ethereum. The People’s Bank of China (PBOC) has led work on the digital Yuan project, which is classified as a central bank digital currency (CBDC) that aims to replace some of the cash in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;China has been trialling the digital currency since late 2020, and in 11 different regions since April, including in major cities such as Suzhou and Shenzhen, where the digital Yuan has been used for transport, food and retail. The digital Yuan bypasses the need for central banks in transaction processes, eliminating service fees and speeding up transaction times. China has plans for international use of the digital Yuan by 2024 or 2025, and has already established partnerships with the UAE, Hong Kong, and Thailand to promote international use of CBDCs. Given the vast extent of China’s bilateral trade relations globally, and the increasing likelihood of China overtaking the US as the world's largest economy, the internalisation of the digital Yuan is seeming inevitable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decline of the Dollar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The emergence of the digital Yuan coincides with a difficult period for the US dollar. The US dollar has become increasingly fragile of late, perhaps mirroring America’s decline within the international system, with its status as the ultimate reserve currency looking increasingly likely to be challenged in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US dollar has seen a steady fall since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is down about 10-12% relative to America’s major trading partners. Some have even suggested that the dollar will decline in value by 35% by the end of 2021. Ongoing political instability in the US has had a detrimental effect on global trust in the US dollar. The debasing of the US dollar through massive US government debt and central bank stimulus raises the question of the dollar’s long-term viability as the ultimate reserve currency.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To demonstrate this effect, we can look at the declining market of the US-China bilateral trade. The US imports from China dropped by $87.3 billion in 2019 from 2018, and continue to drop annually. The Chinese need for the US dollar is declining. The use of the US dollar in China-Russia transactions has declined from 90% in 2015 to less than 50% in the first quarter of 2020. At a rate of 10% annual decline, it will not be long before the US dollar is no longer used at all in China’s transactions. This vacuum left by the USD will allow for the growth of other currencies such as the digital Yuan. As more countries decide not to use the US dollar, the use of alternative currency reserves will increase. Given China’s extensive trade relations, the digital Yuan is well positioned to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China not Attempting to Replace USD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While it appears that the US dollar and digital Yuan are moving in opposite directions, Chinese officials have claimed that the development of the digital Yuan is not intended to ‘replace the USD’ as the ultimate reserve currency. Deputy governor of the PBOC Li Bo claimed that “efforts to create the digital Yuan are aimed at domestic use,” while Governor of the PBOC, Zhou Xiachuan, echoed that Beijing is not aiming to immediately take on the USD as a currency reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Regardless of China’s intentions for the digital Yuan, the reality is that the growth of the new digital currency will likely further contribute to the weakening and destabilisation of the USD. Much like when China developed paper currency in the 7th century during the Tang dynasty, China is today leading the way in a key transitional phase of the global financial system. The CBDC space certainly has potential to be a key battleground in the larger US-China struggle for global hegemony. Perhaps it is time for the US central bank to explore the implementation of a CBDC project more urgently. Should they fail to do so, there is a pressing possibility for the USD to get left behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-Noam Konyn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Noam Konyn is a graduate of the University of Bristol. He is currently pursuing an MA Government Specialisation in diplomacy and conflict at Interdisciplinary Centre Herzliya, Israel. He has previously worked in Elminda, a brain health medical device company in Tel Aviv, Israel.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guest</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Crypto currency mania has gripped the world, as increasing acceptance of blockchain technology by major financial institutions has propelled the likes of Bitcoin into the mainstream. Whether you believe in crypto or not, the emergence of crypto currencies threatens to usurp fiat money. The Chinese government has identified the threat early, and has taken significant steps to ensure they have a meaningful head start on digitising their commercial sector and money supply. China’s long anticipated and recently released digital Yuan threatens to undermine the US dollar’s (USD) supremacy as we know it. China’s digital Yuan project is the first of its kind for any major global economy. It is a version of normal Chinese currency, deployed on a blockchain; the highly encrypted and secure online ledger technology that underpins digital coins like Bitcoin and Ethereum. The People’s Bank of China (PBOC) has led work on the digital Yuan project, which is classified as a central bank digital currency (CBDC) that aims to replace some of the cash in circulation. China has been trialling the digital currency since late 2020, and in 11 different regions since April, including in major cities such as Suzhou and Shenzhen, where the digital Yuan has been used for transport, food and retail. The digital Yuan bypasses the need for central banks in transaction processes, eliminating service fees and speeding up transaction times. China has plans for international use of the digital Yuan by 2024 or 2025, and has already established partnerships with the UAE, Hong Kong, and Thailand to promote international use of CBDCs. Given the vast extent of China’s bilateral trade relations globally, and the increasing likelihood of China overtaking the US as the world's largest economy, the internalisation of the digital Yuan is seeming inevitable.&amp;nbsp; Decline of the Dollar The emergence of the digital Yuan coincides with a difficult period for the US dollar. The US dollar has become increasingly fragile of late, perhaps mirroring America’s decline within the international system, with its status as the ultimate reserve currency looking increasingly likely to be challenged in the long term. The US dollar has seen a steady fall since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is down about 10-12% relative to America’s major trading partners. Some have even suggested that the dollar will decline in value by 35% by the end of 2021. Ongoing political instability in the US has had a detrimental effect on global trust in the US dollar. The debasing of the US dollar through massive US government debt and central bank stimulus raises the question of the dollar’s long-term viability as the ultimate reserve currency.&amp;nbsp; To demonstrate this effect, we can look at the declining market of the US-China bilateral trade. The US imports from China dropped by $87.3 billion in 2019 from 2018, and continue to drop annually. The Chinese need for the US dollar is declining. The use of the US dollar in China-Russia transactions has declined from 90% in 2015 to less than 50% in the first quarter of 2020. At a rate of 10% annual decline, it will not be long before the US dollar is no longer used at all in China’s transactions. This vacuum left by the USD will allow for the growth of other currencies such as the digital Yuan. As more countries decide not to use the US dollar, the use of alternative currency reserves will increase. Given China’s extensive trade relations, the digital Yuan is well positioned to take over. China not Attempting to Replace USD While it appears that the US dollar and digital Yuan are moving in opposite directions, Chinese officials have claimed that the development of the digital Yuan is not intended to ‘replace the USD’ as the ultimate reserve currency. Deputy governor of the PBOC Li Bo claimed that “efforts to create the digital Yuan are aimed at domestic use,” while Governor of the PBOC, Zhou Xiachuan, echoed that Beijing is not aiming to immediately take on the USD as a currency reserve. Regardless of China’s intentions for the digital Yuan, the reality is that the growth of the new digital currency will likely further contribute to the weakening and destabilisation of the USD. Much like when China developed paper currency in the 7th century during the Tang dynasty, China is today leading the way in a key transitional phase of the global financial system. The CBDC space certainly has potential to be a key battleground in the larger US-China struggle for global hegemony. Perhaps it is time for the US central bank to explore the implementation of a CBDC project more urgently. Should they fail to do so, there is a pressing possibility for the USD to get left behind. -Noam Konyn Noam Konyn is a graduate of the University of Bristol. He is currently pursuing an MA Government Specialisation in diplomacy and conflict at Interdisciplinary Centre Herzliya, Israel. He has previously worked in Elminda, a brain health medical device company in Tel Aviv, Israel.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality</title><link href="/Transgenders-in-Sports" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality" /><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Transgenders-in-Sports</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Transgenders-in-Sports">&lt;p&gt;Throughout the U.S., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators&lt;/a&gt; that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Issue at Hand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's &lt;strong&gt;100 meters&lt;/strong&gt; lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.duke.edu/sports/sex-sport/comparative-athletic-performance/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds&lt;/a&gt;. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6391653/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges&lt;/a&gt; (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.olympic.org/the-ioc&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International Olympic Committee&lt;/a&gt; (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/01/sports/transgender-idaho-ban-sports.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ki.se/new-study-on-changes-in-muscle-mass-and-strength-after-gender-affirming-treatment-may-have-an&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-connecticut-girl-challenges-male-domination-of-female-sports-11562885421#&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year&lt;/a&gt;. Within just three years, girls across the state were &lt;a href=&quot;https://mspolicy.org/an-interview-with-selina-soule-a-brave-young-woman-standing-up-for-womens-sports/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/news/hsph-in-the-news/transgender-youth-at-risk-for-depression-suicide/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/trumps-plan-to-redefine-gender-makes-no-scientific-sense/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the limits of what science can offer&lt;/a&gt;, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions still unsolved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moving on, what about Intersex people?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eeshita Verma</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Throughout the U.S., roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about? Terminology Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand. The Issue at Hand The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’ To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly: Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's 100 meters lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp; Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories. So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp; One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the International Olympic Committee (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year.&amp;nbsp; But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (Source) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women. One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp; Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year. Within just three years, girls across the state were denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions. Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp; The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’ To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete. A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established. However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier. Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity. And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge. These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp; This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender? Possible Solutions One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp; For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against the limits of what science can offer, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp; Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels? Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task. If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions. Questions still unsolved To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders? Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago. Moving on, what about Intersex people? Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex. To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well. Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons.</summary></entry></feed>