<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-09-21T16:28:11+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Power Play: China’s Command &amp;amp; Control</title><link href="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power Play: China's Command &amp; Control" /><published>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control">&lt;p&gt;In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/stocks/news/market-darling-tencent-turns-into-worlds-worst-stock-bet-with-170-billion-wipeout/articleshow/84853892.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;had $170 billion shaved off its value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.natlawreview.com/article/china-issues-data-security-law&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;adopted a new cybersecurity law in June&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ride, hailing giant Didi Global&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/startups/china-strengthens-protection-for-food-delivery-workers-in-setback-for-meituan-alibaba/articleshow/84755202.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;announced new worker protection rules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “&lt;em&gt;They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/china-blocked-jack-mas-ant-ipo-after-an-investigation-revealed-who-stood-to-gain-11613491292?mod=searchresults_pos10&amp;amp;page=1&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alternative power centers&lt;/a&gt; in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US electric car maker &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/market-data/quotes/TSLA&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tesla&lt;/a&gt; Inc has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/tesla-to-store-china-data-locally-in-new-data-center-11622015001?mod=article_inline&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/topics/person/donald-trump&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt;, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp; To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years. China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has had $170 billion shaved off its value. For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp; The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week. For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp; China adopted a new cybersecurity law in June, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented. Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's ride, hailing giant Didi Global’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public. The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations. If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government announced new worker protection rules, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp; On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly. The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp; Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp; Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.” Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns. However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties. China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build alternative power centers in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp; In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp; Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp; Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp; US electric car maker Tesla Inc has pledged to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders. “Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.” Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data. Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp; Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, Donald Trump, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp; For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government. Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Most Oppressive Fashion Trends Throughout History</title><link href="/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Oppressive Fashion Trends Throughout History" /><published>2021-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History">&lt;p&gt;For much of history, women have lived as second-class citizens. American women were only given the right to vote in the twentieth century. As recently as in the 1970's, a woman should be denied a credit card unless it had her husband’s signature. The freedom we enjoy today is a fairly recent thing; our grandmothers lived in an era with fewer rights, and the generations that came before them had it even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from having fewer legal rights, women in the past also had fewer fashion choices.&amp;nbsp; As recently as in the 1940's, women were arrested for wearing pants in public, as they were considered to be menswear. In some cases, historical fashion trends should even be deadly. Here are some of the most oppressive fashion trends that have existed throughout history, which give us a gruesome reminder of how women's bodies have been policed since time immemorial to achieve certain extremely artificial ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waist-cinching corsets made it difficult to breathe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corsets are still worn today, but most of them aren’t nearly as restrictive as the ones our ancestors wore. The rise of the corset as a device to slash the waistline dates back to the 16th century. Historical corsets were notoriously uncomfortable, and constructed from confining materials such as whalebone.&amp;nbsp; When laced into a tight, rigid corset, women should not raise their arms above their heads, move too quickly without running out of breath, or slouch. The corsets made women have impeccable posture by essentially locking them in a cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 19th century, doctors were warning women against lacing their corsets too tightly. As the 20th century progressed, bras began to displace the corset as the undergarment of choice, but the corset hasn’t really died out and still sees widespread use in the 21st century.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, it is no longer a fashion staple or considered societally mandated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chinese women had their feet broken to make them smaller&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most horrifying examples of oppressive fashion comes from China during the Tang Dynasty, which lasted from 618 to 906 AD.&amp;nbsp; In the 10th century, small feet were highly prized, and the practice of foot binding in order to achieve 'Golden Lotus' feet began. Girls as young as five would have their four smaller toes bent under their foot and then tightly bound. This would impede the growth of the foot, and permanently deform it. The feet would be kept bound (although the bindings would be regularly changed) for the rest of a woman’s life.&amp;nbsp; Losing toes to infection was not uncommon, and even women who kept all of their toes had great difficulty walking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the practice of foot binding was most common in the upper classes, the lower classes would sometimes adopt the process in order to improve the marriage prospects of their daughters. Foot binding continued well into the 20th century, in spite of several attempts over the centuries to ban it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ridiculously wide skirts led to deadly accidents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the many fashions that inhibited a woman’s ability to walk with ease, wide skirts were some of the most dangerous.&amp;nbsp; Full skirts have cycled in and out of style for centuries. They were in vogue during the Renaissance era. By the end of the 18th century, skirts were straight, but began expanding again in the first half of the 19th century. By the middle of the century, women were wearing massive hoop crinolines underneath their dresses. In Europe, this fad came to be known as Crinolinemania. Skirts could be as large as six feet in diameter, making it difficult to navigate crowded areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, however, wasn’t the greatest drawback of the crinoline. The voluminous skirts could also get stuck in carriage wheels, and also posed a fire hazard. Since the skirts were so large and difficult to maneuver, thousands of women managed to set their dresses aflame when walking by a fire or a lit candle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hobble skirts prevented women from taking large sters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ease of movement was clearly a pretty low priority for women’s fashion designers throughout history. This was particularly apparent in the 1900's, when a new trend hit the fashion scene. The decline of the crinoline resulted in narrower skirts, but this time the fashion went too far in the opposite direction. By the turn of the 20th century, women were wearing skirts so narrow that they were dubbed “hobble skirts.&quot; These hobble skirts were fitted so tightly around the lower legs that women were forced to take tiny steps, hobbling along in their stylish garments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women wearing these dresses not only had trouble walking and dancing, but many also found themselves in dangerous predicaments. The constricting garments led to accidents and even death, making the trend one of the most dangerous of the century. Many people in the era were confused by the popularity of the wildly impractical trend, and hobble skirts were widely mocked in the newspapers of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absurdly large gigot sleeves made it difficult for women to move their arms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, clothing is designed to be aesthetically appealing without being functional. Beginning in the 1820's, women had limited use of their arms thanks to gigot sleeves, also known as leg o’ mutton sleeves.&amp;nbsp; While ruffed sleeves can still be found in clothes today, the sleeves of the 19th century were so outrageously large that women could barely move. The sleeve would balloon at the shoulders, then tarer down along the arm before ending tightly at the wrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sleeves would prevent women from raising their arms above their heads. The large sleeve trend would continue throughout the Vistorian era. Combined with other trends of the time including wider skirts, tighter corsets, and layers of undergarments, women in this era were so encased in fabric that the summer months must have been agonizing for them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These trends resulted in a generation of women who were barely able to move, let alone breathe. A physical manifestation of oppression if we ever heard of one and a practical manifestation of the dangers of 'aesthetic&amp;nbsp; perfection'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, we’re stepping into an age where the media is beginning to celebrate diversity of race and body type — though there’s still a long way to go. Before New York Fashion Week 2017, the Council of Fashion Designers of America sent out a memo to remind designers to seek out healthy models and a wider range of types saying, “New York Fashion Week is also a celebration of our city's diversity, which we hope to see on the runways.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing to remember is that most of the historical standards of beauty were based on a drawing or a painting of a man’s fantasy!&amp;nbsp; Nowadays Photoshop has the same effect, making already-petite models look unattainably perfect. One can’t possibly live up to a fictional piece of art or a masterfully altered photograph. Since standards have changed so much over history (just try to wear big 80's hair and makeup to look hot today), it proves that these standards are really just temporary ideals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your body isn’t considered 'perfect' today?&amp;nbsp; Who cares! 'Perfect' is an illusion that no one can attain. So, be happy with the body you have and celebrate all the things that make up your gorgeous, imperfect self.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tejasvi Joshi</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="culture" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">For much of history, women have lived as second-class citizens. American women were only given the right to vote in the twentieth century. As recently as in the 1970's, a woman should be denied a credit card unless it had her husband’s signature. The freedom we enjoy today is a fairly recent thing; our grandmothers lived in an era with fewer rights, and the generations that came before them had it even worse. Aside from having fewer legal rights, women in the past also had fewer fashion choices.&amp;nbsp; As recently as in the 1940's, women were arrested for wearing pants in public, as they were considered to be menswear. In some cases, historical fashion trends should even be deadly. Here are some of the most oppressive fashion trends that have existed throughout history, which give us a gruesome reminder of how women's bodies have been policed since time immemorial to achieve certain extremely artificial ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp; Waist-cinching corsets made it difficult to breathe Corsets are still worn today, but most of them aren’t nearly as restrictive as the ones our ancestors wore. The rise of the corset as a device to slash the waistline dates back to the 16th century. Historical corsets were notoriously uncomfortable, and constructed from confining materials such as whalebone.&amp;nbsp; When laced into a tight, rigid corset, women should not raise their arms above their heads, move too quickly without running out of breath, or slouch. The corsets made women have impeccable posture by essentially locking them in a cage. By the 19th century, doctors were warning women against lacing their corsets too tightly. As the 20th century progressed, bras began to displace the corset as the undergarment of choice, but the corset hasn’t really died out and still sees widespread use in the 21st century.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, it is no longer a fashion staple or considered societally mandated. Chinese women had their feet broken to make them smaller One of the most horrifying examples of oppressive fashion comes from China during the Tang Dynasty, which lasted from 618 to 906 AD.&amp;nbsp; In the 10th century, small feet were highly prized, and the practice of foot binding in order to achieve 'Golden Lotus' feet began. Girls as young as five would have their four smaller toes bent under their foot and then tightly bound. This would impede the growth of the foot, and permanently deform it. The feet would be kept bound (although the bindings would be regularly changed) for the rest of a woman’s life.&amp;nbsp; Losing toes to infection was not uncommon, and even women who kept all of their toes had great difficulty walking. While the practice of foot binding was most common in the upper classes, the lower classes would sometimes adopt the process in order to improve the marriage prospects of their daughters. Foot binding continued well into the 20th century, in spite of several attempts over the centuries to ban it. Ridiculously wide skirts led to deadly accidents Of the many fashions that inhibited a woman’s ability to walk with ease, wide skirts were some of the most dangerous.&amp;nbsp; Full skirts have cycled in and out of style for centuries. They were in vogue during the Renaissance era. By the end of the 18th century, skirts were straight, but began expanding again in the first half of the 19th century. By the middle of the century, women were wearing massive hoop crinolines underneath their dresses. In Europe, this fad came to be known as Crinolinemania. Skirts could be as large as six feet in diameter, making it difficult to navigate crowded areas. This, however, wasn’t the greatest drawback of the crinoline. The voluminous skirts could also get stuck in carriage wheels, and also posed a fire hazard. Since the skirts were so large and difficult to maneuver, thousands of women managed to set their dresses aflame when walking by a fire or a lit candle. Hobble skirts prevented women from taking large sters Ease of movement was clearly a pretty low priority for women’s fashion designers throughout history. This was particularly apparent in the 1900's, when a new trend hit the fashion scene. The decline of the crinoline resulted in narrower skirts, but this time the fashion went too far in the opposite direction. By the turn of the 20th century, women were wearing skirts so narrow that they were dubbed “hobble skirts.&quot; These hobble skirts were fitted so tightly around the lower legs that women were forced to take tiny steps, hobbling along in their stylish garments. Women wearing these dresses not only had trouble walking and dancing, but many also found themselves in dangerous predicaments. The constricting garments led to accidents and even death, making the trend one of the most dangerous of the century. Many people in the era were confused by the popularity of the wildly impractical trend, and hobble skirts were widely mocked in the newspapers of the time. Absurdly large gigot sleeves made it difficult for women to move their arms Too often, clothing is designed to be aesthetically appealing without being functional. Beginning in the 1820's, women had limited use of their arms thanks to gigot sleeves, also known as leg o’ mutton sleeves.&amp;nbsp; While ruffed sleeves can still be found in clothes today, the sleeves of the 19th century were so outrageously large that women could barely move. The sleeve would balloon at the shoulders, then tarer down along the arm before ending tightly at the wrist. These sleeves would prevent women from raising their arms above their heads. The large sleeve trend would continue throughout the Vistorian era. Combined with other trends of the time including wider skirts, tighter corsets, and layers of undergarments, women in this era were so encased in fabric that the summer months must have been agonizing for them.&amp;nbsp; These trends resulted in a generation of women who were barely able to move, let alone breathe. A physical manifestation of oppression if we ever heard of one and a practical manifestation of the dangers of 'aesthetic&amp;nbsp; perfection'.&amp;nbsp; Luckily, we’re stepping into an age where the media is beginning to celebrate diversity of race and body type — though there’s still a long way to go. Before New York Fashion Week 2017, the Council of Fashion Designers of America sent out a memo to remind designers to seek out healthy models and a wider range of types saying, “New York Fashion Week is also a celebration of our city's diversity, which we hope to see on the runways.&quot; The thing to remember is that most of the historical standards of beauty were based on a drawing or a painting of a man’s fantasy!&amp;nbsp; Nowadays Photoshop has the same effect, making already-petite models look unattainably perfect. One can’t possibly live up to a fictional piece of art or a masterfully altered photograph. Since standards have changed so much over history (just try to wear big 80's hair and makeup to look hot today), it proves that these standards are really just temporary ideals. If your body isn’t considered 'perfect' today?&amp;nbsp; Who cares! 'Perfect' is an illusion that no one can attain. So, be happy with the body you have and celebrate all the things that make up your gorgeous, imperfect self.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Afghanistan Is Not Vietnam: The American Empire Is Dying</title><link href="/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan Is Not Vietnam: The American Empire Is Dying" /><published>2021-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam">&lt;p&gt;The professional pundits of foreign policy are busy discussing the parallels between Afghanistan and Vietnam. But the fact is that the US was a whole different country at the end of the Vietnam war: it was deadlocked with the USSR in a struggle for world domination, its internal politics were beset with the winds of change, welfare statism and economic growth were on the rise, and the new directions that the polity of the ‘Empire’ would take were being thrashed out.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, the social upheavals due to racial tensions, the extreme shifts in the politics of both the Republicans and Democrats, and the challenge presented by the Dragon in the East, do make it appear as though we are back in the 60's and the 70's. But we can sense that we are dealing with a very different America. Like President Joe Biden, the US is growing old, its grip on power is waning, its ability and commitment to expanding and maintaining its vast Empire is declining.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, let us look at America's finances. The US government's deficits and borrowing have been consistently high since the Great Recession. It is expected that the US' debt-to-GDP ratio will reach 277% by 2029, surpassing Japan's 272%, making it the country with the highest debt-to-GDP ratio in the world. Corporate debt, i.e. the debt of the real gods of America, has been steadily increasing as well. It has reached a high of nearly $11 trillion this year, causing grave concern for the Federal Reserve.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that the huge expenses that are needed to maintain America's military might become exceedingly irrational. A quick look at the numbers from the last ten years would indicate that despite the Iraq War having been brought to an end by the Obama administration in 2011, the military budget of the United States has grown by nearly $80 billion. A third of the budget of the Department of Defense is spent on personnel and maintenance, which will probably rise by 100% by 2024 due to retirement and medical care costs. Moreover, the Department of Defense estimates that it is operating with 21% excess capacity in all its bases, since Congressmen cannot afford to allow their constituents to lose the jobs that these bases provide.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It becomes simply impossible to make sense of this kind of wasting of money when the US national debt is touching $22 trillion. It also goes to show that America's massive military might is built on a Jenga of dollar bills that simply cannot withstand that kind of weight. So, when America under the Trump administration brokered the deal with the Taliban and moved to exit swiftly from Afghanistan under the Biden administration, it did so just like that rich bully whose daddy had just been declared bankrupt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the corporate side of things, the burgeoning debt signals its own kind of decline, i.e., the dependence on a chain of debt to sustain the investment and expenditure activities instead of consumer spending. When this is seen along with a real average wage that has the same purchasing power as in 1979, one can see that American corporations are not delivering on the free-market capitalist promise of a market economy that works for everyone. The consequence is that the power and ability of corporations to control American affairs and to benefit from the exploitation of the resources that form part of its Empire is dwindling. The very fact that workers are refusing to take up jobs despite there being a demand in the labour market is symptomatic of the extent to which American corporations are losing their god-like status.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these present day crises can compare with the situation prevailing at the time of the Vietnam War. The total cost of the said war when compared with the $2 trillion cost of the Afghanistan War was a paltry $738 billion, when adjusted for inflation. The debt-to-GDP ratio actually decreased during the years of the Vietnam War. It stood at 43% in 1965, when America entered the war, and reduced to 32% in 1975, when America exited Vietnam.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only does America stand materially diminished in its ability to engage in the enterprise of Empire, its influence over its allies is waning as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allies are the grease which keep the war machines of an empire well-oiled, they are the support system that holds up its edifice. The British Empire in India was built on the Indian aristocracy and financial class switching loyalties from the Mughals to John Bull. It was Oxbridge-educated Indian civil servants, politicians, lawyers, etc., who ran the Empire in India and beyond. The British Empire began to falter the moment the elite class of Indians decided to no longer support the British Raj. From Gandhi to Nehru to Jinnah to Ambedkar, an overwhelming number of India and Pakistan's founding fathers were from elite Indian families, with a quintessentially British upper class education. In fact, it was this upper class education that exposed these leaders to ideas such as liberty, equality, and democracy, which they then used to dismantle the ideological core of the Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America is losing the allies that make its Empire possible in a manner that is no different from the way in which the British lost their allies in India. In an attempt to bombard its allies with its own ideology, America has made its politics, food, music, and culture a global spectacle and phenomenon. From fast food joints to Marvel movies, America's allies, i.e. 'the West', are bombarded with assertions of the Empire's superiority. While at the time of the Vietnam War this cultural messaging united the West in service of the supposedly rules-based, international world order championed by America, it is now coming back to bite&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;America in the behind.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As American media and American culture infect the world, the conflicts and the issues that plague that culture seize the imagination of its allies. As America struggles so heavily with its nationalistic propaganda on one hand and the consequent backlash against the same on the other, the same point of conflict is assuming the centre-stage in very many Western countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Britain this phenomenon has led to Brexit and a renewed call for Scottish independence. In France, we see the rise of Marine Lé Pen. In Germany, we see the rise of the &lt;em&gt;Alternative für Deutschland&lt;/em&gt;. These nationalistic movements question the American hegemony, they call out the skewed nature of the relationship the West has with the US. Serious strains have developed in the 'special relationship' between the UK and the US. In fact, China has even proposed an Africa Quad with France and Germany. The fact of the matter is that American nationalism and populism has made its allies swerve towards their own kind of nationalism and populism as they begin to ask themselves whether accepting American hegemony should really be such an important priority.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it's not like America is trying to keep its allies in mind when formulating its foreign policy objectives. This became starkly apparent during the Trump-era. Trump went straight ahead and questioned the usefulness of the NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Alliance) in a NATO summit itself. He berated Europe for its supposed inability to protect itself and even torpedoed the Iran nuclear deal – coming very close to starting a war with the country, much to the chagrin of key allies like France. In fact, President Macron of France had to step in to try and neutralise the situation after Trump exited the nuclear deal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Trump's America First policy is not being imitated in its rhetoric by the Biden administration, it is quite apparent that the Biden administration does not intend to change course. Biden's sudden withdrawal from Afghanistan and his statement that intervention would be written out of America's defence and foreign policy toolkit is symptomatic of how Biden is as uninterested in the Empire as Trump. The end of the Vietnam War never brought into question the Empire itself. That project was abandoned because it stopped making business sense after a point of time. Afghanistan, on the other hand, is being abandoned because the very task of maintaining world dominance seems too taxing for America to handle any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the issue of social upheaval. Both the Vietnam War and the Afghanistan War were accompanied by a period of intense social unrest in America. With the benefit of hindsight, one can observe that the two are hardly comparable. The Vietnam War came at a time when the Civil Rights Movement was in full swing. It was accompanied by the Sexual Revolution, the Hippie movement, the growth of subaltern literature, and, of course, the Johnson Presidency's welfare reforms. All of these movements ultimately served to reinvigorate American exceptionalism. These movements did critique the American Empire, but they were ultimately the birth pangs of a new age of American domination, not a challenge to the core of the Empire. The abolition of the Jim Crow laws and the implementation of Medicaid made America fairer and more equal, they did not question America itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the social unrest that has plagued America since the Great Recession is of a far more sinister kind. When the riots began after the killing of George Floyd, they did not merely call out racial injustice, they questioned the very existence of America as an entity which was built by slave-owners and continues to be exploitative of racial minorities. The protesters did not have a &quot;dream&quot; when they took down Robert E. Lee's statues, they had a pent up rage that had found its outlet through violent protest. The same sentiments were echoed in the Occupy Wall Street movements, the very basis of America, i.e., capitalism was brought into question by those movements. Large portions of the American populace are hitting the streets to express a desire to &quot;eat the rich&quot; at this point of time. A man calling himself a socialist would never have any popularity during the Vietnam War years, but in 2019, Senator Bernie Sanders nearly bagged the Democratic nomination for the Presidency.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seen in this light, the end of the Afghanistan War comes at a time when the American populace is questioning America itself. The American withdrawal from Afghanistan is an expression of exhaustion from a bloody conflict that the US just cannot afford. It is part of a series of events, both inside and outside America, which indicate that the torch of American hegemony is about to go out very soon, and far more horrifically than we may imagine. May God truly bless America.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The professional pundits of foreign policy are busy discussing the parallels between Afghanistan and Vietnam. But the fact is that the US was a whole different country at the end of the Vietnam war: it was deadlocked with the USSR in a struggle for world domination, its internal politics were beset with the winds of change, welfare statism and economic growth were on the rise, and the new directions that the polity of the ‘Empire’ would take were being thrashed out.&amp;nbsp; At present, the social upheavals due to racial tensions, the extreme shifts in the politics of both the Republicans and Democrats, and the challenge presented by the Dragon in the East, do make it appear as though we are back in the 60's and the 70's. But we can sense that we are dealing with a very different America. Like President Joe Biden, the US is growing old, its grip on power is waning, its ability and commitment to expanding and maintaining its vast Empire is declining.&amp;nbsp; First of all, let us look at America's finances. The US government's deficits and borrowing have been consistently high since the Great Recession. It is expected that the US' debt-to-GDP ratio will reach 277% by 2029, surpassing Japan's 272%, making it the country with the highest debt-to-GDP ratio in the world. Corporate debt, i.e. the debt of the real gods of America, has been steadily increasing as well. It has reached a high of nearly $11 trillion this year, causing grave concern for the Federal Reserve.&amp;nbsp; The result is that the huge expenses that are needed to maintain America's military might become exceedingly irrational. A quick look at the numbers from the last ten years would indicate that despite the Iraq War having been brought to an end by the Obama administration in 2011, the military budget of the United States has grown by nearly $80 billion. A third of the budget of the Department of Defense is spent on personnel and maintenance, which will probably rise by 100% by 2024 due to retirement and medical care costs. Moreover, the Department of Defense estimates that it is operating with 21% excess capacity in all its bases, since Congressmen cannot afford to allow their constituents to lose the jobs that these bases provide.&amp;nbsp; It becomes simply impossible to make sense of this kind of wasting of money when the US national debt is touching $22 trillion. It also goes to show that America's massive military might is built on a Jenga of dollar bills that simply cannot withstand that kind of weight. So, when America under the Trump administration brokered the deal with the Taliban and moved to exit swiftly from Afghanistan under the Biden administration, it did so just like that rich bully whose daddy had just been declared bankrupt.&amp;nbsp; On the corporate side of things, the burgeoning debt signals its own kind of decline, i.e., the dependence on a chain of debt to sustain the investment and expenditure activities instead of consumer spending. When this is seen along with a real average wage that has the same purchasing power as in 1979, one can see that American corporations are not delivering on the free-market capitalist promise of a market economy that works for everyone. The consequence is that the power and ability of corporations to control American affairs and to benefit from the exploitation of the resources that form part of its Empire is dwindling. The very fact that workers are refusing to take up jobs despite there being a demand in the labour market is symptomatic of the extent to which American corporations are losing their god-like status.&amp;nbsp; None of these present day crises can compare with the situation prevailing at the time of the Vietnam War. The total cost of the said war when compared with the $2 trillion cost of the Afghanistan War was a paltry $738 billion, when adjusted for inflation. The debt-to-GDP ratio actually decreased during the years of the Vietnam War. It stood at 43% in 1965, when America entered the war, and reduced to 32% in 1975, when America exited Vietnam.&amp;nbsp; Not only does America stand materially diminished in its ability to engage in the enterprise of Empire, its influence over its allies is waning as well.&amp;nbsp; Allies are the grease which keep the war machines of an empire well-oiled, they are the support system that holds up its edifice. The British Empire in India was built on the Indian aristocracy and financial class switching loyalties from the Mughals to John Bull. It was Oxbridge-educated Indian civil servants, politicians, lawyers, etc., who ran the Empire in India and beyond. The British Empire began to falter the moment the elite class of Indians decided to no longer support the British Raj. From Gandhi to Nehru to Jinnah to Ambedkar, an overwhelming number of India and Pakistan's founding fathers were from elite Indian families, with a quintessentially British upper class education. In fact, it was this upper class education that exposed these leaders to ideas such as liberty, equality, and democracy, which they then used to dismantle the ideological core of the Empire. America is losing the allies that make its Empire possible in a manner that is no different from the way in which the British lost their allies in India. In an attempt to bombard its allies with its own ideology, America has made its politics, food, music, and culture a global spectacle and phenomenon. From fast food joints to Marvel movies, America's allies, i.e. 'the West', are bombarded with assertions of the Empire's superiority. While at the time of the Vietnam War this cultural messaging united the West in service of the supposedly rules-based, international world order championed by America, it is now coming back to bite America in the behind.&amp;nbsp; As American media and American culture infect the world, the conflicts and the issues that plague that culture seize the imagination of its allies. As America struggles so heavily with its nationalistic propaganda on one hand and the consequent backlash against the same on the other, the same point of conflict is assuming the centre-stage in very many Western countries.&amp;nbsp; In Britain this phenomenon has led to Brexit and a renewed call for Scottish independence. In France, we see the rise of Marine Lé Pen. In Germany, we see the rise of the Alternative für Deutschland. These nationalistic movements question the American hegemony, they call out the skewed nature of the relationship the West has with the US. Serious strains have developed in the 'special relationship' between the UK and the US. In fact, China has even proposed an Africa Quad with France and Germany. The fact of the matter is that American nationalism and populism has made its allies swerve towards their own kind of nationalism and populism as they begin to ask themselves whether accepting American hegemony should really be such an important priority.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, it's not like America is trying to keep its allies in mind when formulating its foreign policy objectives. This became starkly apparent during the Trump-era. Trump went straight ahead and questioned the usefulness of the NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Alliance) in a NATO summit itself. He berated Europe for its supposed inability to protect itself and even torpedoed the Iran nuclear deal – coming very close to starting a war with the country, much to the chagrin of key allies like France. In fact, President Macron of France had to step in to try and neutralise the situation after Trump exited the nuclear deal.&amp;nbsp; While Trump's America First policy is not being imitated in its rhetoric by the Biden administration, it is quite apparent that the Biden administration does not intend to change course. Biden's sudden withdrawal from Afghanistan and his statement that intervention would be written out of America's defence and foreign policy toolkit is symptomatic of how Biden is as uninterested in the Empire as Trump. The end of the Vietnam War never brought into question the Empire itself. That project was abandoned because it stopped making business sense after a point of time. Afghanistan, on the other hand, is being abandoned because the very task of maintaining world dominance seems too taxing for America to handle any longer.&amp;nbsp; Finally, there is the issue of social upheaval. Both the Vietnam War and the Afghanistan War were accompanied by a period of intense social unrest in America. With the benefit of hindsight, one can observe that the two are hardly comparable. The Vietnam War came at a time when the Civil Rights Movement was in full swing. It was accompanied by the Sexual Revolution, the Hippie movement, the growth of subaltern literature, and, of course, the Johnson Presidency's welfare reforms. All of these movements ultimately served to reinvigorate American exceptionalism. These movements did critique the American Empire, but they were ultimately the birth pangs of a new age of American domination, not a challenge to the core of the Empire. The abolition of the Jim Crow laws and the implementation of Medicaid made America fairer and more equal, they did not question America itself.&amp;nbsp; In contrast, the social unrest that has plagued America since the Great Recession is of a far more sinister kind. When the riots began after the killing of George Floyd, they did not merely call out racial injustice, they questioned the very existence of America as an entity which was built by slave-owners and continues to be exploitative of racial minorities. The protesters did not have a &quot;dream&quot; when they took down Robert E. Lee's statues, they had a pent up rage that had found its outlet through violent protest. The same sentiments were echoed in the Occupy Wall Street movements, the very basis of America, i.e., capitalism was brought into question by those movements. Large portions of the American populace are hitting the streets to express a desire to &quot;eat the rich&quot; at this point of time. A man calling himself a socialist would never have any popularity during the Vietnam War years, but in 2019, Senator Bernie Sanders nearly bagged the Democratic nomination for the Presidency.&amp;nbsp; Seen in this light, the end of the Afghanistan War comes at a time when the American populace is questioning America itself. The American withdrawal from Afghanistan is an expression of exhaustion from a bloody conflict that the US just cannot afford. It is part of a series of events, both inside and outside America, which indicate that the torch of American hegemony is about to go out very soon, and far more horrifically than we may imagine. May God truly bless America.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Combating the Menace of Counterfeits</title><link href="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combating the Menace of Counterfeits" /><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits">&lt;p&gt;How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhinav Gupta</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp; The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp; The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products. There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp; From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp; Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp; Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp; Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp; The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp; The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp; Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too. The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp; Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp; This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp; In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status. While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp; The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp; Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp; Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp; Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp; High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp; In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp; There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp; For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp; However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked. The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp; Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp; Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Art for Thought</title><link href="/Art-for-Thought" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art for Thought" /><published>2021-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Art-for-Thought</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Art-for-Thought">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It would be a no-brainer today to say that the world is lacking in beauty and happiness. COVID-19 has wreaked havoc on our lives. So many people have lost their jobs. So many people have succumbed to the plague. So much despair colours the air. In all of this turmoil, it is not only easy to believe that there is no light at the end of the tunnel but also stupid to think that happiness can be more than a dream. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, we know that we cannot give in to the demons that beset the path of our whole species. We already know that we must give ourselves hope. For without hope there can be no survival. But the question is how? How can we overcome our human limitations? How do we convince a mind so affected by malaise to believe in a better tomorrow? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The answer lies in art. Art is the yearning of the human soul for something greater than itself. Art screams out to every human being out there that no matter how small they may be, they’re capable of wonderful things. Art is salvation for our restless minds in these times, when our bodies stay caged within four walls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We need art not just in some magnificent Da Vinci painting, but in every-day items: small but necessary things which remind us that life is worth living and that all is not lost. It is here that Vantheshoe comes to our aid. This small start-up, run by a charming young lady, by definition, refuses to give up on the soul of humanity. With charming floral prints and vivacious colours on all kinds of items like handbags, phone covers, and so on, Vantheshoe reminds you that this pandemic cannot take away the beauty that is within you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;No, this is not just some pithy advertorial trying to sell you a product by exploiting your deeper unhappiness. Rather, it is a heartfelt article telling you about the work of someone who is genuinely interested in giving you something that you can truly cherish. We are here not to sell Vantheshoes’s products, but to tell you why at all they are worth buying. In other words, we’re here in true solidarity with the depth of human feeling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, we implore you to explore &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vantheshoe.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vantheshoe’s products&lt;/a&gt;, to appreciate the designs and the hours of work that have gone into making them. We will not ask you to buy the products, that would be presumptuous, but we will ask you to see for yourselves that in every mobile cover, in every handbag, every coaster, there is the soul of an artist trapped inside waiting to be adored by the right person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/vantheshoe1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/vantheshoe2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>.</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="sponsored" /><summary type="html">It would be a no-brainer today to say that the world is lacking in beauty and happiness. COVID-19 has wreaked havoc on our lives. So many people have lost their jobs. So many people have succumbed to the plague. So much despair colours the air. In all of this turmoil, it is not only easy to believe that there is no light at the end of the tunnel but also stupid to think that happiness can be more than a dream. Nevertheless, we know that we cannot give in to the demons that beset the path of our whole species. We already know that we must give ourselves hope. For without hope there can be no survival. But the question is how? How can we overcome our human limitations? How do we convince a mind so affected by malaise to believe in a better tomorrow? The answer lies in art. Art is the yearning of the human soul for something greater than itself. Art screams out to every human being out there that no matter how small they may be, they’re capable of wonderful things. Art is salvation for our restless minds in these times, when our bodies stay caged within four walls.&amp;nbsp; We need art not just in some magnificent Da Vinci painting, but in every-day items: small but necessary things which remind us that life is worth living and that all is not lost. It is here that Vantheshoe comes to our aid. This small start-up, run by a charming young lady, by definition, refuses to give up on the soul of humanity. With charming floral prints and vivacious colours on all kinds of items like handbags, phone covers, and so on, Vantheshoe reminds you that this pandemic cannot take away the beauty that is within you. No, this is not just some pithy advertorial trying to sell you a product by exploiting your deeper unhappiness. Rather, it is a heartfelt article telling you about the work of someone who is genuinely interested in giving you something that you can truly cherish. We are here not to sell Vantheshoes’s products, but to tell you why at all they are worth buying. In other words, we’re here in true solidarity with the depth of human feeling. Thus, we implore you to explore Vantheshoe’s products, to appreciate the designs and the hours of work that have gone into making them. We will not ask you to buy the products, that would be presumptuous, but we will ask you to see for yourselves that in every mobile cover, in every handbag, every coaster, there is the soul of an artist trapped inside waiting to be adored by the right person.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Women in Corporations: Breaking the Glass Ceiling or Standing at the Glass Cliff?</title><link href="/Women-in-Corporations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women in Corporations: Breaking the Glass Ceiling or Standing at the Glass Cliff?" /><published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Women-in-Corporations</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Women-in-Corporations">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While listening to Ava Max’s song &lt;em&gt;Kings and Queens&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;whenever the line ‘&lt;em&gt;If all of the kings had queens on their throne, we would pop champagne and raise a toast’ &lt;/em&gt;comes,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;a gush of enthusiasm runs through my veins and the thought of women leading everywhere leaves me in awe of the world that they would create. However, as I sit down to write this article today, contemplating upon the lyrics, I am left baffled by the thought of whether the problem of gender discrimination is really solved by passing of thrones or is there more to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Historically, men have been perceived to be natural leaders while women and other minority groups have fought for their way upwards in any organisation. Around only 8.1% of the latest fortune 500 companies are being run by women CEOs. Though it is a milestone in itself that should be celebrated, yet the numbers are not so encouraging.&amp;nbsp; This underrepresentation of women in the higher positions of an organisation is called the ‘glass ceiling effect’. But there’s more to the story. Even if a small portion of determined and strong women break the glass ceiling and demonstrate their innate talent of being a leader, they are faced with yet another patriarchal barrier – the glass cliff effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Recently, Blizzard Company appointed Jen Oneal as its first female lead. Though it would have been an encouraging move under normal circumstances, currently it is a testimony to the prevalence of the glass cliff effect. Why? The promotion of Jen was preceded by a big lawsuit of sexual harassment that the company is tackling. More like a sister to the glass ceiling effect, the glass cliff effect refers to the phenomenon whereby women are promoted to higher positions during a precarious situation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This term was coined by two researchers at the University of Exeter, Michelle Ryan and Alexander Haslam in 2005. Haslam and Ryan looked at the 100 companies that were a part of the FTSE 100 Index listed on the London Stock Exchange to analyse what happened at those firms before and after men and women board members were brought on board. The findings suggested that during periods of stock market decline, firms that brought women on their board were more likely to have experienced constantly bad performance in the preceding five months than those who brought men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The glass cliff effect assumes greater importance as it fuels the traditionally-existing stereotypes about women leaders. When women leaders are unable to perform under precarious situations they are dismissed as being not competent enough to hold positions of power. The effect is closely knit with the saviour effect. When women are not able to deliver results under a glass cliff appointment they are immediately replaced by men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, I believe there’s more to the glass cliff effect than just research backed by statistics. I believe the roots of the glass cliff effect go to the way girls are conditioned from the beginning. Apart from painting the picture of a damsel in distress waiting to be saved by a prince in shining armour, a lot of women are conditioned to believe that they are responsible for cleaning the 'mess' that has so far been created by dominant patriarchal characters in their life. The submissive and complacent attitude that is imbibed in girls during their childhood adds up to become a phenomenon like the glass cliff effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Why do women choose to accept an offer of being promoted to a higher stature if they know that the company is currently in a dangerous situation? Well, women as a group have to face a lot of struggles to climb up the corporate ladder. The offer of a C-suite position is just too lucrative for a lot of women to pass on. So, instead, they take up a chance and try to fight the situation; and if we look at the flip side, there have been a lot many instances where women have vigorously fought against the glass cliff effect, pulled companies out of crisis and proved their acumen. Mary Barra, CEO and Chairman of General Motors is one such example. When she was promoted after a controversial bail-out, the odds of her succeeding&amp;nbsp;were low. However, she defied all the odds and succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Though the saddening part still remains. Imagine that you’ve been trying hard to break through the glass and finally succeed. You let out a sigh of relief. However, as soon as you look around, you find yourself standing at the edge of a cliff. You are disheartened. This is what a glass cliff effect looks like. The glass cliff effect is a lesser-known fact however it impacts the lives of almost millions of women working in the corporate sector. Will women ever break out of these shackles or are there more glass barriers waiting for them?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shiksha Mody</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">While listening to Ava Max’s song Kings and Queens, whenever the line ‘If all of the kings had queens on their throne, we would pop champagne and raise a toast’ comes, a gush of enthusiasm runs through my veins and the thought of women leading everywhere leaves me in awe of the world that they would create. However, as I sit down to write this article today, contemplating upon the lyrics, I am left baffled by the thought of whether the problem of gender discrimination is really solved by passing of thrones or is there more to it? Historically, men have been perceived to be natural leaders while women and other minority groups have fought for their way upwards in any organisation. Around only 8.1% of the latest fortune 500 companies are being run by women CEOs. Though it is a milestone in itself that should be celebrated, yet the numbers are not so encouraging.&amp;nbsp; This underrepresentation of women in the higher positions of an organisation is called the ‘glass ceiling effect’. But there’s more to the story. Even if a small portion of determined and strong women break the glass ceiling and demonstrate their innate talent of being a leader, they are faced with yet another patriarchal barrier – the glass cliff effect. Recently, Blizzard Company appointed Jen Oneal as its first female lead. Though it would have been an encouraging move under normal circumstances, currently it is a testimony to the prevalence of the glass cliff effect. Why? The promotion of Jen was preceded by a big lawsuit of sexual harassment that the company is tackling. More like a sister to the glass ceiling effect, the glass cliff effect refers to the phenomenon whereby women are promoted to higher positions during a precarious situation.&amp;nbsp; This term was coined by two researchers at the University of Exeter, Michelle Ryan and Alexander Haslam in 2005. Haslam and Ryan looked at the 100 companies that were a part of the FTSE 100 Index listed on the London Stock Exchange to analyse what happened at those firms before and after men and women board members were brought on board. The findings suggested that during periods of stock market decline, firms that brought women on their board were more likely to have experienced constantly bad performance in the preceding five months than those who brought men. The glass cliff effect assumes greater importance as it fuels the traditionally-existing stereotypes about women leaders. When women leaders are unable to perform under precarious situations they are dismissed as being not competent enough to hold positions of power. The effect is closely knit with the saviour effect. When women are not able to deliver results under a glass cliff appointment they are immediately replaced by men.&amp;nbsp; However, I believe there’s more to the glass cliff effect than just research backed by statistics. I believe the roots of the glass cliff effect go to the way girls are conditioned from the beginning. Apart from painting the picture of a damsel in distress waiting to be saved by a prince in shining armour, a lot of women are conditioned to believe that they are responsible for cleaning the 'mess' that has so far been created by dominant patriarchal characters in their life. The submissive and complacent attitude that is imbibed in girls during their childhood adds up to become a phenomenon like the glass cliff effect. Why do women choose to accept an offer of being promoted to a higher stature if they know that the company is currently in a dangerous situation? Well, women as a group have to face a lot of struggles to climb up the corporate ladder. The offer of a C-suite position is just too lucrative for a lot of women to pass on. So, instead, they take up a chance and try to fight the situation; and if we look at the flip side, there have been a lot many instances where women have vigorously fought against the glass cliff effect, pulled companies out of crisis and proved their acumen. Mary Barra, CEO and Chairman of General Motors is one such example. When she was promoted after a controversial bail-out, the odds of her succeeding&amp;nbsp;were low. However, she defied all the odds and succeeded. Though the saddening part still remains. Imagine that you’ve been trying hard to break through the glass and finally succeed. You let out a sigh of relief. However, as soon as you look around, you find yourself standing at the edge of a cliff. You are disheartened. This is what a glass cliff effect looks like. The glass cliff effect is a lesser-known fact however it impacts the lives of almost millions of women working in the corporate sector. Will women ever break out of these shackles or are there more glass barriers waiting for them?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Far Past Outrage Into Indifference</title><link href="/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Far Past Outrage Into Indifference" /><published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference">&lt;p&gt;I could not read it again. I promise I tried. I would take a deep breath and try to ignore the prickling sensation behind my eye. But the pages would feel as heavy as boulders. So I stopped trying to read and flipped over to random pages to search for the sentences that would help the readers understand the reason behind my failure to reread one of my favourite books; &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Splendid Suns &lt;/em&gt;by&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Khaled Hosseini&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;You will find those sentences italicised as you progress through this article. I cannot sum up the despair that the women in Afghanistan might be feeling at the moment, in a thousand or so words, but I hope I can give you an inkling of what they are to face in the coming months.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Thousand Splendid Suns&lt;/em&gt;, this heart-achingly beautiful book can be interpreted in different ways. When I read it for the first time at 15, it was a love story between Tariq and Laila. When I read it for the second time at 17, it was a story about fate and sisterhood. Now that I wish to reread it at 21, it is a warning. A foreboding tale of what is to become of the women and children in Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The freedoms and opportunities that women had enjoyed between 1978 and 1992 were a thing of the past now --- Laila could still remember Babi saying of those years of communist rule, ‘It’s a good time to be a woman in Afghanistan, Laila’.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is based amidst the Taliban's rule from 1996-2001. While not free from the Taliban’s terror, women in Afghanistan had enjoyed relative freedom according to reports during the twenty long years of the US army’s presence. They were allowed to go to school, university and work. The US army’s presence was the distraction that turned the Taliban’s focus from oppressing individual liberty to battling the US forces. However, now with the withdrawal of the US troops, there is nothing to prevent the Taliban from shifting back to oppressing the women and children of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It was the raids, the reason why they were in the yard digging. Sometimes monthly raids, sometimes weekly. Of late, almost daily. Mostly, the Taliban confiscated stuff, gave a kick to someone's rear, whacked the back of a head or two. But sometimes there were public beatings, lashings of soles and palms.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns )&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the US has chosen to negotiate with terrorists&lt;em&gt; (&lt;/em&gt;The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008)&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; the rest of the world is wary of openly condemning US leadership’s haste in withdrawal and blatant disregard of the plight faced by the people in Afghanistan. The United States President Joe Biden had tweeted “our goal was never nation-building”; a statement that effortlessly pulled the curtain over their overt and aggressive involvement in Afghanistan and puppeteering of the Afghanistan Government. It makes one wonder whether their willingness to pretend that all will be well and their trust in the Taliban’s promises, stems from their guilt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban's promises for women's safety and leniency are being considered a positive sign by many. However, their promises of freedom of choice for women are an illusion. Is it freedom if the bounds are determined and restricted by the men toting guns and firing at any sign of dissent? Many may have adopted blind optimism and faith in the Taliban’s words, however, trusting an organisation that has a history of broken promises doesn’t seem to be a smart move.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broken promises aside, the Taliban poses a huge threat to women’s education. A &lt;em&gt;Human Rights Watch&lt;/em&gt; article reported that as of 2017, only “37 per cent of adolescent girls were literate, compared to 66 per cent of adolescent boys.” (&lt;em&gt;Afghanistan: Girls Struggle for an Education, Human Rights Watch&lt;/em&gt;). UNICEF had reported in 2016 that “&lt;em&gt;an estimated 3.7 million children are out-of-school in Afghanistan-60% of them are girls.&lt;/em&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;Education&lt;/em&gt;. UNICEF Afghanistan)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pre-Taliban statistics were attributed to constant conflict in the region, violence, lack of government support and infrastructure, and backward traditional practices and outdated ideas of women’s role in society. However, there was still hope that women’s education would be prioritised because the government was willing to let international organisations and NGOs take the lead in the education sector. The Taliban, however, has made no such proposals, and if their past actions are considered, they would not be open to any such interference. The Taliban’s rule in Afghanistan will only uphold the backward traditional practices and the medieval ideologies about women’s role in society.&amp;nbsp; This will lead to equal rights for women and their proper education being a distant dream in a country with over 14.2 million female population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another frightening statistic would be the data on different forms of violence used against women. The global database on violence against women reports that at least 51% of women have experienced Lifetime Physical and/or Sexual Intimate Partner Violence, whereas it reported 35% of women reported being coerced into marriage before the age of 18 (UNICEF global databases 2018). These numbers present a devastating picture and yet there exists the possibility that the data might be understated. A country like Afghanistan which was ranked 154 on the Gender Inequality Index Rank in 2015, with the ascent of the Taliban regime, is likely to fall lower.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the Taliban wishes to form a government. And it would seem that even this organisation is not immune to the scrutiny of social media. It is a fact that the Taliban does not have a good reputation. Whether it is because of their terror activities in other nations or human rights violations in their own nation, it cannot be determined. However, it no longer wishes to be seen as just a terrorist organisation. Consequently, we have read reports of the Taliban claiming to have changed. They promise that no longer they shall shut women up in homes or publicly flog them for not wearing a burqa. They have promised that &lt;em&gt;this time &lt;/em&gt;they would rule differently. Women may even be allowed to work and study. There would not be prejudice or violence against women, and they would be allowed to participate in society “within the bounds of Islamic Law”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“They want us to operate in a burqa”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;the doctor explained….to the nurse at the door. “She keeps (a) watch. She sees them coming; I cover” She said this in a pragmatic, almost indifferent tone, and Mariam understood that this is a woman far past outrage. Here is a woman, she thought, who had understood that she was lucky to be even working, that there was always something, someone else, that they could take away”. (&lt;/em&gt;Hosseini, K. &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Thousand Splendid Suns)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this how it will be from now on? Should the women of Afghanistan be grateful that they may be allowed the liberties that should have been their birthright? Should they beg and settle for scraps that the Taliban tosses at them to appease the guilty conscience of the global superpowers and the world watching from the safety of their screens abroad? Women will be the biggest victims in this transition.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Laila and Mariam of the book may have found an escape but millions of Laila and Mariam of this world will disproportionately suffer for decisions they did not make, and the world will turn a blind eye.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">I could not read it again. I promise I tried. I would take a deep breath and try to ignore the prickling sensation behind my eye. But the pages would feel as heavy as boulders. So I stopped trying to read and flipped over to random pages to search for the sentences that would help the readers understand the reason behind my failure to reread one of my favourite books; A Thousand Splendid Suns by Khaled Hosseini. You will find those sentences italicised as you progress through this article. I cannot sum up the despair that the women in Afghanistan might be feeling at the moment, in a thousand or so words, but I hope I can give you an inkling of what they are to face in the coming months.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A Thousand Splendid Suns, this heart-achingly beautiful book can be interpreted in different ways. When I read it for the first time at 15, it was a love story between Tariq and Laila. When I read it for the second time at 17, it was a story about fate and sisterhood. Now that I wish to reread it at 21, it is a warning. A foreboding tale of what is to become of the women and children in Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp; “The freedoms and opportunities that women had enjoyed between 1978 and 1992 were a thing of the past now --- Laila could still remember Babi saying of those years of communist rule, ‘It’s a good time to be a woman in Afghanistan, Laila’.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns) The book is based amidst the Taliban's rule from 1996-2001. While not free from the Taliban’s terror, women in Afghanistan had enjoyed relative freedom according to reports during the twenty long years of the US army’s presence. They were allowed to go to school, university and work. The US army’s presence was the distraction that turned the Taliban’s focus from oppressing individual liberty to battling the US forces. However, now with the withdrawal of the US troops, there is nothing to prevent the Taliban from shifting back to oppressing the women and children of Afghanistan. “It was the raids, the reason why they were in the yard digging. Sometimes monthly raids, sometimes weekly. Of late, almost daily. Mostly, the Taliban confiscated stuff, gave a kick to someone's rear, whacked the back of a head or two. But sometimes there were public beatings, lashings of soles and palms.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns ) While the US has chosen to negotiate with terrorists (The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008), the rest of the world is wary of openly condemning US leadership’s haste in withdrawal and blatant disregard of the plight faced by the people in Afghanistan. The United States President Joe Biden had tweeted “our goal was never nation-building”; a statement that effortlessly pulled the curtain over their overt and aggressive involvement in Afghanistan and puppeteering of the Afghanistan Government. It makes one wonder whether their willingness to pretend that all will be well and their trust in the Taliban’s promises, stems from their guilt.&amp;nbsp; The Taliban's promises for women's safety and leniency are being considered a positive sign by many. However, their promises of freedom of choice for women are an illusion. Is it freedom if the bounds are determined and restricted by the men toting guns and firing at any sign of dissent? Many may have adopted blind optimism and faith in the Taliban’s words, however, trusting an organisation that has a history of broken promises doesn’t seem to be a smart move.&amp;nbsp; Broken promises aside, the Taliban poses a huge threat to women’s education. A Human Rights Watch article reported that as of 2017, only “37 per cent of adolescent girls were literate, compared to 66 per cent of adolescent boys.” (Afghanistan: Girls Struggle for an Education, Human Rights Watch). UNICEF had reported in 2016 that “an estimated 3.7 million children are out-of-school in Afghanistan-60% of them are girls.” (Education. UNICEF Afghanistan)&amp;nbsp; The pre-Taliban statistics were attributed to constant conflict in the region, violence, lack of government support and infrastructure, and backward traditional practices and outdated ideas of women’s role in society. However, there was still hope that women’s education would be prioritised because the government was willing to let international organisations and NGOs take the lead in the education sector. The Taliban, however, has made no such proposals, and if their past actions are considered, they would not be open to any such interference. The Taliban’s rule in Afghanistan will only uphold the backward traditional practices and the medieval ideologies about women’s role in society.&amp;nbsp; This will lead to equal rights for women and their proper education being a distant dream in a country with over 14.2 million female population. Another frightening statistic would be the data on different forms of violence used against women. The global database on violence against women reports that at least 51% of women have experienced Lifetime Physical and/or Sexual Intimate Partner Violence, whereas it reported 35% of women reported being coerced into marriage before the age of 18 (UNICEF global databases 2018). These numbers present a devastating picture and yet there exists the possibility that the data might be understated. A country like Afghanistan which was ranked 154 on the Gender Inequality Index Rank in 2015, with the ascent of the Taliban regime, is likely to fall lower.&amp;nbsp; Now, the Taliban wishes to form a government. And it would seem that even this organisation is not immune to the scrutiny of social media. It is a fact that the Taliban does not have a good reputation. Whether it is because of their terror activities in other nations or human rights violations in their own nation, it cannot be determined. However, it no longer wishes to be seen as just a terrorist organisation. Consequently, we have read reports of the Taliban claiming to have changed. They promise that no longer they shall shut women up in homes or publicly flog them for not wearing a burqa. They have promised that this time they would rule differently. Women may even be allowed to work and study. There would not be prejudice or violence against women, and they would be allowed to participate in society “within the bounds of Islamic Law”. “They want us to operate in a burqa” the doctor explained….to the nurse at the door. “She keeps (a) watch. She sees them coming; I cover” She said this in a pragmatic, almost indifferent tone, and Mariam understood that this is a woman far past outrage. Here is a woman, she thought, who had understood that she was lucky to be even working, that there was always something, someone else, that they could take away”. (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns) Is this how it will be from now on? Should the women of Afghanistan be grateful that they may be allowed the liberties that should have been their birthright? Should they beg and settle for scraps that the Taliban tosses at them to appease the guilty conscience of the global superpowers and the world watching from the safety of their screens abroad? Women will be the biggest victims in this transition.&amp;nbsp; The Laila and Mariam of the book may have found an escape but millions of Laila and Mariam of this world will disproportionately suffer for decisions they did not make, and the world will turn a blind eye.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Combating the Menace of Counterfeits</title><link href="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combating the Menace of Counterfeits" /><published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits">&lt;p&gt;How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhinav Gupta</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp; The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp; The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products. There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp; From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp; Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp; Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp; Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp; The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp; The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp; Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too. The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp; Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp; This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp; In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status. While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp; The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp; Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp; Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp; Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp; High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp; In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp; There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp; For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp; However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked. The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp; Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp; Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Economic Case for a Federal UK</title><link href="/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Economic Case for a Federal UK" /><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK">&lt;p&gt;With regard to economic prosperity, the UK is one of the most divided and unequal countries in Europe. Over the past thirty years, London’s economy has accelerated ahead of the rest of the country, such that by 2020, average wages in Northern Ireland and Wales were only 70% of average wages in London as stated in the 2021 report titled &lt;em&gt;Levelling up the UK’s regional economies&lt;/em&gt; published by the Centre of Cities. This is reflected in a marked national productivity gap, with London having a gross value added (GVA) of £51,000 per worker, compared to £27,000 in the East of England, £23,000 in Yorkshire and £21,000 in the North East of England as suggested in the &lt;em&gt;Median annual earnings for full-time employees in the United Kingdom in 2020, by region&lt;/em&gt; authored by Statista.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These inequalities have led to a much-touted government agenda to ‘level up’ the UK economy. However, a crucial element of the policy debate in the UK that has so far gone under-examined is the fact that the economic difficulties of the North and Midlands of England have coincided with the atrophy of the UK’s system of governance. Whilst Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland now boast powerful regional governments, England has been left underrepresented. The introduction of metropolitan mayoralties in England’s major cities has gone some way in redressing this imbalance, though England’s smaller towns and rural areas are still without sufficient regional representation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic and political inequality are not unrelated phenomena. To level up the economy in the UK's poorer regions, levelling up of the politics needs to happen first. What follows is an argument in favour of federalising the UK government, so that each region of England, along with the three smaller kingdoms, has equal political representation, in the form of powerful regional governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem with Governing a Divided Country&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The socioeconomic disparities within the country mean both major political parties struggle to appeal to different factional interests simultaneously. In 2019, Labour failed to unite conservative, patriotic voters in their heartlands with liberal internationalist voters in metropolitan areas. For the Conservatives, however, there is increasing evidence that a chasm exists within their voter base too, but this divide is fundamentally economic, not social in nature. The recent Chesham and Amersham by-election delivered a bloody nose to the Tories, courtesy of centre-right Southern English voters displeased with a government agenda that seems to prioritise addressing the concerns of traditional Labour voters in the so-called 'red-wall'- namely, Brexit and levelling up. There is certainly a faction of not-so-shy Tory and Liberal Democrat-leaning voters that interpret levelling up the North and Midlands of England as nothing more than levelling down the prosperous South East, and they are unlikely to change their minds anytime soon.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the government deems bold policy agendas as high-risk strategies likely to alienate a generous portion of its voter coalition, the economic policy pursued from Westminster will resemble little more than the path of least resistance; a bland aggregation of the sections of public opinion least likely to offend. For this reason, the power to direct industrial and infrastructure policy must be taken away from the UK government and given to heads of new regional governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the strong divergence of opinion about economic policy (among other issues) within England, it makes little sense for the prime minister to have to make policy for people in North Yorkshire, knowing full well that people in Buckinghamshire will not like it. Instead, it would be much more prudent for a regional government in the North West of England to organise the levelling up agenda for their region, and for a separate authority to do the same for the South East. Under such a system, the details of important economic and infrastructure plans such as levelling up and the green agenda would not be jeopardised due to a change of government policy in Westminster, because the fundamental responsibility for maintaining such details would lie with regional leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of a situation in which greater devolution of responsibility is needed is the rollout of electric vehicles. Whilst the UK government has a target of achieving net-zero carbon emissions by 2050, Greater Manchester’s Combined Authority (GMCA) has a net-zero target of 2038. The largest single source of carbon emissions in Greater Manchester is the transport sector, making an efficient rollout of electric vehicles crucial to achieving the 2038 target. However, Greater Manchester does not have the power to ban the sale of petrol and diesel cars; this power still lies with the government in Westminster, which currently aims to ban sales of these vehicles by 2030. If this is pushed back to 2035, Greater Manchester’s 2038 target for net-zero will likely not be reached, exposing the reliance that local or regional governments have upon the UK government for achieving their own objectives. Such reliance would be eliminated if GMCA were given the considerable devolution powers it desires.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Federalism versus Devolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main criticism of federalism is that having a system of multi-level governments would lead to gridlock during times of disagreement between Westminster and regional governments. Critics of federalism often point to the United States, where the competing mandates of the federal and state governments made it difficult to coordinate concerted responses to the 2008 financial crisis and the COVID-19 pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, my reading is that a federal system would lead to far less gridlock than the current system of devolved parliaments does. In a federal system, the powers of the federal and regional governments are set out in stone, and cannot be changed easily. Crucially, the rights of all the regional governments are equal in relation to one another, and in relation to the central authority. This is not how the UK works currently; here, the powers of the governments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are not equal by default.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the Scottish and Welsh parliaments both now have the power to set their own levels of income tax, they were not granted this power at the same time, and the assembly in Northern Ireland still does not have tax-raising powers. Furthermore, England does not have its own regional parliament at all. This has made the relationship between Westminster and Edinburgh much more dysfunctional than the relationship between the federal government in Washington DC and the US state governments, the rights of which are at least codified in the Constitution. The confusion over different rules in the four kingdoms during the pandemic demonstrated the dysfunctionality of the UK system very well. The cause of gridlock is not devolution, but asymmetrical devolution, and the egalitarian nature of a federal system would eliminate the imbalances within the current UK order.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, recent history has shown that when new regional or local governments are established in the UK, their constituents prefer them to the government in Westminster. Labour ran a lacklustre and unpopular national campaign for the 2021 local elections, losing eight councils, but Mark Drakeford’s Welsh Labour increased its majority in the Welsh Parliament, and Labour retained its mayoralties in London, Manchester, the West of England, and Liverpool, as stated in the report titled &lt;em&gt;Combined authority mayoral elections 2021&lt;/em&gt; published by the UK Parliament.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic rationale for greater, symmetrical devolution is clear. However, radical diffusion of responsibility and power away from London cannot mean that the government in Westminster takes a back seat on levelling up the economy. Whilst regions must be free to choose their own economic future, leadership of overarching innovation missions must still come from the centre. First and foremost, this means making R&amp;amp;D spending levels equitable across the country as a precursor to radical devolution, which will not happen overnight. It also means taking more seriously the fact that the challenges of the COVID-recovery, the advance towards net-zero emissions, and yes, the levelling up agenda, are not separate challenges from improving regional governance, but counterparts to it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal UK would not be a utopia. It would not prevent disagreements between governments in different parts of the country, it would not prevent novel viruses from entering the UK on boats and aeroplanes. It would also not, in and of itself, make the country more effective at reducing its carbon emissions. Ultimately, our ability to reach net-zero emissions or level up the North and Midlands will depend not on which government is solving these problems, but which policies our governments implement to solve them. However, it is clear that regional governments, each responsible for the needs of only a slice of the country rather than the country in its entirety, would be more adept at choosing the right policies for their own respective regions than the far-away government in Westminster.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">With regard to economic prosperity, the UK is one of the most divided and unequal countries in Europe. Over the past thirty years, London’s economy has accelerated ahead of the rest of the country, such that by 2020, average wages in Northern Ireland and Wales were only 70% of average wages in London as stated in the 2021 report titled Levelling up the UK’s regional economies published by the Centre of Cities. This is reflected in a marked national productivity gap, with London having a gross value added (GVA) of £51,000 per worker, compared to £27,000 in the East of England, £23,000 in Yorkshire and £21,000 in the North East of England as suggested in the Median annual earnings for full-time employees in the United Kingdom in 2020, by region authored by Statista.&amp;nbsp; These inequalities have led to a much-touted government agenda to ‘level up’ the UK economy. However, a crucial element of the policy debate in the UK that has so far gone under-examined is the fact that the economic difficulties of the North and Midlands of England have coincided with the atrophy of the UK’s system of governance. Whilst Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland now boast powerful regional governments, England has been left underrepresented. The introduction of metropolitan mayoralties in England’s major cities has gone some way in redressing this imbalance, though England’s smaller towns and rural areas are still without sufficient regional representation.&amp;nbsp; Economic and political inequality are not unrelated phenomena. To level up the economy in the UK's poorer regions, levelling up of the politics needs to happen first. What follows is an argument in favour of federalising the UK government, so that each region of England, along with the three smaller kingdoms, has equal political representation, in the form of powerful regional governments.&amp;nbsp; The Problem with Governing a Divided Country The socioeconomic disparities within the country mean both major political parties struggle to appeal to different factional interests simultaneously. In 2019, Labour failed to unite conservative, patriotic voters in their heartlands with liberal internationalist voters in metropolitan areas. For the Conservatives, however, there is increasing evidence that a chasm exists within their voter base too, but this divide is fundamentally economic, not social in nature. The recent Chesham and Amersham by-election delivered a bloody nose to the Tories, courtesy of centre-right Southern English voters displeased with a government agenda that seems to prioritise addressing the concerns of traditional Labour voters in the so-called 'red-wall'- namely, Brexit and levelling up. There is certainly a faction of not-so-shy Tory and Liberal Democrat-leaning voters that interpret levelling up the North and Midlands of England as nothing more than levelling down the prosperous South East, and they are unlikely to change their minds anytime soon.&amp;nbsp; If the government deems bold policy agendas as high-risk strategies likely to alienate a generous portion of its voter coalition, the economic policy pursued from Westminster will resemble little more than the path of least resistance; a bland aggregation of the sections of public opinion least likely to offend. For this reason, the power to direct industrial and infrastructure policy must be taken away from the UK government and given to heads of new regional governments.&amp;nbsp; Given the strong divergence of opinion about economic policy (among other issues) within England, it makes little sense for the prime minister to have to make policy for people in North Yorkshire, knowing full well that people in Buckinghamshire will not like it. Instead, it would be much more prudent for a regional government in the North West of England to organise the levelling up agenda for their region, and for a separate authority to do the same for the South East. Under such a system, the details of important economic and infrastructure plans such as levelling up and the green agenda would not be jeopardised due to a change of government policy in Westminster, because the fundamental responsibility for maintaining such details would lie with regional leaders.&amp;nbsp; A good example of a situation in which greater devolution of responsibility is needed is the rollout of electric vehicles. Whilst the UK government has a target of achieving net-zero carbon emissions by 2050, Greater Manchester’s Combined Authority (GMCA) has a net-zero target of 2038. The largest single source of carbon emissions in Greater Manchester is the transport sector, making an efficient rollout of electric vehicles crucial to achieving the 2038 target. However, Greater Manchester does not have the power to ban the sale of petrol and diesel cars; this power still lies with the government in Westminster, which currently aims to ban sales of these vehicles by 2030. If this is pushed back to 2035, Greater Manchester’s 2038 target for net-zero will likely not be reached, exposing the reliance that local or regional governments have upon the UK government for achieving their own objectives. Such reliance would be eliminated if GMCA were given the considerable devolution powers it desires.&amp;nbsp; Federalism versus Devolution The main criticism of federalism is that having a system of multi-level governments would lead to gridlock during times of disagreement between Westminster and regional governments. Critics of federalism often point to the United States, where the competing mandates of the federal and state governments made it difficult to coordinate concerted responses to the 2008 financial crisis and the COVID-19 pandemic.&amp;nbsp; However, my reading is that a federal system would lead to far less gridlock than the current system of devolved parliaments does. In a federal system, the powers of the federal and regional governments are set out in stone, and cannot be changed easily. Crucially, the rights of all the regional governments are equal in relation to one another, and in relation to the central authority. This is not how the UK works currently; here, the powers of the governments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are not equal by default.&amp;nbsp; Though the Scottish and Welsh parliaments both now have the power to set their own levels of income tax, they were not granted this power at the same time, and the assembly in Northern Ireland still does not have tax-raising powers. Furthermore, England does not have its own regional parliament at all. This has made the relationship between Westminster and Edinburgh much more dysfunctional than the relationship between the federal government in Washington DC and the US state governments, the rights of which are at least codified in the Constitution. The confusion over different rules in the four kingdoms during the pandemic demonstrated the dysfunctionality of the UK system very well. The cause of gridlock is not devolution, but asymmetrical devolution, and the egalitarian nature of a federal system would eliminate the imbalances within the current UK order.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, recent history has shown that when new regional or local governments are established in the UK, their constituents prefer them to the government in Westminster. Labour ran a lacklustre and unpopular national campaign for the 2021 local elections, losing eight councils, but Mark Drakeford’s Welsh Labour increased its majority in the Welsh Parliament, and Labour retained its mayoralties in London, Manchester, the West of England, and Liverpool, as stated in the report titled Combined authority mayoral elections 2021 published by the UK Parliament.&amp;nbsp; Policies matter The economic rationale for greater, symmetrical devolution is clear. However, radical diffusion of responsibility and power away from London cannot mean that the government in Westminster takes a back seat on levelling up the economy. Whilst regions must be free to choose their own economic future, leadership of overarching innovation missions must still come from the centre. First and foremost, this means making R&amp;amp;D spending levels equitable across the country as a precursor to radical devolution, which will not happen overnight. It also means taking more seriously the fact that the challenges of the COVID-recovery, the advance towards net-zero emissions, and yes, the levelling up agenda, are not separate challenges from improving regional governance, but counterparts to it.&amp;nbsp; A federal UK would not be a utopia. It would not prevent disagreements between governments in different parts of the country, it would not prevent novel viruses from entering the UK on boats and aeroplanes. It would also not, in and of itself, make the country more effective at reducing its carbon emissions. Ultimately, our ability to reach net-zero emissions or level up the North and Midlands will depend not on which government is solving these problems, but which policies our governments implement to solve them. However, it is clear that regional governments, each responsible for the needs of only a slice of the country rather than the country in its entirety, would be more adept at choosing the right policies for their own respective regions than the far-away government in Westminster.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixating on The Male Gaze</title><link href="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixating on The Male Gaze" /><published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve seen&lt;em&gt; Emily in Paris&lt;/em&gt;, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “&lt;em&gt;Is it ‘sexy or sexist?&lt;/em&gt;’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook post&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/movies/bollywood/story/depicting-women-in-bollywood-222702-2014-10-11&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;India Today&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt; decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or &lt;em&gt;'the weaker sex'&lt;/em&gt; (Sana Ranaut from &lt;em&gt;Rajjo&lt;/em&gt;), 'Sanskari Ladki' or &lt;em&gt;'the traditional woman' &lt;/em&gt;(Amrita Rao from &lt;em&gt;Vivah&lt;/em&gt;), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from &lt;em&gt;Deewar&lt;/em&gt;) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from &lt;em&gt;Cocktail&lt;/em&gt;) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spectre&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Grown Ups&lt;/em&gt;, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: &lt;a href=&quot;https://talkiewood.com/2014/07/megan-vs-rosie-vs-nicola-who-was-the-best-transformers-girl-2/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl?&lt;/a&gt; (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (&lt;em&gt;Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman'&lt;/em&gt;) to men being okay with any colour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&quot;&lt;em&gt;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to &lt;em&gt;Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle&lt;/em&gt;, or almost every second rap song. As per a&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt;, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like &lt;em&gt;Chikni Chameli&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Hotline Bling&lt;/em&gt; or Jason Derulo’s &lt;em&gt;Swalla.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors&lt;/a&gt;) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (&lt;em&gt;The Phantom&lt;/em&gt;), Lois Lane (&lt;em&gt;Superman&lt;/em&gt;), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by &lt;em&gt;Downs and Smith&lt;/em&gt;, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lara Croft’s (&lt;em&gt;Tomb Raider&lt;/em&gt; series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.studiobinder.com/blog/what-is-the-male-gaze-definition/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;studiobinder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”&lt;/em&gt;, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;&lt;em&gt;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the first&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;seven women selected&lt;/a&gt; to join the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;VS Collective&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;’&lt;/em&gt; are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice is yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eeshita Verma</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">If you’ve seen Emily in Paris, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less. Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “Is it ‘sexy or sexist?’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is. The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point. The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting Facebook post I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’. Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it): An India Today article decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or 'the weaker sex' (Sana Ranaut from Rajjo), 'Sanskari Ladki' or 'the traditional woman' (Amrita Rao from Vivah), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from Deewar) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from Cocktail) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp; Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like Transformers, Wolf of Wall Street, Spectre, Grown Ups, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films. If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl? (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face). &amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get: “To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function. Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters.” As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for Transformers as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp; This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists and Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman') to men being okay with any colour. &amp;nbsp;&quot;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp; Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot; A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks. It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle, or almost every second rap song. As per a recent study, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp; The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like Chikni Chameli&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s Hotline Bling or Jason Derulo’s Swalla. Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy? Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge. Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry. The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point. Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (The Phantom), Lois Lane (Superman), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk. The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books. In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by Downs and Smith, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze. Lara Croft’s (Tomb Raider series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players. Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp; A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film Aladdin, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A studiobinder article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for Aladdin.&amp;nbsp; I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across: “Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities. Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men. Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him. The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter. Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’. Among the first seven women selected to join the ‘VS Collective’ are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything! Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it? Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them? Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate. Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now. It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off your attention. The choice is yours. Until then.</summary></entry></feed>