<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-04T11:32:35+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?</title><link href="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?" /><published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever there has been any economic crisis, people tend to stay away from the stock market because market crashes are highly unpredictable. We all know about the 2007-08 financial crisis, and how in every country there was reluctance in investing in the stock market. However, people who still had savings went right to the commodity exchange and bought gold. This was clearly visible from the fact that the rally in gold continued from 2007 to 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we are witnessing in this current scenario with the coronavirus spreading all over the world and lockdown of economies leading to bankruptcy for many companies, people are pulling out their money from stocks and other financial instruments and buying bullion to park their money in safe investments. Exchange-Traded Funds (ETFs) have been piling up on gold reserves as well, which has more than made up for the domestic lack of demand. Demand for gold comes from another significant set of investors who tend to invest in real estate. The sector itself being in limbo due to the pandemic has forced such investors to invest in the yellow metal. Additionally, the metal is benefitting from the ultra-loose monetary policies being pursued by bankers and expectation that such a stance will tend to continue in the long run. Rising fiscal deficits and increasing debts are also contributing to the rising shift to gold. The fiscal policies adopted and the printing of more currency have led to inflation and have been the contributing factors in the current rally in gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, central banks around the globe are regularly keeping a check on the economy and are providing liquidity. During the past few months, central banks too, have been buying gold and increasing their gold reserves in order to face any unforeseen circumstances. Central banks of China, Russia and India were the biggest buyers of gold in 2019, and many countries are still adding more to their coffers. This rally is expected to continue until we see any stability in the stock market and people feel safe to buy stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold prices have gone through the ceiling in the past few weeks and every banker has his/her own perception regarding the future price movement. All in all, it remains to be seen whether gold prices will continue to rise, or will gold lose its steam. However, the metal has yet again proven its mettle in trying times, when every other investment fails to provide returns, it keeps its investors happy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rachit Kumar</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal</title><link href="/Online-Delivery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal" /><published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Online-Delivery</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Online-Delivery">&lt;p&gt;Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This market inversion has led to a growth of online delivery marketplaces, with even bigger market players in other segments pivoting their business strategies around home delivery. Delivery service marketplaces have inverted from demand-constrained to supply-constrained almost overnight, but new entrants in the delivery space have reportedly struggled with profits, reporting a boost in sales but thin margins. They claim that it is not terribly profitable, and it probably gets unprofitable with more orders. While many restaurants and supermarkets prefer the lower costs and hassle of having customers collect orders at stores, others see it as a threat to their existing customer relationships that could have been better taken care of, had the customers walked into the store. Online delivery was never a core part of these supplier’s revenue and made up only a small chunk of the total orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues and challenges that marketplaces face today are logistical and reputational, arising from increased demand and customer awareness rather than challenges arising from low consumer penetration and slim demand for services. Consumers are holding brands and companies to a higher standard than previously, favouring those perceived as doing more for society. Pre-crisis, a common complaint on the platforms was that drivers weren’t receiving enough orders. Now, those same drivers are overwhelmed with demand, and platforms have to figure out how to build product solutions to help stores balance their delivery loads. There have been inventory stockouts, closed stores, and supply chain disruptions due to COVID-19 — all while the customer service team has been inundated with order volume. That’s consistent with the experience of all mid-sized delivery platforms, and even that of Amazon. These platforms have had to switch their focus overnight and develop expertise around the new supply-side constraints. The bigger problem here is that many suppliers didn’t have the infrastructure set up to make delivery work at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among all vociferous trumpets about ‘the demise of commuting’, ‘the death of retail’, and ‘the collapse of globalisation’, many executives have come to assume that everything will change accordingly when the recipe for survival is supposed to be a thorough transformation. The economic crisis does not necessarily spell the end of entire industries or companies but it does weed out business models that fail to pivot towards the new reality characterised by shorter value chains, remote work, social distancing, consumer introspection, and enhanced usage of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, now is the time for marketplaces to help their suppliers invest in infrastructure and technology, and indulge in business practices that will enable them to compete in a world in which having a delivery sales presence is essential. Now is the time for them to shift their focus from customer acquisition and retention to investment in metrics for supporting retailer operations. Platforms can be a part of the supplier side transition which, in fact, is happening organically. With in-person retail restricted or outright eliminated, suppliers have been reimagining their store layouts and operations around online fulfilment and omnichannel retail, simultaneously leveraging marketplace platforms, a self-managed online presence, and traditional in-person sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can identify and share best practices around staffing and delivery processes, and provide technology solutions to help small businesses optimise their operations around delivery, with, for example, cloud-based inventory logs and modern point-of-sale systems. Marketplace platforms have vision into the whole market, which enables them to predict demand — an advantage they should use to the benefit of their suppliers. This could be helpful in forecasting when to schedule extra drivers on an hour-by-hour basis, and staffing driver teams in direct proportion to order volume. This can also increase capital efficiency by helping stores match inventory levels to predict future demand. Platforms can lower their tax rates to increase supplier participation — especially among chains and other established supplier networks. Food delivery marketplaces’ supplier-weighted cost structure may have worked when restaurants saw having a small stream of delivery orders as a promotional subsidy for in-person traffic — but it isn’t working in the current, in-person demand constrained marketplace environment. Likewise, some fees should be shifted over to the consumers, since they’re now the ‘long’ side of the market. In particular, it might make sense to institute per-order delivery fees, to encourage consumers to place large delivery orders instead of more frequent small ones, as well as to make it more valuable for a retailer to take an additional order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before COVID-19, a delivery service’s performance was mostly determined by convenience, speed and price. Now, by contrast, safety, availability and breadth of selection are the new priorities. Customers are placing bigger orders and are comfortable with longer lead times with ‘acceptable’ estimated time of arrival windows widening. Platforms also have the leeway to shift customer service efforts to prioritise responsiveness to retailers and allocate developer resources towards solving suppliers’ operational problems. All these solutions will help keep in place, exactly the right products on the supplier’s shelves. These improvements will benefit both parties but would require information sharing and communication on the part of the platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When suppliers make the best or most effective use of marketplace transactions, the consumer experience on the platform improves too — often due to increased availability, selection and price options. Overall, this results in much higher conversion rates: a customer with three stores and 1,000 items to choose from spends 67% more per session than a customer facing just one store with 300 items. Orders are processed more smoothly, and with fewer errors that will help translate fleeting customer relations into stronger consumer engagement post-crisis. Better and more optimised choices lead to more bargaining power in the hands of the customers, thereby increasing satisfaction and chances of application reuse. Bars and restaurants will eventually reopen and consumers will become comfortable shopping for goods in-person again but the supplier networks that marketplace platforms build will remain. When platforms invest in suppliers as partners, those suppliers will come out of the crisis stronger, improving the customer experience in the long run. It’s a three-way win — for suppliers, platforms and consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As worried consumers move to shop more online, choosing online platforms is an easy decision — with a click of the button, they can buy almost anything. But for sellers, doing business with them is a less straightforward proposition. Although partnering opens up access to more customers and offers operational efficiencies, brands risk leveraging power in favour of the platforms. Thus, they face an unavoidable dilemma — form the partnership and risk ceding profits, or eschew the partnership and forgo the operational cost savings and access to new customers. A big threat to these established brands is consumers’ increased willingness to experiment with different offerings during the crisis. Research suggests that consumers react badly even when the bad news extends beyond the company to its supply chain. They are more likely to believe that a company’s product is inferior in quality when there is a supply chain mishap, even when the product quality has nothing to do with the supply chain problem. They assume a product has decreased in quality whether the supply chain problems are related to an economic issue (like consistently low profits), a social issue (like racial discrimination in the hiring process), or an environmental issue (like polluting). Brands must, therefore, realise that pivots must be a lateral extension of the firm’s existing capabilities, cementing — not undermining — its strategic intent.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mehul Goyal</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">When The Faithful Prince Backfired!</title><link href="/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When The Faithful Prince Backfired!" /><published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired</id><content type="html" xml:base="/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired">&lt;p&gt;Remember, four years ago when the entire business world was shocked to hear the allegations made against the ‘not so clean’ Tata &amp;amp; Sons? In today’s highly competitive and capitalistic world, where business rivalry is a routine affair among the giants, there are a few players who prefer to keep it clean. The Tata group is one of them and has maintained its reputation as one of the most honest corporate entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratan Tata, former Chairman of the Tata group is one of the most powerful businessmen in India and one of the most influential in the world. He owns less than 1% of the assets of the group in his own name. He ended up being in the headlines related to a controversy. It all started after the Tata group appointed Cyrus Mistry as the 6th Chairman of Tata Sons in 2012. He had been on the board of Tata Sons since August 2006. Mistry is the son of Pallonji Mistry who was the owner of Shapoorji Pallonji Group till 2012 (presently headed by Shapoor Mistry). The Mistrys are the largest individual shareholders in Tata Sons with 18.4%, which is equally divided between the two sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 24, 2016, Mistry was removed from his post as the Chairman during a board meeting. According to sources, Mr Tata gave him a chance to resign voluntarily, which Mistry denied. The severity of bitterness among the two was made obvious after he was ousted from all the other boards as well. At that point in time, the Mistrys were crippled and the future course was unknown. Ratan Tata was reinstated as the Interim Chairman for about four months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tata Sons stated that a trust deficit with Cyrus Mistry was the major reason for his removal. They also claimed that the members of the board had lost their confidence in Mistry and thus took a collective decision to replace him as the Chairman. On the other hand, Mistry claimed the removal to be illegal and a staged coup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since no concrete reasoning has been given out for the removal, many possible reasons have been floating across. Legacy problems within the Tata group, and differences between Mr Tata and Mr Mistry are also seen as the alleged reasons for Cyrus being ousted. Additionally, Mistry wanted to get rid of certain ventures which proved to be unsuccessful. These included Tata Steel’s European business, Tata Nano, and telecoms. Mr Tata refused these advances and these led to certain conflicts. Mistry made some decisions without consulting the board and Ratan Tata himself. Unsurprisingly, these decisions were not well received by all. Tata group also suffered some losses under Mistry’s reign. At times, he even overlooked the existing ventures and was prioritising new businesses. This was not acceptable to Mr Tata as the existing ventures had some emotional sentiment attached to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistry filed a case against the Tata Sons with the National Company Law Tribunal (NCLT) in December 2016. He stated that even after 8 weeks, he does not have any concrete reason backing the move, and hence he chose to go the legal way. This whole situation has adversely affected the position of the Pallonjis as a minority shareholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistry’s challenge was turned down by the NCLT. After this, he went to the National Company Law Appellate Tribunal (NCLAT) in regard to the NCLT dismissal. His appeal with the tribunal was admitted in August 2018. The appeal was restored later and judgment was passed by the NCLAT in December 2019. The judgment and order reinstated Mistry as the Chairman of Tata Sons and restored his position on all the boards. This order was challenged by the Tata Son’s in the Indian Supreme Court. The Supreme Court put a stay order on the NCLAT’s judgment after it refused to modify the same. Even after various hearings, both the parties are nowhere near satisfied and the conflict is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tata Sons did what they felt was needed for the group’s benefit. This move was not well reasoned by them and the consequences being faced are dreadful. Even the Mistrys are facing uncertainty at their end! This move has not only defamed Cyrus Mistry but has also raised questions on Tata’s working and management. Even though the NCLAT’s judgment was in Mistry’s favour, he believes it’s not enough. His demands for rights in a corporate democracy for a minority shareholder still remain untackled! This forces us to think more about shareholders and how authority should be controlled within the working of business houses in order to maintain the ideals of corporate democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t believe that majority dominance should play a role in the business culture. Decisions being taken affect all the investors equally and thus their approval should be necessary. A democratic process that includes debate and deliberation regarding every big step should be given importance. In this particular feud, both sides had made similar mistakes of taking decisions on an individual level. Be it Cyrus taking company matters and policies in his own hands or Mr Tata scrapping his ideas and at last ousting him without justification. These examples prove how seniority plays an important role in corporate functioning. This also means that views and opinions of other board members who are usually the minority shareholders are negated or delegitimised. Power dynamics need to be minimised in order to protect minority rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interests of a company should be prioritised while taking crucial decisions. Is it safe to assume that all minority shareholders genuinely care about the company as a whole? Personal interests and gains have always been prioritised by individuals. Keeping this in mind, it is important to make sure these rights are not misused and the interests of a company are always taken care of. Does this justify the ousting of Mistry? Oops! We ended up being in a dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These situations are not favourable to any of the parties involved but they do unfold the power play within corporate houses. The Tata group which was known for its values and ideals is facing severe repercussions. It is time to rethink and stand up for minority rights not only within national boundaries but also within the corporate world and make sure they are not tampered with. The ambiguity of this whole situation can be sensed in every article present in my search history and thus it makes it difficult to land upon a conclusion which satisfies all the parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Remember, four years ago when the entire business world was shocked to hear the allegations made against the ‘not so clean’ Tata &amp;amp; Sons? In today’s highly competitive and capitalistic world, where business rivalry is a routine affair among the giants, there are a few players who prefer to keep it clean. The Tata group is one of them and has maintained its reputation as one of the most honest corporate entities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Green Bonds: A New Revolution towards Sustainable Finance in India?</title><link href="/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Bonds: A New Revolution towards Sustainable Finance in India?" /><published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We need bold action on climate change, our generation may not be able to solve all the problems related to climate change, but we can do our part to leave a better planet for the next generation&lt;/em&gt;”, said Kristalina Georgieva, World Bank Group and Interim Chief Executive Officer. Climate change has caused an unprecedented risk to the growth of societies and economies. According to a recent report by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), it has been estimated that around $6-7 trillion of annual investment is globally required to achieve the objective of moving the world economy towards a ‘greener economy’. To get the entire globe out of this trap, we need to make substantial investments that fund projects focussing on creating low carbon economies, clean energy, water transportation, etc. Only with such effective measures shall we be able to build a climate-resilient economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries around the world have been pursuing a shift towards a more sustainable environment. Recently, the European Union launched the Next Generation EU (NGEU) fund to tackle the coronavirus pandemic. The deal puts the issue of climate change at the forefront. According to the deal document, a total of 30% of the expenditure of the €1.82 trillion will be used to reach the climate targets in conformity to the objectives of the Paris agreements. It also has a provision that rules that the European Commission should publish a report on climate expenditure annually. In order to ensure that such legislations bear fruitful results, it is important to provide investors with alternative options of investments, with higher returns and which also give them a feeling of having satisfied their responsibility towards the environment. This is where ‘Green Bonds’ come into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the current status and impetus given to green finance globally, we can not only give credit to institutions that have introduced green bonds but also to the dynamic shift witnessed in the corporate bond market wherein we have more socially responsible investors who want to invest their money in the funding of those projects that would lead to a positive impact on the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite knowing the unmeasured potential of green finance all over the world, the total number of green bonds issued was only around 3% as a percentage of the total corporate bonds issued. This reveals the percentage of untapped potential of the green bond market which should be effectively realised to create a sustainable environment. So, how are these bonds currently being exploited in India?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Green Bond Market and the Road Ahead.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when governments across the world are emphasising on creating low carbon economies, India is not lagging behind in showing its efforts in the same direction. Indian financial institutions such as the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) and the Securities Exchange Board of India (SEBI) are effectively trying to promote green bonds in the country. India is aiming to build 175 gigawatts of renewable energy capacity by 2022. Thus, the financing needs of the renewable energy sector can effectively be addressed by the issuance of green bonds in our country. In the last few years Indian investors, banking institutions, and the government have played a crucial role in developing sustainable finance. They have recognised it as a fundamental tool towards financing the nation’s renewable energy targets through developing strategies for sustainable economic growth and effective policy framework for judicious utilisation of all-natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green bonds in India were introduced in 2015 when Yes Bank issued the first series of green bonds in the country for financing projects of ₹10 billion followed by ₹6 billion issuances of green bonds by CLP India. In order to regulate these issuances, SEBI issued the green bond guidelines on lines of the green bond principles issued by the Institute of Cost and Management Accountants (ICMA). By 2018, the Indian green bond market had risen to ₹500 billion. This clearly indicates that India has an enormous capacity for the development of sustainable finance which just needs to be unlocked with appropriate policies and measures. According to Climate Transparency’s &lt;em&gt;Brown to Green&lt;/em&gt; report, wherein a study was conducted among the G20 countries measuring the Green Bond Issuance as a share of the country’s overall debt, India was ranked 5th, hence, Indian financial institutions and investors should realise that the green bond market has a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the enormous potential, the market is yet to overcome several barriers such as greenwashing, false claims of environmental compliance, etc. Additionally, there exist mismatches between long-term green investment and short-term interests of the investors which tend to make the market less efficient. Exorbitant currency hedging costs because of the high volatility of the Indian rupee, poor sovereign rating, and low tenure of the green bonds pose a hurdle in the path of creating a highly advanced green bond market. Moreover, we need to realise that till date the green bonds that have been issued in India have only been offered by highly established finance companies, whereas internationally, other organisations such as local governments, climate change organisations, and other corporate firms are all coming together to address this issue by diversifying the green bond market in their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On analysing the above situation of green finance in the country, we can clearly conclude that India’s full potential still needs to be explored because currently there exists a shortage of supply as well as the demand for green bonds in the market because of various constraints. In order to increase the efficiency of this particular market, the government and the authorities need to formulate relevant policies and implement them. For starters, the short-term interests of investors as well as issuers, need to be removed by educating them that the advancement of the market in the country not only will fund the necessary environmental projects but also would allow issuers to generate a positive public reputation. Since the main reason for the lack of demand of green bonds in our country is the investors’ perception that they are not competitive enough to give them high financial returns, the governmental agencies need to step up by guaranteeing a fixed rate of return which is marginally higher than other investments so that large institutional investors and retail investors would heavily invest under this domain. Other measures such as reducing foreign exchange hedging costs will attract investors from overseas to invest in clean energy projects of India. RBI, SEBI, Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency Ltd. (IREDA), and the Ministry of Finance can play an important role in the nascent stage development of Green Finance in the country by creating more rupee denominated bonds such as the IFC-Yes Bank Green Masala Bond of 2015. Launching credited and standardised Indian green bonds that would reduce the stigma of the attached risk with green bonds can completely flip the situation upside-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, in order to attract domestic demand, the government should provide tax incentives to individuals for investment in such bonds. The development of sustainable stock exchanges just like the Shanghai Stock Exchange did is essential for continued growth. It has a special index to monitor the green finance situation in the country. Efforts of the government and other institutions have borne positive results. According to the Indian Economic Survey 2019-20, India has become the second-largest market for green bonds after China with $10.3 billion transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government support and a dedicated policy at hand are necessarily required to scale up the level of green bonds market in the country. An enhanced policy framework is required in action to upgrade the current situation of the green finance market in the country. This can also be done by educating investors, and removing information asymmetry between issuers and investors. An increase in investor confidence could give a new shape to the outlook of sustainable finance in our country. Only enhanced collective participation of issuers, corporate firms, financial institutions, policymakers, and regulators will give the fundamental push to the boundary of the green bond market, and would further give rise to other such opportunities in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, green bonds can be seen as the interlinking bridge connecting sustainable finance with funding quintessential environmental projects. Growth in the green bonds in India would set a precedent for other theme-based bonds such as social bonds, water bonds, and sustainability bonds that raise finance for specific developmental purposes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cherry Sharma</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“We need bold action on climate change, our generation may not be able to solve all the problems related to climate change, but we can do our part to leave a better planet for the next generation”, said Kristalina Georgieva, World Bank Group and Interim Chief Executive Officer. Climate change has caused an unprecedented risk to the growth of societies and economies. According to a recent report by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), it has been estimated that around $6-7 trillion of annual investment is globally required to achieve the objective of moving the world economy towards a ‘greener economy’. To get the entire globe out of this trap, we need to make substantial investments that fund projects focussing on creating low carbon economies, clean energy, water transportation, etc. Only with such effective measures shall we be able to build a climate-resilient economy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Expect Us to Be Governed Well after Brexit</title><link href="/Dont-Expect-Us-to-Be-Governed-Well-after-Brexit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don't Expect Us to Be Governed Well after Brexit" /><published>2020-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Dont-Expect-Us-to-Be-Governed-Well-after-Brexit</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dont-Expect-Us-to-Be-Governed-Well-after-Brexit">&lt;p&gt;It’s time to start talking about Brexit again. I hear you sigh. And don’t worry, I share your weariness. The reason we have to bring it up, put simply, is that the UK is barely any closer to leaving the European Union than it was in 2018, or even 2016. All changes up to this point have been symbolic, throwaway gestures. A hopelessly vague withdrawal agreement means that Britain is still under the jurisdiction of the Court of Justice of the European Union, and all of the regulations of the Customs Union remain in place on our shores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This didn’t happen by accident, however. The Prime Minister, in classic fashion, came up with the headline and then proceeded not to write down anything else. The government’s plan was to bundle together the details of Brexit over the course of this year. Since January, however, the government and the Prime Minister have been preoccupied with the coronavirus. Our foreign office ministers, who might have been able to shrug off COVID-19 and focus on the detail of leaving the European institutions, are now engaging in a well-intended but futile dogfight with China over Hong Kong and Huawei.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the government could not have foreseen all that has happened in the last six months. It would be unfair to blame it for not giving the withdrawal agreement their full attention. But we can blame them, and we should, for giving the impression that they had finished the job in January when they had not. We should also blame the Tory Parliament for lining up behind an agreement that is no different to the one they rejected three times under Theresa May. These errors have done nothing but store up problems for the future. When you see Nigel Farage back on the BBC in the Autumn, foaming at the mouth as well at the pint glass, and barking that what we have is not Brexit, you know who to point the finger at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation is bad enough as it is, but it leads us to a much more fundamental point; if our government isn’t fit to take us out of the European Union, then it isn’t fit to govern us afterwards either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government doesn’t just have a handle on Brexit now; it never has, and it probably never will. It has not grasped how fundamentally different our country would have to be if it were to be successful outside the European Union. The young and the poor would have to fill the low-paid jobs which they used to do, but which are currently done very well by incoming Poles and Romanians. The government would have to commit to a real industrial strategy which might give us a chance of improving our account balance. If the government has even realised these issues, it will never do anything about them, because the consequences of their actions would be too unpopular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much hay was made during the referendum about independence and sovereignty. This was an important debate, and it needed to happen. However, this discussion was mostly framed through the narrow lens of the Parliament, and whether Britain should be able to make its own laws. This is misguided because sovereignty and independence are multi-headed creatures. True independence means having control not only over the Parliament and the courts, but also over the economy, industrial capacity, energy supply and foreign policy decisions. What we risk to borrow from Adam Tooze’s description of Britain after the First World War is ending up with the trappings of sovereignty, but not the substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may sound inoffensive enough, but it could be anything. We risk immense economic difficulty if our low-skilled, low-export economy is exposed to the fury of the global market, especially in the midst of the US-China trade war. Without an independent economic clout of our own, we will probably remain closely aligned to the Europeans on issues of trade, but there is always the chance that the European Commission, lenient and reasonable in the negotiations up until this point (sorry, leave voters), makes this difficult to get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this leads to the conclusion that Britain’s governing class lacks the resolve to create the sort of independence that people voted for in 2016. A country can’t just vote for sovereignty, it has to build it over many decades. The possibility of governing ourselves badly is implicit in the idea of governing ourselves. In this sense, the referendum result might turn out to be a good thing, because it gives our political class less wriggle room - no more blaming our problems on the low countries. We can more easily dispense off incompetent leaders, and replace them with people who run the country more sensibly. But, if this is to be the case, you would have to say that Britain’s current government isn’t up to the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>.</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">It’s time to start talking about Brexit again. I hear you sigh. And don’t worry, I share your weariness. The reason we have to bring it up, put simply, is that the UK is barely any closer to leaving the European Union than it was in 2018, or even 2016. All changes up to this point have been symbolic, throwaway gestures. A hopelessly vague withdrawal agreement means that Britain is still under the jurisdiction of the Court of Justice of the European Union, and all of the regulations of the Customs Union remain in place on our shores.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policing the Police</title><link href="/Policing-the-Police" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policing the Police" /><published>2020-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Policing-the-Police</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Policing-the-Police">&lt;p&gt;Breonna Taylor, unarmed and asleep, was shot eight times after the police barged into her home at night suspecting a drug case that proved to be untrue. The policemen who were responsible for this were reassigned but remain free from charges of murder and still hold their positions in the police department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alton Sterling was shot six times after being tasered when he was selling his DVDs. The policeman responsible was fired, while his partner was suspended for a mere three days. They both have not faced any charges for his murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Clark was shot more than twenty times in his grandmother’s backyard because the police thought he was holding a gun. He was actually holding a phone. The police officer did not face charges, and Clark’s family was paid compensation money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just three of the innumerable stories of the victims of police brutality. I request you go through the &lt;em&gt;Know their names&lt;/em&gt; series by Alia Chughtai in Al Jazeera to know more about such stories. Their names deserve to be said aloud and remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such story is that of George Floyd. He was choked to death by officer Derek Chauvin who knelt on his neck for 8 minutes and 46 seconds, on suspicion of use of counterfeit $20 notes. George Floyd’s death proved to be a catalyst for pushing lawmakers into considering the vulnerability of the African-American community and the threat that excess power in the hands of police poses to the minority communities in the United States. The Police Reform Bill is a consequence of widespread public outrage and protests following the video of George Floyd’s murder. The video, while not being the only evidence of the brutal conduct by the police towards the African-American citizens, was the breaking point. The unprecedented yet extremely valid and long-awaited display of anger from the black community and their allies demanded consideration and attention of the lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the police in the United States enjoys qualified immunity, allowing them to get away after committing crimes that led to the death of Breonna Taylor and Alton Sterling. The police do not get proper sensitivity and awareness training. Moreover, there are almost no checks and mechanisms to hold them accountable. In previous cases of police brutality, almost none of the officers faced criminal charges and received a mere slap on the wrist for their grievous offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Police Reform Bill 2020 is aimed towards changing the aforementioned situations. The Bill bans maneuvers like chokeholds and ‘no-knock’ entry, which are the most common causes of death. It sets limits in the use of tear gas, mandates police officers to wear body cameras, and ensures dashboard cameras on police vehicles. This will act as a deterrent towards the use of excessive and violent methods of restraining people. It will limit the transfer of military-grade equipment to state and local police, and allow victims of police brutality to file a case against the police for using excessive force or for violating their constitutional rights. Sensitivity and racial awareness training programmes for police are also a part of the Bill amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Bill is far from being adequate in ensuring police accountability. The new Bill limits qualified immunity but does not remove it from existence. The police will still continue to enjoy immunity in cases of police brutality until the situation is extreme. The lawmakers in many states argue that eliminating qualified immunity would result in frivolous cases and waste of funds. This only highlights the apathy of many lawmakers towards the civil rights and safety of their citizens. Additionally, the Bill does not de-fund or even reduce the funds allocated to the police. This emphasises the importance lawmakers place on the police regardless of their conduct and offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Police Reform Bill having been passed in the house of representatives currently awaits being passed in the Senate, and still has a long way to go before it can become a law. The Bill remains stuck amidst the bipartisan politics, with the Republicans and Democrats fighting to gain the upper-hand in the Senate. States are voting towards passing the Bill with modifications while the Democrats and the Republicans continue to argue on the finer points of the Bill. The Connecticut Police Reform Bill was debated upon the entire night before it was passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The significance of this Bill is not just limited to holding the police accountable and safeguarding the civil rights and liberty of the African-American and other minority communities, it is also an acknowledgement of the atrocities faced by the African-American community. The bill is a step towards recognising the names of the forgotten victims and a promise to do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public’s reaction to this Bill is majorly positive. While they continue to advocate for defunding the police and completely removing qualified immunity, they are willing to listen, ready to fight for a better future, and acknowledge this Bill as a step towards the same. Sadly, yet expectedly, there also exists a faction of the public, thankfully small, that is not pleased with the idea of holding the police accountable. So far, their silly cries of “Blue Lives Matter” have been relatively ignored, and have faced criticism and backlash from their fellow citizens. Yet this faction, no matter how small, still indicates that America has a long way to go. The fight towards racism begins from this Bill, yet it would not do to ignore the root cause of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responsibility for George Floyd’s death does not lie solely with the police. It also lies with the system that provided the perpetrators support, and with the system that was willing to ignore their actions. It lies in the lack of checks and balances on the police and most importantly, it lies with the people who spread the ideas of bigotry and hatred. They may not have been the one pressing the knee to an innocent man’s neck, but they were the ones who stood by, watched, and did nothing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Breonna Taylor, unarmed and asleep, was shot eight times after the police barged into her home at night suspecting a drug case that proved to be untrue. The policemen who were responsible for this were reassigned but remain free from charges of murder and still hold their positions in the police department.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Saviour of Europe</title><link href="/The-Saviour-of-Europe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Saviour of Europe" /><published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Saviour-of-Europe</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Saviour-of-Europe">&lt;p&gt;On July 21, 2020, at 5:30 am, the President of the European Council, Charles Michel posted in a single word tweet, “&lt;em&gt;Deal!&lt;/em&gt;”. He was, of course, referring to a deal that was unanimously voted by all the member nations of the European Union (EU) at the Special meeting of the European Council. The meeting which was supposed to be a four-day summit was extended to a fifth day so as to bring about consensus among the EU members to get a unanimous vote on the proposed deal. So, what is the deal in question and what does it mean for the European Union?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Council, one of the three wings of the European Union, met in Brussels to vote on what is called the Multiannual Financial Framework (MFF). MFF is a seven-year financial framework that regulates the annual budget of the Union. To put it simply, it is the EU’s budget for a period of seven years. This budget is funded by the members on a pro-rata basis. MMF contains a set of goals – an EU-wide common policy, and this ‘EU budget’ allots funds to the members to spend under the agreed heads. The framework which came into force in 2014 is set to expire in 2020. Therefore, a new framework for the period of 2021-2027 had to be agreed on this year. This is precisely the reason for the Brussels summit. However, that does not explain the importance surrounding the summit. Apart from MFF, the EU and its member states agreed on a specific recovery fund, called Next Generation EU (NGEU), for the sole purpose of tackling the COVID-19 crisis. Under NGEU, the European Commission will borrow a sum of €750 billion from the capital markets. Out of this €750 billion, a sum of €390 billion will be disbursed to the members as grants; while the rest, €360 billion, will be provided in the form of loans. While the European Commission as a whole has borrowed only sparsely in the past, it is a first for the Commission to borrow on such a large scale. Therefore, the deal that we are talking about has two parts: MFF and the NGEU. With a €1.074 trillion seven-year budget and the €750 billion recovery fund, the financial package amounts to an enormous €1.82 trillion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three things that stand out in the budget. First is the political authority clause. The deal document states that “&lt;em&gt;[the] Budgetary Authority shall exercise political control, to be defined in the agreement between the European Parliament, the Council and the Commission&lt;/em&gt;”. This can be seen as a measure that could cause problems for Hungary and Poland. The European Commission had initiated proceedings against both these countries over rule of law concerns. Many leaders demanded that the EU funding to its member nations be linked to the condition that states follow democratic principles and “EU’s founding values”. During the discussions in the summit, the Hungarian Prime Minister Viktor Orbán threatened to veto the Commission’s proposal and demanded that the funding not be linked to the rule of law practices. However, the wording “political control” means that the money will also be linked to the observing the rule of law. Second, the deal contained clauses that put “emergency brakes” on the funding to a member state, if the state failed to adhere to the reform conditions attached to the funding. This move came after intense pressure from the premier of Netherlands Mark Rutte, who was the voice of the “frugal four”. Frugal four is an informal association of Sweden, Denmark, Austria, and the Netherlands. Initially, French President Emmanuel Macron had proposed for a sum of €500 billion in the form of grants and another €250 billion in the form of loans to the member countries. The frugal four along with Finland had opposed the idea of providing huge sums in the form of grants and wanted grants to be limited to below €300 billion. This proposal was unacceptable for Italy and Spain; the two countries worst hit by the COVID-19 pandemic refused to accept any total grant amount below €400 billion. Eventually, a compromise was reached and the grant amount was settled at €390 billion. The Netherlands Prime Minister, however, scored a victory by successfully getting the members to agree to a review clause. Third, the deal puts the issue of climate change at the forefront. It says, “&lt;em&gt;Climate action will be mainstreamed in policies and programmes financed under the MFF and NGEU&lt;/em&gt;”. According to the deal document, a total of 30% of the expenditure of the €1.82 trillion will be used to reach the climate targets in conformity to the objectives of the Paris agreements. It also has a provision that rules that the European Commission should publish a report on climate expenditure annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key element to the deal is the specifications about how the revenue will be raised to pay off the debt that the European Commission will borrow under the NGEU provisions. The deal sets the deadline of 2058 to repay the whole amount. It was agreed that a tax on non-recycled plastic should be imposed. Another tax on imported goods from countries with lower carbon-emitting standards than the EU is also envisaged. Revenue from these taxes will be transferred to the EU for the purpose of repayment of the borrowings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal is historic for many reasons. It is the first time ever that all the countries have agreed and empowered the European Commission to borrow a huge amount. But most importantly, with Brexit and the inward-looking policies being adopted all across the globe, many feared that the failure of the EU to reach a deal will pose an existential threat to the Union. However, the euro hit an 18-month high, as soon as the announcement of the deal came out, stock markets across Europe surged, and the European shares bounced. This deal now must pass through the European Parliament and must be ratified by all member states, which in all possibility seems likely. In a world where multilateral institutions and dialogue are on the wane, one can only hope this deal will exemplify the need of international institutions in coordinating responses to 21st-century problems that are increasingly cross-national.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">On July 21, 2020, at 5:30 am, the President of the European Council, Charles Michel posted in a single word tweet, “Deal!”. He was, of course, referring to a deal that was unanimously voted by all the member nations of the European Union (EU) at the Special meeting of the European Council. The meeting which was supposed to be a four-day summit was extended to a fifth day so as to bring about consensus among the EU members to get a unanimous vote on the proposed deal. So, what is the deal in question and what does it mean for the European Union?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lebanon Quagmire Spins Out of Control</title><link href="/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lebanon Quagmire Spins Out of Control " /><published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control">&lt;p&gt;On October 17,  2019, the Government of Lebanon, the world’s third most indebted country, decided to impose a tax on WhatsApp messaging application to engulf its amassed fiscal deficit. Unfortunately, nothing changed except the calamity exacerbating with each passing day. As the prices for basic commodities soar high, people find it difficult to feed themselves and have resorted to selling their gold in order to fill their empty stomachs. Adding to the troubles, the pandemic is likely to downgrade the economy, which is already unable to withstand the jolts it has received, by 12-13%. With an urgent requirement of aid to 75% of its population, an instantaneous revival for the economy reminds me of the Gucci shoes in my shopping wishlist for years that have never been able to find their path to ‘add to cart’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese have been known for maintaining a fine standard of living, the bars and restaurants have always stayed open even during the wars. The unhygienic water, heckling power supply, etc. was never a matter of concern for the middle-class until they enjoyed their affordable foreign tours. Despite a kaput monetary system, the luxuries and seamless interaction with the world have been courtesy of the Lebanese currency’s 22-year-old peg to the US currency, but who knew that this could turn into a substantial contributor to the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For several years, the Government has continued to borrow from global as well as domestic lenders to keep up with the pegged US dollars. As the Central Bank liberally hiked the interest rates, Lebanon became a strong magnet for the opulent investors across the globe. The unrealistic peg at 1,507 Lebanese pounds to a dollar and thriving efforts to keep up with it when there was a shortage of dollars in the market led to enormous debts. Further, to escape from the deficit, the Central Bank increased the interest rate to attract more investors. Nearly 50% of the state revenue goes into paying the debt, a major chunk of the remaining portion is put in effect for the government employees’ salaries, leaving very little margin for infrastructure development, capital investment, and expenditure on human resources. Thus, the Lebanese economy closes its boundary for revenue generation as there is no scope from other sectors, all the money is burned for consumption through imports, real estate and to defend the peg. Despite a sluggish economy, the government kept piling on the debts through depraved spendings, majorly on the expanded public sector which was put in effect to brim up their vote banks and divert focus from an ailing power grid. The situation became even more hostile owing to the political instability and the Prime Minister disappearing into Saudi Arabia, this shook the confidence of the Lebanese affluents who then decided to transfer their deposits out of the country. With the fear of depleting the country’s reserves, the banks had to close owing to the shortage of dollars. This has been a major concern for ordinary citizens, who have to stand in long queues to only return with a tiny amount of cash in hand which is insufficient to buy the daily bread, and have to sleep with an empty stomach during this pandemic. Economists view it as a matter of concern as the government continues to prioritise foreign creditors who hold an enormous $12 billion of the Lebanese debt, at the expense of the empty stomachs of its citizens. The banking sector, which has enjoyed mellow relations with the country’s political elite who held shares in some of these banks is a significant culprit. As the ordinary citizens fear a risk to their deposits, the commercial lenders who were always on the receiving end, even after capital controls in action have managed to pave their way for profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an uncertain political atmosphere, inefficient government policies driven with self-interest, faulty monetary system, and much more on the home-front, there are a few external factors that also act as a cherry to this toppling cake. A small country with a population of six million is largely dependent on remittances. 12.7% of the Lebanese GDP constitutes remittances from family members living abroad and majorly from the majestic oil-producers in the Middle-Eastern country, second only to Palestine. As coronavirus grips the world and the global GDP, numerous people have lost their jobs in various parts of the world. Owing to the global crisis, the number of people transferring and depositing money in Lebanon for their families and for tax exemptions abroad has seen a significant drop. In fact, they seek withdrawal from their already deposited funds in the Lebanese banks. The truncated oil prices have aggravated the revenue crisis for Lebanon. Moving closer, the oil-rich nations neighbouring the state of Lebanon that inhabited Lebanese emigrants have already cut down on the remittances they provided at regular intervals. These nations formulated the major chunk of the revenue Lebanon generated from remittances and used it further to fund its additional debt. With a threat of Saudi Arabia likely to expel Lebanese nationals, the inflow of remittance dollars that would support the dysfunctional peg has begun to diminish at a petrifying rate, making the situation even more muddled up for the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese economy finds itself amidst a thick forest, and the process of revival is definitely going to be a prolonged one along with a dire need for sustained efforts. With an urgent need for external liquidity that is possible only with the IMF reform programme which comes with a set of associated reforms that all the nations need to abide by when subscribing to the stimulus package. As the IMF estimates a debt reaching 155% of the Lebanese GDP, the government remains reluctant to adopt the IMF reforms and slashes the reports presented by the organisation. The economic experts and advisors, both within the state and globally, have to ultimately adopt the IMF reforms package to survive and provide daily bread to its citizens and the refugees. This detailed analysis is food for thought for further plan of action and devastating experience to learn from for the other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">On October 17, 2019, the Government of Lebanon, the world’s third most indebted country, decided to impose a tax on WhatsApp messaging application to engulf its amassed fiscal deficit. Unfortunately, nothing changed except the calamity exacerbating with each passing day. As the prices for basic commodities soar high, people find it difficult to feed themselves and have resorted to selling their gold in order to fill their empty stomachs. Adding to the troubles, the pandemic is likely to downgrade the economy, which is already unable to withstand the jolts it has received, by 12-13%. With an urgent requirement of aid to 75% of its population, an instantaneous revival for the economy reminds me of the Gucci shoes in my shopping wishlist for years that have never been able to find their path to ‘add to cart’.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hagia Sophia: A Tale of Heritance Indignation by Erdogan</title><link href="/Hagia-Sophia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hagia Sophia: A Tale of Heritance Indignation by Erdogan" /><published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Hagia-Sophia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Hagia-Sophia">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of the Heritage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructed by Justinian I, the ruler of the Byzantine Empire, in 532 AD when Istanbul was still Constantinople, the Hagia Sophia (Ayasofya in Turkish) was a 65,000 square feet stone-structured church-cathedral. Throughout the course of its ruling history, the church was turned into a mosque which was then converted to a museum. Its original construction was meant to seat the Patriarch of the Eastern Orthodox Church, and it remained the same for approximately 900 years! In 1453, when the Ottoman forces of the Turk ruler Sultan Mehmet II claimed Constantinople as their land, they ransacked the cathedral that was Hagia Sophia and turned it into a mosque in no time. The monument was changed heavily, as key Orthodox features were re-interiorised, removed, even plastered upon, minarets were added to the exterior of the structure, and ornate Christian mosaics were covered with panels of religious Arabic calligraphy, giving it an essence of architectural, cultural, and of course, religious rebirth. For the longest time, it was Istanbul’s most important mosque until the Atatürk revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listed as a UNESCO (The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation) World Heritage site, a 1500-year-old structure, on the backdrop of a religiously unprecedented heritage, and a history panning not just the entirety of the Ottoman Empire but the Byzantine Empire, the Hagia Sophia has a rich story not only in its cultural sense but in a historically and religiously profound way, one that only former Turkish President Mustafa Kemal Atatürk was wise enough to have appreciated in the course of his modernisation of the nation. After the First World War, the Ottoman Sultans fell apart and Turkey was made into a secular nation by Atatürk. In the 1930’s, Atatürk shut down the mosque and created a museum out of it to preserve its culturally rich heritage, and highlight its historic significance. Interestingly, this shifted the honour of the greatest mosque in the Ummah (the Muslim community) to Masjid-al-Haram, the one in Mecca. It was now when Arab and Turkish tensions rose and gave birth to the debate relating to the state of the Hagia Sophia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erdogan’s Political Intent and Long-Term Desire for the Islamic Centralisation of Turkey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was last year when the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan claimed that turning the Hagia Sophia into a museum was a “very big mistake” and considered reverting it back to a mosque just days before the local elections were supposed to be held. Initially, when Erdogan entered politics three decades ago in Turkey, anything even remotely related to Hagia Sophia was never on his agenda. In fact, he was even reported to have opposed the reconversion of the Hagia Sophia to a mosque maybe in an attempt to seem politically correct, still an objection nonetheless. His rhetoric on the same grew the other way in 2019 when he ended up losing the municipal elections in Istanbul. It was later when the US President Donald Trump recognised Jerusalem as the capital of Israel, that Erdogan brought the same agenda up, attempting to maybe score political recognition that he had been losing since last year by supporting such a big decision, hoping to gain radical followership. And it seemed to have worked as he is currently the Turkish President, and is defending his final decision to exercise the country’s sovereign right in converting the museum back to a mosque, as the highest court annulled the site’s status as a museum. Official reports state that some Christian emblems, including mosaics of the Virgin Mary adorning its soaring golden dome, are still intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erdogan’s changes to the Hagia Sophia are majorly to gain political publicity, but this indicates his desires for the nation from a larger standpoint. This agenda is a disguised symbolic ruse to dismantle Ataturk’s secular legacy by remoulding Turkey according to his own vision. He mounds himself as a modern-day Turkish conqueror who will “save” the nation’s sovereignty, and that any outsider that condemns the same is attacking Turkey directly. This decision is also reflective of his intention to shift the Islamic centre of gravity away from Mecca to Turkey. It is a pronounced declaration to the entirety of the Ummah across nations by reclaiming the honour of reinstating what was once the greatest mosque in hopes of going back to its history. The problem with which is that its legacy has proved why the decision is not only disrespectful to the monument’s history but demeans a great leader that democratised Turkey into what it is today (or &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; before Erdogan). Although, this reclamation sits well with his bases, such as religious conservatives and Turkish nationalists, incentivising further radical support. Imposing ultranationalism and non-democratic sentiments, he is becoming an era-defining strongman and threat of caution to democratised ideals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics have argued that Erdogan is using this as a distraction from the economic damage caused in Turkey due to the COVID-19 pandemic, which is highly plausible. Unfortunately, none of the backlashes affected Erdogan’s decision and shortly after the court’s announcement, the first call to prayer at Hagia Sophia was broadcasted on all of Turkey’s main news channels, subsequently after which the cultural site’s social media handles were taken down. The first Muslim prayers were held after 86 years inside the converted building on July 24 (also the anniversary of Turkey’s established borders due to the 1923 treaty), attended by around a thousand people in the mosque and a lot more others outside with their mats. Four muezzins recited the call to prayer from each of the four minarets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Reactions to the Reconversion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UNESCO stated that it deeply regretted the decision and appealed to the Turkish authorities to “open a dialogue without delay”. It urged Turkey not to finalise anything without discussion, yet was cold-shouldered. Greece has condemned the move gravely, being home to many Eastern Orthodox Church followers. Greek archaeologist and Cultural Minister Lina Mendoni stated that the entire tactic was an “open provocation to the civilised world” and was only raising religious tensions in the region. She claimed the court ruling confirmed the absence of an independent justice system in Turkey. Turkey’s Council of State, its top administrative court, ruled on July 10 stating, &lt;em&gt;“It was concluded that the settlement deed allocated it as a mosque and its use outside this character is not possible legally. The cabinet decision in 1934 that ended its use as a mosque and defined it as a museum did not comply with laws”&lt;/em&gt;. The Russian Church, home to the world’s largest Orthodox Christian community, immediately voiced apprehensions that the Turkish court would not take its community’s concerns into account while ruling on the status of Hagia Sophia. This has led to greater divisions between the communities, as the Pope has expressed “profound sadness”. Popular Turkish author Orhan Pamuk voiced the folly of the move while describing its backward motives of assigning an asterisk on its secular identity as a state which Kemal Ataturk helped restore. &lt;em&gt;“There are millions of secular Turks like me who are crying against this but their voices are not heard”&lt;/em&gt;, he stated in an interview with BBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an adamant historical change, despite severe criticism from the international community, to a monument that must belong to humanity at large and not to Turkey exclusively considering its history. It should remain a museum for bearing the brunt of being a bridge between the two faiths, and a worldwide symbol of coexistence with pride instead of battling a long drawn religious wrath that this decision imbibes. How long will regimens such as Erdogan’s allow for secularly-grey decisions to hold pedestals, being ignorant of histories and heritages, furthering matters of religious intolerance, and torturing secular fabrics?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The History of the Heritage</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Football for Global Influence</title><link href="/Football-for-Global-Influence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Football for Global Influence" /><published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Football-for-Global-Influence</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Football-for-Global-Influence">&lt;p&gt;I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What does Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logo belongs to Gazprom, a Russian natural gas company. Logo sponsorships are normal in football. Teams make money offering jersey spaces to sponsors selling things like credit cards, cars and cell phones but Gazprom isn’t like most sponsors, i.e. private companies with products that football fans can buy. Instead, it’s a company owned by the Russian government that makes money selling natural gas to foreign countries. Yet, it’s everywhere in European football. So, if football fans can’t buy what they are selling, why is Gazprom spending millions to sponsor football games? The answer is part of a larger story that’s changing the sport of football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d7/Major_russian_gas_pipelines_to_europe.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/russiangaspipes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia has the world’s largest natural gas reserves and most of them are located in the Arctic gas fields controlled by Gazprom. The company is led by Alexey Miller, a close ally of Russian President Vladimir Putin. Since 2005, the Russian government has owned a majority stake in Gazprom. This means that the company profits are under Putin’s control, and gas sellers, along with oil, account for around 50% of Russia’s annual budget. Eastern European countries like Finland, Estonia, Lithuania, Poland, Slovakia depend on Russian oil for 75-100% of their natural gas needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move further towards the West, the countries’ dependence begins to fall. At the end of the 20th century, Germany represented the biggest opportunity for Gazprom. German Chancellor Gerhard Schroeder had announced plans to phase out coal and nuclear power which meant Germany needed more natural gas to maintain their energy supply. Gazprom wanted to give it to them but there was a problem. To get to Germany, Russia’s gas needed to pass through pipelines crossing other countries that charged Gazprom transport fees. And most of them went through Ukraine, a country that has complicated political relations with Russia. Today, Ukraine still charges upwards of $3 billion each year to pump gas to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, starting back in 2005, Russia began working on a strategy to bypass Ukraine and ship their gas directly to Western Europe through the Nord Stream pipeline, a route through the Baltic sea straight to Northern Germany. In late 2005, Gazprom was in the final stages of financing the project and Germany’s Chancellor was preparing for an election. During his time in the office, Gerhard Schroeder had become friendly with Putin, and critics in Germany were increasingly concerned about the Russian leader’s growing influence. Just a few weeks before the election, Schroeder met with Putin signing an agreement officially approving the pipeline. Two months later, he lost his re-election. However, by March, he found a new job overseeing Gazprom’s pipeline to Germany. It also came out that, before leaving office Schroeder had approved a secret Gazprom loan that provided over a billion euros to finance the project. This led to Gazprom’s big project being called a “story of scandal, corruption, and the creeping influence of Russia in Germany”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in 2006 the story changed, Gazprom signed a deal to sponsor the German soccer team FC Schalke 04. At the time Schalke’s finances were worrying the team officials and Gazprom’s sponsorship provided money that the team desperately needed. At a press conference announcing the deal, a Gazprom chairman stated that Schalke’s connections with the German energy sector were the reason behind their decision to become its sponsors. Schalke played in Gelsenkirchen, a town in Germany’s Ruhr Valley, where much of the country’s energy industry is based. It’s also near the town of Rehden, a hub for pipelines to the rest of Europe and home to western Europe’s largest natural gas storage facilities. Schalke wasn’t Gazprom’s first football deal. The year before, they had bought a controlling stake in a team on the other end of the Nord Stream route: the Russian team Zenit St Petersburg. Gazprom’s investment made Zenit a major force in football. Two years after taking control, Zenit won their first-ever league championship. They’ve been able to sign expensive foreign stars like Axel Wetzel and Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, as Gazprom logos were revealed around Schalke’s stadium, German headlines were hailing the Russian gas giant for pumping millions into the German team and hence, creating a positive image in German minds for the company. And over the next few years, the Gazprom logo would become a team symbol displayed at Schalke’s games and printed on official merchandise. Schalke also won a championship in 2011. By then, Nord Stream had been completed and it had started pumping gas to Germany. There was also another struggling team whose jerseys started featuring Gazprom’s logo, the Serbian team: Red Star Belgrade. Red Star was about $25 million in debt when Gazprom signed to become their jersey sponsor and again, there was also another pipeline: the south stream would have bypassed Ukraine by going directly through Serbia to Southern Europe. That project closed in 2014, but Gazprom further increased its access to Europe by building Nord Stream 2, a second pipeline doubling the amount of gas flowing from Russia to Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years in addition to its pipeline empire, Gazprom has also expanded its influence over global football to include energy partnership with Chelsea football club, UEFA Champions League, and the sport’s most famous tournament: the FIFA World Cup. These sponsorships have made Gazprom’s logo familiar to not only the fans in Europe but across the world. It also did something which boosted the Russian economy. Russia became the world’s largest exporter of natural gas and provided for almost half of all the natural gas supply to Europe becoming a major player in the energy field in Europe. This created a reliance of other countries on Russia for the supply of natural gas, power and energy generation. The strategy adopted by Russia turned out to be a ‘game-changer’ and as of 2019, Russia supplied 199 billion cubic meters of natural gas to Europe. The oil-and-gas sector accounted for 16% of GDP, 52% of federal budget revenues, and over 70% of total exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Russia is the skipper when it comes to energy supply and generation in Europe and other countries are learning from their example. As the example of Gazprom shows, having prominent soccer sponsorship offers a way around bad publicity by winning approval on the field. Many companies such as Qatar Airways, Etihad Airways and Emirates Airlines have started sponsoring major teams in Europe such as AS Roma, Manchester City and AC Milan respectively. As an avid football supporter, I feel like it’s a big opportunity: their money helps teams win major championships and tournaments, but it is changing the sport itself. Now that it has become common to see a German team sponsored by Russia’s gas company facing off against an Italian team sponsored by Dubai’s state-owned airline, it is starting to seem like the field is hosting two competitions at once: a match between the two teams and larger play for a foreign influence that continues long after the final whistle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What does Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.</summary></entry></feed>