<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-24T11:37:38+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Indian Economic Downturn: A Critique</title><link href="/Indian-Economic-Downturn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Economic Downturn: A Critique" /><published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Indian-Economic-Downturn</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Economic-Downturn">&lt;p&gt;The recent economic downturn in India has been the talk of the hour. The state of Indian economy is at its worst phase since the Modi Government came back to power in 2019. Having lost its coveted title of world’s fastest growing economy to China, India’s GDP growth rate has slipped to a six year low at 5% during the April-June quarter of 2019-20, putting the Reserve Bank of India’s projected GDP growth rate of 6.9% in grave danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decrease in the growth prospects of the Indian economy is largely due to the decline in manufacturing output and lack of consumption demand. This is clearly evidenced by the miserable state of Indian automobile sector, with an 18% dip in overall sales in July, 2019 alone. The worst hit was the passenger vehicles category, which saw a 35% decline in sales, followed by a decline in the sales of commercial vehicles by 25% and two-wheelers by 16%. Many automakers like Tata Motors and Ashok Leyland temporarily shut down their factories and suspended production so as to reduce excess inventories in a situation of weak demand. More than 300 dealerships have been closed and a mammoth of 230 thousand jobs have been lost in the sector. This heavy decline in sales has been caused due to a basket of factors, catalysed by upcoming changes related to environmental regulations and electric cars, and a lack of financing. India’s move to adopt new emission norms from April 1, 2020 has caused consumers to delay their consumption temporarily, partly because of the apprehension regarding validity of registration. A drop in rural demand is also evident from the reduced sale of tractors and two-wheelers in the country. In case of commercial vehicles, an increase in the freight carrying capacity of trucks has shrunk demand for new trucks. Further, an increase in the price of vehicles due to manufacturers having to comply with stringent safety regulations (airbags, anti-lock braking system and other crash norms) has weakened demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has tried to kick start the auto sector by taking steps such as lifting the ban on the purchase of vehicles by government departments, allowing additional 15% depreciation on vehicles acquired from mid-August till March 2020 to lower taxable profits and deferring the increase in one-time registration fee of vehicles until June 2020. However, many economists believe the downturn in auto sector to be cyclical caused by recent developments in the Indian economy which will eventually fade away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real problem comes in when people do not even have the money to buy things of everyday use like soaps, biscuits, tea, spices. The Fast Moving Consumer Goods (FMCG) market is in a lull with slowed down volume growth (number of packs sold) of companies like HUL, Daabur, Britannia during first quarter of the current financial year. On the other hand, the real estate sector is experiencing a downward trend in demand, with 1.28 million unsold houses as of March 2019, a 7% increase in the number from the previous year-end. This slowdown has affected more than 250 ancillaries that have forward and backward linkages with the housing sector, ranging from steel and cement to furnishings and paints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underlying cause of the poor performance of the manufacturing sector is a fall in private consumption and investment. While turbulence in the world economy has impacted India’s exports, the slump in internal demand is a result of falling rural and urban wages. From having high double digit figures, growth rates of both rural and urban areas has plunged to dismal single digit figures, largely due to structural changes like demonetisation and GST in the country as well as a poor monsoon affecting the agricultural income in rural areas. This has resulted in stagnant per capita income (in real terms) and to keep the consumption expenditure at the same level, the household savings have declined, resulting in a subsequent decline in investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a slow growth in retail loans such as home loans, vehicle loans and personal loans granted by banks and non-banking financial companies (NBFCs) during the first quarter of 2019-20. After the DHFL and IL&amp;amp;FS crisis, banks and mutual funds are reluctant to lend out to these institutions. This liquidity crunch of NBFCs has decreased their lending capacity. Borrowers too are apprehensive of their ability to repay loans in a period of decreasing real income and employee layoffs. Further, an inverted yield curve in the US, a symbol of long term lending rates being less than short term rates, is taken as an indicator of impending global recession. This is because banks borrow at short term rates and lend at long-term rates and the downward sloping curve means that the loans of these banks will become unprofitable, forcing banks to reduce their lending in the market, resulting in decreased economic activity globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Modi Government has been quick in initiating a recovery process to bring back the economy on track and undoing the damage done by its Budget 2019. The government recently unveiled the mega plan to merge ten public sector banks into four, reducing the number of public sector banks to merely 12 in the country, as part of plans to create fewer and stronger global-sized lenders to boost economic growth. The Union Budget 2019 also talked about injecting ₹70 trillion for recapitalisation of public sector banks to increase credit offtake in the economy. The Reserve Bank of India has also cut the repo rate for the fourth time in a row in 2019 by 35 base points to peg it at 5.4% giving commercial banks a nudge to reduce their lending rates, thus passing on the benefit to customers and attracting them to borrow more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another smart move off late is certainly the transfer of surplus funds of the central bank, worth ₹176 trillion to the Indian government, which will not only reduce the government’s dependence on external borrowings to finance its fiscal deficit target of 3.3%, but also increase per capita income and job creation via increased government expenditure at a time of weakening private investment. However, this transfer will reduce the wide gap between estimated revenue and expenditure by merely ₹580 billion in this fiscal year, because an amount equivalent to ₹900 billion has already been proposed by the Budget 2019 and an interim dividend worth ₹280 billion has been transferred to the government in FY19. The government has further announced the rollback of enhanced surcharge on foreign portfolio Investments (FPIs) as well as exemption to startups and investors from paying an ‘angel tax’ so as to reverse the outflow of money from the Indian stock market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This current contraction in the Indian economy is neither wholly cyclical that is bound to eventually fade away nor is it wholly structural that will result in a massive recession. It is rather a combination of both, with lower per capita income, especially in rural areas, and low job growth being major structural issues plaguing the economy; and low consumer demand and liquidity crunch being the prime cyclical problems. The government has wisely used both monetary and fiscal measures to combat this slowdown, but there is still a lot that needs to be done like new infrastructure projects, affordable housing schemes, modified GST rates, better irrigation facilities and enhanced liquidity of NBFCs. In a time when the private sector is wary of investment, it is only the government that can nudge the economy out of the rock bottom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The recent economic downturn in India has been the talk of the hour. The state of Indian economy is at its worst phase since the Modi Government came back to power in 2019. Having lost its coveted title of world’s fastest growing economy to China, India’s GDP growth rate has slipped to a six year low at 5% during the April-June quarter of 2019-20, putting the Reserve Bank of India’s projected GDP growth rate of 6.9% in grave danger.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Iceland’s Tourism Story</title><link href="/Iceland-Tourism-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Iceland’s Tourism Story" /><published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Iceland-Tourism-Story</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Iceland-Tourism-Story">&lt;p&gt;Iceland, a small island nation, situated in the Northern Atlantic went from being the 4th richest nation during its economic rise to occupying the center stage role in the financial controversy of 2008. And now, it has become infamous among the economists as an example of “what countries shouldn’t do”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most astonishing part of its journey is that until the 1990’s, the country had very little economic growth, with fishing being its primary source of employment. In 1991, there was a significant shift in the power tectonics of the country and David Oddsson was elected as the new Prime Minister. His ascent to the country’s Prime Ministership changed the fate of the country forever. His Government had inherited an economy built on huge debts, lacking the means of paying them back. This was a result of immense accumulation of unproductive investments made by the earlier governments and to worsen the situation further, the nation’s inflation rate was as high as 20% (which was unbelievably high when compared to other western countries). The stocks of fish, then a major source of income for the economy, began to deplete at an increasing rate. Thus, it called for a change and people voted for it. And oh, what a change did their votes bring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Government rolled out extensive liberalisation policies: the state-owned enterprises were privatised, taxes were slashed and that paved the way for the rise of the private sector in the country. Fortunately, the economy started to revive gradually, and inflation was brought under control. Thus, began an era of growth and it exploded in the 2000’s. Most significant of all was the deregulation of the finance industry which helped the banks to expand and grow at an unbridled speed. They started holding and managing billions of dollars. An exponential progression from the past. Shockingly, the banks dealt with an enormous amount of money, which was almost ten times the country’s GDP. By early 2007, the country had successfully emerged as the 4th richest nation in the world, and Reykjavik, the nation’s capital, had become a financial power hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the rise curve was steep and the short term growth misled people to think that they were invincible. However, as swift the rise to power is, the harder is the fall from grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everything was going well for the country, the financial crisis of 2008, which affected almost every west-world country, took a massive toll on Iceland’s economy. As the global recession started, the value of &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt;, the currency of Iceland, began to plummet and their banks failed the country. Because the banks dealt in enormous volume of money, it proved hard for the government to bail out the big players of the market. Amidst the chaos and tragedy, the country managed to find its way out of the recession far earlier than many of its partners-in-crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we know, some countries grow off manufacturing and the others off services. Likewise, Iceland decided to grow off the latter. They captured a part of the already gigantic worldwide tourism industry and built up a feasible strategy for much-needed economic development. The country leveraged tourism effectively to bounce back from the worst financial crisis that the world has witnessed since the Great Depression of 1929.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iceland has a serene and pure natural beauty with plentiful waterfalls, lakes, glaciers, geysers: pretty much everything that could attract tourists from all over the world. It has one of the most spectacular natural environments in the world, the country is only a few flight hours away from the richest countries like the UK, the US and others. Accessibility and affordability are two major aspects that tourists look for when travelling. Iceland has been very focused on addressing these two primary concerns to boost its tourism sector. The issue of affordability needed no attention as the fall in the value of &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt; made it cheaper for tourists to travel and avail various services in the country. To resolve the issue of accessibility, Iceland had Iceland Air, the national carrier, which by providing attractive fares to the flyers had grown in the trans-Atlantic area, and acted as a boon to the country. This well-reputed airline started more service routes and expanded to different parts of the world. A second airline based in Iceland, Wow Air, was soon launched. The two airlines carried more than half the visitors every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Crisis, word about Iceland spread across the world and grabbed the interest and attention of tourists. This has helped the Nordic nation tremendously in attracting foreign tourists. In one way, the event that crashed the economy had paved the path for its revival. By 2010, the tourism industry was growing by an enormous 20% per annum. As the industry grew, so did the hospitality sector. New hotels began to spring up. Car rentals expanded to carry people all across the pristine country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, Iceland’s real GDP started to grow at almost 7.5% by 2016. Tourism contributed about 10% to the GDP and 30% of the total export revenue of the country. Another central reason for the sudden boom in the tourism sector was immigration. The number of immigrants steadily rose into the country because of the labour shortage and economic boom in the country. They now make up for 32% of the total workforce employed in the tourism industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is one side of the coin, let’s now look at the other side. The tourism industry is highly seasonal and therefore, can’t be expected to generate revenue and employment throughout the year. This largely curtails the period of growth making it difficult for those employed in the sector to find stable employment. Tourism is an industry where most of the people are low-wage workers with limited scope of growth. Tourism also hasn’t exactly been the go-to industry for those white-collared employees who were out of jobs after the crisis. Then there are the negative effects on the environment due to the excessive usage. As heavy infrastructure is needed to accommodate the exponential growth in tourist visits, they come at the expense of damaging the environment. It has reached a level that excess tourism has become a serious concern for the country. The tourism industry has its dark sides, such as illegal employment, paying workers below the minimum wage and human trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this boom did not last for long. The tourism sector began to experience downfall since the third quarter of 2018. Since last December there has been a substantial fall in the number of tourists in the country. Since December 2018, Iceland started reporting negatives in the growth rate of incoming tourists. In April 2019, this had reached a level of negative 26%. There are many reasons for this sharp and sudden downfall. One of the first reasons is the collapse of Wow Air. Albeit being the second-largest airline of the nation, it had collapsed as it never saw profits and ran out of financials. Consequently, the growth estimates for 2019 were revised to -0.4% from the earlier 1.8%. Unemployment was predicted to reach 3.9% as against the earlier 3.1%. The collapse also meant that the thousands of tourists that were supposed to come were suddenly non-existent. Apart from Wow Air’s collapse, the fall of tourism can also be attributed to Iceland becoming expensive as a result of the appreciating &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt; owing to increased GDP growth. If one were to make an intelligent guess, it can also be is simply that Iceland isn’t appealing to people anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it was noted earlier, the tourism boon had devastating effects on the environment. On the other hand, the country did not have the structural capacity to support the huge influx of tourists. Optimistically speaking, Iceland can utilise this period to rebuild itself to expand infrastructure and to restore the lost natural beauty. It can also utilise this time to make plans for revitalising the sector and transforming it into one that can sustain a huge number of tourists and think of a solution to provide year-long stable income stream to the workers involved in this business.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Iceland, a small island nation, situated in the Northern Atlantic went from being the 4th richest nation during its economic rise to occupying the center stage role in the financial controversy of 2008. And now, it has become infamous among the economists as an example of “what countries shouldn’t do”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Hate You Like I Love You: Demythologising The Indian Mother</title><link href="/The-Indian-Mother" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Hate You Like I Love You: Demythologising The Indian Mother" /><published>2019-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Indian-Mother</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Mother">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve cringed at the Mother’s Day wishes that flooded social media a few weeks ago, which were basically variations of ‘she is the world’s smartest, strongest punching bag’, (go Leslie Knope!) you’ll probably see a valid point in what I have to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers are strange creatures. But do you know what’s stranger? The myth of motherhood, carefully curated by patriarchy and capitalism in India. What’s in it for them? Well, everything. This myth furthers their profiteering ventures through the sinister exploitation of a sentiment. They show mothers as goddesses, whose only joy lies in serving you, and her family well. She has no personal wishes, and her sexuality can very well be forgotten about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertisements portray women with ten hands (and I do not mean this figuratively), happily cooking up idlis, dosas, and parathas to serve a perfect breakfast to each member of the family. The grandfather nonchalantly reads the newspaper, the three petulant children complain (among whom is her husband, complaining the loudest about the late breakfast, so go figure), when the mother magically appears with trays full of scrumptious food. The mother is supposed to flutter her eyelashes and cry tears of joy when her husband decides to make her breakfast once a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian mother is supposed to selflessly love and consistently deliver. The ‘progressive’ advertisements are no better. The mother has short hair, works outside the house but god forbid if she comes home and lies down on the sofa after a long day. The ‘woke’ ads are packaged to comfortably suit our definition of empowerment without radically questioning it or demanding any action. The mother must juggle office work and domestic duties dexterously because, well, human fatigue does not apply to mythological beings, and this is what motherhood has mostly been depicted as in popular culture. A myth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m choosing to bypass Bollywood because that would require a separate article of its own, but I am sure you can make the connections. I choose standard examples from advertising because they’re made specifically to appeal to consumers, to make them relate to its essence. The mother usually applies oil to the daughter’s scalp, or some lotion on her skin, or they’re exchanging recipes because what else can mothers and daughters talk to each other about except skin care and cooking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our relationships with our mothers is not one only of careless laughter and light banter. It is the core love story of our lives till adulthood, and it is a burden and a duty. Thankfully, there exist refreshing counter narratives to the myth of motherhood that question the iconic status of motherhood in popular culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rituporno Ghosh’s &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt; is the story of Urmila (played by Aparna Sen) and Rohit Roy (played by Mithun Chakraborty) who were lovers in their youth. Urmila was married off at 20 to a tea estate manager, and Titli is their daughter. Blowing bubblegums and restlessly shaking her legs, the 17 year old Titli develops a massive crush on Rohit, who is now a Bollywood film star. In the beginning of the film, Titli is seen hovering around her mother, asking her to dress her up or put on a specific perfume. There is clear admiration and longing in her voice. This longing is something the myth dare not acknowledge; the physical envy between the mother and the daughter. While the daughter struggles through awkward breasts, menstruation and pimples, the mother is a graceful lady comfortable in her womanhood and her sexuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Titli wistfully asks her mother, “Ma, why can’t I marry someone 20 years older? Grandpa was 20 years older than Grandma. Was grandma unhappy?” Urmila casually replies, “My mother wouldn’t dream of asking her mother this question”, the conversation shows the shift between the mother-daughter dynamic over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a chance meeting, where Titli and Urmila meet Rohit, Titli learns of her mother’s past and the adoration she had changes to jealousy and malice. Titli can not bear that fact that prior to her, her mother had a romantic past. To her, this feels like an intense betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is seen in Ghosh’s film &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; (19th April), where the mother, Sarojini, a renowned classical dancer, is always elegantly dressed in sarees and jewelry. The daughter, Mithu, training to be a doctor, despises dressing up and covers herself in baggy t-shirts and long skirts. She holds the grief of her father’s death against her mother. Her grief makes her powerful, and in her eyes, a better person who &lt;em&gt;conforms&lt;/em&gt; to traditional norms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During her father’s funeral, the other female relatives of the house, while serving tea to guests also spill some gossip. “Sarojini is in Madras…or Mumbai. Who knows? If she wanted to become a famous dancer so badly, she should have just limited herself to that. Why would you marry and have a daughter as well?” There is a tinge of jealousy in this woman’s moralising; Sarojini is living the life she probably was too afraid to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, eighteen years later, on the father’s death anniversary, Sarojini receives a National award, which sets off a chain of reactions between her and Mithu. One can sense the constant ego tussle between the mother and the daughter, but the audience knows that this is due to miscommunication. When Mithu sits and cries in front of the telephone because her boyfriend has refused to marry her (because her mother is a dancer), Sarojini interprets this as her daughter’s jealousy towards her success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I loved the most about these films were their explorations into two important facets of the mother-daughter relationship: envy and miscommunication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt;, Urmila comes into Titli’s room to shut the windows as there is a storm raging outside. In the wind, her shawl falls off and Titli watches her mother’s body, clad in a strappy nightgown, and there is a distinct recognition of her mother as a sexual being in her eyes. She tells her mother, “Whatever idea I had of you, has changed after tonight.” This might seem like an emotionally exaggerated response, but it is something to think about. Why would there be such reluctance to accept the mother as a sexual being? The simple answer is because it makes us uncomfortable. Of course, these conversations are uncomfortable, but that’s verily why they are all the more necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mother is acceptable as long as she lives her life vicariously through others - her husband’s promotion, her son’s academic performance, but never her own achievements or her personal desires. Women’s sexuality is acceptable as long as it comfortably services a man within acceptable social customs. The daughter isn’t supposed to have any knowledge of her mother’s seductive charm. Titli realises she has crossed a line, and Urmila opens up to her about her past relationship. For the first time, they converse as equals. The film &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt; ends with the daughter requesting her mother to recite a poem she knew Urmila recited for Rohit. The envy has faded away, the lines of miscommunication have been bridged. We remember what Urmila had told Rohit during their meeting. “When Titli watches you, I watch her. For as long as she watches you, I watch her. When you fight villains on stage, she chews her gum faster. When you dance with your heroine, envy and anger cloud her face.” The audience realises what the film was always about: the love story between a mother and her daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; too, we have a similar reconciliation. Sarojini returns home to find Mithu has decided to commit suicide on the day of her father’s death, heartbroken by the rejection of her marriage proposal. The constant friction in their conversation fades away as Mithu breaks down and asks her mother “Why didn’t you ever ask me to join your dance class?” This is her deepest grievance, laid bare before us. All the intense tension between the two has been building up to this moment. Mithu never felt needed by her mother, and her way of coping was to immerse herself in books and be a doctor like her father. Sarojini, in between her sobbing, replies, “I did not understand you wanted to. I never asked, Mithu. I’m sorry.” The remarkable aspect of &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; is how Sarojini is unapologetic about her decisions. She offers an explanation for her actions but stands by them. In the end, we find Mithu writing her a prescription to help with her knee pain while Sarojini requests her to accompany her to Madras, to meet her dance guru, making an active effort to include her in her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers make mistakes. This is something mainstream culture refuses to accept. The standards motherhood is held to are unbelievably high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Gilmore Girls&lt;/em&gt;, Lorelai and Rory come across as sisters in the first scene. Rory is often the ‘mother’ in the relationship, asking Lorelai to think through practical decisions, consume a liquid that isn’t Luke’s coffee, and managing the intense drama between her grandmother Emily and her mother. Lorelai makes mistakes, but she makes a significant effort to acknowledge and make up for them. When Rory wanted to drop out of Yale and moved out to live with her grandparents, Lorelai and her get into a huge fight. However, when Rory reconsiders and rejoins Yale, and comes home to apologise, Lorelai says “I should have pulled you out of there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Greta Gerwig’s &lt;em&gt;Lady Bird&lt;/em&gt;, the only moment of peace is perhaps the beginning where Christine “Lady Bird” McPherson and her mother sleep on the same bed. Two minutes later in the movie, Lady Bird jumps out of moving car as her mother tells her, “You know, with your work ethic, you should probably go to City College, then to jail, then back to City College.” From the moment the movie starts, to its very end, their relationship is one of constant pushes and pulls. Her mother reminds her of their financial status when Lady Bird wants to buy a magazine, “that’s what rich people do, we’re not rich people.” When they’re in a thrift store, Lady Bird drags her feet and her mother says “Are you tired? I couldn’t really say, because you were dragging your feet”, to which Lady Bird replies “You are SO INFURIATING!” In the very next second her mother pulls out a dress which both of them begin gushing over, completely forgetting the argument. Lady Bird is fiercely individualistic, dramatic, driven, confident, but she struggles because she wants her mother to &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; her, so bad. You have to love Greta Gerwig for getting it so well. Lady Bird’s mother writes and throws away a dozen letters because she felt she would judge her writing capability. Envy and miscommunication again. This gap is bridged, when after getting super drunk after moving away to college, Lady Bird calls her mother to say, “I love you. Thank you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common thread that runs through &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lady Bird&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Gilmore Girls&lt;/em&gt;, connecting the stories across timelines and countries is a simple one: daughters want to feel validated and acknowledged by their mothers. However, these emotions of envy, jealousy, doubt, resentment and anger that our characters feel &lt;strong&gt;need&lt;/strong&gt; to be celebrated. Why? Because the myth of motherhood says unconditional love and care should come naturally. It makes no space for other healthy human emotions. Since our mothers are inherently programmed to want the best for us and see the best in us, there should be no conflict. These counter narratives show that this path towards a stable, loving relationship is not a linear one. It requires careful negotiation between power dynamics, emotions (of which, not all are pleasant) and effort, just like any other relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is rather unfortunate, even unfair, that we need a demythologising of the mother figure in popular culture in the first place. To put it reductively, I’m glad that women are finally telling their imperfect and messy stories. What we need is more of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ayantika Nath</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">If you’ve cringed at the Mother’s Day wishes that flooded social media a few weeks ago, which were basically variations of ‘she is the world’s smartest, strongest punching bag’, (go Leslie Knope!) you’ll probably see a valid point in what I have to discuss.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?</title><link href="/Greener-Pastures" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?" /><published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Greener-Pastures</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Greener-Pastures">&lt;p&gt;Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem absurd in general terms, how would you be an asset to a team that has already won? However, in politics, numbers are everything. If you defect to the majority, they increase their percentage points and maintain their majority. Each defector is like an additional layer of bubble wrap to the fragile glass of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a realist perspective, defection makes sense. If politics is all about power, then why would a politician willingly remain without any? At the end of the day, what good is ideological and partisan loyalty if you cannot make a dent in the political arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has a long (and borderline funny history) with defection. The phrase ‘&lt;em&gt;Aaya Ram, Gaya Ram&lt;/em&gt;’ (‘God came, God left’) was coined after an MP from the northern state of Haryana, Gaya Lal changed parties thrice on the same day in 1967. The period of continuous defections in the 1980’s is what led to the institution of the Anti-Defection Law in 1985 during the tenure of Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi’s government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anti-defection Law in India disqualifies members of the legislature under any one of the two conditions. Firstly, if they voluntarily give up membership of the party. And secondly, if they go against the party whip. The party whip is a command that comes from the party organisation, usually regarding which bills to pass and which to vote against. Interestingly enough, the first condition subsumes things other than simple resignation from the party. According to court judgments, the giving up of membership can be inferred from conduct. So, if a legislator was to speak against his party or in favour of the opposition, a case could be made against him against this law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many arguments against this law have been formulated in the past years. A major concern is the curbing of the freedom of expression. The defence to this freedom of expression argument is that differing opinions within parties leads to instability in the body politik. Just as defection makes sense for individual interest, the law makes sense for structural interests. However, at the end of the day, it means that if the legislator’s constituency is negatively affected by a certain policy or decision that his party is promoting, he doesn’t have the right to express dissent. The politician stands separated from his conscience. The second condition goes further to impair the legislator from taking any action or even abstaining to act for his party. Consent is dubious in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue was raised in the Supreme Court in 1992, to which it said, “the anti-defection law seeks to recognize the practical need to place the proprieties of political and personal conduct… above certain theoretical assumptions.” There is no right way of reacting when the apex court in your country calls the freedom of speech a “theoretical assumption”, but a bit of shock is valid. It is true that most cases of defection are about being on the winning team, about seeking out greener pastures. However, in situations such as post-poll alliances with an ideologically opposite party, the legislator must remain completely in favour of party decisions even at the cost of disappointing his constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stance of the court clearly states the assumption that the party is always right. While ideological compatibility is the basis for party formation, it is impossible for an entire party to have the same vision even under the same umbrella ideology. Many identities are embraced in a party and most of the times, these identities determine individual priorities. Denying a voice to any legislator goes directly against the spirit of democracy and multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this note, we can look into some of the structural and implemental loopholes that allow defection to continue despite the 1985 law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an exception that protects legislators from disqualification. If two-thirds of the legislators from a party agree to a “merger” with a different party, then this does not fall under the purview of the Anti-Defection Law. Using this loophole, 12 MLAs from the Congress party “merged” with the Telangana Rashtra Samithi, the ruling party in the southern state of Telangana, in June 2019. When read closely, the law provides this exception only when the original party merges with the party being defected to. Also, following certain court judgments, this decision of merger could only have been made by the All India Congress Committee and not the Telangana Pradesh Congress Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Presiding officer of the presiding party decides the verdict on defection cases. This officer is almost always a part of the ruling party. This means that defections &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party will be blocked but the ones &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party never will. Since the latter is the wave that defectors tend to ride, this provision effectively reduces the chances of defectors being disqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom, defection causes expulsion from the party but the legislator retains her seat. They are also only a result of defying a three-line party whip (the most urgent type of whip issued) as a sign of voluntarily giving up membership of the party. In Australia, some minor penalties such as barring of access to party resources is the punishment for defying party whips. It is the mildest in the USA where parties cannot expel their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark increase in defections paints a grim picture of political ethics in India. The Karnataka debacle, where Congress-JD(S) alliance MLAs defected to the BJP in the southern state after the party’s sweeping success in the national elections also reflects the blurred lines of the federal system of governance. 17 MLAs were disqualified after the incident in July 2019, allegations of bribery were thrown at the ruling party. The Indian Parliament’s upper house proceedings were repeatedly adjourned as Congress MPs demanded that the BJP government resign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only solution that seems to be in tandem with the political values that India’s Constitution embodies is that once there is defection to a new party, elections in that legislator’s constituency should be reheld. Admittedly this is a long and tedious process, but the provision might itself act as a deterrent for defection itself. There is a very small chance of a defector to be reelected by his people who most likely will hold feelings of betrayal and contempt for him. No legislator would want to face his constituency so soon after defecting. On the other hand, people would get a fair chance to elect someone with clear and full information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications relating to corruption have not even been discussed above as dissecting the role of money and muscle deserves a whole another article. However, it must be stated at least once that along with power, almost all defections involve promises of money and positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, welcome to the seven-decades old Indian democracy. Here, parties are oligarchic and legislators are for sale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Kalām Cosmological Argument for God’s Existence</title><link href="/Cosmological-Argument" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Kalām Cosmological Argument for God’s Existence" /><published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Cosmological-Argument</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Cosmological-Argument">&lt;p&gt;This is the first article that I have been privileged to write for &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt; on the existence of God. Some might be surprised at this. &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;,  after all, is not a philosophical quarterly. How is this relevant, some might say? To put it simply: in every way. This is an immensely relevant topic because the question of whether or not God exists is surely one of the most significant questions we can ask (in fact, I consider it the most significant). The answer we give to this question will inevitably impact the rest of our worldview as well as influence how we choose to live our lives. Not merely that, this article shall be a bit of an introduction to the field of natural theology: that branch of philosophy devoted to arguments for the existence of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we proceed further, a few disclaimers must be made. Here’s the first one: I am not claiming to provide &lt;em&gt;empirical&lt;/em&gt; evidence for God. Some people have quipped to me in the past, “Show me God, and I’ll believe in Him.” But this statement/challenge presupposes that God is an empirical entity that can be ‘shown’. But God is not an empirical entity; I would argue that He is immaterial and transcendent, not enclosed within space and time. As such, it is not possible for anyone to ‘show’ God to you. But empirical evidence is not the only valid source of knowledge. Logical and philosophical reasoning can play a crucial role too. In fact, the idea that only empirical observations are true sources of knowledge (also called Empiricism) is &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; not an empirical observation – it is rather a philosophical assertion, based upon (I imagine) some kind of inductive (probabilistic) reasoning. To claim that only empirical observations can be true sources of knowledge is by its very nature self-defeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this is an article tailored for a general audience, this article will not presuppose any prior philosophical or theological training. And thus, the argument that has been chosen for this paper is one of the simplest ones out there – the &lt;em&gt;Kalām&lt;/em&gt; Cosmological Argument. However, its simplicity does not imply a lack of strength – quite the contrary, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here’s the second disclaimer: this article is also not going to be extremely comprehensive. Yes, it will be to the point, but it is my hope to reach as broad an audience as I can. As such, the article will not be answering every possible objection that can be made to the argument; instead it will focus primarily on seeking to explain what it actually is rather than defend it in excruciating detail. Comprehensive defences of the argument have already been made by Christian philosophers and there is no need for a humble writer, such as myself, to add to the (quite frankly, saturated) bulk of scholarly literature that already exists on this subject. If you want to study deeper, look no further than Chapter 3 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wiley.com/en-us/The+Blackwell+Companion+to+Natural+Theology-p-9781444350852&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Blackwell Companion to Natural Theology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, one of the most elegantly argued natural theology textbooks of our time (though this present author does not agree with everything that is asserted in that work). Or you can look &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/writings/popular-writings/existence-nature-of-god/the-kalam-cosmological-argument/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for an exposition of the argument, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gtfVds8Kn4s&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for responses to the most popular objections that have been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of this article is to explain why God exists in as simple a manner as I possibly can. This will also give the reader an idea of how philosophical reasoning normally works and how classical theists have argued for the rationality of their faith in God. For, sadly, many of the popular YouTube ‘vlogs’ on the Kalām argument (usually made by posturing theatrical self-congratulatory millennials and other assorted hippies) clearly betray a pitiful lack of understanding of the argument itself, as well as the reasoning that runs through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is a third disclaimer, which may seem trivial, but which I feel must be made for the sake of conscience. While I heartily acclaim the argument itself, I do not endorse every aspect of the philosophy that has been put forward by some of its chief proponents. Particularly, I take issue with the philosopher William Lane Craig’s (one of the argument’s most vocal defenders) denial of God’s intrinsic immutability. However, this does not affect the core of the argument, and so there should be no issue in presenting it as is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, without further ado, let us get into the argument. It can be formulated as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P1.&lt;/strong&gt; Everything which begins to exist must have a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P2.&lt;/strong&gt; The universe began to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C1.&lt;/strong&gt; (From P1 and P2) Therefore, the universe must have a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P4.&lt;/strong&gt; If the universe has a cause, then an uncaused, Personal Creator of the universe exists, Who sans the universe is beginningless, changeless, immaterial, timeless, spaceless and enormously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C2.&lt;/strong&gt; (From C1 and P4) Therefore, an uncaused, Personal Creator of the universe exists, Who sans the universe is beginningless, changeless, immaterial, timeless, spaceless and enormously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we proceed, something very crucial in &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; must be pointed out. It is a common question, often posed by young internet atheists: “If everything which exists must have a cause, then what caused God?” However, this question misses the point of what we are saying. &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; say that &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; which exists must have a cause – rather, it simply asserts that &lt;em&gt;everything which &lt;strong&gt;begins&lt;/strong&gt; to exist&lt;/em&gt; must have a cause. On the face of it, the syllogism is extremely simple and straightforward. P1 is obviously true – or, at the very least, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/media/reasonable-faith-podcast/why-think-whatever-begins-to-exist-has-a-cause/&quot;&gt;it is far, far more probable than its alternative&lt;/a&gt;. As for &lt;strong&gt;P2&lt;/strong&gt;, it can be verified by philosophical arguments as well as scientific evidence. Notice also that the argument is what philosophers call a &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; argument – meaning that if the premises of the argument are true, the conclusion necessarily and inescapably follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the universe has a cause. But, some ask, why does this cause have to be God? Richard Dawkins, for instance, argues that there is no reason at all to believe that this universal cause (if It indeed exists) possesses the attributes that have been traditionally ascribed to It by Jewish, Christian and Muslim theologians. However, in this, Dawkins is thoroughly mistaken. The divine attributes have been rationally argued for and logically defended for centuries now, and they go back all the way &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; to Aristotle and Plotinus, philosophers who lived before the time of Christ and who – although they were neither Jews nor Christians in the formal sense of the term – did come up with a belief in a monotheistic God. It is therefore no wonder that Christian philosophers like St Thomas Aquinas took Aristotle with such enthusiasm (in fact, Catholic theology to this day makes use of Aristotelian terminology to describe spiritual realities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So, why does the Cause of the Universe have to be God?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument can be laid out as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, there must be an Ultimate Uncaused Cause of all things. In other words, we cannot postulate the existence of an infinite regress of causes (the idea that the Universe is caused by A, which is caused by B, which is caused by C… etc. all the way to infinity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosophers William Lane Craig and James D Sinclair offer a simple reason: the reason is that actual infinites cannot exist in reality. Actual infinites do enjoy mathematical existence, that is undeniable. However, mathematical existence does not necessarily equate to metaphysical existence, or existence in the real world. The great German mathematician David Hilbert himself observed, “The infinite is nowhere to be found in reality. It neither exists in nature nor provides a legitimate basis for rational thought… The role that remains for the infinite to play is solely that of an idea”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual infinites cannot exist in reality simply because, if they did, they would create insoluble absurdities. A good example of this is the famous paradox of Hilbert’s Hotel, an exposition of which you can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lobeX6ft6PA&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some, however, claim that infinites exist all around us. For example, they point to the fact that any given distance can be infinitely subdivided. However, here we must make the distinction Aristotle made between an actual and a potential infinite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An actual infinite is something which, to put it bluntly, is &lt;em&gt;actually infinite&lt;/em&gt; – that is, it is a completed infinite. For example, the set of all even numbers truly contains an infinite number of members. However, a potential infinite is quite different. It is anything which keeps increasing and which keeps moving towards infinity but which never actualizes or achieves infinity – it always remains an ever-increasing (or ever-decreasing) finitude. For example, the age of the universe which began to exist but which will never cease to exist in the future. The age would be increasing with every passing moment and be forever progressing towards infinity, but it would never actually reach infinity. It is the same with the example of a finite distance being potentially divisible infinitely. To quote Craig and Sinclair: “The only legitimate sense in which one can speak of the infinite is in terms of potentiality: something may be infinitely divisible or susceptible to infinite addition, but this type of infinity is potential only and can never be fully actualized”. So, “While one can continue indefinitely to divide conceptually any distance, the series of subintervals thereby generated is merely potentially infinite, in that infinity serves as a limit that one endlessly approaches but never reaches”. The same goes for time. “This is the thoroughgoing Aristotelian position on the infinite: only the potential infinite exists. This position does not imply that minimal time atoms, or chronons, exist. Rather time, like space, is infinitely divisible in the sense that division can proceed indefinitely, but time is never actually infinitely divided, neither does one arrive at an instantaneous point.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, when we seek to subdivide any given distance, we must remember that the distance we are seeking to divide is strictly finite – it is not infinite. We can keep dividing it for years and years if we please, but we will never actually reach an infinite number of divisions. At any given point in time, the number of divisions we will have created will still be finite, the size of each division will still be finite and the sum total of the divisions will still be what it originally was: the finite distance we set out to divide. We will never arrive at an actually infinite number of divisions; we will keep on moving towards the infinite without realising it. This is a &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; infinite, not an actual one. For more on the paradoxes related to the infinite, readers can refer to the Oxford philosopher A W Moore’s book &lt;em&gt;The Infinite&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, an actual infinite cannot exist in reality. This naturally implies that the regress of causes cannot be actually infinite; it must terminate in a First/Ultimate Cause. And this First/Ultimate Cause must naturally be Uncaused (otherwise, it would not be a First/Ultimate Cause). So, we have established the first premise of all monotheistic religion – that there is an Ultimate Uncaused Cause of all things. Let us continue with the divine attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the second place&lt;/em&gt;,  an Uncaused Cause must be beginning-less since everything which is uncaused has no beginning to it (we can derive this by contraposition of &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; of the original argument).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly&lt;/em&gt;, there is good reason to believe that the Entity is Immaterial and Timeless. This is powerfully suggested by the fact that it is, in fact, the cause of space and time (causation, it must be remembered, does not itself have to be temporal). But if the Entity is Itself the cause of space and time, it cannot itself be enclosed within space and time. Of course, this assertion itself probably doesn’t clinch the argument on its own. However, there are other arguments by other philosophers which have proven convincing to me that the Ultimate Cause is indeed immaterial and timeless. If you’re interested in reading up on this, refer to Chapters 1 and 3 of philosopher and former atheist Edward Feser’s book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs for the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;. However, since the Immateriality and Timelessness of the First Cause is not – strictly speaking – crucial to the core of the argument, we shall carry on without dwelling on it for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourthly&lt;/em&gt;, the Entity in question must possess enormous power, since it brought the entirety of the universe into existence quite literally from nothing. This is fairly straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifthly and finally&lt;/em&gt;, the Ultimate Cause of all Things must be Personal. This is the linchpin. Craig and Sinclair offer three arguments for this (though many, many more can be offered) in &lt;em&gt;The Blackwell Companion to Natural Theology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first place, as the Oxford philosopher Richard Swinburne notes, there are two types of causal explanations: “scientific explanations in terms of laws and initial conditions and personal explanations in terms of agents and their volitions”. For example, two answers can be given to the question, “Why is the kettle boiling?” We could say: “The heat of the flame is being conducted via the bottom of the kettle to the water, increasing the kinetic energy of the molecules such that they vibrate so violently that they break the surface tension of the water and are thrown off in the form of steam.” Or we could simply say: “I put the kettle on to make a cup of tea.” Both these explanations are true, and one does not necessarily exclude the other. However, one is scientific in nature; the other personal. The ‘First State of the Universe’ cannot have a scientific explanation, since there is nothing before it and it cannot, therefore, be accounted for in terms of laws operating on initial conditions. The only other explanation is in terms of an Agent and His volitions (the personal explanation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the Personhood of the Ultimate/First Cause also seems to follow from the other properties we have laid out in our argumentation. There are only two kinds of things which can be said to be uncaused, beginningless, timeless, spaceless and immaterial – either abstract objects or unembodied minds. However, abstract objects (like numbers for example, or things like roundness, redness, etc.) cannot cause anything at all – that’s part of what it means to be abstract. The only alternative that springs to mind is that of an Unembodied Mind. No other alternatives seem possible, and indeed none have been suggested so far by any major critic of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third argument begins by observing that while the cause is clearly eternal, the effect is not. But this seems strange. Is it not reasonable to expect that if the cause is eternal, the effect would also be co-eternal with it? And yet, we see that the effect only came to be a finite time ago, instead of forever existing side-by-side with its eternal cause, like a person and her shadow, or a subject and his/her reflection in the mirror. The easiest way out of this dilemma, Craig and Sinclair argue, is to accept that the Cause is Personal and Free. That way, it can be Eternal, while still being the cause of a temporal and finite effect. God simply chooses eternally to create a temporally finite world. This does not, of course, mean, that God “one day woke up and decided all upon a sudden to create the world”. No, that assertion is deeply problematic philosophically. Rather, the classical theist position is simply to assert that God eternally wills to create/cause the temporal universe. This decision is eternal (as would be expected if God is omniscient and immutable – though that is a topic for another day), but still, free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those were the arguments made by some of the mainstream philosophers. In addition, I would boldly venture a suggestion of my own. Although I myself lack the credentials of an Oxford don, the example I am about to give I have thought about for some time and – so far – have found no flaw in it. You could take it as a personal insight, which is not too different from Swinburne’s argument described in point one above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example is that of a stone. A stone is an inanimate object. It can never think nor freely chose to do things. This means that it cannot do anything at all unless external forces act upon it. If a stone comes flying through the air and hits you on the head, you can legitimately say, “The stone has hit me!” But because the stone is inanimate (it can neither think nor take free will decisions of its own), you must also recognize that it did not hit you by its own strength or power or will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if there is indeed an Ultimate/First Cause of all things, then it must be animate/living, personal, conscious and endowed with free will. Otherwise, it could not do (or, to be more accurate, cause) anything on its own unless external forces acted upon it – much like the stone. However, the Ultimate/First Cause has no such forces to rely upon – that is precisely &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it is the Ultimate/First Cause to begin with! Therefore, Personhood and Freedom of the Will seem inescapable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in a nutshell, is the Kalām Cosmological Argument. It is a very old argument, having roots in the Islamic tradition, but it has recently been popularised by philosopher of religion William Lane Craig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is up to you, dear reader, at the end of the day to judge whether or not the argument is sound. You must do your own research and make up your own mind. But even if you ultimately disagree, I hope you can at least see that the Classical Theist philosophical tradition is nothing like what it is so often made out to be by the New Atheists and their enthusiastic YouTube supporters. Al-Ghazali, Aquinas, Anselm, Aristotle, Augustine, Bonaventure, Scotus – these were not like the illiterate country bumpkins they are so often made out to be. They were brilliant and careful thinkers. Centuries later, their insights still remain true and science has, in fact, confirmed many of their philosophical deductions (for example: al-Ghazali argued centuries ago, on the basis of philosophical argumentation, that time is finite; modern cosmology largely seems to have vindicated him). If you want to see how the argument holds up in the context of debate, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0tYm41hb48o&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9JVRy7bR7zI&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I hope has become obvious, although I have peppered this article with hyperlinks that will prove useful to you, I have not taken it upon myself to answer every question or refute every objection. There are others who have done that and this article has already exceeded 3,000 words. You’ll have to be satisfied with this much for now, at least from me. Plus, since this is an extremely provocative topic, what better way to end it than with a provocative and cliff-hanging conclusion?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">This is the first article that I have been privileged to write for The Pangean on the existence of God. Some might be surprised at this. The Pangean, after all, is not a philosophical quarterly. How is this relevant, some might say? To put it simply: in every way. This is an immensely relevant topic because the question of whether or not God exists is surely one of the most significant questions we can ask (in fact, I consider it the most significant). The answer we give to this question will inevitably impact the rest of our worldview as well as influence how we choose to live our lives. Not merely that, this article shall be a bit of an introduction to the field of natural theology: that branch of philosophy devoted to arguments for the existence of God.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Examining The Motivations of The Premier Mixed Martial Arts Organisation and Its Charismatic Leader - The UFC and Dana White</title><link href="/UFC-Dana-White" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Examining The Motivations of The Premier Mixed Martial Arts Organisation and Its Charismatic Leader - The UFC and Dana White" /><published>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/UFC-Dana-White</id><content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-Dana-White">&lt;p&gt;From its realisation in 1993 to where we are now in 2019, the Ultimate Fighting Championship has been a pioneer and market leader in Mixed Martial Arts promotion. Founded by David Isaacs alongside owner Bob Meyrowitz, the UFC was created on the ideals of joining together the top martial artists in a no holds barred tournament to determine which of them possessed the more superior skills in combat. The immediate attraction of the UFC was evident. Marketed as a ‘No Rules’ event, it gave casual combat sports fans a chance to experience a more brutal and raw form of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the apparent barbarism of the sport caused major issues with the governing bodies across America, who threatened to cancel cable coverage of the UFC. It became quickly apparent to Meyrowitz that the company was not sustainable and that drastic action was required in order to save it from going under. This led to Dana White, along with Frank and Lorenzo Fertitta, purchasing the UFC for $2 million in 2001, in a deal that was done more out of passion than logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under their guidance, the UFC has grown into what we know it as now; a multi-billion dollar fight promotion that contains some of the highest level fighters on show in MMA. Thanks to the work of Dana White and the Fertittas, we have witnessed the development of names such as Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Anderson Silva to name but a few. Whilst these names have shaped the modern landscape of mixed martial arts, the line between what is beneficial to the fighters in terms of business and what is good for the promotion has become blurred. Obscurity within the sport has grown increasingly since its conception but recent incidents such as the cutting of top ranked female fighter Cris Cyborg from the organisation have left us to question exactly what image Dana White is attempting to portray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyborg has always been regarded as a pioneer of women’s MMA and, despite her recent brutal loss to Amanda Nunes, she had rejoined championship conversation after her latest victory over Felicia Spencer at UFC 240. What made her exit from the UFC even more confusing was her vocalised desire to have a rematch with Nunes after she was previously criticised by Dana White for being afraid of ‘The Lioness’. While the feud between Cyborg and White has certainly been far from a private matter for some time now, it still seems a strange business move from the President of the company, as a rematch with Nunes would no doubt be a pay-per-view success if their last bout is anything to go by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an interview on his Tuesday Night Contender series, Dana White responded to questions about Cyborg by stating “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mmafighting.com/2019/8/7/20757450/morning-report-dana-white-goes-after-cris-cyborg-dealing-with-her-has-been-a-nightmare&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dealing with her has been a nightmare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” (in regard to her past use of steroids and apparent avoidance of fights). Furthermore, the controversy surrounding Cyborg and White’s relationship was brought to a climax when an edited video released by Cyborg’s team after UFC 240 showed White apparently confessing to Cyborg about lying to the media in relation to her desire to rematch Amanda Nunes. Cyborg has since apologised on behalf of her team. It is clear that the divide between what the fighters deem as good business for them and what the promotion sees as good business has widened exponentially, with more and more fighters it seems disagreeing with their treatment within the company. Notable examples in the past include disagreements between White and Al Iaquinta over the allocation of fighter bonuses. Speaking to Ariel Helwani, Iaquinta criticised White’s comments about the fight card after he claimed that the highlight of his night was his plane ride home. Iaquinta went on a verbal rant stating that White has no idea of the fighter’s struggle when they step into the cage, mentioning injuries and the obvious risk each fighter takes when he or she enters the octagon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has never shied from voicing his opinions, arguing that “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KLNlIWupLlc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;the guys who are complaining about this stuff are the guys that don’t matter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;”. Here we can see an outlying trait of the UFC as a promotion; it’s focus is primarily on the big names, which opens up the argument of fighters being neglected the further down the roster they are placed. If we take a look at the average money made by UFC fighters last year, the median figure excluding bonuses and sponsorships came to $68,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when we consider that these fighters risk their wellbeing every time they step into the cage to fight, it seems surprising that this figure is not higher. It is also vital to consider the recovery time for a fighter after an event as sponsorships can only support so much of a fighters income. For instance, after his all out war with Robbie Lawler at UFC 189, Rory Macdonald was out of competition for almost a year due to injury, and received a payout of $139,000 ($59,000 to show, $50,000 performance of the night bonus and $30,000 Reebok sponsorship). For a sport that can bring about life changing injuries for fighters, it has to be questioned why pay for the majority is so low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particularly shocking incident of pay disparity occured at UFC 157. The main card featured a bantamweight match-up between Urijah Faber and Ivan Menjivar, in which Faber won the bout via submission in the first round. Faber walked out of the Honda Center that night having pocketed a comfortable $100,000 including a $50,000 submission of the night bonus. His opponent on the other hand earned a meager $17,000 for his time. Such a gap in pay is astonishing considering both fighters put themselves at equal risk every time they fight. Other fighters on the undercard that night earned as little as $8,000, truly highlighting the shocking divide between those at the top of the sport and the lesser known fighters who risk just as much as those making the big bucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cause of controversy in White’s organisation was the sponsorship deal made with Reebok in 2015 in an effort to “structure athletes’” income outside of fights’. The deal meant that fighters who had previously been sponsored by a variety of companies would no longer be able to receive sponsorship income outside of Reebok. The promise of increased income fell short and Vitor Belfort even compared the deal to “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/andrewbrennan/2016/05/16/is-it-the-ufc-or-is-it-reebok-that-is-exploiting-ufc-fighters-and-condoning-pay-gaps/#705809f24a93&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;living in slavery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” in his post-fight interview at UFC 198. During an interview on The Cruz Show, when questioned about the fighters’ discrepancies with the Reebok deal, White accused fighters of being “short-sighted”, arguing there had previously been a lack of professionalism from fighters who frequently appeared at weigh-ins with unsponsored underwear. Considering the vast sums of money fighters have lost as a result of the deal, it is evident that that the promotion’s care does not lie with the livelihoods of its fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that White has an inability to provide a cohesive response for his fighters’ doubts, often falling back on simply criticising the fighters as people, as shown in the aforementioned interview. White blasted ex-fighter Brendan Schaub after he criticised his business management tactics, saying “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportsjoe.ie/mma/dana-white-brendan-schaub-168046?utm_content=bufferb81e1&amp;amp;utm_medium=Social+organic&amp;amp;utm_source=Twitter&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Buffer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What the f&lt;/em&gt;** does this idiot know about the sport or the business*&lt;/a&gt;”, with Schaub immediately pointing out that White himself has never been involved in an MMA bout so by default cannot know what is best for the fighters. Schaub has long stood on the side of wanting to see White gone from the organisation, citing his own experience as a fighter for the UFC on his Below The Belt Podcast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportsjoe.ie/mma/brendan-schaub-dana-white-ufc-168769&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’ve been in that exact same scenario where you’re working your ass off to fight another man in a cage and you’re looking for some sort of approval from the head guy who controls your destiny who controls what match-ups you get, who controls how much publicity you get, who controls now what sponsors you get, who controls how much success you’re going to have&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a promoter it is White’s job to be capable of building up his fighters confidence alongside being able to sell the fights. If White continues to talk down to his fighters the way he currently does, then it is likely we will see fighters seek opportunities in other promotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an aggressive backlash from an ex-fighter would be a clear indicator that White’s leadership isn’t supported wholeheartedly. However, unfortunately, without Dana White, the UFC would not be the powerhouse promotion it is today and it does not look likely that White will be going anywhere anytime soon. It is evident that the key motivation for the organisation is financial and global growth, championed by the mindset of Dana White. In future we can hope to see a more equal pay bracket for those who risk their wellbeing by fighting in the octagon. However, due to the current atmosphere of the promotion and the longevity of Dana White’s career as president, whether or not this revised pay bracket will come to fruition is too difficult to predict unless some form of fighters union were to be formed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Eakin</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="mma" /><summary type="html">From its realisation in 1993 to where we are now in 2019, the Ultimate Fighting Championship has been a pioneer and market leader in Mixed Martial Arts promotion. Founded by David Isaacs alongside owner Bob Meyrowitz, the UFC was created on the ideals of joining together the top martial artists in a no holds barred tournament to determine which of them possessed the more superior skills in combat. The immediate attraction of the UFC was evident. Marketed as a ‘No Rules’ event, it gave casual combat sports fans a chance to experience a more brutal and raw form of action.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toronto Got Its One Dance, Is There More?</title><link href="/Raptors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toronto Got Its One Dance, Is There More?" /><published>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Raptors</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Raptors">&lt;p&gt;Drake references aside, Toronto finally got over the hump by completing the impossible (defeating the juggernaut team from the Bay), made possible by a preseason acquisition and the emergence of a reliable forward: Pascal Siakam. Despite the success of last season and playing in a weak/top-heavy conference, the Raptors will need to survive the trade deadline without losing any major pieces and receive strong playoff performances from Siakam, Van Fleet and Lowry to have a shot at repeating a championship run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest offseason move for Toronto was a subtraction, rather than an addition - the loss of Kawahi Leonard in free agency. Upper management of the Raptors front office knew that this huge off-season transaction to receive Leonard, preceding the 2018-2019 season, could be a one-year rental, as Leonard has openly expressed his desire to play close to Los Angeles for the past three seasons. Despite this, the Raptors pulled the trigger and were willing to come to terms with the large possibility that this would be a one-year lease. The lease worked, reeling in the franchise’s first Larry O’Brien Trophy; however, they must now move forward without a perennial superstar. A core consisting of Gasol, Van Fleet, Siakam, Lowry, and Ibaka has the power to make the playoffs in a weak Eastern Conference, but with expiring contracts and the aforementioned lack of a star, Toronto will need a lot of external help to repeat last year’s success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see how the team looks come the trade deadline because of these expiring contracts and the strong internal urge from several front office officials to push the reset button and begin the rebuilding process. Doing so will allow the Raptors to gain a little compensation back from players, such as Gasol or Ibaka, who no longer fill the void of being roster centerpieces, but rather are being seen and used as role players. These players could reel in sizeable amounts of young talent from teams in contention who are looking for one more piece from a mid-season pick-up to push them over the hump. Although this could set Toronto up for seasons to come, doing so would effectively end their chances of being a real contender for the championship this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young bucks Siakam and Van Fleet took tremendous strides last season and are now pivotal pieces to the future of Toronto’s franchise. Siakam reeled in the NBA’s Most Improved Player of the year, while Van Fleet put on a complete show during the Finals. A large portion of Toronto’s future success and direction depends directly on the play and development of these two young players. If they continue to build on last season’s performance, the future of Toronto’s core looks extremely bright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Toronto’s chances of repeating as NBA Champions seem to be relatively thin, anything can happen in a league that has undergone so many physical and emotional changes this offseason. As long as player development continues within Toronto’s young core, and the front office refrains from hitting the reset button at the trade deadline, Toronto will be in the picture to come out of the Eastern Conference next summer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gavin Olson</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="basketball" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">Drake references aside, Toronto finally got over the hump by completing the impossible (defeating the juggernaut team from the Bay), made possible by a preseason acquisition and the emergence of a reliable forward: Pascal Siakam. Despite the success of last season and playing in a weak/top-heavy conference, the Raptors will need to survive the trade deadline without losing any major pieces and receive strong playoff performances from Siakam, Van Fleet and Lowry to have a shot at repeating a championship run.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Stoic’s Path to Happiness</title><link href="/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Stoic’s Path to Happiness" /><published>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness">&lt;p&gt;Call it an endless string of experiences or a series of vivid sensations of the world around, we are all suffering from a mysterious condition, called life or existence. Existence is difficult to define in objective terms. One can only derive a vague understanding of existence through the complex fabric of encounters and experiences that shape how we see the world. But does one’s myopic and vague understanding stop one from expressing one’s subjective take on the matter? Certainly not. Discussions on existence have permeated through the history of humankind. Myriad answers have been proposed and rejected over the years but a solitary troubling question has remained unchanged: what is the best way to live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the peculiar existential ‘situatedness’ that is exclusive to every individual, there remains one universal narrative that has seemed to establish its grip on everyone. An idea that has been passionately explored by myriad traditions of the past and the present – life is suffering; a meld of ephemeral pleasures and perpetual despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The murky river of existence, to which we are eternally stuck, is, well, doomed. With every meandering turn it inflicts painful blows, pulverises hopes and leaves us in a state of absolute despondence and melancholia. Sorrow is inextricably linked to existence. Sorrow stems from attachments and poisons our lives; an idea deeply rooted in Buddhist philosophy. This realisation itself is sufficient to make a person depressed for the rest of his life, knowing that whatever he does shall in no way improve his dull existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much deliberation went into the matter, in response to which a Greek man proposed his own tenets to lead a joyful life. This later took the form of a full-fledged school of thought called &lt;em&gt;Stoicism&lt;/em&gt;. Far removed from other philosophies, that expound obscure esoteric questions pertaining to the metaphysics or epistemology of existence, stoicism employs the Socratic approach to discuss practical issues which have a direct bearing on the lives of common people. The idea was to search for the best means to lead a happy life, in the face of the pandemonium that had descended over the political landscape of the Hellenistic period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our tale begins with a sailing merchant by the name of Zeno who, after surviving a major shipwreck, ends up in the city of Athens. During his stay, he visited a bookstore which proved to be the turning point of his life. That was the day he was introduced to the philosophy of Socrates. Fascinated by his findings, Zeno decided to pursue his newly developed interest in philosophy and asked the librarian to suggest a teacher who could guide him. The librarian recommended a man named Crates, who, for the coming years, instructed Zeno on the idea of Cynicism; an outgrowth of Socratic thought. A passionate student, Zeno studied not only Cynicism but also other schools of thought that prevailed during that time. This equipped him with the ability to understand the world through multiple lenses, and much later helped him develop a theory of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Cynicism exposed Zeno to a brand new world of naturalistic existence, one that defied all societal norms, it didn’t quite resonate with his own personal beliefs. After all who would want to lie around, naked in broad daylight, disturbing everybody passing by, like the cynic Diogenes? Dissatisfied with whatever knowledge he had acquired so far, he decided to part ways with the school and set out on a new journey. Zeno took up teaching. He lectured pupils on his own precepts, in the middle of the city, which actually turned out to be quite successful. Several students flocked to the beautiful building of Stoa Poikile, to hear their great teacher speak. It is here that the foundations of Stoicism were finally laid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Zeno remains a major player in our story, he isn’t the only one. Several other intellectuals also subscribed and greatly contributed to the doctrine. These thinkers included greats such as Seneca, Marcus Aurelius and Epictetus. They, together with Zeno, spoke in great detail about the various facets of Stoicism. Here, I’ll be discussing aspects of Stoic ethics that surprisingly enough remain relevant till date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that is studied in Ethics today has a very direct connection with the ideas that were propounded by these thinkers. Stoic ethics mainly investigated happy existence and the conditions required to reach that state. The aim is to end suffering and live in harmony with nature. So, how did they achieve it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core of Stoic ethics lies the idea of &lt;em&gt;Oikeiosis&lt;/em&gt;, loosely translating to orientation. Every living thing in the world has a basic constitution, assigned to it by the natural order. For animals it is self-preservation, but in the case of humans, the oikeiosis is much greater as it involves our extraordinary ability to reason. Thus stoicism takes into account our primitive behaviour along with the potentiality to transcend it, since to be rational one is required to step out of the realm of primitive desires. It ascribes greater importance to the actions that are motivated by reason rather than animalistic desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very simple doctrine of the Stoics, from which one can derive a massive life lesson is that one needs to make a demarcation between things that fall under one’s control and things which don’t. All that is external to us is, quite naturally, in a state of chaos and something that’s independent of us. We can’t impose ourselves on the mechanisms of nature which remain outside the clutches of our will. However, we can change our perspectives and actions towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it. In a brief session of introspection, we can easily discern that our lives are stranded between regrets of the past and fears of the future. All that stoicism asks is - why give a damn? To be Stoic is to remain indifferent to whatever lies beyond you. And it is when you become indifferent that you begin to act out of reason rather than passion. The Stoics may as well be dubbed the Buddhists of the western tradition, in some respects. Their ethics have a striking resemblance to the 2nd noble truth of the Buddha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever something bothers you, stop a second and ask - “Can I change this situation?” If yes, then strive towards that change otherwise be unfazed by it. This might seem difficult at first but if this little ritual of interrupting negativity is followed, life can transform drastically. The key is to halt expectations and to be at peace with oneself. In the words of Marcus Aurelius:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you work at that which is before you, following right reason seriously, vigorously, calmly, without allowing anything else to distract you, but keeping your divine part pure, as if you were bound to give it back immediately; if you hold to this, expecting nothing, but satisfied to live now according to nature, speaking heroic truth in every word that you utter, you will live happy. And there is no man able to prevent this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understand stoicism as a philosophy that prepares you to face the bitter truths of life, without getting affected. It engineers you in a manner such that you can’t help but walk a virtuous path. It imparts the lesson that one must moderate one’s desires and emotions by employing reason, untouched by the highs and lows of life. Stoicism values self-control and an acceptance of whatever comes one’s way. Above all, however, stoicism is about empowering the ‘ruler within you.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that in the 21st century, the age of despair and silenced voices, humans are drawn towards a philosophy which can offer them tranquillity and order. Ours is a generation being pulled by desire with a force we can’t resist. We end up either letting go of the reins of control, becoming slaves to our passions, or fretting over situations which we can’t possibly control. It, therefore, becomes imperative to adopt Stoicism, because honestly, what is a life without happiness? Stoicism is the emancipatory force to guide us towards the path of a more fulfilled and joyful existence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Call it an endless string of experiences or a series of vivid sensations of the world around, we are all suffering from a mysterious condition, called life or existence. Existence is difficult to define in objective terms. One can only derive a vague understanding of existence through the complex fabric of encounters and experiences that shape how we see the world. But does one’s myopic and vague understanding stop one from expressing one’s subjective take on the matter? Certainly not. Discussions on existence have permeated through the history of humankind. Myriad answers have been proposed and rejected over the years but a solitary troubling question has remained unchanged: what is the best way to live?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Hayao Miyazaki Sees The Beauty in The Mundane</title><link href="/Beauty-In-The-Mundane" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Hayao Miyazaki Sees The Beauty in The Mundane" /><published>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Beauty-In-The-Mundane</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-In-The-Mundane">&lt;p&gt;One of the most enjoyed and oft-recounted anecdotes about Hayao Miyazaki- filmmaker, manga author, animator and co-founder of Japan’s Studio Ghibli- is his tussle with Hollywood’s now infamous mascot of predatory behaviour, Harvey Weinstein. Originally printed in &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;, the story runs thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Harvey Weinstein, one of Hollywood’s most belligerent producers, received a samurai sword in the post because his reputation preceded him. It came with a note that said simply: “No cuts.” By 1997, Weinstein’s Miramax Company had been taken over by Disney, which had a distribution deal with Japanese animation revolutionaries Studio Ghibli.  Weinstein became one of Hollywood’s most powerful producers by acquiring and ruthlessly cutting films to make them as commercial as possible. Fearing his masterpiece Princess Mononoke would be butchered, director and animator Hayao Miyazaki sent Weinstein the sword with the note advising him not to do it.
[….]” I did go to New York to meet this man, this Harvey Weinstein, and I was bombarded with this aggressive attack, all these demands for cuts. I defeated him.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to unpack in this tale. Obviously, it carries all the red flags that would later come to be associated with Weinstein. It is an amusing snippet of a battle between two of the biggest names in the global filmmaking industry. But more poignantly, it is, perhaps, a real-life enactment of Miyazaki’s favourite story to tell in each of his works: the desire to preserve a rapidly fading simplicity, which has its roots in a kind of psycho-emotional-cultural nostalgia, but which also faces the risk of obliteration by the hideous tide of forced Western assimilation and glitzy consumerism that Japanese culture and media faces to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I defeated him. No cuts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he is often popularly addressed by the epithet &lt;em&gt;Walt Disney of Japan&lt;/em&gt;,  I have personally always disliked this particular comparison between the animators, each a legend in his own right. That is because Studio Ghibli, the Tokyo-based animation house that is often described as Disney’s whimsical Japanese twin in many ways, acts more like a foil as opposed to a mere Eastern counterpart of the former. Where Disney seeks to impress with the opulence of scale and blissfully escapist glamour (think bewitchingly beautiful princesses, operatic songs, almost demonic villains), Ghibli seeks out what’s relatable even in the extraordinary, tries to make a mark in more subtle ways, not through escapism but through its polar opposite really, through well-crafted realism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, if you ask someone to tell you what the best part is about Ghibli films, nine out of ten times the answer will inevitably end up being, either the delightfully animated technicolour food or the painstakingly drawn verdant landscapes of some sort of quasi-utopian, Kyoto countryside-meets-wonderland realm, peopled with mythical beasts and bizarre spirits. Or perhaps it might just be the underlying extended allegories of ethnic traditions and a love for environmentalism, which seeps through pretty much every Ghibli film in the past two and a half decades. Whatever it is, one thing stands out in crystal-sharp clarity: Miyazaki’s philosophy centres not around grandiose but around the mundane, which he moulds to his own liking through the most skillful blending of cinematic, emotive and artistic devices till the ordinary is idyllic and the commonplace enchanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what constitutes the Hayao Miyazaki school of thought, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his informative visual essay, &lt;em&gt;The Immersive Realism of Studio Ghibli&lt;/em&gt;,  video journalist Asher Isbruker chalks out the main reasons as to why Miyazaki’s creations feel so disarmingly familiar and relevant, despite some of them being as displaced from reality as most of our childhood bedtime tales. “No matter how far-fetched and imaginary [is] the story,” Isbruker emphasizes, “the world of a Ghibli film consistently feels tactile and realistic.” To prove his point, he cites the example of the 2001 Academy Award winning film &lt;em&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/em&gt;, directed and written by Miyazaki. The film revolves around Chihiro, a young human girl forced to work as a servant in a bathhouse frequented and operated by the most incredible array of ghosts and spirits. She does so in an effort to save her parents, who - courtesy of a whirlwind series of unfortunate events - have been turned into pigs by a malevolent witch. While you stop to reread and completely understand that sentence, it is worthwhile to take a look at what Isbruker says about world-building in the film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…the bathhouse feels alive and real. While it is inherently unbelievable, we believe it exists in the context of the world (of the film) because it’s so well established. There are employees with jobs to do, sleeping quarters, a coal-powered furnace that heats the baths, different kinds of soaps for different clients… If you followed another employee, what would their day be like? That’s fun to imagine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting that in a story bristling with absolutely wild events (a river becomes a dragon, the dragon becomes a boy, a witch ‘steals’ the names of her employees, thus rendering them disoriented, a faceless spirit materialises gold coins by clenching his fist) what sticks out as the most endearing bits are the little, uncharted moments that could have easily been from any slice-of-life indie film: waking up alone in an unfamiliar room to the view of an ocean, menial-labour employees gathering at the end of the day on a balcony to wistfully share their future plans of moving to the big city where prospects are better, two young children eating rice cakes in a garden full of spring flowers, the simple beauty of a wide-angle animated shot, downpour on the streets of a ghost-town. Nothing grand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isbruker also speaks of the very specific attention Miyazaki devotes to details as unostentatious as personalising the action of running in different characters. “Movement must be used to convey a sense of relative scale and weight,” he says. “Ghibli not only accomplishes this with grace but also conveys the emotions and traits of their characters through attention to minute details of their behaviour.” Instead of using technical shortcuts like pre-generated run cycles or rotoscoping (tracing live action footage), the veteran director and his animating team painstakingly created different patterns of movement to suit the circumstances and motives of every character, major or minor, be it the swift catlike sprint of wild, mountain-bred San and her horde of wolves from &lt;em&gt;Princess Mononoke&lt;/em&gt; (1997), the giddy, happy, flighty run of the innocent Kusakabe sisters joyfully exploring their new house in &lt;em&gt;My Neighbour Totoro&lt;/em&gt; (1988) or the comical, laboured struggles of the young witch from &lt;em&gt;Kiki’s Delivery Service&lt;/em&gt; (1989) to mount an enchanted broom. These details, seemingly unimportant, embellish and enrich the Ghibli cinematic experience, attesting yet again to the importance of the &lt;em&gt;extraordinary&lt;/em&gt;, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is food. Even those not well acquainted with that particular brand of Japanese animation are largely familiar with the mouth-watering, aesthetically pleasing scenes of food in every single Ghibli film. When we think of a retelling of &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, food is not the first thing that comes to mind. Yet, it is the most enduring motif in &lt;em&gt;Ponyo On the Cliff&lt;/em&gt; (2008), Miyazaki’s lightest, brightest film yet. The most iconic scene in his take on Hans Christian Andersen’s Danish fairytale is a simple, homely scene of little importance plot-wise, where Lisa, the mother of Ponyo’s human companion Sōsuke, prepares a wholesome meal for her; ham and a bowl of steaming ramen noodles. It is a slow, drowsy scene, right after an extended, fatiguing driving sequence through the storm; the warmth and gastronomic aspect of it feel deliciously homely. Not just &lt;em&gt;Ponyo&lt;/em&gt;, who can forget the enchanted buffets of &lt;em&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/em&gt;, the mouth-watering Bento boxes from &lt;em&gt;Totoro&lt;/em&gt;, or the eggs-and-bacon breakfast scene in &lt;em&gt;Howl’s Moving Castle&lt;/em&gt; (2004)? None of these movies are wanting for magic and mischief, conflicts and adventures, yet what we take back at the end of the film are these small, humane moments of nurture and domesticity, opportunities to forge reel-to-real kinship with the protagonists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we speak of Ghibli food and Ghibli landscapes, we cannot avoid the underlying theme that Miyazaki strives to emphasise in his craft: romanticising the ordinary and trying to achieve a sense of balance between the magical extravaganzas of spirit-infested bathhouses and flying castles and benevolent cat-bear tree deities. One of Ghibli’s favourite tropes to use is the incomplete or unexplained aspects of its multilayered, kaleidoscopic universes. We are given rich tapestries of magical worlds- enchanted forests, prehistoric oceans, deserted valleys and idyllic small towns, with creatures and people unlike any of our own- but not all of it revealed through exposition, just enough to make us already familiar with, aware of the sensory experience we’re being thrust into. It definitely helps that Miyazaki prefers to work with young, starry-eyed protagonists for most of his films- it helps to convey a sense of newness and wonder at the good in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A section of critics have theorised that Miyazaki’s repeated emphasis on the synthesis of human-nature relationships, traditional and sustainable ways of living versus technology and economic progress, the portrayal of largely pacifist protagonists, ambiguous and somewhat redeemable antagonists, and anti-war motifs have much to do with Hayao Miyazaki’s personal experiences during the Second World War, particularly the 1945 bombings of Utsunomiya. “The characters who pursue war — generally government officials — are portrayed as vainglorious and arrogant schemers who rashly court cataclysm for the sake of their grandiose ambitions,” writes Dan Sanchez in his essay &lt;em&gt;Miyazaki’s Beautiful Anti War Dreams&lt;/em&gt;, while also noting that Miyazaki allows for even such seemingly irredeemable paragons of wickedness their moments to redeem themselves. “The climax of the film comes not with the hero impaling or detonating his foe, as in so many Hollywood movies, or in the villain falling to his doom, as in so many Disney animated films. Miyazaki’s heroes achieve victory, not through the destruction of their enemies, but by foiling their plans enough such that the belligerents finally relent …. sometimes even …. to the point of converting villains into friends.” He adds, “…. (Although) Tolkien’s &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; is a profound meditation on the corruption of power, its discussion of war and peace is crudely Manichean. Yet on this subject, and so many others, the fantasy of Studio Ghibli — &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; the work of the creative genius Hayao Miyazaki— is wise and deeply moral, as well as exhilarating and achingly beautiful. It is a cultural treasure that stands and soars in a class of its own.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others note that Miyazaki might have been significantly influenced by the ethno-Japanese &lt;em&gt;Shinto&lt;/em&gt; ideology, which attaches great importance to the worship of &lt;em&gt;kami&lt;/em&gt;: the sacred presence that manifests itself everywhere in nature, from rocks to rivers to forests to the creatures that dwell in them. The sacredness and fragility of the Shinto balance is well portrayed in one of Miyazaki’s earliest and most powerful works, &lt;em&gt;Nausicaä of the Valley of Wind&lt;/em&gt; (1984), where the titular protagonist Nausicaä battles fascist forces to establish harmony between the human world and the ancient creatures of the forest- dangerous, insect-like beasts called Ohms- even as Earth teeters on the brink of apocalypse. &lt;em&gt;Mononoke&lt;/em&gt; deals with the same ordeal, when the forest gods are disturbed as their homes are destroyed by an industrial settlement that derives resources from hacking down the pristine mountain foliage. These may sound rather far-fetched in theory, but with the skill that only a Ghibli animator can demonstrate, Miyazaki spreads his messages in a beautiful art-on-celluloid format, preferring to concentrate, as always, more on the ordinary than the other-worldly; not the rampages, or the grand battles, but the lives at the centre of the crossfire between enemies, at the motivations of every character, princess or chieftain or sailor or just a small-town boy with big dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of Miyazaki’s movies come laden with ladles of fantasy, however. &lt;em&gt;Whisper of the Heart&lt;/em&gt; (1995), written by him, is a heart-warming, lush take on childhood and childish dreams, yearning, hoping, loving and losing, all embodied in the very non-fantastic and yet endearing host of characters, especially Shizuku, the 14 year old, book-smart, imaginative protagonist. It is in these understated and realistic films, that could easily be swapped for live-action works, that Miyazaki’s touch works the best. For it is here that you get to see the legacy of Studio Ghibli. How everything becomes dreamy and magical with just the right dose of attention and love, with just the exact dollops of childish whimsy and adult musings to balance each other out. As Isbruker says, “Pay attention to the ordinary, the inconsequential, seemingly unimportant actions and elements … every single one was a conscious choice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We depict hatred, but it is to depict that there are more important things. We depict a curse, to depict the joy of liberation,” says Miyazaki himself. He goes on to talk about the joys of hand-drawn animation, “When I think about the way the computer has taken over and eliminated a certain experience of life, that makes me sad. When we were animating fire some staff said they had never seen wood burning. I said, “Go watch!” It has disappeared from their daily lives. Japanese baths used to be made by burning firewood. Now you press a button. I don’t think you can become an animator if you don’t have any experience.” His words bring us full-circle- the Harvey Weinstein episode, the chronicle of the samurai sword, no cuts … a testament to a mind as fresh and transcendental as it was during his first endeavour, a staunch refusal to bow to artificialities and be a cheap copy of the West. No more being the Walt Disney of Japan, thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The celebration of the common is, then, both the hallmark and the most overlooked facet of Studio Ghibli. There is magic in a nighttime flight across a village on the wings of your friendly neighbour forest spirit, or in your everyday battle against evil scheming fascists, but there is also magic enough in the simple pleasures of a bowl of warm, home-cooked food, served at the right time to suit the right mood, in a lilting conversation with a friendly stranger. It is a befitting paradox really, the harmony of opposites brought about with poise and delicacy. For you see, animation isn’t just for dragons and demons and great spectacles. It is also a medium to narrate stories in their purest, most non-distilled state, unfettered by the boundaries of logistics and science. It is the medium of dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is Hayao Miyazaki after all, but a dreamer?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sritama Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">One of the most enjoyed and oft-recounted anecdotes about Hayao Miyazaki- filmmaker, manga author, animator and co-founder of Japan’s Studio Ghibli- is his tussle with Hollywood’s now infamous mascot of predatory behaviour, Harvey Weinstein. Originally printed in The Guardian, the story runs thus:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hong Kong Protests: Understanding the Deeper Rifts Beneath the Masked Revolution</title><link href="/Hong-Kong-Protests" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hong Kong Protests: Understanding the Deeper Rifts Beneath the Masked Revolution" /><published>2019-08-31T02:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-31T02:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Hong-Kong-Protests</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Hong-Kong-Protests">&lt;p&gt;Since June 2019, Hong Kong has witnessed hundreds and thousands of people march
onto streets to fight for their depleting autonomy, and for their chance at true
democracy. The rallies have sustained for over twelve weeks, despite masked
demonstrations veering into violence with the police using tear gas and water
cannons to disperse the protesters. On July 1, the protesters stormed and
vandalised the HK Legislative Council to commemorate HK’s handover to China.
From 9 to 12 July, millions protested for the suspension of the extradition law
amendments. On August 6, a city-wide transportation shut down took place. On
August 12 and 13, the protesters took over the country’s airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are only some of the protests that have stood out in the past few months,
as Hong Kong has tried to reclaim its status of a ‘special administrative
region’ to protect its own independence, and the humanitarian rights and
liberties that its citizens enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The historical relationship between China and Hong Kong&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a GDP of over 34,000 crore USD, Hong Kong has fast grown into one of the
largest financial hubs of the world. But for over 150 years, HK was a British
colony. A part of it was ceded to the UK  in 1842 and later, China decided to
lease the rest of it, often termed as the ‘New Territories’, to the UK for 99
years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy began flourishing in the 1950s with HK emerging as a major port and
later, as a manufacturing powerhouse. With the deadline of the lease approaching
fast, the communist Chinese government began arguing for a complete return of
the HK territories to China. After significant deliberation, in 1997, the
territory on China’s southern coast gained independence from British imperial
rule and was “handed back” to China under a policy termed as ‘one country, two
systems.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, Hong Kong enjoyed a special federal status that allowed the region
its own system of government, laws and police force. All these clauses were
contained in a document called ‘Basic Rule’ which permitted for the existence
and implementation of a mini-constitution for the governance of HK. The Basic
Rule helped Hong Kong become a part of China while empowering HK citizens with
many liberties denied to citizens on the mainland, including free speech,
unrestricted internet access and the right to free assembly. It was agreed upon
by all parties that the system shall stay in place until at least 2047.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why are the “Hong Kongers” protesting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 Hong Kong anti-extradition bill protests started with a move by China
to propose amendments to HK’s extradition law that would allow case-by-case
extraditions to countries that lack formal extradition treaties with Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, one of the countries that lack formal extradition treaties with HK was
the People’s Republic of China itself, known for stifling and imprisoning any
dissenting citizens. Many critics have argued that the amendments were intended
as a powerful tool to detain Hong Kongers who spoke against the Chinese regime
or advocated pro-democracy sentiments. The amendments would have also applied
retroactively, which means that the hundreds of people who had fallen under the
scrutiny of China in the past for any crime would risk facing trial in the
mainland. One HK lawmaker called the amended bill- “dragnet over all of Hong
Kong.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After smaller protests that started in April and May, HK witnessed its first
gigantic protest on 9 June with over a million people peacefully taking to the
streets. On 12 June, more than two million residents of Hong Kong swarmed HK’s
legislature to delay the procedures that would’ve hastened the implementation of
the amendments. These protests were met with violence, with police firing tear
gas, rubber bullets and beanbags at the crowds. After these massive protests,
chief executive Lam was forced to “indefinitely suspend” the amendments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The underlying fractures in HK’s administration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Retake Hong Kong, Revolution of Our Times”: This is the slogan that has defined
this movement, which started from an extradition bill but has now expanded to
five demands. Before deeper examination of these demands, we must look at the
glaring loopholes in HK’s current system of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, a large portion of HK’s executive powers rest with its chief executive,
who, according to the Basic Rule, should be appointed on the basis of elections
or local consultations. But this process has been entirely taken over by China.
Currently the chief executive, Carrie Lam, who serves a five-year term, is
appointed by a 1200-member election committee, that is replete with
Beijing-loyalists. Thus, the representative of HK’s executive powers is often a
loyalist of China. This constitutes for “Hong Kong’s sham democracy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, there is a great degree of alienation felt by young Hong Kongers from
their Chinese regime. Surveys from the University of Hong Kong show that most
people identify themselves as “Hong Kongers” - only 11% would call themselves
“Chinese” - and 71% of people say they do not feel proud about being Chinese
citizens. Cultural differences that stem from their colonial past further
accentuate this alienation. And finally, China’s attempts to chip away their
autonomy and bring them under direct Chinese rule, have led to recurrent
protests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the residents of HK have five major demands. They, firstly, want the
extradition bill to be suspended. Secondly, they have demanded that the
government retract the word “riot” to denote this movement. Next, they want the
release of all those who have been arrested over the past few months in
association with these protests. Demand number four calls on the government to
convene a serious, independent inquiry into the Hong Kong police and their
tactics. Lastly, they want universal adult franchise, so that they can reclaim
their government and their rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What lies ahead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road ahead is neither safe for HK protesters nor easy for China. The
months-long protests in Hong Kong could usually be expected to invite a severe
crackdown from China, similar to the controversial 1989 Tiananmen Square
massacre. But the situation is significantly different now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong is a large financial capital of the world. The HK stock market is
bigger than that of London. Its citizens enjoy the freedom of expression on
several global media platforms, unlike other Chinese citizens. Any crackdown on
Hong Kong would cause heavy injury to the Chinese economy and the region’s
investments and trade relations may be tarnished for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing trade war between the US and China further complicates the
situation. Supporters from across the world have emerged in favour of the HK
protests against an authoritarian regime. The US President Donald Trump has also
hinted that no repeats of the 1989 Massacre will be tolerated, especially if
China wants to contain the trade war. Thus, with such vested interests, its
reputation as an emerging superpower is also at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Chinese government and police will continue to try to break and
dissolve the movement, perhaps, it is time for China to move the battle from the
streets to a round-table, where no one has to stifle their voices with a mask. A
negotiation between the protesters and the current HK and Chinese government is
clearly the best solution for all parties involved, so that the citizens’
freedoms can be safeguarded and HK’s status be regained, without tampering with
the Chinese economy or global status.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Since June 2019, Hong Kong has witnessed hundreds and thousands of people march onto streets to fight for their depleting autonomy, and for their chance at true democracy. The rallies have sustained for over twelve weeks, despite masked demonstrations veering into violence with the police using tear gas and water cannons to disperse the protesters. On July 1, the protesters stormed and vandalised the HK Legislative Council to commemorate HK’s handover to China. From 9 to 12 July, millions protested for the suspension of the extradition law amendments. On August 6, a city-wide transportation shut down took place. On August 12 and 13, the protesters took over the country’s airport. These are only some of the protests that have stood out in the past few months, as Hong Kong has tried to reclaim its status of a ‘special administrative region’ to protect its own independence, and the humanitarian rights and liberties that its citizens enjoy. The historical relationship between China and Hong Kong With a GDP of over 34,000 crore USD, Hong Kong has fast grown into one of the largest financial hubs of the world. But for over 150 years, HK was a British colony. A part of it was ceded to the UK  in 1842 and later, China decided to lease the rest of it, often termed as the ‘New Territories’, to the UK for 99 years. The economy began flourishing in the 1950s with HK emerging as a major port and later, as a manufacturing powerhouse. With the deadline of the lease approaching fast, the communist Chinese government began arguing for a complete return of the HK territories to China. After significant deliberation, in 1997, the territory on China’s southern coast gained independence from British imperial rule and was “handed back” to China under a policy termed as ‘one country, two systems.’ Essentially, Hong Kong enjoyed a special federal status that allowed the region its own system of government, laws and police force. All these clauses were contained in a document called ‘Basic Rule’ which permitted for the existence and implementation of a mini-constitution for the governance of HK. The Basic Rule helped Hong Kong become a part of China while empowering HK citizens with many liberties denied to citizens on the mainland, including free speech, unrestricted internet access and the right to free assembly. It was agreed upon by all parties that the system shall stay in place until at least 2047. Why are the “Hong Kongers” protesting? The 2019 Hong Kong anti-extradition bill protests started with a move by China to propose amendments to HK’s extradition law that would allow case-by-case extraditions to countries that lack formal extradition treaties with Hong Kong. Notably, one of the countries that lack formal extradition treaties with HK was the People’s Republic of China itself, known for stifling and imprisoning any dissenting citizens. Many critics have argued that the amendments were intended as a powerful tool to detain Hong Kongers who spoke against the Chinese regime or advocated pro-democracy sentiments. The amendments would have also applied retroactively, which means that the hundreds of people who had fallen under the scrutiny of China in the past for any crime would risk facing trial in the mainland. One HK lawmaker called the amended bill- “dragnet over all of Hong Kong.” After smaller protests that started in April and May, HK witnessed its first gigantic protest on 9 June with over a million people peacefully taking to the streets. On 12 June, more than two million residents of Hong Kong swarmed HK’s legislature to delay the procedures that would’ve hastened the implementation of the amendments. These protests were met with violence, with police firing tear gas, rubber bullets and beanbags at the crowds. After these massive protests, chief executive Lam was forced to “indefinitely suspend” the amendments. The underlying fractures in HK’s administration “Retake Hong Kong, Revolution of Our Times”: This is the slogan that has defined this movement, which started from an extradition bill but has now expanded to five demands. Before deeper examination of these demands, we must look at the glaring loopholes in HK’s current system of governance. Firstly, a large portion of HK’s executive powers rest with its chief executive, who, according to the Basic Rule, should be appointed on the basis of elections or local consultations. But this process has been entirely taken over by China. Currently the chief executive, Carrie Lam, who serves a five-year term, is appointed by a 1200-member election committee, that is replete with Beijing-loyalists. Thus, the representative of HK’s executive powers is often a loyalist of China. This constitutes for “Hong Kong’s sham democracy.” Further, there is a great degree of alienation felt by young Hong Kongers from their Chinese regime. Surveys from the University of Hong Kong show that most people identify themselves as “Hong Kongers” - only 11% would call themselves “Chinese” - and 71% of people say they do not feel proud about being Chinese citizens. Cultural differences that stem from their colonial past further accentuate this alienation. And finally, China’s attempts to chip away their autonomy and bring them under direct Chinese rule, have led to recurrent protests. Currently, the residents of HK have five major demands. They, firstly, want the extradition bill to be suspended. Secondly, they have demanded that the government retract the word “riot” to denote this movement. Next, they want the release of all those who have been arrested over the past few months in association with these protests. Demand number four calls on the government to convene a serious, independent inquiry into the Hong Kong police and their tactics. Lastly, they want universal adult franchise, so that they can reclaim their government and their rights. What lies ahead? The road ahead is neither safe for HK protesters nor easy for China. The months-long protests in Hong Kong could usually be expected to invite a severe crackdown from China, similar to the controversial 1989 Tiananmen Square massacre. But the situation is significantly different now. Hong Kong is a large financial capital of the world. The HK stock market is bigger than that of London. Its citizens enjoy the freedom of expression on several global media platforms, unlike other Chinese citizens. Any crackdown on Hong Kong would cause heavy injury to the Chinese economy and the region’s investments and trade relations may be tarnished for years to come. The ongoing trade war between the US and China further complicates the situation. Supporters from across the world have emerged in favour of the HK protests against an authoritarian regime. The US President Donald Trump has also hinted that no repeats of the 1989 Massacre will be tolerated, especially if China wants to contain the trade war. Thus, with such vested interests, its reputation as an emerging superpower is also at stake. Although the Chinese government and police will continue to try to break and dissolve the movement, perhaps, it is time for China to move the battle from the streets to a round-table, where no one has to stifle their voices with a mask. A negotiation between the protesters and the current HK and Chinese government is clearly the best solution for all parties involved, so that the citizens’ freedoms can be safeguarded and HK’s status be regained, without tampering with the Chinese economy or global status.    </summary></entry></feed>