<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-18T19:10:18+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The NBA Runs Through L.A. - Lakers Team to Beat</title><link href="/Lakers-Team-to-Beat" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The NBA Runs Through L.A. - Lakers Team to Beat" /><published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Lakers-Team-to-Beat</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Lakers-Team-to-Beat">&lt;p&gt;The NBA offseason has definitely been one for the books, with foreseeable trades and signings, as well as history-altering pick-ups. Although the Eastern Conference has seemingly stolen the best player in the league (at least up until the Finals - Kevin Durant) and has teams with potentially perennial talents (Giannis Antetokounmpo or the Joel Embiid/Ben Simmons tandem), the power of the NBA will still mostly reside in the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the departure of Kevin Durant and the dreadful injury to Klay Thompson, the Golden State Warriors have seemingly opened the door to the rest of the Western Conference, despite bolstering their roster in the short-term with the sign-and-trade deal with the Brooklyn Nets for D’Angelo Russell. An argument can be made for several teams in the west to pick up the torch (which can be read in my breakdown articles of each team), however this article will focus on the path the Los Angeles Lakers can follow in order to retake the reins of the NBA, which seems to be more open than it has been for the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the 2018/19 season, the Lakers were able to reel in the talents of Lebron James on a four-year deal, with the hopes of luring in another superstar, such as Kawahi Leonard or Paul George, during the offseason. In the short-term, James was tasked with taking an ill-advised, yet somewhat promising, mix of old and new players to the playoffs for the first time since the 2012/13 season. However, early promise shown by youngsters Lonzo Ball, Kyle Kuzma and Brandon Ingram was not enough to prevent the Lakers from their inevitable doom of not reaching the playoffs yet again, as they were frustrated by key injuries and inconsistent contributions from role players across the rotation, with a groin injury to Lebron James on Christmas night being the heaviest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading into this offseason and free agency, the Lakers were drawing a tremendous amount of attention around the NBA circuit, however none of it was pertaining to their plans to sign another big name. The Lakers were bogged down by issues within the front office and ownership, as well as speculation that James wanted out of Los Angeles. This was all silenced when the trade of Anthony Davis, who was previously written off as a potential trade option given the strong opposition from key members within the New Orleans’ front office, was announced. Shortly afterwards, the Lakers were then in the running for the addition of Kawahi Leonard, which would have arguably assembled the most potent big three the league has ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lakers sacrificed the possible signings of several other role players, such as Josh Reddick, so that they would have the financial capability to sign Leonard while still having wiggle room for next season when Anthony Davis will officially become a free agent. In holding out for Leonard, who they ultimately were unable to sign, several players that would have provided much needed shooting support were signed to other teams. Despite the loss of several potential role pieces, the Lakers were still able to benefit by having several contracts with potential bench pieces in place in case their pursuit of Leonard came up short. The same night that Leonard broke the news that he was heading to the other LA-based organization, the Lakers proceeded with this Plan B, and inked deals with Demarcus Cousins, Danny Green, Quinn Cook, Avery Bradley and Jason Dudley. They also resigned Rajon Rondo, JaVale McGee and Kentavious Caldwell-Pope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a potential starting-five of James and Green at the guards, Kuzma and Davis as forwards, and a rotation of Cousins/McGee at the center, the Lakers could replicate the formidable offensive capabilities that the Warriors have been known for with their various starting five line-ups over the past two seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Hamptons Five Lineup was the most dynamic line-up the league has ever seen, the Lakers have set their team up for better success due to the surrounding support of their bench. This past NBA Finals we saw that despite having a star-studded starting rotation, it is still possible to come up short when it matters (although gruesome season-ending injuries to Thompson and Durant did not help the Warriors’ case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James and Davis are proven entities within the NBA, so the Lakers should be in every game that both players are able to suit up and play in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kuzma is the only bright young spot that was not shipped off to New Orleans during the acquisition of Davis, and he has the potential to become a strong third contributor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green is a proven three-point specialist and will have an instant impact on a Lakers team that struggled to shoot from deep last season (33.3%), despite throwing up an average of 31 3-pointers a night. Green will also provide strong defensive support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGee had a strong first season with the Lakers last season. He averaged 12 points and 7.5 rebounds in 22.3 minutes, appearing in 75 games. With the signing of Demarcus Cousins it is probable that McGee will see less minutes, however it will depend largely on the health and conditioning of Cousins. Cousins was unable to land the large, long-term deal that he had anticipated following a cheap one-year deal with the Warriors this past season, largely due to heavy criticism of his lack of conditioning in the back half of the season, as well as the Finals. If Cousins comes to opening night in good shape, he should receive the bulk of minutes at the center position, as he has the potential for a huge bounce-back season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acquisitions of Dudley and Bradley are extremely intriguing, as both have proven their worth in the NBA but neither are more than bodies off the bench. Cook is an interesting back-up guard that has played many minutes as a back-up to Stephen Curry, and Rondo has been a proven dimer since his time in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the NBA Finals it would have been crazy to think that the Lakers would be in the position they are in now. The long-term success of the Lakers is dependent on the health status of James, Davis and Cousins, as well as getting consistent contributions from the bench. If both boxes are checked come the end of the season, and the Lakers head into the playoffs at full health, they will be the toughest team to beat, and should come out of the West on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>gavin.olson</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="basketball" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">The NBA offseason has definitely been one for the books, with foreseeable trades and signings, as well as history-altering pick-ups. Although the Eastern Conference has seemingly stolen the best player in the league (at least up until the Finals - Kevin Durant) and has teams with potentially perennial talents (Giannis Antetokounmpo or the Joel Embiid/Ben Simmons tandem), the power of the NBA will still mostly reside in the Western Conference.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Legitimate a Contender is Ben Askren and What Does the Future Hold for the Former Champion?</title><link href="/Ben-Askren" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Legitimate a Contender is Ben Askren and What Does the Future Hold for the Former Champion?" /><published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Ben-Askren</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Ben-Askren">&lt;p&gt;For many, the news of a deal between One Championship and the UFC to bring one of the hottest welterweight names in MMA in the form of Ben Askren to Dana White’s organisation set pulses racing. The previously undefeated Askren had become widely regarded as one of the welterweight GOATs, amassing an undefeated 18-0 record during his time in both Bellator and One Championship before his move to the UFC. Whilst throughout his career Askren’s stand-up game had been called into question, his incessant grappling and collegiate wrestling background allowed him to dominate almost all of his opponents including big names such as Douglas Lima and Shinya Aoki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, recently the tune has changed for Askren. His unconvincing victory over Robbie Lawler in his UFC debut at UFC 235 drew more questions about the legitimacy of Askren’s talents, after having almost been knocked out in the opening minute of the bout. After he engaged the clinch immediately versus Lawler, Askren was brutally sent into the canvas by a piledriver, from where on Askren absorbed heavy ground and pound from the ex-champion. Once Askren successfully regained the clinch, he was able to take Lawler down and secure a bulldog choke. Referee Herb Dean stepped in to ensure Lawler was still conscious after his arm appeared to go limp. After shaking his arm, Herb Dean assumed Lawler was out, not seeing the thumbs up from Lawler indicating that he was still conscious. Dean promptly ended the bout, which incurred strong protest from Lawler who had clearly been conscious the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his post-fight interview Askren made it clear that he would not entertain the idea of a rematch between himself and Lawler, creating yet more controversy around the manner of his victory, leading many to question whether or not Askren was out of his depth. It appeared as if Askren was simply afraid of losing his undefeated record, which had been extended to 19-0, hence his reluctance to book another fight with Lawler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it can be argued that Askren’s objection to rematching Lawler is because he does not have youth on his side. A title shot did not seem far off for Askren upon his arrival and it would appear a necessity for Askren to get his shot quickly in order to defend and secure his legacy, rather than risk his undefeated record in a rematch that may not better his chances of a title shot. Furthermore, given that Askren talks such a strong game, to almost be denied victory in such an ignominious fashion would potentially spell trouble for Askren, as to falter in such a talent stacked division can severely inhibit a fighter of Askren’s age’s chances of getting back to the top of the division. However, given that Askren is considered a big draw for any fighter at welterweight and the promotion as a whole, it was inevitable he would be given multiple opportunities to prove himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his victory over Lawler, Askren expressed his interest in the winner of Jorge Masvidal and Darren Till at UFC Fight Night London. Till had long made his desire to fight Askren clear, with the two going back and forth on social media. However, the upset of Masvidal viciously knocking Till out cold paved the way for one of, if not the greatest knockout in UFC history at UFC 239 in Las Vegas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an interview on The Joe Rogan Experience Podcast, Masvidal made it evident that his dislike of Askren was personal, detailing how he wanted to ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GQ5075ZFilo&quot;&gt;break his face&lt;/a&gt;’ due to the corny and irritating style in which Askren promotes his fights. When we consider the legitimacy of these threats from Masvidal, it would be easy to see this as just business promotion. In addition, it appeared as if Askren had successfully got under Masvidal’s skin and was apparently living inside his head free of rent. I initially thought Masvidal’s anger would get the better of him in the fight but how wrong I proved to be. Masvidal got his start as a street fighter during the Kimbo Slice days and rapidly shot to notoriety. The ferocity of this form of MMA would force Masvidal to channel his anger into his performances, keeping his composure in the build-up but having the ability to become one of the most formidable fighters to enter the octagon in modern times. During the build-up to the fight Askren appeared relaxed, cracking jokes and frequently questioning Masvidal’s anger, to which I thought Masvidal had no response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masvidal shocked the world on July 6th by knocking Askren out in 5 seconds via a flying knee, silencing his doubters and leaving viewers speechless. To knock out the undefeated Askren in such spectacular fashion makes Masvidal the hottest item in the welterweight division right now, with the hype building around him attracting more and more fans to his camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where does Askren go from here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a 19-0 former champion, to the victim of the fastest KO in history with a 1-1 record in the UFC (with a highly controversial victory), his career has really begun to be questioned by critics and fans alike. Whilst the loss to Masvidal has derailed his title hopes for now, it has also called into question the legitimacy of his fighting abilities, which appear to have been overstated by MMA fans due to his undefeated record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it should not be forgotten that Askren was undefeated for a reason; he still remains a highly regarded fighter and to re-enter the octagon in the premier promotion after a year out of the sport takes a lot of bravery, so hats off to Askren. Fans far and wide believe that this loss will serve as a learning curve for Askren which he will certainly benefit from. Despite this, Askren will still run his mouth as much as he did in the build-up to UFC 239, as he is a smart fighter who understands the necessity of self-promotion, similar to the style of promotion from the likes of Chael Sonnen and Conor McGregor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it is clear that Askren himself believes he can bounce back from this, it is difficult to predict what will happen in such a stacked weight class that contains some of the deadliest strikers in the entire organisation. It is clear that Askren needs a bounce back victory, and with rumours of a fight with Darren Till circulating, I am beginning to question the motivations of the UFC as an organisation, however this is a discussion for another time. Although Till has legitimate one punch knockout power which he has shown in his fights with the likes of Cowboy Cerrone, he has shown a deficiency on the ground which will play into Askren’s hands. Till’s shortcomings on the ground were particularly visible when he fought Tyron Woodley and was submitted via a D’arce choke. As Askren and Woodley are training partners it will be advantageous to Askren to learn from Woodley’s fight with Till and discover the flaws in the British fighter’s game in order to better his chances of a victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst this represents an opportunity for Askren to finally showcase his abilities, it does hold a greater risk than, for example, a match up with a journeyman such as Neil Magny or another lower ranked opponent. News has surfaced over the past couple of days of a match-up between Askren and veteran grappler Demian Maia. Maia has long been regarded as one of the most dangerous grapplers and submission experts in the organisation, so this is a highly desirable match-up. Not only does it allow Askren to prove himself against a highly regarded opponent and put his name back into contention, but it also has the potential to showcase Askren being outclassed at his preferred fighting style. It would certainly be intriguing to see Askren take on another high-level grappler in what is a make-or-break fight for the welterweight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the adversity he has faced, Ben Askren does have a future in the UFC. Whilst it would not be strange for a hype train as large as Askren’s to be derailed, due to the calibre of the competition at welterweight, it would be a shame considering the talent Askren showed in other organisations. Whilst Askren is at risk of fading into the periphery, he remains a big draw for a lot of fighters, so we can only hope that his UFC career picks up from here and he has the chance to showcase his abilities as he has done in One Championship and Bellator.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Eakin</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="mma" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">For many, the news of a deal between One Championship and the UFC to bring one of the hottest welterweight names in MMA in the form of Ben Askren to Dana White’s organisation set pulses racing. The previously undefeated Askren had become widely regarded as one of the welterweight GOATs, amassing an undefeated 18-0 record during his time in both Bellator and One Championship before his move to the UFC. Whilst throughout his career Askren’s stand-up game had been called into question, his incessant grappling and collegiate wrestling background allowed him to dominate almost all of his opponents including big names such as Douglas Lima and Shinya Aoki.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Heartbeat Bill: An Infringement Upon the Right to Choose</title><link href="/Heartbeat-Bill" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heartbeat Bill: An Infringement Upon the Right to Choose" /><published>2019-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Heartbeat-Bill</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Heartbeat-Bill">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Horror Story&lt;/em&gt; is no longer a mere fictional television show, it is a reality for women in the United States. A country, put on a pedestal for its liberal laws and democratic attitude, has taken a turn with the rise of the extreme right-wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, new state laws have been passed in various parts of the US, making abortions physically inaccessible to women. These laws have reduced the number of abortion clinics in several states to one, due to frequent and unnecessary changes in the restrictions placed on them. The clinics that cannot afford such changes end up shutting down altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the US Supreme Court ruled on &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt;, it did not specify when abortions were legal. They vaguely decided to make it unconstitutional to outlaw them until the foetus is ‘viable’. Since scientists had not determined when that was, states exploited this ambiguity and passed specific week bans like (i) when a foetal heartbeat can be detected, (ii) when the foetus can experience the pain of the procedure and (iii) when the foetus has developed into a person. This sparked the pro-life vs pro-choice debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a law was passed, in Alabama, making abortions practically illegal for women. The sole exceptions made are if the mother’s life is at severe risk or if the abortion is carried out before six weeks into the pregnancy. The six-week rule is impractical as most women find out about their pregnancies only after those six weeks. The lack of other exceptions also implies that a woman who is HIV positive or has been impregnated by rape or incest would not be allowed to terminate her pregnancy. Moreover, a doctor carrying out this procedure could face 99 years in prison, so if he/she was to be prosecuted under this law in 2019, he would get out in 2118. The rapist, however, can get out after three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro-life activists support this legislation out of the belief that it addresses an important human rights issue: the right to life of the foetus. The bill, however, is not about protecting an unborn child, but about control over a woman’s body. Most importantly, it acts as an infringement on a woman’s right to life itself. In fact the High Court at Calcutta, in India, a country ostensibly more backward than the United States, brilliantly explains why a practical blanket ban on abortions is truly the infringement of a woman’s right to life, and not the foetus’, in the case of &lt;em&gt;Suparna Debnath v. State of West Bengal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, The Honourable Acting Chief Justice of the Court, Mr Justice Somadder explained that a woman’s “sufferings include the sufferings of her child, whose compromised existence is inextricably linked with the mother. The role of the State in this regard is crucial; both for the well-being of the mother and that of her child.” Mr Justice Somadder added that the reasoning behind this proposition was that “[t]he mother’s personal life and liberty….is inextricably linked with that of the unborn child and will continue even after she gives birth to the child.” Therefore, any person who professes to care about the right to life of the foetus has to care about the right to life of its mother, for the foetus’ existence is, by all means, dependent on its mother. So, if one does not prioritise the woman’s life on the issue of abortion in certain circumstances or understand that the issue is a priori about a woman’s right to life, one only masquerades as ‘pro-life’, when, in fact, they only wish to have dominion over a woman’s body. And this is verily the case with the supporters of the proposed Alabama law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ban is a classic case of a problem-solution mismatch. A government that has failed to strengthen its gun laws, to protect children from mass shootings and has separated immigrant families, is now pretending to care about ‘young and innocent lives’. Currently, Alabama has an F in its status of women’s health and has the highest infant mortality rate. If it were pro-children, the government of Alabama would be working towards increasing the standard of living in the state through measures such as improving the status of women’s health, lowering the infant mortality rates and allocating more resources towards public schools. Instead of adopting policies that keeps people trapped in poverty for generations, because of being forced to support another human being without having the means to do so, the government should to provide comprehensive sex education, free birth control and contraception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many a time there is a substantial risk that a child, if born, would suffer from deformities and diseases. Their treatment not only takes a financial toll but also a mental toll on the parents. Often, parents cannot afford the treatment. Such a birth especially hurts when the child ends up dying only a few years later. The effects on a woman’s physical and mental health, strength, and life because of carrying a specially-abled child full term is an avoidable cost. A woman’s suffering is not only limited to her pain and agony. As explained above, it is interlinked to her child’s suffering too, as the child’s right to life is parasitic. This, however, does not go to say that the parents loved their child any less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A popular justification for anti-abortion laws has been: ‘protecting women’s health’. However, abortion is no danger to their health. Abortion, carried out by a doctor, has a mortality rate of 0.00073%, which is the lowest of all medical procedures. The law will drive women to now undertake unsafe abortions. As defined by the WHO, “unsafe abortion is a procedure for terminating an unintended pregnancy carried out either by persons lacking the necessary skills or in an environment that does not conform to minimal medical standards or both.” These abortions are the third leading cause of maternal deaths worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many pro-lifers argue that a woman who doesn’t wish to raise the child can give the child up for adoption. However, there are certain problems attached to this. Firstly, there are already too many kids waiting to be adopted, trapped in America’s faulty foster care system. The system comes with its own set of problems: assault by foster parents, lack of access to basic amenities. Secondly, women often do not know whether their baby will be cared for and must live in the perpetual guilt of negative possibilities. It is due to this that women are unable to give a baby up for adoption, a baby they carried to full term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The domino effect of the Alabama bill has already spread to multiple states, some following suit and some still considering it. Beyond this, the bill and the conservative judges in the Supreme Court will now have the power to overturn &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt; making abortion illegal all over the country. But America isn’t the only country affected by these laws. In 2017, President Trump reinstated and expanded a policy called the ‘global gag rule’. This rule states, that any overseas organisation which receives US global health funding, cannot even mention abortion as part of their counselling or education programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Kaiser Family Foundation poll of 1,492 Americans, 67% say abortion should be legalised in all or most cases. Women who live in places where abortions are illegal are known to be arrested by police in cases of miscarriage, due to the police believing it to be a conscious attempt to abort. Recently, in Alabama, a pregnant woman who got shot in the stomach was arrested by the police, under similar justifications. From grassroots to the global level, a trend has followed suit, wherein women are being subjected to harsher realities. A voice against these draconian abortion laws made anywhere in the world, be it Ireland or the USA, should be raised by all, irrespective of gender. These regressive laws have no place in any progressive society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">American Horror Story is no longer a mere fictional television show, it is a reality for women in the United States. A country, put on a pedestal for its liberal laws and democratic attitude, has taken a turn with the rise of the extreme right-wing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Of Diplomacy, Domination and the South China Sea</title><link href="/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Of Diplomacy, Domination and the South China Sea" /><published>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea">&lt;p&gt;In his book, &lt;em&gt;On China&lt;/em&gt;, notable American diplomat Henry Kissinger wrote, “The
highest form of warfare is to attack [the enemy’s] Strategy itself; the next, to
attack [his] Alliances. The next, to attack Armies”. As elaborated by Kissinger,
China seems to be following the art of strategic encirclement in diplomacy’s new
theatre, the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/de/South_China_Sea_claims_map.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//South_China_Sea_claims_map.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea is a part of the Pacific Ocean, with the Strait of Taiwan in
the Northeast and the Straits of Malacca in the Southwest (as shown in the map).
The littoral countries of this disputed sea are China, Taiwan, Philippines,
Malaysia, Brunei, Indonesia, Singapore, Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary island chains in the South China Sea are The Paracel, the Pratas and
Spratly Islands. The Scarborough Shoal, a triangle-shaped chain of reefs and
rocks with a total area of 150 square kilometres, is another important
geographical entity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till the end of World War II, not a single island in the South China Sea had
been occupied. In 1947, China demarcated its claims over the South China Sea
with a U-shaped line made up of eleven dashes, covering almost the entire area.
Newer dimensions were added to the conflict following the formation of Taiwan in
1949.  In 1953, the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash line&lt;/em&gt; prevailed over the earlier eleven dashes,
when China withdrew its claim over the Gulf of Tonkin. The claimed area
stretches from Hainan Island, covering Paracel and Spratly Islands which
comprise over 90% of the South China Sea. On diplomatic fora, China justifies
its claim stating the Treaty of Tientsin with France after the Sino-French War
in 1885, and the Cairo and Potsdam declarations after the defeat of Japan in
World War II. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claimants for the Paracel Islands include Taiwan, Vietnam and China. Vietnam
cites 17th century, Vietnamese scholar Do Ba to justify the fact that it once
actively ruled over Paracel and Spratly islands, and thus has territorial rights
over them. As for the Pratas Islands, they are administered by Taiwan but
claimed by China. Malaysia and Brunei also claim the territory that falls in
their exclusive economic zones. While Malaysia claims some islands in Spratly,
Brunei does not. Philippines, Taiwan and China claim the Scarborough Shoal,
which China also calls the Huangyan Island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Importance of the South China Sea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea is an important trade route, supporting trade worth $5
trillion. Secondly, it is a rich source of hydrocarbons and is an abundant
fishing ground. According to the United States Energy Information Agency, there
are 11 billion barrels of oil and 190 trillion cubic feet of natural gas in
deposits under the South China Sea. Its fisheries account for 10% of the global
total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea holds strategic importance for China for two more reasons.
First, China is dependent upon West Asia for its energy needs. The trade via sea
has many choke points like the Straits of Malacca, Sunda Strait and Lombok
Strait that have remained blocked in the past. This proved harmful for China and
thus domination of the sea would be pre-emptive action to save this important
route. Secondly, aggressive posturing in the South China Sea would help China
enhance its domination in the Indian Ocean. This would be a countermeasure to
the United States’ growing hegemony in the Indo-Pacific region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vietnam-China Dispute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1974, China and South Vietnam fought the battle for Paracel Islands. China
won and took over the entire archipelago. Following the Vietnam War, North
Vietnam, which earlier supported China’s claim, put forth a united front against
Chinese domination. As discussed earlier, Vietnam claims the Paracel Islands and
denounces the violation of Vietnam’s sovereignty by the forceful occupation of
these islands. In 1988, another standoff occurred following a skirmish between
Vietnamese and Chinese soldiers over the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johnson_South_Reef&quot;&gt;Johnson South
Reef&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spratly_Islands&quot;&gt;Spratly
Islands&lt;/a&gt; that killed 64
Vietnamese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014 China-Vietnam Oil rig crisis heightened tensions relating to the
ownership of islands in the South China Sea. On May 2, 2014, China National
Offshore Oil Corporation moved its $1 billion &lt;em&gt;Hai Yang Shi You 981&lt;/em&gt; oil rig to
a location closer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triton_Island&quot;&gt;Triton
Island&lt;/a&gt;s, the southwestern-most
island of the Paracels. The location was near Vietnam’s hydrocarbon blocks 142
and 143. Vietnam protested by sending 29 ships to disrupt the rig’s operations.
The tensions at sea led to anti-China protests in Vietnam which escalated into
riots. Many foreign businesses and Chinese workers were subjected to looting and
vandalism. On July 15, China National Offshore Oil Corporation withdrew one
month earlier than originally announced, defusing the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2019, a large-scale standoff took place between the coast guard ships of
China and Vietnam when a Chinese oil exploration ship entered disputed waters
near the Spratly Islands. Vietnam demanded an immediate withdrawal, while China
refused to do so, leading to another dispute between the nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China-Philippines Dispute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 2012, Philippines exercised de-facto control over the shoal. The 2012
Scarborough standoff was initiated when the Philippines accused Chinese
fishermen of illegally collecting corals, giant clams and live sharks. Following
a tense standoff wherein the Chinese vessels refused to leave the shoal, the
unsuccessful bilateral negotiations forced the Philippines to back off. China
gained control and drove Filipino fishermen away from Scarborough Shoal. In
2013, the Philippines took China to the Permanent Court of Arbitration, to
challenge the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash line&lt;/em&gt; that violated the Philippines’ sovereignty under
the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Seas (1982). The court ruled
that China had violated the Philippines’ sovereign waters as the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash
line&lt;/em&gt; included the Scarborough Shoal and the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic
Zone (EEZ). China outrightly rejected the ruling and refused to vacate the
Scarborough Shoal, questioning the court’s ‘jurisdiction’. Philippines rejoiced
this judgement as the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2016/07/philippines-wins-trial-century-160714115011745.html&quot;&gt;trial of the
century&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the ruling of the Hague tribunal, China continues to violate the
Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone and engages in overfishing. On June 9,
2019, a Chinese vessel was involved in a boat ramming incident, which threatened
the lives of 22 Filipino fishermen. In another incident in late July, 113
Chinese fishing vessels were spotted near the Philippine-administered Pag-asa
Island in the Spratly archipelago. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite continuous violations, the Malacañang seems to be wanting warmer ties
with its Chinese counterpart. President Duterte recently revealed that he had
reached a ‘verbal agreement’ with President Xi, for allowing Chinese fishermen
in the Philippines EEZ. As a part of Duterte’s bilateral visit to China in 2018,
a preliminary agreement was reached for oil and gas exploration in the South
China Sea. Critics smell foul play at the increasing proximity and condemn
Duterte for failing to act on the Philippines’ arbitral victory. The reason for
this shift is attributed to China’s economic clout and growing investments in
the infrastructure sector, essential to support the Philippines’ economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aspiring hegemon is proactively utilising money diplomacy to win strategic
partners. According to reports, a secret deal was signed with Cambodia to allow
Chinese forces to use the Ream naval base. As in the Philippines, Chinese funded
soft loans and investment in Cambodian infrastructure projects have brought
‘warmth’ to the bilateral ties. Encirclement Attack is the norm being adopted by
China, and how the nation’s money diplomacy further polarises the South China
Sea dispute would be something to watch out for.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gurleen Kaur</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In his book, On China, notable American diplomat Henry Kissinger wrote, “The highest form of warfare is to attack [the enemy’s] Strategy itself; the next, to attack [his] Alliances. The next, to attack Armies”. As elaborated by Kissinger, China seems to be following the art of strategic encirclement in diplomacy’s new theatre, the South China Sea. Geography The South China Sea is a part of the Pacific Ocean, with the Strait of Taiwan in the Northeast and the Straits of Malacca in the Southwest (as shown in the map). The littoral countries of this disputed sea are China, Taiwan, Philippines, Malaysia, Brunei, Indonesia, Singapore, Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam. The primary island chains in the South China Sea are The Paracel, the Pratas and Spratly Islands. The Scarborough Shoal, a triangle-shaped chain of reefs and rocks with a total area of 150 square kilometres, is another important geographical entity.  The Conflict Till the end of World War II, not a single island in the South China Sea had been occupied. In 1947, China demarcated its claims over the South China Sea with a U-shaped line made up of eleven dashes, covering almost the entire area. Newer dimensions were added to the conflict following the formation of Taiwan in 1949.  In 1953, the nine-dash line prevailed over the earlier eleven dashes, when China withdrew its claim over the Gulf of Tonkin. The claimed area stretches from Hainan Island, covering Paracel and Spratly Islands which comprise over 90% of the South China Sea. On diplomatic fora, China justifies its claim stating the Treaty of Tientsin with France after the Sino-French War in 1885, and the Cairo and Potsdam declarations after the defeat of Japan in World War II.  Claimants for the Paracel Islands include Taiwan, Vietnam and China. Vietnam cites 17th century, Vietnamese scholar Do Ba to justify the fact that it once actively ruled over Paracel and Spratly islands, and thus has territorial rights over them. As for the Pratas Islands, they are administered by Taiwan but claimed by China. Malaysia and Brunei also claim the territory that falls in their exclusive economic zones. While Malaysia claims some islands in Spratly, Brunei does not. Philippines, Taiwan and China claim the Scarborough Shoal, which China also calls the Huangyan Island. Importance of the South China Sea The South China Sea is an important trade route, supporting trade worth $5 trillion. Secondly, it is a rich source of hydrocarbons and is an abundant fishing ground. According to the United States Energy Information Agency, there are 11 billion barrels of oil and 190 trillion cubic feet of natural gas in deposits under the South China Sea. Its fisheries account for 10% of the global total. The South China Sea holds strategic importance for China for two more reasons. First, China is dependent upon West Asia for its energy needs. The trade via sea has many choke points like the Straits of Malacca, Sunda Strait and Lombok Strait that have remained blocked in the past. This proved harmful for China and thus domination of the sea would be pre-emptive action to save this important route. Secondly, aggressive posturing in the South China Sea would help China enhance its domination in the Indian Ocean. This would be a countermeasure to the United States’ growing hegemony in the Indo-Pacific region. Vietnam-China Dispute In 1974, China and South Vietnam fought the battle for Paracel Islands. China won and took over the entire archipelago. Following the Vietnam War, North Vietnam, which earlier supported China’s claim, put forth a united front against Chinese domination. As discussed earlier, Vietnam claims the Paracel Islands and denounces the violation of Vietnam’s sovereignty by the forceful occupation of these islands. In 1988, another standoff occurred following a skirmish between Vietnamese and Chinese soldiers over the Johnson South Reef in the Spratly Islands that killed 64 Vietnamese. The 2014 China-Vietnam Oil rig crisis heightened tensions relating to the ownership of islands in the South China Sea. On May 2, 2014, China National Offshore Oil Corporation moved its $1 billion Hai Yang Shi You 981 oil rig to a location closer to the Triton Islands, the southwestern-most island of the Paracels. The location was near Vietnam’s hydrocarbon blocks 142 and 143. Vietnam protested by sending 29 ships to disrupt the rig’s operations. The tensions at sea led to anti-China protests in Vietnam which escalated into riots. Many foreign businesses and Chinese workers were subjected to looting and vandalism. On July 15, China National Offshore Oil Corporation withdrew one month earlier than originally announced, defusing the crisis. In July 2019, a large-scale standoff took place between the coast guard ships of China and Vietnam when a Chinese oil exploration ship entered disputed waters near the Spratly Islands. Vietnam demanded an immediate withdrawal, while China refused to do so, leading to another dispute between the nations.  China-Philippines Dispute Until 2012, Philippines exercised de-facto control over the shoal. The 2012 Scarborough standoff was initiated when the Philippines accused Chinese fishermen of illegally collecting corals, giant clams and live sharks. Following a tense standoff wherein the Chinese vessels refused to leave the shoal, the unsuccessful bilateral negotiations forced the Philippines to back off. China gained control and drove Filipino fishermen away from Scarborough Shoal. In 2013, the Philippines took China to the Permanent Court of Arbitration, to challenge the nine-dash line that violated the Philippines’ sovereignty under the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Seas (1982). The court ruled that China had violated the Philippines’ sovereign waters as the nine-dash line included the Scarborough Shoal and the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ). China outrightly rejected the ruling and refused to vacate the Scarborough Shoal, questioning the court’s ‘jurisdiction’. Philippines rejoiced this judgement as the ‘trial of the century’. Despite the ruling of the Hague tribunal, China continues to violate the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone and engages in overfishing. On June 9, 2019, a Chinese vessel was involved in a boat ramming incident, which threatened the lives of 22 Filipino fishermen. In another incident in late July, 113 Chinese fishing vessels were spotted near the Philippine-administered Pag-asa Island in the Spratly archipelago.  Despite continuous violations, the Malacañang seems to be wanting warmer ties with its Chinese counterpart. President Duterte recently revealed that he had reached a ‘verbal agreement’ with President Xi, for allowing Chinese fishermen in the Philippines EEZ. As a part of Duterte’s bilateral visit to China in 2018, a preliminary agreement was reached for oil and gas exploration in the South China Sea. Critics smell foul play at the increasing proximity and condemn Duterte for failing to act on the Philippines’ arbitral victory. The reason for this shift is attributed to China’s economic clout and growing investments in the infrastructure sector, essential to support the Philippines’ economy.  The aspiring hegemon is proactively utilising money diplomacy to win strategic partners. According to reports, a secret deal was signed with Cambodia to allow Chinese forces to use the Ream naval base. As in the Philippines, Chinese funded soft loans and investment in Cambodian infrastructure projects have brought ‘warmth’ to the bilateral ties. Encirclement Attack is the norm being adopted by China, and how the nation’s money diplomacy further polarises the South China Sea dispute would be something to watch out for.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Indian Startup Ecosystem: A Global Perspective</title><link href="/A-Global-Perspective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Startup Ecosystem: A Global Perspective" /><published>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Global-Perspective</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Global-Perspective">&lt;p&gt;A proud moment for India was to have been ranked as the 5th most startup-friendly economy in the world, in 2019. This was based on five parameters: human capital investment, research and development, entrepreneurial infrastructure, technical workforce and policy dynamics. Despite losing the first four positions to the USA, UK, Canada and Israel, India has come a long way due to various government schemes such as Startup India, Make In India, Digital India, the setting up of the Biotechnology Industry Research Assistance Council (BIRAC) and many more which foster a culture of entrepreneurship and innovation in the country. However, India has lagged behind other countries in two aspects majorly; innovation and taxation. The persistent dearth of successful innovation and the recent ‘Angel tax issue’ have discouraged investors from providing funds to Indian entrepreneurs for the creation of their own startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per Global Innovation Index 2019, India stood at the 52nd position out of a total of 129 countries for capacity and success in innovation. For a country that is the fifth leading startup- friendly economy globally, to rank so poorly in innovation is nothing short of a disgrace. This lack of innovation is clearly depicted by India’s relatively low expenditure on research and development. Although India stands at the 7th position when it comes to absolute money spent on R&amp;amp;D (after adjusting PPP) with a mammoth expenditure of $48.1 billion. However, this generally isn’t enough, given the large geographical area and population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relative figures show a different reality altogether. India’s expenditure on R&amp;amp;D continues to be as low as 0.8% of the GDP, much lower than countries like South Korea at 4.3%, Israel at 4.2% and Japan at 3.4%. The lack of quality research is evidenced by the fact that many of India’s startups are nothing but an emulation of successful global ideas fine-tuned to serve local needs. Talk about the American Uber and Indians have an Ola. Think about Spotify and we have the Indian version &lt;em&gt;Gaana&lt;/em&gt;. For Amazon, we have Indian competitors, Flipkart and Snapdeal. For Airbnb, we have OYO Rooms. We have the Indian Zomato and Swiggy as replacements of the middle-eastern Talabat. All these foreign startups were established before we Indians copied their ideas and made it our own. One cannot deny that India has become a startup hub with a total of 8625 startups in 2018 across various fields like edtech, traveltech, fintech, logistics and healthtech, yet it is even harder to disagree with the reality that the number of these startups formed out of original new ideas of Indians is laughably low. This is perhaps due to loopholes in the Indian education system that fails to provide the requisite infrastructure, skills and highly-qualified, research-oriented teaching faculty in universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next lies the issue of the ‘Angel tax’ which has been tormenting the Indian startup ecosystem lately. Angel tax is an ‘income tax’ payable on capital raised by ‘unlisted’ companies via issue of shares, where income refers to the share price in excess of the fair market value of the shares sold. The investors providing funds to these companies also have to pay a ‘gift tax’ on the excess amount. The Angel tax was introduced in India in 2012 with the aim to curb money laundering by various small companies by imposing a high tax rate of 30.9% on all unlisted companies in the country, along with a tax on the investors. It all started when owners of small-scale companies started laundering their tax-evaded income by selling their shares to investors at a price above the fair market value. In reality, the investors got the money to be invested in the companies from the owners themselves and charged commission for helping the owners carry out the money laundering process smoothly. The Angel tax successfully curbed such malpractices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this started creating problems for startups (which are often unlisted companies), when honest angel investors who provided seed funding to these startups had to start paying an exorbitant tax on the excess amount, they began putting their money elsewhere. This gave entrepreneurs a hard time in finding that first cheque to kick start their business, thus, resulting in unnecessary road kills of many good ideas. However, there was a sigh of relief when Indian Finance Minister Nirmala Sitharaman announced in her 2019 Budget that startups and their investors, who will provide the requisite declarations on their returns, will not be subject to scrutiny under the Angel tax. The government also eased the norms for companies to qualify as startups by increasing the upper limit for the turnover of the tax exempt startups from ₹250 million to ₹1 billion. Furthermore, an entity will now be considered a startup for upto 10 years after its incorporation, as compared to 7 years earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has definitely come a long way, but still has a lot to learn from how other countries have successfully implemented some out-of-the-box policies to create a vibrant startup ecosystem. The global startup economy has achieved great heights with a total economic value of nearly $3 trillion in 2019, a 20% increase in worth from the prior two periods. This growth is largely driven by high-tech startups in the fields of advanced manufacturing and robotics, blockchain, agritech and new food, and artificial intelligence. Meanwhile, sectors such as edtech, digital media, gaming and adTech have seen falling levels of investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some countries have outperformed others in terms of innovation, friendly government policies and entrepreneurial mindset. Israel is one such country which boasts of the highest venture capital investments as a percentage of GDP. The influx of highly educated Jewish immigrants in the 1990’s and the training of people in sophisticated technology, due to compulsory military service, has given a boost to technological research in this small Middle-Eastern country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has played an instrumental role in ensuring that this abundant human capital does not go to waste by providing adequate funding to convert their ideas into businesses. The Matching Grants Programme is one such government initiative that was launched with the aim to eliminate the financial risk associated with the ambiguity in the outcome of a research. The firms simply have to submit their R&amp;amp;D proposals to the chief scientist, and grants are awarded on a competitive basis, with 66% to 90% of the research costs covered. These grants act as high-risk loans, where successful projects repay the funding received via a deduction of a small percentage of annual sales whereas the government bears the costs of the unsuccessful projects. This policy played a major role in boosting the high-tech industry of Israel and made it the ‘Startup Nation’ that it is today. In India, the government does provide funds to startups to carry on R&amp;amp;D, but it does not bear the risk of failure of startup. With over 90% of Indian startups failing in the initial years due to lack of original ideas and innovation, a government policy mirroring Israel’s will inculcate a sense of confidence conducive to taking bolder risks by entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada is also known for its startup hubs like Montreal, Vancouver and Toronto. Canada has successfully launched and implemented NextAI: the first global programme to build Canada’s Artificial Intelligence ecosystem. It not only provides funding to talented teams and individuals in AI ranging from $50,000 to an additional $150,000 to the top performers, but also provides them with education from AI experts, a network of like-minded innovators and corporate mentors, office space in AI-focused hubs, and easy access to visas to entrepreneurs from abroad. R&amp;amp;D on AI is non-existent in India and initiatives like NextAI must be undertaken in collaboration with educational institutions, the corporate sector and international governments to provide Indian researchers the required expertise and monetary support to kickstart such a programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In European countries, like the UK, private companies help individuals and firms in the paperwork of proving and estimating the costs of R&amp;amp;D for a meagre commission, a facility non-existent in India. This has great prospects in India because this Asian country requires every fund-raising request to go through 14 procedural stages against the global average of 4.3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the single most important aspect which Indians lack is the Israeli ‘chutzpah’, which literally translates to audacity and boldness. Entrepreneurs in countries like USA, UK, Canada, Japan and Germany are risk-takers who are not afraid to fail. Unlike India, where being practical and financially secure is given far more significance than the ability to dream big, failure is merely seen as a learning experience and a stepping stone to success in these counties. The Indian startup economy has not yet seen its full potential due to the timid and risk-averse nature of people, which is reiterated time and again, thus, creating a mental barrier in people. However, India is changing for the better, with a bold, young generation ready to take the risks of having their own businesses. India is treading the correct path. All it needs to do is learn from the best; whether that is innovative governmental policies or Chutzpah, and finally, implement it efficiently in their country.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">A proud moment for India was to have been ranked as the 5th most startup-friendly economy in the world, in 2019. This was based on five parameters: human capital investment, research and development, entrepreneurial infrastructure, technical workforce and policy dynamics. Despite losing the first four positions to the USA, UK, Canada and Israel, India has come a long way due to various government schemes such as Startup India, Make In India, Digital India, the setting up of the Biotechnology Industry Research Assistance Council (BIRAC) and many more which foster a culture of entrepreneurship and innovation in the country. However, India has lagged behind other countries in two aspects majorly; innovation and taxation. The persistent dearth of successful innovation and the recent ‘Angel tax issue’ have discouraged investors from providing funds to Indian entrepreneurs for the creation of their own startups.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age</title><link href="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age" /><published>2019-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age">&lt;p&gt;The first of The Pangean’s &lt;em&gt;pubcasts&lt;/em&gt; is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirandamowbray/&quot;&gt;Dr Miranda Mowbray&lt;/a&gt;, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/harsh.tiwari/&quot;&gt;Harsh Tiwari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/reuben.pritchard/&quot;&gt;Reuben Pritchard&lt;/a&gt; sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology as a replacement for human interaction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(60)&quot;&gt;01:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology in business and politics&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(1203)&quot;&gt;20:03&lt;/a&gt;), or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The accessibility of technology&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2142)&quot;&gt;35:42&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast1-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-1&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>the.pangean</name></author><summary type="html">The first of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Dr Miranda Mowbray, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data. In this podcast, Harsh Tiwari and Reuben Pritchard sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest: Introduction (00:00), Technology as a replacement for human interaction (01:00), Technology in business and politics (20:03), or The accessibility of technology (35:42). Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why So Bad *rse?</title><link href="/Why-So-Bad-Arse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why So Bad *rse?" /><published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Why-So-Bad-Arse</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Why-So-Bad-Arse">&lt;p&gt;Raise your hand if you remember the &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt; fever that gripped Hollywood - and
pretty much the rest of the world too - in the fall of 2013. If you remember the
glittering reviews and the innumerable times ‘&lt;em&gt;shattered the glass ceiling&lt;/em&gt;’,
‘&lt;em&gt;badass princesses&lt;/em&gt;’ or ‘&lt;em&gt;Oscar worthy&lt;/em&gt;’ flashed before your eyes, till you
were made certain that all of life was meaningless unless you booked first-day,
deluxe seat tickets. If you remember how Disney Renaissance enthusiasts, across
the globe, made sure you knew that Anna and Elsa were &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt;, unlike the
&lt;em&gt;girly-girls&lt;/em&gt; you see in other princess movies. They are &lt;em&gt;empowered,&lt;/em&gt; with their
M-slit gowns and absence of a romantic wedding for an ending, jot that down. If
you remember how you found yourself at the theatre, semi-guilt tripped into
watching the movie, and finally realised that Jennifer Lee’s retelling of &lt;em&gt;The
Snow Queen&lt;/em&gt; to be, at most, a well-intentioned but weak tea nod as to what made
a woman ‘badass’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s funny, actually, because when one sits down to look back upon this legacy
of retconning traditionally feminine roles as &lt;em&gt;weak&lt;/em&gt;, so as to prop up
tomboyish, often desensitised heroines, it’s not just the creators, critics and
audience of present day showbiz media who are to blame. Even adored and revered
works like those of C S Lewis and Rowling, &lt;em&gt;yes, Rowling&lt;/em&gt;, have often sought to
perpetuate this trope, often under a carefully arranged veneer of offering
simple didactic messages in children’s literature. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s talk about &lt;em&gt;these girly-girls&lt;/em&gt;. Not just the predecessor Disney
princesses, no, but the so-called wimpy girls in the media, the featherbrained
airheads, the wet blankets. The ones who can’t and won’t punch assassins, knife
through captors or ride horses into sandstorms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For as long as I can remember, it was a struggle for me to find feminine,
unapologetically girly characters in literature and media, who were not
dismissed as prissy, uppity damsels or useless, shivering waifs whose plethora
of interests - sewing, fashion, painting, music, and so forth - were not
dismissed as completely decorative and impractical in the general context of the
storyline. Worse still, if I did manage to find a rare favourite, it was quite
the feat to avoid the barrage of snide remarks from acquaintances, friends, and
even more terrible - overenthusiastic vloggers and literary dissenters who were
sure to hammer home the fact that Sansa Stark and Amy March are, in fact,
horrible sinners doomed to burn in eternal hellfire for their crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sansa Stark, from George R R Martin’s &lt;em&gt;A Song of Ice and Fire,&lt;/em&gt; is a textbook
example of the stern fact that a non-tomboyish, non-sexualised female lead can
do nothing without being written off as a wimp. A young, naive lady of merely
eleven&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; when the series begins, Sansa is held captive, forced to endure the
slaughter of her family and shoulders through being a political pawn and a
hostage with kindness, bravery and resilience. She has no dragons and no swords,
she loves lemon cakes, ballads and handsome knights, and is therefore, by
default, painted by the &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; fandom as a wet blanket airhead. She’s
even seen as a veritable ableist demon for not feeling sexually attracted
towards a man thrice her age (and he hails from the house that murdered her
family, no less). She only manages to garner some sympathy after she is violated
in the TV adaptation, a scene that doesn’t even exist in the books. It is hardly
surprising that many male characters in the series, who do much worse, get away
with their misdeeds way easily. &lt;em&gt;Thrones’&lt;/em&gt; treatment of non-warrior women is
particularly repulsive. Sansa is made to mouth lines showing stoic gratitude
towards her assaulters for teaching her strength, and another female character,
who is often praised for being the snarky cool kid, demurely announces that she
doesn’t plan to be useless during battle, namely ‘sit knitting by the fire’.
Non-canonical lines, inserted because of the directors’ knowledge that they
specifically pander to the audience’s needs and explicit scenes where women
condemn softness and acts of ‘predictable’ ladyship, thereby metamorphosing into
&lt;em&gt;badasses,&lt;/em&gt; are aplenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is alarming that such scenes, in books and films, are often revered and
portrayed as a sort of phoenix-from-the-ashes-moment, worthy of wolf-whistles
and printed merchandise. Even more alarming is how the notion of empowerment has
grown so utterly distorted that nothing, save for panning people who do not go
against the grain, can properly qualify as a wholesome depiction of strong
women. Why, after all, is knitting by the fire, or working in the kitchen so
problematic? Do soldiers magically grow their uniforms? Does food come to us
without the contribution of those who make it? Demeaning the choice of a woman
to do as she pleases or act as she wants, is but an elaborately twisted route,
ultimately ending in degrading womanhood itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When C S Lewis published &lt;em&gt;The Last Battle&lt;/em&gt; in 1956 the final instalment of his
Narnia series, there was quite a bit of hue and outcry over his decision to
close the gates of Narnia upon Susan Pevensie, the older, calmer, more beautiful
and ladylike of the Pevensie sisters. After her family is killed in a car
accident and the souls of her siblings find eternal refuge in Narnia, (a clear
metaphor of an Eden-like realm) Susan is left alone, literally and figuratively
locked out of heaven, her dismissal most summarily executed by Lewis in a couple
of lines: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;My sister Susan,” answered Peter shortly and gravely, “is no longer a friend
of Narnia.&lt;/em&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem? Because it’s not so much a question of &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; her fate
was, as it is of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; she deserved such a peremptory conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Oh Susan!” said Jill. “She’s interested in nothing nowadays except nylons and
lipsticks and invitations. She always was a jolly sight too keen on being
grown-up&lt;/em&gt;…” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, of course. Dresses and makeup, wanting to socialise and have peers;
what could be more heinous a crime for an adolescent? Surely, a crime worthy of
being unpardonable, in a book replete with Biblical imagery and repeated
emphasis on the need to keep the innocence in children untainted, with a fervour
that would make Blake proud. If you are shaking your head at this, slightly
unconvinced, here’s a snippet from Lewis himself, where he makes it clear that
our lipstick-wearing, nylon-loving lady is not enjoying the fruits of the
Promised Land anytime soon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The books don’t tell us what happened to Susan. She is left alive in this
world at the end, having by then turned into a rather silly, conceited young
woman. But there’s plenty of time for her to mend and perhaps she will get to
Aslan’s country in the end… in her own way&lt;/em&gt;…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even while he offers us a glimmer of hope, one can’t help but wince at the last
lines. ‘Plenty of time for her to mend’ what, exactly? What is so indisputably
repulsive about Susan craving extremely normal things, for a girl of her age?
Why is there an immediate need to demonise a female character who chooses to
beautify herself with makeup and pretty clothes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, Susan’s crisis has attracted plenty of sympathetic voices from the
literary community: Philip Pullman, Neil Gaiman, J K Rowling - to name a few,
with Gaiman even creating a sort of spinoff short story with a very Susan-esque
protagonist, giving her a much-needed voice and agency. Still, the older
Pevensie sister remains an outcast of Narnia, a scarring reminder of what
happens to girls who dare to be…well, just be. The ugly implications of
girlish existence in Lewis’ ramrod world of old laws and deep magic are proof
enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Rowling, an interesting and somewhat ironic fact is that while the
&lt;em&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; series, on the forefront, seems chock-full of strong,
three-dimensional female characters, there is something slightly problematic in
the way she treats any character that teeters dangerously into &lt;em&gt;girly-girl&lt;/em&gt;
territory. Two classic examples are Cho Chang, Harry’s first girlfriend, who is
constantly vilified for being ‘too emotional’ and too mopey over her dead
boyfriend, and Fleur Delacour, who while she gets a much better conclusion, is
still written off as the shallow dumb blonde, with a subpar performance in the
Triwizard tournament where she’s the only female competitor. Cho is eventually
cast aside for Ginny, whom Harry considers wonderful because she is ‘rarely
weepy’. Constant misogynistic and slightly racist jabs are directed at Fleur by
none other than Molly and Ginny Weasley, two of the most glorified and
celebrated women in Harry’s life. Not even the minor characters escape
judgement: the Patil twins and Lavender Brown, bubblier and more extroverted
classmates of Hermione, are often reduced to nothing but cartoonish caricatures
vying for Harry and Ron’s affections in the movies. Besides the evocation of
unpleasant racial overtones, it’s something to think about, really. Where does
mild, school cliché-centric humour end and perpetual bracketing-and-bashing of
softness and &lt;em&gt;generic&lt;/em&gt; girlishness begin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal favourite though, is the much-hated Amy March from &lt;em&gt;Little Women&lt;/em&gt;.
Amy’s case is particularly interesting because Alcott never meant to malign her,
no, it’s the audience, unable to look past their ‘JO x LAURIE ENDGAME’ stupor,
who miss the whole point of Amy’s arc - the resourcefulness in her choice to
work within the conventions of traditional femininity instead of rebelling
against it, the raw honesty in her desire as an impoverished girl to enjoy
pretty material pleasures, the flaws and petty mistakes she succumbs to, because
she is not written to be liked, she is written to be &lt;em&gt;real.&lt;/em&gt; Jo’s struggles are
very earthy and very honest, and her staunch refusal to fit in and fulfil
societal expectations is admirable, but Amy’s willingness to maintain a sort of
harmony with her community and work towards self-fulfilment…how is that, in
any way, less gratifying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for that matter, what do all these endless debates actually uncover? What
does this hollow classification system of girls into &lt;em&gt;badasses&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;girly-girls&lt;/em&gt; entail?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is uncertain, but it’s surely not an easy one. One cannot simply go
for a shallow deconstruction of the &lt;em&gt;not-like-other-girls syndrome&lt;/em&gt; without
looking into why this syndrome had to arise at all. And then one finds that the
root of this bizarre phenomenon lies in square one: the &lt;em&gt;trivialisation&lt;/em&gt; of
tenderness in girls and women, leading many to think that female voices and
characters might not be taken seriously unless they are stripped away of all
that could possibly hint at compassion and clemency. While Katniss Everdeen,
Merida and the warrior heroines of some of the later Young Adult franchises may
have arrived at exactly the right moment to prevent oversaturation of the market
by the same kind of feminine representation, the boomerang effect that arose out
of this is girls, in the younger demographic, seeking validation by rejecting
and loudly denouncing traits that could possibly mark them as girly. This
denunciation shows an almost vitriolic hatred in harmless things, marked out as
extremely feminine motifs: anything pink and/or coded as &lt;em&gt;princessy&lt;/em&gt; being the
commonest examples. It’s alarming, it’s potentially harmful that the psyche of
girls is shaped by what they &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; be as opposed to what they prefer to
be, it leans towards the patriarchy having the last laugh at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, as hackneyed as this sounds, there is nothing more
reproachable than the actions and behaviour of one woman being tainted so as to
glorify another. Feminism and badassery don’t spring &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; from elaborate fight
sequences or by being completely stone-cold or perpetually displeased and in a
fighting stance. Yes, female characters so portrayed are valid, beautiful, even
necessary. But they are not the beginning and end of all that’s marvellous and
awe-inspiring about women. It’s definitely heartening to see a much more
positive and varied portrayal of sharp and brilliant women in contemporary
media, who don’t always depend on brawn or magic to achieve unanimous approval,
take the famous Elle Woods (&lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde)&lt;/em&gt; for example, a wonderful
subversion of the dumb blonde stereotype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while we praise Arya for knifing through her tormentors, we cannot forget
Sansa, who comforts children and women with songs during a battle; we can
celebrate angry, rebellious spirits without coming for gentle, tranquil hearts.
We can cherish both sides of the spectrum. We can appreciate that some
rebellions happen quietly, in utter tranquillity, glossed with pink and flowers.
We can, for once, not let the patriarchy win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe, just maybe at the end, Susan, the outcast of Narnia, no longer a
powerful queen but just gloriously and heartbreakingly a human girl, will have
the last laugh.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sritama Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Raise your hand if you remember the Frozen fever that gripped Hollywood - and pretty much the rest of the world too - in the fall of 2013. If you remember the glittering reviews and the innumerable times ‘shattered the glass ceiling’, ‘badass princesses’ or ‘Oscar worthy’ flashed before your eyes, till you were made certain that all of life was meaningless unless you booked first-day, deluxe seat tickets. If you remember how Disney Renaissance enthusiasts, across the globe, made sure you knew that Anna and Elsa were different, unlike the girly-girls you see in other princess movies. They are empowered, with their M-slit gowns and absence of a romantic wedding for an ending, jot that down. If you remember how you found yourself at the theatre, semi-guilt tripped into watching the movie, and finally realised that Jennifer Lee’s retelling of The Snow Queen to be, at most, a well-intentioned but weak tea nod as to what made a woman ‘badass’. It’s funny, actually, because when one sits down to look back upon this legacy of retconning traditionally feminine roles as weak, so as to prop up tomboyish, often desensitised heroines, it’s not just the creators, critics and audience of present day showbiz media who are to blame. Even adored and revered works like those of C S Lewis and Rowling, yes, Rowling, have often sought to perpetuate this trope, often under a carefully arranged veneer of offering simple didactic messages in children’s literature.  So, let’s talk about these girly-girls. Not just the predecessor Disney princesses, no, but the so-called wimpy girls in the media, the featherbrained airheads, the wet blankets. The ones who can’t and won’t punch assassins, knife through captors or ride horses into sandstorms.  For as long as I can remember, it was a struggle for me to find feminine, unapologetically girly characters in literature and media, who were not dismissed as prissy, uppity damsels or useless, shivering waifs whose plethora of interests - sewing, fashion, painting, music, and so forth - were not dismissed as completely decorative and impractical in the general context of the storyline. Worse still, if I did manage to find a rare favourite, it was quite the feat to avoid the barrage of snide remarks from acquaintances, friends, and even more terrible - overenthusiastic vloggers and literary dissenters who were sure to hammer home the fact that Sansa Stark and Amy March are, in fact, horrible sinners doomed to burn in eternal hellfire for their crimes. Sansa Stark, from George R R Martin’s A Song of Ice and Fire, is a textbook example of the stern fact that a non-tomboyish, non-sexualised female lead can do nothing without being written off as a wimp. A young, naive lady of merely eleven, when the series begins, Sansa is held captive, forced to endure the slaughter of her family and shoulders through being a political pawn and a hostage with kindness, bravery and resilience. She has no dragons and no swords, she loves lemon cakes, ballads and handsome knights, and is therefore, by default, painted by the Game of Thrones fandom as a wet blanket airhead. She’s even seen as a veritable ableist demon for not feeling sexually attracted towards a man thrice her age (and he hails from the house that murdered her family, no less). She only manages to garner some sympathy after she is violated in the TV adaptation, a scene that doesn’t even exist in the books. It is hardly surprising that many male characters in the series, who do much worse, get away with their misdeeds way easily. Thrones’ treatment of non-warrior women is particularly repulsive. Sansa is made to mouth lines showing stoic gratitude towards her assaulters for teaching her strength, and another female character, who is often praised for being the snarky cool kid, demurely announces that she doesn’t plan to be useless during battle, namely ‘sit knitting by the fire’. Non-canonical lines, inserted because of the directors’ knowledge that they specifically pander to the audience’s needs and explicit scenes where women condemn softness and acts of ‘predictable’ ladyship, thereby metamorphosing into badasses, are aplenty. It is alarming that such scenes, in books and films, are often revered and portrayed as a sort of phoenix-from-the-ashes-moment, worthy of wolf-whistles and printed merchandise. Even more alarming is how the notion of empowerment has grown so utterly distorted that nothing, save for panning people who do not go against the grain, can properly qualify as a wholesome depiction of strong women. Why, after all, is knitting by the fire, or working in the kitchen so problematic? Do soldiers magically grow their uniforms? Does food come to us without the contribution of those who make it? Demeaning the choice of a woman to do as she pleases or act as she wants, is but an elaborately twisted route, ultimately ending in degrading womanhood itself. When C S Lewis published The Last Battle in 1956 the final instalment of his Narnia series, there was quite a bit of hue and outcry over his decision to close the gates of Narnia upon Susan Pevensie, the older, calmer, more beautiful and ladylike of the Pevensie sisters. After her family is killed in a car accident and the souls of her siblings find eternal refuge in Narnia, (a clear metaphor of an Eden-like realm) Susan is left alone, literally and figuratively locked out of heaven, her dismissal most summarily executed by Lewis in a couple of lines:  “My sister Susan,” answered Peter shortly and gravely, “is no longer a friend of Narnia.”  Why is this a problem? Because it’s not so much a question of what her fate was, as it is of why she deserved such a peremptory conclusion: “Oh Susan!” said Jill. “She’s interested in nothing nowadays except nylons and lipsticks and invitations. She always was a jolly sight too keen on being grown-up…”  Ah, yes, of course. Dresses and makeup, wanting to socialise and have peers; what could be more heinous a crime for an adolescent? Surely, a crime worthy of being unpardonable, in a book replete with Biblical imagery and repeated emphasis on the need to keep the innocence in children untainted, with a fervour that would make Blake proud. If you are shaking your head at this, slightly unconvinced, here’s a snippet from Lewis himself, where he makes it clear that our lipstick-wearing, nylon-loving lady is not enjoying the fruits of the Promised Land anytime soon: “The books don’t tell us what happened to Susan. She is left alive in this world at the end, having by then turned into a rather silly, conceited young woman. But there’s plenty of time for her to mend and perhaps she will get to Aslan’s country in the end… in her own way…” Even while he offers us a glimmer of hope, one can’t help but wince at the last lines. ‘Plenty of time for her to mend’ what, exactly? What is so indisputably repulsive about Susan craving extremely normal things, for a girl of her age? Why is there an immediate need to demonise a female character who chooses to beautify herself with makeup and pretty clothes? Since then, Susan’s crisis has attracted plenty of sympathetic voices from the literary community: Philip Pullman, Neil Gaiman, J K Rowling - to name a few, with Gaiman even creating a sort of spinoff short story with a very Susan-esque protagonist, giving her a much-needed voice and agency. Still, the older Pevensie sister remains an outcast of Narnia, a scarring reminder of what happens to girls who dare to be…well, just be. The ugly implications of girlish existence in Lewis’ ramrod world of old laws and deep magic are proof enough. Speaking of Rowling, an interesting and somewhat ironic fact is that while the Harry Potter series, on the forefront, seems chock-full of strong, three-dimensional female characters, there is something slightly problematic in the way she treats any character that teeters dangerously into girly-girl territory. Two classic examples are Cho Chang, Harry’s first girlfriend, who is constantly vilified for being ‘too emotional’ and too mopey over her dead boyfriend, and Fleur Delacour, who while she gets a much better conclusion, is still written off as the shallow dumb blonde, with a subpar performance in the Triwizard tournament where she’s the only female competitor. Cho is eventually cast aside for Ginny, whom Harry considers wonderful because she is ‘rarely weepy’. Constant misogynistic and slightly racist jabs are directed at Fleur by none other than Molly and Ginny Weasley, two of the most glorified and celebrated women in Harry’s life. Not even the minor characters escape judgement: the Patil twins and Lavender Brown, bubblier and more extroverted classmates of Hermione, are often reduced to nothing but cartoonish caricatures vying for Harry and Ron’s affections in the movies. Besides the evocation of unpleasant racial overtones, it’s something to think about, really. Where does mild, school cliché-centric humour end and perpetual bracketing-and-bashing of softness and generic girlishness begin? My personal favourite though, is the much-hated Amy March from Little Women. Amy’s case is particularly interesting because Alcott never meant to malign her, no, it’s the audience, unable to look past their ‘JO x LAURIE ENDGAME’ stupor, who miss the whole point of Amy’s arc - the resourcefulness in her choice to work within the conventions of traditional femininity instead of rebelling against it, the raw honesty in her desire as an impoverished girl to enjoy pretty material pleasures, the flaws and petty mistakes she succumbs to, because she is not written to be liked, she is written to be real. Jo’s struggles are very earthy and very honest, and her staunch refusal to fit in and fulfil societal expectations is admirable, but Amy’s willingness to maintain a sort of harmony with her community and work towards self-fulfilment…how is that, in any way, less gratifying? And for that matter, what do all these endless debates actually uncover? What does this hollow classification system of girls into badasses and girly-girls entail? The answer is uncertain, but it’s surely not an easy one. One cannot simply go for a shallow deconstruction of the not-like-other-girls syndrome without looking into why this syndrome had to arise at all. And then one finds that the root of this bizarre phenomenon lies in square one: the trivialisation of tenderness in girls and women, leading many to think that female voices and characters might not be taken seriously unless they are stripped away of all that could possibly hint at compassion and clemency. While Katniss Everdeen, Merida and the warrior heroines of some of the later Young Adult franchises may have arrived at exactly the right moment to prevent oversaturation of the market by the same kind of feminine representation, the boomerang effect that arose out of this is girls, in the younger demographic, seeking validation by rejecting and loudly denouncing traits that could possibly mark them as girly. This denunciation shows an almost vitriolic hatred in harmless things, marked out as extremely feminine motifs: anything pink and/or coded as princessy being the commonest examples. It’s alarming, it’s potentially harmful that the psyche of girls is shaped by what they shouldn’t be as opposed to what they prefer to be, it leans towards the patriarchy having the last laugh at the end. Most importantly, as hackneyed as this sounds, there is nothing more reproachable than the actions and behaviour of one woman being tainted so as to glorify another. Feminism and badassery don’t spring just from elaborate fight sequences or by being completely stone-cold or perpetually displeased and in a fighting stance. Yes, female characters so portrayed are valid, beautiful, even necessary. But they are not the beginning and end of all that’s marvellous and awe-inspiring about women. It’s definitely heartening to see a much more positive and varied portrayal of sharp and brilliant women in contemporary media, who don’t always depend on brawn or magic to achieve unanimous approval, take the famous Elle Woods (Legally Blonde) for example, a wonderful subversion of the dumb blonde stereotype. So while we praise Arya for knifing through her tormentors, we cannot forget Sansa, who comforts children and women with songs during a battle; we can celebrate angry, rebellious spirits without coming for gentle, tranquil hearts. We can cherish both sides of the spectrum. We can appreciate that some rebellions happen quietly, in utter tranquillity, glossed with pink and flowers. We can, for once, not let the patriarchy win. And maybe, just maybe at the end, Susan, the outcast of Narnia, no longer a powerful queen but just gloriously and heartbreakingly a human girl, will have the last laugh.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Capitalist Realism</title><link href="/Capitalist-Realism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalist Realism" /><published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Capitalist-Realism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Capitalist-Realism">&lt;p&gt;The Mayan calendar had prophesied that the world would end in 2012. Various
scientists have predicted that life on Earth will end after an asteroid hits the
planet. All these forecasts seem more or less acceptable to the general
populace. But will communism ever be the next world order? Not a chance. If one
were to inspect carefully, it is easier for us to imagine the end of the world
than to think that an alternative to capitalism exists. It is precisely this
phenomenon that Mark Fisher wrote about in his book, &lt;em&gt;Capitalist Realism - Is
There No Alternative?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalist Realism is the acceptance that “not only is capitalism the only
viable political and economic system but also that it is now impossible even to
imagine a coherent alternative to it.” While there is an acceptance of the many
faults in capitalism, the ramifications of those faults are often neglected or
undermined. Capitalist realism exists because it has managed to become
irreplaceable to us and has killed any sort of hope for a new system to take its
place. The narrative says that though we may not live in a condition of perfect
‘Goodness’, we must be grateful that we are saved from the ultimate ‘Evil’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is vehement in the criticism of any alternatives that may be present - while things may not be ideal, the alternatives are much worse. Here, it draws
power by painting contrasts between democracies and dictatorships, between civil
liberties and stark inequality - where one is shown to be a lesser evil, even if
reality may speak differently. The bombing of thousands of innocents in Syria is
justified, as long as it does not imitate the ruthless persecution or ethnic
cleansing that happened in countries like Rwanda. By characterising itself as a
hail-Mary from the disaster that any other alternative would lead to, capitalism
poses as a protector and gives way to capitalist realism - the foregone
conclusion that what persists is the best out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even for those who realise the problem, there is a severe lack of action. What
could be an explanation for this? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea theorised is that the repetition of history has saturated us. In the
time and age we are in, it seems that every action we take has already been
taken in the past. Imagine the despondency of a generation that has come after
history, “whose every move is anticipated, tracked, bought and sold before it
had even happened.” Every act of ours is an experienced cliche, already noted in
the accounts of the past. No protest is novel. The realisation is in itself a
cliche. When all our attempts to create history are old and uninspired, it
eventually leads to a detached witnessing of events instead of active
involvement and engagement. There is a saturation of history, which inspires a
sense of cultural and political exhaustion - almost sterility - into old and
young minds alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger threat of the indoctrination of capitalism is that it has penetrated
our unconscious. Our unconscious shapes our desires, hopes and aspirations. If
one introspects, he/she would realise that our ambitions are driven by a
capitalist narrative - the image of success for us is a rich, privileged
businessman, who enjoys a position of social, economic and political capital in
society. Even while mentally accepting that money is tokenistic and “cannot buy
happiness,” we fetishise money. This acceptance of capitalist aims by society as
a whole and the subsequent trickle down to an individual level further solidify
its existence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengthening the Roots of Capitalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to think of Stalin, Hitler or Mussolini succeeding without
propaganda - their rallies were charged with nationalist sentiment and were
publicised to the extent that the idea of a Great Reich was almost shoved down
people’s throats. But the way that capitalism promotes itself is more nuanced -
the anti-capitalist sentiment is co-opted into capitalism. In a majority of
Hollywood movies, the villain turns out to be the CEO of an evil corporation or
a wealthy fanatic in retirement. Capitalist realism, therefore, is dangerous as
it gets away with including critique within its structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We accept that capitalism has problems - but the way we perceive the solution to
these problems is problematic in itself. Poverty and income inequality are
accepted faults of capitalism. Ask yourself - can we have a world without
poverty? Can we have one where there is income equity? Can an egalitarian
society exist? The answer will be no. Sure, we are striving towards these goals,
but their actual achievement is &lt;em&gt;utopian&lt;/em&gt;. Capitalist realism allows the
acceptance of a state of crisis in a continuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to challenge this idea is to identify how capitalist realism
escapes our notice on a day-to-day basis. Fisher gives three simple examples for
us to understand this: climate change, bureaucracy, and mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is built on the idea of consumerism. A capitalist state aims to grow
and expand markets continuously. A system that wants to be on its feet
constantly, that is principally in support of bulldozing through time for
profits, can never simultaneously aim for sustenance and stability. This
dichotomy in the theory of capitalism itself is something that often gets
unnoticed. Instead of saying that institutionalised inequalities are a result of
consumerism, the narrative is spun on its head by saying that what we buy is
going to change the principle of the political theory. For example, we are told
to consume alternatives instead of questioning the practicality of usage and
reducing our consumption. Buying the right thing, from the right place is
projected as a long term solution - but it still feeds into a structure that
advocates for consumerism. Climate change can never be solved or dealt with in a
capitalist construct because expansion is the ultimate goal and usage of
resources is a way to achieve the ‘target’. We will always, despite our best
efforts, hold resources secondary to this manic need for material progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberal and neo-liberal societies, while criticising socialism and communism,
highlight the problem with giving excess power to bureaucratic structures.
Bureaucrats often exploit their power and it leads to corruption and
inefficiency in the economy. The winning pitch for capitalism to be accepted
originally was to promise that bureaucracy would vanish. Except, what is the
status quo like? Even in late capitalism, bureaucracy still exists. The
difference is that it is morphed into a different kind of bureaucracy - one that
is allowed to penetrate all forms of structures through things like demanding
memos and answering to superiors. This bureaucracy is enforced at all levels of
management, establishing its place in the micro-levels of the economy.
Capitalist realism further reinforces that we cannot ‘practically’ do without
this culture of constantly answering to someone and being monitored, making the
control of societies a self-enforcing reality. Essentially, capitalism has
failed to differentiate itself from its alternatives on this metric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism, in its want to create overachievers and socially acceptable success
stories, has created ‘hustle culture’ - one that essentially relies on the idea
that &lt;em&gt;one mustn’t stop&lt;/em&gt;. If one chooses to listen to music instead of a podcast
on the way home, he/she is actively choosing to not add to his/her productivity.
If one does not succeed, the burden of the failure is wholly individualistic -
one must work harder or do things a particular way because regardless of the
kind of burdens one faces (for instance sociological burdens like racism),
anyone who strives enough &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; succeed. As a society, we have
pressurised people to the extent that mental health issues are on the rise among
young people - and no one ties it back to the inherent dysfunction in
capitalism. Instead of taking responsibility for this mass pressurisation, we
have privatised stress to be caused by individual chemical imbalances. By
placing the onus of a healthy state of mind exclusively on the individual
instead of accepting how society has failed him/her, we have allowed capitalist
realism to become our inevitable reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we establish capitalist realism’s claim to fame, one must wonder how it
sustains itself. Lacan argues that the concept of the ‘big Other’ in this
regard. The PR image that capitalism creates is sustained by those who are
willing to buy into this marketing. The Other is simply one who experiences life
differently even after knowing what the truth may be. The difference between
what one chooses to accept and what exists primarily sustains the ordinary
interactions we have daily. When the Other accepts reality as it is and chooses
to ignore the narrative that is set out, it creates an abnormality. When
Khrushchev’s speech in 1965 accepted the faults in the Soviet Union, it caused
an uproar. It was not as if people did not know of the kind of human rights
violations and corruption that was happening - the declaration just ensured that
‘the Other’ could not ignore it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, unlike Khrushchev in the Soviet Union, there is no incentive for anyone
with legitimacy in the Other’s eye to inform the Other of the kind of abominable
structure it is living in. The persons considered by the Other as leaders enjoy
the power that they hold and acceptance of truth by the masses will threaten
their hold over being able to control narratives. Thus, when people who can make
a difference choose not to, it serves to further crystallise capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Playing the Blame Game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with capitalism is accountability. While, in principle, corporations
are supposed to be the drivers of growth, they do not take responsibility as
they aren’t supposed to look after the welfare of every citizen operating within
the ambit of the care of the government. But the government does not take
responsibility either because it says that its role is minimised and unwanted.
So, any anger towards the system is directed towards an abstraction that is,
thus, unresponsive - someone did something wrong and we are now left with the
burden of cleaning up the mess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to hold collective responsibility for issues that plague all of us -
like climate change needs to be addressed by each one of us to get any tangible
change. The genius of capitalism is especially evident here - it protects itself
while making individuals scapegoats. For any scandal that happens, we tend to
burden the individual and ask for a more ‘morally upright’ replacement. However,
countless examples of upright individuals succumbing to the pressures and power
of a particular appointment and ending up corrupt are a testament to the fact
that vices are engendered in and by the system - as long as the system persists,
these vices will continue to sustain themselves. Therefore, Žižek argues that
placing individual responsibility due to the need for “ethical immediacy” lets
the system shirk the responsibility of cleaning itself up. He uses the example
of the 2008 credit crisis, wherein the blame was put on those ‘horrible people’
who abused the system rather than on the system that encouraged this culture of
abuse itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the acceptance of the possibility of an alternative to capitalism, none
of these problems will be effectively tackled and capitalist realism will
continue to dominate - perhaps as an unconscious undertone, but with immense
power over our economic, social and political interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Road Ahead &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may be a glimmer of hope for the world yet. Neoliberal capitalism is no
longer secure in its throne as the days of democratic socialism are on the
horizon. As the study of late capitalism and its critique increases, protesting
voices have emerged.  There is an increasing acceptance of left leaders like
Jeremy Corbyn, Alexandria Cortez, Bernie Sanders, and their policies in states
that have been the poster-children for capitalism. Healthcare for all, free
education and opportunity for the underprivileged are being accepted by a vast
majority of people - especially those who have been victims of capitalist
structures. The gravity of the stark income inequality is being acknowledged and
called out. Corporates and the wealthy are under increasing pressure and
scrutiny to pay higher taxes and fulfil any responsibility they have towards the
less privileged. While capitalist realism paints a bleak picture of us as a
civilisation, perhaps it is time for the sleeping phoenix to rise from the ashes
and take us to a better tomorrow. The cracks in the existing system are more
prominent and visible today than ever before - the responsibility of analysing
them and creating a new order is now on us to fulfil.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aanandi Arjun</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The Mayan calendar had prophesied that the world would end in 2012. Various scientists have predicted that life on Earth will end after an asteroid hits the planet. All these forecasts seem more or less acceptable to the general populace. But will communism ever be the next world order? Not a chance. If one were to inspect carefully, it is easier for us to imagine the end of the world than to think that an alternative to capitalism exists. It is precisely this phenomenon that Mark Fisher wrote about in his book, Capitalist Realism - Is There No Alternative? Capitalist Realism is the acceptance that “not only is capitalism the only viable political and economic system but also that it is now impossible even to imagine a coherent alternative to it.” While there is an acceptance of the many faults in capitalism, the ramifications of those faults are often neglected or undermined. Capitalist realism exists because it has managed to become irreplaceable to us and has killed any sort of hope for a new system to take its place. The narrative says that though we may not live in a condition of perfect ‘Goodness’, we must be grateful that we are saved from the ultimate ‘Evil’.  Capitalism is vehement in the criticism of any alternatives that may be present - while things may not be ideal, the alternatives are much worse. Here, it draws power by painting contrasts between democracies and dictatorships, between civil liberties and stark inequality - where one is shown to be a lesser evil, even if reality may speak differently. The bombing of thousands of innocents in Syria is justified, as long as it does not imitate the ruthless persecution or ethnic cleansing that happened in countries like Rwanda. By characterising itself as a hail-Mary from the disaster that any other alternative would lead to, capitalism poses as a protector and gives way to capitalist realism - the foregone conclusion that what persists is the best out there. Even for those who realise the problem, there is a severe lack of action. What could be an explanation for this?  One idea theorised is that the repetition of history has saturated us. In the time and age we are in, it seems that every action we take has already been taken in the past. Imagine the despondency of a generation that has come after history, “whose every move is anticipated, tracked, bought and sold before it had even happened.” Every act of ours is an experienced cliche, already noted in the accounts of the past. No protest is novel. The realisation is in itself a cliche. When all our attempts to create history are old and uninspired, it eventually leads to a detached witnessing of events instead of active involvement and engagement. There is a saturation of history, which inspires a sense of cultural and political exhaustion - almost sterility - into old and young minds alike. The bigger threat of the indoctrination of capitalism is that it has penetrated our unconscious. Our unconscious shapes our desires, hopes and aspirations. If one introspects, he/she would realise that our ambitions are driven by a capitalist narrative - the image of success for us is a rich, privileged businessman, who enjoys a position of social, economic and political capital in society. Even while mentally accepting that money is tokenistic and “cannot buy happiness,” we fetishise money. This acceptance of capitalist aims by society as a whole and the subsequent trickle down to an individual level further solidify its existence.  Strengthening the Roots of Capitalism It is impossible to think of Stalin, Hitler or Mussolini succeeding without propaganda - their rallies were charged with nationalist sentiment and were publicised to the extent that the idea of a Great Reich was almost shoved down people’s throats. But the way that capitalism promotes itself is more nuanced - the anti-capitalist sentiment is co-opted into capitalism. In a majority of Hollywood movies, the villain turns out to be the CEO of an evil corporation or a wealthy fanatic in retirement. Capitalist realism, therefore, is dangerous as it gets away with including critique within its structure. We accept that capitalism has problems - but the way we perceive the solution to these problems is problematic in itself. Poverty and income inequality are accepted faults of capitalism. Ask yourself - can we have a world without poverty? Can we have one where there is income equity? Can an egalitarian society exist? The answer will be no. Sure, we are striving towards these goals, but their actual achievement is utopian. Capitalist realism allows the acceptance of a state of crisis in a continuum. The only way to challenge this idea is to identify how capitalist realism escapes our notice on a day-to-day basis. Fisher gives three simple examples for us to understand this: climate change, bureaucracy, and mental health. Capitalism is built on the idea of consumerism. A capitalist state aims to grow and expand markets continuously. A system that wants to be on its feet constantly, that is principally in support of bulldozing through time for profits, can never simultaneously aim for sustenance and stability. This dichotomy in the theory of capitalism itself is something that often gets unnoticed. Instead of saying that institutionalised inequalities are a result of consumerism, the narrative is spun on its head by saying that what we buy is going to change the principle of the political theory. For example, we are told to consume alternatives instead of questioning the practicality of usage and reducing our consumption. Buying the right thing, from the right place is projected as a long term solution - but it still feeds into a structure that advocates for consumerism. Climate change can never be solved or dealt with in a capitalist construct because expansion is the ultimate goal and usage of resources is a way to achieve the ‘target’. We will always, despite our best efforts, hold resources secondary to this manic need for material progress. Liberal and neo-liberal societies, while criticising socialism and communism, highlight the problem with giving excess power to bureaucratic structures. Bureaucrats often exploit their power and it leads to corruption and inefficiency in the economy. The winning pitch for capitalism to be accepted originally was to promise that bureaucracy would vanish. Except, what is the status quo like? Even in late capitalism, bureaucracy still exists. The difference is that it is morphed into a different kind of bureaucracy - one that is allowed to penetrate all forms of structures through things like demanding memos and answering to superiors. This bureaucracy is enforced at all levels of management, establishing its place in the micro-levels of the economy. Capitalist realism further reinforces that we cannot ‘practically’ do without this culture of constantly answering to someone and being monitored, making the control of societies a self-enforcing reality. Essentially, capitalism has failed to differentiate itself from its alternatives on this metric. Capitalism, in its want to create overachievers and socially acceptable success stories, has created ‘hustle culture’ - one that essentially relies on the idea that one mustn’t stop. If one chooses to listen to music instead of a podcast on the way home, he/she is actively choosing to not add to his/her productivity. If one does not succeed, the burden of the failure is wholly individualistic - one must work harder or do things a particular way because regardless of the kind of burdens one faces (for instance sociological burdens like racism), anyone who strives enough can and must succeed. As a society, we have pressurised people to the extent that mental health issues are on the rise among young people - and no one ties it back to the inherent dysfunction in capitalism. Instead of taking responsibility for this mass pressurisation, we have privatised stress to be caused by individual chemical imbalances. By placing the onus of a healthy state of mind exclusively on the individual instead of accepting how society has failed him/her, we have allowed capitalist realism to become our inevitable reality.  Once we establish capitalist realism’s claim to fame, one must wonder how it sustains itself. Lacan argues that the concept of the ‘big Other’ in this regard. The PR image that capitalism creates is sustained by those who are willing to buy into this marketing. The Other is simply one who experiences life differently even after knowing what the truth may be. The difference between what one chooses to accept and what exists primarily sustains the ordinary interactions we have daily. When the Other accepts reality as it is and chooses to ignore the narrative that is set out, it creates an abnormality. When Khrushchev’s speech in 1965 accepted the faults in the Soviet Union, it caused an uproar. It was not as if people did not know of the kind of human rights violations and corruption that was happening - the declaration just ensured that ‘the Other’ could not ignore it anymore. However, unlike Khrushchev in the Soviet Union, there is no incentive for anyone with legitimacy in the Other’s eye to inform the Other of the kind of abominable structure it is living in. The persons considered by the Other as leaders enjoy the power that they hold and acceptance of truth by the masses will threaten their hold over being able to control narratives. Thus, when people who can make a difference choose not to, it serves to further crystallise capitalism. Playing the Blame Game The problem with capitalism is accountability. While, in principle, corporations are supposed to be the drivers of growth, they do not take responsibility as they aren’t supposed to look after the welfare of every citizen operating within the ambit of the care of the government. But the government does not take responsibility either because it says that its role is minimised and unwanted. So, any anger towards the system is directed towards an abstraction that is, thus, unresponsive - someone did something wrong and we are now left with the burden of cleaning up the mess.  We need to hold collective responsibility for issues that plague all of us - like climate change needs to be addressed by each one of us to get any tangible change. The genius of capitalism is especially evident here - it protects itself while making individuals scapegoats. For any scandal that happens, we tend to burden the individual and ask for a more ‘morally upright’ replacement. However, countless examples of upright individuals succumbing to the pressures and power of a particular appointment and ending up corrupt are a testament to the fact that vices are engendered in and by the system - as long as the system persists, these vices will continue to sustain themselves. Therefore, Žižek argues that placing individual responsibility due to the need for “ethical immediacy” lets the system shirk the responsibility of cleaning itself up. He uses the example of the 2008 credit crisis, wherein the blame was put on those ‘horrible people’ who abused the system rather than on the system that encouraged this culture of abuse itself. Without the acceptance of the possibility of an alternative to capitalism, none of these problems will be effectively tackled and capitalist realism will continue to dominate - perhaps as an unconscious undertone, but with immense power over our economic, social and political interactions. The Road Ahead  There may be a glimmer of hope for the world yet. Neoliberal capitalism is no longer secure in its throne as the days of democratic socialism are on the horizon. As the study of late capitalism and its critique increases, protesting voices have emerged.  There is an increasing acceptance of left leaders like Jeremy Corbyn, Alexandria Cortez, Bernie Sanders, and their policies in states that have been the poster-children for capitalism. Healthcare for all, free education and opportunity for the underprivileged are being accepted by a vast majority of people - especially those who have been victims of capitalist structures. The gravity of the stark income inequality is being acknowledged and called out. Corporates and the wealthy are under increasing pressure and scrutiny to pay higher taxes and fulfil any responsibility they have towards the less privileged. While capitalist realism paints a bleak picture of us as a civilisation, perhaps it is time for the sleeping phoenix to rise from the ashes and take us to a better tomorrow. The cracks in the existing system are more prominent and visible today than ever before - the responsibility of analysing them and creating a new order is now on us to fulfil.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk</title><link href="/Beauty-and-Brazen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk" /><published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Beauty-and-Brazen</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-and-Brazen">&lt;p&gt;“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his
humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in
&lt;em&gt;Berserk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of
other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the
least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an
adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his
life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close
to the &lt;strong&gt;Truth&lt;/strong&gt; and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more
interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he
know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to
script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche
refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered
to be, the future of humanity, &lt;em&gt;Ubermensch&lt;/em&gt;, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’.
Thus begins the journey of &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; and its protagonist, the most bad*rse
anime/manga character in history, &lt;em&gt;Guts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the
very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story
is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate
&lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; overtake him and he &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be entwined with his future, with what is
already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not
always free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in
&lt;em&gt;Twilight of the Idols&lt;/em&gt;, where he referred to causality as the cause of
humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning
to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause
behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to
support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; that free
will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians
exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche
thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a
protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it,
at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been
hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him.
When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him.
Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to
survive in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary
group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He
falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and
the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith
sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as &lt;em&gt;Eclipse&lt;/em&gt;, is a momentous image
of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get
killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get
violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He
does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining
several scars of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably
his most interesting piece of work, &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; introduced the
concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and
philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is
an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps:
The Camel, The Lion and The Child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the
knowledge of the &lt;em&gt;Dragon&lt;/em&gt; (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore
listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself.
As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told
to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’
demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a
Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system
in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The
Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of
the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the
system himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to
Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being
who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to
struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’
transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to
integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who
defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very
epitome of the Overman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the
Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company,
unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a
society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man.
Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the
other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of
this ambition. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in the same manner, brings about the reference of
Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not
understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand
the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the
light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all
their goals and dreams as one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of
Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to
resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true
goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs
and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been
highlighted in &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, where we are informed of the existence of a
monotheistic religion, termed as the &lt;em&gt;Holy See&lt;/em&gt;, whose ideals bear similarity to
Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who
could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro
Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all
odds, through Guts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is
all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit
of a fighter. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and
deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled
under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher
Man’, despite not being from the nobility. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in Berserk. Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close to the Truth and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered to be, the future of humanity, Ubermensch, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’. Thus begins the journey of Berserk and its protagonist, the most bad*rse anime/manga character in history, Guts. Berserk is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate will overtake him and he will be entwined with his future, with what is already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not always free. Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in Twilight of the Idols, where he referred to causality as the cause of humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in Twilight that free will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge. Berserk challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it, at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him. When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him. Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to survive in the wild. Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power. The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as Eclipse, is a momentous image of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining several scars of his own. Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably his most interesting piece of work, Thus Spoke Zarathustra introduced the concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps: The Camel, The Lion and The Child. The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the knowledge of the Dragon (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself. As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel. When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’ demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the system himself. That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’ transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very epitome of the Overman. A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company, unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man. Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of this ambition. Berserk, in the same manner, brings about the reference of Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all their goals and dreams as one.” Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been highlighted in Berserk, where we are informed of the existence of a monotheistic religion, termed as the Holy See, whose ideals bear similarity to Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all odds, through Guts. Berserk has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit of a fighter. Berserk, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher Man’, despite not being from the nobility. </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Only I Exist</title><link href="/Only-I-Exist" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only I Exist" /><published>2019-08-01T11:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-01T11:45:00+00:00</updated><id>/Only-I-Exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Only-I-Exist">&lt;p&gt;Questions have been the very heart and soul of philosophy and, unlike any other
discipline, it has raised more questions than it has answered. The dire
intellectual need to discern the abstract, in the form of reality and truth,
consumes all thinkers alike. They all seek answers that spring from an objective
source to bring an end to the seemingly perpetual quest for knowledge. However,
it is not that simple. Philosophy, over the years, has gotten mired down in
countless irrefutable hypotheses, thriving on the body of possibilities and
reason. This is especially true of metaphysical discussions, which have resulted
in the blossoming of unconventional, at times, bizarre theories to explain
reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;? One way to grasp reality amounts to the way you understand the
world external to you. But what if that understanding is faulty? Take, for
instance, the understanding of the earth as a flat disc. Today we can ‘claim to
know’ that the earth is spherical, yet in those times the supposed axiom of the
earth being flat was the foundational truth on which the early peoples developed
an understanding of other concepts and ideas. This is disconcerting, because
there’s a pretty high possibility of us assuming a false belief as an
irrefutable fact, because although there are proofs to make claims, science per
se isn’t perfect, just workable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now go even further to understand the concept of matter that we &lt;em&gt;assume&lt;/em&gt;
to be real. As Bertrand Russell discussed in his &lt;em&gt;Problems of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;,
whatever we perceive is the mere appearance of an object, as opposed to its
reality. The surface of an apple that is seen with the naked eye is very
different when viewed under the microscope, its colour varies with the changing
source of light too. In short, what your perception leads you into believing is
real is actually nothing but the appearance of the apple, in varying degrees of
magnification. If this is the case, then the existence of the apple becomes
questionable. Does an &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; apple exist at all? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some, it does not. A philosopher named Bishop Berkeley, for instance, argued
in favour of &lt;em&gt;immaterialism&lt;/em&gt; – that rather than being a form of matter, an apple
in actuality is the amalgamation of several qualities which cannot exist
independent of the mind. You can test this, try defining an apple devoid of its
qualities and properties. It is almost impossible to do so. So are the qualities
(of the objects) that we perceive in the universe, are they created by our
imagination or do they exist as a comprehensive whole contained in an underlying
substratum called matter? This is the starting point of the idea of ‘solipsism.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solipsism revolves around the idea that only I exist and weave the fabric of my
reality. The &lt;em&gt;certainty&lt;/em&gt; I can ascribe to my experience is limited to my &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt;
existence and thoughts, everything else in this world, including the existence
of this article, is doubtable. This may seem very absurd to hear, at first, but
it’s a possibility that is hard to deny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The empirical experiences one goes through forms an essential part of their own
subjective reality. One can, in no way validate the experience of anybody else
(egocentric predicament). One’s understanding of the apple is theirs alone and
cannot be grasped by anyone else. The comprehension of all that is external to
their consciousness is beyond their ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, your thoughts and ideas are the only undisputed and obvious entities that
exist. This is to say that all humans have their own psychological conceptions
whose understanding is forbidden to others. And so, we cannot be certain of the
independent existence of other bodies and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of solipsism has subtly remained embedded in other philosophical
ideas. One such idea was propounded by Rene Descartes’ principle of “&lt;em&gt;Cogito,
ergo sum&lt;/em&gt;” (I think, therefore I am). Descartes was convinced that he was being
deceived, by an evil genius, into believing some essentially flawed concepts as
true. Maintaining that every thought is dubitable, he cleansed his mind of all
distortions and came up with the most irrefutable, indubitable truth (as the
basic frame of reference to understand all the other truths)- “I think therefore
I am.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solipsism takes this idea of &lt;em&gt;Cogito&lt;/em&gt; way too seriously. Nothing but the mind is
true for the solipsist. While Descartes did believe in rationality and
mathematics as a means to search for truth, for the solipsist (metaphysically
and epistemologically) such conceptions are your own inventions, something you
make up in your head, bereft of any independent existence (here your
consciousness shall assume the place of Descartes’ demon). One can understand it
as a perpetual state of hallucination, characterised by vivid details. If you
are a solipsist, then whatever you experience, this article, your friends,
family, nature, all the coolest things in the world are actually an invention of
your own! An understanding of the world devoid of the ego is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However fascinating it may sound, solipsism has some dire outcomes, when
accepted as a lifestyle choice. It possesses the potential to throw the world
into utter chaos. Since everything that one sees around them is a creation of
their imagination, they would have all the power of calling the shots and
asserting their dominance over the entire world around them. Morality and ethics
would lose their credibility and an individual’s will would determine the fate
of all that is around them. Or else, it could make a person abnegate everything,
despairing about the loneliness they experience every second of their existence,
since they have no proof of the existence of any other. Either way, solipsism
could inflict more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult to refute, solipsism continues to haunt the imagination of humankind.
However, rejecting the theory altogether wouldn’t be right either, given the
crucial questions it raises on reality and the foundations of epistemological
speculations. The question of solipsism has stirred minds and propelled
philosophy from a state of certainty to that of unpredictability, thereby adding
profundity and beauty to the subject. And as long as such ingenious thoughts
continue to flow in the body of philosophy, the answer to this problem, along
with all problems, I believe, is not too far away.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Questions have been the very heart and soul of philosophy and, unlike any other discipline, it has raised more questions than it has answered. The dire intellectual need to discern the abstract, in the form of reality and truth, consumes all thinkers alike. They all seek answers that spring from an objective source to bring an end to the seemingly perpetual quest for knowledge. However, it is not that simple. Philosophy, over the years, has gotten mired down in countless irrefutable hypotheses, thriving on the body of possibilities and reason. This is especially true of metaphysical discussions, which have resulted in the blossoming of unconventional, at times, bizarre theories to explain reality. What is real? One way to grasp reality amounts to the way you understand the world external to you. But what if that understanding is faulty? Take, for instance, the understanding of the earth as a flat disc. Today we can ‘claim to know’ that the earth is spherical, yet in those times the supposed axiom of the earth being flat was the foundational truth on which the early peoples developed an understanding of other concepts and ideas. This is disconcerting, because there’s a pretty high possibility of us assuming a false belief as an irrefutable fact, because although there are proofs to make claims, science per se isn’t perfect, just workable.  Let us now go even further to understand the concept of matter that we assume to be real. As Bertrand Russell discussed in his Problems of Philosophy, whatever we perceive is the mere appearance of an object, as opposed to its reality. The surface of an apple that is seen with the naked eye is very different when viewed under the microscope, its colour varies with the changing source of light too. In short, what your perception leads you into believing is real is actually nothing but the appearance of the apple, in varying degrees of magnification. If this is the case, then the existence of the apple becomes questionable. Does an actual apple exist at all?  For some, it does not. A philosopher named Bishop Berkeley, for instance, argued in favour of immaterialism – that rather than being a form of matter, an apple in actuality is the amalgamation of several qualities which cannot exist independent of the mind. You can test this, try defining an apple devoid of its qualities and properties. It is almost impossible to do so. So are the qualities (of the objects) that we perceive in the universe, are they created by our imagination or do they exist as a comprehensive whole contained in an underlying substratum called matter? This is the starting point of the idea of ‘solipsism.’ Solipsism revolves around the idea that only I exist and weave the fabric of my reality. The certainty I can ascribe to my experience is limited to my own existence and thoughts, everything else in this world, including the existence of this article, is doubtable. This may seem very absurd to hear, at first, but it’s a possibility that is hard to deny. The empirical experiences one goes through forms an essential part of their own subjective reality. One can, in no way validate the experience of anybody else (egocentric predicament). One’s understanding of the apple is theirs alone and cannot be grasped by anyone else. The comprehension of all that is external to their consciousness is beyond their ability. Thus, your thoughts and ideas are the only undisputed and obvious entities that exist. This is to say that all humans have their own psychological conceptions whose understanding is forbidden to others. And so, we cannot be certain of the independent existence of other bodies and minds. The theory of solipsism has subtly remained embedded in other philosophical ideas. One such idea was propounded by Rene Descartes’ principle of “Cogito, ergo sum” (I think, therefore I am). Descartes was convinced that he was being deceived, by an evil genius, into believing some essentially flawed concepts as true. Maintaining that every thought is dubitable, he cleansed his mind of all distortions and came up with the most irrefutable, indubitable truth (as the basic frame of reference to understand all the other truths)- “I think therefore I am.”  Solipsism takes this idea of Cogito way too seriously. Nothing but the mind is true for the solipsist. While Descartes did believe in rationality and mathematics as a means to search for truth, for the solipsist (metaphysically and epistemologically) such conceptions are your own inventions, something you make up in your head, bereft of any independent existence (here your consciousness shall assume the place of Descartes’ demon). One can understand it as a perpetual state of hallucination, characterised by vivid details. If you are a solipsist, then whatever you experience, this article, your friends, family, nature, all the coolest things in the world are actually an invention of your own! An understanding of the world devoid of the ego is impossible. However fascinating it may sound, solipsism has some dire outcomes, when accepted as a lifestyle choice. It possesses the potential to throw the world into utter chaos. Since everything that one sees around them is a creation of their imagination, they would have all the power of calling the shots and asserting their dominance over the entire world around them. Morality and ethics would lose their credibility and an individual’s will would determine the fate of all that is around them. Or else, it could make a person abnegate everything, despairing about the loneliness they experience every second of their existence, since they have no proof of the existence of any other. Either way, solipsism could inflict more harm than good. Difficult to refute, solipsism continues to haunt the imagination of humankind. However, rejecting the theory altogether wouldn’t be right either, given the crucial questions it raises on reality and the foundations of epistemological speculations. The question of solipsism has stirred minds and propelled philosophy from a state of certainty to that of unpredictability, thereby adding profundity and beauty to the subject. And as long as such ingenious thoughts continue to flow in the body of philosophy, the answer to this problem, along with all problems, I believe, is not too far away.</summary></entry></feed>