<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-01T21:58:30+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Siddis: The Black Rulers of India</title><link href="/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Siddis: The Black Rulers of India" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India">&lt;p&gt;Deep in the annals of Indian history, there lies a long-forgotten tale of daring heroes, who, although foreign to the land, quickly got assimilated into her blood and added to her magnificence. This is the story of the first African rulers of India, the Siddis. India has long been acting as a magnet, drawing to her shores communities from lands afar which have flourished and prospered in her. Amongst these communities were the Africans who although arrived as slaves, still emerged as the mightiest of rulers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journeying all the way from Abyssinia, their motherland, through the treacherous waters, the ‘habshis’ (another term used for addressing the Siddis, descendants of the Bantu people) arrived at the Deccan as a part of the ongoing lucrative slave trade by the Arab merchants. The very distinguished Moroccan scholar, Ibn Batutta recounts how the habshis were reputed for being formidable, such that the presence of even a single habshi in a ship would make the pirates turn away from it. While most of the habshis arrived as slaves and soldiers for the armies of the Delhi Sultanate, not all remained so, and some even climbed the social ladder to become dignified nobles. One of such nobles was Jamal-ud-din Yakut, a close confidant of Razia Sultan (the first female monarch to assume the ascendancy over the Delhi Sultanate), who enjoyed a privileged position as the Amir al-Umara (Amir of Amirs), under her patronage. His growing proximity with the Sultana, along with his racial humbleness, earned him great spite from the Turkish clerics, especially Malik Ikhtiar-ud-din Altunia, who led a violent rebellion against the two, ultimately culminating in his tragic end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also other Abyssinian men like the governor general Malik Sarwar who even went to the extent of laying down the foundation of a sovereign state called Jaunpur, which survived for nearly a century as a symbol of cultural amity and unity. Furthermore, some even established themselves in the eastern part of the subcontinent by dethroning the Sultans of Bengal. The very impressive Siddi Sayed mosque in Ahmedabad was also sanctioned for construction by a Habshi in 1572. Other noteworthy cases of Abyssinians entering the political limelight include Suhail Khan, saviour of the beleaguered Queen of Ahmadnagar, Chand Bibi, who was at war with the Mughals, and Yakut Khan, a navy admiral commissioned by the great Mughal emperor, Aurangzeb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these achievements are indeed great, nowhere had the habshis thrived as much as they did in the Deccan region. Many soared up sky-high, attaining extraordinary heights in the administration and military, because of their physical competency and fidelity. They no longer remained subdued, and with social ascendency, came greater power and privilege at their disposal. Such is the story of another Habshi, Malik Ambar, who held the post of the prime minister of the Ahmadnagar Sultanate. Born in the Oromo tribe, he was sold out at a very young age to an Arab merchant and passed through the hands of several owners to ultimately arrive at India and write his own destiny, where he converted to Islam and was renamed Ambar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 1571 that Ambar arrived at the Deccan where he served under a new master, the Peshwa of Ahmadnagar, who was himself a black man. This must have presented to Ambar a tempting prospect of rising above slavery to cease power and wealth. After the death of his master, he established an independent army (with the help of other habshi lords) and provided his valuable services to Adil Shah for which he was even conferred the title of Malik. But his most impressive accomplishment by far was during the invasions of the 1590’s, where he led a pluralistic force of several thousands under his command against the Mughals. His animosity towards the Mughals was especially long drawn, against whom he fought bravely to establish Nizam Shah on the throne of Ahmadnagar as the lawful monarch. Apart from being an able administrator, Malik Ambar is also accredited with engineering the military tactic of guerrilla warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donning Indian clothes and speaking the language of the land, the Siddis over time have coalesced into the culture and tradition of the subcontinent. However, contrary to the honour and fame attained as a part of history, the Siddis of present-day India remain a secluded community. Maintaining their distance from the mainstream culture and society, they live in tiny clusters scattered around the states of Karnataka, Maharashtra, and Gujarat. Having been reduced to mere outsiders in a country of their own, the Siddis have to continuously battle against the evils of racism and poverty. The only positive step taken by the government towards their upliftment was the establishment of the Special Area Games Project, in the hope of nurturing the raw talent for athletics which runs in their blood. This initiative, however, could not sustain for long and the dream of having Indo-African athletes run for the country in the Olympics was lost. Sports being the only way out of their deplorable condition, the Siddi community now dwells in the hope of the revival of SAG project and creation of many such opportunities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With xenophobia and racial attacks on the rise all over the country, there is a dire need to spread greater awareness about this community. The government, especially, needs to shoulder some responsibility and formulate comprehensive policies to harness the enormous potential lying in the Siddi community. This can come in the form of better employment, education, and opportunities in sports, and most importantly, acceptance from the rest of the countrymen. The time has come for us to uproot this deep-seated feeling of prejudice against the Indo-African community and truly embrace them to the core in an attempt to learn from the glorious past and shape a bright future based on mutual recognition and brotherhood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>namya</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Deep in the annals of Indian history, there lies a long-forgotten tale of daring heroes, who, although foreign to the land, quickly got assimilated into her blood and added to her magnificence. This is the story of the first African rulers of India, the Siddis. India has long been acting as a magnet, drawing to her shores communities from lands afar which have flourished and prospered in her. Amongst these communities were the Africans who although arrived as slaves, still emerged as the mightiest of rulers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Only Turkey can save the European dream, but not in the way you think.</title><link href="/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only Turkey can save the European dream, but not in the way you think." /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To unite the EU needs a common enemy and only the wanker from Ankara is ready to play the role.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Europe, where are its borders, who are its people, and why should I die for it? These are the questions the European Union has desperately grappled with since the 2008 crash. National governments derive power from the willingness of their citizens to make sacrifices. Whether its paying an extra 2.9 cents for a litre of petrol, or traveling across the seas to get shot for Uncle Sam, a government’s power comes from the support of its people. But while the idea of the EU remains popular amongst the European people, with over 60% support across the block in 2017 Eurobarometer surveys, few are willing to make sacrifices for the EU. Northern Europeans don’t want to pay for the ‘greedy’ Southerners. Meanwhile, the Western Europeans don’t see the need to defend Eastern Europe against the Russians. It seems as though the EU has millions of supporters, but very few citizens ready to make the sacrifice necessary for a truly united Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So will Europe ever unite? Can the European Union potentially become a single federalised state, or a superpower capable of challenging China or America? Such a force could defeat the Russians over a long weekend and potentially upset the balance of global politics like no event since the unification of Germany or the French revolution. But the EU needs a threat to give the extra push needed for federalisation. Once that would’ve been Russia, but with an aging population and a declining economy, Russia is today truly only a threat to the Baltic republics: Belarus and the Ukraine. From the beaches of Barcelona or Palermo, the idea of Russia as a serious threat is due to Europe’s ‘special relationship’. Even so is the idea of sending their young lads to fight for Estonian sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily an Armenian phrase tells us who could provide the necessary threat to Europe: “when dealing with the Turk, don’t let go of the stick”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only power capable of convincing European nations to unify is the threat of a rising Turkey with an expansionist government. It has two key advantages over Russia: Firstly, by a matter of its geography it is able to threaten far more of the European continent than Russia can. Secondly, because in a conflict between Turkey and Europe, the United States would likely remain neutral (as it did in the Falklands War), Turkey would force the EU to take the leadership position during the conflict. This would be a cold conflict only though, likely to result in direct confrontation only through proxies in hotspots such as Cyprus or North Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the boom years, European integration seemed both logical and inevitable. The EU expanded its influence both geographically and politically, incorporating the A8 nations of eastern Europe in 2004 and increasing the authority of the Commission with the Treaties of Nice (2007) and Lisbon (2007). Then the bad times came. In 2008, the Great Recession began, since then the EU has lumbered from crisis to crisis. The Greek debt crisis, the migrant crisis and Brexit have all rocked the continent. Through it all, the EU Commision has struggled to act decisively and has lost the support of people across the continent, resulting in the surge of populist and eurosceptic parties. In Poland, Italy and Austria, pro-EU governments have been replaced with eurosceptic regemes unafraid of challenging the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new hope appeared in 2017 in the form of Emmanuel Macron, who sweeped to power, defeated Le Penn and promised to reform Europe and save the Union from irrelevance. At first it seemed to work, Macron faced down protestors in France with a neo-liberal zeal, and Merkel made statements to support Macron’s vision. However, following severe losses for the ruling coalition in the 2017 German election and the populist AFD entering the Bundestag, Merkel’s political capital dried-up. Meanwhile, resentment grew in France at the so called “president of the rich”, culminating in the recent Gilets Jaunes protests which may have permanently crippled Macron’s Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade on from the 2008 crash, it’s now perfectly clear that in a vacuum European states will continue to squabble likely forever. But Europe does not exist in a vacuum. The Republic of Turkey has a population of over 80 million of which over half are under 25, it has the largest army in Europe and will soon be home to the world’s largest airport. Also, it has done a good job of challenging Europe in the past, the Ottoman Empire once touched Vienna, Malta and the Moroccan coast opposite southern Spain. As it became clear that the EU could never allow Turkey to join, the nation has become increasingly hostile to Europe. In 2012, French diplomats were expelled following France’s formal recognition of the Armenian Genocide. In 2016, German Parliamentarians were banned from visiting their own pilots at a NATO airbase in Turkey. And in 2017, President Erdogan called the Dutch government “fascist”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Turkish Navy and Airforce can pose a direct threat to Southern and Eastern Europe, the Turkish also have the capability to threaten violence on the streets of Western Europe. Most of Western Europe’s great cities (Berlin, Rotterdam, Brussels) have large impoverished Turkish minorities which the Europeans have utterly failed to integrate or provide economic opportunity to. Amongst the Turkish diaspora, support for President Erdogan is strong, giving Ankara the capability to ignite social unrest on the streets of European capitals. Moreover, Turkey has a strong relationship with the United States, which hopes to use Turkey to check Russian and Iranian influence, and is willing to sidestep allies in order to do so (as we all saw last week when America abandoned the Syria Kurds). While the USA supporting Turkey against Europe remains unthinkable, if the Turks were able to make a confrontation appear to be at least partly the fault of the Europeans, America could be convinced to take a neutral position as it did during the Cyprus Crisis in 1964. In this scenario, Turkey becomes a threat capable of scaring the Europeans like none other, perhaps even enough to form a federation in resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern definition of Europe comes from the time of the Carolingian Renaissance when the word was used to refer to the union of Latin and Germanic Catholic peoples. This was in contrast to the Islamic Al Andalus in the south and the Orthodox Byzantine Empire in the east. From the beginning Europe was about uniting different peoples to face an enemy from outside. This Union formed under Charlemagne was not to last long after his demise, but the idea of a common people without a shared language, but owing a shared civilisation continues. Globalisation has given Europe a common language, even post Brexit over 51% percent of EU citizens can hold a conversation in English and that number will only grow. A United States of Europe is today more possible than ever before, but it will require a rival to give it shape and purpose. And Europe’s old enemy Turkey is going to be that rival.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reuben Pritchard</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">To unite the EU needs a common enemy and only the wanker from Ankara is ready to play the role.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Market and Politics : The New Separation</title><link href="/Market-and-politics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Market and Politics : The New Separation" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Market-and-politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Market-and-politics">&lt;p&gt;The system of production established in the 1920’s, Fordism, entailed mass standardization of goods for societies that were increasingly headed towards urbanization. The demand was for consumer durables that were cheap and reliable, such as televisions and refrigerators. The market, therefore, was run by a few oligopolistic firms and consumers were used to waiting for a long time before getting the goods they had ordered. This period involved the initiation of assembly lines in production. Factories employed unskilled workers who were regarded as a cog in the machine within the capitalist mode of production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time the 70’s rolled around, many workers in industrialized economies refused to subject themselves to alienation under the Taylorist factory regime, demanding shorter working hours and a higher pay. Another setback to capitalist accumulation was posed by the changing products market. In the West, basic needs had largely been covered by this time and the market for standardized consumer durables was undergoing a secular saturation. What resulted was a restructuring of the production process, and the product lines. Capital responded by re-engineering its products and making them less standardized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Products had become differentiated and customized to cater to the preferences of the smallest groups of potential customers. Like never before, markets allowed customers to pay attention to their individual wants, thereby boosting the move towards customization. The two decades of 1980’s and 1990’s ushered in a period of new consumerism. As products got closer to satisfying idiosyncratic preferences, customers became more willing to work harder or borrow to attain the purchasing power required to acquire them. The growth of the industry for luxury goods, which included perfumes, watches and fashion, followed an identical pattern. Global food chains like McDonald’s incorporated aspects of local cuisines in their menus for different countries. Marketing, on one hand, discovered the commercially untapped wants, and on the other hand, it developed consumer wants. When consumer desires exceeded income, upscale emulation resulted in increasing levels of indebtedness and decreased savings. This marked a transition of markets from those that satisfied needs to those that satisfied wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By developing market niches, commercialized diversification allowed the individual to differentiate himself from some social groups and at the same time associate with others, conveying a desire for upward social mobility. The act of shopping is a way of socializing with others. Moreover, specific kinds of clothing and brands can be used to create a sense of group membership. In fact, rejecting consumer brands in itself establishes quasi-group identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What differentiates this from traditional social integration is that this is voluntary. In well-developed post-Fordist markets, collective identities can be formed through a purchase and abandoned without much ado. In one sense, this signifies liberation from the identity associated with one’s family, community and nation, which the individual is born into and does not have much choice in. It also means that social ties have become much more fragile and weaker as individuals shift identities and desert them as per their convenience. Market forces in this sense writhed their way deeper into social life under a capitalist mode of production. Social media acts as another mode to form these voluntary ties. Twitter, Facebook, Instagram and the likes allow for the formation of a community of followers who interact with each other. Companies use this to further their individualized marketing. Celebrities use it to promote their works and stay relevant. Politicians use it to prevent the increasing weakening of traditional party organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets that seek to cater to the idiosyncrasies of consumers have resulted in the development of a political system best described as “politainment”. Since purchasing power in affluent societies allow the average citizens to get what they want, their interest in the political process begins to fade as there is no vested interest. Participation in traditional politics no longer seems worthwhile. Although people continue to follow the news and pay emphasis on being informed, politics is gradually turning into a form of entertainment, and the citizen is made a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move forward, we find ourselves diverting from a vision for social and economic progress to an overemphasis on individual political decisions. Politics, in effect is becoming de-contextualized. Political participation becomes like an act of consumption, something that can be abandoned or replaced if it ceases to be exciting, much like the T-shirt you bought a few months ago. A consequence is that the public begins to perceive politics as a cumulation of antics resulting from a game of power grabbing. What becomes the focus are the scandals, the petty statements made by opposing sides against each other and representatives focus on managing their appearances rather than serving the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;An argument for a separation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what has been discussed, it is evident that goods aren’t merely for consumption, but also a status symbol. Underlying consumer behaviour is a desire for emulation and differentiation. In advanced industrial societies, consumption of a good serves a dual purpose: It should allow the consumer to distinguish himself or herself from other social groups and classes, while simultaneously allowing for the retention of a sense of individuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This affects the allocation of resources between the public and private sphere. Government goods, those produced by government authorities, are designed to be standardized to ensure a sense of equality among those who consume them. In doing so, they fail to serve the purpose of status differentiation. Their inability to allow the consumer to derive a personal status benefit causes government goods to suffer in cases where the consumer is the decision maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it became well accepted that only private firms could satisfy expectations of the consumer for more customized products, the private sector began to be seen as inherently more superior to the public sector. The public sector reforms of the 90’s followed suit. They involved privatisation of government industries that produced consumer goods, decentralisation of government activities, the use of private producers to sell government produced goods and, a change in the mix of government activities, with a greater focus towards education and healthcare. Formerly public functions moved to the private sphere and even in mixed governments, the balance shifted in favour of the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of politics, regardless of how romanticised it may seem in today’s day and age, is the maintenance of social order and parity. Political communities are built on the idea of accepting a collective identity rather than focusing on one’s individuality. They do not allow for the flexibility of choice as in the markets of highly industrialized economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The employment of a democratic procedure entails that one must accept decisions that they don’t personally prefer, even if they aren’t optimal from an individual’s perspective. In its essence, Politics cannot cater to hedonistic individual desires. Rather, it assesses them to form a general idea that supersedes an individual’s wants. Similarly, social goods cannot be diversified at the rate of customization in the consumer market. As a result they will always seem unfavourable in comparison to private goods. Eventually, the incentive to contribute to the provision of public goods and civil services will dry up. Moreover, paying taxes for financing government activities without having prior knowledge of how they are to be used is in contrast to any other market purchase. This decline in interest in collective projects by people with sufficient purchasing power will ensue an increase in tax resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a shift from public to private consumption, those who continue to depend on public provisions will also get affected. In commercial markets that effectively oust the poorer segments, the only effective means to promote their requirements is their power to affect the electoral outcome. When the political system is starved of legitimacy and financial resources, the lower classes will refrain from voting and even symbolically participating in the political process; Consequently, the state’s ability to ensure public order will slowly evaporate. The reorganization of social life under capitalism, culminates today in a dual crisis of the global financial system and the creation of a ‘minimalist’ democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>reema</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The system of production established in the 1920’s, Fordism, entailed mass standardization of goods for societies that were increasingly headed towards urbanization. The demand was for consumer durables that were cheap and reliable, such as televisions and refrigerators. The market, therefore, was run by a few oligopolistic firms and consumers were used to waiting for a long time before getting the goods they had ordered. This period involved the initiation of assembly lines in production. Factories employed unskilled workers who were regarded as a cog in the machine within the capitalist mode of production.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A House Divided: The Secret Civil War of the Catholic Church</title><link href="/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A House Divided: The Secret Civil War of the Catholic Church" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church">&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church is perhaps the most troubled religious organization in modern times. No other sect or group is going through the same crisis Catholics are undergoing today, although this is not immediately apparent to those on the outside. This century – the 21st century – will truly determine the shape of the faith for generations to come. But before we move on, a bit of background information is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1960’s, the Catholic Church held a worldwide council of bishops, called the Second Vatican Council. This was the 21st of the so-called Ecumenical Councils, the deliberations and decrees of which are meant to expound and explain Catholic doctrine in light of contemporary challenges to the faith whilst seeking unity with all other Christian sects. This youngest of the councils was meant to be the Church’s response to the modern world—an attempt at providing a modern discourse not unlike the philosophical consolidation provided by the great Thomas Aquinas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, the Church has focused more on dialogue rather than debate, collaboration rather than conflict. After nearly a thousand years of separation, Pope Paul VI met with Patriarch Athenagoras of the Greek Orthodox Church, and the two hierarchs lifted excommunications which had been in force since 1054. After centuries of war and bloodshed, the Church reached out to the Lutherans and the two groups even drafted a joint declaration on the most controversial point of doctrinal difference between Catholicism and Protestantism. Hopes are high for an eventual reunion of all Christians. And the more general calls for dialogue and peace have been extended not merely to other Christians but even to the various religions of the world, from the folk traditions of North America to the now-resurgent Islam. The Church has not, of course, diluted a single point of Church teaching (both Popes John Paul II and Benedict XVI make that abundantly clear), but the practice of the Church has changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the outside, things might appear to be warm and merry. But under the appearance of serenity lies a harsh reality. The Church is in a state of great turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 20th century, Pope Pius X spent much of his time and energy as head of the Catholic Church to combat a movement called “Modernism”. The Modernists were clerics and laypeople who, while professing to be Catholics and uniting themselves with the external structures of the Church, nevertheless watered down and diluted several elements of Church doctrine and teaching. Pius X was particularly ruthless – he ordered that all priests and seminary professors take the “Oath Against Modernism”. Needless to say, under his pontificate, the modernists were forced to go underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after the Second Vatican Council, under the guise of “pastoral reforms”, the Modernists have had a remarkable resurgence. While they have failed utterly to change official Church teaching, they nonetheless hold opinions at variance with what many consider to unchanging dogma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Popes post the Vatican II have been very strict against this newly resuscitated trend. John Paul II, in particular, reaffirmed orthodox doctrine in his catechism and encyclicals and Benedict promulgated reforms that led to a revival of traditionalism among clerics and laypeople. But the most recent ascendant to the Throne of Peter does not appear to be in the same vein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Is the Pope Catholic?” was considered to be a joke English Catholics said to themselves in the 19th century. It isn’t funny anymore as the current pontiff, Pope Francis, repeatedly makes ambiguous statements that appear to: firstly, question the necessity of faith for salvation; secondly, allow for divorced and remarried couples to receive Communion; thirdly, imply that Catholic couples should control the number of children they have (which some might interpret as a contradiction of age-old Church doctrine on contraception); and fourthly, call for a change in the teaching on the death penalty and sympathy for homosexuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these statements are ambiguously worded, and it is not always clear if a denial has taken place or if it is simply yet another case of authentic doctrine being stated in a slipshod manner. But what is certainly without question is that this is the most controversial pontificate in recent memory. The situation became so bad that it prompted four high-ranking Church leaders to make public an appeal (called “dubia”) to the Pope seeking clarification on his statements – an appeal which, since then, has gone unanswered. There was even talk of a “public fraternal correction” of the Pope, and there has already been a more grass-roots level “filial correction” involving scores of distinguished signatories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is even more worrying is the Holy Father’s response to his critics. When calls for clarification come, the Pope is silent. Subtle attacks on his critics and dissenters abound in his Sunday homilies. Conservative laypeople are up in arms, not least among them being the historian Henry Sire, author of the controversial bestseller The Dictator Pope. While Francis tries his level best to maintain an image of compassion, can that really square with what many are now calling a tyrannical method of internal governance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 25, 2018, a prominent prelate, Archbishop Carlo Maria Vigano, released a damning 11-page letter describing a network of sexual abuse cover-ups that had spread its tentacles all the way to upper echelons of power. In a move virtually unprecedented in recent history, the bishop called upon the pontiff and the others complicit to resign. This is more than a question of moral corruption. In the eyes of countless conservatives, the laxity of moral standards among prelates and priests is not separate from but is rather a direct result of the “Modernist conspiracy” to liberalize Catholic doctrine. The fact that the majority of these abuse cases are instances of homosexual abuse has only added fuel to the fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just a regional crisis. This is a battle for the very heart of the Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conservative Christian with deep sympathy for the Catholic Church’s mission and an appreciation of the richness of her theological heritage, I propose a three-point programme to deal with this crisis once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initiate a Church-wide search-and-destroy operation – better still, if this is handled by outside non-ecclesiastical bodies. Defrock priests found guilty of sexual abuse and hand them over to the secular authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Allow, for the time being, married men to become priests, in accordance with the historical precedents of the Byzantine and other Oriental traditions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Renovate the formation process in theological seminaries
– restore traditional practices abandoned since Vatican II and work to foster ascetic rigour among candidates for the priesthood.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these three points are successfully implemented, we may find ourselves with a smaller Catholic Church. But this will not be a loss. It will be a victory, and the Church will finally have a chance to reclaim her former glory in the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The Catholic Church is perhaps the most troubled religious organization in modern times. No other sect or group is going through the same crisis Catholics are undergoing today, although this is not immediately apparent to those on the outside. This century – the 21st century – will truly determine the shape of the faith for generations to come. But before we move on, a bit of background information is welcome.</summary></entry></feed>