<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-28T17:29:17+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The PMC Bank Fiasco</title><link href="/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The PMC Bank Fiasco" /><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With great power come greater scams. &lt;/em&gt;This is evidently a mantra for India. Politicians getting named in large scams and then using their power to sway the decisions of government bodies has become a typical sight in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative (PMC) bank fiasco is not the first time a major scam has been unearthed which has left a financial institution and its depositors in complete shambles. Call it misgovernance or blindsight of the management - borrowing from one bank to repay another bank has become a common&amp;nbsp;practice&amp;nbsp;in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fraud to the tune of ₹6,500 billion was found in the books of the PMC bank, all of which were loans extended to only a single borrower: Housing Development and Infrastructure Limited (HDIL). This amount was way beyond the statutory limit set by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) for lending to a single entity. Yet the senior management kept quiet on the matter until they were thrown under the bus by the managing director in his confession letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relations between the Wadhawan group and the PMC bank have prevailed since the 1980's, wherein the former had saved the latter from the brink of a financial collapse quite a few times by infusing capital and keeping a majority of their deposits with the establishment. Thus, aiding the PMC bank to maintain the liquidity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But every&amp;nbsp;good story&amp;nbsp;has an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As HDIL’s business started to grow, and their capital requirements grew multifold, the group started to transact with larger banks in order to meet their needs. This hindered the profitability of the cooperative bank as the majority of the institution’s revenue was attributed to transactions in the Wadhawan group’s accounts. Hence, upon request the group started banking with PMC again after a short span of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018-19, the bank had reported a profit of ₹996.9 million in its annual report. The bank showed 3.76% of advances (₹8,3830 million) as gross non-performing assets (NPAs), which was fair as compared to public sector banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, things started to go awry when a few projects undertaken by HDIL were shelved, and this resulted in a liquidity crunch. Consequently, the bank started defaulting on all the loans it had taken from other banks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, due to the past repayment record of the group, the bank continued to treat the loan as a standard loan. But when the loan amount snowballed to more than 73% of the bank’s total exposure, the issue came into the limelight and a strict moratorium was put upon the bank by the RBI. Hence, it's clear that the bank gave false monetary reports to cover its dangerous loan mess and the alleged collusion with HDIL and other firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prevent panic and loss of public confidence, all the depositors were barred from withdrawing more than ₹1,000, but later the withdrawal limit was capped at ₹100,000 per depositor until further notice. In addition to the complaint that was filed with the authorities, the board of directors were suspended and the Wadhawan family members were arrested. The Enforcement Directorate, India's economic offences investigator, even seized movable and immovable assets of approximately&amp;nbsp; ₹40 billion in connection with the case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole case was nothing but another instance of corporate misgovernance and partial treatment to a particular lender by the senior management of banks, just like in the case of the Punjab National Bank scam.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fiasco could have been prevented had the institution increased its collateral against the loans disbursed and classified the Wadhawan group’s account as a NPA at the right time. The central bank should have learned its lesson post the PNB scam, and could have increased its due diligence on public sector banks by placing stricter checks and reporting standards on these financial institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July 2021, the RBI approved the bid of Centrum Financial Services (CFS) and BharatPe to jointly take over the crisis driven cooperative bank, thereby providing some respite to its depositors. The president of BharatPe group said, “One thing was clear in our discussion with RBI that the interest of depositors is supreme”, further emphasising on the management's future intent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RBI was initially reluctant in giving an in-principle nod to the two institutions to set up a small finance bank (SFB), however, it has finally given the licence and has even gone on to provide a lot of other statutory reliefs to the new entity to be jointly formed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different points of view on the RBI's decision to pick Centrum-BharatPe for the takeover of one of the largest cooperative banks in India. A section of the bank’s depositors are unhappy with the decision, as they preferred an established commercial bank to take over the entity rather than a new licensee with no direct experience of running a regular bank.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CFS and BharatPe are set to infuse ₹5 billion each into the new entity when starting over and will increase the capital up to ₹30 billion in due course. Additionally, they also have the option to restructure the liability and convert them into capital instruments, take support from the Depositor Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) for repayment of insured deposits up to ₹50,000, phase withdrawal plans for individuals with higher deposits or convert the same into tier 1 or tier 2 capital.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joint venture is likely to form a good synergy between BharatPe and Centrum Financial Services. While the former is an establishment specialising in fintech with a strong footprint in the digital lending and Unified Payment Interface (UPI) industry, the latter is a non-banking lender with strong holdings and a good history in providing credit to small-mid size firms. Together they can bring innovation and renewed vigour to a fallen institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new entity is to be operational in 120 days post the principal nod given by the central banking authority, and only post this, will the RBI draft a scheme on amalgamation of the two entities with PMC Bank. The plan will then be sent to the government for approval and official notification. Under Section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, only a bank can be merged with another, therefore, the process of handover will start only once the SFB (Small Finance Bank) is created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, the subsidiaries of Centrum namely Centrum Housing Finance and Centrum Microcredit are in the same business as the small finance bank to be set up by them. Hence, this poses a hurdle for Centrum, as one cannot have separate entities doing the same business. Either it will have to sell its majority stake or merge the subsidiaries; or not enter the microcredit and home loan business from the SFB set up, which would mean giving up a major business opportunity for the new joint venture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RBI has now called for sweeping changes in the Banking Regulation Act, and will be actively looking into the regulation of cooperative banks to avoid such a future debacle. But the problem doesn't stop there, the problem only begins here. India massively lacks transparency in the financial sector and this often puts a lot of wrongdoings away from the eyes of the public and regulatory bodies. There are more important questions that this mess raises. The first being, will the public institutions continue to show vigilance only after the chaos unfolds or will they ever learn to step in the moment the lines are crossed?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samyak Jain</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">With great power come greater scams. This is evidently a mantra for India. Politicians getting named in large scams and then using their power to sway the decisions of government bodies has become a typical sight in the country. The Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative (PMC) bank fiasco is not the first time a major scam has been unearthed which has left a financial institution and its depositors in complete shambles. Call it misgovernance or blindsight of the management - borrowing from one bank to repay another bank has become a common&amp;nbsp;practice&amp;nbsp;in India. A fraud to the tune of ₹6,500 billion was found in the books of the PMC bank, all of which were loans extended to only a single borrower: Housing Development and Infrastructure Limited (HDIL). This amount was way beyond the statutory limit set by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) for lending to a single entity. Yet the senior management kept quiet on the matter until they were thrown under the bus by the managing director in his confession letter. Relations between the Wadhawan group and the PMC bank have prevailed since the 1980's, wherein the former had saved the latter from the brink of a financial collapse quite a few times by infusing capital and keeping a majority of their deposits with the establishment. Thus, aiding the PMC bank to maintain the liquidity.&amp;nbsp; But every&amp;nbsp;good story&amp;nbsp;has an end. As HDIL’s business started to grow, and their capital requirements grew multifold, the group started to transact with larger banks in order to meet their needs. This hindered the profitability of the cooperative bank as the majority of the institution’s revenue was attributed to transactions in the Wadhawan group’s accounts. Hence, upon request the group started banking with PMC again after a short span of time. In 2018-19, the bank had reported a profit of ₹996.9 million in its annual report. The bank showed 3.76% of advances (₹8,3830 million) as gross non-performing assets (NPAs), which was fair as compared to public sector banks. However, things started to go awry when a few projects undertaken by HDIL were shelved, and this resulted in a liquidity crunch. Consequently, the bank started defaulting on all the loans it had taken from other banks.&amp;nbsp; Initially, due to the past repayment record of the group, the bank continued to treat the loan as a standard loan. But when the loan amount snowballed to more than 73% of the bank’s total exposure, the issue came into the limelight and a strict moratorium was put upon the bank by the RBI. Hence, it's clear that the bank gave false monetary reports to cover its dangerous loan mess and the alleged collusion with HDIL and other firms. To prevent panic and loss of public confidence, all the depositors were barred from withdrawing more than ₹1,000, but later the withdrawal limit was capped at ₹100,000 per depositor until further notice. In addition to the complaint that was filed with the authorities, the board of directors were suspended and the Wadhawan family members were arrested. The Enforcement Directorate, India's economic offences investigator, even seized movable and immovable assets of approximately&amp;nbsp; ₹40 billion in connection with the case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; This whole case was nothing but another instance of corporate misgovernance and partial treatment to a particular lender by the senior management of banks, just like in the case of the Punjab National Bank scam.&amp;nbsp; This fiasco could have been prevented had the institution increased its collateral against the loans disbursed and classified the Wadhawan group’s account as a NPA at the right time. The central bank should have learned its lesson post the PNB scam, and could have increased its due diligence on public sector banks by placing stricter checks and reporting standards on these financial institutions.&amp;nbsp; In July 2021, the RBI approved the bid of Centrum Financial Services (CFS) and BharatPe to jointly take over the crisis driven cooperative bank, thereby providing some respite to its depositors. The president of BharatPe group said, “One thing was clear in our discussion with RBI that the interest of depositors is supreme”, further emphasising on the management's future intent.&amp;nbsp; The RBI was initially reluctant in giving an in-principle nod to the two institutions to set up a small finance bank (SFB), however, it has finally given the licence and has even gone on to provide a lot of other statutory reliefs to the new entity to be jointly formed.&amp;nbsp; There are different points of view on the RBI's decision to pick Centrum-BharatPe for the takeover of one of the largest cooperative banks in India. A section of the bank’s depositors are unhappy with the decision, as they preferred an established commercial bank to take over the entity rather than a new licensee with no direct experience of running a regular bank.&amp;nbsp; CFS and BharatPe are set to infuse ₹5 billion each into the new entity when starting over and will increase the capital up to ₹30 billion in due course. Additionally, they also have the option to restructure the liability and convert them into capital instruments, take support from the Depositor Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) for repayment of insured deposits up to ₹50,000, phase withdrawal plans for individuals with higher deposits or convert the same into tier 1 or tier 2 capital.&amp;nbsp; The joint venture is likely to form a good synergy between BharatPe and Centrum Financial Services. While the former is an establishment specialising in fintech with a strong footprint in the digital lending and Unified Payment Interface (UPI) industry, the latter is a non-banking lender with strong holdings and a good history in providing credit to small-mid size firms. Together they can bring innovation and renewed vigour to a fallen institution.&amp;nbsp; The new entity is to be operational in 120 days post the principal nod given by the central banking authority, and only post this, will the RBI draft a scheme on amalgamation of the two entities with PMC Bank. The plan will then be sent to the government for approval and official notification. Under Section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, only a bank can be merged with another, therefore, the process of handover will start only once the SFB (Small Finance Bank) is created. Apart from that, the subsidiaries of Centrum namely Centrum Housing Finance and Centrum Microcredit are in the same business as the small finance bank to be set up by them. Hence, this poses a hurdle for Centrum, as one cannot have separate entities doing the same business. Either it will have to sell its majority stake or merge the subsidiaries; or not enter the microcredit and home loan business from the SFB set up, which would mean giving up a major business opportunity for the new joint venture. The RBI has now called for sweeping changes in the Banking Regulation Act, and will be actively looking into the regulation of cooperative banks to avoid such a future debacle. But the problem doesn't stop there, the problem only begins here. India massively lacks transparency in the financial sector and this often puts a lot of wrongdoings away from the eyes of the public and regulatory bodies. There are more important questions that this mess raises. The first being, will the public institutions continue to show vigilance only after the chaos unfolds or will they ever learn to step in the moment the lines are crossed?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II</title><link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II" /><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II">&lt;p&gt;In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked &lt;em&gt;en masse, &lt;/em&gt;as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=8&amp;amp;v=fvoWoMIwr-g&amp;amp;feature=emb_logo&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in&lt;/a&gt; which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp; A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp; The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp; Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp; Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp; Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp; While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp; As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp; In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp; In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp; Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp; In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp; “In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked en masse, as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.” Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp; Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp; Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I</title><link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I" /><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I">&lt;p&gt;“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (&lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt;) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of &lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt; is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named &lt;em&gt;Bala&lt;/em&gt; was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: &lt;em&gt;Gully Boy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Super 30&lt;/em&gt; and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called &lt;em&gt;Khali Peeli&lt;/em&gt; came under attack for having a song titled &lt;em&gt;Beyonce Sharma Jayegi&lt;/em&gt; (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“&lt;em&gt;tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi&lt;/em&gt;”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. &lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt;, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in &lt;em&gt;Ghost In The Shell&lt;/em&gt; (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the &lt;em&gt;MCU&lt;/em&gt; (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in &lt;em&gt;Dear White People&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (Snow White) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of Snow White is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism. To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp; Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp; In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named Bala was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: Gully Boy, Super 30 and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called Khali Peeli came under attack for having a song titled Beyonce Sharma Jayegi (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp; Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp; In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp; Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. Fate: The Winx Saga, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon Winx Club, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the Twilight series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in Ghost In The Shell (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the MCU (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in Aloha (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp; In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in Bridgerton and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp; Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in Dear White People). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in Bridgerton or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from Bridgerton.&amp;nbsp; All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp; Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp; The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp; In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job. Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Future of Energy!</title><link href="/The-Future-of-Energy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Energy!" /><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Future-of-Energy-</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Future-of-Energy">&lt;p&gt;With the latest round of global climate talks coming up in a few weeks, all eyes are set on our world leaders and their stand on the issue. The members of business groups, media, civil society, etc, will gather for the event to express their views and concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The global climate conference will be held in Glasgow, United Kingdom and can be referred to as the COP26 (Conference of the Parties to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-convention/what-is-the-united-nations-framework-convention-on-climate-change&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1992 United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;). The nations have finally realised the impacts of climate change and the need to counter it.	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of renewable energy is being promoted across continents in order to cut carbon emissions and hence, decarbonise the planet. At present, the major renewable energy resources are centered around solar, wind and water energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However recently, Green Hydrogen has been making headlines, owed mainly to its ease and efficient mode of production. Unlike coal and oil, it only emits water vapours and with hydrogen being the most abundant element available to us, this gas has the potential to be used across industries. Some observers even dub it as the ‘fuel of the future’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, there are a few challenges which need to be dealt with before this hydrogen produced fuel makes its way to commercial and domestic use. Until now, hydrogen is used as a building block to produce other carbon-neutral synthetic fuels. Use of pure hydrogen as an energy source is a fairly new practice and thus, new infrastructure and technology will be a prerequisite.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive in to understand the so-called future of energy!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is green hydrogen and how is it produced?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green hydrogen is a hydrogen fuel which is formed using renewable resources instead of fossil fuels. The generation of green hydrogen is done through the chemical process of electrolysis. This process separates the hydrogen from oxygen in water with the help of an electric current. It can help in supplying up to 25% of the world’s energy needs. The entire process is sustainable and can help cut carbon emissions by a huge amount.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost of production and other challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of production of green hydrogen is very expensive. In a report published in 2019, the&amp;nbsp;International Energy Agency (IEA)&amp;nbsp;puts the cost of producing green hydrogen at&amp;nbsp;$3-$7.50 per kilo, compared to the production cost of $0.90- $3.20 of steam methane reformation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrolysers constitute a major proportion of the costs involved and it needs to be cut down in order to make the production process effective. According to the claims of IEA, This will only be possible by 2040.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storage and transportation of green hydrogen is not an easy task either. It is a highly inflammable gas and requires a lot of space, making steel pipes and welds brittle, and prone to failure. A safe transportation of the gas requires construction of pipelines which would eventually add to the price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the major uses of green hydrogen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green hydrogen is an efficient and sustainable source of energy which makes it an attractive source. It can be applied across various industries, thus making its versatility a lucrative option for big business houses and nations. Issues pertaining to storage and transportation do not impede its acceptance as they are not just exclusive to this fuel alone.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green hydrogen in the Indian context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is already working on various sustainable energy projects. It has emerged as the sixth largest producer of wind and solar energy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a developing country, which is yet to fully realise its potential, investing in sustainable energy is a huge dilemma. Nonetheless, the nation has never backed out of protocols and has always supported the steps needed to be taken to curb global emissions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the country’s 75th Independence Day, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the government’s vision of making the nation ‘energy independent by 2047’. This goal is a very ambitious target for a country which heavily relies on fossil fuels for its energy requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech, he also initiated the National Hydrogen Mission (NHM) to curb global warming, consequently accelerating the country’s pace of embarking on the sustainable journey. The Ministry of New and Renewable Energy has been undertaking&amp;nbsp; research &amp;amp; developmental programmes on the sustainable future including hydrogen fuels. Additionally, the country has collaborated with Norway to manufacture India-centric technology for green hydrogen production.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Kerry, the US presidential envoy for climate, in his visit to India in September 2021, also launched the Climate Action and Finance Mobilisation Dialogue (CAFMD) under India-US Climate Clean Energy Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main objectives of CAFMD is finance mobilisation which would focus on attracting capital and technologies for India to scale up its renewable energy generation capacities. The US envoy said, ”&lt;em&gt;Over the past months, six of the largest banks in America had publicly committed to investing a minimum of $4.16 trillion in the next 10 years to make the transition happen&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nations such as Germany are extending financial help outside their region for investment in sustainable projects, particularly relating to green hydrogen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, China is the largest producer of green hydrogen with an output of 20 million ton. The European Union is also following the same steps by investing heavily in this fuel. Their extensive network of underground pipelines and storage facilities would enable them to store and even have the potential to transport green hydrogen across the continent. This can act to their advantage by allowing them to dominate the green hydrogen market in the near future. Oil rich nations such as Oman and Saudi Arabia are also proceeding in this direction.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter of 2021-22, Mukesh Ambani, the chairman of the largest company of the country - Reliance Industries, unveiled the company's push into green energy by committing to invest $10.1 billion in the sector by 2024. This investment will involve setting up energy production plants (including those for hydrogen fuels) and building battery grids to store electricity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coal shortage in India in early October 2021 and the consequent fears of power blackouts gives us yet another reason to move to an untapped and unlimited source of sustainable energy. The mass availability and properties of hydrogen seems to be the perfect alternative for most of our energy needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every nation is on the move to decarbonise, and is looking for sustainable substitutes for mass production with lower costs. The goal of minimum cost will be achieved in future by means of economies of scale, however at present, it is essential to make the investments with new and appropriate infrastructure and technology. This will require time and consistent efforts but the outcome makes it worth the effort.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first major step towards a sustainable planet has been taken and many more are yet to come.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll have to wait till COP26 to find out about the latest green initiatives our world leaders have in store for us, till then let's all make a conscious effort to move towards sustainable habits in day-to-day lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">With the latest round of global climate talks coming up in a few weeks, all eyes are set on our world leaders and their stand on the issue. The members of business groups, media, civil society, etc, will gather for the event to express their views and concerns.&amp;nbsp; The global climate conference will be held in Glasgow, United Kingdom and can be referred to as the COP26 (Conference of the Parties to the&amp;nbsp;1992 United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change). The nations have finally realised the impacts of climate change and the need to counter it. The use of renewable energy is being promoted across continents in order to cut carbon emissions and hence, decarbonise the planet. At present, the major renewable energy resources are centered around solar, wind and water energy. However recently, Green Hydrogen has been making headlines, owed mainly to its ease and efficient mode of production. Unlike coal and oil, it only emits water vapours and with hydrogen being the most abundant element available to us, this gas has the potential to be used across industries. Some observers even dub it as the ‘fuel of the future’. Nonetheless, there are a few challenges which need to be dealt with before this hydrogen produced fuel makes its way to commercial and domestic use. Until now, hydrogen is used as a building block to produce other carbon-neutral synthetic fuels. Use of pure hydrogen as an energy source is a fairly new practice and thus, new infrastructure and technology will be a prerequisite.&amp;nbsp; Let's dive in to understand the so-called future of energy!&amp;nbsp; What is green hydrogen and how is it produced? Green hydrogen is a hydrogen fuel which is formed using renewable resources instead of fossil fuels. The generation of green hydrogen is done through the chemical process of electrolysis. This process separates the hydrogen from oxygen in water with the help of an electric current. It can help in supplying up to 25% of the world’s energy needs. The entire process is sustainable and can help cut carbon emissions by a huge amount.&amp;nbsp; Cost of production and other challenges The cost of production of green hydrogen is very expensive. In a report published in 2019, the&amp;nbsp;International Energy Agency (IEA)&amp;nbsp;puts the cost of producing green hydrogen at&amp;nbsp;$3-$7.50 per kilo, compared to the production cost of $0.90- $3.20 of steam methane reformation.&amp;nbsp; Electrolysers constitute a major proportion of the costs involved and it needs to be cut down in order to make the production process effective. According to the claims of IEA, This will only be possible by 2040.&amp;nbsp; Storage and transportation of green hydrogen is not an easy task either. It is a highly inflammable gas and requires a lot of space, making steel pipes and welds brittle, and prone to failure. A safe transportation of the gas requires construction of pipelines which would eventually add to the price.&amp;nbsp; What are the major uses of green hydrogen? Green hydrogen is an efficient and sustainable source of energy which makes it an attractive source. It can be applied across various industries, thus making its versatility a lucrative option for big business houses and nations. Issues pertaining to storage and transportation do not impede its acceptance as they are not just exclusive to this fuel alone.&amp;nbsp; Green hydrogen in the Indian context India is already working on various sustainable energy projects. It has emerged as the sixth largest producer of wind and solar energy.&amp;nbsp; For a developing country, which is yet to fully realise its potential, investing in sustainable energy is a huge dilemma. Nonetheless, the nation has never backed out of protocols and has always supported the steps needed to be taken to curb global emissions.&amp;nbsp; On the country’s 75th Independence Day, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the government’s vision of making the nation ‘energy independent by 2047’. This goal is a very ambitious target for a country which heavily relies on fossil fuels for its energy requirements.&amp;nbsp; In his speech, he also initiated the National Hydrogen Mission (NHM) to curb global warming, consequently accelerating the country’s pace of embarking on the sustainable journey. The Ministry of New and Renewable Energy has been undertaking&amp;nbsp; research &amp;amp; developmental programmes on the sustainable future including hydrogen fuels. Additionally, the country has collaborated with Norway to manufacture India-centric technology for green hydrogen production.&amp;nbsp; John Kerry, the US presidential envoy for climate, in his visit to India in September 2021, also launched the Climate Action and Finance Mobilisation Dialogue (CAFMD) under India-US Climate Clean Energy Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp; One of the main objectives of CAFMD is finance mobilisation which would focus on attracting capital and technologies for India to scale up its renewable energy generation capacities. The US envoy said, ”Over the past months, six of the largest banks in America had publicly committed to investing a minimum of $4.16 trillion in the next 10 years to make the transition happen”.&amp;nbsp; Nations such as Germany are extending financial help outside their region for investment in sustainable projects, particularly relating to green hydrogen.&amp;nbsp; Currently, China is the largest producer of green hydrogen with an output of 20 million ton. The European Union is also following the same steps by investing heavily in this fuel. Their extensive network of underground pipelines and storage facilities would enable them to store and even have the potential to transport green hydrogen across the continent. This can act to their advantage by allowing them to dominate the green hydrogen market in the near future. Oil rich nations such as Oman and Saudi Arabia are also proceeding in this direction.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In the first quarter of 2021-22, Mukesh Ambani, the chairman of the largest company of the country - Reliance Industries, unveiled the company's push into green energy by committing to invest $10.1 billion in the sector by 2024. This investment will involve setting up energy production plants (including those for hydrogen fuels) and building battery grids to store electricity.&amp;nbsp; The coal shortage in India in early October 2021 and the consequent fears of power blackouts gives us yet another reason to move to an untapped and unlimited source of sustainable energy. The mass availability and properties of hydrogen seems to be the perfect alternative for most of our energy needs.&amp;nbsp; Every nation is on the move to decarbonise, and is looking for sustainable substitutes for mass production with lower costs. The goal of minimum cost will be achieved in future by means of economies of scale, however at present, it is essential to make the investments with new and appropriate infrastructure and technology. This will require time and consistent efforts but the outcome makes it worth the effort.&amp;nbsp; The first major step towards a sustainable planet has been taken and many more are yet to come.&amp;nbsp; We’ll have to wait till COP26 to find out about the latest green initiatives our world leaders have in store for us, till then let's all make a conscious effort to move towards sustainable habits in day-to-day lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stand Up and Economics</title><link href="/Stand-Up-and-Economics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stand Up and Economics" /><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Stand-Up-and-Economics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Stand-Up-and-Economics">&lt;p&gt;Who would be a perfect partner for a tub of Popcorn and a day drowned in gloom? For me, it has always been Kenny Sebastian cracking jokes on coffee or biscuits. Not just Kenny Sebastian, but as a matter of fact, stand-up comedians in general have been my saviour in times of crisis. The giggles and the laughs indeed help one escape from reality and live in the moment. However, there is one not so known fact about stand-ups - they share a close relationship with everybody’s favourite subject, economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This relationship between Economics and Stand Ups is bilateral, and however funny and astonishing it may sound, we have someone with the title of 'Stand-up Economist'. Yoram Bauman is deemed to be the first Stand up Economist in the world. He is a microeconomist and his key focus area is the environment. He once wrote a parody on the 'ten principles of Economics'&amp;nbsp; by N Mankiw which kick-started his side-career in comedy. Now, he regularly performs at colleges, clubs and institutes&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;The difference, of course, being that microeconomists are people who are wrong about specific things and macroeconomists are wrong about things in general&quot; &lt;/em&gt;was one of his lines at a 45- minute comedy show performed at Mission College which made the audience burst into laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving ahead, while we look at the first half of the relationship, we will be looking at stand-ups as economics. A lot of people have drawn similarities between jokes and currency. Some went overboard and termed jokes as a 'Strange Currency'. The value of this currency rests on a shared agreement and it keeps fluctuating, i.e., increases or decreases, over time. Moreover, if we visualise stand-up as a market, the market does have a point of saturation wherein the joke becomes so diffused that it no longer pleases the audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, like everything else, jokes react to the principles of supply and demand. Jokes, in this market, are characterised as investments. Not everyone can wake up one day, go on the stage and become a stand up comedian. There’s a lot of refinement and honing that goes behind a successful joke (or investment) which can be presented to a paid audience and in turn yield money. &lt;a href=&quot;http://marknormandcomedy.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mark Normand&lt;/a&gt;’s line “&lt;em&gt;If I can get a joke to work on [a free] show, that joke is worth money” &lt;/em&gt;sums up the idea pretty well. These jokes have a lasting or terminal value like any other investment. However, when does the value of a joke fade away? The lasting value depends on the person who’s making the joke. For example, stand-up comedians who have been in the business for as long as decades can dig out old jokes and please the audience with the reference. Thus, the jokes still have a lasting value for them even after decades. Generally, it is considered that non-conventional jokes have a longer lasting value than the conventional ones.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we have walked through the streets of the stand-up industry, there’s another visualisation of the joke market which was proposed by Yoram Bauman. Instead of considering jokes as a currency, Bauman considers jokes to be like public goods such as fresh air, water, etc. If one of the members enjoys the joke, it doesn’t take away the right of enjoying it from any other member. However, even estimating the value of a public good is difficult, as no one puts equal value on a nice view or a nice joke. Again like any other goods, jokes face saturation in the market. If a comedy show has the same specific bit of jokes about the same things, the value of the jokes would reduce. Ultimately the audience would refuse to buy these jokes by either not laughing at them or worse by heckling. However, one fundamental question that still remains is how one puts a value on a creative intangible hobby because a lot of stand up comedians don’t really want money in exchange for their “goods” but are satisfied by the giggles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now exploring the second half of the relationship, a lot of stand-ups have economic concepts entwined in them. Stand ups provide a really holistic view of human behavior. Since most of the jokes are centered on everyday life; these comedians analyze our behavior to derive jokes out of them. Hence, economics lovers should definitely watch stand ups apart from reading the usual microeconomics textbook. As was noted in one of the articles by Mint, there are various instances where stand-up comedians have explained complex economics issues through jokes. For example, when in one of his gigs, Abhishek Upmanyu said that, in his childhood, on his grandmother’s death anniversary, his mother used to request him to offer food to poor people. While he agrees that it is a noble deed to do, he also states that it creates an unwanted incentive. If poor people get to know that elderly people dying means food, they’ll start hurting elderly people. This, in economics, is called ‘The Cobra Effect’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it’s stand-up comedy in economics or economics in stand-up comedy, there’s one thing clear that there is a relationship between the two. So, the next time you sit with a tub of popcorn and Kenny Sebastian, you can skip your microeconomics tuition!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shiksha Mody</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Who would be a perfect partner for a tub of Popcorn and a day drowned in gloom? For me, it has always been Kenny Sebastian cracking jokes on coffee or biscuits. Not just Kenny Sebastian, but as a matter of fact, stand-up comedians in general have been my saviour in times of crisis. The giggles and the laughs indeed help one escape from reality and live in the moment. However, there is one not so known fact about stand-ups - they share a close relationship with everybody’s favourite subject, economics. This relationship between Economics and Stand Ups is bilateral, and however funny and astonishing it may sound, we have someone with the title of 'Stand-up Economist'. Yoram Bauman is deemed to be the first Stand up Economist in the world. He is a microeconomist and his key focus area is the environment. He once wrote a parody on the 'ten principles of Economics'&amp;nbsp; by N Mankiw which kick-started his side-career in comedy. Now, he regularly performs at colleges, clubs and institutes. &quot;The difference, of course, being that microeconomists are people who are wrong about specific things and macroeconomists are wrong about things in general&quot; was one of his lines at a 45- minute comedy show performed at Mission College which made the audience burst into laughter. Moving ahead, while we look at the first half of the relationship, we will be looking at stand-ups as economics. A lot of people have drawn similarities between jokes and currency. Some went overboard and termed jokes as a 'Strange Currency'. The value of this currency rests on a shared agreement and it keeps fluctuating, i.e., increases or decreases, over time. Moreover, if we visualise stand-up as a market, the market does have a point of saturation wherein the joke becomes so diffused that it no longer pleases the audience.&amp;nbsp; And again, like everything else, jokes react to the principles of supply and demand. Jokes, in this market, are characterised as investments. Not everyone can wake up one day, go on the stage and become a stand up comedian. There’s a lot of refinement and honing that goes behind a successful joke (or investment) which can be presented to a paid audience and in turn yield money. Mark Normand’s line “If I can get a joke to work on [a free] show, that joke is worth money” sums up the idea pretty well. These jokes have a lasting or terminal value like any other investment. However, when does the value of a joke fade away? The lasting value depends on the person who’s making the joke. For example, stand-up comedians who have been in the business for as long as decades can dig out old jokes and please the audience with the reference. Thus, the jokes still have a lasting value for them even after decades. Generally, it is considered that non-conventional jokes have a longer lasting value than the conventional ones.&amp;nbsp; While we have walked through the streets of the stand-up industry, there’s another visualisation of the joke market which was proposed by Yoram Bauman. Instead of considering jokes as a currency, Bauman considers jokes to be like public goods such as fresh air, water, etc. If one of the members enjoys the joke, it doesn’t take away the right of enjoying it from any other member. However, even estimating the value of a public good is difficult, as no one puts equal value on a nice view or a nice joke. Again like any other goods, jokes face saturation in the market. If a comedy show has the same specific bit of jokes about the same things, the value of the jokes would reduce. Ultimately the audience would refuse to buy these jokes by either not laughing at them or worse by heckling. However, one fundamental question that still remains is how one puts a value on a creative intangible hobby because a lot of stand up comedians don’t really want money in exchange for their “goods” but are satisfied by the giggles. Now exploring the second half of the relationship, a lot of stand-ups have economic concepts entwined in them. Stand ups provide a really holistic view of human behavior. Since most of the jokes are centered on everyday life; these comedians analyze our behavior to derive jokes out of them. Hence, economics lovers should definitely watch stand ups apart from reading the usual microeconomics textbook. As was noted in one of the articles by Mint, there are various instances where stand-up comedians have explained complex economics issues through jokes. For example, when in one of his gigs, Abhishek Upmanyu said that, in his childhood, on his grandmother’s death anniversary, his mother used to request him to offer food to poor people. While he agrees that it is a noble deed to do, he also states that it creates an unwanted incentive. If poor people get to know that elderly people dying means food, they’ll start hurting elderly people. This, in economics, is called ‘The Cobra Effect’.&amp;nbsp; While it’s stand-up comedy in economics or economics in stand-up comedy, there’s one thing clear that there is a relationship between the two. So, the next time you sit with a tub of popcorn and Kenny Sebastian, you can skip your microeconomics tuition!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pace of EV Adoption in India</title><link href="/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pace of EV Adoption in India" /><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India">&lt;p&gt;Over the past ten years, the automobile sector has been gravitating towards electrification. Electrification is essentially the replacement of conventionally used Internal Combustion Engine (ICE) vehicles with more powerful, simpler, smarter and greener Electric Vehicles (EV).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EVs came into being before its ICE counterparts but due to lack of infrastructure, high upfront costs and absence of incentives, they could not gain the deserved spotlight. So, are we to believe that the right time has come to think about the electrification of our cars?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the situation better, let us look at why it is imperative for India to adopt electric mobility. The Indian automobile market has earned the distinction of being a unique market; the Indian auto and ancillary market is among the largest in the world and constitutes 9% of the country’s GDP. 84% of vehicles sold domestically are either two or three Wheelers (2W/3Ws) and therefore, it is imperative for the nation to adapt to electrification now.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV adoption in India is more than just a technological upgradation in the automotive sector. There are varying reasons which make it essential for the fifth largest economy to pace up the process of electrification.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extensive and often reckless use of ICE vehicles paired with exorbitant industrial pollution has worsened the nation’s Air Quality Index (AQI), making it the third most polluted country in the world. Moreover, considering the macroeconomic factors, India imports $100 billion worth of crude oil to quench its industrial and retail demand (which is mostly generated by operational ICE vehicles).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the intent is clear, let’s see how long is the road ahead of our goal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric mobility targets can only be achieved with joint efforts of all the players in the EV ecosystem. Government incentives, appropriate charging infrastructures, battery costs and manufacturing coupled with Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) transitioning from ICE to EV can help in&amp;nbsp; ramping up the process of electrification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade, Indian policymakers have been extensively promoting adoption of electric vehicles, mostly under the umbrella of the National Mission for Electric Mobility (The EV Mission) led by the Department of Heavy Industries (DHI).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction of schemes like FAME II (Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid &amp;amp; Electric Vehicles) and Production Linked Incentive (PLI) coupled with GST incentives are pushed to achieve adoption targets, localisation of key components with an aim to foster electric adoption in both private and public transportation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FAME II aims to provide direct financial benefits to EV manufacturers which would benefit in reducing the cost of acquisition for end-customers. As a mechanism, OEMs first pass on the subsidy support to the end-customer by way of decreased purchase price, and later claim the amount from the DHI.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a mismatch between the market demand and the policy’s vision, as since inception, FAME II has only been able to achieve less than 10% of its target of supporting one million electric two-wheelers, half a million of 3Ws, 55,000 four-wheelers and 7,000 buses by 2022. To tackle the same, new amendments were introduced in June 2021 to reduce the overall vehicle cost and revamp the EV adoption scenario in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the new amendments, the subsidy offered has been revised from ₹10,000 to ₹15,000 per kWh per electric 2W vehicle, thereby increasing the demand incentive by 50%. Maximum cap on subsidies offered has also increased from 20% to 40% of the cost of E-2W, which drastically bridged the Total Cost of Ownership (TCO) gap between conventional ICE and electric two wheelers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric charging infrastructure in the country is at a very nascent stage and the charging grid is more like a mandate to support the operational leg of the electrification process. Therefore, it is important for India to have the required charging infrastructure to accelerate the process.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India needs about 400 thousand charging stations to meet the requirement for two million&amp;nbsp;electric vehicles&amp;nbsp;that could potentially move on its roads by 2026. Currently, it has about 18 hundred charging stations, most of which are slow chargers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest players in this segment is Tata Power which owns a network of over 500 public chargers in 100+ cities across India, and has recently tied up with HPCL to further expand its network.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support the forecasted electricity demand that EV adoption is expected to bring with itself, it is a must for the nation to develop grids which are capable of handling the multitudinous increase in load. India relying on its coal dependent grid is said to be one of the most inefficient ones in the world, thus giving a reason for the nation to shift the composition of the grid towards renewables to truly address the pollution problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of his announcements, the Union Power and New and Renewable Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh disclosed the country’s plans to set up around 14 gigawatt-hour (GWh) grid-scale battery storage system at the world’s largest renewable energy park at Khavda in Gujarat. This is in addition to the plan to invite bids for the largest global tender for setting up a 13GWh grid-scale battery storage system in Ladakh. This strategic push is to make India’s grid-scale battery storage programme the largest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the government's action in this regard but there still lays a long road ahead for the nation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another gap which needs to be bridged to achieve EV adoption is the TCO (Total Cost Ownership) disparity between ICE and EVs. TCO is the sum of upfront and operational costs which a customer has to incur through the life of the vehicle. With batteries constituting 35% of the vehicle cost, it is one of the major drivers of EV’s upfront costs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With inefficient indigenous cell technology and limited access to battery raw materials like Lithium and Cobalt, India is yet to become a leading player in the EV battery industry. Local players like Exicom Power, Amar Raja Batteries, Tata Power have plans to turn this around.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric 2W are smaller vehicles and are easier to electrify, hence they require smaller and simpler batteries and are much closer to economic parity. Li-ion battery based e-rickshaws form a major portion of electric 3W base in the country and have in fact achieved TCO parity and are benefitting from the lower charging costs and time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there still exists a wide gap between TCO parity of electric 4W and buses with their ICE counterparts, mostly due to large battery sizes requirements and lack of complementary infrastructure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla in its recent pitch to the government was successful in lowering import duties on EVs which would eventually make electric vehicles more affordable for the Indian masses. However, the administration is in favor of high import duties as it wishes to encourage domestic production. Therefore, it's too early to show such excitement as only time can vouch for its implementation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the 2W segment being the frontrunner followed by 3W in the ICE-EV shift in India and 4W premium and commercial vehicles yet to achieve the value for money proposition, a lot more has to be done by the government on many fronts such as OEMs transitioning to electric mobility, customers considering EVs over ICE vehicles and other players in the EV segment actively working to achieve India’s goal of becoming a 100% electric vehicle nation by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Agrawal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Over the past ten years, the automobile sector has been gravitating towards electrification. Electrification is essentially the replacement of conventionally used Internal Combustion Engine (ICE) vehicles with more powerful, simpler, smarter and greener Electric Vehicles (EV).&amp;nbsp; EVs came into being before its ICE counterparts but due to lack of infrastructure, high upfront costs and absence of incentives, they could not gain the deserved spotlight. So, are we to believe that the right time has come to think about the electrification of our cars?&amp;nbsp; To understand the situation better, let us look at why it is imperative for India to adopt electric mobility. The Indian automobile market has earned the distinction of being a unique market; the Indian auto and ancillary market is among the largest in the world and constitutes 9% of the country’s GDP. 84% of vehicles sold domestically are either two or three Wheelers (2W/3Ws) and therefore, it is imperative for the nation to adapt to electrification now.&amp;nbsp; EV adoption in India is more than just a technological upgradation in the automotive sector. There are varying reasons which make it essential for the fifth largest economy to pace up the process of electrification.&amp;nbsp; Extensive and often reckless use of ICE vehicles paired with exorbitant industrial pollution has worsened the nation’s Air Quality Index (AQI), making it the third most polluted country in the world. Moreover, considering the macroeconomic factors, India imports $100 billion worth of crude oil to quench its industrial and retail demand (which is mostly generated by operational ICE vehicles).&amp;nbsp; Now that the intent is clear, let’s see how long is the road ahead of our goal.&amp;nbsp; Electric mobility targets can only be achieved with joint efforts of all the players in the EV ecosystem. Government incentives, appropriate charging infrastructures, battery costs and manufacturing coupled with Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) transitioning from ICE to EV can help in&amp;nbsp; ramping up the process of electrification. Over the last decade, Indian policymakers have been extensively promoting adoption of electric vehicles, mostly under the umbrella of the National Mission for Electric Mobility (The EV Mission) led by the Department of Heavy Industries (DHI).&amp;nbsp; Introduction of schemes like FAME II (Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid &amp;amp; Electric Vehicles) and Production Linked Incentive (PLI) coupled with GST incentives are pushed to achieve adoption targets, localisation of key components with an aim to foster electric adoption in both private and public transportation.&amp;nbsp; FAME II aims to provide direct financial benefits to EV manufacturers which would benefit in reducing the cost of acquisition for end-customers. As a mechanism, OEMs first pass on the subsidy support to the end-customer by way of decreased purchase price, and later claim the amount from the DHI.&amp;nbsp; There was a mismatch between the market demand and the policy’s vision, as since inception, FAME II has only been able to achieve less than 10% of its target of supporting one million electric two-wheelers, half a million of 3Ws, 55,000 four-wheelers and 7,000 buses by 2022. To tackle the same, new amendments were introduced in June 2021 to reduce the overall vehicle cost and revamp the EV adoption scenario in the country. As per the new amendments, the subsidy offered has been revised from ₹10,000 to ₹15,000 per kWh per electric 2W vehicle, thereby increasing the demand incentive by 50%. Maximum cap on subsidies offered has also increased from 20% to 40% of the cost of E-2W, which drastically bridged the Total Cost of Ownership (TCO) gap between conventional ICE and electric two wheelers.&amp;nbsp; Electric charging infrastructure in the country is at a very nascent stage and the charging grid is more like a mandate to support the operational leg of the electrification process. Therefore, it is important for India to have the required charging infrastructure to accelerate the process.&amp;nbsp; India needs about 400 thousand charging stations to meet the requirement for two million&amp;nbsp;electric vehicles&amp;nbsp;that could potentially move on its roads by 2026. Currently, it has about 18 hundred charging stations, most of which are slow chargers.&amp;nbsp; One of the biggest players in this segment is Tata Power which owns a network of over 500 public chargers in 100+ cities across India, and has recently tied up with HPCL to further expand its network.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; To support the forecasted electricity demand that EV adoption is expected to bring with itself, it is a must for the nation to develop grids which are capable of handling the multitudinous increase in load. India relying on its coal dependent grid is said to be one of the most inefficient ones in the world, thus giving a reason for the nation to shift the composition of the grid towards renewables to truly address the pollution problem.&amp;nbsp; In one of his announcements, the Union Power and New and Renewable Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh disclosed the country’s plans to set up around 14 gigawatt-hour (GWh) grid-scale battery storage system at the world’s largest renewable energy park at Khavda in Gujarat. This is in addition to the plan to invite bids for the largest global tender for setting up a 13GWh grid-scale battery storage system in Ladakh. This strategic push is to make India’s grid-scale battery storage programme the largest in the world. It is encouraging to see the government's action in this regard but there still lays a long road ahead for the nation.&amp;nbsp; Another gap which needs to be bridged to achieve EV adoption is the TCO (Total Cost Ownership) disparity between ICE and EVs. TCO is the sum of upfront and operational costs which a customer has to incur through the life of the vehicle. With batteries constituting 35% of the vehicle cost, it is one of the major drivers of EV’s upfront costs.&amp;nbsp; With inefficient indigenous cell technology and limited access to battery raw materials like Lithium and Cobalt, India is yet to become a leading player in the EV battery industry. Local players like Exicom Power, Amar Raja Batteries, Tata Power have plans to turn this around.&amp;nbsp; Electric 2W are smaller vehicles and are easier to electrify, hence they require smaller and simpler batteries and are much closer to economic parity. Li-ion battery based e-rickshaws form a major portion of electric 3W base in the country and have in fact achieved TCO parity and are benefitting from the lower charging costs and time.&amp;nbsp; However, there still exists a wide gap between TCO parity of electric 4W and buses with their ICE counterparts, mostly due to large battery sizes requirements and lack of complementary infrastructure.&amp;nbsp; Tesla in its recent pitch to the government was successful in lowering import duties on EVs which would eventually make electric vehicles more affordable for the Indian masses. However, the administration is in favor of high import duties as it wishes to encourage domestic production. Therefore, it's too early to show such excitement as only time can vouch for its implementation.&amp;nbsp; With the 2W segment being the frontrunner followed by 3W in the ICE-EV shift in India and 4W premium and commercial vehicles yet to achieve the value for money proposition, a lot more has to be done by the government on many fronts such as OEMs transitioning to electric mobility, customers considering EVs over ICE vehicles and other players in the EV segment actively working to achieve India’s goal of becoming a 100% electric vehicle nation by 2030.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Winner, Only Victims</title><link href="/No-Winner-Only-Victims" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Winner, Only Victims" /><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/No-Winner-Only-Victims</id><content type="html" xml:base="/No-Winner-Only-Victims">&lt;p&gt;What do you call a Nobel Peace prize winner, an international community favourite and all-around country darling who starves his people and sanctions mass murders? This sparkling introduction belongs to Mr Abiy Ahmed, the Prime Minister of Ethiopia, a 45-year-old computer science and economics major, lauded for his peace efforts and political activism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2010, Abiy Ahmed joined the Ethiopian Parliament. In 2017, he portrayed himself as a symbol of hope: an Oromo Muslim (a marginalised ethnic community of Ethiopia that faced oppression and has a history of land loss) who rose to power despite the obstacles in his path. In 2018, Mr Ahmed won a landslide election amid large-scale anti-government protests to become the Prime Minister. In 2019, he won the Nobel Peace Prize for his initiative in resolving the conflict with the bordering country of Eritrea. In 2020, the civil war began in Tigray.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethiopian troops launched air and ground strikes in Tigray on October 9, 2021. Human Rights Watch reports looting, rape and murder of innocent Tigrayans in this conflict between Abiy Ahmed’s government and the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF), Tigray’s ruling party. To win this civil war, the Ethiopian government is currently starving its citizens in Tigray. International aid organisations send food and medicine, but the military intercepts them before they reach Tigray. Tigray has a population of over seven million. Over two million Tigrayans who have fled their homeland are seeking refuge in Sudan and other neighbouring countries. Newspapers reported patients gunned down in hospitals and young men and boys gunned down in the church.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the victims of this civil war are not limited to Tigrayan and Ethiopian citizens. In September 2021, an international human rights watchdog reported that the Tigrayan military and the Eritrean soldiers raped, murdered and looted Eritrean refugees in the UN camp. Tigray houses thousands of Eritrean refugees in the UN camps established in the region. After the peace resolution between Ethiopia and Eritrea, the Eritrean government sent its military to aid the Ethiopian government in Tigray. Tigrayans responded to this aid by brutalising the Eritrean refugees. The Eritrean military joined in because they considered the refugees as traitors. Both sides of the civil war denied these allegations, and the Eritrean government refused to acknowledge their military’s participation in the destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed started this civil war in November 2020 when he sent troops to topple the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF). He justified his decisions by claiming that he was protecting the country from rebels after the TPLF attacked federal army camps. The actions of TPLF, an anti-government organisation, are a consequence of the Ethiopian government’s marginalisation of Tigray.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The history of this conflict is relevant to what is happening in Ethiopia today. The reason behind the civil war of 2020 is rooted in the conflict of 1991. Derg, a military junta, ruled Ethiopia from 1974-1991. They were responsible for the Red Terror, a violent political campaign to repress dissent and opposition. It was systematic, state-sanctioned mass murder. The Ethiopian People’s Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) overthrew the Derg in 1991. EPRDF was a coalition of TPLF, the Amhara Democratic Party, the Oromo Democratic Party and the Southern Ethiopian People’s Democratic Movement (SEPDM). Each party represented a different ethnicity; the TPLF belonged to the Tigrayan people, The Oromo Democratic for the Oromo people and the Amhara Democratic for the Amhara ethnicity. However, the TPLF dominated the coalition.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the coalition’s rule, the TPLF-dominated EPRDF party was responsible for brutal repressions and human rights violations. They also ostracised the Oromo and Amhara people and were finally kicked out of the coalition by the joint strength of the Oromo Democratic and the Amhara Democratic party in 2018. Abiy Ahmed was consequently voted in as the Prime Minister. He combined all parties of EPRDF and the opposition to form the current ruling party, the Prosperity Party. When the TPLF refused to join and accept his ascent, Mr Ahmed retaliated with military enforcement in Tigray to squash dissent, sparking the civil war in Ethiopia.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a year of violent clashes, murder, rape and human rights violations, the Ethiopian government has stooped lower to creating a famine in Tigray. Tigrayans have not received enough food, medicine and fuel in months. Over 50 thousand Tigrayans have died of starvation. The world leaders are dismayed by Mr Amed’s behaviour. The United States of America has threatened Ethiopia with sanctions if they continue to starve their people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ethiopian economy depends upon duty-free export to America under the African Growth and Opportunity Act. Ethiopia cannot dismiss the threat. However, China and Russia’s involvement and support of the Ethiopian government reduces the magnitude of prospective loss to the Ethiopian economy. The African country depended upon its European allies (France, Germany and America) to supply Ethiopia with arms. But they are now turning to Turkey and Iran. China and Russia are preventing the UN Security Council from putting a stop to the arms trade. The international aid has significantly reduced after Mr Ahmed’s callous disregard of its Western allies, and he has requested an external debt bail-out from the International Monetary Fund. The US and France should consider this debt as a deterrent and capitalise upon it to keep the conflict in Ethiopia from spiralling further out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Eritrean people are angry at their government for sending young men to fight a war in Ethiopia, the country they had until recently called their enemy. Tigrayan people are enraged over the systematic marginalisation and heavy military control in their region. However, neither side can claim innocence after brutalising the refugees. The Ethiopian government is starving its people. The Tigray rebels and Eritrean soldiers are raping and murdering innocent refugees.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Violent conflicts mar Ethiopian history. The EPRDF gave hope to Ethiopia only to snatch it away once it gained power. The Tigray People’s Liberation Front’s rebellion is no longer a fight for a marginalised Tigray but a war for political clout and revenge for being kicked out of the coalition it once led. Mr Ahmed stopped the war with Eritrea only to start one in his homeland. Ethiopia’s story comprises broken promises and selfish governments, and regardless of how it will end, the civil war will not have a winner, only victims.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">What do you call a Nobel Peace prize winner, an international community favourite and all-around country darling who starves his people and sanctions mass murders? This sparkling introduction belongs to Mr Abiy Ahmed, the Prime Minister of Ethiopia, a 45-year-old computer science and economics major, lauded for his peace efforts and political activism.&amp;nbsp; In 2010, Abiy Ahmed joined the Ethiopian Parliament. In 2017, he portrayed himself as a symbol of hope: an Oromo Muslim (a marginalised ethnic community of Ethiopia that faced oppression and has a history of land loss) who rose to power despite the obstacles in his path. In 2018, Mr Ahmed won a landslide election amid large-scale anti-government protests to become the Prime Minister. In 2019, he won the Nobel Peace Prize for his initiative in resolving the conflict with the bordering country of Eritrea. In 2020, the civil war began in Tigray.&amp;nbsp; Ethiopian troops launched air and ground strikes in Tigray on October 9, 2021. Human Rights Watch reports looting, rape and murder of innocent Tigrayans in this conflict between Abiy Ahmed’s government and the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF), Tigray’s ruling party. To win this civil war, the Ethiopian government is currently starving its citizens in Tigray. International aid organisations send food and medicine, but the military intercepts them before they reach Tigray. Tigray has a population of over seven million. Over two million Tigrayans who have fled their homeland are seeking refuge in Sudan and other neighbouring countries. Newspapers reported patients gunned down in hospitals and young men and boys gunned down in the church.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; However, the victims of this civil war are not limited to Tigrayan and Ethiopian citizens. In September 2021, an international human rights watchdog reported that the Tigrayan military and the Eritrean soldiers raped, murdered and looted Eritrean refugees in the UN camp. Tigray houses thousands of Eritrean refugees in the UN camps established in the region. After the peace resolution between Ethiopia and Eritrea, the Eritrean government sent its military to aid the Ethiopian government in Tigray. Tigrayans responded to this aid by brutalising the Eritrean refugees. The Eritrean military joined in because they considered the refugees as traitors. Both sides of the civil war denied these allegations, and the Eritrean government refused to acknowledge their military’s participation in the destruction. Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed started this civil war in November 2020 when he sent troops to topple the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF). He justified his decisions by claiming that he was protecting the country from rebels after the TPLF attacked federal army camps. The actions of TPLF, an anti-government organisation, are a consequence of the Ethiopian government’s marginalisation of Tigray.&amp;nbsp; The history of this conflict is relevant to what is happening in Ethiopia today. The reason behind the civil war of 2020 is rooted in the conflict of 1991. Derg, a military junta, ruled Ethiopia from 1974-1991. They were responsible for the Red Terror, a violent political campaign to repress dissent and opposition. It was systematic, state-sanctioned mass murder. The Ethiopian People’s Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) overthrew the Derg in 1991. EPRDF was a coalition of TPLF, the Amhara Democratic Party, the Oromo Democratic Party and the Southern Ethiopian People’s Democratic Movement (SEPDM). Each party represented a different ethnicity; the TPLF belonged to the Tigrayan people, The Oromo Democratic for the Oromo people and the Amhara Democratic for the Amhara ethnicity. However, the TPLF dominated the coalition.&amp;nbsp; During the coalition’s rule, the TPLF-dominated EPRDF party was responsible for brutal repressions and human rights violations. They also ostracised the Oromo and Amhara people and were finally kicked out of the coalition by the joint strength of the Oromo Democratic and the Amhara Democratic party in 2018. Abiy Ahmed was consequently voted in as the Prime Minister. He combined all parties of EPRDF and the opposition to form the current ruling party, the Prosperity Party. When the TPLF refused to join and accept his ascent, Mr Ahmed retaliated with military enforcement in Tigray to squash dissent, sparking the civil war in Ethiopia.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; After a year of violent clashes, murder, rape and human rights violations, the Ethiopian government has stooped lower to creating a famine in Tigray. Tigrayans have not received enough food, medicine and fuel in months. Over 50 thousand Tigrayans have died of starvation. The world leaders are dismayed by Mr Amed’s behaviour. The United States of America has threatened Ethiopia with sanctions if they continue to starve their people.&amp;nbsp; The Ethiopian economy depends upon duty-free export to America under the African Growth and Opportunity Act. Ethiopia cannot dismiss the threat. However, China and Russia’s involvement and support of the Ethiopian government reduces the magnitude of prospective loss to the Ethiopian economy. The African country depended upon its European allies (France, Germany and America) to supply Ethiopia with arms. But they are now turning to Turkey and Iran. China and Russia are preventing the UN Security Council from putting a stop to the arms trade. The international aid has significantly reduced after Mr Ahmed’s callous disregard of its Western allies, and he has requested an external debt bail-out from the International Monetary Fund. The US and France should consider this debt as a deterrent and capitalise upon it to keep the conflict in Ethiopia from spiralling further out of control. The Eritrean people are angry at their government for sending young men to fight a war in Ethiopia, the country they had until recently called their enemy. Tigrayan people are enraged over the systematic marginalisation and heavy military control in their region. However, neither side can claim innocence after brutalising the refugees. The Ethiopian government is starving its people. The Tigray rebels and Eritrean soldiers are raping and murdering innocent refugees.&amp;nbsp; Violent conflicts mar Ethiopian history. The EPRDF gave hope to Ethiopia only to snatch it away once it gained power. The Tigray People’s Liberation Front’s rebellion is no longer a fight for a marginalised Tigray but a war for political clout and revenge for being kicked out of the coalition it once led. Mr Ahmed stopped the war with Eritrea only to start one in his homeland. Ethiopia’s story comprises broken promises and selfish governments, and regardless of how it will end, the civil war will not have a winner, only victims.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Circular Economy in India</title><link href="/Circular-Economy-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Circular Economy in India" /><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Circular-Economy-in-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Circular-Economy-in-India">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Industrial development in the last century has been dominated by the linear model of production and consumption, in which the goods are manufactured from raw materials, sold, used and then discarded as waste.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, sharp volatility increases across the global economy and increasing signs of resource depletion in the last few years have resulted in a growing push for a new economic model.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;These changes have incentivised businesses to explore ways to restore their inputs through reuse and recycle of the products or components. This forms the essence of a circular economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What, how, and why&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Ellen MacArthur Foundation defines circular economy as an &quot;&lt;em&gt;industrial system that is restorative or regenerative by intention and design&lt;/em&gt;.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It replaces the linear economy concept with restoration; shifts to the use of renewable energy; eliminates the use of toxic chemicals that impair reuse and return to the biosphere; and strives for waste elimination through superior design of materials, products, systems and business models.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In other words, a circular economy model seeks to bridge the gap between production and the natural ecosystems' cycles, on which humans ultimately rely.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The capability to recover the value of materials, labour, energy and capital incorporated in products after each cycle of use is a key motivator for adopting the circular economy, which would not be achievable with conventional produced products (not designed for reverse cycles).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Additionally, if resource prices&amp;nbsp;witness a significant growth in near future, and the costs of establishing the necessary reverse cycle networks drop, the attractiveness of these circular models intensify. As long as these two conditions are actually in place, the time is now appropriate to accelerate the transition to a circular economy on a large scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The circular economy concept entails two sets of activities: first, waste elimination through biodegradable waste composting and reusing, remanufacturing, and recycling of transformed and non-biodegradable waste, and second, switching to renewable energy instead of chemical substances.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In a circular economy, no product goes to waste; everything is designed to maximise the value of the materials contained inside it while preserving their high utility at all times. This can be understood better with the help of figure below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-10-12-Circular-Economy-in-India-cicrcular-economy-in-india-image1.png&quot; /&gt;Source: Ellen MacArthur Foundation, Towards the Circular Economy (2013).&lt;/div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://reports.weforum.org/toward-the-circular-economy-accelerating-the-scale-up-across-global-supply-chains/from-linear-to-circular-accelerating-a-proven-concept/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://reports.weforum.org/toward-the-circular-economy-accelerating-the-scale-up-across-global-supply-chains/from-linear-to-circular-accelerating-a-proven-concept/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The transition to a circular model is expected to benefit economies in a variety of ways.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In its report:&lt;em&gt; Towards the Circular Economy &lt;/em&gt;(2013), the Ellen MacArthur Foundation forecasts significant&amp;nbsp;net material savings, price volatility and supply risk reduction, enhanced rates of innovation&amp;nbsp;employment and capital productivity, decreased externalities, and long-term economic resilience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The approach would thus shift the economic balance away from energy-intensive materials and primary extraction to create a new sector dedicated to reverse cycle activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The emerging market economies in particular will have the opportunity to dive straight into establishing circular setups when developing their manufacturing-based sectors because they are not as ‘restricted’ as advanced economies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, since many emerging market economies are more material intensive than the developed economies, circular business models could result in even greater relative savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circular Economy in India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Circular economy ideals (reuse, re-purpose, and recycling) have been prevalent and practiced in Indian society for a long time, passed down as lessons from generation to generation, making a strong case for India to transition to a circular economy. Doing so will not only&amp;nbsp;reduce resource dependency but&amp;nbsp;also increase&amp;nbsp;competitiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to the Ellen MacArthur Foundation, a circular economic development path in India could generate a yearly value of $218 billion in 2030 and $624 billion in 2050, as compared to the existing development scenario.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;These cost savings could amount to 11% of current Indian GDP in 2030 and 30% in 2050. Adopting the strategy would also help businesses save expenditure on materials by improving product design, developing new business models, and utilising reverse logistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, compared to the current scenario, greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions might be 23% lower in 2030 and 44% lower in 2050. Other negative externalities, such as those caused by the linear use of raw materials and water, as well as the use of synthetic fertilizers&amp;nbsp;would be reduced. On the circular growth path, the cost of delivering the promised services to each citizen would be far lower than on the current path, increasing disposable income.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, because India is well-known for its IT sector, it is well-positioned to capitalise on the prospects for value creation provided by the interaction of the circular economy and digital technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Three key sectors of Indian economy that provide significant prospects for a circular economy transition are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cities and construction:&lt;/strong&gt; India is urbanising at an unprecedented rate against a background of resource constraints. According to the recent estimates, there exists a necessity to construct an estimated 700-900 million square meters of additional commercial and residential space a year to meet this increasing demand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In this scenario, employing renewable and recycled resources as well as modular construction technologies will effectively reduce waste and construction costs.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, circular economy ideas might be integrated into the infrastructure required to provide water, sanitation, and waste disposal services on a large scale.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food and agriculture:&lt;/strong&gt; The agriculture sector employs half of the country's workforce and is crucial to food security. By using the existing&amp;nbsp;farm system, India has the opportunity to develop large-scale networks of farmers that are interconnected and symbiotic in their operations and devoted to regenerative approaches.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In addition, combining local knowledge and traditional methods with modern technology holds&amp;nbsp;potential to increase production while substantially lowering the use of resources like water, synthetic fertilizers, and pesticides. This will ultimately result in making&amp;nbsp;the Indian food system even more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobility and vehicle manufacturing:&lt;/strong&gt; Personal mobility in India is expected to double, if not triple, by 2030, overtaking China and the United States as the world's third largest market. Therefore, the circular economy strategy can aid in the development of a mobility system that serves the growing needs of its citizens, particularly in cities, while reducing negative externalities such as GHG emissions, traffic congestion, and pollution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Given the advantages of a circular economy, the government has been developing rules and encouraging projects to drive the country closer to the model. In this regard, it has already notified several rules, including the Plastic Waste Management Rules, e-Waste Management Rules, Construction and Demolition Waste Management Rules, Metals Recycling Policy, and so on.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, many parts of circularity are deeply embedded in people's habits, as seen by high rates of vehicle utilisation and maintenance, as well as distributed post-use material recovery and recycling. These, albeit informal, activities provide a source of income to some of India's poorest sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Despite the efforts of governments, businesses, and other stakeholders to align their activities with circular economy concepts, the consequences have been underwhelming. In reality, we are actually dealing with an enormously growing waste problem. This is because most efforts are made at the very end of value chains, resulting in sub-optimal economic and environmental outcomes as well as health risks for people involved.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, as the Indian economy and middle class expand, these practices will become less appealing unless a more systematic plan is implemented to modernise and move them up the value ladder.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, as India becomes more linked with the global market and its linear supply chains, economies of scale may drag the country towards the same one-way growth model that developed economies adopted, limiting the impact of present circular practices and perhaps establishing a linear lock-in.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rajsi Sah</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Industrial development in the last century has been dominated by the linear model of production and consumption, in which the goods are manufactured from raw materials, sold, used and then discarded as waste.&amp;nbsp; However, sharp volatility increases across the global economy and increasing signs of resource depletion in the last few years have resulted in a growing push for a new economic model.&amp;nbsp; These changes have incentivised businesses to explore ways to restore their inputs through reuse and recycle of the products or components. This forms the essence of a circular economy.&amp;nbsp; What, how, and why The Ellen MacArthur Foundation defines circular economy as an &quot;industrial system that is restorative or regenerative by intention and design.&quot;&amp;nbsp; It replaces the linear economy concept with restoration; shifts to the use of renewable energy; eliminates the use of toxic chemicals that impair reuse and return to the biosphere; and strives for waste elimination through superior design of materials, products, systems and business models.&amp;nbsp; In other words, a circular economy model seeks to bridge the gap between production and the natural ecosystems' cycles, on which humans ultimately rely.&amp;nbsp; The capability to recover the value of materials, labour, energy and capital incorporated in products after each cycle of use is a key motivator for adopting the circular economy, which would not be achievable with conventional produced products (not designed for reverse cycles).&amp;nbsp; Additionally, if resource prices&amp;nbsp;witness a significant growth in near future, and the costs of establishing the necessary reverse cycle networks drop, the attractiveness of these circular models intensify. As long as these two conditions are actually in place, the time is now appropriate to accelerate the transition to a circular economy on a large scale. The circular economy concept entails two sets of activities: first, waste elimination through biodegradable waste composting and reusing, remanufacturing, and recycling of transformed and non-biodegradable waste, and second, switching to renewable energy instead of chemical substances.&amp;nbsp; In a circular economy, no product goes to waste; everything is designed to maximise the value of the materials contained inside it while preserving their high utility at all times. This can be understood better with the help of figure below: Source: Ellen MacArthur Foundation, Towards the Circular Economy (2013).&amp;nbsp; Source: https://reports.weforum.org/toward-the-circular-economy-accelerating-the-scale-up-across-global-supply-chains/from-linear-to-circular-accelerating-a-proven-concept/&amp;nbsp; The transition to a circular model is expected to benefit economies in a variety of ways.&amp;nbsp; In its report: Towards the Circular Economy (2013), the Ellen MacArthur Foundation forecasts significant&amp;nbsp;net material savings, price volatility and supply risk reduction, enhanced rates of innovation&amp;nbsp;employment and capital productivity, decreased externalities, and long-term economic resilience.&amp;nbsp; The approach would thus shift the economic balance away from energy-intensive materials and primary extraction to create a new sector dedicated to reverse cycle activities.&amp;nbsp; The emerging market economies in particular will have the opportunity to dive straight into establishing circular setups when developing their manufacturing-based sectors because they are not as ‘restricted’ as advanced economies.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, since many emerging market economies are more material intensive than the developed economies, circular business models could result in even greater relative savings. Circular Economy in India Circular economy ideals (reuse, re-purpose, and recycling) have been prevalent and practiced in Indian society for a long time, passed down as lessons from generation to generation, making a strong case for India to transition to a circular economy. Doing so will not only&amp;nbsp;reduce resource dependency but&amp;nbsp;also increase&amp;nbsp;competitiveness. According to the Ellen MacArthur Foundation, a circular economic development path in India could generate a yearly value of $218 billion in 2030 and $624 billion in 2050, as compared to the existing development scenario.&amp;nbsp; These cost savings could amount to 11% of current Indian GDP in 2030 and 30% in 2050. Adopting the strategy would also help businesses save expenditure on materials by improving product design, developing new business models, and utilising reverse logistics.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, compared to the current scenario, greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions might be 23% lower in 2030 and 44% lower in 2050. Other negative externalities, such as those caused by the linear use of raw materials and water, as well as the use of synthetic fertilizers&amp;nbsp;would be reduced. On the circular growth path, the cost of delivering the promised services to each citizen would be far lower than on the current path, increasing disposable income.&amp;nbsp; Finally, because India is well-known for its IT sector, it is well-positioned to capitalise on the prospects for value creation provided by the interaction of the circular economy and digital technology. Three key sectors of Indian economy that provide significant prospects for a circular economy transition are: Cities and construction: India is urbanising at an unprecedented rate against a background of resource constraints. According to the recent estimates, there exists a necessity to construct an estimated 700-900 million square meters of additional commercial and residential space a year to meet this increasing demand.&amp;nbsp; In this scenario, employing renewable and recycled resources as well as modular construction technologies will effectively reduce waste and construction costs.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, circular economy ideas might be integrated into the infrastructure required to provide water, sanitation, and waste disposal services on a large scale.&amp;nbsp; Food and agriculture: The agriculture sector employs half of the country's workforce and is crucial to food security. By using the existing&amp;nbsp;farm system, India has the opportunity to develop large-scale networks of farmers that are interconnected and symbiotic in their operations and devoted to regenerative approaches.&amp;nbsp; In addition, combining local knowledge and traditional methods with modern technology holds&amp;nbsp;potential to increase production while substantially lowering the use of resources like water, synthetic fertilizers, and pesticides. This will ultimately result in making&amp;nbsp;the Indian food system even more efficient. Mobility and vehicle manufacturing: Personal mobility in India is expected to double, if not triple, by 2030, overtaking China and the United States as the world's third largest market. Therefore, the circular economy strategy can aid in the development of a mobility system that serves the growing needs of its citizens, particularly in cities, while reducing negative externalities such as GHG emissions, traffic congestion, and pollution. Given the advantages of a circular economy, the government has been developing rules and encouraging projects to drive the country closer to the model. In this regard, it has already notified several rules, including the Plastic Waste Management Rules, e-Waste Management Rules, Construction and Demolition Waste Management Rules, Metals Recycling Policy, and so on.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, many parts of circularity are deeply embedded in people's habits, as seen by high rates of vehicle utilisation and maintenance, as well as distributed post-use material recovery and recycling. These, albeit informal, activities provide a source of income to some of India's poorest sections. Despite the efforts of governments, businesses, and other stakeholders to align their activities with circular economy concepts, the consequences have been underwhelming. In reality, we are actually dealing with an enormously growing waste problem. This is because most efforts are made at the very end of value chains, resulting in sub-optimal economic and environmental outcomes as well as health risks for people involved.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, as the Indian economy and middle class expand, these practices will become less appealing unless a more systematic plan is implemented to modernise and move them up the value ladder.&amp;nbsp; Finally, as India becomes more linked with the global market and its linear supply chains, economies of scale may drag the country towards the same one-way growth model that developed economies adopted, limiting the impact of present circular practices and perhaps establishing a linear lock-in.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Ambani or Tata the Ratan the Answer We’ve Been Looking For?</title><link href="/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Ambani or Tata the Ratan the Answer We've Been Looking For?" /><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For">&lt;p&gt;The dynamics of the power and influence that the Ambanis and the Tatas hold in the Indian market has evolved considerably in the past few decades. While some may argue that the Reliance group has surpassed the Tata conglomerate, here’s a take on why that’s not even marginally correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preconceived notions, pertaining to money and wealth, are the main reason behind such false assumptions. Mukesh Ambani is indeed the richest man in India with a net worth of $91 billion, while Shri Ratan Tata’s worth is estimated at $1 billion. Based on these statistics alone, people jump to conclusions that the richer party, in this case the Ambanis, is superior to the other side, the Tatas. But is monetary wealth enough of a metric to label which group possesses the higher ground?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ambanis are known for their affluent nature and have never shied away from displaying their prosperity. From throwing weddings of the century, hosting private Beyoncé concerts to living in a 27-storey sky palace, ‘Antilia’, they’ve often caused social media uproar and made headlines.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In stark contrast, Tatas live a relatively humble life with 66% of their company stake held by charitable organisations such as the Sir Ratan Tata Trust, Sir Dorabji Tata Trust, Tata Education Trust to name a few. Their primary goal was, and has always been, the financial and social empowerment of the entire nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To delve further into the details of this ill-conceived and strikingly biased opinion, one must start to understand the elementary difference between a businessman and an industrialist. The former is more concerned with maximising their own profits while, the latter makes it their concern to consider the best interests of the society at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Booming Businessman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dhirubhai Ambani and his rise to fortune is a true rags-to-riches story. His success in taking his company public in 1977, expanding from textiles to other sectors such as petrochemicals, which in-turn led to the formation of what we know today as ‘Reliance Industries’, was largely owed to his sharp business acumen, excellent entrepreneurial skills and great oratorship. He was what we refer to as a ‘one in a million’ case wherein a high school dropout, with no significant education, made it big!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major reasons behind his success was the value and vitality he placed on the quality of service that was associated with the Ambani name. He prioritised his promise to the shareholders, declared regular dividends and held annual meetings to strengthen mutual trustworthiness.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After his death in 2002, the company was divided between his two sons, Mukesh and Anil. While the former inherited his father’s business instincts, the same seemed to have been lost in the case of the latter. Mukesh Ambani expanded the spectrum covered under Reliance Industries far beyond expectations, and one of his most remarkable achievements was the launch of Reliance Jio in 2016. Not only was Jio a real game changer, but it also sparked a price war in the super-competitive telecom market in India, and gave otherwise unparalleled companies like Airtel a run for its money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliance was the first Indian company to be included in the Fortune 500 companies list. The consolidated efforts of two generations, branching from Vimal to Jio, resulted in an increase in annual revenue from ₹700 million at the time its IPO was first launched, to over ₹750 billion in the year 2002.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today RIL is an oil-to-telecom conglomerate with a valuation of about ₹6.10 trillion. It is the first company to have a market capitalisation of ₹9 trillion on the Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE). Out of this, about 48% stake is personally controlled by Mukesh Ambani, and while Reliance did purchase some gas companies in the US and occasionally in Europe, it largely remains an Indian entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Business must serve a larger societal purpose.” – &lt;/em&gt;Mukesh Ambani&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above statement is quite ironic as the Ambanis, like most business families, donate only a small fraction of their wealth. To substantiate, in 2018, Ambani donated a seemingly grand amount of ₹4.02 billion, which in reality amounted only to 0.1% of his net worth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the world came to a standstill during the pandemic, Reliance Jio continued its successful operations based on the philosophy that the show must go on. Not only did it see a 15.5% growth in net profit to ₹34.89 billion in the fourth quarter of 2020-21, but also an additional increase of 5.2 million customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At such times of crisis, despite having enjoyed phenomenal growth and profits, Mukesh Ambani pledged to donate only ₹50 million to Maharashtra Chief Minister’s Relief Fund as monetary contributions whereas Mr. Ratan Tata, Tata Sons and Tata Trusts collectively pledged a total of ₹15 billion for combating the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The International Industrialist&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey of the trailblazers began in 1868, when Jamsetji Tata invested ₹21,000 in his own trading business. However, his sight was set on the textile business. Following his newfound objective, he returned from England equipped with knowledge and moved out of Mumbai to Nagpur which was comparatively economical.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What made Tatas the true tycoons was the care they extended to their workers and the importance they laid on the welfare of the society. These measures resonated among the masses with the same level of loyalty and appreciation reciprocated by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jamsetji Tata had four major goals in life: an iron and steel company, a world class educational institution, a hydroelectric power plant and a five star hotel. However, in his lifetime he could only manage to accomplish the task of building the Taj hotel in Mumbai, which serves as a symbol of his glorious march into the future till date. The rest of his dreams were realised by his son Dorabji Tata.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This proud legacy was carried on by JRD Tata, under whom the Tata Group grew from $100 million to over $5 billion, establishing itself as a conglomerate of 95 companies including Tata Tea, Tata Motors &amp;amp; TCS.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, The Tata Group has products and services in 150 countries spread over 6 continents, with a ₹6.11 trillion valuation, $100 billion in revenues, i.e., over ₹11 trillion of market capitalisation and 29 publicly listed companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite such a remarkable feat it's quite intriguing as to why the Tatas are not the richest businessmen in India, though the Tata Group is India’s numero uno conglomerate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Tatas have done much to introduce industrial capitalism in India in place of the old mercantile and petty capitalism. As the companies progressed, they socialised the business by transferring much of the ownership to charitable trusts.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;- &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Professor Gras of Harvard Business School.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staying true to this promise, Shri Ratan Tata’s personal stake in Tata industries is less than 1%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other business tycoons, he donates a big chunk of his wealth to several trusts, the largest being the Sir Dorabji Tata Trust (28%), followed by the Sir Ratan Tata Trust (23.5%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Bigger of the Big Fish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to when asked why he was not the richest man in the world, Ratan Tata said, &lt;em&gt;“Ambanis are businessmen and the Tatas are industrialists.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This difference in outlook represents a bigger value difference between the two behemoths and their line of thinking. While both the groups create livelihood for millions and represent big parts of India, one chooses to add to the bottom of the pyramid in his own capacity, while one leaves the bigger machinery to its own devices.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is moot to discuss who is doing “more”, but if not for his philanthropic nature, Ratan Tata could easily be one of the richest people in the world, let alone India, making it clear without an iota of doubt that Mukesh Ambani may be the richest man in India but the Tata Conglomerate reigns supreme over Reliance Industries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Raisa Azad</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The dynamics of the power and influence that the Ambanis and the Tatas hold in the Indian market has evolved considerably in the past few decades. While some may argue that the Reliance group has surpassed the Tata conglomerate, here’s a take on why that’s not even marginally correct. Preconceived notions, pertaining to money and wealth, are the main reason behind such false assumptions. Mukesh Ambani is indeed the richest man in India with a net worth of $91 billion, while Shri Ratan Tata’s worth is estimated at $1 billion. Based on these statistics alone, people jump to conclusions that the richer party, in this case the Ambanis, is superior to the other side, the Tatas. But is monetary wealth enough of a metric to label which group possesses the higher ground? The Ambanis are known for their affluent nature and have never shied away from displaying their prosperity. From throwing weddings of the century, hosting private Beyoncé concerts to living in a 27-storey sky palace, ‘Antilia’, they’ve often caused social media uproar and made headlines.&amp;nbsp; In stark contrast, Tatas live a relatively humble life with 66% of their company stake held by charitable organisations such as the Sir Ratan Tata Trust, Sir Dorabji Tata Trust, Tata Education Trust to name a few. Their primary goal was, and has always been, the financial and social empowerment of the entire nation. To delve further into the details of this ill-conceived and strikingly biased opinion, one must start to understand the elementary difference between a businessman and an industrialist. The former is more concerned with maximising their own profits while, the latter makes it their concern to consider the best interests of the society at large. The Booming Businessman Dhirubhai Ambani and his rise to fortune is a true rags-to-riches story. His success in taking his company public in 1977, expanding from textiles to other sectors such as petrochemicals, which in-turn led to the formation of what we know today as ‘Reliance Industries’, was largely owed to his sharp business acumen, excellent entrepreneurial skills and great oratorship. He was what we refer to as a ‘one in a million’ case wherein a high school dropout, with no significant education, made it big!&amp;nbsp; One of the major reasons behind his success was the value and vitality he placed on the quality of service that was associated with the Ambani name. He prioritised his promise to the shareholders, declared regular dividends and held annual meetings to strengthen mutual trustworthiness.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; After his death in 2002, the company was divided between his two sons, Mukesh and Anil. While the former inherited his father’s business instincts, the same seemed to have been lost in the case of the latter. Mukesh Ambani expanded the spectrum covered under Reliance Industries far beyond expectations, and one of his most remarkable achievements was the launch of Reliance Jio in 2016. Not only was Jio a real game changer, but it also sparked a price war in the super-competitive telecom market in India, and gave otherwise unparalleled companies like Airtel a run for its money. Reliance was the first Indian company to be included in the Fortune 500 companies list. The consolidated efforts of two generations, branching from Vimal to Jio, resulted in an increase in annual revenue from ₹700 million at the time its IPO was first launched, to over ₹750 billion in the year 2002.&amp;nbsp; Today RIL is an oil-to-telecom conglomerate with a valuation of about ₹6.10 trillion. It is the first company to have a market capitalisation of ₹9 trillion on the Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE). Out of this, about 48% stake is personally controlled by Mukesh Ambani, and while Reliance did purchase some gas companies in the US and occasionally in Europe, it largely remains an Indian entity. “Business must serve a larger societal purpose.” – Mukesh Ambani The above statement is quite ironic as the Ambanis, like most business families, donate only a small fraction of their wealth. To substantiate, in 2018, Ambani donated a seemingly grand amount of ₹4.02 billion, which in reality amounted only to 0.1% of his net worth.&amp;nbsp; While the world came to a standstill during the pandemic, Reliance Jio continued its successful operations based on the philosophy that the show must go on. Not only did it see a 15.5% growth in net profit to ₹34.89 billion in the fourth quarter of 2020-21, but also an additional increase of 5.2 million customers. At such times of crisis, despite having enjoyed phenomenal growth and profits, Mukesh Ambani pledged to donate only ₹50 million to Maharashtra Chief Minister’s Relief Fund as monetary contributions whereas Mr. Ratan Tata, Tata Sons and Tata Trusts collectively pledged a total of ₹15 billion for combating the coronavirus pandemic. The International Industrialist&amp;nbsp; The journey of the trailblazers began in 1868, when Jamsetji Tata invested ₹21,000 in his own trading business. However, his sight was set on the textile business. Following his newfound objective, he returned from England equipped with knowledge and moved out of Mumbai to Nagpur which was comparatively economical.&amp;nbsp; What made Tatas the true tycoons was the care they extended to their workers and the importance they laid on the welfare of the society. These measures resonated among the masses with the same level of loyalty and appreciation reciprocated by them. Jamsetji Tata had four major goals in life: an iron and steel company, a world class educational institution, a hydroelectric power plant and a five star hotel. However, in his lifetime he could only manage to accomplish the task of building the Taj hotel in Mumbai, which serves as a symbol of his glorious march into the future till date. The rest of his dreams were realised by his son Dorabji Tata.&amp;nbsp; This proud legacy was carried on by JRD Tata, under whom the Tata Group grew from $100 million to over $5 billion, establishing itself as a conglomerate of 95 companies including Tata Tea, Tata Motors &amp;amp; TCS.&amp;nbsp; Currently, The Tata Group has products and services in 150 countries spread over 6 continents, with a ₹6.11 trillion valuation, $100 billion in revenues, i.e., over ₹11 trillion of market capitalisation and 29 publicly listed companies. Despite such a remarkable feat it's quite intriguing as to why the Tatas are not the richest businessmen in India, though the Tata Group is India’s numero uno conglomerate.&amp;nbsp; “Tatas have done much to introduce industrial capitalism in India in place of the old mercantile and petty capitalism. As the companies progressed, they socialised the business by transferring much of the ownership to charitable trusts.” - Professor Gras of Harvard Business School. Staying true to this promise, Shri Ratan Tata’s personal stake in Tata industries is less than 1%.&amp;nbsp; Unlike other business tycoons, he donates a big chunk of his wealth to several trusts, the largest being the Sir Dorabji Tata Trust (28%), followed by the Sir Ratan Tata Trust (23.5%). The Bigger of the Big Fish In response to when asked why he was not the richest man in the world, Ratan Tata said, “Ambanis are businessmen and the Tatas are industrialists.” This difference in outlook represents a bigger value difference between the two behemoths and their line of thinking. While both the groups create livelihood for millions and represent big parts of India, one chooses to add to the bottom of the pyramid in his own capacity, while one leaves the bigger machinery to its own devices.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It is moot to discuss who is doing “more”, but if not for his philanthropic nature, Ratan Tata could easily be one of the richest people in the world, let alone India, making it clear without an iota of doubt that Mukesh Ambani may be the richest man in India but the Tata Conglomerate reigns supreme over Reliance Industries.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Female Labour Force Participation in India: Why Is It So Stunted?</title><link href="/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Female Labour Force Participation in India: Why Is It So Stunted?" /><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Recently, India has found itself in the monetary and segment conditions that would prompt an increased female workforce participation rate. Financial development has been high, averaging at 6-7% during the 1990's and 2000's. On the other hand, fertility has significantly fallen alongside the drastic rise in training of females.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, according to the International Labour Organisation's (ILO) estimates, the female labour force participation rate (FLPR) in India has declined from 30.27% in 1990 to 20.33% in 2020. The average value of the said figure for India during the period between 1990-2020 was 27.38%, with a minimum of 20.33% (in 2020) and maximum of 31.79% (in 2005).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The average for 2020, based on 182 countries, was 51.86%. Rwanda scored the highest rate of 83.95% and Yemen the lowest at 5.69%. The FLPR for China, the country with the largest population, was 64% while for the US, it was 56.3%. Women remained underrepresented in the Indian workforce, a circumstance that has not changed in the last 30 years.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Among its neighbouring countries, India’s FLPR is shockingly the lowest, falling even behind Afghanistan and Pakistan, which had scored half of India’s rates back in 1990. Nepal has a FLPR of 83% which is an all-time high amongst all the South Asian economies, and Pakistan (India’ biggest rival) has secured a higher position by 4 points, sitting at a FLPR of 24.6%. Globally only Yemen, Iraq, Jordan, Syria, Algeria, Iran, the West Bank and Gaza have lower rates than India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Analysis of National Sampling Survey Office (NSSO) data (1970-2018) shows that women have largely been undertaking home-based and labour intensive informal work concentrated in low-productivity sectors. During the period of 1977-2017, the proportion of women working in agriculture fell from 88.1% to 73.2% in the rural areas, while their share in the service sector rose from 35.7% to 60.7% in the urban areas. Females in the tertiary sector concentrated in professions such as teaching and nursing, which provided restricted scope for progression in their careers. However, unlike their male counterparts, females could not increase their presence in the secondary sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What explains low participation in India?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the last decade, fertility has declined rapidly while wages have expanded considerably, and the contribution for this goes to the high speed of development in the country. Furthermore, avenues for job seekers are not rare, except for the educated workforce where there is a distinct relative shortage. So why are more females not entering the workforce?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to a paper published in 2008, much of the discussion on the falling trends in female labour force participation has focused on four key elements:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;1) rising enrolment in secondary schooling;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;2) wage and sex discrimination in the workplace;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;3) increase in household incomes; and&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;4) females engaged in either unpaid family jobs or marginal jobs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There has been an increase in the percentage of women who have completed a minimum of secondary level education or more, particularly in rural India. The NSSO data also confirms younger women have greater aspirations to participate in the labour market than the previous generations, however, due to norms around chastity and early marriage (still heavily prevalent in the country), they are prevented from doing so. The average age of marriage for girls in rural India is around 21.7 years. Additionally, there has been a fall in participation rate of approximately 30% owing to greater demand on their time to pursue education. Post their education, absence of appropriate job availability leads to their lower participation in the workforce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There exists a U-shaped relation between education and paid work participation, yet the rate of return for each year of education is lower for women than men in India. This relation also asserts the fact that illiterate women are forced to rely on the unorganised sector for meeting their basic needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Wage and sex dicrimination within the workplace is an addition amongst the above mentioned factors where females are rewarded with a lower pay and greater discrimination than their male counterparts. This is serious as it not only affects the economic growth of the nation but also speaks volume on the prevalent working conditions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Males are awarded with a pay of more than 19% than their female colleagues. This income disparity has only narrowed by 1% in 2018 from the 20% of the preceding year. The pay inequality can be corresponded to the following factors - discriminaton and occupational decisions by females into lower paying jobs, such as clerical work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another interesting reason for lower female workforce participation can be attributed to the fact that many educated females drop out of the workforce due the family income effect, i.e., with an increase in family earnings, the dependency on females to work fall, thereby shifting their attention towards domestic chores and child care. As a result women hailing from higher economic status are less likely to work than women belonging from lower income strata.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This gap widens when we look at the 2019 report by the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation, wherein it becomes evident that the burden of unpaid labour falls on women significantly in the country. The report states that an average Indian woman spends nearly 84% of her working hours on unpaid work while the men spend 80% of their working hours on paid work.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the government doing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Government has taken several steps to increase the female workforce participation rate in India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Ministry of Skill Development and Entrepreneurship (MSDE) has been set up for improving the involvement rate across sectors and areas. Likewise the government has also initiated the National Career Service (NCS) project which entails a digital portal to link jobseekers and businesses for work and incorporate a repository of enlarged career content.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Other steps include incorporation of the &lt;em&gt;Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act, 2017 &lt;/em&gt;by institutions which focuses on improvement in paid maternity leaves from 12 weeks to 26 weeks, and arrangement for compulsory crèche services in establishments having at least 50 employees; issue of an advisory to the States under the &lt;em&gt;Factories Act, 1948&lt;/em&gt; for allowing women workers of night shifts with sufficient safety measures.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, to improve the employability of female labourers, numerous institutes have been set up to provide them with training ranging from vocational to industrial. Various work laws have been amended to foster a more safe and amicable work environment for women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Laws for a fairer work environment passed by the government include:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Minimum Wage Act 1948&lt;/em&gt;, the wages set by the corresponding government are equally applicable to male and female workers, and therefore, the law doesn't segregate on the premise of sex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Equal Remuneration Act 1976 &lt;/em&gt;provides for equal wages to be paid to employees for similar jobs, with no discrimination based on sex, class, caste or religion followed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Protection of Women against Sexual Harassment at Workplace Act 2013&lt;/em&gt; characterizes lewd behavior or sexual harassment at the workplace, and helps in the redressal of such objections. It provides shields against fake or noxious charges.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, many government policies are targeted towards the organised workforce while the&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;unorganised sector that homes the largest number of females has very little to no penetration of such&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;schemes, thereby making government policies ineffective to some extent. Additionally, in several areas, these policies are only restricted to documentation, thus, never making it to actual implementation. For instance, severe expenditure cuts associated with the centrally sponsored National Crèche Scheme had led to the closure of multiple crèches across the country, thus, de-incentivising female workers who could work earlier only because of the availability of such facilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover the government policies regularly fail to focus on the real audience. In order to avail most of the above listed benefits, there's an enormous process and cumbersome documentation requirement which excludes the illiterate or marginalised women of the country. While issues like corruption conjointly attack the system, and the welfare policies fail to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comprehensive approaches are needed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In India, the gender gap in labour force participation is high and is worsening continually when looked at from a global point of view. The decline in female employment&amp;nbsp; is primarily attributed to the sharp fall in female agricultural employment, which till date employs more than 65% of the total women in the workforce; half of them working as unpaid family workers. This decline in agriculture share is not accompanied by a commensurate increase in non-agricultural activities, except for construction. Employment opportunities are very limited for women, and are solely concentrated in only a few sub-sectors, mainly in low value-added activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Agriculture, which is as yet the biggest employer of female labour, can be used as a wellspring of economic growth and job creation for women, if they are guaranteed possession rights and power over grounds while at the same time, movement of women is required towards the production of high value-added crops. These of course should be supplemented by other strategy measurements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover, promotion of female entrepreneurship can give way to economic elevation of women, and thus, distribution of its benefits more equitably. But lack of credit facilities in the absence of collateral, and complications of the established formalities present a major roadblock to such entrepreneurial ambitions. Self Help Groups (SHGs) can be utilised to improve access to finance, and links with formal financial institutions would enable women (especially from lower economic status) to access the market better.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Women in India face many barriers to enter the workforce, such as pre dominant socio-cultural practices, access to choice of work, poor working conditions, wage disparity, exploitation, balancing domestic and work responsibilities, and more. It is essential that policy makers adopt strategies to improve the labour market for women through gender neutral norms, education, proper infrastructure, and the creation of more opportunities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;At last, the objective isn't simply to increase the female labour force participation rate but to build opportunities for decent work and economic progression which can add to the financial strengthening of women and the economy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cheshta Sharma</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Recently, India has found itself in the monetary and segment conditions that would prompt an increased female workforce participation rate. Financial development has been high, averaging at 6-7% during the 1990's and 2000's. On the other hand, fertility has significantly fallen alongside the drastic rise in training of females.&amp;nbsp; However, according to the International Labour Organisation's (ILO) estimates, the female labour force participation rate (FLPR) in India has declined from 30.27% in 1990 to 20.33% in 2020. The average value of the said figure for India during the period between 1990-2020 was 27.38%, with a minimum of 20.33% (in 2020) and maximum of 31.79% (in 2005).&amp;nbsp; The average for 2020, based on 182 countries, was 51.86%. Rwanda scored the highest rate of 83.95% and Yemen the lowest at 5.69%. The FLPR for China, the country with the largest population, was 64% while for the US, it was 56.3%. Women remained underrepresented in the Indian workforce, a circumstance that has not changed in the last 30 years.&amp;nbsp; Among its neighbouring countries, India’s FLPR is shockingly the lowest, falling even behind Afghanistan and Pakistan, which had scored half of India’s rates back in 1990. Nepal has a FLPR of 83% which is an all-time high amongst all the South Asian economies, and Pakistan (India’ biggest rival) has secured a higher position by 4 points, sitting at a FLPR of 24.6%. Globally only Yemen, Iraq, Jordan, Syria, Algeria, Iran, the West Bank and Gaza have lower rates than India.&amp;nbsp; Analysis of National Sampling Survey Office (NSSO) data (1970-2018) shows that women have largely been undertaking home-based and labour intensive informal work concentrated in low-productivity sectors. During the period of 1977-2017, the proportion of women working in agriculture fell from 88.1% to 73.2% in the rural areas, while their share in the service sector rose from 35.7% to 60.7% in the urban areas. Females in the tertiary sector concentrated in professions such as teaching and nursing, which provided restricted scope for progression in their careers. However, unlike their male counterparts, females could not increase their presence in the secondary sector.&amp;nbsp; What explains low participation in India? In the last decade, fertility has declined rapidly while wages have expanded considerably, and the contribution for this goes to the high speed of development in the country. Furthermore, avenues for job seekers are not rare, except for the educated workforce where there is a distinct relative shortage. So why are more females not entering the workforce? According to a paper published in 2008, much of the discussion on the falling trends in female labour force participation has focused on four key elements:&amp;nbsp; 1) rising enrolment in secondary schooling;&amp;nbsp; 2) wage and sex discrimination in the workplace;&amp;nbsp; 3) increase in household incomes; and&amp;nbsp; 4) females engaged in either unpaid family jobs or marginal jobs.&amp;nbsp; There has been an increase in the percentage of women who have completed a minimum of secondary level education or more, particularly in rural India. The NSSO data also confirms younger women have greater aspirations to participate in the labour market than the previous generations, however, due to norms around chastity and early marriage (still heavily prevalent in the country), they are prevented from doing so. The average age of marriage for girls in rural India is around 21.7 years. Additionally, there has been a fall in participation rate of approximately 30% owing to greater demand on their time to pursue education. Post their education, absence of appropriate job availability leads to their lower participation in the workforce.&amp;nbsp; There exists a U-shaped relation between education and paid work participation, yet the rate of return for each year of education is lower for women than men in India. This relation also asserts the fact that illiterate women are forced to rely on the unorganised sector for meeting their basic needs.&amp;nbsp; Wage and sex dicrimination within the workplace is an addition amongst the above mentioned factors where females are rewarded with a lower pay and greater discrimination than their male counterparts. This is serious as it not only affects the economic growth of the nation but also speaks volume on the prevalent working conditions.&amp;nbsp; Males are awarded with a pay of more than 19% than their female colleagues. This income disparity has only narrowed by 1% in 2018 from the 20% of the preceding year. The pay inequality can be corresponded to the following factors - discriminaton and occupational decisions by females into lower paying jobs, such as clerical work. Another interesting reason for lower female workforce participation can be attributed to the fact that many educated females drop out of the workforce due the family income effect, i.e., with an increase in family earnings, the dependency on females to work fall, thereby shifting their attention towards domestic chores and child care. As a result women hailing from higher economic status are less likely to work than women belonging from lower income strata.&amp;nbsp; This gap widens when we look at the 2019 report by the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation, wherein it becomes evident that the burden of unpaid labour falls on women significantly in the country. The report states that an average Indian woman spends nearly 84% of her working hours on unpaid work while the men spend 80% of their working hours on paid work.&amp;nbsp; What is the government doing? The Government has taken several steps to increase the female workforce participation rate in India.&amp;nbsp; The Ministry of Skill Development and Entrepreneurship (MSDE) has been set up for improving the involvement rate across sectors and areas. Likewise the government has also initiated the National Career Service (NCS) project which entails a digital portal to link jobseekers and businesses for work and incorporate a repository of enlarged career content.&amp;nbsp; Other steps include incorporation of the Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act, 2017 by institutions which focuses on improvement in paid maternity leaves from 12 weeks to 26 weeks, and arrangement for compulsory crèche services in establishments having at least 50 employees; issue of an advisory to the States under the Factories Act, 1948 for allowing women workers of night shifts with sufficient safety measures.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, to improve the employability of female labourers, numerous institutes have been set up to provide them with training ranging from vocational to industrial. Various work laws have been amended to foster a more safe and amicable work environment for women.&amp;nbsp; Laws for a fairer work environment passed by the government include:&amp;nbsp; Minimum Wage Act 1948, the wages set by the corresponding government are equally applicable to male and female workers, and therefore, the law doesn't segregate on the premise of sex.&amp;nbsp;The Equal Remuneration Act 1976 provides for equal wages to be paid to employees for similar jobs, with no discrimination based on sex, class, caste or religion followed.&amp;nbsp;The Protection of Women against Sexual Harassment at Workplace Act 2013 characterizes lewd behavior or sexual harassment at the workplace, and helps in the redressal of such objections. It provides shields against fake or noxious charges. However, many government policies are targeted towards the organised workforce while the&amp;nbsp; unorganised sector that homes the largest number of females has very little to no penetration of such schemes, thereby making government policies ineffective to some extent. Additionally, in several areas, these policies are only restricted to documentation, thus, never making it to actual implementation. For instance, severe expenditure cuts associated with the centrally sponsored National Crèche Scheme had led to the closure of multiple crèches across the country, thus, de-incentivising female workers who could work earlier only because of the availability of such facilities.&amp;nbsp; Moreover the government policies regularly fail to focus on the real audience. In order to avail most of the above listed benefits, there's an enormous process and cumbersome documentation requirement which excludes the illiterate or marginalised women of the country. While issues like corruption conjointly attack the system, and the welfare policies fail to deliver. Comprehensive approaches are needed In India, the gender gap in labour force participation is high and is worsening continually when looked at from a global point of view. The decline in female employment&amp;nbsp; is primarily attributed to the sharp fall in female agricultural employment, which till date employs more than 65% of the total women in the workforce; half of them working as unpaid family workers. This decline in agriculture share is not accompanied by a commensurate increase in non-agricultural activities, except for construction. Employment opportunities are very limited for women, and are solely concentrated in only a few sub-sectors, mainly in low value-added activities.&amp;nbsp; Agriculture, which is as yet the biggest employer of female labour, can be used as a wellspring of economic growth and job creation for women, if they are guaranteed possession rights and power over grounds while at the same time, movement of women is required towards the production of high value-added crops. These of course should be supplemented by other strategy measurements.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, promotion of female entrepreneurship can give way to economic elevation of women, and thus, distribution of its benefits more equitably. But lack of credit facilities in the absence of collateral, and complications of the established formalities present a major roadblock to such entrepreneurial ambitions. Self Help Groups (SHGs) can be utilised to improve access to finance, and links with formal financial institutions would enable women (especially from lower economic status) to access the market better.&amp;nbsp; Women in India face many barriers to enter the workforce, such as pre dominant socio-cultural practices, access to choice of work, poor working conditions, wage disparity, exploitation, balancing domestic and work responsibilities, and more. It is essential that policy makers adopt strategies to improve the labour market for women through gender neutral norms, education, proper infrastructure, and the creation of more opportunities.&amp;nbsp; At last, the objective isn't simply to increase the female labour force participation rate but to build opportunities for decent work and economic progression which can add to the financial strengthening of women and the economy.</summary></entry></feed>