<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-15T21:55:06+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">‘Missing’ Firms in GDP Calculation</title><link href="/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Missing' Firms in GDP Calculation" /><published>2019-06-13T17:34:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-13T17:34:00+00:00</updated><id>/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation">&lt;p&gt;The controversies regarding India’s GDP numbers, with 2011-2012 as the base
year, seem to be not coming to an end. The Indian National Sampling Survey
Office’s (NSSO) study, ending June 2017, revealed that 38% of the companies
which are a part of the MCA21 database (the Modi government’s e-governance
initiative) were missing. The study implied that the inclusion of data from such
companies would grossly overestimate GDP figures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the Central Statistical Office (CSO) of India issued a new GDP series,
wherein the routine 2004-05 base year was replaced with 2011-12. According to Dr
R. Nagaraj, such a revision usually leads to a slight expansion of the absolute
GDP in the base year, keeping the growth rate constant. But this time, the
absolute GDP was reduced slightly in the base year and the growth rate had an
unprecedented rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were significant changes in the methodology this time. The CSO had shifted
to the latest global template, the System of National Accounts 2008, for
calculations. Moreover, the income accruing to the Private Corporate Sector
(PCS) was directly estimated using the Ministry of Corporate Affairs’ (MCA)
statutory filing of financial returns, i.e. the aforementioned MCA-21. The PCS
accounts for over one-third of the GDP, and has affected estimates of many
industries. The CSO claims that GDP calculation through MCA-21, which is a
larger database than the Annual Survey of Industries for Manufacturing used
previously, better captures the economy’s value addition, especially of smaller
enterprises and services activities. The critics, however, fear that this has
led to a gross overestimation of GDP.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The NSSO Survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent report of the NSSO titled &lt;em&gt;Technical Report on Service Sector
Enterprises in India&lt;/em&gt; found nearly 38% of the companies surveyed using MCA21
database to be unusable for data collection purposes. Of this, 21% were “out of
coverage” firms, 12% were designated untraceable and 4.5% were closed. Many of
these companies according to Dr R. Nagaraj, are shell/fake/spurious entities
that remain legally registered (but merely on paper) but do not produce goods
and services. The only purpose is to help the owner hide the profits and, thus,
reduce the taxable income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is GDP Overestimated?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pronab Sen, former Chief Statistician, disagrees with the fact that GDP is
overestimated due to the data from the ‘missing’ firms. He explains that for the
purpose of measurement of GDP, it is more important for the statisticians that
the shell companies are submitting their balance sheets regularly to the MCA21.
These firms are involved in some form of economic activity, and not measuring
their output would mean severe underestimation of the GDP. The value creation is
happening by some other company, but the transactions are being routed through
these shell companies. Ignoring them would mean a part of the business of the
registered company is being ignored, which is wrong. Hence, the GDP will only be
correctly estimated if we include the data from the shell companies. However,
the taxable income accruing to the private sector and thus the private savings
will surely be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, growth rates are measured over a period of time and are influenced by
the regularity with which the companies file the returns. Thus, the fact that a
large number of companies are not being measured affects the level of the
economy, but not the growth profile.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the MCA21 database is a compilation of the audited financial returns
filed by the companies. The returns are reconciled with the corporate tax
collected by the Income Tax Department. Mr Sen explains that the audit data from
MCA21 would always be better than unaudited data, the one collected from the
field. The MCA data captures value creation by an entity which is a registered
corporate. The value may be coming from the company itself or simply a book
entry from some other company. This doesn’t matter as far as gross value
addition (GVA) is concerned.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MCA21: Foolproof?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of MCA21 database, however, does have its disadvantages. The presence of
spurious firms creates low-level problems related to growth rates and gross
value addition (GVA) by different sectors. For instance, a manufacturing company
can create a shell company as a trading firm. The creation of a fake company of
such kind will lead to some of the GVA by the manufacturing sector being counted
as the GVA by the services sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To consider the argument that all active companies under the MCA have filed
statutory returns at least once during the last three years to be true will be a
mistake. If it were true, there would at least be one year for which there would
existent data for seven to eight hundred thousand companies, which has never
been the case. For most years data is available for around three hundred
thousand active companies. The estimates of gross value added for these three
hundred thousand companies is inflated to obtain the GVA of the universe of 10
hundred thousand companies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be no denying the fact that MCA21 contains information from shell
companies. The data from such fictitious units cannot be ignored to prevent
underestimation. The only way to make the process of GDP calculation efficient
and transparent would be to weed out these shell companies. The Ministry of
Corporate Affairs (MCA) has started the process of geo-tagging the registered
offices in the returns filed with the Registrar of Companies (RoC). Geo-tagging
is the process of attaching geographical meta-data (exact latitudinal and
longitudinal information) with an online return filing system, alerting the
government if too many companies are registered on the same premises. The
process of geo-tagging is still underway and it would be too early to comment on
its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate on the inclusion of figures from shell companies for the calculation
of GDP and the veracity of the GDP numbers is raging. There is a need for
statisticians, economists and policymakers to sit together and find solutions to
these technical issues related to GDP calculation. Additional steps need to be
taken by the Income Tax Department and the Enforcement Directorate (India’s
white collar crime watchdog) to clamp down on the operations of such spurious
companies. The Justice Shah Commission, constituted in 2015, highlighted the
role of such companies in money laundering, which is a punishable offence under
Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002. A holistic government approach is
necessary to fight the menace of shell companies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gurleen Kaur</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The controversies regarding India’s GDP numbers, with 2011-2012 as the base year, seem to be not coming to an end. The Indian National Sampling Survey Office’s (NSSO) study, ending June 2017, revealed that 38% of the companies which are a part of the MCA21 database (the Modi government’s e-governance initiative) were missing. The study implied that the inclusion of data from such companies would grossly overestimate GDP figures.   The Background In 2015, the Central Statistical Office (CSO) of India issued a new GDP series, wherein the routine 2004-05 base year was replaced with 2011-12. According to Dr R. Nagaraj, such a revision usually leads to a slight expansion of the absolute GDP in the base year, keeping the growth rate constant. But this time, the absolute GDP was reduced slightly in the base year and the growth rate had an unprecedented rise. There were significant changes in the methodology this time. The CSO had shifted to the latest global template, the System of National Accounts 2008, for calculations. Moreover, the income accruing to the Private Corporate Sector (PCS) was directly estimated using the Ministry of Corporate Affairs’ (MCA) statutory filing of financial returns, i.e. the aforementioned MCA-21. The PCS accounts for over one-third of the GDP, and has affected estimates of many industries. The CSO claims that GDP calculation through MCA-21, which is a larger database than the Annual Survey of Industries for Manufacturing used previously, better captures the economy’s value addition, especially of smaller enterprises and services activities. The critics, however, fear that this has led to a gross overestimation of GDP.   The NSSO Survey A recent report of the NSSO titled Technical Report on Service Sector Enterprises in India found nearly 38% of the companies surveyed using MCA21 database to be unusable for data collection purposes. Of this, 21% were “out of coverage” firms, 12% were designated untraceable and 4.5% were closed. Many of these companies according to Dr R. Nagaraj, are shell/fake/spurious entities that remain legally registered (but merely on paper) but do not produce goods and services. The only purpose is to help the owner hide the profits and, thus, reduce the taxable income. Is GDP Overestimated? Mr Pronab Sen, former Chief Statistician, disagrees with the fact that GDP is overestimated due to the data from the ‘missing’ firms. He explains that for the purpose of measurement of GDP, it is more important for the statisticians that the shell companies are submitting their balance sheets regularly to the MCA21. These firms are involved in some form of economic activity, and not measuring their output would mean severe underestimation of the GDP. The value creation is happening by some other company, but the transactions are being routed through these shell companies. Ignoring them would mean a part of the business of the registered company is being ignored, which is wrong. Hence, the GDP will only be correctly estimated if we include the data from the shell companies. However, the taxable income accruing to the private sector and thus the private savings will surely be underestimated. Second, growth rates are measured over a period of time and are influenced by the regularity with which the companies file the returns. Thus, the fact that a large number of companies are not being measured affects the level of the economy, but not the growth profile.   Moreover, the MCA21 database is a compilation of the audited financial returns filed by the companies. The returns are reconciled with the corporate tax collected by the Income Tax Department. Mr Sen explains that the audit data from MCA21 would always be better than unaudited data, the one collected from the field. The MCA data captures value creation by an entity which is a registered corporate. The value may be coming from the company itself or simply a book entry from some other company. This doesn’t matter as far as gross value addition (GVA) is concerned.   MCA21: Foolproof? The use of MCA21 database, however, does have its disadvantages. The presence of spurious firms creates low-level problems related to growth rates and gross value addition (GVA) by different sectors. For instance, a manufacturing company can create a shell company as a trading firm. The creation of a fake company of such kind will lead to some of the GVA by the manufacturing sector being counted as the GVA by the services sector.   To consider the argument that all active companies under the MCA have filed statutory returns at least once during the last three years to be true will be a mistake. If it were true, there would at least be one year for which there would existent data for seven to eight hundred thousand companies, which has never been the case. For most years data is available for around three hundred thousand active companies. The estimates of gross value added for these three hundred thousand companies is inflated to obtain the GVA of the universe of 10 hundred thousand companies.   There can be no denying the fact that MCA21 contains information from shell companies. The data from such fictitious units cannot be ignored to prevent underestimation. The only way to make the process of GDP calculation efficient and transparent would be to weed out these shell companies. The Ministry of Corporate Affairs (MCA) has started the process of geo-tagging the registered offices in the returns filed with the Registrar of Companies (RoC). Geo-tagging is the process of attaching geographical meta-data (exact latitudinal and longitudinal information) with an online return filing system, alerting the government if too many companies are registered on the same premises. The process of geo-tagging is still underway and it would be too early to comment on its effectiveness. The debate on the inclusion of figures from shell companies for the calculation of GDP and the veracity of the GDP numbers is raging. There is a need for statisticians, economists and policymakers to sit together and find solutions to these technical issues related to GDP calculation. Additional steps need to be taken by the Income Tax Department and the Enforcement Directorate (India’s white collar crime watchdog) to clamp down on the operations of such spurious companies. The Justice Shah Commission, constituted in 2015, highlighted the role of such companies in money laundering, which is a punishable offence under Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002. A holistic government approach is necessary to fight the menace of shell companies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Table</title><link href="/table" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Table" /><published>2019-06-04T21:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-04T21:22:00+00:00</updated><id>/table</id><content type="html" xml:base="/table">&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manager&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;UEFA Champions League Finals &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;loss&lt;/span&gt; record (year)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL semi-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL quarter-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of seasons managed in CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL win percentage (%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luis Enrique&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jupp Heynckes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 -1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;98&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zinedine Zidane&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louis Van Gaal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;95&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;96&lt;/span&gt;, 10)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diego Simeone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carlo Ancelotti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Alex Ferguson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;99&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Mourinho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jürgen Klopp&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>table</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">Manager UEFA Champions League Finals win/loss record (year) CL semi-finals reached CL quarter-finals reached Number of seasons managed in CL CL win percentage (%)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can Uncle Sam’s Economic Wars Pave Way for Nuclear Peace?</title><link href="/Uncle-Sam-Economic-Wars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Uncle Sam’s Economic Wars Pave Way for Nuclear Peace?" /><published>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Uncle-Sam-Economic-Wars</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Uncle-Sam-Economic-Wars">&lt;p&gt;In May 2018, President Trump’s administration shocked the global community by unilaterally pulling out of the three-year-old Iran Nuclear Deal. The Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA), under which Iran traded its nuclear ambitions for economic growth and stability, was signed between Iran, the United States, Britain, China, Germany, Russia, and France in 2015. In November, after Trump’s conditions for re-forging a deal were left unattended, the U.S. government responded with a ballistic package of severe economic penalties against Iran. The Trump administration called it the biggest sanctions action the United States had ever undertaken against Iran. Iran’s president called it an act of “economic war” and said that his country would win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diplomatic history between Iran and the U.S. is littered with the repetitive and hostile imposition of sanctions by the American government. The first of the many sanctions came in 1979. This was in response to the Iran Hostage crisis wherein citizens and diplomats were held hostage at the US embassy by extremist groups. Citing Iranian support for international terrorism as the reason, the Reagan administration reinforced sanctions in 1987. Thereafter, between 1995 and 1997, the US banned “involvement with petroleum development in Iran”, and later “virtually all trade and investment activities with Iran, by US persons”. After another series of sanctions in 2010 and 2011, the landmark Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA), popularly known as the Iran Nuclear Deal, was signed in 2015. In this multilateral deal, Iran’s nuclear programme was subjected to periodic checks in exchange for relief from economic sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite such a long-drawn battle for peace, the Trump administration wasn’t too content about the current state of matters. “The Iranian regime supports terrorism and exports violence, bloodshed and chaos across the Middle East. That is why we must put to an end Iran’s continued aggression and nuclear ambitions. They have not lived up to the spirit of their agreement,” Trump said in October 2017. In the following May, his government set out 12 predicaments for Iran to follow, to prevent sanctions from being imposed. These included providing the IAEA (International Atomic Energy Agency) with unqualified access to all sites throughout the entire country, ending support to Middle East “terrorist” groups, such as Hezbollah, Hamas and Islamic Jihad, withdrawing all forces under Iran’s command throughout the entirety of Syria, and ending its military support for the Houthi rebels and work towards a peaceful, political settlement in Yemen among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others argue that Trump has abandoned this deal, much like he was abandoned all the other deals of his Democrat predecessor, Barack Obama. From the Trans-Pacific Partnership to the Paris Agreement, Trump seems intent on killing the achievements of the former government. Another reason for his withdrawal involves Trump’s bigger motives in the Middle-East. As he looks to build stronger ties with Saudi Arabia and Israel, sacrificing control over Iran’s nuclear plans seems like a small price to pay. Mr. Trump won strong backing from Saudi Arabia and Israel, whose leader, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, hailed him for a “historic move” and “courageous leadership.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When those twelve demands were left unmet, the U.S. waged a full-scale economic war: hegemon style. The administration threatened to penalize buyers of Iranian oil. This was part of its stated goal to reduce Iran’s petroleum exports to zero. It blacklisted 50 Iranian banks and subsidiaries, more than 200 people and ships, Iran’s national airline and more than 65 Iranian aircrafts. Under such sanctions, the United States can seize assets under its jurisdiction that are owned by blacklisted people and entities, and has forbidden all commercial relations with such persons or entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Iranian President promised to take up arms against, and even defeat the U.S., the state of the Iranian economy suggests otherwise. The banking and services sector has taken a major hit since the imposition of the sanctions. The Iranian currency was already faltering, and has gone on to weaken further. Most importantly, its main source of revenue is being dangerously encroached upon. Initially, it was stated that Iran’s biggest petroleum customers, like China and India, would not be penalized, at least for six months. Now, as the sixth month draws to a close, and waivers for India and China have not been extended, the severity of these sanctions will be felt by Iranians, in full effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first big question is: who will take Iran’s place in the crude oil market? Although Iran has stated that it remains irreplaceable, many expect Saudi Arabia, Iraq, and the U.S. to fill in the void. Petroleum prices are expected to surge in the global markets, as supply is bound to fall. The surge will be even more dramatic as India and China have been forced to abandon the Iranian crude reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the U.S. is the only country to have withdrawn from the agreement. Iran, China, France, Russia, the U.K., and Germany are still parties. However, if Iran continues to bear the brunt of the sanctions, the deal might eventually collapse altogether. This means that Iran will be at liberty to construct its own nuclear weapons and missiles. It has said it could restore its uranium-enriching capability quickly, but this could isolate it from Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One diplomatic sword that Iran has already flashed is its Afghani refugees. Iran hosts an estimated three million documented and undocumented Afghans, including an estimated one million refugees that the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) describes as “one of the largest and most protracted urban refugee populations worldwide”. During a May 8th interview on the state television, Iran’s deputy Foreign Minister for political affairs, Abbas Araghchi, warned that Iran may be forced to “ask our Afghan brothers and sisters to leave” if the economic crisis, spawned by sanctions from the United States, continues to squeeze the economy. Essentially, Iran pointed out to European leaders that unless sanctions are lifted, it would push out the Afghani refugees, and this would stir more trouble into the brewing refugee crisis in the continent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, there may not have been a clear agreement among the United States and its allies about how to handle Iran’s nuclear ambitions, but there was an agreement that something had to be done. Today, the other parties to the JCPOA (China, Russia, France, Germany, the United Kingdom, and the European Union) are of the view that the agreement is working and Iran is upholding its end of the bargain. Facing an extraterritorial sanctions threat from the United States, the European Union could look at reintroducing the “blocking regulation,” which is a European Council regulation from the 1990s that was designed precisely to shield European firms from American sanctions on Cuba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, it is impossible to predict what could unfold as a consequence of these economic sanctions. In the short term, when looking at the oil and energy markets, especially those of India and China, they are bound to face some turbulent times. However, in the long run, the EU has to take its stand, keeping in mind its own interests and those of the United States. That will further determine whether or not the Iran Nuclear will sustain at all. If not, world security will be greatly compromised as a strong player of West Asia will transform into a major nuclear power.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In May 2018, President Trump’s administration shocked the global community by unilaterally pulling out of the three-year-old Iran Nuclear Deal. The Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA), under which Iran traded its nuclear ambitions for economic growth and stability, was signed between Iran, the United States, Britain, China, Germany, Russia, and France in 2015. In November, after Trump’s conditions for re-forging a deal were left unattended, the U.S. government responded with a ballistic package of severe economic penalties against Iran. The Trump administration called it the biggest sanctions action the United States had ever undertaken against Iran. Iran’s president called it an act of “economic war” and said that his country would win.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Champions League Final Preview</title><link href="/CL-Final-Preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Final Preview" /><published>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/CL-Final-Preview</id><content type="html" xml:base="/CL-Final-Preview">&lt;p&gt;Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino’s Legacy and Klopp’s Final Troubles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tottenham are undoubtedly the underdogs but the narrative surrounding Mauricio Pochettino ahead of his first major European final is wholly favourable. If Tottenham prevail on Saturday, Pochettino will be lauded for his principal role in masterminding the North London club to the greatest prize in club football. In any case, Pochettino’s immense coaching qualities are unequivocal; it is no wonder that some of the world’s richest and most successful clubs, such as Juventus, Manchester United and Real Madrid have attempted to lure the Argentine away from N17. Spurs are on the brink of an unforgettable achievement and Pochettino will be a Tottenham legend regardless of the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Pochettino has previously faced criticism from fans and pundits for repeatedly asserting that he is not interested in winning the FA or League Cup and for never having won a major trophy in his managerial career, there is no question that the philosophy and attitude he has inculcated at the club has led to the greatest period of sustained success since the 1950s and 60s. Tottenham’s squad is too thin to compete on all four fronts, therefore it is no wonder that Pochettino has focused on the two most significant club competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to Pochettino, Tottenham’s history of having only won two major trophies since 1991 (2 League Cups) underlied the club’s reputation for ‘bottling’ and being a ‘nearly’ team. There is a strong sense in and around the club that Pochettino’s meticulous management, combined with mindful investment from chairman Daniel Levy to introduce dazzling new training facilities and stadium, has led to the instillment of a winning mentality that had been lacking at Tottenham for too long. The 47 year-old Argentine has indicated that a result in Tottenham’s favour could spell the end of his 5 year stay at Tottenham; he recently stated it is unlikely he will be able to repeat a victory of this magnitude for the club and is therefore open to moving on and seeking a new challenge elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry Kane’s role in the game as well as whether Tottenham can handle the big game pressure and the inexperience of winning finals will be crucial. The latest word from the Spurs camp is that Mauricio Pochettino and his staff will delay telling their players the starting line-up until Saturday afternoon in order to give themselves the more time to assess the fitness of the England captain. Surprising though it may seem, some of Spurs’ best performances this season have occurred without their star striker. It has been argued that this could be due to other players in the squad upping their game in order to account for the loss of Kane’s supreme talent. Nevertheless, everyone can agree that having Kane fit for the final gives Spurs a huge boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pochettino’s equivalent on Saturday evening will be none other than Jürgen Klopp. Klopp has already experienced managing a Champions League final in 2013 and 2018; the former saw his Borussia Dortmund side suffer a 2-1 defeat to Bayern Munich after a late Arjen Robben goal eventually penetrated Dortmund, who had been astutely tactically organised until the 80th minute mark when they were caught out of position as they began to take more risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since, Klopp has lost 5 successive cup finals, leading to questions over his big game management. There is a tendency for Klopp’s sides to lose their shape towards the end of games if they are eagerly attempting to score late in the game. If Spurs are to pull off an upset, they must recognise that in the few games Liverpool have lost this season - such as against Manchester City, Barcelona, Chelsea and Napoli - the Reds have typically conceded goals beyond the 80th minute mark. Nonetheless, the context and reality of Klopp guiding his teams to such a large number of cup finals is testament to his eminent coaching abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparisons can be drawn between Liverpool’s and Spurs’ recent histories. Klopp is bidding to win his first trophy as Liverpool manager, and he has ably reintroduced the consistency needed for success at Anfield. Before his arrival, the Scousers were to failing to compete in the major competitions. It is easy to see why Liverpool are favourites among bookmakers to become Champions of Europe for the sixth time in their history; Klopp has turned Liverpool into a leading European powerhouse once again: the upturn in performances over the last two seasons has been astounding, culminating in reaching two successive Champions League finals and finishing second with 97 points and 1 loss (to champions Manchester City) - no mean feats. The German recently described his current team as the best squad he has worked with in his managerial career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New signings Virgil Van Dijk, Fabinho, Alisson and Shaqiri have all played their part in Liverpool’s excellence and they are subsequently a well-rounded elite team wholly capable of competing among the very best. In the same time period that Liverpool made these formidable signings, Tottenham chose not to spend a single penny across 2 transfer windows. Furthermore, although the pressure on Liverpool to win is greater than their adversary, the Reds have shown many times over that they are able to perform masterfully under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May the best team win.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ali Abdi</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inflation - Dead Or Dormant?</title><link href="/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inflation - Dead Or Dormant?" /><published>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant">&lt;p&gt;The US Federal Reserve, in its recent Open Market Operations Committee Meeting, chose an ambiguous stance by leaving the federal funds rate unchanged at the range of 2.25-2.5%, much to the dismay of the markets and the Government, who long awaited a rate cut. As the growth rates declined across Europe, China and US in Q1 2019, the Fed was expected to finally move away from the rate hikes, which were also offsetting the fiscal concessions provided by the US government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This monetary tightening began in late 2015, as an attempt to counter the inflation that was expected in the aftermath of using heterodox mutations like Quantitative Easing (QE) to recover demand in the largest Post-War Recession of 2008. While the Fiscal Policy has become increasingly pro-cyclical in the recent (Trump) years, the hawkish Monetary Policy attempts to counter the inflation that is already locked far behind its 2% benchmark, which has resulted in the Trump’s disapproval of Jerome Powell (thus, the threats of replacing him with political cronies like Herman Cain). The low expected inflation has not only caused the recessionary air to resurface but has also invited wild justifications for credibility restoration. Fed’s Loretta Mester recently went as far as to claim that the economy has finally reached its equilibrium in her (neo)classic defense of the recent speculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of the justifications explained why inflation is globally stifled for the developed economies despite the rising-but-low rates. The observation remains that the Monetary Policy is losing grip over the rate of inflation. Prices are no longer as sensitive to the interest rates as they used to be, thus, explaining the recent surge in various financial forums pronouncing inflation dead, attributing it mainly to technological advancements. In times of prosperity, inflation is high due to the increased productivity and employment, which gives the workforce the ability to bargain for greater wages, that will push up the costs and then the prices. With improved technology and reduced labour intensity, the ability of the workers to demand greater wages during an upswing has declined. Additionally, the prophecy paradox, that embodies the self-fulfilling nature of expectations in economics, comes to play. The general level of expected inflation in the markets is low which is seen to be taking its effect on the actual figures, and though these expectations are being publicized as a reflective of the credibility of the Fed, they certainly don’t go in tandem with the economic or the fiscal cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the major setback has been taken by the theory of the Phillips curve, which describes the inverse relationship between inflation and unemployment via the cost-wage spiral. This relation was violated once back in the 70s when stagflation hit the American economy. It was chiefly blamed at the rising oil prices, when in fact it was the abolition of Bretton Woods by Nixon that took a toll on the economy. Though its collapse provided the US with a monetary policy that extended beyond the clasp of the Special Drawing Rights, it immediately resulted in inflation which was previously limited to the $35/ounce gold peg. In order to tackle the inflation, the government bought in price controls which reduced the profitability of businesses, and ended up in large scale layoffs. But this direct relation had helped Milton Friedman in developing a long run perspective to the theory, and concluding that in the long run, the Phillips curve is vertical. In the short-run, however, there is sufficient scope for monetary policy to smooth out fluctuations around the independent pathway of potential output by affecting cyclical unemployment and price levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curve has currently flattened, and this relation is no longer as strong for the developed economies as it used to be, considering how unemployment is presently at 3.9% in the USA, below its natural rate that stands at 4%, but inflation has shown no signs of a revival. A similar pattern had been witnessed right before the tech bubble had burst. This flattening of the curve is possibly a structural problem, not amenable to macroeconomic measures and it reduces the capability of the Central Banks to reach their inflation targets. But if the theory still survives, it could only mean that the Fed anticipates a pending risk for the inflation to resurface, for which the rate hikes, under the alias of a ‘friendly normalisation’, are being pursued. Perhaps inflation is not dead, but dormant and potentially on a rise, although it is ‘inflation targeting’ that might be officially dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this inflation-interest rate relation, which is hardly ever questioned, was never a strong one, to begin with. J.Stiglitz asserts &lt;em&gt;“this rudimentary method is based on a weak economic theory and little empirical evidence…and there is no reason to believe that, whatever the source of inflation, the best solution is to raise interest rates.”&lt;/em&gt; The Central Banks have been over-relying on the Monetary Policy for every minor inconvenience as if it is a panacea for the dearth of aggregate demand. And why not? It’s the easiest way out, 2008 stands witness. But that is if we remain unreasonably adamant on the “In the long run, we’re all dead” approach. While the Fiscal Policy, despite its implementation imperfections, attempts to systematically address the economic issues at their core, the monetary policy has been globally reduced to an interest fluctuation switch, whose volatility takes its toll on its own ability. It is an important but overexploited tool that was ideally supposed to address the Dual Mandate on both price stability and employment issues through a suitable policy mix, but there seems to be no coordination among the fiscal and the monetary policy. The past few centuries stand witness to the fact that no monetary system has stood firm for over 50 years, citing the changes that the monetary policy faced in 1913, 1933, 1945 and 1971. And considering its ageing ability to address inflation, people have already started coming up with alternatives to the existing system, the most prominent one being the Modern Monetary Theory (MMT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a fringe economic model, MMT stems out of the monetary theory of Marx, which later seems to have influenced Keynes, and is nowadays gaining mainstream attention, such as being proposed for financing the Green New Deal by Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez. It basically states that a country with its own currency can simply pay off its debt by printing more currency. The idea would seem questionable even to a layman, but this is only true if the debt is denominated in the domestic currency, which though is not the case for most of the nations, it’s certainly applicable for the USA as an advantage of USD being the major global reserve currency. This theory is often criticised for its utter disregard for the size of the deficits and the impact on inflation, but it does address these issues by manipulating the revenue side. Additionally, being a brain-child of the left doesn’t imply that it will not be accepted by the right since it can just as easily help in financing tax cuts. Major investors such as Ray Dalio, who feed off of capitalism, have stated that something like MMT will inevitably be replacing the Central Banks. In fact, MMT appears to be the only way to elude the burgeoning debt and the declining credibility of the Fed. It will help finance the fiscal profligacy every US government has inherited from its fear of lobbyists, be it progressive or conservative. Either way, it might ameliorate the system after the hawks have devoured what’s left of their monetary policy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The US Federal Reserve, in its recent Open Market Operations Committee Meeting, chose an ambiguous stance by leaving the federal funds rate unchanged at the range of 2.25-2.5%, much to the dismay of the markets and the Government, who long awaited a rate cut. As the growth rates declined across Europe, China and US in Q1 2019, the Fed was expected to finally move away from the rate hikes, which were also offsetting the fiscal concessions provided by the US government.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can Effective Altruism Truly Work?</title><link href="/Effective-Altruism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Effective Altruism Truly Work?" /><published>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Effective-Altruism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Effective-Altruism">&lt;p&gt;If I told you about a $60 million project aimed at providing water pumps for villages in Africa to 10 million people backed by the US government and various celebrities, you would probably think it’s a sound idea. The way the project actually works, is that the pump is connected to a merry-go-round and as children play on the apparatus, the energy is used to power the pump. It sounds like a great idea, which is why in 2006 this very project was put into place. However, it turned out to be a complete disaster. After some number crunching, it was calculated that children would have to be playing on the roundabout non-stop for 27 hours each day to reach the water production targets set by the initiative. Moreover, simply investing the money into regular water pumps would have been far less expensive and more efficient. As a different water NGO put it; “their marketing is perfect, but the final idea does not work.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaway here is not about water pumps, or even water aid in general. This is but one of hundreds of examples of &lt;em&gt;heart over head&lt;/em&gt; charity. In a world which is inundated with people who need help, it is becoming increasingly hard to know how and where we should give our time and money. Indeed, I would argue that we all experience “charity fatigue”; with so many causes available, it becomes increasingly difficult for an individual charity to stand out. Consequently, charities turn to shock advertising to draw our attention – think of heart-breaking pictures of starving children. By using this visceral imagery, the charities are appealing directly to your heart, to your emotions. They are not asking you to think about the cause, but to believe in it; two very different propositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, giving any sort of charity is better than giving none at all. However, for those looking for a more critical and rational approach to charity, I would highly suggest examining effective altruism. Simply put, effective altruism is a quasi-utilitarian form of charity. It aims to do the most good possible with the resources available. As Peter Singer, one of the gurus of the theory, puts it;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s important because it combines both the heart and the head. The heart, of course, you feel… But it’s really important to use the head as well to make sure that what you do is effective and well-directed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example that Singer gives, that I think concisely explains how one would practically apply the theory. In this instance, he talks about service dogs for blind people, a cause which most definitely fits the criteria of ‘pulling at the heartstrings.’ It costs about $40,000 in the US to train a guide dog and to train the recipient so that the guide dog can be of effective help to the blind person. It costs somewhere between $20 and $50 to cure a blind person in a developing country, if they have trachoma. After doing the maths, it works out that you could provide one guide dog for one blind American, or you could cure between 400 and 2,000 people of blindness. He finishes by stating that he thinks it’s perfectly clear what the better thing to do is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find his argument truly compelling, and in recent years it has become increasingly relevant in my own personal life. After completing various volunteer roles, I became fully aware of the importance and necessity of critically examining and evaluating our altruistic efforts. Indeed, volunteering serves as a very good example of ineffective altruism. International volunteers are usually low-skilled, studying or recently graduated young people from affluent countries. Often, they come for short periods of time, do not speak the local language, and do not have expertise in the field of work that they are helping in. A particular issue in South America and other developing parts of the world, these volunteers are frequently assumed to have more knowledge and relevant skills, purely because they come from more developed countries. Add into the mix the issues of voluntourism, and what you are left with is a situation where volunteers do not benefit, or even harm the local community. We all love the idea of helping other people, but unfortunately it is not so simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economics of volunteering are unconvincing at best, and I am going to use myself as an example to demonstrate it. A bit of background first; I spent five months volunteering in an NGO in a very small town near Cusco, Peru. The NGO works with disabled and disadvantaged children, and my work specifically consisted of helping out at a school for disabled children and also a care home for children who cannot live with their parents. I speak Spanish and have relevant work experience with children, so I, at least, was able to offset some of the issues that I mentioned earlier. However, a deeper look at the money is where problems start to arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of return flights = £600&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accommodation costs for 5 months= £1,600&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living costs = £40/week x 20 = £800&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total = £3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, even without taking into account my various trips to other South American countries whilst I was there, and any other additional costs, we are looking at a value of at least £3,000. When people ask me about the experience, I always say that it is one of the best things I have done in my life, and I felt that I made a real positive impact on the people I worked with. But asking about my experience is not the question that should be asked. As an effective altruist, the real question is, was the help I gave worth what a £3,000 investment could have done in my local area? In my mind, the answer is clearly no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herein lies one of the main problems with effective altruism. Altruism is, inevitably, emotional and personal. It is very hard to simply give without caring at all. A consequence of this is that we, the giver, also gain something through the act of giving. I would argue, therefore, that it is impossible to be altruistic in a purely selfless way. Whether personal gain is your primary aim or not, some part of giving away your time or your money positively benefits yourself. And here it gets complicated. How can we possibly be effective altruists, if we are at the same time, emotional altruists? How is it possible to analyse and calculate the best possible use of your money, without letting your subconscious emotions affect this decision? Peter Singer does come up with an answer for this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many effective altruists say that in doing good, they feel good. Effective altruists directly benefit others, but indirectly they often benefit themselves. If doing the most you can for others means that you are also flourishing, then that is the best possible outcome for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not disagree with him, but like most things, this is far simpler in theory than in practice. It is near-impossible to act without any self-interest, and the line between benefiting ourselves and benefiting other people is very thin. Once the giver starts to achieve their own goals through giving to charity, then it is hard for the process to not become emotional rather than rational. Moreover, it is human nature to generally favour ourselves and people similar to us, instead of others who may need and deserve the help more. It is easier to relate to somebody with whom we share common traits or experiences; another potential pitfall of where our emotions interfere with the aim of being rational and critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory also suffers from the same critiques that utilitarianism faces. Strictly adhering to benefitting the greatest number of people, instead of individual cases, can lead to some particularly troubling moral decisions. A good example of this was given in the Guardian; “would you really save a large bag of cash from a burning building rather than your neighbour’s terrified child, even if you could donate that cash and save the lives of a thousand strangers?” It’s good food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with these two valid criticisms, I am still a firm believer in effective altruism. Perhaps its applications are limited in practice, and not everyone has the luxury of being able to take the time or have the money, to give to charity in such a specific way. Yet, I believe that many people would greatly benefit by at least being aware of the theory and taking inspiration from it. The more rational and critical we can be, the better equipped we are to make informed, successful and effective altruistic decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An image that helps visualise the theory of effective altruism -&amp;gt; https://blog.ted.com/why-how-effective-altruism-peter-singer-visualized/ (Blog)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Daniel Harris</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">If I told you about a $60 million project aimed at providing water pumps for villages in Africa to 10 million people backed by the US government and various celebrities, you would probably think it’s a sound idea. The way the project actually works, is that the pump is connected to a merry-go-round and as children play on the apparatus, the energy is used to power the pump. It sounds like a great idea, which is why in 2006 this very project was put into place. However, it turned out to be a complete disaster. After some number crunching, it was calculated that children would have to be playing on the roundabout non-stop for 27 hours each day to reach the water production targets set by the initiative. Moreover, simply investing the money into regular water pumps would have been far less expensive and more efficient. As a different water NGO put it; “their marketing is perfect, but the final idea does not work.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the Ethics of Immigration: The Morality behind Closed Borders</title><link href="/Ethics-of-Immigration" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Ethics of Immigration: The Morality behind Closed Borders" /><published>2019-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Ethics-of-Immigration</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Ethics-of-Immigration">&lt;p&gt;In a world that is witnessing an unprecedented range of humanitarian crises, can it be ethical for states to shut their doors on victims of war, armed conflict, sexual violence or organized crime? Do these countries have the right to close their borders in the absence of such calamities alike? Notwithstanding, do all humans have a moral right to cross borders at will? While immigration has emerged as an important subject of debate and policies have been argued extensively in economic, political, and cultural contexts, the need for a nuanced understanding of the ethics of immigration has received little attention. There is an urgent need to address such questions whilst discussing the moral implications of immigration policies in light of global ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay argues that legitimate states, regardless of reason, have a moral right to close their borders to potential immigrants, and that these would-be immigrants do not have a moral right to cross borders at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of my essay argues that &lt;em&gt;“legitimate states are morally entitled to unilaterally design and enforce their own immigration policies,”&lt;/em&gt; even if such intensive policies restrict the entry of prospective immigrants. Every state, by virtue of its territorial integrity and sovereignty, is entitled to have dominion over deciding who may enter and who may not, a view deeply rooted in the moral right of countries to be politically self-determining over self-regarding affairs. In numerous instances, the United States has been pulled up for promoting violent coups in Middle-Eastern countries or been accused of meddling with autonomous elections in Central and Latin American nations. Interestingly, it isn’t the illegitimacy and immorality of the interference itself that provokes the rightful criticism and censure of the United States but the &lt;em&gt;very act of intrusion&lt;/em&gt;, that violates the territorial integrity and sovereignty of the targeted states. The essence of such criticism seems to stem from our expectation of political self-determination from the targeted countries. Therefore, political self-determination is an indispensable part of a state’s autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it is for individuals and groups that international law prescribes self-determination and not states, I believe stripping a country of its political self-determination takes away the right of its citizens and groups to control their self-interested affairs as well. A country’s immigration policy determines who may contribute to shaping the future of that nation: economically, politically and culturally, among other ways. Such a policy holds deep importance because it has the potential to determine the political course of that country and hence the course of its citizens’ lives in turn. The right to political self-determination of a country is simply the collection of individual and group self-determining rights of its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the politically self-determining nature of legitimate states is sufficient moral ground to let them make their own immigration policies &lt;em&gt;regardless&lt;/em&gt; of the nature of such policies, whether restrictive or liberal, egalitarian or utilitarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second dimension of my argument suggests that legitimate states have a right to freedom of association that includes the right to refuse association too. For instance, the freedom of association of an unmarried man emanates from his dominion over his own affairs, like any other person. While he may choose to marry a particular woman, he may choose not to marry that woman as well. At the same time, it is at the discretion of that woman as well, to marry him or not; it is a two-way process. While one may join a particular partner by virtue of one’s freedom of association, one may also not join that partner on accord of the same freedom. Similarly, legitimate states should be allowed to associate themselves with potential immigrants as well as refuse association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might argue that such an analogy is flawed since a matrimonial relationship is discretionary and can be avoided, while statelessness is not. Therefore, one does not have control over one’s citizenship as one does over a voluntary relationship such as marriage. Nevertheless, a different approach to the same argument could give us a clearer picture. What if we compared a state to property? International law requires a state to control a well-defined area under its jurisdiction for it to be called a state. Now, the right to property inherently includes the right to exclude others from its ownership. It can hence be inferred that a legitimate state, or more appropriately, a legitimate property, reserves the right to freedom of association with potential owners, and can deny such ownership by virtue of that freedom. While existent owners in the guise of citizens may rightfully denounce their ownership in the form of emigration, it is not obligatory for the state to entertain new ownership to its property in the form of immigration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the right to exclude prospective immigrants is a right born of the state’s indisputable jurisdiction over the property within its internationally recognized borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final facet of my argument justifies that the previous two hypotheses are not adverse to the moral rights of potential immigrants by any means. The right of a country to reject association with would-be immigrants does not violate their rights as liberalists and egalitarians often try to portray. The main reason is that human beings do not have a moral right to freedom of movement beyond the territory of their citizenship in the first place! Article 13 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights grants us the right to freedom of movement within our own state only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, arguments in favour of open borders often advocate that ‘humanity is equal’ and that ‘every human has an equal right to the natural resources on the planet’. Liberalists are of the view that it is terribly unjust for a person’s life prospects to be so greatly dependent on something as uncontrollable as the country she is born in. However, my views are more in harmony with &lt;em&gt;The Law of Peoples&lt;/em&gt; by John Rawls, who concedes to the inevitability of inequalities among states. As per Michael Blake, it is more thoughtful to accept that &lt;em&gt;“membership is not itself a good whose distribution is to be evaluated by distributive justice; rather, membership in a territorial state is required before [the] theory of distributive justice [can] have applicability”&lt;/em&gt;. The goods at stake when discussing immigration are connected more to better political institutions and social opportunities rather than a yearning for natural resources. These prospects include better lifestyles, progressive education, developed healthcare, and assured safety among others. Citizens of countries rich in oil are fleeing to havens in Europe without blinking an eye. Why? They value their safety more than their natural reserves, so do the Rohingya Muslims of forest-rich Myanmar that are ever-increasing as refugees in India. Abundantly resource-decorated Chinese and Indian nationals number highest as immigrants in the United States. Why? They value better economic opportunity more than the natural resources back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, this explanation clearly corroborates that immigration today is applied as a technique to avail of better opportunities or safer sanctuaries, and not as a means to ensure moral equality among human beings. Thus, it cannot be judged a moral human right by any means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recapitulate my argument, I firstly assert that legitimate states have a right to political self-determination by virtue of their territorial integrity and sovereignty, and on accord of the right to self-determination of its people. Successively, I prove how the freedom of association is an important component of a state’s right to political self-determination, adjudicating next that it is the sole owner of all political institutions within its recognized borders. Therefore, the first two facets of my arguments help me justify why legitimate states have a moral right to close their borders to potential immigrants, regardless of a specific reason. Finally, the concluding facet of my hypotheses helps me validate that human beings do not have a moral right to cross borders at will. I rest my case by affirming that a state’s right to exclude potential immigrants is not detrimental to their individual freedom and states need not present reasons to exercise this innately moral right.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivang Singh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">In a world that is witnessing an unprecedented range of humanitarian crises, can it be ethical for states to shut their doors on victims of war, armed conflict, sexual violence or organized crime? Do these countries have the right to close their borders in the absence of such calamities alike? Notwithstanding, do all humans have a moral right to cross borders at will? While immigration has emerged as an important subject of debate and policies have been argued extensively in economic, political, and cultural contexts, the need for a nuanced understanding of the ethics of immigration has received little attention. There is an urgent need to address such questions whilst discussing the moral implications of immigration policies in light of global ethics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“It’s hard to be down when you’re up” – Control, Understanding and The City.</title><link href="/Control-Understanding-and-The-City" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“It’s hard to be down when you’re up” – Control, Understanding and The City." /><published>2019-05-14T23:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-14T23:18:00+00:00</updated><id>/Control-Understanding-and-The-City</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Control-Understanding-and-The-City">&lt;p&gt;“I wonder what is the source of this pleasure of “seeing the whole,” of looking
down on, totalizing the most immoderate of human texts. To be lifted to the
summit of the World Trade Center is to be lifted out of the city’s grasp… It’s
hard to be down when you’re up.” Michel de Certeau&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quote from French psychoanalyst Michel de Certeau condenses a feeling that
many will have had, though cannot quite fully explain: Why do we take pleasure
in viewpoints, lookouts and the top floors of skyscrapers? What is it about
these vantage points that give us that ‘larger than life’ feeling?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city is a confusing entity. Whether it has been meticulously planned, or has
simply developed naturally over centuries, it is often incredibly difficult to
truly understand. When arriving for the first time, we are hit with a barrage of
new sights, smells, people and culture. Indeed, the first reaction is usually to
find something to orient ourselves, finding a system or service that we know
exists in other similar cities that we have already inhabited, and then working
from there. Examples of this could be a train station, bank, church,
supermarket; by finding universal facilities that exist in nearly all cities, it
becomes easier to navigate a new environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settling in to a new urban environment can be seen as matching and modifying an
old system of living to fit a new and different place. The building blocks of
how we live, work and function will be similar, but the specificities of how we
do it must adapt. Once you are settled, you solidify this routine until it
becomes second nature. You might even forget the way that you used to live, the
consequence of becoming accustomed to a new style of living, in a city that you
now call home. When eventually you move on, the same process is repeated. Now
you may draw on multiple past experiences, but the process is essentially the
same. By using tried and tested formulas, we manage our inherent human desire
for routine, and implement these plans on whatever the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The city also falls into this dual scripting. It is often branded as
  “evil”, harbouring the underbelly of modern society, while at the same time,
  it is heralded as the pinnacle of civilization, as man’s triumph over the
  barbarism of uncivilized earlier times and as a hallmark of the success of
  the project for pushing forwards the frontier of a wild and untamed nature.”
  Maria Kaika&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing on what Kaika comments, it can be argued that the city, in its most
basic form, is the representation of the human need to exercise control over
their surroundings. We do not wish to simply live in nature but to tame it,
master it, and modify it for our own desires. Moreover, this does not only apply
to the design of cities themselves but the way in which an individual chooses to
inhabit cities. We create routines, schedules and centre our whole way of living
around having control. The very thought of being out of control can lead to
serious mental health consequences, anxiety and a lack of self-worth. Although,
as stated before in this article, the building blocks of our lives are generally
constant and non-changeable, having the autonomy to decide the details, the
small things, is absolutely key. Your choice of supermarket, regular coffee
shop, the route you take to work; all of these are small but significant ways in
which we exert control over our schedules. Our habits are not just customs we
coincidentally act out, but an integral part of how we inhabit a city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to de Certeau, it is this relationship between control, understanding
and the city, that explains our love for skyscrapers, viewpoints and lookouts.
By simply being above all of the chaos of the city, above of all the individuals
going about their normal routines, we exercise control not just of ourselves,
but of the very city itself. New York, La Paz and Lisbon all provide perfect
examples of confusing, alive, bustling cities, with spectacular and stunning
lookouts. Suddenly, all of the confusion and anxiety of occupying the city is
lost, and the city is legible and intelligible. We transform into, as de Certeau
explains, a ‘god’, gaining the omniscient perspective that is simply not
possible from the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“His elevation transfigures him into a voyeur. It puts him at a distance. It
  transforms the bewitching world by which one was “possessed” into a text
  that lies before one’s eyes. It allows one to read it, to be a solar Eye,
  looking down like a god.” Michel de Certeau&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, power is the key dynamic at play. Rather than the being the
inhabitant, the apprehensive pedestrian who is just trying to survive in a
confusing and ever-changing environment, all of us wish to be, at least for a
while, sitting up on high reading and understanding the beauty and confusion of
the city. It sure is hard to be down when you are up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;A selection of my own photos, demonstrating how elevation helps to understand
the city.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Daniel Harris</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“I wonder what is the source of this pleasure of “seeing the whole,” of looking down on, totalizing the most immoderate of human texts. To be lifted to the summit of the World Trade Center is to be lifted out of the city’s grasp… It’s hard to be down when you’re up.” Michel de Certeau This quote from French psychoanalyst Michel de Certeau condenses a feeling that many will have had, though cannot quite fully explain: Why do we take pleasure in viewpoints, lookouts and the top floors of skyscrapers? What is it about these vantage points that give us that ‘larger than life’ feeling? The city is a confusing entity. Whether it has been meticulously planned, or has simply developed naturally over centuries, it is often incredibly difficult to truly understand. When arriving for the first time, we are hit with a barrage of new sights, smells, people and culture. Indeed, the first reaction is usually to find something to orient ourselves, finding a system or service that we know exists in other similar cities that we have already inhabited, and then working from there. Examples of this could be a train station, bank, church, supermarket; by finding universal facilities that exist in nearly all cities, it becomes easier to navigate a new environment. Settling in to a new urban environment can be seen as matching and modifying an old system of living to fit a new and different place. The building blocks of how we live, work and function will be similar, but the specificities of how we do it must adapt. Once you are settled, you solidify this routine until it becomes second nature. You might even forget the way that you used to live, the consequence of becoming accustomed to a new style of living, in a city that you now call home. When eventually you move on, the same process is repeated. Now you may draw on multiple past experiences, but the process is essentially the same. By using tried and tested formulas, we manage our inherent human desire for routine, and implement these plans on whatever the environment. “The city also falls into this dual scripting. It is often branded as “evil”, harbouring the underbelly of modern society, while at the same time, it is heralded as the pinnacle of civilization, as man’s triumph over the barbarism of uncivilized earlier times and as a hallmark of the success of the project for pushing forwards the frontier of a wild and untamed nature.” Maria Kaika Drawing on what Kaika comments, it can be argued that the city, in its most basic form, is the representation of the human need to exercise control over their surroundings. We do not wish to simply live in nature but to tame it, master it, and modify it for our own desires. Moreover, this does not only apply to the design of cities themselves but the way in which an individual chooses to inhabit cities. We create routines, schedules and centre our whole way of living around having control. The very thought of being out of control can lead to serious mental health consequences, anxiety and a lack of self-worth. Although, as stated before in this article, the building blocks of our lives are generally constant and non-changeable, having the autonomy to decide the details, the small things, is absolutely key. Your choice of supermarket, regular coffee shop, the route you take to work; all of these are small but significant ways in which we exert control over our schedules. Our habits are not just customs we coincidentally act out, but an integral part of how we inhabit a city. Returning to de Certeau, it is this relationship between control, understanding and the city, that explains our love for skyscrapers, viewpoints and lookouts. By simply being above all of the chaos of the city, above of all the individuals going about their normal routines, we exercise control not just of ourselves, but of the very city itself. New York, La Paz and Lisbon all provide perfect examples of confusing, alive, bustling cities, with spectacular and stunning lookouts. Suddenly, all of the confusion and anxiety of occupying the city is lost, and the city is legible and intelligible. We transform into, as de Certeau explains, a ‘god’, gaining the omniscient perspective that is simply not possible from the ground. “His elevation transfigures him into a voyeur. It puts him at a distance. It transforms the bewitching world by which one was “possessed” into a text that lies before one’s eyes. It allows one to read it, to be a solar Eye, looking down like a god.” Michel de Certeau Once again, power is the key dynamic at play. Rather than the being the inhabitant, the apprehensive pedestrian who is just trying to survive in a confusing and ever-changing environment, all of us wish to be, at least for a while, sitting up on high reading and understanding the beauty and confusion of the city. It sure is hard to be down when you are up. A selection of my own photos, demonstrating how elevation helps to understand the city.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Eternal Life a Good Thing?</title><link href="/Eternal-Life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Eternal Life a Good Thing?" /><published>2019-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Eternal-Life</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Eternal-Life">&lt;p&gt;It is basic human nature to mourn the death of our loved ones for they are no longer with us. Similarly, death seems to be a loss for the ones who die, at least in the human imagination, since the dead no longer exist for themselves or for others. In this context, death can be considered overwhelmingly ‘bad’ or harmful to human existence. So, if death is ‘bad’, then not dying must be ‘good’. Would this mean immortality is, in some ways, good because life itself is the essence of ‘goodness’ or the antithesis of death?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the above exposition might be a common assumption where immortality seems desirable, we can answer the question posed above only if we have an accurate evaluation of what is actually good. This essay investigates the metaphysical nature of death and its moral implications only to argue that death is better than an immortal existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Battle of Defining Death&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical professionals today command consensus over the scientific dogma that “human death is the irreversible cessation of the functioning of the brain including the brainstem”– as argued by Mr Thomas in the journal called &lt;em&gt;Bioethics&lt;/em&gt;. But there still exists a vibrancy of contentions that scholars often include in their respective theories of death. One school of thought considers death to be the inevitable end of a person’s existence, while another believes that only the body perishes on dying, for the soul lives forever. Deductions from the latter argument open doors for discussions on salvation, Heaven, Hell and the beyond. But, how much do we actually know about them for us to discuss them fruitfully? Great spiritual gratification may be found in death by those who believe in the latter, however, it is more convincing to approve of the former argument, given the limited knowledge we have about death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current knowledge at least verifies a universal truth that death is the common fate of all human beings, post which they stop existing physically. There is no concrete evidence to support any concept of another life, an after-life, or a reincarnation, among other divine hypotheses. Though a few mythological and religious texts support supernatural theories like these, the scientific age has turned them down on grounds of insufficiency of rationale and absence of proof. Also, even if we were to agree that there is an aftermath to death, it is certainly devoid of one’s original identity, thus terminating that particular life anyhow. The seemingly eternal soul will find a new body to sustain in, and leave that too one day before finding another body for a cycle of death to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if we analyse only the knowledge we are certain of, it is easy to accept death as a state of individual non-existence and nothing more. Consequently, it is a permanent annihilation of a person (at least as we know him/her) from the face of the earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nature of Death: The Deprivation Account of Badness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosophical discussions surrounding the nature of death – good or bad – has been in a constant argument among diverse schools of thought for several centuries now. My belief resonates with the ideas of deprivation theorists like Thomas Nagel and Shelly Kagan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deprivation Theory elucidates that death is bad because we can no longer experience the good things in life by virtue of our non-existence. When we cease to exist, we are naturally deprived of the good things in life. Therefore, being dead may not be intrinsically bad, but, it is relatively bad when compared to a situation that could allow us to continue watching the sunset, keep playing with our children and keep eating favorite delicacies, among other fortunes. Hence, the state of death makes us worse off than we were alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, some may argue that a person who was suffering when alive is better off once dead. He does not need to feel the pain and agony anymore. While the context of this argument may seem reasonable, even in this case we are worse off dead since we have no knowledge of what awaits us after death. For all we know, one might end up suffering to a greater extent than he already was when alive. A known devil is better than an unknown angel: we are better off being a part of what we know than walking into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second, stronger rebuttal can be drawn from the Epicurean argument that suggests we be indifferent to death. It explains that death cannot be good or bad since there is no existing person who can describe or value its pleasant or harmful nature. However, if an existing person were to be stripped of all the good things in his life, he would curse whoever did that. Similarly, if it were ever possible, he would curse death as well. Just because he exists no more is no reason for us to disregard the harm that death did to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a Roman philosopher named Lucretius offers yet another contention to my viewpoint. He believes that our non-existence after dying is just like the non-existence we underwent before birth. Since the latter is not bad, the former should not be bad either. To answer his claim, it can be expounded that our prenatal period did not involve any loss. On the contrary, death is a result of the loss of our life. Losing the good things in life is attached to a negative connotation. This way, we have proved yet again that death is a bad venture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Mortal’s Assessment of Immortality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the introduction of this essay, I had questioned if life was a good thing, provided death is bad. Now that we have established “death is bad,” we must assess immortality to see what life actually is. In order for immortality to be good, says Bernard Williams, two conditions need to be met simultaneously: the ‘Attractiveness Condition’ and the ‘Identity Condition’. Therefore, in order for immortality to be bad, or worse than death, these two conditions must not get fulfilled simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attractiveness Condition requires a life to have attractive meaning forever. Imagine doing something you love for one month straight. Then a year. Then a decade. Then a century. Then millions and billions of years. Regardless of how much you love that experience inherently, it will eventually lose its attractiveness when done repeatedly over a significant length of time. Such repetition will only lead to boredom and monotony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, a counter-argument could be that an immortal person would have a diverse routine, doing everything immortally possible. So, let Monday be music day, Tuesday – singing day, Wednesday – travelling day, and so on… Furthermore, imagine the schedule changes every week with new activities every day. Still, how long before we exhaust doing the things we like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take the argument to an all new level, let us take Robert Nozick’s Experience Machine. Even if we were to feel a variety of pleasures, every single day of our lives, over and over again, ultimately all our desires would lose meaning, leaving nothing for us to live for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may also delay participating in activities that we were keen to be a part of when mortally alive. Immortality might swing us towards a ‘will-do-it-tomorrow’ attitude because our days are no longer numbered. The ambition that a finite life instills in us would be lost to the drudgery of time, hence compromising the attractiveness of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us also discuss the Identity Condition, which requires that our personality and uniqueness always stay intact. It is difficult to consciously fulfill this condition, given the human mind is easily prone to tedium and ennui. In order to prevent this, an immortal person could attempt to transform himself in a way that divests him of his real-self and creates an existential crisis. Such attempts could include a ‘removal of higher consciousness’ so as to become ignorant towards an unending life or ‘inducing mental forgetfulness’ so as to experience every activity as if it were the first time, even if it were the millionth. This would artificially preserve the attractiveness of life but compromise our true identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it can be concluded that the Attractiveness Condition and the Identity Condition cannot be met simultaneously because of a clearly presented dilemma: If we live forever as our true selves, boredom will eventually set in and life would not remain as attractive; and if boredom does not set in, then it is not our true self that is living immortally; in both ways making immortality bad or in fact worse than death. While a finite existence promotes ambition, passion, motivation, and determination, an infinite life endorses dispiritedness, indifference, and lethargy over time. The balance of nature makes sure an unnatural phenomenon like immortality is worse than the natural principle of death. In other words, it is verily because of death that life becomes good, and it is verily because of life that death becomes bad. It is this metaphysical dichotomy and the epistemic limitations to a true understanding of death which makes life better than death. But, at the same time, this is what makes an unending life valueless too, for, without death, life is, quite unironically, pointless.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivang Singh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">It is basic human nature to mourn the death of our loved ones for they are no longer with us. Similarly, death seems to be a loss for the ones who die, at least in the human imagination, since the dead no longer exist for themselves or for others. In this context, death can be considered overwhelmingly ‘bad’ or harmful to human existence. So, if death is ‘bad’, then not dying must be ‘good’. Would this mean immortality is, in some ways, good because life itself is the essence of ‘goodness’ or the antithesis of death?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Robots: Magic to Manic to Toxic</title><link href="/Magic-Manic-Toxic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robots: Magic to Manic to Toxic" /><published>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Magic-Manic-Toxic</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Magic-Manic-Toxic">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can mankind prevail in the face of such exponential and encompassing technological change?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each new development comes at a cost. We frequently witness the dawn of a new era at the expense of the old, such as the Iron Age following the Bronze, which itself followed the Stone Age. The advent of the Industrial Revolution wiped out the livelihood of millions, such as cobblers and weavers who were forced to adapt or be left behind, and this dynamic process continues today, only now at a much faster rate. In this era of ‘The New Machine Age’, we enter a dramatical phase where even highly skilled jobs are at risk, and where there will be increasing technology and potentially decreasing jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The realities of the new Machine Age are becoming clear and we can use them to chart the challenging yet abundant economy that we are creating. According to research at Oxford University, almost one out of every two jobs has a high risk of being automated by machines. Machine Learning, the most powerful branch of Artificial Intelligence, is the technology which is to be blamed for this alarming disruption. It basically permits machines to learn from data and mimic some of the routine jobs that we humans perform, but much more efficiently. And, evidently, this can prove game-changing or extremely problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent study from Forrester Research goes so far as to predict that 25 million jobs might disappear over the next decade. To put that in perspective, that is three times as many as jobs lost in the aftermath of the Financial Crisis. In fact, 87% of the lost manufacturing jobs have been eliminated as a result of improvements to our own productivity through automation. Automation is spreading to every production sector in every country around the globe. Output in the manufacturing sector in the US is actually growing, but we are losing jobs and lots of them. In fact, from 2000-2010, 5.7 million manufacturing jobs were lost to machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just the blue-collar jobs that are at risk, even those at the top of the ladder, including the highest-paid people, will be affected. What is clear that no matter whatever your job, at least some of it will be done by a robot in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that the reason why visionaries like Mark Zuckerberg and Bill Gates are talking about government-funded minimum income levels? By the time today’s elementary school students are college-aged, we could be living in a robotic world largely unemployed and stuck in an ‘ungreat depression’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is supplemented by the dangers of technological advancement beyond automation and job replacement. Consider the tasks that are now done by a phone. Navigating a strange city? Impossible without Google Maps. Can’t decide where to take your next trip? MakeMyTrip will tell me. No time to answer all my texts? Siri will do it for me. These “artificial brains” are modifying quickly from knowing me to representing me to being me. In fact, they are starting to become an e-copy of us—and if that thought is not yet disturbing, imagine the power of this digital human amplified 100x in the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we give an AI programme the goal to make humans smile. When the AI is weak, it causes humans to smile by performing normal amusing actions. However, when the AI is super intelligent, it realises there is a more effective way to achieve this goal: take control of the world and stick electrodes into the facial muscles of humans to cause constant, beaming grins. Of course, while such a scenario sounds very alarmistic, it does highlight a fundamental problem. AI is a genie inside a bottle, so the only solution is to find a way that when it gets out, it is on our side through shared values. This does not involve spelling out a long list of what we care about in computer code, rather an AI could use its ‘intelligence’ to learn what we value. Because, after all, the real worry isn’t enmity, but competence. A superintelligent AI can attain its goals, however for the common good of the world, we need to ensure that its goals are aligned with ours. For instance, humans don’t generally hate bees, but we’re more intelligent than they are – so if humans want to build a home in the place of a beehive, too bad for the bees. The beneficial AI movement is simply a way of avoiding placing humanity in the position of those bees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work that brings everyday surprise is designed for humans and not machines. And an area in which we are most certainly able to compete with and beat any machine conceivable is creativity. Machines have made very little progress in tackling novel situations. The fundamental limitation of Machine Learning is that it requires huge volumes of past data which we humans don’t require. We have the capability to connect seemingly disparate threads to find a solution to crisis situations or problems we have never seen before. The ability of the human mind to take strands from reality and weave them into something beautiful using a vivid imagination cannot be surpassed by bits of code, no matter how intelligent it is. Indeed, an AI programme has made music, but the capacities of such programmes have a critical limitation: they cannot do something new, which is the foundation of human creativity, they can only replicate and mutate the data that is given them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it would seem that, with the right kind of limitations on what Machine Learning is used for and an investment in human beings, we can really herald a society where man and AI work together. First, we need to change our educational institutions to help foster more and more creativity, thereby preparing the jobs market for a situation where humans no longer do many mundane jobs. The efficiencies created by this division of labour between humans and AI will reap rewards that can only be imagined. Second, we need to align AI with our value systems and morals, using it as a purposeful instrument for human betterment rather than as a sterile but disastrously potent machine. With these two broad approaches, we humans can reach even greater heights of civilisation in the coming Age. After all, to quote Max Tegmark, President of the Future of Life Institute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Everything we love about civilization is a product of intelligence, so amplifying our human intelligence with artificial intelligence has the potential of helping a civilization flourish like never before – as long as we manage to keep the technology beneficial.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>unnati.jain sailesh.buchasia</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">How can mankind prevail in the face of such exponential and encompassing technological change?</summary></entry></feed>