<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-23T13:04:53+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Pandemic of Inequality</title><link href="/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pandemic of Inequality" /><published>2021-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality">&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus outbreak has plunged the entire globe into a deep ‘shock’ with simultaneous disruptions to both the demand and supply side in a highly interdependent and interconnected world economy. The increased incidence of infections has led to a large reduction in labour supply and the initial period of lockdowns have led to a loss of income for several households. Yet, there has been one section of people that have been worst hit by the pandemic - ‘the poor’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a general view that crises and pandemics like this often lead to the redistribution of resources among the masses, as the spread of the virus sees no caste, class and gender differences. However, this couldn’t be further away from reality. The COVID-19 has had a uniform impact on the entire world when it comes to the possibilities of being infected, but the social and economic impacts have been the most on the vulnerable sections of the society. In a recent study by the World Bank, “&lt;em&gt;Global extreme poverty is expected to rise in 2020 for the first time in over 20 years. The COVID-19 pandemic is estimated to push an additional 88 million to 115 million people into extreme poverty this year, with the total rising to as many as 150 million by 2021.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is thus an attempt to shed light on how the pandemic transformed into a pandemic of inequality using various arguments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past Experiences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A comparative analysis of the novel coronavirus and other past epidemics is often made to understand the relationship between the pandemics and inequalities caused across countries. The first example that comes into the mind is that of the 14th century Black Death which suggested that pandemics seem to reduce inequality in the long run. According to various studies conducted, the Black Death re-balanced the population, and available resources led to a useful reorganisation of agrarian production and triggered significant increases in real wages across the European continent. But the pandemics in recent history seem to have defied this theory. If recent episodes of pandemics are included, ranging from plagues to cholera pandemic &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, they fail to prove the substantial reduction in inequality levels. Instead, the levels have been observed to be increasing substantially, coinciding with the occurrence of these events. Therefore the impact of Black Death turns out to be an ‘exception’ in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Uneven Playing Field&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we begin analysing this relationship between a pandemic and inequality, have a look at the rising income trend in the figure given below and keep it in mind. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/#:~:text=The%20world%20population%20increased%20from,to%201.05%25%20per%20year%20today.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldbank1.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 1. Source: World Bank &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, economic inequality refers to the unequal distribution of income and opportunity between different groups in society. According to Tony Atkinson, a renowned British economist, “&lt;em&gt;Inequality of outcome among today’s generation is the source of the unfair advantage received by the next generation. If we are concerned about equality of opportunity tomorrow, we need to be concerned about inequality of outcome today.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s world, inequality is a pressing concern transforming into a situation of emergency. The figure below visualises the inequality in living conditions between the world’s best-off and worst-off countries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/#:~:text=The%20world%20population%20increased%20from,to%201.05%25%20per%20year%20today.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldbank2.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 2. Source: World Bank&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Income and wealth inequality have particularly witnessed an upward trend in all major advanced economies while for the emerging ones, the income distribution trends have been mixed but most of them are experiencing an upward trend too, led by major emerging economies such as China and India. In this scenario, the increase in inequality due to the current pandemic is quite worrisome.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a study conducted Oxfam, a non-profit operating across the world, it is estimated that there are as much as 121 million more people on the brink of starvation today due to mass unemployment, disruption to food production and supplies. “&lt;em&gt;As many as 12,000 people could die every day from COVID-linked hunger&lt;/em&gt;,” stated Oxfam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the wake of these figures, it becomes imperative to understand the two-way relationship between pandemics and inequality, i.e. inequality is not just an impact of the pandemic, it is the cause of the outbreak itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no doubt that it is the extreme socio-economic inequalities and the lack of access to public healthcare facilities that have led to stark ill-proportioned costs being borne by these downtrodden individuals, both in terms of infection incidences as well as the economic well-being. But how exactly does this play out?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, the countries facing a sustained rise in population levels also experience an increasing population density, which therefore leads to a rise in the ability of the disease to reproduce and spread. At the same time, due to an increase in the labour force, the wages are driven down due to an excess supply of labour. On the other hand, the richer and affluent sections of the society become richer and richer, on account of declining labour wages. These sections are generally the ones having major wealth in the form of capital holdings.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of the stark differences in the income levels, the poor people face a major problem of poverty and undernutrition, the cause of which can be broken down into three aspects: Parental Resources (low awareness and education among the poor, high morbidity), Household Resources (income levels of households) and Community Resources (unavailability of safe drinking water and sanitation). This leads to higher susceptibility to infections making them less capable to fight the pathogens. And when it comes to being tested positive for the virus, these individuals are likely to face higher mortality due to lack of access to public health services. Apart from this, we also observe large scale migration of poor from rural to urban areas in search of employment opportunities, which leads to increased population density in cities and makes them breeding ground for diseases again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly, the outbreak of novel coronavirus has led to an emergence of the ‘new normal’- work from home (WFH), since it is the only option to continue working and minimising the risk of virus exposure. Even though recent studies have shown an increase in average labour incomes because of this positive shift to work from home, the potential benefit will be highly asymmetrical,&amp;nbsp; favouring highly-educated and high-paid employees. Also, there are numerous jobs which cannot come under the ambit of this new normal, and individuals in these sectors have been rendered unemployed, worsening the income distribution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IMF, in its recent study, has analysed the aggregate decrease in income levels using its GDP growth projections for 2020. It has been found that the estimated effect of COVID-19 will be larger than that caused by the past pandemics and that gains achieved since the global financial crisis (2008) might be reversed. The analysis shows that the average &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gini_coefficient&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gini coefficient&lt;/a&gt; for emerging markets and developing economies will rise to 42.7, which is comparable to the level in 2008. The impact would be larger for low-income developing countries despite slower progress since 2008. The pandemic could also possibly reduce welfare by about 8% in emerging economies and developing nations with more than 50% change coming from the increase in inequality due to WFH feasibility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/WEO#:~:text=Description%3A%20Global%20growth%20is%20projected,Economic%20Outlook%20(WEO)%20forecast.&amp;amp;text=In%202021%20global%20growth%20is,19%20projections%20of%20January%202020.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldecon1.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 2. Source: World Bank&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems don’t end here. When the vaccines for the virus come out, the market mechanism comes into play to dictate the distribution over and within the countries. The poor countries are very likely to be crowded out of the markets as they receive the vaccines at the very end, as these countries are plagued with poor health infrastructure. Within countries, the most vulnerable sections will find themselves unable to access the necessary medical aid. Even if in the end they are able to administer the vaccine, the damage would have been done. The pathogens might have been rendered ineffective. And therefore, the future generation is bound to face the ripples of the pandemic too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way the generation is doomed is the asymmetries in access to health and education services. With the mode of teaching being shifted online, children belonging to poor households face an amplified barrier to schooling and education.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the social inequalities will create ‘avenues for development of unrest and discontentment among the people’ which in the long run leads to political upheavals and the rise of populist leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the pandemic proves to be perilous to the society in a multitude of ways that go over and above health risks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned impact is on a global level. Now let’s analyse the impact of the pandemic so far on India, to understand how it is particularly bad.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August 2020, Mukesh Ambani became the 4th richest person in the world. On the same day, a man reportedly committed suicide and killed his family because of job loss induced by the pandemic. The above case exactly represents the tale of two Indias and how badly this pandemic has affected the already high inequality in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last 20 years, the increase in inequality has been the highest in India except Russia. As the rich get richer even amidst a pandemic, nearly 400 million workers are at the cusp of falling into abject poverty, as reported by the International Labour Organisation (ILO).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is often said that epidemics are true mirrors of society, and the COVID-19 outbreak has effectively mirrored the broken public healthcare system in India. In India, there exists significant inter-state and intra-state disparities. When it comes to distribution of doctors in urban and rural areas, there is a huge skewness observable. In terms of availability of hospital beds, states like Bihar are well below the national average of 0.55 beds in the public sector per 1,000 population while others like West Bengal (2.25 beds/1000) and Sikkim (2.34 beds/1000) have considerably more. The pandemic hit the country at a time when the country was facing an economic slowdown, and the public health crisis of this magnitude is going to have a further negative impact on the Indian economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of inequality is with respect to gender. With many companies enforcing strict social distancing guidelines and WFH policy, women even with full-time paid employment are facing reduced efficiency because of the additional and disproportionate share of the workload. Additionally, the concerns of rising domestic violence and sexual abuse paints a grim picture of state of women currently.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the line with the foregoing discussion, the first and foremost task is to secure the livelihoods of the most vulnerable sections of the society. The empowerment and growth of the global community is linked to the socio-economic well-being of each individual. While the impact of the pandemic can never be ascertained 100%, the policy measure taken today will be responsible for the outcomes for the future generations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rajsi Sah</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The coronavirus outbreak has plunged the entire globe into a deep ‘shock’ with simultaneous disruptions to both the demand and supply side in a highly interdependent and interconnected world economy. The increased incidence of infections has led to a large reduction in labour supply and the initial period of lockdowns have led to a loss of income for several households. Yet, there has been one section of people that have been worst hit by the pandemic - ‘the poor’.&amp;nbsp; It is a general view that crises and pandemics like this often lead to the redistribution of resources among the masses, as the spread of the virus sees no caste, class and gender differences. However, this couldn’t be further away from reality. The COVID-19 has had a uniform impact on the entire world when it comes to the possibilities of being infected, but the social and economic impacts have been the most on the vulnerable sections of the society. In a recent study by the World Bank, “Global extreme poverty is expected to rise in 2020 for the first time in over 20 years. The COVID-19 pandemic is estimated to push an additional 88 million to 115 million people into extreme poverty this year, with the total rising to as many as 150 million by 2021.” The article is thus an attempt to shed light on how the pandemic transformed into a pandemic of inequality using various arguments.&amp;nbsp; Past Experiences A comparative analysis of the novel coronavirus and other past epidemics is often made to understand the relationship between the pandemics and inequalities caused across countries. The first example that comes into the mind is that of the 14th century Black Death which suggested that pandemics seem to reduce inequality in the long run. According to various studies conducted, the Black Death re-balanced the population, and available resources led to a useful reorganisation of agrarian production and triggered significant increases in real wages across the European continent. But the pandemics in recent history seem to have defied this theory. If recent episodes of pandemics are included, ranging from plagues to cholera pandemic et al, they fail to prove the substantial reduction in inequality levels. Instead, the levels have been observed to be increasing substantially, coinciding with the occurrence of these events. Therefore the impact of Black Death turns out to be an ‘exception’ in this case. An Uneven Playing Field Before we begin analysing this relationship between a pandemic and inequality, have a look at the rising income trend in the figure given below and keep it in mind. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Figure 1. Source: World Bank Fundamentally, economic inequality refers to the unequal distribution of income and opportunity between different groups in society. According to Tony Atkinson, a renowned British economist, “Inequality of outcome among today’s generation is the source of the unfair advantage received by the next generation. If we are concerned about equality of opportunity tomorrow, we need to be concerned about inequality of outcome today.” In today’s world, inequality is a pressing concern transforming into a situation of emergency. The figure below visualises the inequality in living conditions between the world’s best-off and worst-off countries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Figure 2. Source: World Bank&amp;nbsp; Income and wealth inequality have particularly witnessed an upward trend in all major advanced economies while for the emerging ones, the income distribution trends have been mixed but most of them are experiencing an upward trend too, led by major emerging economies such as China and India. In this scenario, the increase in inequality due to the current pandemic is quite worrisome.&amp;nbsp; In a study conducted Oxfam, a non-profit operating across the world, it is estimated that there are as much as 121 million more people on the brink of starvation today due to mass unemployment, disruption to food production and supplies. “As many as 12,000 people could die every day from COVID-linked hunger,” stated Oxfam. In the wake of these figures, it becomes imperative to understand the two-way relationship between pandemics and inequality, i.e. inequality is not just an impact of the pandemic, it is the cause of the outbreak itself.&amp;nbsp; It is no doubt that it is the extreme socio-economic inequalities and the lack of access to public healthcare facilities that have led to stark ill-proportioned costs being borne by these downtrodden individuals, both in terms of infection incidences as well as the economic well-being. But how exactly does this play out?&amp;nbsp; To begin with, the countries facing a sustained rise in population levels also experience an increasing population density, which therefore leads to a rise in the ability of the disease to reproduce and spread. At the same time, due to an increase in the labour force, the wages are driven down due to an excess supply of labour. On the other hand, the richer and affluent sections of the society become richer and richer, on account of declining labour wages. These sections are generally the ones having major wealth in the form of capital holdings.&amp;nbsp; As a result of the stark differences in the income levels, the poor people face a major problem of poverty and undernutrition, the cause of which can be broken down into three aspects: Parental Resources (low awareness and education among the poor, high morbidity), Household Resources (income levels of households) and Community Resources (unavailability of safe drinking water and sanitation). This leads to higher susceptibility to infections making them less capable to fight the pathogens. And when it comes to being tested positive for the virus, these individuals are likely to face higher mortality due to lack of access to public health services. Apart from this, we also observe large scale migration of poor from rural to urban areas in search of employment opportunities, which leads to increased population density in cities and makes them breeding ground for diseases again.&amp;nbsp; Particularly, the outbreak of novel coronavirus has led to an emergence of the ‘new normal’- work from home (WFH), since it is the only option to continue working and minimising the risk of virus exposure. Even though recent studies have shown an increase in average labour incomes because of this positive shift to work from home, the potential benefit will be highly asymmetrical,&amp;nbsp; favouring highly-educated and high-paid employees. Also, there are numerous jobs which cannot come under the ambit of this new normal, and individuals in these sectors have been rendered unemployed, worsening the income distribution.&amp;nbsp; The IMF, in its recent study, has analysed the aggregate decrease in income levels using its GDP growth projections for 2020. It has been found that the estimated effect of COVID-19 will be larger than that caused by the past pandemics and that gains achieved since the global financial crisis (2008) might be reversed. The analysis shows that the average Gini coefficient for emerging markets and developing economies will rise to 42.7, which is comparable to the level in 2008. The impact would be larger for low-income developing countries despite slower progress since 2008. The pandemic could also possibly reduce welfare by about 8% in emerging economies and developing nations with more than 50% change coming from the increase in inequality due to WFH feasibility.&amp;nbsp; Figure 2. Source: World Bank The problems don’t end here. When the vaccines for the virus come out, the market mechanism comes into play to dictate the distribution over and within the countries. The poor countries are very likely to be crowded out of the markets as they receive the vaccines at the very end, as these countries are plagued with poor health infrastructure. Within countries, the most vulnerable sections will find themselves unable to access the necessary medical aid. Even if in the end they are able to administer the vaccine, the damage would have been done. The pathogens might have been rendered ineffective. And therefore, the future generation is bound to face the ripples of the pandemic too.&amp;nbsp; Another way the generation is doomed is the asymmetries in access to health and education services. With the mode of teaching being shifted online, children belonging to poor households face an amplified barrier to schooling and education.&amp;nbsp; And lastly, the social inequalities will create ‘avenues for development of unrest and discontentment among the people’ which in the long run leads to political upheavals and the rise of populist leaders.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the pandemic proves to be perilous to the society in a multitude of ways that go over and above health risks.&amp;nbsp; The above-mentioned impact is on a global level. Now let’s analyse the impact of the pandemic so far on India, to understand how it is particularly bad.&amp;nbsp; In August 2020, Mukesh Ambani became the 4th richest person in the world. On the same day, a man reportedly committed suicide and killed his family because of job loss induced by the pandemic. The above case exactly represents the tale of two Indias and how badly this pandemic has affected the already high inequality in the country.&amp;nbsp; In the last 20 years, the increase in inequality has been the highest in India except Russia. As the rich get richer even amidst a pandemic, nearly 400 million workers are at the cusp of falling into abject poverty, as reported by the International Labour Organisation (ILO). It is often said that epidemics are true mirrors of society, and the COVID-19 outbreak has effectively mirrored the broken public healthcare system in India. In India, there exists significant inter-state and intra-state disparities. When it comes to distribution of doctors in urban and rural areas, there is a huge skewness observable. In terms of availability of hospital beds, states like Bihar are well below the national average of 0.55 beds in the public sector per 1,000 population while others like West Bengal (2.25 beds/1000) and Sikkim (2.34 beds/1000) have considerably more. The pandemic hit the country at a time when the country was facing an economic slowdown, and the public health crisis of this magnitude is going to have a further negative impact on the Indian economy.&amp;nbsp; Another aspect of inequality is with respect to gender. With many companies enforcing strict social distancing guidelines and WFH policy, women even with full-time paid employment are facing reduced efficiency because of the additional and disproportionate share of the workload. Additionally, the concerns of rising domestic violence and sexual abuse paints a grim picture of state of women currently.&amp;nbsp; In the line with the foregoing discussion, the first and foremost task is to secure the livelihoods of the most vulnerable sections of the society. The empowerment and growth of the global community is linked to the socio-economic well-being of each individual. While the impact of the pandemic can never be ascertained 100%, the policy measure taken today will be responsible for the outcomes for the future generations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Love Letter to Fellow Scapegoats</title><link href="/A-Love-Letter-to-Fellow-Scapegoats" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Love Letter to Fellow Scapegoats" /><published>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Love-Letter-to-Fellow-Scapegoats</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Love-Letter-to-Fellow-Scapegoats">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This is a love letter, let me begin with that. It's Christmas today, and no, I don’t have a glass of wine on me, nor do I have a roaring fireplace beside me. I’m definitely not surrounded by a loved one’s arms, and I most definitely don’t have a black Persian cat with heterochromia fast asleep on my lap. What I’m trying to say here is, Santa put me in the naughty-people list and nothing I wanted has been afforded to me. Not even the Post-Grad admission I had bribed (may I add, heavily) God for. You must wonder why am I writing words of amore when not a lot of what I wanted has been given to me. Or is that wishful thinking on my part?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;I wonder in what words I could explain that I might be grateful for all of my turmoil-induced-emotions. I wonder if my fervour for these emotions has anything to do with the mindless novelty of them, or perhaps, it is due to their unrestricted nature. I’m not a Godless person, but neither am I someone who completely believes in God’s idealistic characters. Yet, in recent times, I’ve found charm in begging, bribing and accepting the Higher Presence. With not one thing in my hand, I enjoy the idea of having left the utter discourse of my life on the One higher-up. I may not have what I want, not even what I possibly deserve, but who’s to blame? Not me. I wish I were one of those who felt ‘touched’ by The Presence, or the ones who believe only the good is destined, and maybe I’m paving a path towards that, but I’m not there, yet (most likely, I never will be). But, I must accept, I’ve felt much better about coursing the blame through someone else. There’s less to it than devotion and yet, it’s pristine enough to maybe be beyond it. It may be called a defence mechanism, or maybe it’s simply just a change of tact, a diversion, if you will. Either way, it has saved me quite a lot of tears and several hours of self-loathing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;If one were to search ‘God is a micromanager?’, the likeness of a treasure trove may be found. My favourite answers (very obviously) belong to Quora. Jim Whitehead, Former Subatomic whisperer answered ‘&lt;em&gt;No we do!&lt;/em&gt;’ and, I’m here for it, his answer is eloquent and metaphorical and everything I wanted from a Quora answer. However, after much deliberation, I decided to forego further research, mostly because of Jim, and partially because I wasn’t in the mood to give up on the blame game, yet. The feeling of guilt I tried not to feel, or even the remorse, I suppose, caught up to me. The &lt;em&gt;7 Laws of Magical Thinking&lt;/em&gt; by Matthew Hutson gives a purview into why we do what we do - it speaks quite a lot about God’s Plan (not the fun Drake kind) and about negative agency bias (my favourite kind of bias). What it suggests is that acts of consequence, particularly unfavourable consequence, arouse feelings of divine authorship. The negative agency bias also results from the fact that we like to take credit for positive outcomes and blame failures on someone else. But I’ve spoken about that before, many times, if I recall correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I would say I was simply looking for a scapegoat, one who doesn’t retort back. They don’t unfollow you, or tweet you back, or worse, block you. Or do they? Ah, I’ll try not to give myself a scare. I’m sure you’re screaming at me to just take responsibility, fess up and get on with the ‘real’ world. Believe me, Sir Louis Cohen, off-of-Quora’s answer, “&lt;em&gt;The only gods are fictional characters in fairy tales. You’re in charge so don’t try to pass the buck&lt;/em&gt;” really tried to do a number on me. But it’s Christmas, in the middle of a pandemic with new mutant versions popping out each day, and don’t you remember? My cat is not here for support. And like I said, this is a love letter, to fellow scapegoats, whose presence are sometimes questioned, always appreciated and very well monetised. If this pity party of mine has managed to affront you, I heartily apologise, I’m open to new learnings (mostly, because I’m Uni-less at the moment) and will like, follow and subscribe if you put a good word for me to the One Above. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><summary type="html">This is a love letter, let me begin with that. It's Christmas today, and no, I don’t have a glass of wine on me, nor do I have a roaring fireplace beside me. I’m definitely not surrounded by a loved one’s arms, and I most definitely don’t have a black Persian cat with heterochromia fast asleep on my lap. What I’m trying to say here is, Santa put me in the naughty-people list and nothing I wanted has been afforded to me. Not even the Post-Grad admission I had bribed (may I add, heavily) God for. You must wonder why am I writing words of amore when not a lot of what I wanted has been given to me. Or is that wishful thinking on my part? I wonder in what words I could explain that I might be grateful for all of my turmoil-induced-emotions. I wonder if my fervour for these emotions has anything to do with the mindless novelty of them, or perhaps, it is due to their unrestricted nature. I’m not a Godless person, but neither am I someone who completely believes in God’s idealistic characters. Yet, in recent times, I’ve found charm in begging, bribing and accepting the Higher Presence. With not one thing in my hand, I enjoy the idea of having left the utter discourse of my life on the One higher-up. I may not have what I want, not even what I possibly deserve, but who’s to blame? Not me. I wish I were one of those who felt ‘touched’ by The Presence, or the ones who believe only the good is destined, and maybe I’m paving a path towards that, but I’m not there, yet (most likely, I never will be). But, I must accept, I’ve felt much better about coursing the blame through someone else. There’s less to it than devotion and yet, it’s pristine enough to maybe be beyond it. It may be called a defence mechanism, or maybe it’s simply just a change of tact, a diversion, if you will. Either way, it has saved me quite a lot of tears and several hours of self-loathing.&amp;nbsp; If one were to search ‘God is a micromanager?’, the likeness of a treasure trove may be found. My favourite answers (very obviously) belong to Quora. Jim Whitehead, Former Subatomic whisperer answered ‘No we do!’ and, I’m here for it, his answer is eloquent and metaphorical and everything I wanted from a Quora answer. However, after much deliberation, I decided to forego further research, mostly because of Jim, and partially because I wasn’t in the mood to give up on the blame game, yet. The feeling of guilt I tried not to feel, or even the remorse, I suppose, caught up to me. The 7 Laws of Magical Thinking by Matthew Hutson gives a purview into why we do what we do - it speaks quite a lot about God’s Plan (not the fun Drake kind) and about negative agency bias (my favourite kind of bias). What it suggests is that acts of consequence, particularly unfavourable consequence, arouse feelings of divine authorship. The negative agency bias also results from the fact that we like to take credit for positive outcomes and blame failures on someone else. But I’ve spoken about that before, many times, if I recall correctly. At this point, I would say I was simply looking for a scapegoat, one who doesn’t retort back. They don’t unfollow you, or tweet you back, or worse, block you. Or do they? Ah, I’ll try not to give myself a scare. I’m sure you’re screaming at me to just take responsibility, fess up and get on with the ‘real’ world. Believe me, Sir Louis Cohen, off-of-Quora’s answer, “The only gods are fictional characters in fairy tales. You’re in charge so don’t try to pass the buck” really tried to do a number on me. But it’s Christmas, in the middle of a pandemic with new mutant versions popping out each day, and don’t you remember? My cat is not here for support. And like I said, this is a love letter, to fellow scapegoats, whose presence are sometimes questioned, always appreciated and very well monetised. If this pity party of mine has managed to affront you, I heartily apologise, I’m open to new learnings (mostly, because I’m Uni-less at the moment) and will like, follow and subscribe if you put a good word for me to the One Above.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yemen: A Pawn in the Game of Middle Eastern Checkers?</title><link href="/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yemen: A Pawn in the Game of Middle Eastern Checkers?" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers">&lt;p&gt;On December 31, 22 people were killed and 50 others injured in an attack at the Aden airport in South Yemen. The attack was directed at the Saudi-backed cabinet of the new Unity Government which had landed in the same airport at that time. A second explosion was reported from Aden's Maasheq presidential palace which housed the cabinet members including the Yemeni Prime Minister Maeen Abdulmalik and the Saudi ambassador to Yemen. The Yemeni government had been sworn in on December 26, 2020, days prior to the incident, comprising 24 ministers representing the major political powers of the nation including the Southern Transitional Council. The government placed the responsibility of the attack upon the Houthis. This even should not be interpreted in isolation but in the context of a diplomatic and military crisis that goes back years into the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yemen's Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roots of the long-drawn conflict can be traced back to the multi-sided war between the Abrabbuh Mansur Hadi led Yemeni government in the South and the Houthi rebels who have seized control of Northern Yemen including the capital city of Sana'a, adjoining the Saudi border. The civil war started in 2014 and is largely attributed to the religious angle. The Zaidis, a sect of Shias, faced discrimination during the rule of Muhammad al-Shawkani, who propounded Sunnification as the means to consolidate a unified Yemen. This was in defiance to Zaidi Shi'ism. The Houthis trace their ancestry from a Zaidi group located at the Sa'dah governorate on the Northern borders of Yemen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of the Houthi rebellion was seen in 2004, when Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi, a former member of the Yemeni Parliament was killed by government military forces following his protests against governmental regulations. The political situation escalated following the 2011 Yemeni Revolution of Dignity, an offshoot of the broader Arab Spring revolution. Abdul- Malik al-Houthi supported the rebel organisations' demand for the resignation of the Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh and its siege of the Salafi village of Dammaj in Northern Yemen, boycotting the 2012 single-candidate elections aimed at making Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi the President of Yemen (a post which he still holds).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2014, the Sunni-Houthi conflict engulfed the rest of Yemen including the Sana'a Governorate by August 2014. The civil war was marked by several military milestones including the Battle of Taiz, at Yemen's third-largest city. The Houthis employed a Tochka missile (ballistic) against the Saudi-led coalition. At the battle of Aden in 2015, Hadi escaped to Riyadh, seeking assistance from Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman Al Saud, the Saudi heir apparent. The war no longer remained confined within Yemeni borders and was immediately internationalised. A Saudi-led coalition including UAE attempted at restoring the previous Yemeni Government. Sudanese and Egyptian troops had also cooperated against the Houthi advances. Amidst a geopolitical crisis, the ISIS too had been actively involved, conducting a series of suicide bombings that resulted in the death of 15 soldiers affiliated with the Saudi coalition. They, however, didn't side with the Houthi rebels either - exhorting their followers to kill the Zaidis as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the Saudi led coalition launched a major offensive mission to regain control of the city of Hudaydah, adjoining the Red Sea, in spite of warnings by the UN that the port's destruction would serve as a “crossing of Rubicon” moment. Basically, it was a point of no return as it would be impossible to avert massive loss of life due to the famine conditions that would ensue due to the disastrous effects on the shipping of food supplies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;In August 2019, there was a rift in Southern Yemen between the government forces backed by the Saudi government and the Southern Transitional Council (STC) which enjoyed UAE support. Following the failure of the Kuwait initiative seeking a political solution, the 2019 Riyadh agreement was brokered as a power-sharing deal between the Yemeni government and the Southern separatists aimed at transcending this difference between the friends turned foes. However, the conflict resumed on January 7, 2020, when the Houthi rebels shot down a Saudi coalition drone at Jawf.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the COVID-19 outbreak, an air raid ceasefire had been declared while 10,000 people had been displaced, and 13 million civilians denied access to clean and safe drinking water. Yemen had previously faced a cholera epidemic in 2017 affecting 20 out of the 22 Yemeni provinces. As of July 2020, the UNHCR estimated that 3.6 million people had been displaced and 24 million await urgent aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geopolitical ramifications&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The civil war has been at the heart of a much larger international political equation. Despite the fact that United States spokesperson Bernadette Meehan has openly stated: “&lt;em&gt;It remains our assessment that Iran does not exert command and control over the Houthis in Yemen”,&lt;/em&gt; many have viewed this as a larger Iranian proxy war. Iran and Yemen are composed of Shia Islamist, albeit with minor differences - the Iranians are followers of the Twelve Imam Shias while the Houthis are Zaidi Shias. This is in contrast to the Saudi Arabia-led coalition that largely comprises Sunni-majority nations. Ali Khamenei has even explicitly stated that he shall provide “spiritual support&quot; to the movement of the Houthis in 2019. Eritrea too has been accused of providing Iranian ammunition to the Houthis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni government on the other hand has received military as well as financial aid from the United States, which conducted drone strikes in Sana’a aiming to neutralise Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP). Reports published by Amnesty International in 2019 also indicate logistical assistance from the UK in the form of laser-guided bombs and other weaponry. Interestingly, the US Arms Export Control Act was believed to have been violated by the United States Department while ratifying arms sales to the Gulf states of Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates in August 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The launch of the ballistic missile by Houthis aimed at Saudi Arabia in 2017 led to a further strengthening of the Yemen blockade by the Saudi coalition under the pretext of preventing weapon smuggling by Iranian rebels, an accusation Tehran vehemently denies. In hindsight, this led to a hike in the price of food and fuel, adding a food security dimension to the military conflict.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yemen continues to suffer from the world's worst humanitarian crisis. The crisis is not only a concern to the Middle Eastern neighbours of Yemen but fuels the threat perception pertaining to that of the West's War on Terror against terrorism at large, particularly Al-Qaeda and ISIS. Yemen enjoys superior strategic significance, located as it is geographically on the strait linking the Red Sea with the Gulf of Aden which constitutes the zone from which most of the world's oil cargo travels. Many had blamed Saudi Arabia for its lack of security provisions on the day of the Aden airport blast, yet this might be considered as the tip of the iceberg of a deep-seated problem concerning the 'unity government.' What needs to be understood is that in more ways than one, Yemen has become a pawn in the clutches of the broader strategic dynamics of the Arab world and Uncle Sam’s War on Terror.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">On December 31, 22 people were killed and 50 others injured in an attack at the Aden airport in South Yemen. The attack was directed at the Saudi-backed cabinet of the new Unity Government which had landed in the same airport at that time. A second explosion was reported from Aden's Maasheq presidential palace which housed the cabinet members including the Yemeni Prime Minister Maeen Abdulmalik and the Saudi ambassador to Yemen. The Yemeni government had been sworn in on December 26, 2020, days prior to the incident, comprising 24 ministers representing the major political powers of the nation including the Southern Transitional Council. The government placed the responsibility of the attack upon the Houthis. This even should not be interpreted in isolation but in the context of a diplomatic and military crisis that goes back years into the past. Yemen's Civil War The roots of the long-drawn conflict can be traced back to the multi-sided war between the Abrabbuh Mansur Hadi led Yemeni government in the South and the Houthi rebels who have seized control of Northern Yemen including the capital city of Sana'a, adjoining the Saudi border. The civil war started in 2014 and is largely attributed to the religious angle. The Zaidis, a sect of Shias, faced discrimination during the rule of Muhammad al-Shawkani, who propounded Sunnification as the means to consolidate a unified Yemen. This was in defiance to Zaidi Shi'ism. The Houthis trace their ancestry from a Zaidi group located at the Sa'dah governorate on the Northern borders of Yemen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The first of the Houthi rebellion was seen in 2004, when Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi, a former member of the Yemeni Parliament was killed by government military forces following his protests against governmental regulations. The political situation escalated following the 2011 Yemeni Revolution of Dignity, an offshoot of the broader Arab Spring revolution. Abdul- Malik al-Houthi supported the rebel organisations' demand for the resignation of the Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh and its siege of the Salafi village of Dammaj in Northern Yemen, boycotting the 2012 single-candidate elections aimed at making Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi the President of Yemen (a post which he still holds). By 2014, the Sunni-Houthi conflict engulfed the rest of Yemen including the Sana'a Governorate by August 2014. The civil war was marked by several military milestones including the Battle of Taiz, at Yemen's third-largest city. The Houthis employed a Tochka missile (ballistic) against the Saudi-led coalition. At the battle of Aden in 2015, Hadi escaped to Riyadh, seeking assistance from Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman Al Saud, the Saudi heir apparent. The war no longer remained confined within Yemeni borders and was immediately internationalised. A Saudi-led coalition including UAE attempted at restoring the previous Yemeni Government. Sudanese and Egyptian troops had also cooperated against the Houthi advances. Amidst a geopolitical crisis, the ISIS too had been actively involved, conducting a series of suicide bombings that resulted in the death of 15 soldiers affiliated with the Saudi coalition. They, however, didn't side with the Houthi rebels either - exhorting their followers to kill the Zaidis as well.&amp;nbsp; In 2018, the Saudi led coalition launched a major offensive mission to regain control of the city of Hudaydah, adjoining the Red Sea, in spite of warnings by the UN that the port's destruction would serve as a “crossing of Rubicon” moment. Basically, it was a point of no return as it would be impossible to avert massive loss of life due to the famine conditions that would ensue due to the disastrous effects on the shipping of food supplies.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;In August 2019, there was a rift in Southern Yemen between the government forces backed by the Saudi government and the Southern Transitional Council (STC) which enjoyed UAE support. Following the failure of the Kuwait initiative seeking a political solution, the 2019 Riyadh agreement was brokered as a power-sharing deal between the Yemeni government and the Southern separatists aimed at transcending this difference between the friends turned foes. However, the conflict resumed on January 7, 2020, when the Houthi rebels shot down a Saudi coalition drone at Jawf.&amp;nbsp; Following the COVID-19 outbreak, an air raid ceasefire had been declared while 10,000 people had been displaced, and 13 million civilians denied access to clean and safe drinking water. Yemen had previously faced a cholera epidemic in 2017 affecting 20 out of the 22 Yemeni provinces. As of July 2020, the UNHCR estimated that 3.6 million people had been displaced and 24 million await urgent aid. Geopolitical ramifications&amp;nbsp; The civil war has been at the heart of a much larger international political equation. Despite the fact that United States spokesperson Bernadette Meehan has openly stated: “It remains our assessment that Iran does not exert command and control over the Houthis in Yemen”, many have viewed this as a larger Iranian proxy war. Iran and Yemen are composed of Shia Islamist, albeit with minor differences - the Iranians are followers of the Twelve Imam Shias while the Houthis are Zaidi Shias. This is in contrast to the Saudi Arabia-led coalition that largely comprises Sunni-majority nations. Ali Khamenei has even explicitly stated that he shall provide “spiritual support&quot; to the movement of the Houthis in 2019. Eritrea too has been accused of providing Iranian ammunition to the Houthis.&amp;nbsp; The Yemeni government on the other hand has received military as well as financial aid from the United States, which conducted drone strikes in Sana’a aiming to neutralise Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP). Reports published by Amnesty International in 2019 also indicate logistical assistance from the UK in the form of laser-guided bombs and other weaponry. Interestingly, the US Arms Export Control Act was believed to have been violated by the United States Department while ratifying arms sales to the Gulf states of Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates in August 2020.&amp;nbsp; The launch of the ballistic missile by Houthis aimed at Saudi Arabia in 2017 led to a further strengthening of the Yemen blockade by the Saudi coalition under the pretext of preventing weapon smuggling by Iranian rebels, an accusation Tehran vehemently denies. In hindsight, this led to a hike in the price of food and fuel, adding a food security dimension to the military conflict.&amp;nbsp; The way forward Yemen continues to suffer from the world's worst humanitarian crisis. The crisis is not only a concern to the Middle Eastern neighbours of Yemen but fuels the threat perception pertaining to that of the West's War on Terror against terrorism at large, particularly Al-Qaeda and ISIS. Yemen enjoys superior strategic significance, located as it is geographically on the strait linking the Red Sea with the Gulf of Aden which constitutes the zone from which most of the world's oil cargo travels. Many had blamed Saudi Arabia for its lack of security provisions on the day of the Aden airport blast, yet this might be considered as the tip of the iceberg of a deep-seated problem concerning the 'unity government.' What needs to be understood is that in more ways than one, Yemen has become a pawn in the clutches of the broader strategic dynamics of the Arab world and Uncle Sam’s War on Terror.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Intangible Behind the Pink</title><link href="/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Intangible Behind the Pink" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink">&lt;p&gt;Lydia Michaels in her book, &lt;em&gt;La Vie En Rose: Life in Pink&lt;/em&gt;, gives readers Emma Sanders, a seemingly ordinary girl who wound up being the strongest woman Riley Lockhart (the protagonist, if you may) had ever known. Below is an excerpt from the erotic, intellectual, and haunting journey of the deceptive pink bow that shines on its cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Emma shut her laptop and scowled at them. “I’m pink.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She wasn’t sure when her opinion of the colour changed or why, but she now took offence to outsiders putting down the pink as much as she took offence to corporations abusing the colour. What she once criticized she now understood. Despite all the exploitation, there was something intangible behind the pink, a sense of connectedness, and she wanted to embrace that camaraderie.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am certain that pink reminded her of her love for dance. The innocence of being young. Tutus. Strawberry frosting on a vanilla cake. And lipstick (I bet she loves a good lipstick). Perhaps, it reminds her that she should take pride in her feminine traits, in being a woman. There is nothing remotely wrong with enjoying femininity. Curves. Hips. Lips. Empathy. Vulnerability. Sensuality. Patience. Intuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knew capitalists would take her intangible behind the pink quite so literally. Have you ever wondered why there exists a price difference for male and female shoppers’ while buying similar products? Masculine products come in dark-coloured packages while female products come in packages of pink and purple, coated with fruity and floral fragrance. And while colour and scent are the notable elements that distinguish one from the other, there is another yet indistinct facet that is costing those who buy women-based products more – the infamous “pink tax”&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;pink tax&lt;/strong&gt;, also known as an episode of gender-based price discrimination, is an invisible cost that women have to pay for products and services designed for them, while the male constituent of the same is priced less, more often than not.&amp;nbsp;There is a rambling tendency for products marketed specifically toward women to be pricier than those marketed for men, despite either gender's preference to purchase either product. And this tax is not confined to the wealthiest nations of the world, women in developing nations too pay a higher price for feminine products.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Weiss-Wolf, a lawyer, Vice President for the Brennan School of Justice at NYU School of Law, and co-founder of Period Equity says that from a technical standpoint, it isn’t really a tax, rather an income-generating scenario for private corporations who found a money minting technique. Part of the reason why products that are considered ‘pink’ are priced more is that society typically places women to a higher standard when it comes to appearance, providing big business houses with a window of opportunity to push women from all backgrounds to spend more on their appearance. Then, pricing products higher becomes part of the marketing strategy and companies are happy to rake in a bit more from women. So, razors for women cost more than the razors for men. And just because they &lt;em&gt;can &lt;/em&gt;explicitly make money off of pink tax, they think that they should, a classic capital stance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pink tax coupled with wage discrimination makes even basic hygiene products for women unaffordable. The Consumer Reports of California, Florida, Connecticut and South Dakota reveal that women pay as much as 50% more than men do for similar products. However, women and men are not even completely aware of the existence of a pink tax or gender tax. In a survey conducted with a small sample size in the age group of 18-25, 67% of the respondents had never heard either of the terms.&amp;nbsp;However, interestingly, 93%&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;of the respondents felt that similar consumer products were charged at a higher price for women than for&amp;nbsp;men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Surbhi Singh, a practising gynaecologist and founder and president of the menstrual awareness NGO 'Sacchi Saheli', says that in general, most of our choices in life are determined by marketing and advertising. With this in mind, we are drawn towards products that are marketed to make us feel prettier or fairer, etc. For this, women certainly pay the “extra price”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fashion industry, a matrix to look into is the bridal segment. Retailers and designers lay a great deal of emphasis on the bridal apparel or jewellery or all those accessories that go into making a bride (like Emma Sanders), versus all those that go into making a groom (like Riley Lockhart). There is clearly an extensive disparity. A chunk of it is certainly developed by branding, marketing and a push from the marketers; rest is gender stereotyping. A study on shoppers and their buying habits vouchsafed that women consumers are more at the mercy of this kind of marketing because it appeals to their ‘lower’ self-esteem and self-pride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2018, Mrs Indra Nooyi, the then chief executive of PepsiCo went over the board with ‘Lady’ Doritos in a podcast. The masses didn’t take it well, obviously. Mrs Nooyi told the interviewer that women did not eat Doritos the same way men did. “They don’t like to crunch too loudly in public,” she said. “And they don’t lick their fingers generously, and they don’t like to pour the little broken pieces and the flavouring into their mouth.” She further suggested that “snacks for women can be designed and packaged differently,” or in other words, PepsiCo was planning “a male and female version of chips.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women want equal pay for equal work and an end to sex discrimination in the workplace, and all our society has to offer is a bag of Lady Doritos so they won’t have to crunch too loudly in front of their male colleagues. What most people believed and I’m sure still would, if Lady Doritos actually becomes a thing, is that Lady Doritos are just regular Doritos but when a woman buys a bag, she only gets 70% of the chips a guy would. Funny how mysteriously our pink tax finds its way to things as ordinary as a packet of chips.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet gender tax is not an issue that infuriates women, even educated and gender-sensitive ones. Gender tax would be visible, perhaps, if we all knew that it exists. However, consumers are getting aware of it gradually. And hence, strategies and policies are bound to change in future. Companies like Burger King have staged their campaign against pink pricing. Hopefully, a time shall come where women may not have to pay more for products just because they are considered pink or feminine. If we think about the enduring and complex history of the color pink, it was considered masculine by virtue of being a diminutive of red, before it was considered girlish or feminine. It wasn’t until the 19th century, that it became coded as female, while blue became an indicator of masculinity. Perhaps, the problem that we’re trying to solve would ask us, society as a whole, to change the very definition of what does and doesn’t qualify as a gender specific notion, &lt;em&gt;vox populi&lt;/em&gt;. And a lot of work needs to be done to make it happen but as Lily Pulitzer, one of the greatest American fashion designers, says, &lt;em&gt;“anything is possible with sunshine and a little pink”&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anjali Harjani</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Lydia Michaels in her book, La Vie En Rose: Life in Pink, gives readers Emma Sanders, a seemingly ordinary girl who wound up being the strongest woman Riley Lockhart (the protagonist, if you may) had ever known. Below is an excerpt from the erotic, intellectual, and haunting journey of the deceptive pink bow that shines on its cover. 'Emma shut her laptop and scowled at them. “I’m pink.” She wasn’t sure when her opinion of the colour changed or why, but she now took offence to outsiders putting down the pink as much as she took offence to corporations abusing the colour. What she once criticized she now understood. Despite all the exploitation, there was something intangible behind the pink, a sense of connectedness, and she wanted to embrace that camaraderie.” I am certain that pink reminded her of her love for dance. The innocence of being young. Tutus. Strawberry frosting on a vanilla cake. And lipstick (I bet she loves a good lipstick). Perhaps, it reminds her that she should take pride in her feminine traits, in being a woman. There is nothing remotely wrong with enjoying femininity. Curves. Hips. Lips. Empathy. Vulnerability. Sensuality. Patience. Intuition. Who knew capitalists would take her intangible behind the pink quite so literally. Have you ever wondered why there exists a price difference for male and female shoppers’ while buying similar products? Masculine products come in dark-coloured packages while female products come in packages of pink and purple, coated with fruity and floral fragrance. And while colour and scent are the notable elements that distinguish one from the other, there is another yet indistinct facet that is costing those who buy women-based products more – the infamous “pink tax”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The&amp;nbsp;pink tax, also known as an episode of gender-based price discrimination, is an invisible cost that women have to pay for products and services designed for them, while the male constituent of the same is priced less, more often than not.&amp;nbsp;There is a rambling tendency for products marketed specifically toward women to be pricier than those marketed for men, despite either gender's preference to purchase either product. And this tax is not confined to the wealthiest nations of the world, women in developing nations too pay a higher price for feminine products.&amp;nbsp; Jennifer Weiss-Wolf, a lawyer, Vice President for the Brennan School of Justice at NYU School of Law, and co-founder of Period Equity says that from a technical standpoint, it isn’t really a tax, rather an income-generating scenario for private corporations who found a money minting technique. Part of the reason why products that are considered ‘pink’ are priced more is that society typically places women to a higher standard when it comes to appearance, providing big business houses with a window of opportunity to push women from all backgrounds to spend more on their appearance. Then, pricing products higher becomes part of the marketing strategy and companies are happy to rake in a bit more from women. So, razors for women cost more than the razors for men. And just because they can explicitly make money off of pink tax, they think that they should, a classic capital stance. Pink tax coupled with wage discrimination makes even basic hygiene products for women unaffordable. The Consumer Reports of California, Florida, Connecticut and South Dakota reveal that women pay as much as 50% more than men do for similar products. However, women and men are not even completely aware of the existence of a pink tax or gender tax. In a survey conducted with a small sample size in the age group of 18-25, 67% of the respondents had never heard either of the terms.&amp;nbsp;However, interestingly, 93% of the respondents felt that similar consumer products were charged at a higher price for women than for&amp;nbsp;men.&amp;nbsp; Dr Surbhi Singh, a practising gynaecologist and founder and president of the menstrual awareness NGO 'Sacchi Saheli', says that in general, most of our choices in life are determined by marketing and advertising. With this in mind, we are drawn towards products that are marketed to make us feel prettier or fairer, etc. For this, women certainly pay the “extra price”.&amp;nbsp; In the fashion industry, a matrix to look into is the bridal segment. Retailers and designers lay a great deal of emphasis on the bridal apparel or jewellery or all those accessories that go into making a bride (like Emma Sanders), versus all those that go into making a groom (like Riley Lockhart). There is clearly an extensive disparity. A chunk of it is certainly developed by branding, marketing and a push from the marketers; rest is gender stereotyping. A study on shoppers and their buying habits vouchsafed that women consumers are more at the mercy of this kind of marketing because it appeals to their ‘lower’ self-esteem and self-pride. Back in 2018, Mrs Indra Nooyi, the then chief executive of PepsiCo went over the board with ‘Lady’ Doritos in a podcast. The masses didn’t take it well, obviously. Mrs Nooyi told the interviewer that women did not eat Doritos the same way men did. “They don’t like to crunch too loudly in public,” she said. “And they don’t lick their fingers generously, and they don’t like to pour the little broken pieces and the flavouring into their mouth.” She further suggested that “snacks for women can be designed and packaged differently,” or in other words, PepsiCo was planning “a male and female version of chips.” Women want equal pay for equal work and an end to sex discrimination in the workplace, and all our society has to offer is a bag of Lady Doritos so they won’t have to crunch too loudly in front of their male colleagues. What most people believed and I’m sure still would, if Lady Doritos actually becomes a thing, is that Lady Doritos are just regular Doritos but when a woman buys a bag, she only gets 70% of the chips a guy would. Funny how mysteriously our pink tax finds its way to things as ordinary as a packet of chips.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; And yet gender tax is not an issue that infuriates women, even educated and gender-sensitive ones. Gender tax would be visible, perhaps, if we all knew that it exists. However, consumers are getting aware of it gradually. And hence, strategies and policies are bound to change in future. Companies like Burger King have staged their campaign against pink pricing. Hopefully, a time shall come where women may not have to pay more for products just because they are considered pink or feminine. If we think about the enduring and complex history of the color pink, it was considered masculine by virtue of being a diminutive of red, before it was considered girlish or feminine. It wasn’t until the 19th century, that it became coded as female, while blue became an indicator of masculinity. Perhaps, the problem that we’re trying to solve would ask us, society as a whole, to change the very definition of what does and doesn’t qualify as a gender specific notion, vox populi. And a lot of work needs to be done to make it happen but as Lily Pulitzer, one of the greatest American fashion designers, says, “anything is possible with sunshine and a little pink”.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper</title><link href="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 5: Connecting the Dots&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “&lt;em&gt;it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge&lt;/em&gt;.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samakshi Garg</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp; Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp; Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp; With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp; Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people. The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes. Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp; Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp; Part 5: Connecting the Dots Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp; Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive. Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sign the Deal and Bob’s your Uncle!</title><link href="/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sign the Deal and Bob’s your Uncle!" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle">&lt;p&gt;The tortuous ordeal of Britain’s divorce from the European Union finally came to a rather anticlimactic conclusion on January 24, 2020. Teetering from the raging pandemic on shaky ground, Britain will now have to learn to navigate the tumultuous seas of global trade, defence and foreign alliances without the backing of 27 European nations. The journey forward is difficult. Leadership suffers from a lack of confidence. There is a lot that could go wrong, but there are things to look forward too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and the resulting double-dip recession, triggered Britain’s scepticism of the European Union. But their reasons for holding a referendum for Brexit were largely entrenched in the anti-immigrant sentiments and “burdensome” economic regulations. While the new deal may assuage the fear of many Brits of “immigrants from the European countries stealing their jobs,” Britain’s quest to leave behind the troublesome and meddling economic regulations may cause a slightly bigger problem.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a positive note, this is an opportunity for Britain to redefine its role in the global arena. International leadership is undergoing a major structural change. The United States of America has replaced their 74-year-old President with a 78 year old one although this one is far-more saner and far-less fascist. China is becoming a dangerous superpower. An increasing number of Scandinavian and European nations are formulating plans to become clean-energy spaces with zero fossil fuel usage.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain can choose to redefine itself. It holds a prominent position on the negotiation table when it comes to defence and trade. It has a permanent position in the defence and security tables in the form of its position in the United Nations Security Council and membership of North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.&amp;nbsp; Britain would be chairing the G7 summit in 2021 and consequently has an opportunity to shape trade and defence policies to its advantage. However, with the current leadership and an overwhelming public distrust because of COVID-19, there is a bleak possibility of the aforementioned. Britain has also suffered from a blow to its reputation in the international arena because of its poor response to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada has not been a fan of Boris Johnson’s friendship with Donald Trump, and it would not be looked upon favourably by the Biden administration either. Considering the broken ties with the EU members, the UK better make plans for mending the bridges with these two immediate neighbours. Britain can use this time to build stronger alliances with Asian countries. India, China and now Bangladesh are becoming active participants in global trade and security. It would be beneficial for Britain to look for alternate market channels because the likelihood of the EU countries looking favourably upon trade from Britain is very low. Alternatively, trade with the EU was a major source of income for Britain, and they would need to move fast to fill the gaping hole left from Brexit. However, Boris Johnson’s cancellation of his visit to India as the chief guest for India's Republic Day celebration marks an inauspicious start to their decision to build a stronger alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calls for a united Ireland and Scottish independence have also been making waves in Britain. This has been a contentious issue for Britain for a long time. The possibility of rising waves of separatist movements in the midst of Britain’s shaky future in the global sphere is not a situation that Britain could possibly endure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal signed has left Britain and the EU worse off, though it did its best to leave Britain the worst off. British citizens lost more than just their right to live and work in 27 European countries. British goods would now face tariffs and restrictions at EU borders, and the deal has not managed to finalise negotiations for foreign policy, external security and defence. Foreign investors fear an economic decline and their confidence has been an all-time low, consequently foreign investments have dropped. The only sweet spot in this deal has been Britain’s success in securing a greater portion of fishes in the UK waters.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The small traders and business owners in the UK would suffer the most. They were the worst affected by the lockdown and the COVID-19 pandemic. The Brexit deal would ensure they lose the market channels and international avenues for trade and a major chunk of their profits. While the members of the EU would too lose access to British markets, they would still have the remaining 27 member countries to satisfy themselves with. Unsurprisingly, British citizens are unhappy with the government’s inability to negotiate a profitable deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major source of income for Britain is the influx of foreign students. The year-long pandemic and now the new strain of COVID-19 has already resulted in substantial loss of revenue for the country. Universities fear that this scenario, compounded by the anti-immigrant sentiments that triggered Brexit in the first place and the on-going global recession would be the catalyst for a downward spiral of the British economy. The offer for a two-year tier-4 work visa is a step in the right direction. Hopefully, this would incentivise students from abroad, and the year 2021 would revive the revenue influx.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain now has to determine the path that it would take regarding the pandemic, foreign policy, security, defence and international development. It needs to formulate plans to revive the demand for domestic goods and investor confidence. The political and public dissatisfaction and a weakening social fabric of the country await the current government. The economy is slowing and the growth trajectory is moving south. The list is long. The stakes are high. Britain has more to lose than just economic prosperity. Political turmoil, a changing social fabric, and safe transitions should also be on the British government’s vision for 2021. No one would want to be in Boris Johnsons’s shoes right now, but perhaps the citizens of Britain would be more sympathetic to his plight, had he not been the orchestrator of this terrible political opera.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The tortuous ordeal of Britain’s divorce from the European Union finally came to a rather anticlimactic conclusion on January 24, 2020. Teetering from the raging pandemic on shaky ground, Britain will now have to learn to navigate the tumultuous seas of global trade, defence and foreign alliances without the backing of 27 European nations. The journey forward is difficult. Leadership suffers from a lack of confidence. There is a lot that could go wrong, but there are things to look forward too.&amp;nbsp; The aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and the resulting double-dip recession, triggered Britain’s scepticism of the European Union. But their reasons for holding a referendum for Brexit were largely entrenched in the anti-immigrant sentiments and “burdensome” economic regulations. While the new deal may assuage the fear of many Brits of “immigrants from the European countries stealing their jobs,” Britain’s quest to leave behind the troublesome and meddling economic regulations may cause a slightly bigger problem.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; On a positive note, this is an opportunity for Britain to redefine its role in the global arena. International leadership is undergoing a major structural change. The United States of America has replaced their 74-year-old President with a 78 year old one although this one is far-more saner and far-less fascist. China is becoming a dangerous superpower. An increasing number of Scandinavian and European nations are formulating plans to become clean-energy spaces with zero fossil fuel usage.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Britain can choose to redefine itself. It holds a prominent position on the negotiation table when it comes to defence and trade. It has a permanent position in the defence and security tables in the form of its position in the United Nations Security Council and membership of North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.&amp;nbsp; Britain would be chairing the G7 summit in 2021 and consequently has an opportunity to shape trade and defence policies to its advantage. However, with the current leadership and an overwhelming public distrust because of COVID-19, there is a bleak possibility of the aforementioned. Britain has also suffered from a blow to its reputation in the international arena because of its poor response to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Canada has not been a fan of Boris Johnson’s friendship with Donald Trump, and it would not be looked upon favourably by the Biden administration either. Considering the broken ties with the EU members, the UK better make plans for mending the bridges with these two immediate neighbours. Britain can use this time to build stronger alliances with Asian countries. India, China and now Bangladesh are becoming active participants in global trade and security. It would be beneficial for Britain to look for alternate market channels because the likelihood of the EU countries looking favourably upon trade from Britain is very low. Alternatively, trade with the EU was a major source of income for Britain, and they would need to move fast to fill the gaping hole left from Brexit. However, Boris Johnson’s cancellation of his visit to India as the chief guest for India's Republic Day celebration marks an inauspicious start to their decision to build a stronger alliance. Calls for a united Ireland and Scottish independence have also been making waves in Britain. This has been a contentious issue for Britain for a long time. The possibility of rising waves of separatist movements in the midst of Britain’s shaky future in the global sphere is not a situation that Britain could possibly endure.&amp;nbsp; The deal signed has left Britain and the EU worse off, though it did its best to leave Britain the worst off. British citizens lost more than just their right to live and work in 27 European countries. British goods would now face tariffs and restrictions at EU borders, and the deal has not managed to finalise negotiations for foreign policy, external security and defence. Foreign investors fear an economic decline and their confidence has been an all-time low, consequently foreign investments have dropped. The only sweet spot in this deal has been Britain’s success in securing a greater portion of fishes in the UK waters.&amp;nbsp; The small traders and business owners in the UK would suffer the most. They were the worst affected by the lockdown and the COVID-19 pandemic. The Brexit deal would ensure they lose the market channels and international avenues for trade and a major chunk of their profits. While the members of the EU would too lose access to British markets, they would still have the remaining 27 member countries to satisfy themselves with. Unsurprisingly, British citizens are unhappy with the government’s inability to negotiate a profitable deal. Another major source of income for Britain is the influx of foreign students. The year-long pandemic and now the new strain of COVID-19 has already resulted in substantial loss of revenue for the country. Universities fear that this scenario, compounded by the anti-immigrant sentiments that triggered Brexit in the first place and the on-going global recession would be the catalyst for a downward spiral of the British economy. The offer for a two-year tier-4 work visa is a step in the right direction. Hopefully, this would incentivise students from abroad, and the year 2021 would revive the revenue influx.&amp;nbsp; Britain now has to determine the path that it would take regarding the pandemic, foreign policy, security, defence and international development. It needs to formulate plans to revive the demand for domestic goods and investor confidence. The political and public dissatisfaction and a weakening social fabric of the country await the current government. The economy is slowing and the growth trajectory is moving south. The list is long. The stakes are high. Britain has more to lose than just economic prosperity. Political turmoil, a changing social fabric, and safe transitions should also be on the British government’s vision for 2021. No one would want to be in Boris Johnsons’s shoes right now, but perhaps the citizens of Britain would be more sympathetic to his plight, had he not been the orchestrator of this terrible political opera.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Big Daddy’s Gamble: the Indian Securities Regulator Challenges India’s Oligarch</title><link href="/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Daddy’s Gamble: the Indian Securities Regulator Challenges India's Oligarch" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch">&lt;p&gt;On January 1, 2021, the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) slapped a fine on the largest company in India by market capitalisation, i.e. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), and its Chairman and Managing Director Mukesh Ambani of ₹250 million and ₹150 million respectively, along with two other entities, for manipulative trading in the shares of the erstwhile Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what activity did RIL engage in to receive a penalty from the market regulator?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) was a refinery, partly owned by RIL, which later got merged with the latter in 2009. However, the conglomerate got itself under the radar of the watchdog for the transaction that occurred between the company and its agents in November, 2007, in the cash and futures segment of the secondary market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RIL had decided to sell off its 4.1% stake in RPL. According to SEBI, in order to make undue gains from the sale, the former had entered into an agreement with 12 agents, who booked large short positions of the refinery’s shares in the futures market. Short positions refer to a situation when a trader sells the security first with the intention of repurchasing it later at a lower price, hence the steeper the decline, greater is the profit for the trader. Following this, in the last ten minutes of the trading session of November 29, 2007, RIL sold close to 20 million RPL shares. This large scale selling triggered mass panic and within a moment’s notice, the stock price collapsed.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, it also happened to be the same day that the futures contracts were meant to pay-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, SEBI contends that RIL and the agents colluded together in a bid to make a profit estimated to be around ₹44.7 billion off of this transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selling of securities by promoters in the capital markets in order to raise cash is a widely accepted practice, however, this act of secretive plotting that can distort the natural price discovery system in the market and cheat investors via non-transparent mechanisms is impermissible and against the objectives of the SEBI or any securities regulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEBI’s adjudicating officer B J Dilip said, “&lt;em&gt;any manipulation in the volume or price of securities always erodes investor confidence in the market when investors find themselves at the receiving end of market manipulators&lt;/em&gt;.” He further added, “&lt;em&gt;In the instant case, the general investors were not aware that the entity behind the above F&amp;amp;O segment transactions was RIL. The execution of the... fraudulent trades affected the price of the RPL securities in both cash and F&amp;amp;O [Futures and Options] segments and harmed the interests of other investors&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SEBI order states that Mukesh Ambani as the Managing Director of RIL was equally involved in the malpractice. Apart from the conglomerate and its chairman, SEBI also imposed penalties of ₹2 million and ₹1 million on Navi Mumbai SEZ Pvt Ltd and Mumbai SEZ Ltd respectively, both promoted by Anand Jain, a former member of the Reliance Group, for providing margin payments for the agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2017, the market watchdog had ordered RIL and other entities to disgorge ₹4.47 billion in the RPL’s case, against which the latter appealed in the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT). The verdict announced by the tribunal in November 2020 was against the appellant. However, the petrochemicals to telecommunication multinational corporation said that it would appeal against the Tribunal’s ruling in the Indian Supreme Court.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time that RIL and a government entity were at loggerheads. In 2014, the Indian market regulator had imposed a fine of ₹1.3 million on the corporation for non-disclosure of a key earnings ratio, which would have impacted investors’ evaluation on the shares. In 2018, the RIL-led consortium of BP Plc and Niko Resources won an award against the Indian government in international arbitration. The case related to a dispute over a penalty of $1.55 billion slapped by the Indian government on the petrochemical companies for allegedly drawing gas from the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation or ONGC’s (a state-owned oil and gas concern) block in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEBI was established with the purpose of protecting investors and the development and regulation of capital markets in India. Over the years, it has evolved to meet its objective and has always taken a strong stance against any form of malpractice. However, it is essential that in order to mitigate any future wrongdoing, it penalises defaulters such that cost in fulfilling the punishment supersedes the gain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">On January 1, 2021, the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) slapped a fine on the largest company in India by market capitalisation, i.e. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), and its Chairman and Managing Director Mukesh Ambani of ₹250 million and ₹150 million respectively, along with two other entities, for manipulative trading in the shares of the erstwhile Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) in 2007. So, what activity did RIL engage in to receive a penalty from the market regulator?&amp;nbsp; Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) was a refinery, partly owned by RIL, which later got merged with the latter in 2009. However, the conglomerate got itself under the radar of the watchdog for the transaction that occurred between the company and its agents in November, 2007, in the cash and futures segment of the secondary market. RIL had decided to sell off its 4.1% stake in RPL. According to SEBI, in order to make undue gains from the sale, the former had entered into an agreement with 12 agents, who booked large short positions of the refinery’s shares in the futures market. Short positions refer to a situation when a trader sells the security first with the intention of repurchasing it later at a lower price, hence the steeper the decline, greater is the profit for the trader. Following this, in the last ten minutes of the trading session of November 29, 2007, RIL sold close to 20 million RPL shares. This large scale selling triggered mass panic and within a moment’s notice, the stock price collapsed.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, it also happened to be the same day that the futures contracts were meant to pay-out. So, SEBI contends that RIL and the agents colluded together in a bid to make a profit estimated to be around ₹44.7 billion off of this transaction. Selling of securities by promoters in the capital markets in order to raise cash is a widely accepted practice, however, this act of secretive plotting that can distort the natural price discovery system in the market and cheat investors via non-transparent mechanisms is impermissible and against the objectives of the SEBI or any securities regulator. SEBI’s adjudicating officer B J Dilip said, “any manipulation in the volume or price of securities always erodes investor confidence in the market when investors find themselves at the receiving end of market manipulators.” He further added, “In the instant case, the general investors were not aware that the entity behind the above F&amp;amp;O segment transactions was RIL. The execution of the... fraudulent trades affected the price of the RPL securities in both cash and F&amp;amp;O [Futures and Options] segments and harmed the interests of other investors.” The SEBI order states that Mukesh Ambani as the Managing Director of RIL was equally involved in the malpractice. Apart from the conglomerate and its chairman, SEBI also imposed penalties of ₹2 million and ₹1 million on Navi Mumbai SEZ Pvt Ltd and Mumbai SEZ Ltd respectively, both promoted by Anand Jain, a former member of the Reliance Group, for providing margin payments for the agents. In March 2017, the market watchdog had ordered RIL and other entities to disgorge ₹4.47 billion in the RPL’s case, against which the latter appealed in the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT). The verdict announced by the tribunal in November 2020 was against the appellant. However, the petrochemicals to telecommunication multinational corporation said that it would appeal against the Tribunal’s ruling in the Indian Supreme Court.&amp;nbsp; This is not the first time that RIL and a government entity were at loggerheads. In 2014, the Indian market regulator had imposed a fine of ₹1.3 million on the corporation for non-disclosure of a key earnings ratio, which would have impacted investors’ evaluation on the shares. In 2018, the RIL-led consortium of BP Plc and Niko Resources won an award against the Indian government in international arbitration. The case related to a dispute over a penalty of $1.55 billion slapped by the Indian government on the petrochemical companies for allegedly drawing gas from the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation or ONGC’s (a state-owned oil and gas concern) block in 2016. SEBI was established with the purpose of protecting investors and the development and regulation of capital markets in India. Over the years, it has evolved to meet its objective and has always taken a strong stance against any form of malpractice. However, it is essential that in order to mitigate any future wrongdoing, it penalises defaulters such that cost in fulfilling the punishment supersedes the gain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ditching the Donald</title><link href="/Ditching-the-Donald" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ditching the Donald" /><published>2021-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Ditching-the-Donald</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Ditching-the-Donald">&lt;p&gt;Joe Biden is getting ready for the day he has waited for his entire life. Whilst there’s plenty about his politics which is easy to dislike, I can’t help but admire Biden’s resilience. I also have to commend him for finally putting an end to the round-the-clock coverage of the man he will replace as president on January 20. With every passing day, Donald Trump looks more and more like yesterday’s man. But the more he fades into the background, the harder the 45th President tries to stay centre-stage. Luckily, a substantial part of the Republican Party is distancing itself from Trump. Others, though, are sticking by him. This is a mistake; the time has come to banish Trump from politics altogether.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even on Republican’s own terms, Trump hasn’t been a good President. The Tea Party railed non-stop against irresponsible government spending for Obama’s two terms in the White House. And yet, almost as soon as Trump was inaugurated in 2017, demands for fiscal responsibility fell on deaf ears. The new President engineered a large tax cut at the end of his first year in office, increased spending, and, even with a united Republican Congress behind him, chickened out of pursuing much-needed welfare reform. The collective result of this was that even before COVID-19, the US government deficit was running at nearly 5% of the GDP. The lockdowns caused this figure to rise inexorably, and Trump’s reckless spending for the three years previous meant that the US had less fiscal headroom to deal with the worst crisis since the War than it might have liked. At the end of the worst economic year on record, Trump’s “tremendous” pre-pandemic economy, built on little but cheap borrowing, feels like a bad joke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, there is the endless damage that Trump has done to American culture. Conservatives ostensibly don’t like society to run at a constant fever pitch. There is not a single instance, however, of Trump lowering the tempo of a disagreement in American politics since he first sought the Presidency in 2015. He has run head-first into every facet of the culture war, utterly unaware of his responsibility to lead, console, and unify. Republicans always claimed they wanted to get the government out of people’s lives. Trump hasn’t got out of the way but hangs over every dinner table with the subtlety of a car alarm at four in the morning. A virus had infected American discourse long before any of us heard of COVID-19.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Republicans, the nail-in-the-coffin for Trump’s legacy should be that this endless culture-bashing has delivered a Democratic administration which is more left-wing than the one which left the White House in 2017. The problem with polarising the political space to the extent that Trump has is that everybody abandons the centre-ground. In response to Trump’s promise to build a wall along America’s border with Mexico, several Democrat presidential hopefuls called for the abolition of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, known as ICE. In 2019, Senator Kamala Harris, due to become Vice President in a little over a week, called for the government to decriminalise America’s borders; in essence, to eliminate altogether the distinction between legal and illegal immigration. There are few policy areas on which the Democratic party has not moved left in the past four years: this has been the case on immigration, clearly, but also on public spending, policing, healthcare and environmental regulations. Each of these leftward movements can, to a large extent, be traced back to Trump’s idiotic and misinformed remarks on a whole range of issues. Trump might have remoulded the Republicans in his own image, but he has gone a long way in transforming the Democrats too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More worrying still for Republicans is the fact that this new Democratic party may wield real power very soon. If the Democrats win the Georgia run-off (results are still being counted as I write this), then President-elect Biden will take office with a unified Democratic Congress behind him. Now that the sixty-vote ‘filibuster’ is used less and less, a simple Democrat majority in the Senate could be enough to see the new President enact substantial parts of his policy agenda. If Republicans didn’t like Barack Obama’s legislative programme, they would loathe Joe Biden’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they want to stop Biden in his tracks, the GOP cannot afford to spend the next four years giving credence to Donald Trump’s claims that the election was stolen from him, just as the Democrats wasted far too much time after 2016 looking for evidence that Trump colluded with Russia. Republicans need to focus on the issues at hand, rather than getting caught up in Trump’s ridiculous soap opera. The soon-to-be-former President’s phone call to Georgia’s Secretary of State demonstrates that Trump still hasn’t accepted his defeat, and provides Republicans with yet another reason to show him the door.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, whether the Republicans walk away from Donald Trump is only half the issue; an equally pertinent question to ask is whether Trump will walk away from them. There are already suggestions that the President is planning a third Presidential run in 2024. Republicans would do well to see this for the disaster that it is. Whilst Trump undeniably pulled off a remarkable victory in 2016, he proved himself to be an electoral liability twice thereafter; once at the mid-terms in 2018, and again a few weeks ago. At the same time, the Democrats showed that when they turn out their voters, they win big. They have built a multi-ethnic, multi-generational coalition larger than the one which their opponents have been able to cobble together. Republicans haven’t won the popular vote at a presidential election since 2004. Whether abandoning Trump&lt;em&gt;ism&lt;/em&gt; would help the Republicans find a more reliable formula for electoral success is a topic for another day. But, if the party is to return to the White House in 2024, it is becoming increasingly obvious that they shouldn’t gamble on Trump taking them there.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Joe Biden is getting ready for the day he has waited for his entire life. Whilst there’s plenty about his politics which is easy to dislike, I can’t help but admire Biden’s resilience. I also have to commend him for finally putting an end to the round-the-clock coverage of the man he will replace as president on January 20. With every passing day, Donald Trump looks more and more like yesterday’s man. But the more he fades into the background, the harder the 45th President tries to stay centre-stage. Luckily, a substantial part of the Republican Party is distancing itself from Trump. Others, though, are sticking by him. This is a mistake; the time has come to banish Trump from politics altogether.&amp;nbsp; Even on Republican’s own terms, Trump hasn’t been a good President. The Tea Party railed non-stop against irresponsible government spending for Obama’s two terms in the White House. And yet, almost as soon as Trump was inaugurated in 2017, demands for fiscal responsibility fell on deaf ears. The new President engineered a large tax cut at the end of his first year in office, increased spending, and, even with a united Republican Congress behind him, chickened out of pursuing much-needed welfare reform. The collective result of this was that even before COVID-19, the US government deficit was running at nearly 5% of the GDP. The lockdowns caused this figure to rise inexorably, and Trump’s reckless spending for the three years previous meant that the US had less fiscal headroom to deal with the worst crisis since the War than it might have liked. At the end of the worst economic year on record, Trump’s “tremendous” pre-pandemic economy, built on little but cheap borrowing, feels like a bad joke. Then, there is the endless damage that Trump has done to American culture. Conservatives ostensibly don’t like society to run at a constant fever pitch. There is not a single instance, however, of Trump lowering the tempo of a disagreement in American politics since he first sought the Presidency in 2015. He has run head-first into every facet of the culture war, utterly unaware of his responsibility to lead, console, and unify. Republicans always claimed they wanted to get the government out of people’s lives. Trump hasn’t got out of the way but hangs over every dinner table with the subtlety of a car alarm at four in the morning. A virus had infected American discourse long before any of us heard of COVID-19.&amp;nbsp; For Republicans, the nail-in-the-coffin for Trump’s legacy should be that this endless culture-bashing has delivered a Democratic administration which is more left-wing than the one which left the White House in 2017. The problem with polarising the political space to the extent that Trump has is that everybody abandons the centre-ground. In response to Trump’s promise to build a wall along America’s border with Mexico, several Democrat presidential hopefuls called for the abolition of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, known as ICE. In 2019, Senator Kamala Harris, due to become Vice President in a little over a week, called for the government to decriminalise America’s borders; in essence, to eliminate altogether the distinction between legal and illegal immigration. There are few policy areas on which the Democratic party has not moved left in the past four years: this has been the case on immigration, clearly, but also on public spending, policing, healthcare and environmental regulations. Each of these leftward movements can, to a large extent, be traced back to Trump’s idiotic and misinformed remarks on a whole range of issues. Trump might have remoulded the Republicans in his own image, but he has gone a long way in transforming the Democrats too.&amp;nbsp; More worrying still for Republicans is the fact that this new Democratic party may wield real power very soon. If the Democrats win the Georgia run-off (results are still being counted as I write this), then President-elect Biden will take office with a unified Democratic Congress behind him. Now that the sixty-vote ‘filibuster’ is used less and less, a simple Democrat majority in the Senate could be enough to see the new President enact substantial parts of his policy agenda. If Republicans didn’t like Barack Obama’s legislative programme, they would loathe Joe Biden’s.&amp;nbsp; If they want to stop Biden in his tracks, the GOP cannot afford to spend the next four years giving credence to Donald Trump’s claims that the election was stolen from him, just as the Democrats wasted far too much time after 2016 looking for evidence that Trump colluded with Russia. Republicans need to focus on the issues at hand, rather than getting caught up in Trump’s ridiculous soap opera. The soon-to-be-former President’s phone call to Georgia’s Secretary of State demonstrates that Trump still hasn’t accepted his defeat, and provides Republicans with yet another reason to show him the door.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Of course, whether the Republicans walk away from Donald Trump is only half the issue; an equally pertinent question to ask is whether Trump will walk away from them. There are already suggestions that the President is planning a third Presidential run in 2024. Republicans would do well to see this for the disaster that it is. Whilst Trump undeniably pulled off a remarkable victory in 2016, he proved himself to be an electoral liability twice thereafter; once at the mid-terms in 2018, and again a few weeks ago. At the same time, the Democrats showed that when they turn out their voters, they win big. They have built a multi-ethnic, multi-generational coalition larger than the one which their opponents have been able to cobble together. Republicans haven’t won the popular vote at a presidential election since 2004. Whether abandoning Trumpism would help the Republicans find a more reliable formula for electoral success is a topic for another day. But, if the party is to return to the White House in 2024, it is becoming increasingly obvious that they shouldn’t gamble on Trump taking them there.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The One Time You Shouldn’t Be Appropriate</title><link href="/The-One-Time-You-Shouldn-t-Be-Appropriate" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The One Time You Shouldn't Be Appropriate" /><published>2021-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-One-Time-You-Shouldn-t-Be-Appropriate</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-One-Time-You-Shouldn-t-Be-Appropriate">&lt;p&gt;Jack Skellington, uninspired, and in a rut, discovers Christmas Town, falls head over heels with a culture that is not his to begin with, does not talk to a single person who actually lives there, and thus fails to understand the significance of its elements, then goes on to falsify their image in order to appeal to a different audience, and despite their reluctance, decides that he, the Pumpkin King of Halloweentown, can in fact do Christmas better than Christmas Town. At which he fails. Spectacularly.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike what John Mulaney would say, we, dear readers, absolutely do have the time to unpack all of that.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Nightmare Before Christmas&lt;/em&gt; (1993) is an excellent conversation starter and explanation tool if you are completely new to the concept of cultural appropriation. The &lt;em&gt;Cambridge Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; defines cultural appropriation as “&lt;em&gt;the&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/act&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;of taking or using things from a&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/culture&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;culture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;that is not&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/your&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;own,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/especially&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;without&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/showing&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;showing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;that you&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/understand&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;or&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/respect&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;respect&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;the original&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/culture&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;culture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the story begins, Jack is shown disheartened with the usual Halloween festivities – as he leads the celebration each year, he privately grows weary of it. Thus, it is an extremely delightful experience for him when he discovers the even gates representing different festivals – and goes through the one leading to the Christmas Town. He discovers a brand new world, a different festival, and a wildly different way of living. Enthused, he takes back some of the things he likes (Christmas baubles, candy canes, etc.) in an attempt to understand what it was that made Christmas so magical. Notice how he doesn’t even try to talk to the residents of the town, who would have answered his questions in depth had he just thought to ask. The residents of Halloween Town are also confused, since without any context as to why things are done a certain way, all the Christmas elements can only be compared to what they already know, and do not come at par. As expected, Jack fails at understanding Christmas because even after the multiple experiments and equations back at his crib, he is, after all, using his egregiously narrow perspective to explain something totally out of his scope.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Jack can neither understand nor rationally explain Christmas to anyone – not even to himself, he simply decides that he is going to ‘improve Christmas’ as it is unfair that only Christmas Town gets to celebrate it. He tasks different citizens with jobs like ‘singing carols’, ‘preparing gifts’ and even ‘kidnapping Santa’ to make sure he is fully prepared to lead the festivities. Despite getting warned not to proceed, Jack goes on to botch the entire festival, ruin Christmas for the normal world, and as a return gift, gets shot out of the sky.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key fact about cultural appropriation that is missing from the above story is that it is always people of the dominant culture that appropriate the culture of the minorities. While Christmas is in no way a ‘minority culture’ – the &lt;em&gt;Nightmare before Christmas&lt;/em&gt; serves some excellent points in what not to do when taking inspiration from another culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is cultural appropriation a problem? What is so wrong in getting influenced by another culture, especially in a world where there is increased access to everything that exists on earth? The problem arises when the ‘influence’ and ‘inspiration’ is taken for the wrong reasons. When white musicians use music pioneered by black artists and make a killing off of it, when fashion houses host shows inspired by black culture but have only white people modelling for them, or when white people dress up as geishas or put tribal paint on for Halloween – that is when they cross the line from appreciation to appropriation. It is problematic when artists like Zendaya get ridiculed for wearing dreadlocks (which is a common hairstyle for people of African ethnicities) while white celebrities like many of the Kardashian – Jenners continue to do the same and garner millions of Instagram likes and shares despite significant backlash from the black community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an Indian, I am not new to watching my culture get appropriated for profit or aesthetic, even though every new instance in an apparently increasingly educated world does make me infuriated. Music festivals are a breeding ground for not just STDs, but also for blatant disrespect of ‘exotic’ cultures, as white people wear bindis, apply henna, or get dressed in the traditional garb of other cultures, all for the aesthetic. While doing the same in normal settings would lead to immense amounts of ridicule not to the white person, but to the Indian just trying to wear something common in their community. White people may profit hugely and be seen as ‘cool’ from doing the same things that people of colour have been doing since long. Even many K-pop artists have remorselessly appropriated different cultures – from randomly wearing dreadlocks in rap videos, to the girl group Blackpink most recently using a statue of the Hindu god Ganesha in an unrelated music video, no amount of fan led educational discourse seems to stop them in their tracks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cultural appropriation does more than harm the sentiments of the non-dominant community. It perpetuates offensive stereotypes, and may blind people to the true origins of the culture being appropriated. When Miley Cyrus famously twerked in her ‘We Can’t Stop’ music video – generations of people formed the misconception that it was she who had invented the dance move rather than African-American artists from New Orleans in the early 1990's. This kind of appropriation also opens the gate to fetishisation of concepts not meant to be sexual – the glaring popularity of ‘sexy kimono’ or ‘sexy geisha outfit’ searches during Halloween in America is a testament to this very fact. Kimono is the traditional dress of the Japanese woman, with a rich history that does not deserve to be reduced to a costume for an entitled brat. And geishas have a long history of being dignified artists and performers, not some sort of glorified sex workers. In fact, the entire premise of Halloween is based on appropriation– the people who most fervently celebrate it remain ignorant of its roots, using it as an excuse to wear costumes that degrade cultures different from them. The ancient Samhain tradition of wearing masks to scare away evil spirits has devolved into misogynistic and appropriative debauchery for the amusement of many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using elements of a different culture merely ‘for the aesthetic’ and because you apparently can’t think of something original – cultural appropriation is, in a nutshell, plagiarism of the oppressed. And in a world where Google can be opened on nearly any electronic device, there is no excuse for anyone to remain ignorant of the culture they are supposedly being inspired by.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swati Mathuria</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Jack Skellington, uninspired, and in a rut, discovers Christmas Town, falls head over heels with a culture that is not his to begin with, does not talk to a single person who actually lives there, and thus fails to understand the significance of its elements, then goes on to falsify their image in order to appeal to a different audience, and despite their reluctance, decides that he, the Pumpkin King of Halloweentown, can in fact do Christmas better than Christmas Town. At which he fails. Spectacularly.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Unlike what John Mulaney would say, we, dear readers, absolutely do have the time to unpack all of that.&amp;nbsp; The Nightmare Before Christmas (1993) is an excellent conversation starter and explanation tool if you are completely new to the concept of cultural appropriation. The Cambridge Dictionary defines cultural appropriation as “the&amp;nbsp;act&amp;nbsp;of taking or using things from a&amp;nbsp;culture&amp;nbsp;that is not&amp;nbsp;your&amp;nbsp;own,&amp;nbsp;especially&amp;nbsp;without&amp;nbsp;showing&amp;nbsp;that you&amp;nbsp;understand&amp;nbsp;or&amp;nbsp;respect&amp;nbsp;the original&amp;nbsp;culture.” As the story begins, Jack is shown disheartened with the usual Halloween festivities – as he leads the celebration each year, he privately grows weary of it. Thus, it is an extremely delightful experience for him when he discovers the even gates representing different festivals – and goes through the one leading to the Christmas Town. He discovers a brand new world, a different festival, and a wildly different way of living. Enthused, he takes back some of the things he likes (Christmas baubles, candy canes, etc.) in an attempt to understand what it was that made Christmas so magical. Notice how he doesn’t even try to talk to the residents of the town, who would have answered his questions in depth had he just thought to ask. The residents of Halloween Town are also confused, since without any context as to why things are done a certain way, all the Christmas elements can only be compared to what they already know, and do not come at par. As expected, Jack fails at understanding Christmas because even after the multiple experiments and equations back at his crib, he is, after all, using his egregiously narrow perspective to explain something totally out of his scope.&amp;nbsp; When Jack can neither understand nor rationally explain Christmas to anyone – not even to himself, he simply decides that he is going to ‘improve Christmas’ as it is unfair that only Christmas Town gets to celebrate it. He tasks different citizens with jobs like ‘singing carols’, ‘preparing gifts’ and even ‘kidnapping Santa’ to make sure he is fully prepared to lead the festivities. Despite getting warned not to proceed, Jack goes on to botch the entire festival, ruin Christmas for the normal world, and as a return gift, gets shot out of the sky.&amp;nbsp; A key fact about cultural appropriation that is missing from the above story is that it is always people of the dominant culture that appropriate the culture of the minorities. While Christmas is in no way a ‘minority culture’ – the Nightmare before Christmas serves some excellent points in what not to do when taking inspiration from another culture.&amp;nbsp; Why is cultural appropriation a problem? What is so wrong in getting influenced by another culture, especially in a world where there is increased access to everything that exists on earth? The problem arises when the ‘influence’ and ‘inspiration’ is taken for the wrong reasons. When white musicians use music pioneered by black artists and make a killing off of it, when fashion houses host shows inspired by black culture but have only white people modelling for them, or when white people dress up as geishas or put tribal paint on for Halloween – that is when they cross the line from appreciation to appropriation. It is problematic when artists like Zendaya get ridiculed for wearing dreadlocks (which is a common hairstyle for people of African ethnicities) while white celebrities like many of the Kardashian – Jenners continue to do the same and garner millions of Instagram likes and shares despite significant backlash from the black community. As an Indian, I am not new to watching my culture get appropriated for profit or aesthetic, even though every new instance in an apparently increasingly educated world does make me infuriated. Music festivals are a breeding ground for not just STDs, but also for blatant disrespect of ‘exotic’ cultures, as white people wear bindis, apply henna, or get dressed in the traditional garb of other cultures, all for the aesthetic. While doing the same in normal settings would lead to immense amounts of ridicule not to the white person, but to the Indian just trying to wear something common in their community. White people may profit hugely and be seen as ‘cool’ from doing the same things that people of colour have been doing since long. Even many K-pop artists have remorselessly appropriated different cultures – from randomly wearing dreadlocks in rap videos, to the girl group Blackpink most recently using a statue of the Hindu god Ganesha in an unrelated music video, no amount of fan led educational discourse seems to stop them in their tracks.&amp;nbsp; Cultural appropriation does more than harm the sentiments of the non-dominant community. It perpetuates offensive stereotypes, and may blind people to the true origins of the culture being appropriated. When Miley Cyrus famously twerked in her ‘We Can’t Stop’ music video – generations of people formed the misconception that it was she who had invented the dance move rather than African-American artists from New Orleans in the early 1990's. This kind of appropriation also opens the gate to fetishisation of concepts not meant to be sexual – the glaring popularity of ‘sexy kimono’ or ‘sexy geisha outfit’ searches during Halloween in America is a testament to this very fact. Kimono is the traditional dress of the Japanese woman, with a rich history that does not deserve to be reduced to a costume for an entitled brat. And geishas have a long history of being dignified artists and performers, not some sort of glorified sex workers. In fact, the entire premise of Halloween is based on appropriation– the people who most fervently celebrate it remain ignorant of its roots, using it as an excuse to wear costumes that degrade cultures different from them. The ancient Samhain tradition of wearing masks to scare away evil spirits has devolved into misogynistic and appropriative debauchery for the amusement of many. Using elements of a different culture merely ‘for the aesthetic’ and because you apparently can’t think of something original – cultural appropriation is, in a nutshell, plagiarism of the oppressed. And in a world where Google can be opened on nearly any electronic device, there is no excuse for anyone to remain ignorant of the culture they are supposedly being inspired by.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Religious Conversions, Marriage, Love: A Conspiracy or a Valid Contract?</title><link href="/Religious-Conversions-Marriage-Love" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Religious Conversions, Marriage, Love: A Conspiracy or a Valid Contract?" /><published>2021-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Religious-Conversions-Marriage-Love</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Religious-Conversions-Marriage-Love">&lt;p&gt;On November 28, 2020, the Uttar Pradesh government in North India further entrenched ‘communalism by law’ in the state by activating the Uttar Pradesh Prohibition of Unlawful Conversion of Religious Ordinance, 2020. This Ordinance prohibits conversion from one religion to another by “misrepresentation, force, fraud, undue influence, coercion, allurement or marriage”. The stated goal of the law is to check “unlawful religious conversion” and “interfaith marriages with the sole intention of changing a girl’s religion”. It criminalises conversions in violation of the provisions of the law and punishes the guilty with a jail term of up to 10 years. The offences defined and stated in the Ordinance are cognisable and non-bailable. Many&amp;nbsp;BJP-ruled states have expressed an interest to legislate similar provisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this P Chidambaram, the former Indian Finance Minister, wrote that “&lt;em&gt;the ‘love jihad’ law is an onslaught on choice; on freedom; on privacy; on dignity; on the equality of man and woman; and on the right to love or live together or marry.&lt;/em&gt;” India’s journey since the implementation of this law has shown a trend where most experts are questioning the secular fabric of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The World Watch Monitor in one of its articles claimed&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;that the leaders of Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh (RSS), a militant Hindu nationalist group, has stated on national media that the&amp;nbsp;RSS will make India free of Christians and Muslims by December 31, 2021. One way it intends to do this is through forced ‘re-conversions’. Hundreds of Christians were forced to reconvert to Hinduism last year through intimidation and pressure&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article claimed that&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Despite being the world’s largest democracy, with a constitution that guarantees freedom of religion and belief, such extremism is thriving in India. Hindu nationalists see Hinduism as the true religion of India, so when an Indian ‘returns’ to Hinduism, it is not seen as a ‘conversion’ from another faith, but a ‘ghar wapsi’ or ‘homecoming’: so they are exempt from the anti-conversion laws.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian media have come under serious fire for not having extensively covered the issue. Nevertheless, in recent articles, some media platforms like &lt;em&gt;India Today&lt;/em&gt; examined the minute specifics of the law. At least 10 states have passed anti-conversion legislation in India in the past. Odisha, Madhya Pradesh, Arunachal Pradesh, Chhattisgarh, Gujarat, Himachal Pradesh, Rajasthan, Tamil Nadu and Jharkhand are among these states. In the case of Tamil Nadu, the law was repealed in 2004. In Rajasthan, the anti-conversion bill passed by the state legislature was returned by the Centre. Most of these laws ban religious conversion by force or allurement. At least four states have recently said they will come up with laws against 'love jihad', which requires conversion in a marriage. In February this year, the Centre had told Parliament 'love jihad' is not defined in any of the existing laws.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Madhya Pradesh Act was further amended in July 2020, providing that the district magistrate and the priest or organisation performing the conversion need to be informed by a person wishing to change his religion. The police would then verify the priest's credentials to ensure that this was not done by force or by seduction. Penal action provisions exist against priests/individuals who do not inform the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court, however, supported the laws saying, “&lt;em&gt;What is freedom for one is freedom for the other in equal measure and there can, therefore, be no such thing as a fundamental right to convert any person to one’s own religion&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saumya Saxena, in an article published by &lt;em&gt;The Wire&lt;/em&gt;, claims that&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;The Hindu Mahasabha and the RSS’ recent propaganda against 'love jihad' geared against religious marriage conversion may appear as an argument that favours the Special Marriage Act (which allows inter-religious marriage without conversion). However, in fact, with or without conversion, these organisations have traditionally opposed mixed marriages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The adoption of the Special Marriage Act is itself a tale of the suspicions of exogamy by India, its frustration with religious conversions, and remains one of the many surveillance mechanisms. The adoption of the Special Marriage Act in 1954 remains the closest legislation that can somewhat assert religious neutrality. Lok Sabha debates at the time of its enactment reveal that for many parliamentarians, the Act embedded secularism in the institution of marriage as a ‘freedom’ to love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Couples who marry without their parents' permission mostly opt for temple-weddings, Arya Samaj weddings, or weddings after Islamic conversion. Conversion has emerged in practice as the realistic way to cohabit as a couple, albeit far from ideal, in a country where neither inter-faith, inter-caste nor living-in couples can achieve societal acceptance. While the courts have settled the issue of fraud or bigamous marriages solemnised by abuse of religious conversion, propagandists would have us believe that if it were not for the temptations of Muslim personal rule, Hindu men would remain monogamous and Hindu women would still prefer endogamy without easy options to convert. However, marriage is only one of the planks used in opposition to religious conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are again facing a similar situation in which state governments are seeking to enact restrictive legislation to ban conversion, but targeted at another religious minority. But the danger of a national law curtailing religious freedom is now very real, and judicial independence to properly guard against this is diminishing now more than ever. The law will be camouflaged as a discussion on family law, on a uniform civil code, or on marriage fraud but will be guided, like much else in this regime has been, against minorities and against freedom, says Saxena in her bold critique.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issues with the law have caused sufficient unrest to which citizens continue to deliberate and react upon till date. A public interest petition filed very recently through advocates&amp;nbsp;Devesh Saxena, Shashwat Anand&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Vishesh Rajvanshi&amp;nbsp;contends that the Uttar Pradesh Ordinance is both morally and constitutionally repugnant. &quot;&lt;em&gt;The aforesaid ordinance requires every religious conversion to be scrutinised and certified by the state. The very concept of forcing an individual to explain and justify a decision, which is closely personal to him/her, before an officer of the State is contrary to Constitutionalism,&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;the plea states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ordinance introduced by the UP government, the plea alleges, is to merely serve a political purpose and is motivated by communally divisive agendas which could impact societal peace and harmony. &quot;&lt;em&gt;The issue is emotive and seeks to divide communities. It is yet another way to polarise our polity and reaping electoral dividend,&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;the petition has contended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What remains unclear is to what extent the plea will help in tackling an Ordinance which remains backed by a majority government in UP and an overwhelming population of citizens who continue to see love and marriage as a plot laid by Muslim men. In an age where India’s secular fabric is alleged to have been shaken by its very core, this Ordinance seems to be the cherry on the communalism cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What remains extremely daunting is the fate of inter-religious marriages henceforth, whose battles have just become even more gruesome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aniba Junaid</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">On November 28, 2020, the Uttar Pradesh government in North India further entrenched ‘communalism by law’ in the state by activating the Uttar Pradesh Prohibition of Unlawful Conversion of Religious Ordinance, 2020. This Ordinance prohibits conversion from one religion to another by “misrepresentation, force, fraud, undue influence, coercion, allurement or marriage”. The stated goal of the law is to check “unlawful religious conversion” and “interfaith marriages with the sole intention of changing a girl’s religion”. It criminalises conversions in violation of the provisions of the law and punishes the guilty with a jail term of up to 10 years. The offences defined and stated in the Ordinance are cognisable and non-bailable. Many&amp;nbsp;BJP-ruled states have expressed an interest to legislate similar provisions. To this P Chidambaram, the former Indian Finance Minister, wrote that “the ‘love jihad’ law is an onslaught on choice; on freedom; on privacy; on dignity; on the equality of man and woman; and on the right to love or live together or marry.” India’s journey since the implementation of this law has shown a trend where most experts are questioning the secular fabric of the country. The World Watch Monitor in one of its articles claimed that the leaders of Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh (RSS), a militant Hindu nationalist group, has stated on national media that the&amp;nbsp;RSS will make India free of Christians and Muslims by December 31, 2021. One way it intends to do this is through forced ‘re-conversions’. Hundreds of Christians were forced to reconvert to Hinduism last year through intimidation and pressure. The article claimed that “Despite being the world’s largest democracy, with a constitution that guarantees freedom of religion and belief, such extremism is thriving in India. Hindu nationalists see Hinduism as the true religion of India, so when an Indian ‘returns’ to Hinduism, it is not seen as a ‘conversion’ from another faith, but a ‘ghar wapsi’ or ‘homecoming’: so they are exempt from the anti-conversion laws.” The Indian media have come under serious fire for not having extensively covered the issue. Nevertheless, in recent articles, some media platforms like India Today examined the minute specifics of the law. At least 10 states have passed anti-conversion legislation in India in the past. Odisha, Madhya Pradesh, Arunachal Pradesh, Chhattisgarh, Gujarat, Himachal Pradesh, Rajasthan, Tamil Nadu and Jharkhand are among these states. In the case of Tamil Nadu, the law was repealed in 2004. In Rajasthan, the anti-conversion bill passed by the state legislature was returned by the Centre. Most of these laws ban religious conversion by force or allurement. At least four states have recently said they will come up with laws against 'love jihad', which requires conversion in a marriage. In February this year, the Centre had told Parliament 'love jihad' is not defined in any of the existing laws.&amp;nbsp; The Madhya Pradesh Act was further amended in July 2020, providing that the district magistrate and the priest or organisation performing the conversion need to be informed by a person wishing to change his religion. The police would then verify the priest's credentials to ensure that this was not done by force or by seduction. Penal action provisions exist against priests/individuals who do not inform the authorities. The Supreme Court, however, supported the laws saying, “What is freedom for one is freedom for the other in equal measure and there can, therefore, be no such thing as a fundamental right to convert any person to one’s own religion.” Saumya Saxena, in an article published by The Wire, claims that The Hindu Mahasabha and the RSS’ recent propaganda against 'love jihad' geared against religious marriage conversion may appear as an argument that favours the Special Marriage Act (which allows inter-religious marriage without conversion). However, in fact, with or without conversion, these organisations have traditionally opposed mixed marriages. The adoption of the Special Marriage Act is itself a tale of the suspicions of exogamy by India, its frustration with religious conversions, and remains one of the many surveillance mechanisms. The adoption of the Special Marriage Act in 1954 remains the closest legislation that can somewhat assert religious neutrality. Lok Sabha debates at the time of its enactment reveal that for many parliamentarians, the Act embedded secularism in the institution of marriage as a ‘freedom’ to love. Couples who marry without their parents' permission mostly opt for temple-weddings, Arya Samaj weddings, or weddings after Islamic conversion. Conversion has emerged in practice as the realistic way to cohabit as a couple, albeit far from ideal, in a country where neither inter-faith, inter-caste nor living-in couples can achieve societal acceptance. While the courts have settled the issue of fraud or bigamous marriages solemnised by abuse of religious conversion, propagandists would have us believe that if it were not for the temptations of Muslim personal rule, Hindu men would remain monogamous and Hindu women would still prefer endogamy without easy options to convert. However, marriage is only one of the planks used in opposition to religious conversion. We are again facing a similar situation in which state governments are seeking to enact restrictive legislation to ban conversion, but targeted at another religious minority. But the danger of a national law curtailing religious freedom is now very real, and judicial independence to properly guard against this is diminishing now more than ever. The law will be camouflaged as a discussion on family law, on a uniform civil code, or on marriage fraud but will be guided, like much else in this regime has been, against minorities and against freedom, says Saxena in her bold critique.&amp;nbsp; The issues with the law have caused sufficient unrest to which citizens continue to deliberate and react upon till date. A public interest petition filed very recently through advocates&amp;nbsp;Devesh Saxena, Shashwat Anand&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Vishesh Rajvanshi&amp;nbsp;contends that the Uttar Pradesh Ordinance is both morally and constitutionally repugnant. &quot;The aforesaid ordinance requires every religious conversion to be scrutinised and certified by the state. The very concept of forcing an individual to explain and justify a decision, which is closely personal to him/her, before an officer of the State is contrary to Constitutionalism,&quot; the plea states. The Ordinance introduced by the UP government, the plea alleges, is to merely serve a political purpose and is motivated by communally divisive agendas which could impact societal peace and harmony. &quot;The issue is emotive and seeks to divide communities. It is yet another way to polarise our polity and reaping electoral dividend,&quot;&amp;nbsp;the petition has contended. What remains unclear is to what extent the plea will help in tackling an Ordinance which remains backed by a majority government in UP and an overwhelming population of citizens who continue to see love and marriage as a plot laid by Muslim men. In an age where India’s secular fabric is alleged to have been shaken by its very core, this Ordinance seems to be the cherry on the communalism cake. What remains extremely daunting is the fate of inter-religious marriages henceforth, whose battles have just become even more gruesome.</summary></entry></feed>