<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-02T19:48:35+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Private Data: A Public Good?</title><link href="/Private-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Private Data: A Public Good?" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Private-Data</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Private-Data">&lt;p&gt;While global economies have sent their growth-obsessed capitalistic policy approach on a hiatus for the year, with even the disgraced dragon dropping its annual economic growth targets for the first time since the 1990’s, the competitive aspect of the battle against COVID-19 has not left the grounds of policy-making. Taiwan has surfaced as a recent beneficiary of the comparative analysis initiated by global media houses. The nation is being rightfully lauded for managing to contain the current number of active cases under 500, despite its close proximity and intimate relations with China, the epicentre of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides proper screening, increasing testing capacity and mass insurance, the nation implemented a dynamic containment plan that required the government to partner with the local telecom operators in order to ensure that suspects were properly quarantined by tracking their GPS locations. The surveillance is said to be so precise that one asymptomatic carrier claimed via Twitter that the local police arrived at his doors within half an hour when he accidentally switched off his phone in the early morning hours, back in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During ordinary times, even a mild parliamentary discussion on tracking private data by the government would have been globally marketed as a sign of the nation becoming a digital dictatorship. However, the current crisis has demonstrated that perhaps drawing inferences from private data and using them as a public good has benefits that exceed the costs involved, while simultaneously upholding the privacy of individuals. (A public good is a non­-excludable, non-rivalrous good, i.e., individuals may consume without paying for it and one individual’s consumption does not hinder that of the other individuals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to correctly recognise the benefits of private data as a public good, one must acknowledge that the lack of information is a fundamental economic problem, in the non-textbook economic setup. Lack of resources then becomes a secondary issue in policy making, since a data inference needs to be drawn first to decide the direction of redistribution before subjecting it to any resource constraints. Often policymakers resolve the information problem by statistical sampling which is in itself expensive. Data can become quickly outdated which may lead to non-representative samples and other specification errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when digitalisation comes into the picture, it brings in better solutions to the information problem. It assists not only in policymaking but also in enforcing free-market equilibrium in certain markets by increasing the degree of market efficiency and allowing smoother real-time price discovery mechanisms, thus minimising distortions. An example would be E-NAM (Electronic National Agricultural Market), the online trading platform for agricultural goods, launched by the Indian government, which now has a membership of nearly 4.5 million farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other indirect and more relevant advantages of digitalisation include the large scale database of the digital footprints of a population. Presently, smartphones have become a very accessible device in even developing and emerging nations. The data generated by these devices is mainly with the concerned individual’s telecom operator, as well as other private parties that collect data from the users who install their mobile applications, e.g. Google, Facebook, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the private app developers have facilitated the birth of controversial practices like that of surveillance capitalism, by utilising the competitive edge provided in advertising avenues, the data generated can still be deemed an instrumental tool in studying various macro-level indicators about the population. For instance, by studying the pathway of the telecom antennae one’s device was connected to, one can easily track the real-time mobility of a population and generate migration patterns. Upon analysing the frequency and multitude of online transactions made in a certain period, one can even concretise their hypothesis about the direction of the economy in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If governments, like that of Taiwan, consistently manage to extract benefits out of aggregates of anonymised private data, they can manage to do so without violating individual rights as well as without robbing private benefactors off of the competitive edge generated by the data. The Economic Survey 2019, published by the Indian government, rightfully stated that data is of the people, for the people, and by the people. It acknowledged the lack of clarity and sophistication in the law specifying the ownership of data and elaborated upon the need to take advantage of the multitude of data that is generated. Due to data explosion, the marginal costs of data storage have fallen drastically, with one-gigabyte storage requiring a mere ₹3.48 now, as compared to ₹61,000 back in 1981.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even dissemination costs are negligible owing to real-time transfers over the internet. The marginal benefits, which include evidence-based policymaking, targeted implementation of the same and augmentation of accountability, easily outweigh the costs involved. Of course, in order for these benefits to be realised, there needs to be uniformity in the data circulated. Many schemes have already been launched as an initiative to merge data, such as the ‘Samagra Vedika’ initiative by the Telangana State government in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concerns about privacy are certainly valid since once the government gets its hands on the data; it may do with it as it pleases, which is why better laws need to be in place. Private data is very intimate individually, but collectively, it generates great value for the society, and hence, it is important to provide the data in an anonymised and aggregated form to the government. In the light of COVID-19, greater weight is added to the argument of involving public officials in the picture, not simply because we must track the cases and localise the spread, but also because it will help in conducting future studies to deduce patterns and give early warning signs. The debate is ongoing, but it is high time we make use of the data that is at our disposal to its full potential, in a manner that aligns with the population’s core values about the issue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">While global economies have sent their growth-obsessed capitalistic policy approach on a hiatus for the year, with even the disgraced dragon dropping its annual economic growth targets for the first time since the 1990’s, the competitive aspect of the battle against COVID-19 has not left the grounds of policy-making. Taiwan has surfaced as a recent beneficiary of the comparative analysis initiated by global media houses. The nation is being rightfully lauded for managing to contain the current number of active cases under 500, despite its close proximity and intimate relations with China, the epicentre of the crisis.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume</title><link href="/Lockdown-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Lockdown-Diaries</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Lockdown-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t know how to start; the last time I wrote to myself was in the eighth grade, when I wished desperately for the English exam to end, lest my hand fall off and I live without one with an awkward story to tell for as long as the world sustains. It’s not as weird as I thought it would be, honestly. I do talk to myself all the time, at 3 AM, wavering between what I should’ve said to some people two years back and all the possible ways that the world might end in (Armageddon is not left unconsidered, by the way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure this time is hard for every living person on the surface of this planet, and I’m not in this alone. Sometimes, my problems seem like a tiny little whine when I open the news and read about the horrible things happening around; people trying to survive, to get food and just breathe every day, hoping the sun doesn’t set, because if it does, there is another day of suffering waiting for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas as soon as I wake up, I wait eagerly for the dusk, creating a mental picture of the day ahead in my head, trying to bring a sense of organisation and calm to this commotion that life has become. It is almost like an annoying traffic jam, cars glued to the ground, an utterly piercing horn in the background that isn’t ready to subside and your foot on the pedal trying to move your car one bit at a time, as much as you can, to get out of this rut so that you can finally glide onto the highway, roll down your windows and let the cool autumn breeze embrace you until it touches your feet and you feel like all is okay in the world again. I feel as if these days I’m just waiting for this jam to clear, so that I can take in that air again as I rush my car through the freeway, and go anywhere I want, no restrictions, just the journey and the destination ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I just romanticise a pandemic? I’m afraid so. Reading a little too much of Mitch Albom, watching a string of Jane Austen classic movies and smelling books and teas doesn’t make you a &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; millennial, I’m sure. Just your average old-school -person, who loves cardigans and sighs when they look at &lt;em&gt;tiktoks&lt;/em&gt;, referring to it as ‘these kids’ when you’re a 20-year-old yourself (or more like an 80-year-old woman stuck in a 20-year-old’s body).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even though I enjoy my old-person traits most days, it’s certainly hard to keep up with it when you live in the year 2020, jailed amidst the four walls of your room. The internet and social media isn’t a respite because you cannot for the life of you comprehend the conundrum that is #quarantineandchill or the Dalgona coffee trend? (I mean it’s just coffee upside down). I know that I have all the time in the world to read all those books and literary wonders that I keep crying about when I didn’t have enough time or listen to Sam Cooke all day and Paul McCartney the next. And it was all about those books, songs and heartwarming movies but only for a good four weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the fifth week started to unfold, I missed the smell of freshly roasted coffee that came wafting from the cafes that I walked past, pulling me towards themselves as the moon does to the tides - just simple laws of gravity. And that’s just not it. I miss my entire commute to university every day - waking up early yet late, at 7 am (yes that was sadly late) and crying about it, while I rush to get ready and catch a ride to the metro-station as my hair is soaking wet and I drench the marble floors of my house as I sprint around, trying to find my glasses and earphones. I would gulp my cold coffee whole, while my mother gave me a sniggering look for skipping breakfast and yet would sneak in a sandwich wrapped in aluminium foil in my bag when I wasn’t looking. I miss the morning breeze that air-dried my hair in the auto-rickshaw, while I fiddled with my earphones and rummaged through my playlist for a morning boost of Mumford and Sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would give up all of the social media, yes, Instagram and Snapchat and whatever new application the kids are using these days for a train ride to college, filled with strangers, all so hurried, so hasty, to reach somewhere, pushing and fumbling through the metro - I would find an uncanny sense of calm in it. This uncertainty and muddled life has made me realize how much I also miss studying or skipping the first-morning class to hang out in the cafeteria instead with a cup of steaming coffee and half-forgotten anecdotes from old nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me or does anyone else also miss the yellow and red flowers strewn about on the streets in March? It is not easy for a memory hoarder to get through these tough times without lapsing into nostalgia every other minute. Not easy for a person who loves stray discourses on politics, life, love, career and books over a cup of tea to text people and still have that fiery enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not undermining my privilege, for I know these aren’t the issues that matter in the least right now. But I think writing them down makes me feel a tad better - like I’m ranting to someone as I would in the &lt;em&gt;old days&lt;/em&gt;, if I may.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like a true old-soul, these past three months have made me realize how much I enjoy my own company rather than texting away or relying on social media to get through the day. And I don’t think less of anyone who does that; whatever one finds their peace in. But it’s hard to blend in sometimes for monochromes in this vibrant world, when all you want is to cook yourself nice, steaming-hot banana bread and curl into your bed with a sad PDF. (I miss the smell of books).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think all I want is a redo sometimes. I know I couldn’t change anything; I couldn’t stop the pandemic because that is beyond my corporeal control. However, if I do get a redo, as I imagine- &lt;em&gt;I see myself standing at the jostling platform of Rajiv Chowk Metro Station in Delhi- people brushing past and into each other. I might be looking at them indifferently, as my earphones pulse to the tunes of The Beach Boys. It looks like a tiresome day and I don’t pay heed to the stranger next to me, who smells like Fijian Water Lotus mist. If only I knew it was the last time I’d smell an unfamiliar perfume, I would’ve stepped a little lighter, would’ve breathed a little longer. I would’ve lingered for a slow second before stepping out the metro doors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waiting,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poorvi.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?</title><link href="/European-Central-Bank" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?" /><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/European-Central-Bank</id><content type="html" xml:base="/European-Central-Bank">&lt;p&gt;Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms Lagarde, however, is of the view that monetary policy is not the first line of defence and feels that fiscal response must be given much more importance. The persistent heterogeneity in the Euro area has also been a long-standing concern for the single monetary policy. It severely complicates the conduct of this policy. The current crisis exposed these vulnerabilities, once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since 2008, the EU has been in a non-stop crisis mode. Even the interest rate it charges to the commercial banks is almost nil leaving very little margin for further rate cuts to stimulate the economy out of this rut. The ECB has acknowledged how they are facing an unprecedented crisis with historic consequences which might just push the European economy to worse than what it was in 2008. If the crisis is not controlled by the stimuli, it risks pushing the already wobbly European economy to the state of recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 16, the ECB went ahead and announced the measures it will be taking on the monetary policy front while it gives time to the respective governments to formulate fiscal policy measures. The ECB took certain measures to prevent the crisis from becoming a full-blown financial crisis with two broad objectives: first, to restore the orderly functioning of presently volatile European financial markets, and second, to ensure that the accommodative monetary policy measures support firms and households in incurring the social and economic costs of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECB response consists of three major mutually reinforcing grounds. The first one relating to broad-based asset purchases to address illiquidity and volatility in core segments of the European economy. The temporary Pandemic Emergency Purchase Programme (PEPP) constitutes the core of this component. The economies in the entire Eurozone have been struggling with tightening fiscal and economic conditions, the PEPP expects to release the pressure on these economies. It foresees purchases at a volume of €750 billion of eligible private and public securities throughout this year, and longer if needed.  The ECB also aims to mitigate the impact of the crisis on the funding conditions of businesses and banks. For the same, it has decided to divert a considerable fraction of the additional €120 billion purchase envelope under the Asset Purchase Programmes (APP), as well as of the PEPP, for eligible private sector bonds. However, one cannot turn a blind eye to the fact that the bank has already been conducting purchases of government bonds, and now, it does not have much to re-purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, measures to ensure that the banks remain effective carriers of the monetary policy of the ECB have been introduced. The enhanced Targeted Longer-Term Refinancing Operations (TLTROs), as well as a comprehensive set of collateral easing measures, form part of this component.  The interest rate on all targeted TLTROs was reduced by 25 basis points to -0.5% from June 2020 to June 2021. Measures to ensure the solvency of banks by holding up the role of lender of the last resort to the banks which will help the ECB drive the way for economic growth. This becomes all the more necessary considering that the European economy is majorly a bank-based economy than a financial market one, so just supporting the financial markets would not help alleviate the effects of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures for small and medium-sized firms are equally necessary, which include bank lending and loan guarantee schemes to protect the already overdrawn credit lines by cash strapped firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Italy, for example, bank lending conditions for firms remained remarkably resilient in recent years despite significant swings in market-based funding conditions of the banks and firms. Again, the measures can provide a valuable bridge to the future and help keep aggregate external funding costs of firms stable until the economy recovers and uncertainty diminishes further. This also includes accepting a wider range of assets as collaterals from small and medium-sized firms along with consistently working on the liquidity conditions of the banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ECB fails to improve liquidity indirectly through these measures, it always has the option to exercise its right to issue ‘helicopter money’. This alternative would put the money straight into the ‘hands’ of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these measures, the ECB hopes to improve liquidity and market behaviour in the sovereign yield bonds market, which in turn form the basis of pricing of assets in the economy. The ECB uses the GDP-weighted Euro area government bond yield curve as a measure for the effectiveness of the economy, but currently, this curve has been badly disrupted. So the ECB will focus on stabilising this curve and reversing the steepness of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while the Eurozone faces an increasingly threatening risk of a slowdown in the economy, which can take years to recover from and get back to the normal levels, the ECB and various governments are taking steps to tackle this challenge. The cluster of countries has recovered from far worse situations in the past, like the global economic crisis of 2008, and emerged stronger than ever. It remains to be seen what other steps the European Union takes as a much worse crisis than COVID-19 awaits the global economy and how the relief package unravels for the Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kashish Jindal</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can Self-Reliance be the New Norm: A Take on India’s ‘Atma-nirbharata’</title><link href="/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Self-Reliance be the New Norm: A Take on India’s ‘Atma-nirbharata’" /><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm">&lt;p&gt;“To stand on one’s own feet” is how 10th-grade economics teachers sum up the concept of self-reliance. The thinking behind India’s advocacy for this concept is premised upon the scars of colonialism. However, with the liberalisation of the Indian economy by the Narasimha Rao-led government, the concept had practically faded away from Indian public policy discourse. 29 years later, with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calling upon Indians to ‘be vocal for local’ and emphasising self-reliance, it seems to be taking the centre-stage once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-reliance can be defined as “dependence on one’s own natural resources to produce goods and services to satisfy the demand”. One of the many problems with this is that every economy faces a dearth of resources, which are inputs required to produce goods (and services). One rather famous quip in economics goes like this: ‘resources are limited, while [human] wants are unlimited’. Every nation cannot produce everything on a scale sufficient to meet its domestic demand. Even if we suppose, for argument’s sake, that we could achieve the impossible, it is important to realise that self-reliance is a dynamic concept. If you look at it, achieving self-reliance is to successfully meet the aggregate demand of all the people in an economy; that is, conforming production along the lines of consumers’ tastes and preferences. There is no guarantee that these tastes will remain constant (unless, of course, if states ‘determine’ tastes!). So, if one were to adhere to the definition of self-reliance, one ought to change production constantly, keeping pace with the change in tastes and demands of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, the scarcity of resources prompts states to resort to protectionist measures so as to encourage local producers. There is no ruling-out of a misallocation of resources in such circumstances, due to lack of economies of scale (a resultant of protectionist policies). This leads to a drastic loss in the productivity of a country and results in a deadweight loss for society. To put this in perspective, let us look at the total factor productivity of India. Total Factor Production may be defined as the increase in the growth of output that can be attributed to factors other than capital and labour. This can be the result of many reasons including a change in the quality of inputs, new techniques of production, better management of resources, and so on. One study finds that the average total factor productivity growth was negative for the 1970’s, when protectionism was at its heyday. In fact, there were frequent instances of negative growth in total factor production (where total factor production fell below zero) before 1991. Only after reforms, did the metric pick up pace, remaining positive throughout. From 2001-2008, total factor production grew at an average of 3.36%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second impact of protectionist measures is that the cost of production is (relatively) high and results in higher prices for the consumers. Why should a government, in the name of self-sufficiency, let its consumers pay a higher price for a good that would be available for a cheaper price when imported? This certainly is not how a rational entity would (or should) behave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of self-reliance also begs the question of who is to determine the scale and intensity of production to achieve this self-reliance and how is this to be determined. If history is any guide, this is often determined by the state. And this means curtailing of choices on the part of the consumer and a massive involvement of the government in the supply side or the production side. It implies that the allocation of resources is controlled by the government and every producer (or entrepreneur) relies heavily on the government to take any decision. This control is exercised by the way of issuing licenses. The infamously dubbed practice of ‘license raj’ is exactly this. This can also discourage potential entrepreneurs from coming forward to start a business. Accepting this excessive government control would mean that bureaucrats, with no experience in business management whatsoever, would run the businesses rather than people competent to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, this is not the type of self-reliance a country should be aiming for. A country should be aiming at self-reliance in terms of human capital. In today’s global world, ideas and innovation are what sets a country apart. As renowned economist and Nobel laureate Paul Romer said, “&lt;em&gt;Growth springs from better recipes, not just from better cooking&lt;/em&gt;”. His view was that ideas of non-rival character, generated by profit-maximising entrepreneurs will lead to economic growth. This emphasises the role of human capital in the course of economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for many reasons, there has been a constant outflow of human capital from our country to advanced nations like the US and the UK. It is crucial for India to recognise that every emigrant is productivity lost and innovation foregone. So, when I say self-reliance on human capital, I mean the creation of institutions of the highest excellence to truly harness human capital. However, the disappointing budget allocation for education by the Indian government (4.6% of the GDP in 2019-2020) shows that it has no plans to improve in this specific sector. India ought to increase education spending and allocate (and disburse) more funds toward PhD research, which are now sparse and available mainly for technology courses. Only self-reliance in terms of human capital is sustaining and yields increasing returns and hence should be a priority for the government. This is important to arrest the outflow of human capital out of the country whether for studies or permanent migration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">“To stand on one’s own feet” is how 10th-grade economics teachers sum up the concept of self-reliance. The thinking behind India’s advocacy for this concept is premised upon the scars of colonialism. However, with the liberalisation of the Indian economy by the Narasimha Rao-led government, the concept had practically faded away from Indian public policy discourse. 29 years later, with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calling upon Indians to ‘be vocal for local’ and emphasising self-reliance, it seems to be taking the centre-stage once again.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Post-Pandemic Perspective</title><link href="/A-Post-Pandemic-Perspective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Post-Pandemic Perspective" /><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Post-Pandemic-Perspective</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Post-Pandemic-Perspective">&lt;p&gt;An establishment of the number of deaths and active cases is no longer required to emphasise on the sweeping destruction of SARS COVID-19. The extensive information overload from all sources surrounding us is enough to apprise us of the problems caused by the pandemic. Minimal equipment, lack of hospital beds for patients, poor people struggling, and crumbling health care facilities and social systems currently characterise the countries previously overflowing with wealth and social status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, the aforementioned problems are not surprising in the face of an epidemic as intense as COVID-19 with burgeoning cases across the globe, except what is surprising is how quickly and badly these different institutions and structures crumbled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it may not even be as surprising as soon as one is to look towards the perspective with which society and government institutions treat these public institutions, services and systems. They have majorly functioned on the idea of profitability for decades. The governments, the firms and the producers depended upon their ability to exploit resources and individuals. On-demand economies and immediate pay-offs had the governments accustomed to overlooking the means as long as the ends were achieved. As a consequence, governments did not care if the hospitals were ill-equipped, or charged exorbitantly for basic healthcare services as long as the capitalists and industrialists provided superficial happiness and continued funding the political parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, this issue is only aggravated by the value (or lack thereof) attached to human life. The productivity and profitability of an individual determine the value they hold in a society. Case in point, the Indian government happily and willingly spent money to bring non-resident Indians (NRIs) home free of cost, while migrant labourers died on roads travelling to their home barefoot and hungry. The social cost of an NRI was less than that of migrant labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The justification offered by institutions at this point in time is lack of funds, except that is not true. It is the lack of willingness of the institutions to use methods that displease the industrialists to gather those funds, whether it is taxing the extremely wealthy 5% people or forcing private industries to provide services for a cheaper cost or reallocating resources and funds. The money spent on military and weapons of mass destruction exceeded the amount spent on building sustainable public institutions and healthcare systems by millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the warnings by scientists and research institutions regarding climate change and global warming, the governments of the countries that are currently suffering have no excuse to offer for the lack of preparedness and crumbling structures except for gross neglect and greed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk is opening his stores and factories despite stringent lockdown and has not even received a slap on the wrist so to speak. Jeff Bezos is ready to become the first trillionaire while millions of people are currently facing unemployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the above is a result of the pre-COVID-19 structures and systems. Understandably, the public is upset. It is evident that a change in existing public structures and systems of governance is needed for the world to survive COVID and rebuild itself post-COVID. Countries like New Zealand, Finland, Norway, Germany, Switzerland, Japan which previously prioritised strengthening and spending upon their public services and social systems are currently surviving far better than countries like the USA, which left it’s governance and institutions to the profit-mongering industrialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists and researchers reckon a change in outlook towards social systems and public services by the governing institutions, as enforced and instituted by the pressures and demands of the general masses. The dissatisfaction and unrest in the public is expected to be the catalyst for changing social structures. Currently, a majority of the world is focused on surviving the pandemic and will have to start anew once a vaccine is developed. One can hope that the countries rebuilt post-pandemic put more effort and careful consideration towards their social systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another change in the post-COVID world is attributed to global trade and governance. A month before the spread of COVID-19, the two largest economies were engaged in a vastly damaging trade-war. Simultaneously the rest of the countries were realising the unbelievable dependence of their basic services on global trading and how a disturbance such as the one caused by the trade war resulted in hindering the free-flow of goods and essential items in multiple countries. Many also depended upon the delivery of protective equipment and essential medication from other countries to be able to fight the pandemic which further aggravated the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only the woe of dependence but the power dynamic established due to the extensive trading by countries like China and the USA is also the reason for the anticipated change in global trading. The reason being that these countries used trading services as leverages to influence decisions in independent institutions like the European Union, United Nations and the International Monetary Fund to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-COVID trade is expected to be different in terms of restrictions as countries begin to question and subsequently dismiss the benefits of ‘free trade’. Countries are already beginning to work towards changing the trading system and minimising the dependence upon the global world. Japan is urging firms to re-establish factories in Japan through subsidies in its COVID-19 stimulus packages, the Indian government is actively marketing the idea of ‘self-reliance’ through catchy slogans and tax incentives, and the European Union is working towards ‘strategic autonomy’ through the purchase of stakes in local firms. Likewise, the USA has doubled down on coercing IT firms to build more local plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the shift in focus and priority towards social systems and public services can only bring in positive results and benefits for the poor and underprivileged, the same cannot be said for the shift away from globalisation. Self-reliance and independence of countries may change the global power structures, but the cost of such a change in terms of less freedom, expensive goods and production, lack of resources, and inaccessibility in poor and developing nations may exceed the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">An establishment of the number of deaths and active cases is no longer required to emphasise on the sweeping destruction of SARS COVID-19. The extensive information overload from all sources surrounding us is enough to apprise us of the problems caused by the pandemic. Minimal equipment, lack of hospital beds for patients, poor people struggling, and crumbling health care facilities and social systems currently characterise the countries previously overflowing with wealth and social status.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Minimalist Manifesto</title><link href="/A-Minimalist-Manifesto" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Minimalist Manifesto" /><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Minimalist-Manifesto</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Minimalist-Manifesto">&lt;p&gt;It is irrefutably substantial to propose that the lockdown has generally made us a little less obsessive about how we look all the time, the outfits we wear every day, and has led to a daily decrease in the shopaholic nature of our rapid consumption. It is all seeming a lot simpler because we are at home not having to conform to our social constructs. We all struggle with the daily clutter of having to manage an nth number of things, which can get to the most sorted people’s heads. The pandemic has, in a way, somehow tidied our minds with respect to the number of things we own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimalist movement started out as an art movement emphasising on and advocating simplistic living, that a lot of people mistook only for aesthetics. As the unruly laws of humans always tend to find a way to corrupt anything, a floating zen ideal is already stigmatised. It is not impractical, privileged thinking that undermines the consequences of capitalism. Consumerism is an important aspect that the world functions on today. It becomes devilish when it is used to play with people’s minds in a way that forces them to buy things they don’t necessarily need. Minimising the number of things one assigns ownership to declutters our minds, and leads one to a freer lifestyle. For instance, after a person’s death, one can notice how many of that person’s memories are attached to his/her things. It’s intriguing how we let things play such a central role in a person’s being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jean-Paul Sartre’s interesting and famous existentialist theories were based on the inevitability of the mantra “being precedes essence”. Being is important, and essence is only secondary to that. There is peace and freedom in living that virtue. The daily chase after the things we want to buy and/or want to ‘own’ is taking over the real purposes of life. We are all involved in the rat race of earning the most amount of money, which translates in our head as buying the best, most expensive commodity, thinking of happiness or purpose in quantifiable and tangible terms. The measurable quality of ‘success’ these days is hooked onto this opaque idea of ownership. Not to devalue the importance of this success, but we achieve it in a way that we never prioritise our well being again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimalism focuses on the uncontroversial preaching that one should think critically about what is necessary and what is not. In practice, therefore, it translates into, as Chayka and other have noted, a form of conspicuously inconspicuous consumption. Minimalism, however, is today characterised as the glamourisation of a simplistic lifestyle. So the original intention has now taken a back seat, and the aesthetic it happens to represent has blinded some of its followers. But this psychological impact, fortunately, or unfortunately, could add to the legacy of the notion. It’s morally a slightly grey perspective to approach the growth of the phenomena, nonetheless welcomed if it helps increase the awareness around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of minimalism is described by critics and analysts to be highly curative, hyper-reluctant, over meticulous, stringently restrictive and arrogantly ignorant. These might just be mere consequences of some personally enhanced interpretations of the minimalist philosophy. There is no denying its mantra being overworked upon by highly organised individuals, but that’s a different representation that needn’t be projected upon the ethical commands of what the movement truly advocates. All the movement is about is cutting down consumption, monitoring usage, reducing arbitrary decisions, avoiding having to manage futility, lowering chances of redundancy, leading a reclusive path, and so on to create a lifestyle that can focus more upon the meaningful aspects of life. If we spend most of our lives worrying about things and the more superficially-aligned aspects of living, that’s all our way of thinking will stay limited to. The ascetic undertones it propagates, are crafted in relation to the lesser focused-upon connotations of simplicity that have forever fascinated its followers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sick to think that minimalism romanticises poverty or the unprivileged sects. This critique is oblivious to such a highly principled phenomenon and what it aims to achieve. It is ignorant of its depths and it misunderstands the underlying spiritual faith. A capitalist-critical argument that is essential to consider argues that minimalism is highly imperative to achieve a more equitable society in terms of people’s consumption being proportionate to their needs. This will create a socio-economic environment that protects and celebrates inclusivity and actively preaches egalitarian principles. What must be criticised, if at all, should be the over-fetishisation of the curated ‘simplicity’ that the ultra-rich like to benefit from by pretending it is their ‘style of aesthetic’. The movement has been curdled into more of its ostentatious implications by such classes as ‘show off’ and ‘superficiality’. However, this is exactly what the movement proposes to combat today, added to destructuring the capitalist overindulgence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine a few artistic derivations of minimalism, where the expression authentically originates from. At the School of the Art Institute, Chicago, a contemporary art professor David Raskin states, “&lt;em&gt;Minimalism can return you to this basic state where you’re perceiving purely. Less is more because you strip away the familiar&lt;/em&gt;”. A plain, monochromatic painting or object might seem mundane and dull on the surface, but actually engender a stark sensory experience the mind has never been exposed to before. It inculcates an opportunity to view the world without any preconceptions a mind is previously latched onto. Its existence is simply representative of a clean slate for one to reflect onto. The art radically imbibes the actuality of infinite possibilities and makes one not only think, but delve into introspection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that, as human beings, we must not just preach minimalism in our daily lives but constantly remind ourselves why such spiritual, socio-economic change is required in this rather belittled world of everlasting consumerist societies continually propagating capitalist ideologies, and demanding the grind and hustle to exploit our passions by rapidly creating commodities and products out of it that appeal only to the competitive politics of capitalist regimes, thereby, ultimately crumbling our innate need to stop, absorb and think.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It is irrefutably substantial to propose that the lockdown has generally made us a little less obsessive about how we look all the time, the outfits we wear every day, and has led to a daily decrease in the shopaholic nature of our rapid consumption. It is all seeming a lot simpler because we are at home not having to conform to our social constructs. We all struggle with the daily clutter of having to manage an nth number of things, which can get to the most sorted people’s heads. The pandemic has, in a way, somehow tidied our minds with respect to the number of things we own.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Racism in the Time of Corona</title><link href="/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Racism in the Time of Corona" /><published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona">&lt;p&gt;Racial discrimination and prejudice aren’t novel for this world, unlike the COVID-19. Race and ethnicity have been the two major building blocks of our society. We can trace its origin back to the slavery of the Africans and African-Americans in the United States during the 18th century, the anti-Semitism that blew up in Germany during the Second World War or Islamophobia post 9/11; &lt;em&gt;new disease, old story.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society has always found it comforting and easy on their minds to deflect their insecurities and frustrations onto a group, a minority or a defined culture. This is what is generally referred to as the Scapegoat Theory, that is, the tendency to blame someone else for one’s problems, a process that often results in feelings of prejudice toward the group that one is blaming. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When struck with this unforeseen disease that no one thought would erupt and set alight the world, with no prospects of fizzling out any time soon, people turned to the old blame-game. The uncertainty, the fear, the anger and frustration, although no justification for such acts of racism, led to a huge rise in Sinophobia (or Anti-Chinese sentiment). It also led to xenophobia and violence against people of East Asian and Southeast Asian descent around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coronavirus that originated in Wuhan, China has not only infected people physically but mentally and as stereotypically as it could. Draconian comments such as “wipe the Chinese people out” and “hope this virus gets all of them” etc. have been expressed throughout the world, apathetically. However, this discrimination isn’t a result of just the pandemic, or the lockdown frustration because that would be a fairly a simple explanation for the centuries of entrenched racism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Race Conflict Theory, the race came about as a tool to justify and maintain the economic and political power held by those of European descent ages ago. The prejudice that we hold against certain communities, is, by and large, an extension of the stereotypes we create with an implicit bias that comes into play while making judgments about them. And this chain of stereotype leading to prejudice creates discrimination-unequal treatment of different groups of people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The matter in question today is the virus and its origin in China that has led us to fabricate a stereotype and deplorable feelings towards the Chinese and Asian people. This includes incidents of Northeast-Indian students facing odious and hurtful remarks in colleges, more than 1,000 South Korean tourists being instructed to avoid public places and remain in isolation in their hotels, and even being rejected by hotels and forced to spend nights at the airport, a woman being called “coronavirus”, threatened, and spat on by youths in Schaerbeek and a French newspaper &lt;em&gt;Le Courrier Picard&lt;/em&gt; featuring an Asian woman wearing a mask on its front page on January 26, 2020 with a headline “Yellow Alert”. The paper also titled an editorial “A New Yellow Peril”. These instances are overlooked every day by most of us as they are not considered undignified or moralistically unrighteous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yellow, a term mindlessly anointed to the Asians isn’t new. Segregation based on colour has been a rite as archaic as the Old Testament itself. To think that Racism is not a 21st century paradigm would be a self-delude, a ‘Racism without Racists’, because even though the explicit views might have become less prominent due to their social condemnation and fewer people’s willingness to say them, doesn’t mean that this racism doesn’t exist. It has morphed into a more structural and anchored form of racism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has manifested some economic repercussions too, as nations are withdrawing their faith in China, particularly the United States, whose President Donald Trump has been ramping up his censure of Beijing and threatening new tariffs on China. The United States is considering retaliatory measures against China over the outbreak. A commentator from a US news channel even went so far ahead as to criticise the country for selling virus-infected bats in open-air marketplaces and have business and tourist travel between “that country” and the “civilized world”. These slurs and scorn are touching new bottoms of impropriety across the world, emanating their ideas of what is civilised, as we just saw. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this sentiment hasn’t been restricted to just the Chinese people. Sinophobia was an antechamber into a spur of punitive sentiment against many communities, like the Muslims and the Jews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamophobia reinforced its clutches in India after an incidence of Muslim gatherings organised by the Tablighi Jamaat that resulted in large increased cases in India, which has triggered Islamophobic reactions and increased communal tensions. Fabricated videos falsely claiming to show members of the missionary group spitting on police and others quickly went viral on social media, hospitals refused to treat Muslim patients which led to the deaths of at least two newborn babies, and the Indian media hopped onto the bandwagon of anti-Muslim stories and headlines like a moth to fire.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a country already beset with 70 years of friction between the Hindus and Muslims following the partition of the Indian subcontinent in 1947; gory wars, terrorist attacks and the recent CAA-NRC bill, this new information spread animosity across the country like a wildfire. Instead of dealing with the issue of the virus getting out of hand, due to unequivocal carelessness on the part of certain people, the quandary shifted seamlessly from the economic and social situation of the country to the incongruous matter of factitious religious sentiments. This hate-mongering has ignited the ember of aversion that is already extant in this nation, making hashtags like #CoronaVirusJihaad viral. It’s both shocking and commonplace at the same time for India to spew such hatred against the Muslims amidst a larger issue of a threatening pandemic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authoritarian societies tend to see the societal structure as people who are naturally superior (as they say), having the right to power over others (minorities). It’s a perpetual cyclical motion of various ideas that lead to something grave. A difference based on racial heritage, called ’Pluralism’ gives birth to this pattern which then leads to what sociology refers to as cultural ’Assimilation’ and further ’Segregation’. However, this cycle doesn’t cease until it reaches the point of ’Genocide’. This is a theory, but it cannot be discredited as purely abstract because history has given us enough &lt;em&gt;corpus delicti&lt;/em&gt; to believe that such a heinous crime can occur. The Holocaust and the Rwandan Genocide are testaments to the exacerbated results of racism and pluralism into something inconceivably ghastly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pandemic has shed light not only on the flaws of our societal structure but the general hierarchy of the Capitalist nature of the economic and political organisation that we follow in the 21st century, necessitating a huge change in both our attitudes and the way we function at large. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s prejudice has blinded them, making them ignorant of the fact that this virus is affecting everyone equally, affecting &lt;em&gt;‘them’&lt;/em&gt; as much as it is distressing any other person; that it is us against the malady and not each other. But hasn’t that always been the human folly? &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Racial discrimination and prejudice aren’t novel for this world, unlike the COVID-19. Race and ethnicity have been the two major building blocks of our society. We can trace its origin back to the slavery of the Africans and African-Americans in the United States during the 18th century, the anti-Semitism that blew up in Germany during the Second World War or Islamophobia post 9/11; new disease, old story.  </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis</title><link href="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis" /><published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 China Financial Stability Report published by the People’s Bank of China officially deems 586 out of 4,379 Chinese lenders to be ‘high-risk’. The figures came into light only after the failure of a third bank within three months as national economic growth manifested a 30-year low. The Hengfeng Bank has become the third bank, after Baoshang Bank and Bank of Jinzhou, to suffer an economic collapse after a $40 trillion debt. But the Chinese government isn’t exceedingly famous for its honesty and transparency, thus the reported figure is likely masking the true extent of the banking quandary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has bailed out many of the high risk lenders. Precarious private shareholders have been effectively replaced by the ones backed by the state, often weaker in terms of their finances. The fact that bailouts are offered only for companies whose bankruptcy has a grave adverse impact on the economy as a whole and not just on a specified sector, cannot be ignored. Moreover, any amount of bailout allocated to this sector will have a domino effect on the Chinese economy which will be several times greater. For instance, the banking system calls for a 5-6% bailout which is equal to 20-24% of the Chinese GDP. A bailout of 20% of the GDP is a non-viable deal for any economy, even if it is China. The numeric is a statement of the fact that any pebble aimed at the banking sector shall bring ripples to the entire economy that in turn will shake China’s status of being a global economic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The People’s Bank of China conducted a stress test in the first half of 2019 on 1,171 commercial banks, 7.7% were stated to be at ‘extreme risk’ and deemed incapable of absorbing even a light shock, 13.6% will probably not be able to endure the financial crisis that shall follow. In November, Yingkou Coastal Bank and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/economy/china-economy/article/3035596/wechat-rumour-sparks-run-rural-chinese-bank-fresh-sign&quot;&gt;Yichuan Rural Commercial Bank&lt;/a&gt; – despite boasting healthy capital adequacy ratios – suffered bank runs as customers rushed to withdraw cash, fearing that the banks would close down, displaying a lack of confidence in banking institutions. The current situation is very similar to the one that cropped up in the late 1990’s. Towards the end of 1997, 20% of the main banks were non-performing, which was equivalent to a value of ¥1.19 trillion on the books of state-owned banks, which was deemed to be equal to 15.6% of the GDP. In order to resolve these crises and recapitalise the banks, ¥270 billion of special government bonds were issued and injected by August 1998. Walking on the same rope, the Chinese government is peddling its way through the crisis by adopting a somewhat similar technique. Today, the interbank market has been injected with around ¥2 trillion by the People’s Bank of China after the Baoshang Bank collapse. Along with this, a helping hand of the sovereign fund, China Investment Corporation, the Central Huijin Investment Company is injecting ¥60 billion into Hengfeng Bank. One of the 12 nationwide joint-stock banks in China, Hengfeng Bank is stacked up with non-performing loans and the situation became grimmer as the bank’s former president was handed out a death sentence for purloining funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, overlooking the different macroeconomic situation shall prove fatal to the Chinese economy in the present scenario. The key antidote for the crisis back then was the spurt of hyper economic growth in the early 2000’s. If China wants to avoid tormenting its economy with the inevitability of bad loans and its weakening banking structure, it will have to aim for a masterful economic growth. However, this stands as a challenge with the outbreak of COVID-19 and its likely aftermath on the global economy. Secondly, continuous evolution over the years has resulted in an entwined and fragile banking structure. The financial system in modern times has given rise to an integrated market that ensures banking transactions are speeded up and are facile in nature. Since the speed of transactions and their impact on the economy is brisk, it also means that any kind of shock in the structure is transmitted faster than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate and interbank customers suffer heavy losses, the volume of negotiable certificates of deposit—which are securities traded between financial institutions for short-term liquidity—has plunged by 90%. The situation threatens to cause the entire banking system to seize up as small and medium-sized banks are heavily dependent on liquidity in the interbank market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crisis should be an eye-opener for the administration as it calls for reforms in the entire financial system which has been overreliant on its banking sector for channeling funds. The fact that the financial structure has changed barely in the last fourteen years is an explanation for the crisis at hand. The world continues to keep a close watch on China, as this crisis is far too big to ignore because any large scale disruption in the driving engine of the global economy will lead the other economies into recession.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Know Your Worth</title><link href="/Know-Your-Worth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Know Your Worth" /><published>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Know-Your-Worth</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Know-Your-Worth">&lt;p&gt;I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But how do I know if the details of my income or personal life will be taken into account when I am standing in the court of law?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when ‘Forensic Economics’ comes into play. Conceived as economics applied to legal matters, forensic economics assesses major issues regarding economic damages in the context of litigation. It is a broad discipline that applies economic theories and methods to matters which are subject to legal review. A forensic economist creates an alternative world with assumptions, wherein the particular citizen is not faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand better where Forensic Economics can be applied in a citizen’s daily life, we will use the most widely accepted defining factor of an individual’s life, that is, ‘work’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worth of a citizen, economically, can be found out by measuring his/her human capital. In order to measure that, one is required to estimate the work-life expectancy of an individual. Now the question is: &lt;em&gt;What is work-life expectancy?&lt;/em&gt; As the word itself suggests, it is the number of years an individual is expected to be in the workforce. The factors that affect each individual’s work-life expectancy include education attained, race, marital status, parental status, and, most importantly, gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists resort to the approach of Forensic Economics to be able to measure an individual’s work-life expectancy, which is contingent on the underlying factors of the individual’s personal life. Under this, they establish the fact that work is not restricted to being involved in only paid employment, but also unpaid non-market work, which also holds certain economic value, thereby, defining ‘total work-life expectancy’ as a sum of market work and non-market work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us establish two imaginary individuals to make our observation simpler: Sheila, a woman, and Joel, a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gender as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The idea that taking care of a household or family is actual work is uncontested and women lead men in that activity. Many times the reason people usually cite for not participating in market work is taking care of household or family. Let’s consider here that both Joel and Sheila are between the ages of 18 to 24. Using the approach of forensic economics, it is found out that the maximum number of men who take care of their households belong to the age group of 18 to 24. However, as we start moving up the total percentage of men participating in non-market work reduces. On the contrary, the percentage of women participating in non-market work starts rising from 18 to 24 and reaches its peak in the age group of 30 to 34, after which it starts to decline. Therefore, a 25-year-old Joel would have about 35 years of market work-life and 1 year of non-market work-life remaining, whereas a 25-year-old Sheila would have about 30 years of market work-life and 6 years of non-market work-life. Both their ‘total work-life expectancy’ would equal 36 years but the difference lies in the market and non-market work based on their gender. This conclusion has been drawn from the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Race, education, and marriage as factors of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The factors of race, education, and marital status of an individual are inherently intertwined in determining his/her work-life expectancy. Let us assume that Sheila is a 30-year-old white woman and X is a non-white woman. If both, Sheila and X, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree then, Sheila’s work-life expectancy will exceed that of X by only a year. Conversely, if both Sheila and X are employed and have high school degrees, the work-life expectancy of Sheila will exceed that of X by over two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we consider Joel to be a 30-year-old white man and Y to be a non-white man, we get different results. If both, Joel and Y, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree, they get the same result as Sheila and X. However, if Joel and Y (both single) have high school degrees, then the work-life expectancy for Joel exceeds that of Y by around 4 years; and by 3.5 years if both men were married. This acute difference between white and non-white men is essentially because men tend to face more discrimination on the basis of their race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a negative relationship between marriage and the work-life expectancy of women. Generally, women of all races face a setback in their market work participation post-marriage. Women with higher degrees face a larger setback than those with lower or no degree at all. This is largely because of two reasons– (a) women tend to be more productive in non-market or household work, and (b) women have a lesser dilemma to face in terms of opportunity cost because women already get lesser pay in comparison to their male counterparts. This leads me to establish the fact that the relationship between marriage and work-life expectancy for men is essentially positive. The work-life expectancy of a married white man exceeds that of an unmarried white man by about 3 years, and a married non-white man has a work-life expectancy of about 4 years more than an unmarried non-white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parental status as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: Let us suppose that Sheila wants to bear a child, but she also wants to keep her work-life expectancy high. To achieve that, she turns to Forensic Economics and realises that the work-life expectancy of a single mother exceeds that of a married mother by 2-3 years. On the contrary, Joel realises that a married man’s work-life expectancy changes negligibly in the case of a child but changes considerably if he chooses to be a single father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having analysed the most basic underlying factors to the work-life expectancy of individuals, it is imperative to establish the fact that the aforementioned observations were made using the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID) under Forensic Economics. This brings us to the conclusion that when the productivity of non-market work is recognised, the work-life expectancy of women is negligibly different than that of men, which busts the myth that men are more productive than women. Therefore, we come to where we started off: the worth of a citizen is measured only after taking into account what I, as an individual citizen, possess with regard to my personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hence, the deliberation ends.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Plato, Pythagoras and Liturgy: The Argument for the Wealth Tax</title><link href="/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Plato, Pythagoras and Liturgy: The Argument for the Wealth Tax" /><published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax">&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greece was known for its military, culture, architecture and many important contributions to science, philosophy and astronomy. However, what was ignored under the discoveries of Pythagoras (yes, that triangle guy) and Plato was its innovative and frankly very sly system of taxation, which could be attributed to the beauty of the liturgy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally, the term Liturgy means a form of public worship, which in ancient Greece meant that the authorities did not tax consumption, instead all public services and development, from building roads to fighting wars, depended upon the &lt;em&gt;benevolence of the rich&lt;/em&gt;. The rich paid taxes voluntarily because the greater the tax, the higher prestige and honour your name and family would get. The rationale behind this was that the rich should shoulder the expense because of the unequal wealth distribution and simply because &lt;em&gt;they can&lt;/em&gt;. While the rich who paid higher taxes enjoyed a greater sway in decision-making and more respect, the poor benefitted by free and quality essential services. Consequently, ancient Greece grew and flourished economically and their citizens lived happily until, of course, the Romans came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only imagine if the same system was implemented today and the same idea of benevolence ruled instead of our usual money and patriarchy. It may seem impossible, yet there are people who are working to (re)introduce a taxation system built on the same ideas of the rich paying for development, if not wholly then at least substantially. Except this time, it is not because of benevolence but because of the dominant and staggering wealth inequality and insane accumulation of wealth by the few people who managed to hack the capitalist system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we go further exploring this idea of taxing the rich, we need to understand who exactly do we mean when we talk about the rich. The answer is simply the super rich who account for more that 70% of a particular country’s wealth and assets. Which surprisingly, or not if you’ve ever studied about wealth distribution, is less than 2% of the population of any country. For example, in America the super rich are 0.5% of the population, while in India they are 1% of the population. This means people like Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and Beyonce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping this in mind, Elizabeth Warren proposed the ‘wealth tax’ which if implemented would tax as little as 2-4% of the wealth above a fixed point. Walking along a similar line, demands for wealth tax are being raised in countries like India, South Africa and Argentina. The International Monetary Fund (IMF) also recommended considering the wealth tax especially after the financial crunch that all countries are facing due to COVID-19. This pandemic has revealed the crumbling structure of public healthcare and services. Additionally, countries would require massive influx to be able to survive and then recover from this pandemic. Furthermore, the overall population demographic is changing and increasing exponentially, hence, the cost of basic necessary services like healthcare, education and housing is skyrocketing, and considering the wealth inequality and poverty rates, a huge majority of the population won’t be able to afford them if the government does not subsidise them, if not make them completely free. And the one possible way for any and all governments to do this is through tax revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, governments can tax income, consumption or wealth. Most countries tax only the first two, in essence, the income you earn through income tax and consumption of goods and services through sales tax, service tax, value added tax and GST etc. However, this is pretty unfair because according to studies conducted by prominent think tanks like Brookings Institution, the lower income group spend more on day-to-day items as compared to the rich; consequently, they bear the brunt of consumption tax far more than the rich, furthering the divide between rich and poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason why wealth tax is a good idea because the people who belong to the category of the super rich, have earned that money not primarily because of hard work, but because of exploiting systems, institutions and people for their benefit. Take Amazon owner Jeff Bezos for example; he became the richest man on earth by predatory pricing and exploiting his workers without paying the basic wages for overtime work. Hence, it makes sense for people who have benefitted from society and the people to give back to the same people and institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant point of conjecture is whether the wealth tax is enough? And whether it would change anything? And the answer is yes. According to Vox, had Elizabeth Warren’s proposed wealth tax been implemented, the collected tax revenue would have been sufficient to pay for public college three times over, all food assistance programs two times over and reduce poverty by 60%, and that is only for America. One can only imagine the extent towards which public services can be improved and poverty reduced if wealth tax was collected along with the usual tax revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only reason why countries and governments shy away from the idea of wealth tax is that they are controlled and dependent upon these super rich people. Their wealth is proportional to the power and sway they hold with the authorities. And the reason why many people don’t demand and argue for the same is because we live in a world that is shrouded by the farcical garb of productivity, where people believe that cheaper or free public services makes people lazy and incompetent instead of the idea that basic healthcare and education is a fundamental right that every individual deserves regardless of their &lt;em&gt;productivity and contribution&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this belief is not carried to the post pandemic world. COVID-19 has made us all painfully aware of the deficiencies in the existing system and structures. The fact that we need to change our priorities is inevitable, the awareness of the privilege of wealth and overwhelming wealth disparities is apparent and one can only hope that this awareness brings forth a change towards a kinder and more benevolent world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Ancient Greece was known for its military, culture, architecture and many important contributions to science, philosophy and astronomy. However, what was ignored under the discoveries of Pythagoras (yes, that triangle guy) and Plato was its innovative and frankly very sly system of taxation, which could be attributed to the beauty of the liturgy.</summary></entry></feed>