<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-11-19T16:51:01+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Quad: A New Chance for India</title><link href="/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Quad: A New Chance for India" /><published>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The coming together of four countries on the common grounds of democratic politics, pluralistic societies and market economies is believed to have been fueled by the aggressive expansionist policy(s) adopted by China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QUAD) first came up in the aftermath of the 2004 tsunami in the Indian Ocean to coordinate humanitarian responses to the devastation. While China has chosen to delay any formal statement on the coming together of the United States of America, Japan, India and Australia, a prominent editorial in a Chinese publication has called it America's &quot;hegemonic anxiety&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Few political observers and economic experts have also called out the QUAD as an attempt of the States to re-establish its position in the post-pandemic world with continued McDonaldisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Coming Together of the Quad&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst the attempts of the two superpowers (US and China) to establish their strong presence in the Indo-Pacific region, the QUAD offers India an opportunity to closely work with the developed economies and strategise for long-term infrastructure benefits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US, Japan and Australia are well-aware of the fact that India is the only substitute in the Indo-Pacific region that can counterbalance Chinese aggression. It is vital to note that India is the perfect state to handle China with its maritime presence along East Africa in the Indian Ocean and its location at the confluence of Southeast Asia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The four nations of the QUAD have agreed to work in cooperation in order to ensure a free and open Indo-Pacific, which will be both resilient and inclusive. The new areas of collaboration include cybersecurity, infrastructure, space, education and people-to-people relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On the ground of cybersecurity, India witnessed the second-highest number of cyber attacks in the world between 2016 and 2018 according to the Nasscom’s Data Security Council of India Report published in 2019. In 2020, India witnessed a total cost data breach of approximately $2 million on average. All of this comes at a time when India is predicted to have a digital economy valued at $435 billion by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India lacks a national cybersecurity policy and the adequate setup for it, which definitely calls for some assistance from it’s partners, in particular the US. The then Defence Minister Manohar Parrikar’s visit to the US Cyber Command in Fort Meade, MD, in 2016 definitely conveyed a message that both the countries are taking cybersecurity seriously and are working on the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The onset of the pandemic has brought the global supply chain to a halt. This looks like a remarkable opportunity for India to shuffle the cards in its favour and redraw the hub for manufacturing and production. While China is aggressively trying to capture the market, at least in the Indo-Pacific region; India can, with the able assistance of its partners, compete at par with its Asian neighbour. In a region dominated by Chinese products, India’s move to voice self-reliance and ‘vocal for local’ has been viewed as ‘brave’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Additionally, India is being viewed as the next viable option for investment in the post-COVID world as various developed nations have sought to move out their production units from China. Apple establishing a manufacturing base in India in collaboration with Foxconn is an example of this development. South Korea’s decision to shut its operation for Samsung in China and relocate its units to India should be viewed from the same lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In order to welcome more such developments, India has begun to identify land parcels. Not only will this uplift the Indian economy with more employment opportunities and infrastructural development, but shall also add to India’s role in the global supply chain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India’s Supply Chain Resilience&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India should view the above-mentioned scenario as a stepping stone instead of a milestone. It needs to explore the partnerships with the QUAD members and European nations that are both strategically and geopolitically aligned.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the post-COVID world, there is a consensus amongst nations to design trade policies to address vulnerabilities, reduce concentration and manage disruption. India can attract global value chains by leveraging these changes. The three principles - financing for resilience, addressing raw-material dependencies and attracting technology multinationals - will be guiding the country’s supply chain resilience within the QUAD.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To begin with, Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) and Foreign Institutional Investors (FII) in India have come mainly from the capital-rich countries of the OECD and G7 which include the UK, USA, Japan and Europe. These investments are received through financial centres like Mauritius, Netherlands and Singapore.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In order to make India an economic pivot for the QUAD in the Indo-Pacific region, it is essential that these nations commit to financing and supporting India’s entry into the supply chains that are led by them. Objectives such as &lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;enhancing the impact of multilateral public finance”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“mobilisation of private finance for development finance”&lt;/em&gt; have been announced by the QUAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, these objectives and the Supply Chain Resilience Initiative remain unsupported by any serious joint funding commitments. India needs to make alterations in its policies which shall make it business-friendly because without the support of capital-intensive industries like telecommunications and automobiles, it will be impossible for India to move forward.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Secondly, seeking entry into global value chains focused on telecommunications, electronics and electrical machinery should be a priority for India. Despite 40% of all FDI in India flowing into these sectors and electronic manufacturing growing at a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 23% in the past five years, India is still dependent on China for electrical machinery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, recent commitments of $7 billion by the Government of India for large-scale electronics manufacturing shows India’s commitment towards becoming a global hub for Electronics System Design and Manufacturing (ESDM).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, It is unfortunate to note that when India plans to further globalise its economy, most developed nations across the globe have begun to de-globalise by near-shoring or reshoring their economic activities in the post-COVID world. Multinationals corporations now have a choice to diversify their supply chains to manage risks arising from pandemics, climate change and conflicts. In order to choose diversification to India over reshoring, the QUAD needs to convince the multinational corporations of the strategic benefits of investing in India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thirdly, it is very important for India to diversify its own supply chains, especially the ones that it is the most dependent on. For instance, the onset of the pandemic revealed the world’s dependency on Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients (APIs), 70% of which were being controlled by China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, the critical minerals that are needed by India for various new-age industries like renewable energy and electronics come from very limited sources. It is quite ironic to read that India has the fifth largest deposits of rare-earths in the world but it accounts for only 2% of the global production.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There exists a very high degree of interdependence and concentration in the supply chains for chips, sophisticated displays and lithium-ion batteries between China, Taiwan, Japan, South Korea and the US. China is the leader in assembly, providing raw materials and fabrication. India has the potential of developing its own base and further collaborating with developing technologies with the investments from the QUAD members.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the above arguments, it can be concluded that the coming together of the QUAD is critical for India. It is in fact for the very first time that India is placed as an equal partner in a plurilateral organisation of major economies. India should leave no opportunity unexplored to build new habits of cooperation and leverage the old ones. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The coming together of four countries on the common grounds of democratic politics, pluralistic societies and market economies is believed to have been fueled by the aggressive expansionist policy(s) adopted by China.&amp;nbsp; The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QUAD) first came up in the aftermath of the 2004 tsunami in the Indian Ocean to coordinate humanitarian responses to the devastation. While China has chosen to delay any formal statement on the coming together of the United States of America, Japan, India and Australia, a prominent editorial in a Chinese publication has called it America's &quot;hegemonic anxiety&quot;.&amp;nbsp; Few political observers and economic experts have also called out the QUAD as an attempt of the States to re-establish its position in the post-pandemic world with continued McDonaldisation.&amp;nbsp; The Coming Together of the Quad&amp;nbsp; Amidst the attempts of the two superpowers (US and China) to establish their strong presence in the Indo-Pacific region, the QUAD offers India an opportunity to closely work with the developed economies and strategise for long-term infrastructure benefits.&amp;nbsp; The US, Japan and Australia are well-aware of the fact that India is the only substitute in the Indo-Pacific region that can counterbalance Chinese aggression. It is vital to note that India is the perfect state to handle China with its maritime presence along East Africa in the Indian Ocean and its location at the confluence of Southeast Asia.&amp;nbsp; The four nations of the QUAD have agreed to work in cooperation in order to ensure a free and open Indo-Pacific, which will be both resilient and inclusive. The new areas of collaboration include cybersecurity, infrastructure, space, education and people-to-people relations. On the ground of cybersecurity, India witnessed the second-highest number of cyber attacks in the world between 2016 and 2018 according to the Nasscom’s Data Security Council of India Report published in 2019. In 2020, India witnessed a total cost data breach of approximately $2 million on average. All of this comes at a time when India is predicted to have a digital economy valued at $435 billion by 2025. India lacks a national cybersecurity policy and the adequate setup for it, which definitely calls for some assistance from it’s partners, in particular the US. The then Defence Minister Manohar Parrikar’s visit to the US Cyber Command in Fort Meade, MD, in 2016 definitely conveyed a message that both the countries are taking cybersecurity seriously and are working on the same. The onset of the pandemic has brought the global supply chain to a halt. This looks like a remarkable opportunity for India to shuffle the cards in its favour and redraw the hub for manufacturing and production. While China is aggressively trying to capture the market, at least in the Indo-Pacific region; India can, with the able assistance of its partners, compete at par with its Asian neighbour. In a region dominated by Chinese products, India’s move to voice self-reliance and ‘vocal for local’ has been viewed as ‘brave’. Additionally, India is being viewed as the next viable option for investment in the post-COVID world as various developed nations have sought to move out their production units from China. Apple establishing a manufacturing base in India in collaboration with Foxconn is an example of this development. South Korea’s decision to shut its operation for Samsung in China and relocate its units to India should be viewed from the same lens. In order to welcome more such developments, India has begun to identify land parcels. Not only will this uplift the Indian economy with more employment opportunities and infrastructural development, but shall also add to India’s role in the global supply chain.&amp;nbsp; India’s Supply Chain Resilience&amp;nbsp; India should view the above-mentioned scenario as a stepping stone instead of a milestone. It needs to explore the partnerships with the QUAD members and European nations that are both strategically and geopolitically aligned.&amp;nbsp; In the post-COVID world, there is a consensus amongst nations to design trade policies to address vulnerabilities, reduce concentration and manage disruption. India can attract global value chains by leveraging these changes. The three principles - financing for resilience, addressing raw-material dependencies and attracting technology multinationals - will be guiding the country’s supply chain resilience within the QUAD.&amp;nbsp; To begin with, Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) and Foreign Institutional Investors (FII) in India have come mainly from the capital-rich countries of the OECD and G7 which include the UK, USA, Japan and Europe. These investments are received through financial centres like Mauritius, Netherlands and Singapore.&amp;nbsp; In order to make India an economic pivot for the QUAD in the Indo-Pacific region, it is essential that these nations commit to financing and supporting India’s entry into the supply chains that are led by them. Objectives such as “enhancing the impact of multilateral public finance” and “mobilisation of private finance for development finance” have been announced by the QUAD. However, these objectives and the Supply Chain Resilience Initiative remain unsupported by any serious joint funding commitments. India needs to make alterations in its policies which shall make it business-friendly because without the support of capital-intensive industries like telecommunications and automobiles, it will be impossible for India to move forward.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, seeking entry into global value chains focused on telecommunications, electronics and electrical machinery should be a priority for India. Despite 40% of all FDI in India flowing into these sectors and electronic manufacturing growing at a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 23% in the past five years, India is still dependent on China for electrical machinery.&amp;nbsp; However, recent commitments of $7 billion by the Government of India for large-scale electronics manufacturing shows India’s commitment towards becoming a global hub for Electronics System Design and Manufacturing (ESDM).&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, It is unfortunate to note that when India plans to further globalise its economy, most developed nations across the globe have begun to de-globalise by near-shoring or reshoring their economic activities in the post-COVID world. Multinationals corporations now have a choice to diversify their supply chains to manage risks arising from pandemics, climate change and conflicts. In order to choose diversification to India over reshoring, the QUAD needs to convince the multinational corporations of the strategic benefits of investing in India.&amp;nbsp; Thirdly, it is very important for India to diversify its own supply chains, especially the ones that it is the most dependent on. For instance, the onset of the pandemic revealed the world’s dependency on Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients (APIs), 70% of which were being controlled by China.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, the critical minerals that are needed by India for various new-age industries like renewable energy and electronics come from very limited sources. It is quite ironic to read that India has the fifth largest deposits of rare-earths in the world but it accounts for only 2% of the global production.&amp;nbsp; There exists a very high degree of interdependence and concentration in the supply chains for chips, sophisticated displays and lithium-ion batteries between China, Taiwan, Japan, South Korea and the US. China is the leader in assembly, providing raw materials and fabrication. India has the potential of developing its own base and further collaborating with developing technologies with the investments from the QUAD members.&amp;nbsp; From the above arguments, it can be concluded that the coming together of the QUAD is critical for India. It is in fact for the very first time that India is placed as an equal partner in a plurilateral organisation of major economies. India should leave no opportunity unexplored to build new habits of cooperation and leverage the old ones.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wall Street’s New Leviathan</title><link href="/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wall Street’s New Leviathan" /><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church.”&lt;/em&gt; (Matthew 16:18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are high you’ll find a person who knows about this Peter, the bedrock of Christianity – it is the religion with the greatest number of adherents, after all. About two millennia later, the modern-day Peter has emerged, albeit less popular.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans pride themselves on being intelligent people, the folks who are good at everything – from fast food to babysitting world peace. Even if we were to believe these claims, one thing they’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; good at is answering a simple question – ‘&lt;em&gt;How much is too much?&lt;/em&gt;’&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unanswered question has hurt the States time and again, and yet, answering it is &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; an ex-post job and not ex-ante. A decade after Wall Street fell victim to its own greed, regulations and investment trends of people who grew up through this collapse have shifted all headwinds to the buy-side, making them the new apex predators of what the country chooses to call capitalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the buy-side firms are becoming as large as pre-crash investment banks, one particular name stands apart from the rest – literally and figuratively. It controls $9.5 trillion worth of assets and chances are, you have not heard of this firm - BlackRock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm and its asset growth are the true embodiment of the word exponential. Compared to the century-old financial behemoths such as Deutsche Bank, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, BlackRock was founded in 1988, a meagre three-decade-old company.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founder Larry Fink was the man behind the infamous Mortgage-Backed Securities (MBS) market, which led to the 2008 crisis and subsequently his fall at Wall Street’s bulge bracket. Investment company First Boston used this as an opportunity and made him start an asset management firm: BlackRock, with an emphasis on risk management as their ace in the hole.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with a humble $5 million credit line from Blackstone, Fink and BlackRock quadrupled their assets within the year, a pace that continues till date - the firm adds a trillion to its asset base every year or so, which is the equivalent of saying it adds the &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; asset base of leading asset management firms till date, to its balance sheet every year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock is like a Swiss-Army knife. As you’d expect, it is difficult to find a sector where the firm is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in. Currently, it is an institutional investor, money manager, consultant and private equity firm. It effectively is involved on all sides of the table in most industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A funny example is that of the environment. In 2017, announcements were made to support ESG practices within owned firms and improve the investment landscape in sustainable practices with new products. Two years later, BlackRock was a major shareholder in every big oil company and in seven of the leading producers of the other black rock – coal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this became public knowledge, protests were staged outside of BlackRock‘s France division, leading Fink to announce an exit from coal and fossil fuel assets. Alongside, revelations were made of letters to the boards of companies to improve sustainability and gender diversity practices or risk losing business with BlackRock.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other times, it simply has stakes in leading competitors – Apple and Microsoft, Deutsche Bank, JP Morgan Chase and Wells Fargo, just to name a few. It simply cannot lose money unless the entire sector goes bust.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can figure out other conflicts as well – a company goes to raise debt and BlackRock, a major shareholder, is already out to be a buyer of this debt. BlackRock is an advisor to most firms it’s an investor in. The ownership structure should ring a few alarms as well – Vanguard, another asset manager and a direct competitor of BlackRock, is its biggest shareholder. Many institutions that BlackRock invests in, are shareholders of BlackRock themselves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another part of BlackRock’s business that took flight in 1999 and is dubbed as “&lt;em&gt;a tech start-up&lt;/em&gt;” by CEO Fink – Aladdin, the risk management system. One would be damned if their start-up was managing risk for $21.6 trillion worth of assets including those of the Federal Reserve Board and the European Central Bank. BlackRock’s internal ‘Tech 2025’ plan aims to make Aladdin the standard, and perhaps the only used risk management platform in the industry. But that’s a monopoly for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, BlackRock is begging to be labelled as the present-day Illuminati, but that isn’t the case. However, it is a marionettist in its own right, and here is where things get murky. Back in the mid-to-late 00’s, Goldman Sachs was well known for hiring prominent policymakers who would go on to be part of America’s cabinet and ensure nothing went too awry for Wall Street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 2008, one would expect that things would change and the blurred lines between White House and Wall Street would be redrawn but that’s the exact opposite of what happened. Who do you call when a set of financial products is threatening to, or rather, causing the biggest financial crisis in almost a century? Of course, it’s the creator!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the MBS markets were rearranging the food chain by the minute, one was eyeing the newly vacated spot of the apex predator – BlackRock. The Federal Reserve called in Fink and his team to manage the mess and has been a loyal customer ever since – be it Aladdin’s risk management, or an appropriate response to the coronavirus pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the pandemic hit, the Fed announced that it will purchase assets other than Treasury bonds as well – Corporate Bonds and Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs). Who else do we know as a major firm dealing in Corporate Bonds and ETFs? Do the math. The funds the Fed poured money in were a hit among retail investors and no prizes for guessing the issuer of the funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are conversant with US law, you must have thought at least once about how BlackRock is not under the purview of ‘too big to fail’ or why the Dodd-Frank reform, which has riddled the powerhouses of the sell-side with multiple regulations on risk-taking, is not handicapping their earning potential?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is the same as that with Goldman – it has multiple former executives in Washington and multiple former Washington policymakers reside at the 52nd Street in Manhattan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cosy revolving door is not just limited from Manhattan to Washington rather extends to Ottawa and Mexico City. For example, PEMEX, Mexico’s state-owned oil company was opened to private investment, and BlackRock quickly jumped in. Then it acquired a loss-making, scandalous private equity firm in the country, I Cuadrada, and a month down the line, Sierra Oil, a year-old portfolio company of the former, which had not had a project in its short life was awarded two major exploration contracts as the sole bidder.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock also holds the distinction of being the first global asset manager which has set up an onshore shop in China. There are multiple examples, from private to public sectors where the private firm has played on both sides of the court to benefit itself, earning the title of a white-collar mafia. Europe has dealt a stricter hand with criticism of the European Commission for awarding BlackRock a contract with a significant conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the common person was never directly under attack from this leviathan but as it extends its power, it now faces a direct confrontation with the people – housing. The American Dream has always consisted of owning a place you can call home, however, that soon might not be the case as BlackRock and multiple other funds are outbidding individuals or paying the entire amount upfront with no inspection. These bids are too sweet for developers to pass.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought this was excessive, mega-funds are buying out entire neighbourhoods for a few factors above the listed prices and immediately putting them out on exorbitant rents. A new monopoly is unfolding before us and one can only hope America finds an answer to its age-old dilemma sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his soul?”&lt;/em&gt; (Mark 8:36)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aaradhya Daga</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church.” (Matthew 16:18) Chances are high you’ll find a person who knows about this Peter, the bedrock of Christianity – it is the religion with the greatest number of adherents, after all. About two millennia later, the modern-day Peter has emerged, albeit less popular.&amp;nbsp; Americans pride themselves on being intelligent people, the folks who are good at everything – from fast food to babysitting world peace. Even if we were to believe these claims, one thing they’re not good at is answering a simple question – ‘How much is too much?’&amp;nbsp; This unanswered question has hurt the States time and again, and yet, answering it is still an ex-post job and not ex-ante. A decade after Wall Street fell victim to its own greed, regulations and investment trends of people who grew up through this collapse have shifted all headwinds to the buy-side, making them the new apex predators of what the country chooses to call capitalism.&amp;nbsp; While the buy-side firms are becoming as large as pre-crash investment banks, one particular name stands apart from the rest – literally and figuratively. It controls $9.5 trillion worth of assets and chances are, you have not heard of this firm - BlackRock. The firm and its asset growth are the true embodiment of the word exponential. Compared to the century-old financial behemoths such as Deutsche Bank, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, BlackRock was founded in 1988, a meagre three-decade-old company.&amp;nbsp; Founder Larry Fink was the man behind the infamous Mortgage-Backed Securities (MBS) market, which led to the 2008 crisis and subsequently his fall at Wall Street’s bulge bracket. Investment company First Boston used this as an opportunity and made him start an asset management firm: BlackRock, with an emphasis on risk management as their ace in the hole.&amp;nbsp; Starting with a humble $5 million credit line from Blackstone, Fink and BlackRock quadrupled their assets within the year, a pace that continues till date - the firm adds a trillion to its asset base every year or so, which is the equivalent of saying it adds the total asset base of leading asset management firms till date, to its balance sheet every year.&amp;nbsp; BlackRock is like a Swiss-Army knife. As you’d expect, it is difficult to find a sector where the firm is not in. Currently, it is an institutional investor, money manager, consultant and private equity firm. It effectively is involved on all sides of the table in most industries. A funny example is that of the environment. In 2017, announcements were made to support ESG practices within owned firms and improve the investment landscape in sustainable practices with new products. Two years later, BlackRock was a major shareholder in every big oil company and in seven of the leading producers of the other black rock – coal.&amp;nbsp; When this became public knowledge, protests were staged outside of BlackRock‘s France division, leading Fink to announce an exit from coal and fossil fuel assets. Alongside, revelations were made of letters to the boards of companies to improve sustainability and gender diversity practices or risk losing business with BlackRock.&amp;nbsp; Other times, it simply has stakes in leading competitors – Apple and Microsoft, Deutsche Bank, JP Morgan Chase and Wells Fargo, just to name a few. It simply cannot lose money unless the entire sector goes bust.&amp;nbsp; You can figure out other conflicts as well – a company goes to raise debt and BlackRock, a major shareholder, is already out to be a buyer of this debt. BlackRock is an advisor to most firms it’s an investor in. The ownership structure should ring a few alarms as well – Vanguard, another asset manager and a direct competitor of BlackRock, is its biggest shareholder. Many institutions that BlackRock invests in, are shareholders of BlackRock themselves.&amp;nbsp; There is another part of BlackRock’s business that took flight in 1999 and is dubbed as “a tech start-up” by CEO Fink – Aladdin, the risk management system. One would be damned if their start-up was managing risk for $21.6 trillion worth of assets including those of the Federal Reserve Board and the European Central Bank. BlackRock’s internal ‘Tech 2025’ plan aims to make Aladdin the standard, and perhaps the only used risk management platform in the industry. But that’s a monopoly for another time. At this point, BlackRock is begging to be labelled as the present-day Illuminati, but that isn’t the case. However, it is a marionettist in its own right, and here is where things get murky. Back in the mid-to-late 00’s, Goldman Sachs was well known for hiring prominent policymakers who would go on to be part of America’s cabinet and ensure nothing went too awry for Wall Street. After 2008, one would expect that things would change and the blurred lines between White House and Wall Street would be redrawn but that’s the exact opposite of what happened. Who do you call when a set of financial products is threatening to, or rather, causing the biggest financial crisis in almost a century? Of course, it’s the creator! When the MBS markets were rearranging the food chain by the minute, one was eyeing the newly vacated spot of the apex predator – BlackRock. The Federal Reserve called in Fink and his team to manage the mess and has been a loyal customer ever since – be it Aladdin’s risk management, or an appropriate response to the coronavirus pandemic.&amp;nbsp; As the pandemic hit, the Fed announced that it will purchase assets other than Treasury bonds as well – Corporate Bonds and Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs). Who else do we know as a major firm dealing in Corporate Bonds and ETFs? Do the math. The funds the Fed poured money in were a hit among retail investors and no prizes for guessing the issuer of the funds. If you are conversant with US law, you must have thought at least once about how BlackRock is not under the purview of ‘too big to fail’ or why the Dodd-Frank reform, which has riddled the powerhouses of the sell-side with multiple regulations on risk-taking, is not handicapping their earning potential? The answer is the same as that with Goldman – it has multiple former executives in Washington and multiple former Washington policymakers reside at the 52nd Street in Manhattan.&amp;nbsp; This cosy revolving door is not just limited from Manhattan to Washington rather extends to Ottawa and Mexico City. For example, PEMEX, Mexico’s state-owned oil company was opened to private investment, and BlackRock quickly jumped in. Then it acquired a loss-making, scandalous private equity firm in the country, I Cuadrada, and a month down the line, Sierra Oil, a year-old portfolio company of the former, which had not had a project in its short life was awarded two major exploration contracts as the sole bidder.&amp;nbsp; BlackRock also holds the distinction of being the first global asset manager which has set up an onshore shop in China. There are multiple examples, from private to public sectors where the private firm has played on both sides of the court to benefit itself, earning the title of a white-collar mafia. Europe has dealt a stricter hand with criticism of the European Commission for awarding BlackRock a contract with a significant conflict of interest. While the common person was never directly under attack from this leviathan but as it extends its power, it now faces a direct confrontation with the people – housing. The American Dream has always consisted of owning a place you can call home, however, that soon might not be the case as BlackRock and multiple other funds are outbidding individuals or paying the entire amount upfront with no inspection. These bids are too sweet for developers to pass.&amp;nbsp; If you thought this was excessive, mega-funds are buying out entire neighbourhoods for a few factors above the listed prices and immediately putting them out on exorbitant rents. A new monopoly is unfolding before us and one can only hope America finds an answer to its age-old dilemma sooner. “For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his soul?” (Mark 8:36)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Quad: A New Chance for India</title><link href="/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Quad: A New Chance for India" /><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The coming together of four countries on the common grounds of democratic politics, pluralistic societies and market economies is believed to have been fueled by the aggressive expansionist policy(s) adopted by China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QUAD) first came up in the aftermath of the 2004 tsunami in the Indian Ocean to coordinate humanitarian responses to the devastation. While China has chosen to delay any formal statement on the coming together of the United States of America, Japan, India and Australia, a prominent editorial in a Chinese publication has called it America's &quot;hegemonic anxiety&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Few political observers and economic experts have also called out the QUAD as an attempt of the States to re-establish its position in the post-pandemic world with continued McDonaldisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Coming Together of the Quad&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst the attempts of the two superpowers (US and China) to establish their strong presence in the Indo-Pacific region, the QUAD offers India an opportunity to closely work with the developed economies and strategise for long-term infrastructure benefits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US, Japan and Australia are well-aware of the fact that India is the only substitute in the Indo-Pacific region that can counterbalance Chinese aggression. It is vital to note that India is the perfect state to handle China with its maritime presence along East Africa in the Indian Ocean and its location at the confluence of Southeast Asia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The four nations of the QUAD have agreed to work in cooperation in order to ensure a free and open Indo-Pacific, which will be both resilient and inclusive. The new areas of collaboration include cybersecurity, infrastructure, space, education and people-to-people relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On the ground of cybersecurity, India witnessed the second-highest number of cyber attacks in the world between 2016 and 2018 according to the Nasscom’s Data Security Council of India Report published in 2019. In 2020, India witnessed a total cost data breach of approximately $2 million on average. All of this comes at a time when India is predicted to have a digital economy valued at $435 billion by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India lacks a national cybersecurity policy and the adequate setup for it, which definitely calls for some assistance from it’s partners, in particular the US. The then Defence Minister Manohar Parrikar’s visit to the US Cyber Command in Fort Meade, MD, in 2016 definitely conveyed a message that both the countries are taking cybersecurity seriously and are working on the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The onset of the pandemic has brought the global supply chain to a halt. This looks like a remarkable opportunity for India to shuffle the cards in its favour and redraw the hub for manufacturing and production. While China is aggressively trying to capture the market, at least in the Indo-Pacific region; India can, with the able assistance of its partners, compete at par with its Asian neighbour. In a region dominated by Chinese products, India’s move to voice self-reliance and ‘vocal for local’ has been viewed as ‘brave’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Additionally, India is being viewed as the next viable option for investment in the post-COVID world as various developed nations have sought to move out their production units from China. Apple establishing a manufacturing base in India in collaboration with Foxconn is an example of this development. South Korea’s decision to shut its operation for Samsung in China and relocate its units to India should be viewed from the same lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In order to welcome more such developments, India has begun to identify land parcels. Not only will this uplift the Indian economy with more employment opportunities and infrastructural development, but shall also add to India’s role in the global supply chain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India’s Supply Chain Resilience&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India should view the above-mentioned scenario as a stepping stone instead of a milestone. It needs to explore the partnerships with the QUAD members and European nations that are both strategically and geopolitically aligned.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the post-COVID world, there is a consensus amongst nations to design trade policies to address vulnerabilities, reduce concentration and manage disruption. India can attract global value chains by leveraging these changes. The three principles - financing for resilience, addressing raw-material dependencies and attracting technology multinationals - will be guiding the country’s supply chain resilience within the QUAD.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To begin with, Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) and Foreign Institutional Investors (FII) in India have come mainly from the capital-rich countries of the OECD and G7 which include the UK, USA, Japan and Europe. These investments are received through financial centres like Mauritius, Netherlands and Singapore.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In order to make India an economic pivot for the QUAD in the Indo-Pacific region, it is essential that these nations commit to financing and supporting India’s entry into the supply chains that are led by them. Objectives such as &lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;enhancing the impact of multilateral public finance”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“mobilisation of private finance for development finance”&lt;/em&gt; have been announced by the QUAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, these objectives and the Supply Chain Resilience Initiative remain unsupported by any serious joint funding commitments. India needs to make alterations in its policies which shall make it business-friendly because without the support of capital-intensive industries like telecommunications and automobiles, it will be impossible for India to move forward.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Secondly, seeking entry into global value chains focused on telecommunications, electronics and electrical machinery should be a priority for India. Despite 40% of all FDI in India flowing into these sectors and electronic manufacturing growing at a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 23% in the past five years, India is still dependent on China for electrical machinery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, recent commitments of $7 billion by the Government of India for large-scale electronics manufacturing shows India’s commitment towards becoming a global hub for Electronics System Design and Manufacturing (ESDM).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, It is unfortunate to note that when India plans to further globalise its economy, most developed nations across the globe have begun to de-globalise by near-shoring or reshoring their economic activities in the post-COVID world. Multinationals corporations now have a choice to diversify their supply chains to manage risks arising from pandemics, climate change and conflicts. In order to choose diversification to India over reshoring, the QUAD needs to convince the multinational corporations of the strategic benefits of investing in India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thirdly, it is very important for India to diversify its own supply chains, especially the ones that it is the most dependent on. For instance, the onset of the pandemic revealed the world’s dependency on Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients (APIs), 70% of which were being controlled by China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, the critical minerals that are needed by India for various new-age industries like renewable energy and electronics come from very limited sources. It is quite ironic to read that India has the fifth largest deposits of rare-earths in the world but it accounts for only 2% of the global production.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There exists a very high degree of interdependence and concentration in the supply chains for chips, sophisticated displays and lithium-ion batteries between China, Taiwan, Japan, South Korea and the US. China is the leader in assembly, providing raw materials and fabrication. India has the potential of developing its own base and further collaborating with developing technologies with the investments from the QUAD members.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the above arguments, it can be concluded that the coming together of the QUAD is critical for India. It is in fact for the very first time that India is placed as an equal partner in a plurilateral organisation of major economies. India should leave no opportunity unexplored to build new habits of cooperation and leverage the old ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The coming together of four countries on the common grounds of democratic politics, pluralistic societies and market economies is believed to have been fueled by the aggressive expansionist policy(s) adopted by China.&amp;nbsp; The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QUAD) first came up in the aftermath of the 2004 tsunami in the Indian Ocean to coordinate humanitarian responses to the devastation. While China has chosen to delay any formal statement on the coming together of the United States of America, Japan, India and Australia, a prominent editorial in a Chinese publication has called it America's &quot;hegemonic anxiety&quot;.&amp;nbsp; Few political observers and economic experts have also called out the QUAD as an attempt of the States to re-establish its position in the post-pandemic world with continued McDonaldisation.&amp;nbsp; The Coming Together of the Quad&amp;nbsp; Amidst the attempts of the two superpowers (US and China) to establish their strong presence in the Indo-Pacific region, the QUAD offers India an opportunity to closely work with the developed economies and strategise for long-term infrastructure benefits.&amp;nbsp; The US, Japan and Australia are well-aware of the fact that India is the only substitute in the Indo-Pacific region that can counterbalance Chinese aggression. It is vital to note that India is the perfect state to handle China with its maritime presence along East Africa in the Indian Ocean and its location at the confluence of Southeast Asia.&amp;nbsp; The four nations of the QUAD have agreed to work in cooperation in order to ensure a free and open Indo-Pacific, which will be both resilient and inclusive. The new areas of collaboration include cybersecurity, infrastructure, space, education and people-to-people relations. On the ground of cybersecurity, India witnessed the second-highest number of cyber attacks in the world between 2016 and 2018 according to the Nasscom’s Data Security Council of India Report published in 2019. In 2020, India witnessed a total cost data breach of approximately $2 million on average. All of this comes at a time when India is predicted to have a digital economy valued at $435 billion by 2025. India lacks a national cybersecurity policy and the adequate setup for it, which definitely calls for some assistance from it’s partners, in particular the US. The then Defence Minister Manohar Parrikar’s visit to the US Cyber Command in Fort Meade, MD, in 2016 definitely conveyed a message that both the countries are taking cybersecurity seriously and are working on the same. The onset of the pandemic has brought the global supply chain to a halt. This looks like a remarkable opportunity for India to shuffle the cards in its favour and redraw the hub for manufacturing and production. While China is aggressively trying to capture the market, at least in the Indo-Pacific region; India can, with the able assistance of its partners, compete at par with its Asian neighbour. In a region dominated by Chinese products, India’s move to voice self-reliance and ‘vocal for local’ has been viewed as ‘brave’. Additionally, India is being viewed as the next viable option for investment in the post-COVID world as various developed nations have sought to move out their production units from China. Apple establishing a manufacturing base in India in collaboration with Foxconn is an example of this development. South Korea’s decision to shut its operation for Samsung in China and relocate its units to India should be viewed from the same lens. In order to welcome more such developments, India has begun to identify land parcels. Not only will this uplift the Indian economy with more employment opportunities and infrastructural development, but shall also add to India’s role in the global supply chain.&amp;nbsp; India’s Supply Chain Resilience&amp;nbsp; India should view the above-mentioned scenario as a stepping stone instead of a milestone. It needs to explore the partnerships with the QUAD members and European nations that are both strategically and geopolitically aligned.&amp;nbsp; In the post-COVID world, there is a consensus amongst nations to design trade policies to address vulnerabilities, reduce concentration and manage disruption. India can attract global value chains by leveraging these changes. The three principles - financing for resilience, addressing raw-material dependencies and attracting technology multinationals - will be guiding the country’s supply chain resilience within the QUAD.&amp;nbsp; To begin with, Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) and Foreign Institutional Investors (FII) in India have come mainly from the capital-rich countries of the OECD and G7 which include the UK, USA, Japan and Europe. These investments are received through financial centres like Mauritius, Netherlands and Singapore.&amp;nbsp; In order to make India an economic pivot for the QUAD in the Indo-Pacific region, it is essential that these nations commit to financing and supporting India’s entry into the supply chains that are led by them. Objectives such as “enhancing the impact of multilateral public finance” and “mobilisation of private finance for development finance” have been announced by the QUAD. However, these objectives and the Supply Chain Resilience Initiative remain unsupported by any serious joint funding commitments. India needs to make alterations in its policies which shall make it business-friendly because without the support of capital-intensive industries like telecommunications and automobiles, it will be impossible for India to move forward.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, seeking entry into global value chains focused on telecommunications, electronics and electrical machinery should be a priority for India. Despite 40% of all FDI in India flowing into these sectors and electronic manufacturing growing at a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 23% in the past five years, India is still dependent on China for electrical machinery.&amp;nbsp; However, recent commitments of $7 billion by the Government of India for large-scale electronics manufacturing shows India’s commitment towards becoming a global hub for Electronics System Design and Manufacturing (ESDM).&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, It is unfortunate to note that when India plans to further globalise its economy, most developed nations across the globe have begun to de-globalise by near-shoring or reshoring their economic activities in the post-COVID world. Multinationals corporations now have a choice to diversify their supply chains to manage risks arising from pandemics, climate change and conflicts. In order to choose diversification to India over reshoring, the QUAD needs to convince the multinational corporations of the strategic benefits of investing in India.&amp;nbsp; Thirdly, it is very important for India to diversify its own supply chains, especially the ones that it is the most dependent on. For instance, the onset of the pandemic revealed the world’s dependency on Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients (APIs), 70% of which were being controlled by China.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, the critical minerals that are needed by India for various new-age industries like renewable energy and electronics come from very limited sources. It is quite ironic to read that India has the fifth largest deposits of rare-earths in the world but it accounts for only 2% of the global production.&amp;nbsp; There exists a very high degree of interdependence and concentration in the supply chains for chips, sophisticated displays and lithium-ion batteries between China, Taiwan, Japan, South Korea and the US. China is the leader in assembly, providing raw materials and fabrication. India has the potential of developing its own base and further collaborating with developing technologies with the investments from the QUAD members.&amp;nbsp; From the above arguments, it can be concluded that the coming together of the QUAD is critical for India. It is in fact for the very first time that India is placed as an equal partner in a plurilateral organisation of major economies. India should leave no opportunity unexplored to build new habits of cooperation and leverage the old ones.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Optimistic Economics</title><link href="/Optimistic-Economics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Optimistic Economics" /><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Optimistic-Economics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Optimistic-Economics">&lt;p&gt;Reason and expectations have a peculiar connection. It would seem that expectations emanate from reasonable assumptions or logical discourse amongst the public. Facts are juxtaposed with their probabilities and resource capacities, and then expectations are formed. However, the opposite happens. Popular reason derives from the people’s expectations. People find a way to justify what they expect. But how are their expectations formed?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the former half of 2020, when some parts of the world, including India, were experiencing the lethal first wave of COVID-19, predictions of economic recovery were more or less inclined towards a swoosh-shaped recovery. It is a layman’s way to state that an economy would first experience a sharp plunge, a slow rebound and an even slower recovery in the long term. There is a major role of expectations in the economy after this. But before that, it is important to know the expectations. People thought a V-shaped economic recovery was too optimistic. So, they discounted their optimism a little to come down to the level of reality. They shaped their predictions to expect a recovery only a little slower compared to the V-shaped, which boiled their expectations down to a U-shaped recovery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first wave of COVID-19 in 2020, the world still suffered from optimism bias because they had not yet felt the shock of the second wave. Financial analysts across the world predicted a K-shaped recovery, which stands to mean that after an economy crashes, some sectors not only recover but scale up to more than pre-recession levels, and some sectors plummet even below the pre-recession levels. This happens because there was an anticipation of an approaching second wave in the world. It made the majority of the population increase its acceptance of the virtual means of entertainment, education, pharmacy, and shopping etc.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This culminated in thriving ed-tech, internet pharmacy, over the top (OTT) platforms and e-commerce businesses. Taking the complete picture into account, this is resources reallocation in play: schools and coaching centres to ed-tech, local chemist shops to internet pharmacies, cable TVs and cinemas to OTT platforms and from local stores and malls to e-commerce. Hence, just the expectation of a second wave brought about such a drastic change not only in the GDP increase from -24% in the first quarter of 2020-21 to 1.64% in the fourth quarter of 2020-21 but also in the composition of GDP due to the increased contribution of some sectors and decreasing contribution of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A noteworthy observation in this interplay of people’s expectations and economic outcomes is that you would never find L-shaped, W-shaped or Z-shaped recoveries in these predictions, however hard you hunt. In case you are wondering if it is because of the low probability of these recovery shapes, then let me tell you it is not so.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Great Depression of the 1930’s is a testament to the reality of L-shaped economic recoveries when the economy experiences a sudden crash followed by stagnation in GDP and persistent unemployment over a long period. L-shape signifies the most horrendous recovery prospects because it essentially means no recovery at all for a considerable period. It stands for lost incomes and production. It is a nightmare, to say the least. Even India in the 1960’s and 1970’s lost a major portion of its production owing to wars with hostile neighbours and global oil price shocks. Japan experienced the same in 1989 and the following decade, which is often called the Lost Decade for Japan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the pre-2008 years as well, people, as well as the governments, failed to acknowledge any possibility of an economic collapse even in the face of public debates and discussions about the approaching collapse of the housing bubble in the United States and the consequent financial crisis. People’s optimistic expectations led them to invest more and more in the housing market to expand it so much that when the bubble burst, not just the US but the whole world felt the economic shock.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even today, when the debate about a post-COVID economic recovery is piping hot across the world, there are fewer economists and even fewer people talking about L or W or Z shaped recoveries even though a W or Z shaped recovery seems almost logical. A W-shaped recovery is when an economic recession is followed by a recovery attempt, unfortunately leading to another economic crash followed by a steady recovery. The incoming nature of the second wave of COVID-19 wave in 2020 should have warranted predictions of a W-shaped recovery, logically speaking. However, even in the survey of financial analysts across the world, only 11% thought that a W-shaped recovery would be imminent. Even a Z-shaped recovery that symbolises an economy that first experiences a sudden crash, recovery followed by another recession would seem likely. But these ideas were rarely found in post-COVID expectations and predictions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, there is a major tilt towards optimism when people talk about economic recovery. The idea of economic recovery is covertly hazy in people’s minds. It is unnecessarily associated with utopian optimism. In economics, they call it pro-growth expectations.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of India, the first and second waves of COVID-19 blatantly exposed the ill state of education and health infrastructure in the country, depriving millions of poor children of a year or more of learning and giving hundreds of people an ignominious death of oxygen scarcity. Millions of workers migrating across states on foot lay bare the callous anomalies of the informal sector and urban economy based on casual labour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time a crisis happens, it does well to expose the loopholes of the economic system. In the face of such shocks, how the governments and the people respond determines how the economy responds. As discussed, V, U and swoosh-shaped recoveries lie at the heart of most macroeconomic predictions. This optimism is reflected in the stock market bubble. With the Government of India’s numerous lines of credit and welfare schemes flowing like water to stimulate the economy, investor sentiment and consumer demand are positive as well. Whether this is a bubble that will burst in the following three to four years or would it be accompanied by correction mechanisms to culminate in long-term growth will largely depend on the actions of financial institutions and governments. Simply put, for all optimists, a V is out of reach now, and a U or swoosh is some reforms away!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Priyal Batheja</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Reason and expectations have a peculiar connection. It would seem that expectations emanate from reasonable assumptions or logical discourse amongst the public. Facts are juxtaposed with their probabilities and resource capacities, and then expectations are formed. However, the opposite happens. Popular reason derives from the people’s expectations. People find a way to justify what they expect. But how are their expectations formed?&amp;nbsp; In the former half of 2020, when some parts of the world, including India, were experiencing the lethal first wave of COVID-19, predictions of economic recovery were more or less inclined towards a swoosh-shaped recovery. It is a layman’s way to state that an economy would first experience a sharp plunge, a slow rebound and an even slower recovery in the long term. There is a major role of expectations in the economy after this. But before that, it is important to know the expectations. People thought a V-shaped economic recovery was too optimistic. So, they discounted their optimism a little to come down to the level of reality. They shaped their predictions to expect a recovery only a little slower compared to the V-shaped, which boiled their expectations down to a U-shaped recovery.&amp;nbsp; After the first wave of COVID-19 in 2020, the world still suffered from optimism bias because they had not yet felt the shock of the second wave. Financial analysts across the world predicted a K-shaped recovery, which stands to mean that after an economy crashes, some sectors not only recover but scale up to more than pre-recession levels, and some sectors plummet even below the pre-recession levels. This happens because there was an anticipation of an approaching second wave in the world. It made the majority of the population increase its acceptance of the virtual means of entertainment, education, pharmacy, and shopping etc.&amp;nbsp; This culminated in thriving ed-tech, internet pharmacy, over the top (OTT) platforms and e-commerce businesses. Taking the complete picture into account, this is resources reallocation in play: schools and coaching centres to ed-tech, local chemist shops to internet pharmacies, cable TVs and cinemas to OTT platforms and from local stores and malls to e-commerce. Hence, just the expectation of a second wave brought about such a drastic change not only in the GDP increase from -24% in the first quarter of 2020-21 to 1.64% in the fourth quarter of 2020-21 but also in the composition of GDP due to the increased contribution of some sectors and decreasing contribution of others.&amp;nbsp; A noteworthy observation in this interplay of people’s expectations and economic outcomes is that you would never find L-shaped, W-shaped or Z-shaped recoveries in these predictions, however hard you hunt. In case you are wondering if it is because of the low probability of these recovery shapes, then let me tell you it is not so.&amp;nbsp; The Great Depression of the 1930’s is a testament to the reality of L-shaped economic recoveries when the economy experiences a sudden crash followed by stagnation in GDP and persistent unemployment over a long period. L-shape signifies the most horrendous recovery prospects because it essentially means no recovery at all for a considerable period. It stands for lost incomes and production. It is a nightmare, to say the least. Even India in the 1960’s and 1970’s lost a major portion of its production owing to wars with hostile neighbours and global oil price shocks. Japan experienced the same in 1989 and the following decade, which is often called the Lost Decade for Japan.&amp;nbsp; In the pre-2008 years as well, people, as well as the governments, failed to acknowledge any possibility of an economic collapse even in the face of public debates and discussions about the approaching collapse of the housing bubble in the United States and the consequent financial crisis. People’s optimistic expectations led them to invest more and more in the housing market to expand it so much that when the bubble burst, not just the US but the whole world felt the economic shock.&amp;nbsp; Even today, when the debate about a post-COVID economic recovery is piping hot across the world, there are fewer economists and even fewer people talking about L or W or Z shaped recoveries even though a W or Z shaped recovery seems almost logical. A W-shaped recovery is when an economic recession is followed by a recovery attempt, unfortunately leading to another economic crash followed by a steady recovery. The incoming nature of the second wave of COVID-19 wave in 2020 should have warranted predictions of a W-shaped recovery, logically speaking. However, even in the survey of financial analysts across the world, only 11% thought that a W-shaped recovery would be imminent. Even a Z-shaped recovery that symbolises an economy that first experiences a sudden crash, recovery followed by another recession would seem likely. But these ideas were rarely found in post-COVID expectations and predictions.&amp;nbsp; Needless to say, there is a major tilt towards optimism when people talk about economic recovery. The idea of economic recovery is covertly hazy in people’s minds. It is unnecessarily associated with utopian optimism. In economics, they call it pro-growth expectations.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In the case of India, the first and second waves of COVID-19 blatantly exposed the ill state of education and health infrastructure in the country, depriving millions of poor children of a year or more of learning and giving hundreds of people an ignominious death of oxygen scarcity. Millions of workers migrating across states on foot lay bare the callous anomalies of the informal sector and urban economy based on casual labour.&amp;nbsp; Every time a crisis happens, it does well to expose the loopholes of the economic system. In the face of such shocks, how the governments and the people respond determines how the economy responds. As discussed, V, U and swoosh-shaped recoveries lie at the heart of most macroeconomic predictions. This optimism is reflected in the stock market bubble. With the Government of India’s numerous lines of credit and welfare schemes flowing like water to stimulate the economy, investor sentiment and consumer demand are positive as well. Whether this is a bubble that will burst in the following three to four years or would it be accompanied by correction mechanisms to culminate in long-term growth will largely depend on the actions of financial institutions and governments. Simply put, for all optimists, a V is out of reach now, and a U or swoosh is some reforms away!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evergrande: A Cave-in of Real Estate?</title><link href="/Evergrande" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evergrande: A Cave-in of Real Estate?" /><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Evergrande</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Evergrande">&lt;p&gt;The year 2020 was the worst year for economic growth since World War II - all economies came to a standstill with the raging spread of the virus. However, China, the country where the first outbreak of COVID-19 was reported, was the only major economy in the world to report a positive GDP growth in that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to November 2021, the second-largest economy seems to be in a precarious situation with various credit rating firms cutting down on its growth forecasts owing to glaring uncertainties in the nation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my last article, I covered &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;China's crackdown on its tech sector&lt;/a&gt;. Now the ball has come rolling to its real estate sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergrande Group, China's second-largest property developer and the world’s most indebted real estate firm with liabilities amounting to $300 billion, informed bondholders in early September about its inability to honour its interest obligation. (For context, Russia's state debt &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.themoscowtimes.com/2021/02/24/russias-government-debt-rose-40-in-2020-a73044&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;in 2020 was $257 billion&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergrande was founded by Mr Xu Jiayin, who was once the country’s richest man, in 1996, and was in the bottled water business. Later the company expanded into several areas, including pig farming, owning a football club, wealth management and the electric car segment. However, it was its real estate business for which it was widely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, it recorded a gross profit of nearly $19 billion and in the year before that, it was on the Fortune Global 500 list. The company owns 2% of all newly-constructed real estate in China and employs about 200,000 people directly and helps in sustaining more than 3.8 million jobs indirectly every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possible collapse of an organisation this big can be brushed aside as a one-time occurrence, however, one cannot turn a blind eye when many such firms in that line of business are on the same path: Chinese luxury developer Fantasia Holding Group and the Sinic Holdings group have also announced a default on their debt repayment obligations in mid-October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cause of worry intensifies when one observes that around 30% of China’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is related to its real estate sector. Therefore, the fall of real estate companies can leave a dent not only in the Chinese economy but the global economy as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The State Of Real Estate In China&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980's, China started moving from public housing to the commercial property model. Post-1994, The central government decentralised the goals and interests of the policymakers - passing the responsibility of social welfare services to local administration but with taxes to be submitted back to them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imbalance of funds led provincial governments to create state-owned shell companies called Local Government Financing Vehicles (LGFV). They gave these LGFV free valuable lands which were then used to take out loans that the administration themselves could not. Consequently, this made the administration seem healthier because their debt was now hidden while at the same time they met quotas set by Beijing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, land became the backbone of local economies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, steep discounts and low-interest rates were offered to citizens as an act of welfare. Strict regulation by the government on how much money leaves the country left citizens with limited investment options - stock markets became synonymous with volatility and risk and housing gained the reputation of safe and profitable investments in the country. Housing prices were also such that they fell only once in the two decades that followed the Asian Financial Crisis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the aforementioned reasons, real estate is one of the most loved sectors of the economy with homeownership in China being the highest in the world, i.e. around 90%. It has become the country's leading pillar of economic growth with a contribution of around 15-30% to the GDP. In the COVID-19 period alone, the sector has grown by 4.9%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, an unusual trend is seen in the country. The boom in real estate is coming at a cost: high vacancy rates in cities due to the vast majority of home purchases being second/third homes. In 2018, 87% of new home buyers already owned at least one flat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the societal norm in China is such that male marriages demand homeownership. Decades of the one-child policy have resulted in an imbalance between males and females with scales tipping in favour of the latter. As a result, female families have become awfully picky, with the groom's homeownership being one of the prerequisites. As per a study, home prices are higher in cities of disproportionate male-to-female ratios.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cities like Shenzhen, Beijing, Shanghai - it takes nearly 40 years worth of an accumulated average income to afford a home. Thus the vast majority of homes are purchased even before the construction has begun, sometimes years in advance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With overhead demand, some developers undertake techniques such as selling batches of properties in glitzy online events or through raffles-off in lotteries where thousands of apartments are often sold out in minutes, giving the winners mere hours to submit down payments or lose the opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What all these instances, numbers and facts point towards is that of a speculative market, i.e. the assumption that prices would only go up.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the demographic of the country suggests otherwise. In the next ten years, the country’s over-55 cohort will increase in size by 120 million, but by the end of the century, the overall population will be cut in half. The majority of present home buyers are precisely from this segment which China would soon lose. In addition, with age, home requirements keep differing.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was reasonable to anticipate a decade ago that the rapid urbanisation demand would be met by bringing in more than enough migrants to effectively cancel out the effects of ageing. Nonetheless, the statistics prove otherwise with the migration rate falling below the country’s 60% urbanisation rate. Moreover, such exorbitant home prices act as a further deterrent to the very people that were to be attracted by the construction of so many homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the demand-supply misproportion is haunting the real estate space.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coming Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the context of speculative and overpriced real estate being understood, what consequences are in store, given the defaults of Evergrande and other real estate firms?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trigger for this fall is attributed to new guidelines, known as The Red Lines, introduced by the government in August 2020 for property developers. The rule requires the ratio of liabilities-to-assets of developers and their net debt-to-equity ratio to be below 70% and 100% respectively whilst requiring real estate firms to maintain the cash-to-short term debt ratio at a minimum of 100%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any borrower failing to meet these requirements would be restricted from raising more funds, practically cutting off developers from taking on more debts. This means a complete alteration in the nature of the real estate business, which relies heavily on borrowing for its capital requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown on developers is in line with China’s supremo Xi Jinping's slogan of ‘Common Prosperity’, where the estate market is being regulated so as to puncture the property bubble and make housing more affordable. Some also see this as an example of the government taking on influential private businessmen under the guise of the ‘common prosperity’ programme to fight income inequality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule is about-turn, the government previously encouraged developers to take on huge debt through the heavily state-controlled financial sector to develop new properties. In the past, they have even bailed out troubled business entities thereby leading to the indiscriminate allocation of resources to the sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per an analyst, “&lt;em&gt;A regime shift is occurring without necessarily the markets fully comprehending the enormous underlying change to the structure of the economy.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many have called the Evergrande fiasco China’s own ‘Lehman moment', alluding to the failure of the US bank Lehman Brothers, which precipitated the 2008 financial crisis. Some observers believe that the current crisis was a long time coming owing to the company's unsustainable business model.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012, Andrew Left of Citron Research argued that Evergrande was insolvent and that the company was engaged in aggressive accounting practices to cover up its troubles.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was said that the company held properties that it could not sell on its balance sheet as inventory, thus avoiding the booking of losses. The company was also accused of running a Ponzi scheme as it relied on the constant inflow of funds to prop up a business model that is fundamentally unsustainable. Interestingly, Evergrande has over the years consistently reported strong profits and has showcased a strong balance sheet with sufficient liquid assets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A letter leaked last year by &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; showed Evergrande’s executives seeking financial assistance from the Chinese government by admitting their inability to meet their debt obligations to banks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per a &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; report, the administration is potentially going ahead with the restructuring of debt. The company has sold off various units at a discounted price to meet funding requirements. The organisation's deal with state-owned Yuexiu Property to sell a 51% stake in its property services unit has also been put on hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markets are closely observing the Chinese economic environment owing to growing uncertainties. Various countries are concerned about a possible slowdown resulting from the rebalancing of the economy away from the property sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China is the biggest steel importer and a drop in construction activities would affect the global steel prices. The IMF has estimated that a fall of 1% in demand from China would decrease global GDP by 25%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese administration has sent a clear signal: the only expectation one should have is unpredictability and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The year 2020 was the worst year for economic growth since World War II - all economies came to a standstill with the raging spread of the virus. However, China, the country where the first outbreak of COVID-19 was reported, was the only major economy in the world to report a positive GDP growth in that year. Fast forward to November 2021, the second-largest economy seems to be in a precarious situation with various credit rating firms cutting down on its growth forecasts owing to glaring uncertainties in the nation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In my last article, I covered China's crackdown on its tech sector. Now the ball has come rolling to its real estate sector.&amp;nbsp; Evergrande Group, China's second-largest property developer and the world’s most indebted real estate firm with liabilities amounting to $300 billion, informed bondholders in early September about its inability to honour its interest obligation. (For context, Russia's state debt in 2020 was $257 billion.) Evergrande was founded by Mr Xu Jiayin, who was once the country’s richest man, in 1996, and was in the bottled water business. Later the company expanded into several areas, including pig farming, owning a football club, wealth management and the electric car segment. However, it was its real estate business for which it was widely known. In 2020, it recorded a gross profit of nearly $19 billion and in the year before that, it was on the Fortune Global 500 list. The company owns 2% of all newly-constructed real estate in China and employs about 200,000 people directly and helps in sustaining more than 3.8 million jobs indirectly every year. The possible collapse of an organisation this big can be brushed aside as a one-time occurrence, however, one cannot turn a blind eye when many such firms in that line of business are on the same path: Chinese luxury developer Fantasia Holding Group and the Sinic Holdings group have also announced a default on their debt repayment obligations in mid-October. The cause of worry intensifies when one observes that around 30% of China’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is related to its real estate sector. Therefore, the fall of real estate companies can leave a dent not only in the Chinese economy but the global economy as well.&amp;nbsp; The State Of Real Estate In China&amp;nbsp; In the late 1980's, China started moving from public housing to the commercial property model. Post-1994, The central government decentralised the goals and interests of the policymakers - passing the responsibility of social welfare services to local administration but with taxes to be submitted back to them.&amp;nbsp; The imbalance of funds led provincial governments to create state-owned shell companies called Local Government Financing Vehicles (LGFV). They gave these LGFV free valuable lands which were then used to take out loans that the administration themselves could not. Consequently, this made the administration seem healthier because their debt was now hidden while at the same time they met quotas set by Beijing.&amp;nbsp; As a result, land became the backbone of local economies.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, steep discounts and low-interest rates were offered to citizens as an act of welfare. Strict regulation by the government on how much money leaves the country left citizens with limited investment options - stock markets became synonymous with volatility and risk and housing gained the reputation of safe and profitable investments in the country. Housing prices were also such that they fell only once in the two decades that followed the Asian Financial Crisis.&amp;nbsp; Due to the aforementioned reasons, real estate is one of the most loved sectors of the economy with homeownership in China being the highest in the world, i.e. around 90%. It has become the country's leading pillar of economic growth with a contribution of around 15-30% to the GDP. In the COVID-19 period alone, the sector has grown by 4.9%.&amp;nbsp; However, an unusual trend is seen in the country. The boom in real estate is coming at a cost: high vacancy rates in cities due to the vast majority of home purchases being second/third homes. In 2018, 87% of new home buyers already owned at least one flat.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, the societal norm in China is such that male marriages demand homeownership. Decades of the one-child policy have resulted in an imbalance between males and females with scales tipping in favour of the latter. As a result, female families have become awfully picky, with the groom's homeownership being one of the prerequisites. As per a study, home prices are higher in cities of disproportionate male-to-female ratios.&amp;nbsp; In cities like Shenzhen, Beijing, Shanghai - it takes nearly 40 years worth of an accumulated average income to afford a home. Thus the vast majority of homes are purchased even before the construction has begun, sometimes years in advance.&amp;nbsp; With overhead demand, some developers undertake techniques such as selling batches of properties in glitzy online events or through raffles-off in lotteries where thousands of apartments are often sold out in minutes, giving the winners mere hours to submit down payments or lose the opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; What all these instances, numbers and facts point towards is that of a speculative market, i.e. the assumption that prices would only go up.&amp;nbsp; However the demographic of the country suggests otherwise. In the next ten years, the country’s over-55 cohort will increase in size by 120 million, but by the end of the century, the overall population will be cut in half. The majority of present home buyers are precisely from this segment which China would soon lose. In addition, with age, home requirements keep differing.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It was reasonable to anticipate a decade ago that the rapid urbanisation demand would be met by bringing in more than enough migrants to effectively cancel out the effects of ageing. Nonetheless, the statistics prove otherwise with the migration rate falling below the country’s 60% urbanisation rate. Moreover, such exorbitant home prices act as a further deterrent to the very people that were to be attracted by the construction of so many homes.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the demand-supply misproportion is haunting the real estate space.&amp;nbsp; Coming Back With the context of speculative and overpriced real estate being understood, what consequences are in store, given the defaults of Evergrande and other real estate firms?&amp;nbsp; The trigger for this fall is attributed to new guidelines, known as The Red Lines, introduced by the government in August 2020 for property developers. The rule requires the ratio of liabilities-to-assets of developers and their net debt-to-equity ratio to be below 70% and 100% respectively whilst requiring real estate firms to maintain the cash-to-short term debt ratio at a minimum of 100%.&amp;nbsp; Any borrower failing to meet these requirements would be restricted from raising more funds, practically cutting off developers from taking on more debts. This means a complete alteration in the nature of the real estate business, which relies heavily on borrowing for its capital requirements.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown on developers is in line with China’s supremo Xi Jinping's slogan of ‘Common Prosperity’, where the estate market is being regulated so as to puncture the property bubble and make housing more affordable. Some also see this as an example of the government taking on influential private businessmen under the guise of the ‘common prosperity’ programme to fight income inequality. This rule is about-turn, the government previously encouraged developers to take on huge debt through the heavily state-controlled financial sector to develop new properties. In the past, they have even bailed out troubled business entities thereby leading to the indiscriminate allocation of resources to the sector.&amp;nbsp; As per an analyst, “A regime shift is occurring without necessarily the markets fully comprehending the enormous underlying change to the structure of the economy.” Many have called the Evergrande fiasco China’s own ‘Lehman moment', alluding to the failure of the US bank Lehman Brothers, which precipitated the 2008 financial crisis. Some observers believe that the current crisis was a long time coming owing to the company's unsustainable business model.&amp;nbsp; In 2012, Andrew Left of Citron Research argued that Evergrande was insolvent and that the company was engaged in aggressive accounting practices to cover up its troubles.&amp;nbsp; It was said that the company held properties that it could not sell on its balance sheet as inventory, thus avoiding the booking of losses. The company was also accused of running a Ponzi scheme as it relied on the constant inflow of funds to prop up a business model that is fundamentally unsustainable. Interestingly, Evergrande has over the years consistently reported strong profits and has showcased a strong balance sheet with sufficient liquid assets.&amp;nbsp; A letter leaked last year by Bloomberg showed Evergrande’s executives seeking financial assistance from the Chinese government by admitting their inability to meet their debt obligations to banks.&amp;nbsp; As per a Bloomberg report, the administration is potentially going ahead with the restructuring of debt. The company has sold off various units at a discounted price to meet funding requirements. The organisation's deal with state-owned Yuexiu Property to sell a 51% stake in its property services unit has also been put on hold. Markets are closely observing the Chinese economic environment owing to growing uncertainties. Various countries are concerned about a possible slowdown resulting from the rebalancing of the economy away from the property sector.&amp;nbsp; China is the biggest steel importer and a drop in construction activities would affect the global steel prices. The IMF has estimated that a fall of 1% in demand from China would decrease global GDP by 25%. The Chinese administration has sent a clear signal: the only expectation one should have is unpredictability and nothing more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data</title><link href="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-Our-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data" /><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-Our-Data</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-Our-Data">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData, #MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary The Great Hack have brought the issue to the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data, I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for ‘nefarious’ - I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual - purposes on a whole, the tool known as data analytics has brought far more benefits than harm to society…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to the full session here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-2&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/2021-11-04-The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-Our-Data.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Or watch it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f_0aWrVURq4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; width: 100%; height: 0; padding-top: 56.2500%;
 padding-bottom: 48px; box-shadow: 0 2px 8px 0 rgba(63,69,81,0.16); margin-top: 1.6em; margin-bottom: 0.9em; overflow: hidden;
 border-radius: 8px; will-change: transform;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; style=&quot;position: absolute; width: 100%; height: 100%; top: 0; left: 0; border: none; padding: 0;margin: 0;&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.canva.com&amp;#x2F;design&amp;#x2F;DAEm-hZBeLc&amp;#x2F;view?embed&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;*This session was recorded at Qworky Academy on 14th August 2021 and moderated by &lt;a href=&quot;/author/kheeran.naidu/&quot;&gt;Kheeran Naidu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Avinash Naidu</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="featured" /><category term="the-faraday-corner" /><category term="podcast" /><summary type="html">In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData, #MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary The Great Hack have brought the issue to the limelight.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The PMC Bank Fiasco</title><link href="/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The PMC Bank Fiasco" /><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With great power come greater scams. &lt;/em&gt;This is evidently a mantra for India. Politicians getting named in large scams and then using their power to sway the decisions of government bodies has become a typical sight in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative (PMC) bank fiasco is not the first time a major scam has been unearthed which has left a financial institution and its depositors in complete shambles. Call it misgovernance or blindsight of the management - borrowing from one bank to repay another bank has become a common&amp;nbsp;practice&amp;nbsp;in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fraud to the tune of ₹6,500 billion was found in the books of the PMC bank, all of which were loans extended to only a single borrower: Housing Development and Infrastructure Limited (HDIL). This amount was way beyond the statutory limit set by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) for lending to a single entity. Yet the senior management kept quiet on the matter until they were thrown under the bus by the managing director in his confession letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relations between the Wadhawan group and the PMC bank have prevailed since the 1980's, wherein the former had saved the latter from the brink of a financial collapse quite a few times by infusing capital and keeping a majority of their deposits with the establishment. Thus, aiding the PMC bank to maintain the liquidity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But every&amp;nbsp;good story&amp;nbsp;has an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As HDIL’s business started to grow, and their capital requirements grew multifold, the group started to transact with larger banks in order to meet their needs. This hindered the profitability of the cooperative bank as the majority of the institution’s revenue was attributed to transactions in the Wadhawan group’s accounts. Hence, upon request the group started banking with PMC again after a short span of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018-19, the bank had reported a profit of ₹996.9 million in its annual report. The bank showed 3.76% of advances (₹8,3830 million) as gross non-performing assets (NPAs), which was fair as compared to public sector banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, things started to go awry when a few projects undertaken by HDIL were shelved, and this resulted in a liquidity crunch. Consequently, the bank started defaulting on all the loans it had taken from other banks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, due to the past repayment record of the group, the bank continued to treat the loan as a standard loan. But when the loan amount snowballed to more than 73% of the bank’s total exposure, the issue came into the limelight and a strict moratorium was put upon the bank by the RBI. Hence, it's clear that the bank gave false monetary reports to cover its dangerous loan mess and the alleged collusion with HDIL and other firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prevent panic and loss of public confidence, all the depositors were barred from withdrawing more than ₹1,000, but later the withdrawal limit was capped at ₹100,000 per depositor until further notice. In addition to the complaint that was filed with the authorities, the board of directors were suspended and the Wadhawan family members were arrested. The Enforcement Directorate, India's economic offences investigator, even seized movable and immovable assets of approximately&amp;nbsp; ₹40 billion in connection with the case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole case was nothing but another instance of corporate misgovernance and partial treatment to a particular lender by the senior management of banks, just like in the case of the Punjab National Bank scam.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fiasco could have been prevented had the institution increased its collateral against the loans disbursed and classified the Wadhawan group’s account as a NPA at the right time. The central bank should have learned its lesson post the PNB scam, and could have increased its due diligence on public sector banks by placing stricter checks and reporting standards on these financial institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July 2021, the RBI approved the bid of Centrum Financial Services (CFS) and BharatPe to jointly take over the crisis driven cooperative bank, thereby providing some respite to its depositors. The president of BharatPe group said, “One thing was clear in our discussion with RBI that the interest of depositors is supreme”, further emphasising on the management's future intent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RBI was initially reluctant in giving an in-principle nod to the two institutions to set up a small finance bank (SFB), however, it has finally given the licence and has even gone on to provide a lot of other statutory reliefs to the new entity to be jointly formed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different points of view on the RBI's decision to pick Centrum-BharatPe for the takeover of one of the largest cooperative banks in India. A section of the bank’s depositors are unhappy with the decision, as they preferred an established commercial bank to take over the entity rather than a new licensee with no direct experience of running a regular bank.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CFS and BharatPe are set to infuse ₹5 billion each into the new entity when starting over and will increase the capital up to ₹30 billion in due course. Additionally, they also have the option to restructure the liability and convert them into capital instruments, take support from the Depositor Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) for repayment of insured deposits up to ₹50,000, phase withdrawal plans for individuals with higher deposits or convert the same into tier 1 or tier 2 capital.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joint venture is likely to form a good synergy between BharatPe and Centrum Financial Services. While the former is an establishment specialising in fintech with a strong footprint in the digital lending and Unified Payment Interface (UPI) industry, the latter is a non-banking lender with strong holdings and a good history in providing credit to small-mid size firms. Together they can bring innovation and renewed vigour to a fallen institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new entity is to be operational in 120 days post the principal nod given by the central banking authority, and only post this, will the RBI draft a scheme on amalgamation of the two entities with PMC Bank. The plan will then be sent to the government for approval and official notification. Under Section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, only a bank can be merged with another, therefore, the process of handover will start only once the SFB (Small Finance Bank) is created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, the subsidiaries of Centrum namely Centrum Housing Finance and Centrum Microcredit are in the same business as the small finance bank to be set up by them. Hence, this poses a hurdle for Centrum, as one cannot have separate entities doing the same business. Either it will have to sell its majority stake or merge the subsidiaries; or not enter the microcredit and home loan business from the SFB set up, which would mean giving up a major business opportunity for the new joint venture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RBI has now called for sweeping changes in the Banking Regulation Act, and will be actively looking into the regulation of cooperative banks to avoid such a future debacle. But the problem doesn't stop there, the problem only begins here. India massively lacks transparency in the financial sector and this often puts a lot of wrongdoings away from the eyes of the public and regulatory bodies. There are more important questions that this mess raises. The first being, will the public institutions continue to show vigilance only after the chaos unfolds or will they ever learn to step in the moment the lines are crossed?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samyak Jain</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">With great power come greater scams. This is evidently a mantra for India. Politicians getting named in large scams and then using their power to sway the decisions of government bodies has become a typical sight in the country. The Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative (PMC) bank fiasco is not the first time a major scam has been unearthed which has left a financial institution and its depositors in complete shambles. Call it misgovernance or blindsight of the management - borrowing from one bank to repay another bank has become a common&amp;nbsp;practice&amp;nbsp;in India. A fraud to the tune of ₹6,500 billion was found in the books of the PMC bank, all of which were loans extended to only a single borrower: Housing Development and Infrastructure Limited (HDIL). This amount was way beyond the statutory limit set by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) for lending to a single entity. Yet the senior management kept quiet on the matter until they were thrown under the bus by the managing director in his confession letter. Relations between the Wadhawan group and the PMC bank have prevailed since the 1980's, wherein the former had saved the latter from the brink of a financial collapse quite a few times by infusing capital and keeping a majority of their deposits with the establishment. Thus, aiding the PMC bank to maintain the liquidity.&amp;nbsp; But every&amp;nbsp;good story&amp;nbsp;has an end. As HDIL’s business started to grow, and their capital requirements grew multifold, the group started to transact with larger banks in order to meet their needs. This hindered the profitability of the cooperative bank as the majority of the institution’s revenue was attributed to transactions in the Wadhawan group’s accounts. Hence, upon request the group started banking with PMC again after a short span of time. In 2018-19, the bank had reported a profit of ₹996.9 million in its annual report. The bank showed 3.76% of advances (₹8,3830 million) as gross non-performing assets (NPAs), which was fair as compared to public sector banks. However, things started to go awry when a few projects undertaken by HDIL were shelved, and this resulted in a liquidity crunch. Consequently, the bank started defaulting on all the loans it had taken from other banks.&amp;nbsp; Initially, due to the past repayment record of the group, the bank continued to treat the loan as a standard loan. But when the loan amount snowballed to more than 73% of the bank’s total exposure, the issue came into the limelight and a strict moratorium was put upon the bank by the RBI. Hence, it's clear that the bank gave false monetary reports to cover its dangerous loan mess and the alleged collusion with HDIL and other firms. To prevent panic and loss of public confidence, all the depositors were barred from withdrawing more than ₹1,000, but later the withdrawal limit was capped at ₹100,000 per depositor until further notice. In addition to the complaint that was filed with the authorities, the board of directors were suspended and the Wadhawan family members were arrested. The Enforcement Directorate, India's economic offences investigator, even seized movable and immovable assets of approximately&amp;nbsp; ₹40 billion in connection with the case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; This whole case was nothing but another instance of corporate misgovernance and partial treatment to a particular lender by the senior management of banks, just like in the case of the Punjab National Bank scam.&amp;nbsp; This fiasco could have been prevented had the institution increased its collateral against the loans disbursed and classified the Wadhawan group’s account as a NPA at the right time. The central bank should have learned its lesson post the PNB scam, and could have increased its due diligence on public sector banks by placing stricter checks and reporting standards on these financial institutions.&amp;nbsp; In July 2021, the RBI approved the bid of Centrum Financial Services (CFS) and BharatPe to jointly take over the crisis driven cooperative bank, thereby providing some respite to its depositors. The president of BharatPe group said, “One thing was clear in our discussion with RBI that the interest of depositors is supreme”, further emphasising on the management's future intent.&amp;nbsp; The RBI was initially reluctant in giving an in-principle nod to the two institutions to set up a small finance bank (SFB), however, it has finally given the licence and has even gone on to provide a lot of other statutory reliefs to the new entity to be jointly formed.&amp;nbsp; There are different points of view on the RBI's decision to pick Centrum-BharatPe for the takeover of one of the largest cooperative banks in India. A section of the bank’s depositors are unhappy with the decision, as they preferred an established commercial bank to take over the entity rather than a new licensee with no direct experience of running a regular bank.&amp;nbsp; CFS and BharatPe are set to infuse ₹5 billion each into the new entity when starting over and will increase the capital up to ₹30 billion in due course. Additionally, they also have the option to restructure the liability and convert them into capital instruments, take support from the Depositor Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) for repayment of insured deposits up to ₹50,000, phase withdrawal plans for individuals with higher deposits or convert the same into tier 1 or tier 2 capital.&amp;nbsp; The joint venture is likely to form a good synergy between BharatPe and Centrum Financial Services. While the former is an establishment specialising in fintech with a strong footprint in the digital lending and Unified Payment Interface (UPI) industry, the latter is a non-banking lender with strong holdings and a good history in providing credit to small-mid size firms. Together they can bring innovation and renewed vigour to a fallen institution.&amp;nbsp; The new entity is to be operational in 120 days post the principal nod given by the central banking authority, and only post this, will the RBI draft a scheme on amalgamation of the two entities with PMC Bank. The plan will then be sent to the government for approval and official notification. Under Section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, only a bank can be merged with another, therefore, the process of handover will start only once the SFB (Small Finance Bank) is created. Apart from that, the subsidiaries of Centrum namely Centrum Housing Finance and Centrum Microcredit are in the same business as the small finance bank to be set up by them. Hence, this poses a hurdle for Centrum, as one cannot have separate entities doing the same business. Either it will have to sell its majority stake or merge the subsidiaries; or not enter the microcredit and home loan business from the SFB set up, which would mean giving up a major business opportunity for the new joint venture. The RBI has now called for sweeping changes in the Banking Regulation Act, and will be actively looking into the regulation of cooperative banks to avoid such a future debacle. But the problem doesn't stop there, the problem only begins here. India massively lacks transparency in the financial sector and this often puts a lot of wrongdoings away from the eyes of the public and regulatory bodies. There are more important questions that this mess raises. The first being, will the public institutions continue to show vigilance only after the chaos unfolds or will they ever learn to step in the moment the lines are crossed?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II</title><link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II" /><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II">&lt;p&gt;In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked &lt;em&gt;en masse, &lt;/em&gt;as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=8&amp;amp;v=fvoWoMIwr-g&amp;amp;feature=emb_logo&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in&lt;/a&gt; which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp; A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp; The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp; Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp; Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp; Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp; While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp; As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp; In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp; In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp; Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp; In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp; “In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked en masse, as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.” Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp; Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp; Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I</title><link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I" /><published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I">&lt;p&gt;“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (&lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt;) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of &lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt; is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named &lt;em&gt;Bala&lt;/em&gt; was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: &lt;em&gt;Gully Boy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Super 30&lt;/em&gt; and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called &lt;em&gt;Khali Peeli&lt;/em&gt; came under attack for having a song titled &lt;em&gt;Beyonce Sharma Jayegi&lt;/em&gt; (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“&lt;em&gt;tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi&lt;/em&gt;”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. &lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt;, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in &lt;em&gt;Ghost In The Shell&lt;/em&gt; (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the &lt;em&gt;MCU&lt;/em&gt; (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in &lt;em&gt;Dear White People&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (Snow White) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of Snow White is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism. To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp; Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp; In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named Bala was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: Gully Boy, Super 30 and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called Khali Peeli came under attack for having a song titled Beyonce Sharma Jayegi (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp; Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp; In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp; Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. Fate: The Winx Saga, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon Winx Club, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the Twilight series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in Ghost In The Shell (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the MCU (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in Aloha (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp; In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in Bridgerton and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp; Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in Dear White People). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in Bridgerton or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from Bridgerton.&amp;nbsp; All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp; Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp; The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp; In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job. Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Future of Energy!</title><link href="/The-Future-of-Energy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Energy!" /><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Future-of-Energy-</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Future-of-Energy">&lt;p&gt;With the latest round of global climate talks coming up in a few weeks, all eyes are set on our world leaders and their stand on the issue. The members of business groups, media, civil society, etc, will gather for the event to express their views and concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The global climate conference will be held in Glasgow, United Kingdom and can be referred to as the COP26 (Conference of the Parties to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-convention/what-is-the-united-nations-framework-convention-on-climate-change&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1992 United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;). The nations have finally realised the impacts of climate change and the need to counter it.	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of renewable energy is being promoted across continents in order to cut carbon emissions and hence, decarbonise the planet. At present, the major renewable energy resources are centered around solar, wind and water energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However recently, Green Hydrogen has been making headlines, owed mainly to its ease and efficient mode of production. Unlike coal and oil, it only emits water vapours and with hydrogen being the most abundant element available to us, this gas has the potential to be used across industries. Some observers even dub it as the ‘fuel of the future’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, there are a few challenges which need to be dealt with before this hydrogen produced fuel makes its way to commercial and domestic use. Until now, hydrogen is used as a building block to produce other carbon-neutral synthetic fuels. Use of pure hydrogen as an energy source is a fairly new practice and thus, new infrastructure and technology will be a prerequisite.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive in to understand the so-called future of energy!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is green hydrogen and how is it produced?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green hydrogen is a hydrogen fuel which is formed using renewable resources instead of fossil fuels. The generation of green hydrogen is done through the chemical process of electrolysis. This process separates the hydrogen from oxygen in water with the help of an electric current. It can help in supplying up to 25% of the world’s energy needs. The entire process is sustainable and can help cut carbon emissions by a huge amount.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost of production and other challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of production of green hydrogen is very expensive. In a report published in 2019, the&amp;nbsp;International Energy Agency (IEA)&amp;nbsp;puts the cost of producing green hydrogen at&amp;nbsp;$3-$7.50 per kilo, compared to the production cost of $0.90- $3.20 of steam methane reformation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrolysers constitute a major proportion of the costs involved and it needs to be cut down in order to make the production process effective. According to the claims of IEA, This will only be possible by 2040.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storage and transportation of green hydrogen is not an easy task either. It is a highly inflammable gas and requires a lot of space, making steel pipes and welds brittle, and prone to failure. A safe transportation of the gas requires construction of pipelines which would eventually add to the price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the major uses of green hydrogen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green hydrogen is an efficient and sustainable source of energy which makes it an attractive source. It can be applied across various industries, thus making its versatility a lucrative option for big business houses and nations. Issues pertaining to storage and transportation do not impede its acceptance as they are not just exclusive to this fuel alone.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green hydrogen in the Indian context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is already working on various sustainable energy projects. It has emerged as the sixth largest producer of wind and solar energy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a developing country, which is yet to fully realise its potential, investing in sustainable energy is a huge dilemma. Nonetheless, the nation has never backed out of protocols and has always supported the steps needed to be taken to curb global emissions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the country’s 75th Independence Day, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the government’s vision of making the nation ‘energy independent by 2047’. This goal is a very ambitious target for a country which heavily relies on fossil fuels for its energy requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech, he also initiated the National Hydrogen Mission (NHM) to curb global warming, consequently accelerating the country’s pace of embarking on the sustainable journey. The Ministry of New and Renewable Energy has been undertaking&amp;nbsp; research &amp;amp; developmental programmes on the sustainable future including hydrogen fuels. Additionally, the country has collaborated with Norway to manufacture India-centric technology for green hydrogen production.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Kerry, the US presidential envoy for climate, in his visit to India in September 2021, also launched the Climate Action and Finance Mobilisation Dialogue (CAFMD) under India-US Climate Clean Energy Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main objectives of CAFMD is finance mobilisation which would focus on attracting capital and technologies for India to scale up its renewable energy generation capacities. The US envoy said, ”&lt;em&gt;Over the past months, six of the largest banks in America had publicly committed to investing a minimum of $4.16 trillion in the next 10 years to make the transition happen&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nations such as Germany are extending financial help outside their region for investment in sustainable projects, particularly relating to green hydrogen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, China is the largest producer of green hydrogen with an output of 20 million ton. The European Union is also following the same steps by investing heavily in this fuel. Their extensive network of underground pipelines and storage facilities would enable them to store and even have the potential to transport green hydrogen across the continent. This can act to their advantage by allowing them to dominate the green hydrogen market in the near future. Oil rich nations such as Oman and Saudi Arabia are also proceeding in this direction.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter of 2021-22, Mukesh Ambani, the chairman of the largest company of the country - Reliance Industries, unveiled the company's push into green energy by committing to invest $10.1 billion in the sector by 2024. This investment will involve setting up energy production plants (including those for hydrogen fuels) and building battery grids to store electricity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coal shortage in India in early October 2021 and the consequent fears of power blackouts gives us yet another reason to move to an untapped and unlimited source of sustainable energy. The mass availability and properties of hydrogen seems to be the perfect alternative for most of our energy needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every nation is on the move to decarbonise, and is looking for sustainable substitutes for mass production with lower costs. The goal of minimum cost will be achieved in future by means of economies of scale, however at present, it is essential to make the investments with new and appropriate infrastructure and technology. This will require time and consistent efforts but the outcome makes it worth the effort.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first major step towards a sustainable planet has been taken and many more are yet to come.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll have to wait till COP26 to find out about the latest green initiatives our world leaders have in store for us, till then let's all make a conscious effort to move towards sustainable habits in day-to-day lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">With the latest round of global climate talks coming up in a few weeks, all eyes are set on our world leaders and their stand on the issue. The members of business groups, media, civil society, etc, will gather for the event to express their views and concerns.&amp;nbsp; The global climate conference will be held in Glasgow, United Kingdom and can be referred to as the COP26 (Conference of the Parties to the&amp;nbsp;1992 United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change). The nations have finally realised the impacts of climate change and the need to counter it. The use of renewable energy is being promoted across continents in order to cut carbon emissions and hence, decarbonise the planet. At present, the major renewable energy resources are centered around solar, wind and water energy. However recently, Green Hydrogen has been making headlines, owed mainly to its ease and efficient mode of production. Unlike coal and oil, it only emits water vapours and with hydrogen being the most abundant element available to us, this gas has the potential to be used across industries. Some observers even dub it as the ‘fuel of the future’. Nonetheless, there are a few challenges which need to be dealt with before this hydrogen produced fuel makes its way to commercial and domestic use. Until now, hydrogen is used as a building block to produce other carbon-neutral synthetic fuels. Use of pure hydrogen as an energy source is a fairly new practice and thus, new infrastructure and technology will be a prerequisite.&amp;nbsp; Let's dive in to understand the so-called future of energy!&amp;nbsp; What is green hydrogen and how is it produced? Green hydrogen is a hydrogen fuel which is formed using renewable resources instead of fossil fuels. The generation of green hydrogen is done through the chemical process of electrolysis. This process separates the hydrogen from oxygen in water with the help of an electric current. It can help in supplying up to 25% of the world’s energy needs. The entire process is sustainable and can help cut carbon emissions by a huge amount.&amp;nbsp; Cost of production and other challenges The cost of production of green hydrogen is very expensive. In a report published in 2019, the&amp;nbsp;International Energy Agency (IEA)&amp;nbsp;puts the cost of producing green hydrogen at&amp;nbsp;$3-$7.50 per kilo, compared to the production cost of $0.90- $3.20 of steam methane reformation.&amp;nbsp; Electrolysers constitute a major proportion of the costs involved and it needs to be cut down in order to make the production process effective. According to the claims of IEA, This will only be possible by 2040.&amp;nbsp; Storage and transportation of green hydrogen is not an easy task either. It is a highly inflammable gas and requires a lot of space, making steel pipes and welds brittle, and prone to failure. A safe transportation of the gas requires construction of pipelines which would eventually add to the price.&amp;nbsp; What are the major uses of green hydrogen? Green hydrogen is an efficient and sustainable source of energy which makes it an attractive source. It can be applied across various industries, thus making its versatility a lucrative option for big business houses and nations. Issues pertaining to storage and transportation do not impede its acceptance as they are not just exclusive to this fuel alone.&amp;nbsp; Green hydrogen in the Indian context India is already working on various sustainable energy projects. It has emerged as the sixth largest producer of wind and solar energy.&amp;nbsp; For a developing country, which is yet to fully realise its potential, investing in sustainable energy is a huge dilemma. Nonetheless, the nation has never backed out of protocols and has always supported the steps needed to be taken to curb global emissions.&amp;nbsp; On the country’s 75th Independence Day, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the government’s vision of making the nation ‘energy independent by 2047’. This goal is a very ambitious target for a country which heavily relies on fossil fuels for its energy requirements.&amp;nbsp; In his speech, he also initiated the National Hydrogen Mission (NHM) to curb global warming, consequently accelerating the country’s pace of embarking on the sustainable journey. The Ministry of New and Renewable Energy has been undertaking&amp;nbsp; research &amp;amp; developmental programmes on the sustainable future including hydrogen fuels. Additionally, the country has collaborated with Norway to manufacture India-centric technology for green hydrogen production.&amp;nbsp; John Kerry, the US presidential envoy for climate, in his visit to India in September 2021, also launched the Climate Action and Finance Mobilisation Dialogue (CAFMD) under India-US Climate Clean Energy Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp; One of the main objectives of CAFMD is finance mobilisation which would focus on attracting capital and technologies for India to scale up its renewable energy generation capacities. The US envoy said, ”Over the past months, six of the largest banks in America had publicly committed to investing a minimum of $4.16 trillion in the next 10 years to make the transition happen”.&amp;nbsp; Nations such as Germany are extending financial help outside their region for investment in sustainable projects, particularly relating to green hydrogen.&amp;nbsp; Currently, China is the largest producer of green hydrogen with an output of 20 million ton. The European Union is also following the same steps by investing heavily in this fuel. Their extensive network of underground pipelines and storage facilities would enable them to store and even have the potential to transport green hydrogen across the continent. This can act to their advantage by allowing them to dominate the green hydrogen market in the near future. Oil rich nations such as Oman and Saudi Arabia are also proceeding in this direction.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In the first quarter of 2021-22, Mukesh Ambani, the chairman of the largest company of the country - Reliance Industries, unveiled the company's push into green energy by committing to invest $10.1 billion in the sector by 2024. This investment will involve setting up energy production plants (including those for hydrogen fuels) and building battery grids to store electricity.&amp;nbsp; The coal shortage in India in early October 2021 and the consequent fears of power blackouts gives us yet another reason to move to an untapped and unlimited source of sustainable energy. The mass availability and properties of hydrogen seems to be the perfect alternative for most of our energy needs.&amp;nbsp; Every nation is on the move to decarbonise, and is looking for sustainable substitutes for mass production with lower costs. The goal of minimum cost will be achieved in future by means of economies of scale, however at present, it is essential to make the investments with new and appropriate infrastructure and technology. This will require time and consistent efforts but the outcome makes it worth the effort.&amp;nbsp; The first major step towards a sustainable planet has been taken and many more are yet to come.&amp;nbsp; We’ll have to wait till COP26 to find out about the latest green initiatives our world leaders have in store for us, till then let's all make a conscious effort to move towards sustainable habits in day-to-day lives.</summary></entry></feed>