<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-09T17:41:18+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Call for Concord to Capitalise</title><link href="/Concord-to-Capitalise" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Call for Concord to Capitalise" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Concord-to-Capitalise</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Concord-to-Capitalise">&lt;p&gt;Peace is a term of our lexicon that has been a part of the discourse vis-a-vis our mind, between communities, within nations, and across boundaries. It is defined as a concept of societal camaraderie in the absence of hostility and violence. We’re well acquainted with the ironic word ‘peace-keeping forces’ which entail and propagate the use of force and coercion to maintain the virtue of peace, which should come naturally to us otherwise. Correlation between peace and other disciplines like political science, psychology, geography, cognitive science, anthropology and sociology is prevalent. However, little do we know that there is a strong nexus between peace and economics. They are central to each other and act as catalysts in each other’s process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start from the beginning. The austerity of the post-Second World War world isn’t unknown to us. The cost of human lives and their intangible grief is a deep loss that can neither be redressed nor measured using a statistical tool. Talking in monetary terms, the governments of both the axis and allied forces lost about $1 trillion in a war. Here comes the importance of peace and peace enabling structures from a financial point of view as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a discipline that acts as a bridge between development and harmony. ‘Peace Economics’ is a specialised division of economics. It focuses on the creation of the landscape’s political, economic, and cultural institutions and aims at preventing, alleviating, and reconciling the violent conflict between and within societies using relevant policies. Violent conflict can both be latent or active. Peace Economics talks about the benefits of rebuilding and restoring societies based on our presumed knowledge of the cost of violence. Peace Economics has a sweeping view of attaining stable and irrevocable peace. The use of economics here is to comprehend the causes and the repercussions of hostility thereafter in the international system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another definition of the subject has been furnished by Jan Tinbergen, a Nobel prize winner in Economics. As per his scrutiny economic science is made use of to preclude war. It is used as an instrument to settle the disputes among nations and design a world order where warfare is punished. It encircles the concept of negative peace which is a word coined by Johan Galtung that equals the absence of aggression and not the presence of peace. To throw a little more light on this through a simple question, does the absence of poverty in a nation necessarily indicate the presence of opulence? A major exclusion from these definitions is the reference to international relations and no mention of civil war or violence at the individual level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a recognition that Peace Economics forms a part of both positive and normative economics. For those who are alien to these rather heavy-sounding terms, the former simply studies economic phenomena with the ‘what is’ backdrop, that is with facts and figures of the current situation. Whereas the latter as the name suggests covers the ‘what ought to be’ perspective by furnishing corrective recommendations and solutions. Contemporary economists prefer positive economics to evaluate the policies as they are and give relevant suggestions thereafter. On the other hand, normative economics sets the ‘norm’ for peace and then looks for systems that help realise this norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable economic growth can’t be achieved without peace and peace is at risk without sustainable economic growth. The above quip safely interlaces the two subjects. When governments, for instance, make sure to eradicate youth radicalisation by investing in labour-intensive public projects, it leads to full and efficient utilisation of potential, thereby assuring their operation as resources on the Production Possibility Curve (PPC) and not inside it. They become an asset for their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quoting an example of trade here. A free trade zone is created and a treaty signed not just with the goal of bettering bilateral or multilateral relations but also facilitating the promotion of peace. The trail of this link can be traced from the 19th century, a classic case of the English Tory rebels. A modern-day illustration of the same is the South Asian Free Trade Area which ensures non-belligerent relations in the region and promises peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dating back to 1914, during the First World War there was a peace conference held in Paris. A book titled &lt;em&gt;The Economic Consequences of the Peace&lt;/em&gt; by John Maynard Keynes came into being and stated how the terms of the allies regarding truce were financially impossible to achieve for Germany and how those acted as a stimulant in encouraging them to stand steadfast, again. Keynes’ theory also very explicitly mentioned the high rise in employment being conducive to peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crunching some numbers and putting facts into the picture, the global economy is liable to pay more than $14 trillion a year owing to conflict according to the World Economic Forum. The breakdown includes spending on the military, internal security, conflict losses, and crime. India, to be specific, forfeited 9% of its GDP due to friction in 2018. It was on the 136th rank in the Global Peace Index out of 163 nations. Down at the bottom was the war-torn Syria which had to lose a massive 68% of its GDP. Iceland is at the top of this list. Another intriguing certitude is that the countries which are placed higher on the Global Peace Index have observed trends of per capita GDP growing thrice as fast as those which are not as peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important for international organisations like the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund (IMF) to bolster the presence of an infrastructure that ameliorates the livelihoods of those indulged in any sort of clash. Governments need to take affirmative actions with peacebuilding attempts at the core, philanthropists and businesses should contribute and comply with the directives. An instance of the same from the new world order is of Colombia. Over 100 companies in the country marched forward towards peace by coupling their own advertising with the national peace campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crucial reform would be to ensure domestic violence between intimate partners, workplace violence and even self-harm forms the nucleus of present-day research for peace studies. This will go a long way in delivering positive solutions and will make resorting to violence inconceivable. The Institute for Economics and Peace, a think tank is developing a yardstick to analyse peace and quantify its economic value. This will act as a concrete step in laying a firm association between peace and prosperity. Let’s hope for a world in which this theme is self-explanatory and doesn’t have to be this persuasive. Let’s live for the day when world peace isn’t a pipe dream anymore.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushi Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Peace is a term of our lexicon that has been a part of the discourse vis-a-vis our mind, between communities, within nations, and across boundaries. It is defined as a concept of societal camaraderie in the absence of hostility and violence. We’re well acquainted with the ironic word ‘peace-keeping forces’ which entail and propagate the use of force and coercion to maintain the virtue of peace, which should come naturally to us otherwise. Correlation between peace and other disciplines like political science, psychology, geography, cognitive science, anthropology and sociology is prevalent. However, little do we know that there is a strong nexus between peace and economics. They are central to each other and act as catalysts in each other’s process.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Role of Caste in Indian Elections</title><link href="/The-Role-of-Caste" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Role of Caste in Indian Elections" /><published>2020-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Role-of-Caste</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Role-of-Caste">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Jaati na Poocho Sadhu ki, Pooch lijiye gyaan’&lt;/em&gt; is a part of a &lt;em&gt;doha&lt;/em&gt; (couplet) by an Indian mystic, poet and saint Kabir Das, which directly translates to – ‘Do not judge a saint by their caste, but ask for their knowledge’. Yet, this &lt;em&gt;doha&lt;/em&gt; is categorically ignored in Indian elections, when the most-asked question during an election is about the candidate’s surname, caste or religion and not what they have to offer or the values they will bring to the table. From political analysts to voters, everyone has this question on their mind, which is why the candidates standing in an election want to play their caste game right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think of, when you first hear the word &lt;em&gt;caste&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be anything, literally. Albeit in the contemporary world, it mostly has a negative connotation attached to itself; being the sole reason for many ills which impair the world’s largest democracy. And, what is the caste system? It is an old social-stratification system that provides a hierarchy of social roles which hold inherent characteristics and, more importantly, are supposed to remain fixed throughout life. Even though Indian politicians didn’t create the mighty caste system, they surely know how to exploit this fault-line, exacerbating the caste animosities to build vote banks. In India, caste (and religion) is something people are very sensitive about and hence political parties face a difficult choice – they try to woo the oppressed castes in order to collect more votes. And in doing so, they antagonize some of the upper castes. Religiosity and tradition expect them to respect the caste boundaries, which is way too tempting to not exploit. A large number of parties draw up their poll strategies on the basis of the constituency’s caste demographic. Messages in the election speeches are tailored to suit the dominant caste of that constituency, and ideological coherence is sacrificed. And that’s why, while making the decision of choosing a candidate to represent them, voters tend to focus on caste and tend to overlook how adequately he/she would be able to represent them and focus on key issues. If a candidate belongs to caste X, his rival belonging to caste Y fields dummy candidates of caste X to divide the opponent’s votes. Caste determines the nature, organisation and working of most political parties, interest groups, and their functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of caste for gaining political popularity is not a new phenomenon and pre-Independence Indian politics also involved the use of caste, in different ways. The British Imperialists used religion as well as caste for political division of the nation. Unfortunately, even after Independence, India could not stop caste from becoming a factor that would influence politics. Even though the scenario is changing in urban India as voters are becoming more educated and aware about important issues, a large part of India still resides in rural areas, where people are not so much aware; for them, caste still plays a very important role in the election processes. Now, what can be the reason that people prefer to choose someone for their representation who belongs to their own caste rather than choosing someone who guarantees good work, amenities and development? It is because of an emotion – the feeling of belongingness. People tend to have an inherent desire to belong and be an important part of something that is greater than themselves; a relationship that is greater than simple acquaintance. This is a strong and inevitable feeling that exists in human nature. And due to this feeling, people have a strange natural trust that someone from their community, from their social group would be the apt representative for them; that he/she would protect them, provide them with opportunities and take care of them because after all, they belong to one big family, right? Sadly, that is not the case. Most of the times, this trust is taken for granted. Many political parties take advantage of these sentiments and fracture the society in such a manner that they gain from the divisions hence created; not to forget how deeply these divisions can damage the society. Politicians appeal to the sentiments of the voters of their respective caste groups and try to mobilize votes on that basis so as to capture and retain political power. Not only this, politicians have also managed to divert the attention of voters from issues relating to jobs, development, education, etc. by portraying caste as the paramount metric they should keep in mind while voting. The biggest harms of caste being involved in India’s electoral processes? There are many – incompetent leadership, ineffective governance, failed public policies, and most importantly, stagnancy. In a country where more than half of its population lives on less than 2$/day, it becomes highly important to make people realise the importance of proper representation and how it can change their lives. However, people are beginning to understand how such superficial factors are good for nothing and only poison the society at large. As is the case with any social evil, this is something which will require a lot of time and effort to be flushed out from the society, but that doesn’t mean it is impossible at all, right?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">‘Jaati na Poocho Sadhu ki, Pooch lijiye gyaan’ is a part of a doha (couplet) by an Indian mystic, poet and saint Kabir Das, which directly translates to – ‘Do not judge a saint by their caste, but ask for their knowledge’. Yet, this doha is categorically ignored in Indian elections, when the most-asked question during an election is about the candidate’s surname, caste or religion and not what they have to offer or the values they will bring to the table. From political analysts to voters, everyone has this question on their mind, which is why the candidates standing in an election want to play their caste game right.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Photograph</title><link href="/The-Photograph" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Photograph" /><published>2020-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Photograph</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Photograph">&lt;p&gt;The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photojournalism is a subset of broadcast journalism, referring to the presentation of a news story through photographs. The use of the medium of photography to compliment a news article or fully tell a story on its own has been a major source of authentic information and facts presentation. However, in order to understand the meaning of ‘photojournalism’, it is important to trace the legacy of it and examine the ways in which it was used in the period when we did not have a term to define this type of art. Here is one such early news story that made it to the headlines and grabbed the attention of its target audience by the camera’s capture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/f/fe/W._Eugene_Smith_-_Tomoko_Uemura_in_Her_Bath.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tomokobath.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup of this photograph is a Japanese, black and white image captured in 1971.  American photojournalist W Eugene Smith captured ‘Tomoko Uemura in Her Bath’, a photograph of a mother holding her severely deformed and naked child in a bathroom. The photojournalist wanted to depict the severity of the disease, Minamata, which is caused by mercury poisoning. It was first discovered in Minamata city of Japan, in 1956. Loss of peripheral vision, numbness in body muscles, and damage of speech and hearing are some of the symptoms. In extreme cases, it also affects foetuses in the womb.  This was not the only photograph that Smith picked to depict the trauma and condition of the people affected in Japan. He picked several photos that even made it to some of the publications, but he was searching for one striking photograph to gain the attention of the entire world. Smith had a symbolic vision of this photograph in his mind before he actually captured it and turned it into a reality. He explained his idea to Tomoko Uemura’s parents and when they agreed to get their daughter clicked, Smith began working on the set up of the photograph. Tomoko Uemura wanted the photo to depict the reality and plight of the people affected and dying in Minamata because of the pollution. Ryoko Uemura (mother) wanted a sympathetic portrayal of the photograph of her daughter and helped Smith in developing his ideas for the shots. She herself suggested the bathing chamber as the location of the photograph. The final capture was done on a chilly evening in December 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first publication of the photograph was done in 1972 in the American magazine, &lt;em&gt;Life&lt;/em&gt;, as a centrepiece for a short photo essay on Minamata. Smith developed an entire book featuring all his clicks of the disease. This photo became famous globally and shed light on the victims, raising their concerns of compensation. With this attention came rumours that Ryoko Uemura’s family was financially benefiting from all the interviews as the photograph had brought them into the spotlight. This intensified worries that the rumours might have an impact on Tomoko’s mental health. Tomoko died at the age of 21 in 1977. The photograph was withdrawn from publication in 1997, 20 years after Tomoko’s death, as per the wishes of the family. They refused the copyright on the photograph and interviews as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s father said &lt;em&gt;“I wanted Tomoko to be laid to rest and this feeling was growing steadily”&lt;/em&gt; in a refusal to permit exploitation of his daughter’s photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s capture brings to light a lot of aspects involved in the field of photojournalism, both from the reporter’s side and the victim’s side. There is always a story that is carried by an image on a news media platform and there are hundreds of stories behind that one capture. Only a photojournalist is remotely close to knowing them in detail. Photojournalism is a globally recognised and much-appreciated form of journalism today. It is an artistic presentation based on the recognition of realism in stories that are constantly changing and evolving as the audience awaits new concepts of storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W Eugene Smith’s journey provides us with insights of photojournalism in the western nations, whereas when talking specifically about the Indian context, many consider Kulwant Roy as a pioneer of Indian Photojournalism. He was one of the photographers who captured the birth of independent India and documented the freedom struggle. Digital photography and online editing have been revolutionary evolutions in photography, but realism is what attaches the term journalism and ethics to these captures. This is one of the major reasons why archival photos of Eugene Smith and Kulwant Roy are till date found to be inspirational to many growing photojournalists. It is interesting to see how far the camera’s click can deliver the news to its target audiences and whether or not it will take over the conventional mediums of journalism reporting in the digital era.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Himanshi Saini</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What COVID-19 Means for the US Education System?</title><link href="/COVID-19-US-Education-System" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What COVID-19 Means for the US Education System?" /><published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/COVID-19-US-Education-System</id><content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-US-Education-System">&lt;p&gt;Every generation of humanity has experienced their share of transitional periods, be it as consequential as the Second World War, or as small as being temporarily bedridden due to injury. The same concept can be used to study history in a different light - as a compilation of events that initiated the strongest ripples of transition in the various aspects of human life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As any mature and experienced enough man would tell you, change is a constant in the universe. It’s this change that led to human evolution and towards the development of society and the invention of all the things that make life worth living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as everything has exceptions, one of the few constants in life is the importance of education. It is something that has been so deeply ingrained in our culture that we cannot let go of it irrespective of the substitutes available to us. Today we see a scenario which is a clash between this constant and the period of fundamental transition fostered by COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States is a global education hub, with some of the most coveted educational institutes across the field of STEM, business, law and the arts. Students from all over the world dedicate a significant portion of their lives to the cause of securing admission into an elite US university. The country also greatly benefits from the international student community, as their annual contribution to the US GDP is at a massive $41 billion. Additionally, the cultural influence and innovation that the international community brings has, over the years, furthered the stronghold of many American companies in their respective markets. Nevertheless, the Trump administration has been rooting against international students who migrate to the USA in search of education and livelihood. That paired with a disease outbreak that has no fool-proof methods of containment has damaged educational prospects for a lot of international students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Council of Education predicts that a fall of as much as 25% in foreign student applications is anticipated for the upcoming academic year. This, though backed by the administration in charge, sets off a loud alarm as the impact would be drastic on the American corporate sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, America may be the pioneer in education, but it’s not the only player in the game. A lot of other countries like the UK, Canada and Australia offer equally enticing educational opportunities and have better migration and settlement policies. This may turn out to be the deciding factor for international students for whom an investment in a country other than the USA brings more to the table, especially in a highly uncertain situation like that of the present. The growing culture of administrative hostility towards immigrants would eventually lead to stagnation in diversity and curb the advantages that it offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, America is severely undermining the importance of international talent in keeping its corporate sector afloat. The influx of international funds in the form of fees, taxes, healthcare, bank deposits, etc contributes significantly to the economy. Due to the strictness of pre-existing work visa and green card policies, the proportion of foreign students that enrol in US programmes to those who actually find employment in the US to those who receive special work visas like H1B or obtain green cards moves in a decreasing order. Moreover, 1 out of 4 US startups, which are worth millions of dollars, are founded by international students. Therefore, calculation of the net impact of international students on the economy, irrespective of the time period, would yield a positive quotient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the lack of foreign influence would push the US into a state of cyclical perpetuity. The presence of international student communities supports more than just the economy, as it has been pivotal in reforming American society, and overcoming racial and cultural prejudice. This has helped American companies expand and explore international opportunities, and develop a workforce that is comfortable working outside their countries. It has popularised US education across the globe, which, over the years, has attracted countless employers and investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, many American institutions have moulded personalities who would go on to become leaders and forerunners in their respective fields. It has helped the American education system develop a global imprint, as a lot of individuals, that are its product, represent it in any sphere they venture into. Reduction in international students, after a certain point, would reduce this influence that the US enjoys in shaping leaders of various sectors, disciplines, and even nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summing it all up, the US, like any other nation, needs to evolve in various respects as and when required to maintain its reputation as a global leader. The driving force behind such evolution is the product of interactions between the international and local communities. A long term trend of decline in international students would cause the nation to involuntarily impose a glass ceiling on its growth potential. Therefore, it is indispensable for American colleges and universities to acknowledge the “new normal” and devise methods to attract international student applications. The first step that can be taken in this regard would be dismissing the suspension of student and special work visas, and ensuring that the impact of the pandemic-induced economic slowdown is minimal on college fees, educational loans and international student aid.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aryaman Dhiman</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Every generation of humanity has experienced their share of transitional periods, be it as consequential as the Second World War, or as small as being temporarily bedridden due to injury. The same concept can be used to study history in a different light - as a compilation of events that initiated the strongest ripples of transition in the various aspects of human life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Big Data and Big Entertainment</title><link href="/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Data and Big Entertainment" /><published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment">&lt;p&gt;Go to a supermarket to buy chocolates and you’ll find yourself eyeing some fancy stationery pens, which you most definitely don’t need. You’ll find yourself at the billing counter with the chocolates you needed, but also a couple of pens that were visually appealing to you. You end up buying them and on your way back home, you think of how we all do small, silly things to find happiness in these little things. And while you walk home with a smile on your face, the shopkeeper is most likely smirking at the fact that he/she was able to control your purchase by strategically placing the stationery shelf at the best spot of the store, right at the same eye level as yours. He/She is now proud of themselves for having read the &lt;em&gt;Retailer Magazine&lt;/em&gt; that told them how consumer behaviour in a supermarket is driven by eye-candies and strategically-placed products which makes consumers think that they’re choosing to buy a product out of their own will. In turn, the &lt;em&gt;Retailer Magazine&lt;/em&gt; is happy to have influenced consumerism through the use of consumer databases that come under ‘Big Data’. Therefore, in short, your choice of buying a couple of pens was actually driven by tools of capitalism, and not your short-lived happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The air of this generation is electric with the talk of big data. Consider that the world is a kingdom, then big data is the know-it-all wish-granting ruler of this kingdom, and the subjects of this kingdom are not humans, but in fact just information databases. In layman’s language, big data is a huge volume of data that is stored, controlled and analysed to draw insights on human behaviour. Not just supermarkets, like in our example, but also multinational corporations are nothing without big data. Businesses, retailers and corporations use databases to understand consumer preferences and control them via tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the usage and impacts of big data better, we’re going to take an unconventional path and look into it through the lens of pop-culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documentary &lt;em&gt;Amazon Empire: The Rise and Reign of Jeff Bezos&lt;/em&gt; highlights some extremely important takeaways on the functioning of multinational corporations and how the organisation was instrumental in paving a new course for e-commerce. The documentary shows that consumer data is the most important base for the foundation of Amazon. Using this data, Amazon devised pricing strategies and took advantage of it, being the only e-commerce company back when it started, and took a head start to get a hold of the “market segment share”, even if it meant foregoing profits in the short run. Jeff Bezos was in it for monopolisation in the long run. A widely unknown truth is that ‘Alexa’, Amazon’s virtual assistant, that is sitting idle in a lot of our homes is, in fact, the most cunning strategy of data collection, as it records our conversations and is used to improve the Alexa algorithm. The documentary also reveals insider information that the products sold on Amazon don’t necessarily meet the safety standards, but they are marketed in a way that the consumer feels like they need the product, and not just want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an omnipresent fear of big data in our minds because we’re constantly afraid of how it is going to control our lives and it may be an inherent threat to our beings if, one day, our lives are taken over by these big corporates or the government. The very same fear of big data has been highlighted well enough in George Orwell’s 1984 which paints a dystopian world wherein a totalitarian regime exists, with an undisclosed head of state called ‘Big Brother’. This head is an ever-watching eye on the public and uses surveillance to tightly control the public and the ‘thought police’ persecutes their independent thinking and individuality. This furthermore increases people’s distrust on the controller of their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing parallels from the dystopian satire, &lt;em&gt;Ninety Eighty-Four&lt;/em&gt; brings me to Netflix’s &lt;em&gt;House of Cards&lt;/em&gt;, a series that highlights political campaigning in the US elections. To taint young Presidential candidate Will Conway’s election rallying, Frank Underwood deploys illegal mechanisms of obtaining voter data to be able to skew votes in his favour. While there is no inherent problem with the collection of voter data, doing so without the knowledge or permission of the voters is simply immoral and falsifies the entire meaning of election campaigning, which is to ensure interaction between the Presidential candidates and the public. This is also known as “hacking” the electorate, which means using data to appeal to specific voter groups and predicting how they will vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to a very important inclusion in this article, Netflix’s &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt;. This documentary portrays the stark reality of how Facebook and Twitter use data analysis tools to exploit information on its users through tweets, posts, friends, likes and dislikes. They slyly convince us into taking certain quizzes like “What Disney character are you?” which takes up our information through permissions we usually ignore to read. All this data was passed on to a company called Cambridge Analytica, which was hired by one of the political parties in the 2016 US elections. Cambridge, in turn, used all the collected data to create fear and apathy to achieve favourable results for this political party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam McKay’s star-studded &lt;em&gt;The Big Short&lt;/em&gt; would be a great example to digress from the impact of data in politics to the impact of data in economics. The movie revolves around how data, coupled with unconventional tools to explain financial instruments like ‘Jenga’, were used to predict that the housing market is going to lead to the downfall of the US economy, which in fact proved to be true as it led to the 2007-08 Global Economic Recession. Owing to the prediction, the protagonist makes a strategic long-term investment that yields his company a $2.69 billion profit, while the entire world saw a pitfall. Moving onto a more micro example, Bennett Miller’s &lt;em&gt;Moneyball&lt;/em&gt; shows the general manager of a baseball team having to sieve out players due to underperformance and a budget crunch, he does this, amidst criticism, using tools of sabermetrics and on-base percentage depending on each player’s information. This led to a slow but eventual victory for the team he had constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that we’re surrounded by big data seems a little scary and we owe it to how big data has been fed to us via pop-culture. A movie like &lt;em&gt;Minority Report&lt;/em&gt; that uses big data analysis to predict crime before it occurs makes one wrong prediction which starts to disrupt the system, inevitably hurting the minority. This, in fact, strengthens the distrust in the system. The series &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;, through its different episodes highlighting different themes, showcases that we are governed by the black mirror that is the screen in our lives, which ranges from TV shows to social media and smartphones. The series focuses on how this may be just the tip of an iceberg of the myriad technologies that may unravel over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is it that makes us afraid of big data or technology? The answer is that we’re not inherently afraid of data or technology, but the people who control it. &lt;em&gt;“More data equals more inference”&lt;/em&gt; seems fine until the controller of this data infers more than they’re supposed to. But the ultimate truth lies in the fact that we cannot escape big data. What we can do is empower ourselves with the tool of education to learn about the mechanisms of regulation and accountability that exist, and learn to adopt a system of checks and balances to avoid any breach of privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Go to a supermarket to buy chocolates and you’ll find yourself eyeing some fancy stationery pens, which you most definitely don’t need. You’ll find yourself at the billing counter with the chocolates you needed, but also a couple of pens that were visually appealing to you. You end up buying them and on your way back home, you think of how we all do small, silly things to find happiness in these little things. And while you walk home with a smile on your face, the shopkeeper is most likely smirking at the fact that he/she was able to control your purchase by strategically placing the stationery shelf at the best spot of the store, right at the same eye level as yours. He/She is now proud of themselves for having read the Retailer Magazine that told them how consumer behaviour in a supermarket is driven by eye-candies and strategically-placed products which makes consumers think that they’re choosing to buy a product out of their own will. In turn, the Retailer Magazine is happy to have influenced consumerism through the use of consumer databases that come under ‘Big Data’. Therefore, in short, your choice of buying a couple of pens was actually driven by tools of capitalism, and not your short-lived happiness.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe</title><link href="/The-Silent-Genocide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Silent-Genocide</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Silent-Genocide">&lt;p&gt;On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incident is just one of the many unreported and completely avoidable deaths. Many patients are forced to be turned away from hospitals either due to lack of staff or lack of equipment. There have been reports of pregnant women giving birth in unconventional and unsafe places leading to increased mortality rates. Doctors and nurses have consistently been underpaid and overworked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this situation is common to many countries as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the situation in Zimbabwe has been dire for a long time. In September 2019, medical personnel across the country went on a 4-month long strike to protest their devastatingly low wages and poor working conditions. It was not that they did not want to work, it was that they could not afford to work. In the face of triple-digit inflation, doctors and nurses could barely meet their food and transport costs. In fact, the doctors did not call it a strike - rather an “incapacitation”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s response was disheartening, stating that it was not just medical personnel, but all workers who were suffering under inflation, including civil servants. However, looking at the standard of life of government officials, this did not seem plausible. Suspiciously enough, not long after the strike began, their union leader, Dr Peter Magombeyi, was abducted for five days under mysterious circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staff only returned to work in January 2020 when the telecoms tycoon Strive Masiyiwa offered to supplement the government wages with a monthly subsistence allowance through his charitable foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in March 2020, COVID-19 reached Zimbabwe. President Emmerson Mnangagwa fell short in governance. Not just the healthcare system but the entire economy is facing an insurmountable challenge. The unemployment level is close to 90%, with most people falling deeper into poverty and being unable to afford a proper meal a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, the High Court ordered the government to ensure all healthcare workers were supplied with Personal Protective Equipment (PPE). However, according to doctors, there is still hardly any PPE available. N-95 masks are occasionally provided but mostly a surgical mask and plastic aprons are given to last an entire day. An increasing number of medical personnel are being affected and there is no insurance for them. Adding to this risk of practicing, the pay has been dismally low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is even more terrible for nurses. Many of them receive just $30 per month and cannot even afford proper food and housing. On these grounds, nurses in Zimbabwe went on a strike in June 2020. Instead of providing PPE kits and improving pay and working conditions, the government brought in student nurses and those who had been out of work for a long time. Thus, many wards were staffed with nurses who were either inexperienced or who had not received recent training. Shortly after, doctors followed them, demanding PPE, better conditions and equipment in hospitals, decent pay, and for salaries to be paid in US dollars rather than the RTGS dollar (or “Zimdollar”) which is subject to hyperinflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinaldo Ortuno, head of mission at Médecins Sans Frontières Zimbabwe said, &lt;em&gt;“Hospitals and clinics are now manned by student nurses, junior doctors, and other staff who have no choice as they are still under training. This has compromised quality of care and has inadvertently contributed to high morbidity and mortality rates”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government seems to have little incentive to bring a change. The people in power do not exert pressure for a better healthcare system as they do not get treated in government hospitals. When they fall sick, they go abroad. Ex-President Robert Mugabe received treatment in Singapore before he passed away in 2019, at the age of 95. Vice-President Constantino Chiwenga, the former military man who played a major role in overthrowing Mugabe, has received four months of medical treatment in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government even saw the pandemic as a money-making opportunity. This clearly revealed the multi-million-dollar equipment procurement scandal that led to the recent arrest of the Health Minister as well as the vindictive detention of Hopewell Chin’ono, the journalist who uncovered it. The government then appointed Constantine Chiwenga as the new Health Minister, even though he had made insulting and abusive comments against doctors in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has led to strikes by medical personnel all across the world. This presents a dilemma of whose needs should be put above the others. Should doctors and nurses suffer through their long hours and low wages as a part of their duty to society? The reality is that in Zimbabwe, they have been making this sacrifice for a long time. However, now the nature of COVID-19 means that this sacrifice could cost them their lives. Norman Matara, head of Zimbabwe Hospital Doctors Association said that about 15% of the nationally recorded virus infections had been detected among health workers. The lack of attention from the government has broken their spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many have called this crisis in Zimbabwe a “silent genocide”. The government must increase public spending in the healthcare sector on an emergency basis, and should also look towards securing foreign assistance for equipment and personnel, like Cuba has been providing, to support them through the pandemic. Refusing the demands of the workers and degrading their protest by accusing them of not fulfilling their duty is not beneficial to any side. President Emmerson Mnangagwa needs to act in order to rebuild the trust of doctors and nurses in the government. They are at the frontline of the fight against the pandemic, and their wellbeing, both physical and mental, is quite literally a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Era of Online Stock Trading: Robinhood Misleads Gen-Z</title><link href="/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Era of Online Stock Trading: Robinhood Misleads Gen-Z" /><published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z">&lt;p&gt;The novel coronavirus has led to a situation of crisis and has drastically impacted consumer behaviour and supply chains, thus creating an imbalance. While this disparity has proven to be a nightmare for most of the business houses, some of them are really making it big. As people adjust to this new normal, technology has been their friend in disguise to learn new skills and explore their areas of interest. App developers are among those few who are benefitting from this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lockdown has also led to a surge in first-time investors/traders entering the stock market. Stocks with “zero equity value” and even penny stocks have doubled since April this year. This increase is mainly due to easy access to the process via stock market apps which have seen maximum sign-ups in the past few months. Robinhood - one such stock market app has been in the headlines for quite some time now. They gained 3,000,000 new users within the first 6 months of 2020, which is literally half of the new trading accounts created this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company has become one of the fastest-growing tech startups in recent times. The ease of trading that the app provides, has turned into a cultural phenomenon, and Robinhood has climbed to the billion-dollar mark. With investors pouring in money, its valuation has reached $11.2 billion. The app has been a hit since its launch in 2013 and has been growing since then. It recorded 4.3 million DART’s (Daily Average Revenue Trades), surpassing all its competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This huge traffic of day traders has also been affecting the American stock market. This is being referred to as the “Robinhood Effect”. It is described as the irrational stock price changes in the market. This effect began when apps like Robinhood attempted to democratise investing by providing platforms that simplified the methods and thus people with no background or knowledge joined the trading world. Today, youth with minimum capital are playing around as shares have become affordable due to the current economic situation. According to research, users buying small inexpensive stocks are generating solid returns which gives them an incentive to stay. Thus, it seems like the hype is not going to die anytime soon for this huge army of day traders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app even offers the facility to buy fractional shares which lowers the risk. Robinhood doesn’t charge trading commissions, which further increases its popularity. These day traders are becoming known as the “risk-takers”. The accounts are mostly handled by youngsters who are stuck in their homes due to the norms of social distancing. They are ready to take immediate action and trade shares without much consideration. These investors are inexperienced and don’t have much prior knowledge. Not only are they indulging in basic trades but also in advanced level trading like futures and options. This behaviour has proven to be beneficial for the company but can cause serious losses to the traders. Many investors have shared their traumatic experiences which were mainly caused due to their uninformed choices. A 20-year-old college student from Nebraska killed himself as his balance dropped to negative $730,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences being faced are intense and the developers should take accountability for the same. Educating the newcomers and providing enough information should be an important aspect of the whole trading process. The new day traders who start playing with their capital end up bearing losses which can thereby lead to some detrimental conditions. Certain restrictions within the app will definitely ensure some responsibility by these individuals. Another problem being faced by the company is of technical glitches. These tech issues have increased with the rise in the number of users and sometimes, these also lead to losses due to the fluctuating nature of stocks. In order to solve these issues and have better customer service, Robinhood plans to expand its team. They have more than a hundred positions available in many American cities. This move will benefit the consumers and might also help the issue of unemployment at some level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While every firm has its own set of difficulties, dealing with them in a strategic manner is the best way out. Robinhood too has its own set of criticisms. Even in this capitalistic world, ethics still hold high regard and companies should take decisions after considering certain moral grounds. The idea of providing easy access to the stock market is ideal but it still has its own problems that need attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has totally changed our outlook towards the stock market and trading. It has provided an avenue to millions of people to invest and has also led to certain prominent changes in the market which might be fruitful. But, at the same time, its harms are no less in terms of losses being suffered. The uncertainty of the stock market has also blurred my perspective on Robinhood’s future. It definitely hasn’t proven to be as generous as the animated character! Until then, the uncertainty will remain a constant source of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The novel coronavirus has led to a situation of crisis and has drastically impacted consumer behaviour and supply chains, thus creating an imbalance. While this disparity has proven to be a nightmare for most of the business houses, some of them are really making it big. As people adjust to this new normal, technology has been their friend in disguise to learn new skills and explore their areas of interest. App developers are among those few who are benefitting from this pandemic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking Up Big Tech</title><link href="/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking Up Big Tech" /><published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It’s about as likely as is Mexico paying for Trump’s wall”&lt;/em&gt;, commented an equity researcher in response to Elizabeth Warren’s proposal. Have Google and Facebook become too powerful in our economy, should they be broken up? Are they creating some sort of monopoly in the technology space? All these are questions that have been in our minds for quite some time now. A decade ago, Amazon, Google, Facebook, Apple, and other networking sites were not a part of our lives the way they are today. However, in recent times, the emergence of these e-commerce websites and search engines has immensely increased, with everything, from purchasing groceries to online classes, taking place through these established tech agents. The issue cropped up after the US Senator Elizabeth Warren proposed to break down these companies into smaller units. This is gaining quite some popularity on both sides of the US political divide. Even President Donald Trump has made comments disparaging big tech and called for the government to sue companies like Google and Facebook. Lawmakers back in the US are thinking to disintegrate these companies because they feel that these companies have absolutely dismantled the healthy competitive spirit in their respective domains and have completely violated the antitrust laws of the country. So, let’s start unfolding the various layers of this recently heated debate by getting down to the history of the antitrust laws of the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Brief History of the Antitrust Laws in the USA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States has a history of breaking up large companies. Back then the railroad, oil, steel and sugar industries formed monopolies because of the very few competitors they had. Thus, they became wealthier at the expense of the consumer. The most well-known example is that of Standard Oil which controlled the entire industry of oil due to which they could completely change the price of the product by changing the supply. The oil industry at that time was prone to natural monopolies because of the rarity of the products. At this juncture, the federal government was forced to bust many of these large businesses with the help of the newly created ‘Antitrust Laws’ to protect the interests of the consumers. The first of these was the Sherman Act, passed in 1890 which aimed at preventing mergers between companies that led to unfair competition in the market. Despite this Act’s approval in 1890, the next fifty years saw the formation of many monopolies. Also, the profits of  Standard Oil and the generous dividends encouraged investors to invest in monopolistic firms. Succeeding it in 1914, the Federal Trade Commission Act was passed to monitor and track unfair business practices that deter the spirit of competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very well-known example of this Act being used is that of Microsoft  which was believed to be the tech giant of its time and aimed at establishing dominance in the area of web browsing but then the federal government intervened and sued it for violating anti-monopoly laws and reached an agreement with it. One school of thought says that the antitrust case on Microsoft that time helped shape a path for big tech giants like Google and Amazon to emerge. However, some analysts are of the view that in today’s times these antitrust laws seem inapplicable to the tech giants because they are already a century old and they were created to protect the interests of the consumers differently, specifically we mean that they were built in an era where financial domination led to the creation of monopolies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Role of Big Tech and the Present Debate Related to It&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US economy has been on an upward trend which can to some extent be attributed to the tech sector. Nearly, half of the e-commerce goes through Amazon, more than 70% of all internet referral traffic goes through sites owned and operated by Google and Facebook. Instagram, today, has one billion active monthly users – two-thirds of whom visit the platform on a daily basis. More than two million businesses have bought ads there, many of which are intended to drive users to their websites to buy products. And Senator Elizabeth Warren feels that these companies have too much power over our economy, society and democracy. Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders has also clashed with Amazon on multiple occasions, and criticised Facebook and Google for destroying local media. He said that he will look into breaking up big tech companies. This proposal enjoys support from not just the majority of Democrats but in similar proportions of Republicans and Independents, claiming it to be a bipartisan issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent online poll, it has been shown that around 7 in 10 Americans say it’s a good idea to break up big tech companies when the content that they are showing is ranked depending on whether the company is making money or not. On these lines, it is being argued that the current landscape of technology has left consumers with little privacy even as their data is converted into vast corporate profit. These American big tech companies have mainly achieved the level of dominance by using two strategies- using mergers to limit competition and using the proprietary marketplace to limit competition. Take the example of Facebook, which purchased potential competitors such as Instagram and WhatsApp. Amazon used its extreme market power to force smaller competitors such as Diapers.com to sell its products at a discounted rate. Weak antitrust enforcement laws have led to the culminating dominance created by these tech companies in the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venture capitalists are also hesitant to fund new tech because they feel that either these start-ups would be purchased by these monopolists or else, they will completely crash. It is also claimed that with fewer tech companies entering the market, these large tech agents don’t have to compete in matters such as protecting our data privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two sorts of measures that can be taken to break these monopolies, first by passing legislation that requires large tech platforms to be designated as ‘platform utilities’ (companies with annual global revenue of $25 billion or more that offer to the public an online marketplace, an exchange, or a platform connecting third parties would be termed as ‘platform utilities’) that would be broken apart from any participant on that platform, with them not being allowed to share data with any third parties. Also, they should be required to meet a standard of fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory dealing with third parties. Such measures would also ensure that the sovereignty of America is upheld and no third-country can influence its election results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will Breaking Up these Tech Giants Really Fix it Up?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experts from Wharton have challenged Warren’s proposals and said that breaking them up won’t actually provide a level playing field, but instead in the long term would again route down profits to other successful business ventures. I believe that the reason why this political debate has come up is completely valid but the solution that is being offered is not the most practical, this is because even in the past this has not worked. The breaking up of AT&amp;amp;T into eight companies unleashed competition for a time, lowering prices but as landlines gave way for wireless, the industry reconsolidated. Thus, the enforcement of antitrust laws will not solve the issues of high prices and privacy. For example, removing WhatsApp from Facebook won’t let Facebook collect any lesser data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consumers would also be at a loss because, if suppose, we disintegrate Google then we won’t be able to simultaneously use Google Drive and Google Chrome, imagine the number of complexities involved. Also, the Antitrust Doctrine has focused on two things, one is the conduct and the other is the structure. The Federal Trade Commission and Department of Justice should focus on the conduct and behaviour of big tech companies to make sure that they don’t use their market power to become anticompetitive. The size of these companies have enabled them to make big investments in future, if we try to break them up, we’re going to lose that. Also, even if antitrust laws would prevent mergers, we need to understand the chain reaction that would follow, which is when prices are lowered the wages will be lowered too, jobs would be cut, and product quality would also fall discouraging innovation. All of these changes would unknowingly harm the consumers in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s in Store for these Large Tech Giants?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we can not deny the fact that these large tech giants have created some sort of dominance in the society with their products, lucrative offers and better policies at hand to gain maximum profits and to drive out other competitors from the business, we should not deny the fact that they have always driven the economy on an upward trend, providing better opportunities for employees. We should also realise the fact that disintegrating them based on antitrust laws is not correct because globalisation and the ever-increasing world economy have called out for the retirement of the antitrust laws. Further, ultimately, we as consumers are also to be blamed because, in the end, it’s we who have given them the title of large tech giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, most of them started on a level playing field and now they have reached their present level due to a lot of effort. Instead of just relying on one individual’s statement and subsequently taking action against these tech giants is not justified, the regulators and politicians should ask the consumers how ‘bad’ they find the tech giants to be at present and then decide. We need to understand that instead of breaking them up, we should think of fixing up issues like data privacy. Moreover, we should look at the fact that even though an investigation can be carried on for years accusing them of many things but ultimately proving them in court with proofs would be another thing because they would also leave no stone unturned to prove themselves not guilty. With some forces standing against them and others supporting it, the future of these big tech companies remains uncertain and largely depends on what shall happen in the courts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cherry Sharma</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“It’s about as likely as is Mexico paying for Trump’s wall”, commented an equity researcher in response to Elizabeth Warren’s proposal. Have Google and Facebook become too powerful in our economy, should they be broken up? Are they creating some sort of monopoly in the technology space? All these are questions that have been in our minds for quite some time now. A decade ago, Amazon, Google, Facebook, Apple, and other networking sites were not a part of our lives the way they are today. However, in recent times, the emergence of these e-commerce websites and search engines has immensely increased, with everything, from purchasing groceries to online classes, taking place through these established tech agents. The issue cropped up after the US Senator Elizabeth Warren proposed to break down these companies into smaller units. This is gaining quite some popularity on both sides of the US political divide. Even President Donald Trump has made comments disparaging big tech and called for the government to sue companies like Google and Facebook. Lawmakers back in the US are thinking to disintegrate these companies because they feel that these companies have absolutely dismantled the healthy competitive spirit in their respective domains and have completely violated the antitrust laws of the country. So, let’s start unfolding the various layers of this recently heated debate by getting down to the history of the antitrust laws of the USA.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stranded by the Sea</title><link href="/Stranded-by-the-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stranded by the Sea" /><published>2020-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Stranded-by-the-Sea</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Stranded-by-the-Sea">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;Refugee&lt;/em&gt; is a term we read and hear about often, on the internet or the news and dissect into it like any other topic that we came across on a particular day. Be it the Syrian refugee crisis, the Afghanistan refugee crisis, people displaced in the Middle East fleeing to Europe for desperate rehabilitation, the partition of India or the result of a civil war. These are all issues originating in different parts of the world, delineated by boundaries and separated based on geography or the cause or origin of conflict. However, even though conflicts might vary in terms of nature- political, economic or social - it’s corollary remains immutable across borders and religion, that is, displacement of people and wreckage of homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve fled your country (or have been chased out by the majority population/authoritarian government), it’s nearly impossible to come back. The unsafe and riotous situation in certain countries caused by wars or feud creates conditions that make it fatal to a come back to a place they once called home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rohingya are one such community, facing persecution and fleeing from one place to another since 58 years, circa 1962.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of the persecution of the Rohingyas can be traced back to the colonization of India by the British, which endured for over 200 years. Tracing back to the British colonial period in the 1800’s, many people from India and Bangladesh were brought to Myanmar to work in the British led administration, doubling the Muslim community in Myanmar. This decision was received with acrimony by the local Myanmar people. This stands as one of the root cause of the animosity against the Rohingyas. During the World Wars, this hostility further deepened its roots since the majority of the Muslim population supported the British whereas the Buddhist population was predisposed towards the Japanese. This incongruity, as a result of the disparity between The Allies and The Axis Powers, aggravated the situation for the Muslim population in Myanmar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official status of “refugee” is something the Rohingya people have struggled with for years now. In 1962, military rule became the norm and law throughout Myanmar. As a result, the Muslim population in Rakhine State was overpowered by militants and the Buddhist majority, thus causing the refugees to flee to Bangladesh. Since then, from 1962 to 2017 a large number of Rohingya people have migrated to the neighbouring countries, especially Bangladesh, having faced oppression in their own country. In 1982, an official Myanmar announcement declared 135 nationally recognized ethnic groups and the Rohingya were not included in the list, leaving them stateless and without citizenship. Further, in 2012 riots were waged against the Rohingyas and 200 people were killed while leaving 15,000 homeless and displaced. The Myanmar government even prohibited them from participating in the national census and the voting procedure during the elections. These acts of negligence, violence and repression continued till 2017 causing more than 600,000 Rohingya people to flee the Rakhine State since their communities were destroyed. But that doesn’t mean that things are any safer for them now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there are some 860,000 Rohingya people seeking refuge in Bangladesh and at least 1.3 million people — Rohingya refugees and Bangladeshi host communities — who rely on humanitarian assistance to meet their basic needs. More than half of them are children. These populations live in desperately overcrowded camps and communities, highly vulnerable to oncoming monsoon and cyclone seasons, violence, sexual harassment and unhygienic environment. These camps provide them with less than the meagre amenities, leaving them to live a life of ignorance, in a vicious cycle of poverty, violence and substandard living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) and Médecins Sans Frontières (MSF) (also known as Doctors without Borders) describes the Rohingya as one of the most persecuted people in the world. The world we live in prides itself on its safety and peacekeeping system at the international level. Since after the Second World War, many nations came together and pledged to save vulnerable people and nations in crises. Yet, their (Rohingyas) struggle and oppression has been one of the most under-reported humanitarian crises in the world. The international media and community have practically ignored the situation of these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of this because of one reason, deeply entrenched in our parochial minds: ethnic animosity and conflict on the grounds of religion and historical beliefs of territory and ownership. This practice has left the Rohingya people without a beacon of hope for a better future. It has normalized a humanitarian crisis of this gravity, leading us to believe that it’s okay to treat a community of people with mindless hostility and utter disregard for their lives. (Because they might’ve done something to deserve it)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having faced persecution even in the camps of Bangladesh’s Cox Bazaar (and Myanmar, of course) the Rohingya people have made attempts to reach Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia and other countries for years now. Since they lack visas, travel documents and are subjected to strict restrictions, boats are often the only option left for them to undertake transnational crossing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to MSF, it is estimated that around 167 countries across the world have fully or partially closed their borders during COVID-19 pandemic and 57 states made no exception for people seeking asylum. Even though closing borders is an acceptable reaction to the pandemic, not providing a concession for people looking for a refugee status amidst these tough times, stranded by the sea and in between nations is unacceptable. Countries such as Italy and Malta closed their ports for refugees and are using the excuse of the pandemic to reject refugees from entering their land and water borders. Several hundred Rohingyas fleeing persecution at home and refugee camps in Bangladesh have been stranded for months after countries sealed their borders to block the spread of the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have reported that their relatives are stranded by the sea and their traffickers, holding hundreds of Rohingya refugees, are demanding money to release them from boats that have been off Southeast Asia since February, trying to find a place to land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Material cupidity has yet again taken precedence over humanity in a situation of a deadly life-crisis. The refugees travelling on these boats could hardly gather the money and documents to take this journey across the sea, and now with the pandemic having engulfed the world, they’re stuck on these boats, suffering, starving and seething in pain, waiting to get across any border to find some refuge and shelter from these treacherous circumstances. On top of this, they are being exploited for money in a situation of utmost helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To think why these people landed in such a chronic crisis, which has persisted for over five decades now; to think why we as a community allow and tolerate a humanitarian crisis at such a cosmic level. It is because somewhere deep down, we all have our own set of ideas and beliefs tied by social norms of caste, creed and culture. Because we all have ingrained the idea of &lt;em&gt;Us vs Them&lt;/em&gt;, so concretely in our heads that it’s almost impossible to break down those walls around us. But if there’s something that this pandemic has taught us, it’s that we’re all in this together. No problem is a standalone issue - it’s always linked to a larger affliction and it’s not outside the ambit of possibility for it to find its way to you. If we don’t untangle this issue as a community and for the community, it’ll always remain unresolved and will surface time and again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">A Refugee is a term we read and hear about often, on the internet or the news and dissect into it like any other topic that we came across on a particular day. Be it the Syrian refugee crisis, the Afghanistan refugee crisis, people displaced in the Middle East fleeing to Europe for desperate rehabilitation, the partition of India or the result of a civil war. These are all issues originating in different parts of the world, delineated by boundaries and separated based on geography or the cause or origin of conflict. However, even though conflicts might vary in terms of nature- political, economic or social - it’s corollary remains immutable across borders and religion, that is, displacement of people and wreckage of homes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Western Media Texts</title><link href="/Western-Media-Texts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Western Media Texts" /><published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Western-Media-Texts</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Western-Media-Texts">&lt;p&gt;The digital revolution of old media into new media has taken shape very rapidly. Old media has seldom been given its due recognition. Traditional sources of information like newspapers and radio have sustained their quality in truth telling for ages. Its comparison is unparalleled when it comes to new media, which is why it still has a wide market and is almost irreplaceable. On the other hand, new media rose to power because of its instantaneous quality to connect and communicate. News became easy to deliver as new media defined its timeliness. It has definitely changed the dynamics of public consumption of news, heralding a phase in humanity where everything can be reported, by anyone, and at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this has caused a severe decline in the ethics and philosophies of news providers. The power of creating news and gathering information is privy to distortion. Popularising preconceived notions as news is an emerging norm. This leads to misrepresentation and unfortunate consequences. The multiplicity of perspectives, opinions, and beliefs, entailing even factual wrongdoings, mixed with propaganda, has corrupted what was once considered an industry full of good samaritans. It is now a blotch on the entire concept of truth, information and news. Even traditional media faced this deterioration. The downward spiral of media credibility first footed at the advent of selling sensational news. The entire concept of ‘tabloidisation’ in garnering an audience, for the sake of business growth by corporations, led to a complete dilution in the way the public’s sensibilities allowed them to evaluate news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the media’s very history has dictated cultural behaviour throughout the course of time, it has become a core part of our lives. From newspapers to television networks to the abundance of information disseminated on social media, different types of media have both evolved and learnt to coexist. Thus, understanding the people and corporations behind these media networks, and the faces that decide news value, will further provide transparency in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Television is a writer’s playground, and online platforms only widen this space. The artistic freedom and the creative liberty that comes with it, was hitherto unheard of. So what would earlier be written for network audience traction is now developing into its own qualitative entity. All shows based on varied walks of life, using diverse plots, and being highly representative, have a loyal audience. Film and television also influence us in the most impactful ways. Therefore, the story and the way of storytelling employed is imperative to the niche audience it targets. When we talk about journalism and media, it is easy to assume how its machine functions. However, we hardly know the works behind the scenes. That is news nobody can tell us. We are oblivious to what goes into reporting a two minute segment, or a five page article. It always varies depending on the story, the source, the journalist, the editor, and the thousand inbetweeners that it takes to put a story out there. There have been innumerable assumptions around what a media workplace should be or how a journalistic practice must work, usually tied around speculation and hearsay. There’s seldom any representation within media texts portraying the media itself. Let us analyse two stand out accomplishments that tried to do it right, and well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Newsroom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Aaron Sorkin original, HBO’s &lt;em&gt;The Newsroom&lt;/em&gt; revolves around the dramatisation of a fictional news broadcast media network - Atlantis Cable Network. The name itself suggests that it is a fictional, idealistic world of the media elite. It is essentially a newsroom drama, a tale only seen panned out in movies before. Therefore, the scope for incorporating real time journalistic stories is high. And Sorkin knows how to merge that plethora of opportunity through witty dialogue and righteous ethical commentary. The plot revolves around some passionate workaholic journalists who only live by their virtues of delivering the unfiltered truth, without being bothered about the network ratings or audience commands. It is representative of what every journalist wants to be - equally intellectual and ethical - despite being held back by outside forces. The show reiterates that the value of journalistic integrity is above all else. It is a stark contrast to broadcast networks in real life, which are constantly required to entertain rather than provide information. In this day and age, ratings and viewership is highly important for a network to sustain itself. Thus, this show posits itself as an ideal of how every journalist wants to work and does not delve into a practical solution for how broadcast may allow its journalists to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The show tends to remain positive even during the darkest stories that have plagued the United States of America, by the up and coming celebration of democracy that the nation prevails to be. Its coverage of real time political events and serious stories, is not only well written but amazingly performed by the ensemble cast. While the show does not accurately portray broadcast networks in the West (and is especially inaccurate in doing that), it sure lives up to the narrative it is trying to convey - that which every network must strive to achieve. The show also satires and ridicules networks that have different ideologies and functions. Its constant snarky digs at &lt;em&gt;Thirty Mile Zone (TMZ)&lt;/em&gt; for exploitation, and &lt;em&gt;Cable News Network (CNN)&lt;/em&gt; for false reporting, is well-handled and brave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorkin’s masterful writing aids him in articulating some narratives within the media industry that need to be heard. For networks not just in the US, but even worldwide. Even if it’s not an accurate representation, the technical representation and the chaotic nuance of a newsroom workplace is on point. With some admirable takeaways from beloved performances of some truly heroic characters, the show does its job and does it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Morning Show&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Apple TV+ venture, &lt;em&gt;The Morning Show&lt;/em&gt; represents a morning broadcast media show and what the happy rosy environment actually masks. Its script originally dealt with a common plot threading various stories in between, but it ended up changing to accentuate the overarching common storyline due to its relevance. Entailing the #MeToo movement, the show focuses on the alleged sexual harassment cases that women at the media house workplace suffered at the hands of a powerful lead anchor. The anchor is fired and denies the claims. While fictionalised, this premise is taken from what happened to Matt Lauer at the &lt;em&gt;Today Show&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows the complicity of the workplace environment in perpetuating the harassment. This is representative of not just media organisations but of any working environment. Through its complex characters, and dramatic plot twists, the first season does justice in representing the consequences of such unfortunate workplace incidents. It humanises every character involved and doesn’t judge through its writing. It’s everything that is expected from a gripping drama. The story explores the nuanced details of the #MeToo movement, but leaves the audience in suspense about the actual truth until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its course, the show is riddled with characters that are dayside journalists, so the media premise is naturally different. Everything from the type of stories covered, to the positivity that it propagates, it is accurately representative of that broadcast niche. The lead anchors are shown being vain and self absorbed. But the entrance of a righteous journalist who enters this feel-good world, shakes the flow of the show. She has doubts about the kind of journalism this media group stands for. She has constant outbursts of journalistic integrity (much like she’s plucked out of the Sorkin universe), is absolutely apprehended by the overly narcissistic environment, and continually calls out the hypocrisies of the organisation. She acts as a conscience trope for journalism as a virtue. The news producer, and the owner have their own tensions and roles at the backdrop of the story. They show is well-balanced in its media representation that way and does for the media industry, what was long overdue. Gearing up for its second season, the show can further elevate or deteriorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were some of the representations of new broadcast media in the West, and of the West, that were worth analysing due to their brilliant execution. The developing countries of the East, like India, are still short of well-made media representations. Recent releases like &lt;em&gt;Paatal Lok&lt;/em&gt; have stirred this conversation in a much-needed direction, by accurately representing the dichotomies and hypocrisies of Indian journalism and media. Being a fourth pillar to democracy, we mustn’t infuriatingly bash our media sources. A way of portraying gratitude is through such media texts, and encouraging that is reinstating our belief in journalism and truth-telling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The digital revolution of old media into new media has taken shape very rapidly. Old media has seldom been given its due recognition. Traditional sources of information like newspapers and radio have sustained their quality in truth telling for ages. Its comparison is unparalleled when it comes to new media, which is why it still has a wide market and is almost irreplaceable. On the other hand, new media rose to power because of its instantaneous quality to connect and communicate. News became easy to deliver as new media defined its timeliness. It has definitely changed the dynamics of public consumption of news, heralding a phase in humanity where everything can be reported, by anyone, and at any time.</summary></entry></feed>