<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-03T12:23:36+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ole ‘Goner’ Solskjaer?</title><link href="/Ole-Goner" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ole ‘Goner’ Solskjaer?" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Ole-Goner</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Ole-Goner">&lt;p&gt;Since being appointed as permanent Manchester United manager, Ole Gunnar Solskjær’s win rate in the Premier League is just 32%, a figure meagre enough for any manager to get sacked, let alone one of a club who are so accustomed to glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do the problems begin and end at Manchester United?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to appoint Ole Gunnar Solskjær on a full-time basis in March 2019, after a 3 month period in which he was greatly successful, epitomised the naivety and ineptitude of the United board. For whatever reason, the United board could not wait until the end of the season to take a more balanced, level-headed decision on the managerial appointment. The fans could be forgiven for believing that the initial honeymoon period which saw a huge upturn in results made Ole the right man for the job, but for the board to buy into this delirium exhibits an utter lack of prudence and shrewdness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their haste to appoint the legendary former striker as manager, they took a risk which has backfired and the decision becomes ever more questionable and costly as each day passes by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last season, when Jose Mourinho was relieved of his duties by Ed Woodward, he had accumulated 26 points from 17 games in the league. This campaign, Ole has managed 25 points in the same number of games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester United have seemingly settled for mediocrity under Solskjær. In recent weeks, Arsenal, Tottenham and Everton have all fired their underperforming managers and replaced them. While United have dithered and dallied, Everton have been able to allure one of the most decorated managers in the world in Carlo Ancelotti, a man who surely would have been of interest to United.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If United were to sack Solskjær soon, Max Allegri and Mauricio Pochettino would be among the favourites to succeed the Norwegian. Ed Woodward and co. have long been admirers of former Spurs boss Pochettino, but they will have to act quickly if they wish to acquire his services. The Argentine has become one of the most sought after coaches in world football during the last few years and he will have no shortage of job offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hit and Miss Signings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signings have also been a sticking point of United’s in recent years. The £80m expended to obtain Harry Maguire was exorbitant, excessive and another example of United overpaying for a player. He’s undoubtedly one of the best centre-halves in the league, but his quality still fails to justify such an inflated fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexis Sanchez was another extortionate mistake, and while Fred has improved in recent weeks, the Brazilian is yet another player who has failed to vindicate such a large price tag. Meanwhile, defenders Diogo Dalot and Eric Bailly have failed to flourish and have subsequently fallen out of favour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youngsters Daniel James and Aaron Wan-Bissaka have been better signings, but both are still raw and will take time to develop into the class of player that United were previously famed for. They would also both benefit from competition for their places; ironically, they are more nailed on to start for Manchester United than they were at their respective previous clubs, Swansea City and Crystal Palace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back even further, the acquisitions of Wilfried Zaha and Memphis Depay perhaps came too early in their careers. Both have gone on to forge formidable reputations for themselves and proven that the Red Devils should have remained patient with them when they didn’t immediately thrive at such young ages. The star quality they possess certainly wouldn’t go amiss at United at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lacking a Playmaker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot has been made of the fact that the Red Devils struggle to break down opposition teams who sit deep. United are bereft of ideas when facing low blocks; they are crying out for a playmaker who can control the tempo of games and break teams down with line-breaking passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In games which tend to be more open, typically against higher quality opposition, United have enjoyed more success. They have the benefit of being able to utilise the lightning quick pace of Rashford, Martial and James, enabling them to be menacing on the break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one damning statistic which proves this notion. United currently lie in 6th place, and they have amassed 13 points from the 5 teams that sit above them, but just 12 points from the teams below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With recent victories over Spurs and rivals City, Ole has bought himself more time to prove to the Old Trafford faithful that he’s got what it takes to be successful in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a positive note, Solskjær is bringing the best out of Marcus Rashford this year. The 22-year-old is in sumptuous form, enjoying his best goal scoring season to date. This is perhaps one reason that the United hierarchy have no plans to sack their manager anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason for sticking with the Norweigian is stability. Stability is vital for any football club and group of players, and a club who had the same manager for 26 years prior to 2013 know that better than anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the reasons outlined above, United’s decay is not entirely the fault of the former Molde manager. He is struggling with an incompetent board and an imbalanced squad, but questions remain over whether Ole has the managerial experience and tactical acumen needed to prevail at the biggest club in England. With long-term managerial target Mauricio Pochettino currently out of a job, it would make sense for Ed Woodward to try to entice Pochettino towards Carrington.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ali Abdi</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">Since being appointed as permanent Manchester United manager, Ole Gunnar Solskjær’s win rate in the Premier League is just 32%, a figure meagre enough for any manager to get sacked, let alone one of a club who are so accustomed to glory.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Labour’s Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election</title><link href="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Labour's Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election">&lt;p&gt;In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boris Johnson, in pledging not only to deliver Brexit but to increase public expenditure by £13.4 billion in 2020–2021, which would be the largest increase in spending in 15 years, clearly provided a theoretical break from the austerity policies and supply-side economics which had characterised the Conservatives’ previous administrations in the wake of the Financial Crisis, enabling him to win over voters in Labour strongholds. It is unclear, however, if this ‘One-Nation Conservative’ rhetoric will translate into policy, as Boris Johnson has voted consistently in favour of austerity policies since being returned as an MP in 2015. Moreover, it is entirely probable that having won a demonstrable majority, the Conservatives may use their relative unaccountability to continue the same cuts to income tax and spending that they were previously committed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Labour, a schism between the Europhile, metropolitan, London-centric PLP and the Eurosceptic so-called ‘Red Wall’ of Northern, working class seats was the main source of their undoing. Labour lost 10.4% of the vote share in seats where 60% or more people voted Leave, as seats such as Sedgefield, Bolsover and Workington fell to the Conservatives. Dennis Skinner, a veteran Labour MP and former miner, lost his Bolsover seat after 49 years in Parliament. In 2017, when Labour had promised to honour the result of the referendum, they held 72 of the 100 constituencies in the most working class (C2DE) households. In 2019, this figure fell to 53, and the Conservatives increased their share from 13 to 31. Labour’s decision to cleave towards the centre to placate the Blairite elements of the Party was, therefore, an unmitigated catastrophe. Ian Lavery MP, who held onto his seat in Wansbeck in Northumberland by an unfathomably slender majority of just 800 votes, stated: “Ignore democracy and to be quite honest the consequences will come back and bite you up the backside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many voters in the aforementioned deindustrialised Northern towns now beset by a dismal combination of unemployment and precarious, low-wage service sector work, the fact that Labour had failed to completely acknowledge their Eurosceptic stance eroded their faith in democracy. Devoid for the most part of media influence or capital, the vote was the only way of making their voices heard. Having been neglected by a London-centric party and a political consensus dominated for decades by financialisation, the City of London and an obsession with GDP as the sole indicator of the prosperity of the nation, they struck a lethal blow against those who purported but failed to represent them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perception of Jeremy Corbyn as an inadequate leader was another prevalent theme both on the doorstep and in mainstream political coverage throughout the election. Media coverage of Corbyn was relentlessly brutal. The virulent anti-Corbyn rhetoric even predated the election, as during the past 3 years, he has been referred to as a Czech spy, a Russian agent, an anti-semite and a Communist. It is undeniable that there are antisemitic elements within the Labour Party that Corbyn has been indecisive in removing, and that the British Left has a long and disgraceful history of indulging antisemitism, aptly described by August Bebel as “the socialism of fools”. Keir Hardie, the first ever Labour leader, blamed Jewish financial houses for the outbreak of the First World War. However, Corbyn himself has a long and understated history of opposing antisemitism. As far back as 1977, for example, Corbyn organised a counter-demonstration in defence of London’s Jewish community against 1,000 National Front members who attempted to march through Wood Green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blairites and moderate voices within the Labour movement continue to portray this election as proof that it is left wing policies that are unpopular rather than the party’s Brexit stance and alienation of its core voting bloc. They suggest that the Labour Party must revert to a pro-corporate ideology, being at ease with privatisation, marketisation and a bellicose foreign policy. Yet this is directly contradicted by the available evidence: a 2017 YouGov poll found that 60% of the British public support renationalising the railways, 59% support taking water into public ownership, and 53% supported public ownership of the energy companies. 60% also back higher levels of taxation and spending. To argue that the statistical success of Tony Blair compared to Jeremy Corbyn represents a necessity to return to a Blairite brand of politics is to misunderstand that the political context has changed significantly since 1997. A global financial crash, the longest squeeze in wages since the Napoleonic Wars, and house prices rising to 7.8 times the amount of annual salaries demonstrate that a significantly greater amount of fiscal intervention is required to alleviate the crises of the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technocratic, Blairite conception of politics, which focuses entirely on winning power for its own sake and ignores the broader contexts in which new political and economic ideas come to the fore, has subsided. It has been proposed, therefore, that the future of the Labour Party is a combination of a culturally conservative, patriotic communitarianism with economic leftism of the kind espoused by figures such as Clement Attlee and George Lansbury. The resurgence of ‘Blue Labour’ attests to this. However, it must be acknowledged that Labour is a party that, for decades, has attempted to straddle a coalition of voters with fundamentally different outlooks and views of the world that may be considered irreconcilable. Socially-liberal graduates in Manchester and London, harbouring an instinctual aversion to the monarchy and the nation-state, on whom the Labour Party also depends, would be alienated by such a platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reconnect with its core vote, and to pull together its fractured coalition of voters, Labour will need a sustained and coordinated presence within areas of the country which perceive them to be London-centric and elitist, rather than merely turning up a week prior to the election and expecting votes. The neoliberal atomisation and individualism which characterise the present political era have torn asunder many community institutions which once fostered political dialogue and enabled people to become involved with politics. Therefore, much of the impetus must come from the grassroots elements of the party, with a priority placed on engaging in programmes such as the National Food Service and serving the concerns of local residents regarding ordinary issues such as education, housing and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the schisms and fissures within the Labour Party, and between the party and the electorate have been destructive and have led to the party’s near annihilation. There is a significant amount of soul-searching to be done, as the Labour Party desperately attempts to avoid decades in political oblivion. Reconnection with the party’s Northern heartlands will be a clear priority, as will grassroots level organising and education. But some of these ideological vicissitudes, such as the gap between voters in the Northern heartlands and those in the major cities, run so deep that it is difficult to see the party recovering from them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">India Under Siege: How the Hindu Extremists are Destroying India</title><link href="/India-Under-Siege-How-Hindu-Extremists-are-Destroying-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="India Under Siege: How the Hindu Extremists are Destroying India" /><published>2019-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/India-Under-Siege-How-Hindu-Extremists-are-Destroying-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/India-Under-Siege-How-Hindu-Extremists-are-Destroying-India">&lt;p&gt;The Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2019 of the Parliament of India, which received Presidential assent on December 12, has a stated objective that appears upon first glance to be rather innocent. The purported goal is to provide a safe haven in India for persecuted religious minorities from other countries. However, hidden beneath the sophisticated wording of the Act lies a nefarious intention, one which has not gone unnoticed, thanks be to God. You see, although the proponents of this legislation speak with great orchestrated zeal about the need to welcome people from the vicinity of South-East Asia, the Act actually covers only three of India’s neighbours: Pakistan, Bangladesh and Afghanistan. All of these three are – notice! – Islamic countries. Other neighbours such as Nepal, China, Myanmar and Sri Lanka are very quietly left out, despite the fact that there is strong evidence of religious minorities experiencing persecution in many of these countries, the Rohingya Muslims from Myanmar and the Tamil Hindus of Sri Lanka being two prominent examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This careful (and obviously deliberate) exclusion is itself suspicious and meritorious of outrage and protest, but it gets even worse. Even with the inclusion of these three nations mentioned in the Act, only six religious communities are actually offered refuge: Hindus, Buddhists, Jains, Sikhs, Zoroastrians and Christians. If you notice, there is one community that is left out: Islam, despite the fact that the Ahmadiyya and Shia communities – both of which identify very strongly as Muslim and have a significant following in these areas – are sometimes just as marginalized and persecuted as Hindus and Buddhists, if not more so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this Act effectively results in is a horrendous state of affairs that would have scandalized the founding fathers of the modern Indian Republic. For the very first time in our history, citizenship is being offered in a special and expedited manner to members from some religious communities and not others, in clear contravention of the right to equality enshrined in the Indian Constitution, which has been held by the Indian Supreme Court to apply to all and not just Indian citizens. Perhaps if no Muslims in the neighbouring countries were being persecuted on religious grounds, this Act could have been justified. But there are Muslims being persecuted on the basis of their beliefs – quite a lot of them actually! – and this law silently excludes them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proponents of this law have argued that although certain Muslim communities are indeed marginalized in these lands, these are ultimately inter-sectarian disputes and therefore not nearly as grave a divide as the inter-religious schisms. However, this is patently false. There are quite a few Muslim fundamentalists who are of the opinion, for example, that Ahmadis are not a competing sect of Islam, but rather are entirely outside the fold of Islam. If you want evidence of this, see an example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nMunEdtjqJ0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; of extreme anti-Ahmadi rhetoric by an ultra-conservative Sunni. This has also spilled out into the political sphere. In 1984, an amendment was passed in Pakistan which prohibited Ahmadis from calling themselves Muslim or from posing as Muslims, a crime which was punishable by three years in prison!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, one might ask what the need was to selectively mention religious communities in the Act. Why not simply offer refuge to anyone who has been persecuted on the grounds of his/her religious belief? What difference does it make whether he/she is an adherent of an ancient faith like Hinduism or a community founded five years ago? Religious persecution is religious persecution, regardless of which faith or community we are talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Indian government is adamant. The Indian Home Minister Amit Shah insists that no Muslims are persecuted in Afghanistan, Pakistan and Bangladesh on religious grounds. &lt;em&gt;This is manifestly false&lt;/em&gt; (as I mentioned earlier), but suppose for a moment (for the sake of argument) that it is true. Even then, this still leaves an important question unanswered: why are other neighbouring states left out? Why not talk about Myanmar and the Rohingya community who have suffered so terribly at the hands of fundamentalists? Why include Bangladeshi Hindus and ignore Burmese Muslims. India’s government insists that they are not anti-Muslim, but their acts (as well as the words of many of their leaders) suggest otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, however, the country has not stayed silent on this issue. India has, quite literally erupted in protest. Be it &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/politics-and-nation/delhi-anti-caa-protesters-set-fire-on-bbuses-jamia-millia-islamia-students-blamed/videoshow/72683068.cms&quot;&gt;Delhi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/india/story/cab-protest-violent-protests-west-bengal-buses-railway-station-torched-1628289-2019-12-14&quot;&gt;West Bengal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/patna/anti-caa-stir-mob-torches-police-post-and-bikes-in-patna/articleshow/72696682.cms&quot;&gt;Bihar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livemint.com/news/india/protests-hit-the-streets-against-cab-in-hyderabad-11576412081945.html&quot;&gt;Hyderabad&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/et-explains/citizenship-bill-why-is-assam-protesting/articleshow/72483294.cms&quot;&gt;North East&lt;/a&gt; of India, thousands are coming out onto the streets to oppose this discriminatory legislation, though not always for the same reasons. Almost every opposition party – including the right-wing former BJP ally Shiv Sena – has voiced its disapproval. And in many cases, protests have turned violent. Obviously, I condemn any form of unlawful violence, but I do not think it can be reasonably denied that the BJP government is responsible for passing a bill that has angered and divided large sections of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In such a situation of unprecedented public unrest, the right thing for the government to do is halt all legislation and seek dialogue with the protesters. After all, India is still – at least in theory – a democratic country in which the government is directly accountable to the people. However, this is not happening. Rather, the authorities have seen fit to resort to seemingly totalitarian measures in an attempt to suppress public dissent. &lt;a href=&quot;https://gadgets.ndtv.com/internet/news/assam-cab-protests-internet-shutdown-december-16-2148819&quot;&gt;The internet was shut down in Assam for more than 24 hours&lt;/a&gt;, and now &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.news18.com/news/tech/citizenship-act-protests-internet-shutdown-in-aligarh-meerut-and-west-bengal-2425545.html&quot;&gt;in parts of West Bengal as well&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://scroll.in/latest/946906/citizenship-act-protestors-clash-with-police-in-delhi-buses-set-on-fire&quot;&gt;Delhi police stormed the campus of Jamia Milia University&lt;/a&gt; on the night of December 15, firing live rounds on students and tear gas shells in the university library, giving us scenes from an Orwellian novel rather than a constitutional democracy. A female journalist from the &lt;em&gt;BBC&lt;/em&gt; reported being the target of male law officers: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/india/story/citizenship-amendment-act-protest-jamia-millia-islamia-students-journalist-attacked-delhi-police-1628500-2019-12-15&quot;&gt;her hair was pulled, she was beaten and her phone was broken&lt;/a&gt;. These are but a few examples of public vandalism and violence perpetrated by the very people tasked with maintaining law and order. In short, the country is in flames.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue has not gone unnoticed by the international community. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thewire.in/rights/united-nations-high-commissioner-for-human-rights-cab&quot;&gt;The United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights &lt;/a&gt; has criticised the Indian government over the “fundamentally discriminatory” nature of the law. The United States Commission for International Religious Freedom (USCIRF) &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/politics-and-nation/cab-passed-in-ls-federal-us-commission-seeks-american-sanctions-against-amit-shah/videoshow/72450703.cms&quot;&gt;even sought sanctions against the Home Minister Amit Shah&lt;/a&gt;. The Act has also drawn strong (though perhaps hypocritical) criticism from both &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/videos/news/pakistan-pm-imran-khan-strongly-condemns-citizenship-amendment-bill/videoshow/72452874.cms&quot;&gt;Pakistan&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/india/video/bangladesh-hits-out-at-india-after-parliament-passes-cab-1627664-2019-12-12&quot;&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/a&gt;. In all of this, my heart goes out especially to the Ahmadi community. They are perhaps the most peaceful religious denomination that self-identifies as Muslim, and yet they are subject to horrific persecution. Shias still have a safe haven in Iran, but Ahmadis literally have nowhere to go in the Islamic world. The exclusion of Ahmadis from the Act is bizarre and barbaric. But it only serves to show the regressive mindset of the current government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indians need to wake up and realize that this is not at all a harmless piece of legislation. This may well be the first step to a &lt;em&gt;‘Hindu Rashtra’&lt;/em&gt; or ‘Hindu Country’. This is a frightening prospect; for centuries India has been a land of religious tolerance and cultural pluralism. Any attempt to homogenise the country is a direct assault not merely on its Constitution but on the very spirit of what it means to be Indian. As an Indian, I think it is incumbent upon every one of us to take a strong stand against this exclusionary bill and to resist this attempted move towards what truly seems to look like fascism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anonymous</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="conscience" /><summary type="html">The Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2019 of the Parliament of India, which received Presidential assent on December 12, has a stated objective that appears upon first glance to be rather innocent. The purported goal is to provide a safe haven in India for persecuted religious minorities from other countries. However, hidden beneath the sophisticated wording of the Act lies a nefarious intention, one which has not gone unnoticed, thanks be to God. You see, although the proponents of this legislation speak with great orchestrated zeal about the need to welcome people from the vicinity of South-East Asia, the Act actually covers only three of India’s neighbours: Pakistan, Bangladesh and Afghanistan. All of these three are – notice! – Islamic countries. Other neighbours such as Nepal, China, Myanmar and Sri Lanka are very quietly left out, despite the fact that there is strong evidence of religious minorities experiencing persecution in many of these countries, the Rohingya Muslims from Myanmar and the Tamil Hindus of Sri Lanka being two prominent examples.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Atheism Destroys Science and Progress. Here’s How.</title><link href="/Atheism-Destroys" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atheism Destroys Science and Progress. Here’s How." /><published>2019-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Atheism-Destroys</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Atheism-Destroys">&lt;p&gt;It might sound strange to say that atheism destroys science. Indeed, many will laugh merely upon reading the heading of this article. However, my interactions with sceptics and postmodernists have convinced me that while it may seem to many that atheism leads to science and moral progress, the truth is exactly the opposite. Rather than upholding science, atheism destroys the foundations that underlie science; and far from promoting human progress, atheism degrades humanity and inevitably leads to moral decay in society. Not only that, I am also deeply convinced that a postmodernist attitude is simply the result of centuries of atheist influence upon the West; a true atheist will, in my opinion, adopt a postmodern outlook sooner or later. In this article, I hope to show why I think this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a Christian, let’s talk about Christianity for a moment. As the Oxford mathematician and Christian thinker John Lennox has remarked multiple times, many of the scientists of the early Modern era were Christians because their faith in God led them to expect order and stability in the universe. Indeed, many of the very people who laid the foundations of science in the post-Reformation West were devoutly Christian people, believing that the study of the creation was a kind of worship to God. Indeed, that is my own opinion as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Christian, I believe that God gave us rationality so that we could use it to study and learn more about the world in which we live. My belief that my mind and my sense organs are a gift of God gives me sufficient ground to trust it as being reliable in giving me information about this wonderful universe which we are privileged to call home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, an atheist cannot say the same thing. For suppose that we live in a world that is merely a cosmic accident, and suppose – for the sake of argument – that the material reality is all that exists and there is no spiritual dimension whatsoever. Under this view, the mind is purely a material phenomenon and is directly equivalent to the brain. There is no aspect whatsoever to the mind that is immaterial under this view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the brain is merely a conglomeration of nerves and chemicals. In a purely physical, materialistic world, what we perceive as emotions, thoughts and feelings are merely the result of chemicals firing around in our brain. Even our deepest moral sentiments are simply the products of how our brain has been evolved to think and perceive reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this is true, then how can the atheist say that his senses and rational powers are capable of giving him an accurate depiction of reality? If the mind is simply a physical organ that is determined to function and act in a particular way (because of the evolutionary path that it happened to take), then there are no rational grounds for trusting your perception or your ability to reason. After all, everything – in an atheistic worldview – is a cosmic accident and the way your brain thinks and perceives something to be ‘rational’ or ‘logical’ or ‘reasonable’ is merely an accident as well. If evolution had taken a different path, then your brain might not even have existed… or it would have existed, but it would be operating in a different manner, giving you a different perception of what you call ‘reality’. But in that situation, you would have had radically different beliefs and ways of perceiving the world. What you today call ‘reasonable’ might under that circumstance appear absurd or farcical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that the atheist falls into a bit of a quandary. One alternative is that he can admit the fact and say that he simply ‘trusts’ his ability to reason and operates with that as his basic epistemological presupposition. But if this is so, then he cannot in good conscience criticize religious faith, since that too is a kind of trust in things we might not be able to “prove” with mathematical accuracy. Another alternative is that he can admit the fact I have mentioned and collapse into a kind of postmodernism, looking at all things – science included! – with scepticism, since even scientific observations are dependant upon human perception, which cannot be ‘proven’ per se to be reliable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, if we were living in the Matrix, chances are we wouldn’t know that we were!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same thing holds true for morality. We all – atheists and Christians included – have basic moral instincts. From a Christian point of view, I believe that God is perfect and he gives us a basic knowledge of what is right and wrong. Thus, as a Christian, I can say with conviction that certain things are basically right and others are basically wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can the atheist say such a thing? Certainly, atheists have moral beliefs, but can they justify those beliefs? After all, if there is no God and if materialistic naturalism is true, then there are no objective moral principles. Whatever morality we might have is purely subjective. Our mind is conditioned to think in a particular way – morally speaking - because of external accidental circumstances. Morality, in an atheistic worldview, inevitably becomes either a psychological construct or a societal one. On the former view, it is primarily evolution that conforms us to have certain moral instincts – and, remember, there is no guarantee that evolution would have taken the path it ultimately took! On the latter view, morality is primarily the result of societal conditioning – we happen to live in a society that values liberty and freedom; therefore, we have learned to value them as well. Had we lived in a cannibalistic society we would have had different moral values. This is called the doctrine of Cultural Relativism, and in this philosophy, no particular moral code is intrinsically superior to another, since they are all cultural constructs and all cultures are equally true and equally false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is not that atheists don’t have a sense of morality – they certainly do. The problem, rather, is that their metaphysical worldview cripples them from having an objective foundation for their morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is heart-breaking for me as a Christian to see prominent thinkers and philosophers encourage people to embrace a worldview in which everything is fundamentally meaningless and to “get used to it” (quoting Dr Susan Blackwood in her dialogue with Professor Jordan Peterson on the &lt;em&gt;Unbelievable?&lt;/em&gt; radio podcast). It is just as upsetting to see the rise of postmodern thinking in our world. I am convinced that such a mode of looking at the world will inevitably give birth to a society of depression and despair. And this observation vindicates my deeply Christian belief that only God can give true meaning and value to our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People might find it similarly shocking that I claim atheism degrades human beings. After all, don’t many atheists identify as ‘humanists’? Don’t so many atheists fight so vigorously for human rights and don’t humanists try and oppose oppression around the world? An atheist friend of mine once quipped to me that the modern West is proof that we can have morality without God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t disagree more. And here’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give one example: most atheists don’t, as far as I know, fight for the rights of the unborn. In fact, prominent atheists like Sam Harris complain that religious bigots such as myself still try to stop embryonic stem cell research. Similarly, I have never heard an atheist oppose the recent legislations that have effectively allowed the monstrosity of late-term abortions in New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not only the unborn who are being marginalized. Peter Singer, a prominent atheist ethicist, openly declares that – like unborn foetuses – new-born infants similarly lack what he calls the essential characteristics of personhood. The troubling implications of such a horrendous line of thinking are so alarming that words fail to convey the emotions that stir up in my heart as I write this article. And what is even more scandalous is that Singer is a vegan, although – as he would put it – a ‘flexible vegan’. In other words, he goes to great lengths to ensure that cows and buffaloes don’t suffer because of him… but that same privilege is not extended even to new-born babies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing. I believe that deep down, everyone has a sense of right and wrong. And this sense has been given to them by God. If you want proof that a Divine Law does indeed exist, then turn to your own conscience. I believe that deep down, everyone knows that good and evil are real, but over time they manufacture philosophies and ideologies to rationalise away what they do not want to be true. Because if there is a Divine Law, you are not ‘free’ to enjoy things that are evil, however attractive or pleasurable that might be. And if there is a Divine Law, there must also be a Divine Law-giver before whom we are all accountable for our actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that you can’t be good without fear of punishment. On the contrary, I believe that the good should be sought for its own sake, rather than merely out of servile fear. Rather, what I am saying is that if there is no God, then good and evil are both illusions and have no real existence. And if that is so, then everything is permitted, since all things are then morally equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the disastrous implications of the revolution that our world has initiated against God. And you will then forgive me when I say that atheism is not a boon. It is, in fact, poison.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It might sound strange to say that atheism destroys science. Indeed, many will laugh merely upon reading the heading of this article. However, my interactions with sceptics and postmodernists have convinced me that while it may seem to many that atheism leads to science and moral progress, the truth is exactly the opposite. Rather than upholding science, atheism destroys the foundations that underlie science; and far from promoting human progress, atheism degrades humanity and inevitably leads to moral decay in society. Not only that, I am also deeply convinced that a postmodernist attitude is simply the result of centuries of atheist influence upon the West; a true atheist will, in my opinion, adopt a postmodern outlook sooner or later. In this article, I hope to show why I think this is the case.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India’s Side</title><link href="/Sikhs-in-Canada" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India's Side" /><published>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Sikhs-in-Canada</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Sikhs-in-Canada">&lt;p&gt;For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘&lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when &lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the broader picture of Indo-Canadian relations shows a little more animosity between the two countries. The two countries share various complementarities, like their democratic character and association with the Commonwealth. Despite this and both countries recognising the economic potential in their bilateral ties, the relationship has been rather tense on the political front and thus has not prospered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major factor for this has been the activities of the Khalistan supporters in Canada. Canada’s criticism of India has also been responsible for denting India’s interest in engaging with Canada as a strategic partner. These criticisms have involved past events such as the military action in Amritsar’s Golden Temple and the 1984 riots. Relations reached one of their lowest points in 1985, when Sikh extremists blew up Air India Flight 182 as it left Vancouver Airport for India, killing all 329 passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides these issues, the current political scenario of Canada has also caused some concern for India. Because of the prominent involvement of Sikhs in Canada’s politics and the regionalisation of Indo-Canadian politics, issues affecting the Sikh diaspora have often become a part of the political discourse in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While moderates view India favourably and oppose secessionist sentiments, the fundamentalist groups, such as the Babbar Khalsa, vehemently advocate for the Khalistan cause. Events like the 1984 riots and the Golden Temple incident have been frequently introduced in Canada’s provincial legislatures, often in the form of petitions. In 2010, for instance, Liberal MPs Sukh Dhaliwal and Andrew Kania introduced a petition in the House of Commons asking Canada to consider the 1984 riots as an act of genocide and discuss the issue with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin Trudeau has often been caught in the crossfire between pandering to the Sikh population in his country and maintaining peaceful relations with India. Canadian politicians tread a fine line when attempting to involve themselves in the Sikh community, ensuring that people do not see them advocating for separatist causes inadvertently. The Sikhs in Canada form a voting bloc for Trudeau. In April 2019, his government removed a reference to Sikh extremism from a report that had earlier termed Sikh terrorism as one of the five threats facing Canada. He even attended a Khalsa Day parade organized by a radical Gurudwara in Toronto in 2017 where people waved Khalistani flags and put images of Sikh separatist leaders and militants on display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada cannot curtail the right to freedom of speech and expression of its Sikh citizens, but New Delhi wants Trudeau to distance himself from Sikh separatists, publicly. PM Narendra Modi clarified that India would not tolerate any attempts to undermine India’s sovereignty and unity in his press conference with Trudeau. Punjab’s Chief Minister, Amarinder Singh has publicly accused Trudeau’s ministers of having sympathies with Canadian Sikh extremists and secessionists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 Sikhs were voted into the 338-seat lower house of the Canadian Parliament in the 2019 Federal Elections. However, only 13 candidates from the Sikh community were elected to the 543-seat Lok Sabha in the 17th General Elections in India. Sikhs form approximately 2% of the population both in Canada and India, but their representation in politics is unmatched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of these 18 Sikhs is the leader of the National Democratic Party (NDP), Jagmeet Singh. A former criminal lawyer, Singh created political history in Canada when he made his debut in the House of Commons as the first non-white leader of a major opposition party in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-election polls showed he was the most popular of the three party leaders. Singh is your poster woke boy with swag. Recognised in Canadian media for his fashion sense and style, Singh identifies as a progressive and a social democrat. He supports a progressive tax system and a $15 per hour minimum wage. He strongly advocates for equality, and supports LGBTQ rights. He also wants to save the planet by reducing the carbon emissions levels of Canada to 30% of 2005 levels by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Canada’s highly decentralised federation, forming the government at the provincial level makes the NDP an influential political force. Being led federally by a “visible minority” makes it a prominent symbol of the maturity of Canada’s multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Democratic Party, despite winning only 24 seats in the 2019 General Elections, has become one of the most talked-about parties. We can attribute two key factors to this popularity: (i) Singh’s speech in the democratic debate and (ii) the Liberal Party emerged as a minority party in the elections. Despite the Liberal Party staying a minority party in the House of Commons, forming a coalition with the NDP to govern, as the majority party, had been a general suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canadian media refer to Singh as the “kingmaker” in the legislative. The Liberal Party would need NDP’s votes on issues where the NDP and Liberals are more aligned than the Conservatives are, to pass any bill. For India, its interest in Singh is not one of pride that an Indian rose to become the leader of a major political party in a powerful Western state. Instead, the power Singh holds having entered the Canadian parliament has become a matter of concern for India. He has had a history of defending militants fighting for a separate Sikh homeland and lobbying for labeling a 1984 pogrom against Sikhs in India a ‘genocide’ by the government of Ontario. While he has not offered unqualified support to the Khalistan cause and remains vague on the issue, he has criticised India for Operation Blue Star. Singh will now have a far more consequential platform to continue his activism concerning attempting to seek justice for several violent episodes in India’s past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, India denied Jagmeet Singh a visa to visit because he was “misusing the pretext of human rights to pursue his insidious agenda of disturbing the social fabric of India and undermining the peace, harmony and territorial integrity of India.” For a provincial politician, this is notable. But as the leader of a major political party with a seat in the country’s main legislative body, this suspicion towards Singh by a friendly country is of more substantial potential consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has dealt with a partition once before and thus has little tolerance for movements that could threaten further division of the state. This and the fact that India comprises culturally distinct regions make its current integrity reliant on a compact of pluralism. Khalistan seems to have more significant traction in the Sikh diaspora than it does in Punjab. Because of which India seems more concerned about diaspora movements that agitate for its creation than internal movements. Thus, India is sensitive towards anything that it perceives as a threat to its unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Singh is leading a deeply divided party that is facing severe fundraising deficits and a significant number of experienced MPs who won’t be seeking re-election. If he wishes to use his new platform to bring light to the injustices of India in the 1980’s, Singh would have to wait until he has dealt with the more direct concerns of his party first. The primary focus of the realities of Singh’s role at home may just save New Delhi from having to be overly concerned with him for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘Caneda’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when Caneda’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Indian Anchor in the Baltic Sea</title><link href="/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Anchor in the Baltic Sea" /><published>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea">&lt;p&gt;The Vice President of India, M Venkaiah Naidu visited the three Baltic nations: Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia from August 17-21, 2019. The visit was unprecedented, it was the first high-level trip from India to these nations. While India has hosted the Lithuanian Vice President, the Latvian President and Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister of Estonia in the past, there had been no reciprocal high-level visits until recently. It was only in 2016 when Minister for Electronics and Information Technology, Mr Ravishankar Prasad visited Estonia. This visit corrected the imbalance between incoming and outgoing heads of states, sending out the message that India recognises the importance of the Baltic nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Baltic nations have come a long way from the history of occupations, finally gaining independence in 1991. Today, they stand as global leaders in artificial intelligence, e-governance and e-security. Coming to the Fourth Industrial Revolution, India sees an organic alliance with these countries, thus, calling for outreach from the Indian side. Furthermore, China is fast increasing its footprint in the Baltic region in the setup of the ‘New Great Game,’ so, India has to step up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s foreign policy for Europe has concentrated only on Western Europe, with the UK, France, Germany, Italy and Spain. The Baltic outreach is a correction of this skewed worldview and a move to strengthen bilateral relations with small nations rather than treating them as subsets of their relationships with other big powers. The Vice President’s visit is expected to open more novel opportunities for cooperation in sectors discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bilateral trade between India and Latvia stood at about US$141 million in 2015-16. Major Indian exports were tea, coffee, tools, pharmaceuticals, chemicals, garments, iron and steel. Indian imports majorly composed of chemicals, fertilizers, iron and steel, and machinery. In the case of Estonia, total bilateral trade in 2018-19 was US$172.53 million with machinery and equipment, garments, knitwear, coffee, tea, spices, footwear and pharmaceutical products as major export items. Imports from Estonia were mainly in iron and steel, fertilizers, electrical machinery, paper and paperboard, and paper pulp. Bilateral trade between India and Lithuania stood at about US$ 215 million in 2015-16. Major Indian exports to Lithuania included vegetable saps and extracts, fish fillets and other fish meat, medicaments, footwear, ferroalloys, carpets and rice. Lithuanian exports to India included mineral or chemical fertilizers, potassic, dried leguminous vegetables, wadding of textile materials, nickel waste and scrap, diagnostic or laboratory reagents on backing and machzone-therapy appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a scope for growth of textiles, agro-products, gems and jewellery, chemical dyes and pharmaceuticals exports to the Baltic nations. Import of technology would be an important area in the relationship between these nations and India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connectivity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a response to China’s Belt and Road Initiative, India is keenly pushing the International North-South Transport Corridor. This is meant to provide an alternative to the Mediterranean Sea and the Suez Canal as a shorter route for the movement of trade through Central Asia and Russia. A major plus point of the project is that it will help Asian and European countries to transport their cargo at double the speed compared to the Suez Canal. This route can be expanded to connect Baltic, Nordic and Arctic regions and thus enhance connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latvia’s ice-free Riga port connects the Baltic region with the rest of Europe, Russia and Central Asia. An agreement on this port can help Indian exports reach European markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Union is developing the “Rail Baltica” project under the Trans-European Transport Network (TEN-T). This project connects cooperating member states to the Baltic nations with the existing European Rail network. This project aimed at taking the Baltic nations out of the Soviet shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cyber-Security and IT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia is a world leader in information technology, e-governance, cyber-security and innovation. The software developers from the country developed the code for Skype and Kazaa. The country is home to NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence. In 2007, it became the first country to allow online voting in the general elections. High-tech industries now account for 15% of the country’s GDP. The Indian government and businesses are trying to come to terms with the disruption caused by artificial intelligence and big data. Deeper collaboration between Estonian and Indian businesses can reap benefits for both. The experiments with proxy voting and simultaneous polls would call for government-to-government collaboration and best practices from Estonia would come handy. An MoU for Cooperation in e-Governance and emerging digital technologies and Cooperation in Cyber Security has been signed in this regard. Lithuania sees an opportunity in Brexit and is fast emerging as a hub in Fintech. With the Fourth Industrial revolution, these bilateral relationships will become vital for India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lithuania can be a strong technology partner in agro-processing and pharma, with expertise in dairy and cheese production. Agri-tech can help realise the vision of improving agricultural productivity hence, doubling farmer incomes by 2022 for India. It can help fuel growth in India’s food processing industry which is at a nascent stage with only 5% of the total production being processed. Laser technology has emerged as a strategic trade item from Lithuania to India, especially sought after by Indian universities and research centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renewable Energy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania have very high energy dependence on Russian gas pipelines, owing to their Soviet past. The European Union Climate and Energy Package has helped the Baltic Nations improve the energy security stance by increasing production from renewable sources of energy. Despite its shale oil reserves, Estonia is transitioning away from fossil fuels to biofuels, photovoltaics (PV) and wind. Estonia was the first European country to adopt electric and hybrid cars. It hosts big solar parks with a total capacity of 3GWh. The Baltic nation is planning to plunge into wind power, despite the shale reserves fulfilling 85% of the energy needs. Lithuania too is venturing into the renewable energy space through wind power and biomass (biogas and waste). The country aims to increase the share of renewables in its electricity mix to 23% by 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the speed with which these nations are diversifying their energy needs, they can be useful partners in the International Solar Alliance started in Paris by PM Modi. They could play a vital role in enabling the rapid deployment of solar energy globally and facilitating technology transfer. Given high import dependency for its energy needs, India can facilitate study tours for officials for the transfer of best practices from these countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education &amp;amp; Employment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been an increase in the number of outbound students to the Baltic Nations. According to data from the Indian embassy, 100 Indian students are currently studying in Latvia, 211 in Estonia and 600 in Lithuania. The main attraction is affordable education without compromising on the quality. Indian Vice President also lauded the e-residency scheme launched in 2014 by Estonia as “a launchpad for Indians in the Baltic, Nordic and European markets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite encouraging numbers, the mobility of students and the workforce is still below potential. Education fairs and awareness programmes are essential to tap the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian companies such as Indorama, Wipro, Tata Consultancy Services, Larsen &amp;amp; Toubro and Bharat Forge have made investments in the region. Indian companies are being wooed by promoting this region as a cost-effective and productive destination with high research capabilities. An investment of US$200 million has been made by Indorama, a Lohia Group company in the Klaipeda Economic Zone in Lithuania on a plant to manufacture plastic resin. The Indian embassy and Assocham carried out ‘Make in India: Roadshow’ to promote India as an exciting investment location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India and Baltic regions have common linguistic roots and cultural similarities. For instance, Sanskrit and Lithuanian have around 10,000 words in common. The study of Indian languages (mainly Hindi and Sanskrit) is carried in Vilnius University at the Centre of Indian Studies, under the Department of Oriental Studies. The University of Tartu in Estonia began teaching Sanskrit in 1837. The Baltic nations have a great interest in Yoga and Ayurveda. The University of Latvia in collaboration with the Arya Vaidya Pharmacy, Coimbatore has been conducting a 3-month Diploma course in Introduction to Ayurveda since February 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooperation in Multilateral Forums&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outreach to Baltic nations has helped India secure a non-permanent seat in the United Nations Security Council from 2021-22. These nations have also supported India as a permanent member in an enlarged and reformed UNSC. The support from small nations puts pressure on bigger nations to pay attention to the agenda of reforms. Besides, Estonia would have a non-permanent seat in the UNSC beginning from 2020. India and Estonia can support each other in the UNSC if bilateral relations see an upward trend. A seasoned diplomat noted that these nations can prove to be good interlocutors for India vis-a-vis the European Union. A bone of contention between India and the European Union has been the Comprehensive Bilateral Trade and Investment Agreement (BTIA), and Baltic nations can play a constructive role in negotiating that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the vibrancy of the partnership, it can be safely concluded that only sky’s the limit. Governmental support, availability of skilled labour, ease of doing business and a conducive environment are essential to realise the objectives of the partnership. Godspeed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gurleen Kaur</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The Vice President of India, M Venkaiah Naidu visited the three Baltic nations: Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia from August 17-21, 2019. The visit was unprecedented, it was the first high-level trip from India to these nations. While India has hosted the Lithuanian Vice President, the Latvian President and Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister of Estonia in the past, there had been no reciprocal high-level visits until recently. It was only in 2016 when Minister for Electronics and Information Technology, Mr Ravishankar Prasad visited Estonia. This visit corrected the imbalance between incoming and outgoing heads of states, sending out the message that India recognises the importance of the Baltic nations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?</title><link href="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?" /><published>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donald Trump on the eve of the 18th anniversary of the 9/11 commemorations on September 11, 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This will lead to more losses to the US. Its credibility will be affected, its anti-peace stance will be exposed to the world, losses to lives and assets will increase.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zabihullah Mujahid, a Talib spokesman criticising the US President for calling off the dialogue between the US and the Taliban.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest concerns pervading global geopolitics in the second decade of the 21st century is the solution to what may be referred to as the “Afghanistan policy of the United States.” The peace process, a mediation attempt in what is regarded as one of the greatest standoffs of our times, has met a dead-end. Peace negotiations between the two sides were stalled off unexpectedly, with the US pulling from the expected accord using a proverbial reason too flimsy for most observers of global politics. Trump has pushed the reason that there has been an uptick in Taliban-inflicted violence all across Afghanistan as well the death of an American soldier along with 11 other people in a suicide bombing which shook the national capital of Kabul in the month of September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To receive a better understanding of this more recent development, it is imperative to cast a glance at the intricacies that have led to the stalemate today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term Taliban can be literally translated as ‘students.’ It can be referred to as an attempt to construct an Islamic Empire in Afghanistan. The Sunni Islamic organisation rose to prominence in 1994, as part of an attempt to end the power vacuum that had exerted itself in the nation as an immediate after-effect of the Afghan Civil War. The Afghan Civil War had resulted in the drop of Kabul’s population from 2 million to 500,000 within a span of a year. It began when Hezb-e-Islami led by Gulbuddin Hekmatyar with the support of neighbouring Pakistan’s Inter-Services Intelligence (ISI) had refused to be a part of the coalition government along with other Mujahideen Groups, establishing their sole authority over Kabul. It was only a year later in 1995-1996 that the militia of the Talibans, having secured sufficient support from Pakistan and ISI, established its supremacy and invaded Kandahar, followed by Herat, with their authority receiving a formal seal of suzerainty with the successful invasion of Kabul in 1996. Al-Qaeda had been granted sanction to operate by the Taliban on the condition that it would not indulge in any activity that could incur the wrath of the US. But the subsequent actions of its leader, Osama Bin Laden’s attack on the American embassies of East Africa, caused a rift between the Taliban and the Al-Qaeda. Many may sight that Al-Qaeda harboured a greater ambition - that of global jihad while Talibans had a restrictive operational base called Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post 9/11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Powell had famously remarked, “You can be sure that the American Spirit will prevail over this tragedy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest turning points of the new millennium had been the four coordinated terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001 at three prime locations in the heart of the United States that killed 2,977 people, injuring 25,000 more. Truly, American foreign policy never remained the same with Islamic nations across the globe, and with Afghanistan, quite obviously, having to bear the brunt. The US demanded that the Taliban hand over Osama Bin Laden, the mastermind behind the tragedy, which was rejected by the Taliban as they demanded greater evidence of his involvement in the terror attack. In response, the US-NATO alliance launched Operation Enduring Freedom. George W Bush, the then President of the US had declared a “War on Terror,” as reported by the New York Times on September 20, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the operation was clearly evident, with the Taliban being driven out of power by the Christmas of 2001. The United Nations Security Council later formed the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF) with the aim of providing multidimensional training to Afghan Security forces, which would rebuild the social and political institutions which had been demolished by the Taliban regime. These institutions also included the establishment of the Afghan Transitional Administration with Hamid Karzai as the President. ISAF spread through four stages all over the Taliban-inflicted ruins of the nation. The Operation Enduring Freedom ended after 13 years in 2014, with Bush’s successor Barack Obama declaring its end with these words of significance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For more than 13 years, ever since nearly 3,000 innocent lives were taken from us on 9/11 our nation has been at war with Afghanistan……our combat mission in Afghanistan is ending, and the longest war in American history is coming to a responsible end.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, he also stressed that in order to preserve the gains made by the US military (as also by the invitation of the Afghan government), a limited military presence would remain in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely stated that negotiations with the Taliban had always been in the pipeline, having been strongly endorsed by the former Afghan president, Hamid Karzai (2004-2014), but American efforts had never been either eager or decisive in the matter. Karzai, on returning from a foreign trip, had offered peace negotiations in 2007, but the Taliban insurgents citing the proliferation of foreign troops had squarely rejected the offer. The precondition that there be a withdrawal of 50,000 NATO troops and US military couldn’t be fulfilled. Karzai had offered to allocate government posts to the Taliban with Hekmatyar even being allowed to contest elections in 2009, but to no avail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2009 Afghan Presidential elections had been widely contested on the issue of whether the war should come to an end or not. In one of his Presidential campaigns, Karzai offered “Loya Jirga” (a traditional Afghan Pashtun ceremony organised for choosing a new head of state). However, the elections, which were widely blood-splattered with the death of 59 Americans, resulted in the increase of the presence of American troops in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2010 marked a significant turn of events, with Karzai stating that “the peace process will be with the Talibans and other militants who are not part of the Al Qaeda or other terrorist networks or ideologically against us.” The then US Secretary of State Hillary Clinton supported the contention. The second-in-command of the Taliban, Abdul Ghani Baradar favoured talks with both the US and the Afghan government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change of political strategy of the US government took place in 2010, with the Taliban Quetta Shura (Taliban Leadership Commanders) leaving Pakistan and being escorted to Kabul by NATO aircraft for discussions, according to Reuters, only to be revealed that one of the leaders Akhtar Mansour was an imposter disguised as senior Taliban commander. A round of talks stood cancelled in 2012 and another stood cancelled in 2013 as a direct consequence of a dispute between the Taliban and Karzai, where the latter felt that the former were portraying themselves as a “government in exile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 2018 marked an abrupt increase in violence, with Ashraf Ghani, the Afghan President offering the Taliban a full recognition as a legal political party and a release of Taliban political prisoners. The Los Angeles Times referred to this as “the most significant peace overture.” Surprisingly, in July 2018, American officials had reportedly met a few members of the Taliban at their political office in Qatar. Zalmay Khalilzad joined the US State Department as Trump’s Special Advisor on Afghanistan, with the sole aim of initiating an intra-Afghan peace process. Fuelling diplomatic speculation, Russia successfully held talks with the Taliban and officials of the Afghanistan High Peace Council. After the February 2019 talks, Khalilzad reported “this round of talk was more productive than they have ever been in the past.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 12, 2019, the US and the Taliban completed the 8th round of negotiations, and US media had been abuzz with the news that the US had been close to reaching a peace deal with Afghanistan which would include the withdrawal of 5,000 troops from Afghanistan. The ‘agreement-in-principle’ was awaiting final approval by the President, which it fortunately or unfortunately did not get. Its cancellation, however, prompted the Talibans to remark that the “doors were open” for further discussions with Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conjectures are afloat that a peace agreement with the Talibans could result in their rise to power, replicating the defeat of the US-backed South Vietnamese government after the 1973 Paris peace accords. US Defence Secretary Mark Esper had visited Afghanistan in late October 2019. He stated that the US could reduce its force in Afghanistan to 8,600 without damaging its counter-terrorism capabilities. On a world diplomacy stage, war with Afghanistan is largely recognised as an unwinnable war. For a concrete conclusion of the war, it is imperative that the US gets rid of its mirage of a perfect deal and allure foŕ hard power. Otherwise, like the North Korean nuclear standoff, there seems no end in sight. Every month this stalemate claims thousands of Afghan lives and almost $4 billion from the US government.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Memoirs of an Ex-Muslim: Lies, Propaganda and Truth</title><link href="/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Memoirs of an Ex-Muslim: Lies, Propaganda and Truth" /><published>2019-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is an opinion piece submitted by a contributor who wishes to remain anonymous.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time in Iran as a Muslim now seems like the distant past. The beautiful and almost transcendent experience of being a Muslim comes with its costs. But what are these costs, some people ask? Is it not true that having a religious foundation helps society and isn’t Islam the religion of peace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the answers to those questions are all ‘yes’ if you are a typical person living in Iran. However, let’s not forget that belief - or even fanatical conviction - is not the same as truth. At the time, I was only 16 and was certainly influenced by the constant Islamic propaganda that pervaded every aspect of the Iranian society. I now ask myself whether it was even possible not to believe in the Islamic doctrines at the time since everything ranging from music to media and books were heavily shaped by Islamic beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our epistemology was based on supposedly revealed scriptures and doctrines. In schools, for instance, the humanities were taught from a purely Islamic perspective, as though these were objective facts alongside science. Any criticism of these would be like saying that atoms do not exist. I am not exaggerating. It is extremely important for non-Iranians to understand how much of an independent thinker one must be in order to go against Islamic doctrines in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did I leave Islam? Well, after my migration to the UK in 2014, the Islamic propaganda was no longer present in my life. There was this sense of mental liberation that had begun to manifest itself. Despite this, the toxicity and the virus-like the behavior of Islamic ideas made it such that it took me two years to abandon all of my faith in Islam. So for those of you who are reading this, the first step is to understand your religion from within. In my case, I started educating myself about the &lt;em&gt;Hadith&lt;/em&gt; and the history of Islam and the more I investigated, the more disillusioned I became with the faith. It was as though I was walking in a dark tunnel, and soon enough I realised that my expectation of the existing light at the end of the tunnel was illusory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a 16 year old Iranian studying these texts and the history of Islam, I soon became aware that it was not that difficult to lose faith in Islam. Why was it so easy? It would not have been easy in Iran but here in the UK I had access to a vast number of resources and was being exposed to various points of view. In Iran, all I was taught was that the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; was a text filled with amazing scientific truths as well as accurate historical facts. Conversely, it was only in the UK that for the first time I had heard criticism against Muhammad’s character. Surely he was the perfect human being, right? Well, with some study, I realised that that was not the case at all. In fact, all I found was that in the Islamic sources themselves such as in Bukhari and other Hadiths, Muhammad was not only a prophet without any prophecy, but that his actions and beliefs utterly and precisely mirrors that of those in the so-called Islamic State of Iraq and Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, the clue is in the name ‘The Islamic State’ and I am not naïve enough to think that a name could on its own make this proposition true. But, when one looks at the history of Islam and learns about Muhammad who had, on many occasions, committed acts of genocide, pedophilia and had engaged in the institution of sex slavery, one need not go any further. Are those accusations accurate? It depends on what sources you think are credible and statistically speaking, the &lt;em&gt;Hadiths&lt;/em&gt; especially by Bukhari  are believed by Muslims to provide the life of Prophet Muhammad with a fair amount of accuracy. And, for those who do not subscribe to the credibility of these texts, there is an even more challenging problem; which is that, they do not have any credible source of even making the proposition that Muhammad existed as a person in history. So either, Muhammad was a morally repugnant human being or he never existed, and even if he did, there is not enough historical evidence to render that belief plausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something even more embarrassing is that Muhammad is actually rarely mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt;, which is, also a book filled with commands for sex slavery and genocide; in addition to that, the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; clearly places women on a far lower pedestal than men. All these are not mere assertions. Those who study these texts are well aware of the existence of these commands and events but they try to contextualise them and give reasons for why they happened. Here, I think I am completely justified to compare this to someone who justifies the crimes committed by Hitler by giving reasons as to why they happened, in order to provide a moral account for the actions committed by him. There is no excuse for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the most reprehensible of all crimes against humanity: to justify the evils of the past and to not recognise them. For if we don’t recognise them, we are doomed to repeat them. The fact that Muhammad (PeACE Be UPoN hIM) married a six year old should not be something up for contextualisation or debate. The fact that Muhammad took sex slaves should not be a matter for contextualisation or debate. Some actions are just so intrinsically wrong that no reasoning could render them moral&lt;/em&gt;. Similarly, there is absolutely no situation under which Muhammad was justified to take sex slaves (&lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; 33:50, &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; 4:24). Let’s look at the latter example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;And all married women (are forbidden unto you) save those (captives) whom your right hands possess.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we see that slaves regardless of their marital status are basically the property of those who capture them, as Nadia Murad was. In essence, the deity of the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; clearly permits rape for war slaves. This is what I mean when I say that there are actions which are never justified. And hopefully, now you see why I lost my faith so rapidly after reading these texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really hope that Muslims start to read and educate themselves with their own sources, for if not, history is bound to repeat itself as it is repeating itself now and no one is paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anon.anon</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The following is an opinion piece submitted by a contributor who wishes to remain anonymous.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Here’s to Feeling Good All The Time!</title><link href="/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Here’s to Feeling Good All The Time!" /><published>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time">&lt;p&gt;If you were to walk through my door today, I’d only welcome you with a question: Are you happy? I’m no Dr. Phil, it’s not so much as to check on your well-being (well, not completely), it is mostly to comprehend how happiness became the most important thing ever. Personally, I’ve come to a conclusion. Happiness is overrated and way too popular. Happiness is that jock in high school that everybody crushes on, but no one knows how to talk to. I can put a million researches here explaining how it all works: the biology, physiology, and all of the rest. But, why are we so attracted to the concept? What is this constant desire to be happy? And, pressure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several aspects of our lives revolve around trying to be happy, wanting to be happy. God! take a shot every time you read happy. Or maybe do that every time you see a sunny post on Instagram giving you lessons on how to be more joyous. Believe you me, you’re about to be very intoxicated. We’re now living in a world where even several social media platforms have changed their algorithm so as to promote a more positive content. We’ve all, in a way, turned into Sisyphus, continuously pushing for joy and happiness, but in return only to find it rolling back on nearing the top. This push seems like it’s going to last us a lifetime, and the irony is not lost on any of us. Out of all the ‘feels’ one could feel- why stick to one and work for it so hard that we forget to feel the rest of the lot?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever heard of ‘struggle porn’? It has been trending in the business world for a long time- it alludes to how romanticised entrepreneurs make struggle out to be. Well, I think, what we have in our hands is- ‘happiness porn’. I’m not here to tell you that feeling good is bad—friend, feeling good is always great, but by putting this impractical expectation on oneself we are actually hurting our manifesting powers more than we are helping them. This constant need to feel a certain way restricts our way to ascertain what we’re feeling all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re almost, in most ways, taught to judge our feelings as wrong. There are negative feelings and positive ones, but right or wrong? I don’t think so. It’s like being in a battle with yourself, which is causing resistance, which is really the only obstacle that stands between you and the realisation of your feelings. Therefore, feeling bad is not the problem, feeling bad about feeling bad definitely is. Quite an inception. One distinction I have to make is that the opposite of happiness is not sadness, it couldn’t be. Its apathy. It is the opposite of every feeling- not feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feeling good is good, this is a belief that is so intuitive to be almost axiomatic, and there is now substantial data to support it. Yet, most of us do know that perpetual joy is not a practical goal. Recent research is actually starting to suggest that it may actually be a harmful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Galen_Bodenhausen&quot;&gt;Bodenhausen&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/scientific-contributions/79839499_Geoffrey_P_Kramer&quot;&gt; Kramer&lt;/a&gt; (pretty credible names, wouldn’t you say?) stated that “happiness is a kind of a safety signal, indicating that there is no current need for problem solving…..Unhappy people will think more deeply about their social environment (in an effort to solve their problems), whereas happy people can contentedly coast on cruise control, not bothering to think very deeply about surrounding events unless they impinge directly on their well-being”—basically suggesting you’re better off solving things when you’re not obliterated with absolute joy. Serious focus may not be pleasant, but it may be the optimal mood for certain tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that might be troubling? People who are in a good mood are more likely to jump to conclusions about others and less likely to consciously correct any stereotypical notions they harbour. There you go people, want to be in 2020 still harbouring stereotypes? In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/222401249_On_being_happy_and_gullible_Mood_effects_on_skepticism_and_the_detection_of_deception&quot;&gt;2008 study&lt;/a&gt;, nearly 120 students were induced to feel amused, neutral, or sad (by watching a comedy video, a nature documentary, or a film clip about cancer). Then, they watched interrogation videos where other students lied or told the truth about stealing a movie ticket (yeah, they were very thorough). It was seen that the negative-mood group was better at detecting deception than the neutral or positive groups, correctly identifying the liars more often. So, you better keep your Kanye West on when trying to check if people are trying to pull one over you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon talking to a friend this morning about this ‘high school jock’, she expressed that feeling sad is when she feels the most creative. Feeling FOMO may actually foster a more proactive approach. What I’m trying to imply is that all of the rest feelings we’re constantly combating? They ain’t so bad! Instead, let’s look into how, when we express high levels of happiness, research suggests, we are &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.obhdp.2016.05.006&quot;&gt;perceived as more naive&lt;/a&gt; and are more likely to be targets of exploitation than when we express moderate happiness. This obviously explains why we wait for people to be in a good mood before we ask them for money, hoping that they won’t be as critical and careful in considering our request. Listen, the evolutionary psychologists have made a living off of telling us just what I’m trying to say- that other, less-blissful feelings serve a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people who have an irrational aversion to being happy, they’re said to suffer from something called ‘cherophobia’, another term could be ‘hedonophobia’, which is defined as the fear of pleasure. This is not what yours truly is drawing upon, not at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember the very, very famous movie (that may be credited for the increased tourism in India) -* Eat, Pray, Love*? There was an entire monologue by Elizabeth, herself- “Happiness is the consequence of personal effort. You fight for it, strive for it, insist upon it, and sometimes even travel around the world looking for it, you have to participate relentlessly in the manifestations of your own blessings. And once you have achieved a state of happiness, you must make a mighty effort to keep swimming upward into that happiness forever, to stay afloat on top of it. If you don’t, you will leak away your innate contentment.” This chips at a person’s ability to ever feel okay about loneliness or personal failure. It reads to you that nothing except complete and absolute happiness is all one warrants. Downright absurd, right? People might set very high standards for their own happiness as a function of this view- they may think they should be happy all the time, or extremely happy, and that can set people up to feel disappointed with themselves, that they fall short- and that could have these self-defeating effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world focuses on happiness and treats unhappiness as an unnecessary or useless feeling. In a 2017 article titled, “The Secret of Happiness, Feeling Good or Feeling Right,” published in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Psychology General&lt;/em&gt;, 2,324 university students in eight countries were studied. The researchers found that people may be happier when they feel the emotions they desire, regardless of whether those desired emotions were pleasant or unpleasant. In other words, feeling our feelings is important, more so than whether they are positive or negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I can use the word happy anymore, especially if you’ve been taking those shots this entire time. All I have to say is that if you were to play &lt;em&gt;Seinfeld&lt;/em&gt;’s S05E04 at 11:46:47, you will hear Kramer say, “here’s to feeling good all the time!” And let’s just remember, that’s not all there is to life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">If you were to walk through my door today, I’d only welcome you with a question: Are you happy? I’m no Dr. Phil, it’s not so much as to check on your well-being (well, not completely), it is mostly to comprehend how happiness became the most important thing ever. Personally, I’ve come to a conclusion. Happiness is overrated and way too popular. Happiness is that jock in high school that everybody crushes on, but no one knows how to talk to. I can put a million researches here explaining how it all works: the biology, physiology, and all of the rest. But, why are we so attracted to the concept? What is this constant desire to be happy? And, pressure!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why PSG Should be Champions League Favourites</title><link href="/Why-PSG-Should-be-Champoins-League-Favourites" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why PSG Should be Champions League Favourites" /><published>2019-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Why-PSG-Should-be-Champoins-League-Favourites</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Why-PSG-Should-be-Champoins-League-Favourites">&lt;p&gt;After a summer that was dominated by transfer rumours focused around wantaway Brazillian star Neymar, it’s been easy to overlook Paris Saint-Germain when it comes to considering Champions League contenders. Coupled with perennial European underachievement since their 2011 Qatar takeover, the Parisians still aren’t seen as a major Champions League contender by many and that won’t change until they advance past the Champions League quarter-finals, but could this be their year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Squad&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst history isn’t on their side, they undoubtedly have one of the very best squads in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve arguably never had an elite goalkeeper since the takeover, with Salvatore Sirigu, Kevin Trapp, Alphonse Areola and 41-year-old Gianluigi Buffon all having stints in goal. Last season Buffon was directly at fault for a goal in their 3-1 knockout round loss to Manchester United and to solve this issue they made the astute acquisition of 3 times Champions League winner Keylor Navas from Real Madrid. Despite riding the bench last season, the Costa Rican has established himself as one of Europe’s elite shot-stoppers over the last 5 seasons and represents a marked improvement from their previous options, and at just 32 years old, should still have a few top seasons left in the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the back, their squad remains largely the same, with the exception of Dani Alves’ departure and the arrival of Abdou Diallo from Borussia Dortmund, but it’s difficult to improve upon the excellent central defensive trio of Marquinhos, Thiago Silva and Presnel Kimpembe. Full-back is arguably the Parisians’ weakest area, although Juan Bernat and Thomas Meunier are both very capable going forward, especially when used as wing-backs alongside a back three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outfield signing, which will likely have the biggest impact on their defensive solidity, is 30-year-old midfielder Idrissa Gana Gueye. The tenacious Senegal international arrived from Everton with little fanfare compared to some of PSG’s previous star signings but could be just as important. Since the decline and subsequent departure of Blaise Matuidi in 2017, PSG have been lacking some athleticism in the middle of the park which Gueye will no doubt provide. He has already hit the ground running with a man-of-the-match performance in a 3-0 win over Real Madrid and he has been joined by another industrious, tough-tackling midfielder in the shape of Ander Herrera. Herrera and Gueye, along with Marco Verratti, are exactly the type of midfielders that top teams need to succeed in Europe; energetic, hardworking and defensively solid. Verratti has become one of Europe’s premier central midfielders over the past half decade and PSG’s success will depend on him remaining disciplined and avoiding a repeat of his costly red card against Real Madrid in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top, PSG’s attacking firepower speaks for itself: Neymar, Kylian Mbappe, Edinson Cavani, Angel Di Maria and Mauro Icardi ensure that PSG will never be lacking in firepower. Nevertheless, it is essential that PSG have a fit and available Neymar for the knockout stages if they want to go all the way. The Brazil star is one of the best players in the world, yet he has only managed to play one Champions League knockout match since arriving in Paris due to injury and is once again sidelined, this time by a hamstring problem, after three serious ankle injuries in the previous 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst PSG have improved their already impressive attacking depth with the signings of Icardi and Pablo Sarabia from Inter and Sevilla respectively, Neymar’s deadly combination of goal-scoring, dribbling and creativity can only be matched by Lionel Messi and he has the ability to completely alter the outcome of a Champions League knockout match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PSG’s attacking depth should allow for a lot of rotation and rest for Neymar in order to keep him fresh. And when the Brazilian superstar lines up alongside Mbappe and Cavani, they create an attacking trio that would fancy their chances against any opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//parissaintgermain-1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:40%&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//parissaintgermain-2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; margin-left:10%; text-align: left; width:40%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newly formed superclubs such as PSG, Roman Abramovich’s Chelsea and Manchester City under the Abu Dhabi United Group have all historically tended to underperform in the Champions League in the first years of their projects, relative to financial investment and expectations. This may be partly attributed to a lack of European pedigree and winning culture, where lots of players and staff involved with the club haven’t experienced much in the way of major continental success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PSG, however, now have a wealth of Champions League experience in their squad with Silva, Marquinhos, Verratti, Cavani, Draxler, Neymar, Di Maria and Navas all having over forty Champions League appearances to their name, with the latter three winning the competition during their spells at Barcelona and Real Madrid respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even at his young age, Kylian Mbappe already has eight Champions League knockout goals and the young World Champion and his teammates should be able to avoid mental issues which have crippled them in the past, most notably in the humiliating 6-1 defeat to Barcelona in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Contenders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Real Madrid’s European domination came to an end last year, there hasn’t been an obvious favourite in a wide-open competition that featured several improbable comebacks last year (including one at PSG’s expense), and it’s looking like a similar story this year. Liverpool are naturally one of the favourites after last season’s triumph and whilst they have an excellent starting XI, injuries to key players could damage their hopes due to a lack of squad depth in certain areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fellow Premier League juggernauts Manchester City may be the favourites this year, but they have failed to get past the quarter-finals in the past three years under Pep Guardiola largely due to poor results in away legs and are also suffering from a lack of depth in defensive positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spanish teams are the most successful of any nation in European cup competitions, and Barcelona, Real Madrid and Atletico Madrid have been 3 of Europe’s top teams this decade, however all 3 have issues which could prevent them from going all the way. After failing to re-sign Neymar, Barcelona’s over-reliance on Lionel Messi will once again be evident this season due to Luis Suarez’s decline and the misuse of Antoine Griezmann, who has often found himself stuck out on the left-wing. Meanwhile Ernesto Valverde is a manager under pressure due to embarrassing collapses in Rome and Liverpool in the last two UCL campaigns as well as an unconvincing start to this season. So, there are understandable doubts about this very talented side’s ability to go all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over in Madrid, Real have gotten off to a shocker in the Champions League, losing to PSG and drawing to Club Brugge with the absence of Cristiano Ronaldo still felt despite Eden Hazard’s arrival. When you look at the likes of Marcelo, Sergio Ramos, Luka Modric, Gareth Bale and Toni Kroos all seemingly in a state of decline and the comprehensive manner in which Ajax ended their 3-season reign as European champions last season, it certainly appears as though this edition of Real Madrid’s team is coming to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Down the road from the Bernabeu, Diego Simeone’s Atletico will always be a well-drilled unit but have struggled for goals so far this season, netting only 10 in 10 league games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the likes of Juventus and Bayern can never be written off. Juventus under Sarri have a well-rounded team but neither them nor Bayern look as strong as they did in previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most prestigious club competition in the world is wide open this year. With a tactically astute manager and top squad featuring some of the best attackers in the world, don’t bet against PSG finally going all the way this year.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">After a summer that was dominated by transfer rumours focused around wantaway Brazillian star Neymar, it’s been easy to overlook Paris Saint-Germain when it comes to considering Champions League contenders. Coupled with perennial European underachievement since their 2011 Qatar takeover, the Parisians still aren’t seen as a major Champions League contender by many and that won’t change until they advance past the Champions League quarter-finals, but could this be their year? Squad Whilst history isn’t on their side, they undoubtedly have one of the very best squads in Europe. They’ve arguably never had an elite goalkeeper since the takeover, with Salvatore Sirigu, Kevin Trapp, Alphonse Areola and 41-year-old Gianluigi Buffon all having stints in goal. Last season Buffon was directly at fault for a goal in their 3-1 knockout round loss to Manchester United and to solve this issue they made the astute acquisition of 3 times Champions League winner Keylor Navas from Real Madrid. Despite riding the bench last season, the Costa Rican has established himself as one of Europe’s elite shot-stoppers over the last 5 seasons and represents a marked improvement from their previous options, and at just 32 years old, should still have a few top seasons left in the tank. At the back, their squad remains largely the same, with the exception of Dani Alves’ departure and the arrival of Abdou Diallo from Borussia Dortmund, but it’s difficult to improve upon the excellent central defensive trio of Marquinhos, Thiago Silva and Presnel Kimpembe. Full-back is arguably the Parisians’ weakest area, although Juan Bernat and Thomas Meunier are both very capable going forward, especially when used as wing-backs alongside a back three. The outfield signing, which will likely have the biggest impact on their defensive solidity, is 30-year-old midfielder Idrissa Gana Gueye. The tenacious Senegal international arrived from Everton with little fanfare compared to some of PSG’s previous star signings but could be just as important. Since the decline and subsequent departure of Blaise Matuidi in 2017, PSG have been lacking some athleticism in the middle of the park which Gueye will no doubt provide. He has already hit the ground running with a man-of-the-match performance in a 3-0 win over Real Madrid and he has been joined by another industrious, tough-tackling midfielder in the shape of Ander Herrera. Herrera and Gueye, along with Marco Verratti, are exactly the type of midfielders that top teams need to succeed in Europe; energetic, hardworking and defensively solid. Verratti has become one of Europe’s premier central midfielders over the past half decade and PSG’s success will depend on him remaining disciplined and avoiding a repeat of his costly red card against Real Madrid in 2018. Up top, PSG’s attacking firepower speaks for itself: Neymar, Kylian Mbappe, Edinson Cavani, Angel Di Maria and Mauro Icardi ensure that PSG will never be lacking in firepower. Nevertheless, it is essential that PSG have a fit and available Neymar for the knockout stages if they want to go all the way. The Brazil star is one of the best players in the world, yet he has only managed to play one Champions League knockout match since arriving in Paris due to injury and is once again sidelined, this time by a hamstring problem, after three serious ankle injuries in the previous 18 months. Whilst PSG have improved their already impressive attacking depth with the signings of Icardi and Pablo Sarabia from Inter and Sevilla respectively, Neymar’s deadly combination of goal-scoring, dribbling and creativity can only be matched by Lionel Messi and he has the ability to completely alter the outcome of a Champions League knockout match. PSG’s attacking depth should allow for a lot of rotation and rest for Neymar in order to keep him fresh. And when the Brazilian superstar lines up alongside Mbappe and Cavani, they create an attacking trio that would fancy their chances against any opposition. &amp;lt; Experience Newly formed superclubs such as PSG, Roman Abramovich’s Chelsea and Manchester City under the Abu Dhabi United Group have all historically tended to underperform in the Champions League in the first years of their projects, relative to financial investment and expectations. This may be partly attributed to a lack of European pedigree and winning culture, where lots of players and staff involved with the club haven’t experienced much in the way of major continental success. PSG, however, now have a wealth of Champions League experience in their squad with Silva, Marquinhos, Verratti, Cavani, Draxler, Neymar, Di Maria and Navas all having over forty Champions League appearances to their name, with the latter three winning the competition during their spells at Barcelona and Real Madrid respectively. Even at his young age, Kylian Mbappe already has eight Champions League knockout goals and the young World Champion and his teammates should be able to avoid mental issues which have crippled them in the past, most notably in the humiliating 6-1 defeat to Barcelona in 2017. The Contenders After Real Madrid’s European domination came to an end last year, there hasn’t been an obvious favourite in a wide-open competition that featured several improbable comebacks last year (including one at PSG’s expense), and it’s looking like a similar story this year. Liverpool are naturally one of the favourites after last season’s triumph and whilst they have an excellent starting XI, injuries to key players could damage their hopes due to a lack of squad depth in certain areas. Fellow Premier League juggernauts Manchester City may be the favourites this year, but they have failed to get past the quarter-finals in the past three years under Pep Guardiola largely due to poor results in away legs and are also suffering from a lack of depth in defensive positions. Spanish teams are the most successful of any nation in European cup competitions, and Barcelona, Real Madrid and Atletico Madrid have been 3 of Europe’s top teams this decade, however all 3 have issues which could prevent them from going all the way. After failing to re-sign Neymar, Barcelona’s over-reliance on Lionel Messi will once again be evident this season due to Luis Suarez’s decline and the misuse of Antoine Griezmann, who has often found himself stuck out on the left-wing. Meanwhile Ernesto Valverde is a manager under pressure due to embarrassing collapses in Rome and Liverpool in the last two UCL campaigns as well as an unconvincing start to this season. So, there are understandable doubts about this very talented side’s ability to go all the way. Over in Madrid, Real have gotten off to a shocker in the Champions League, losing to PSG and drawing to Club Brugge with the absence of Cristiano Ronaldo still felt despite Eden Hazard’s arrival. When you look at the likes of Marcelo, Sergio Ramos, Luka Modric, Gareth Bale and Toni Kroos all seemingly in a state of decline and the comprehensive manner in which Ajax ended their 3-season reign as European champions last season, it certainly appears as though this edition of Real Madrid’s team is coming to an end. Down the road from the Bernabeu, Diego Simeone’s Atletico will always be a well-drilled unit but have struggled for goals so far this season, netting only 10 in 10 league games. Additionally, the likes of Juventus and Bayern can never be written off. Juventus under Sarri have a well-rounded team but neither them nor Bayern look as strong as they did in previous years. The most prestigious club competition in the world is wide open this year. With a tactically astute manager and top squad featuring some of the best attackers in the world, don’t bet against PSG finally going all the way this year.</summary></entry></feed>