<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-01T13:59:53+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Work Hard, Pay Hard</title><link href="/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Work Hard, Pay Hard" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard">&lt;p&gt;On my way to university, I heard two women chatting beside me on the train and I couldn't help but eavesdrop at the horrors exchanged in their dialogue. They were engrossed in discussing or rather denouncing the daughter-in-law of one of their acquaintances for her values and time devoted to her family. From what I heard, they believed that she doesn't contribute much to the household chores as she continues to work after marriage (a heinous crime apparently) and comes home late. One of them said that this is bound to happen when women study too much.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made me spiral into thinking about what most women, both married or unmarried, but mostly married, living with huge families and kids go through. They work from 9-5 or more I assume, complete their chores, handle their kids and still are not compensated enough for the same, be it the remuneration at their jobs in terms of money or the healthcare and safety provisions, and, on top of that, they are conveniently expected to undertake relentless unpaid work at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after all the effort that women put in every sphere of life, they still earn less respect and salary than their male counterparts for the same job, irrespective of their qualification and experience, contingent merely on their gender. &lt;em&gt;Because women are child-bearers and menstruators who expect the bare minimum of maternity and period leaves as an employee. Because women can't lead teams as capably as their male counterparts, since they aren't dominant by birth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led me to realise that the gender-pay-gap is one of the most exploitative and discriminative features of our economic systems staring us in the face. One would expect a better system of rewards based on one’s merit and calibre, but even in the 21st century only six countries in the world, namely, Belgium, Denmark, France, Latvia, Luxembourg and Sweden grant men and women equal legal work rights, which is a concept as old as only a decade, according to a report by &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, bringing about legal changes does not translate into effective actions. In Sweden, women still earn about 5% less than their male counterparts and, globally, women earn 79 cents for every dollar paid to a man - which might not sound like a huge gap in theory but again, this is just a statistic which might not even reflect the actual situation flailing about in our system. It might not even consider the many women who are employed in the informal sectors of developing countries or are labouring away in the agricultural-sector without reaping any significant benefits out of it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wage gap exists for women of all educational backgrounds - from high school graduates to women with advanced degrees. According to a report by the Economic Policy Institute, this gap ranges from three dollars for women having an education level of less than high school to twelve dollars for women with advanced degrees. This is the opposite of what one would expect and a strong argument against how gender-wage-gap stems from the lower education levels of women. The gap only widens as the level of education increases, which is testament to the fact that the more literate and intelligent the woman, the more of a threat she is made out to be.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this bias is not limited to merely the pecuniary aspect of the work culture; it is deeply embedded in how women are treated in offices, always put on a rung lower than men, listened to but never heard or appreciated. From bearing the ‘motherhood penalty’ to being biologically ‘complicated’, women around the world are stifled at every step of their way to success. A recent American study deduced the average by which women’s future wages fall—at 4% per child, and 10% for the highest-earning, most skilled white women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women are considered assets as long as they do not ask for anything that lies outside the zone of anyone's convenience - be it providing maternity leaves or transportation for late work hours. And are also looked at like a nuisance for any lawsuits and uncomfortable conversations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the famous #MeToo movement, many companies and men in position suggested that hiring a woman nowadays can prove to be a risky investment because everything these days leads to lawsuits. Blaming the MeToo movement, many men claim that they are afraid to be alone with women in the workspace or hesitant to be around in their close vicinity - which is a complete rationalisation of the actions that are not okay in any workspace. And these men flagrantly choose to ignore that the issue doesn’t lie in women’s capability to live by the rules created by men but in men’s inability to treat them like human beings with boundaries that are to be respected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zomato, a food-delivery service was one of the first major-league companies in India to grant paid period leaves - an action heavily slated by men. Even so, only bringing a policy in place doesn't seem enough to provoke a change because most women might be hesitant to take those leaves due to the pronounced stigma around menstruation and being considered weak and fragile for going through with it. Menstruation is not given enough medical importance, contingent on how potent its symptoms can be- from nausea and backache to stomach cramps that can invalidate any healthy and strong person. The hope is that with policies like these there is wider acceptance towards the gravity of this issue without it being used as a pretext for inequality or inferiority in the workplace.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though women are more substantially employed now, occupying more positions in the workspace than before especially in developed countries, the proportion of women in managerial and top executive positions still remains abysmally low and according to the Enterprise Survey by the World Bank, only 18% of businesses had a female CEO. On the other hand in legislatures, the proportion of women is approximately 24%. Women, in their entirety, comprise less than one-fourth of the major domains of the working world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is not just gender-based discrimination but also discrimination against occupations that are majorly dominated by women. Professions of nurses, teachers, secretaries, child-care workers are found to be respected less and paid less too. According to a report by &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, Primary teachers in the OECD countries earn 81% of the average for graduate jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue leads to a polarity in the jobs pursued by men and women and thus demotivates and intimidates women to take up jobs in the field of law and litigation, engineering and the police force. It is found that only 3.5% of women are firefighters, which is one of the most heavily male-dominated industries next to male technicians and mechanics who dominate 99.19% of the industry. Even something as universal as religion is dominated by men, according to &lt;em&gt;the Insider&lt;/em&gt;, only 17.6% of the clergy is female. And I am pretty sure this is not pertinent only to America but most of the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, an important solution to gender-wage-gap is the migration of genders from female-dominated sectors to the male-dominated sectors and vice-versa. As important as it is for women to pursue fields that are considered too ambitious for them, it is equally imperative for men to be accepted in industries that are primarily governed by women. It is also important for the parental-care axle to shift from mothers, who drop out of the workforce or shift to less-intensive jobs to take care of their children to fathers, with a higher emphasis on the implementation of paternity leaves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While discussing gender-based discrimination, to not consider the prejudice faced by trans people and other non-binary genders in the workplace would be unjust to the cause of equal wages for all. Trans people have even lesser representation and provisions to fall back on than women in the workplace and face persistent abuse and hiring-discrimination throughout the world, but more so in third-world and developing countries. Let alone provisions in the workplace, third-world countries like Kenya, Uganda, Senegal and Haiti do not even have basic anti-discriminatory laws for trans people. The transgender social acceptance rate, according to a report by Kimberly Tower is -2 whereas, in countries like India, Nepal and Argentina, it is positive yet wretchedly low, that is, 3, 2 and 1.5 respectively. Thus, there is still a long way to go for other genders to have equal remuneration and dignity as our &lt;em&gt;patriarchal lords&lt;/em&gt; in the workplace.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These statistics and facts only substantiate the actuality of domination of men in most sectors of the world, which leads to the gender-wage-gap. This majority that men enjoy in legislation, business or the sciences, is what propagates ideas, policies and products fabricated by men, which more often than not are not gender-friendly. Representation is salient as it leads to better targeted economic and social policies which will help bridge this widening gap and actualise acceptance - thus ameliorating the social and economic status of minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">On my way to university, I heard two women chatting beside me on the train and I couldn't help but eavesdrop at the horrors exchanged in their dialogue. They were engrossed in discussing or rather denouncing the daughter-in-law of one of their acquaintances for her values and time devoted to her family. From what I heard, they believed that she doesn't contribute much to the household chores as she continues to work after marriage (a heinous crime apparently) and comes home late. One of them said that this is bound to happen when women study too much.&amp;nbsp; This made me spiral into thinking about what most women, both married or unmarried, but mostly married, living with huge families and kids go through. They work from 9-5 or more I assume, complete their chores, handle their kids and still are not compensated enough for the same, be it the remuneration at their jobs in terms of money or the healthcare and safety provisions, and, on top of that, they are conveniently expected to undertake relentless unpaid work at home.&amp;nbsp; Even after all the effort that women put in every sphere of life, they still earn less respect and salary than their male counterparts for the same job, irrespective of their qualification and experience, contingent merely on their gender. Because women are child-bearers and menstruators who expect the bare minimum of maternity and period leaves as an employee. Because women can't lead teams as capably as their male counterparts, since they aren't dominant by birth.&amp;nbsp; This led me to realise that the gender-pay-gap is one of the most exploitative and discriminative features of our economic systems staring us in the face. One would expect a better system of rewards based on one’s merit and calibre, but even in the 21st century only six countries in the world, namely, Belgium, Denmark, France, Latvia, Luxembourg and Sweden grant men and women equal legal work rights, which is a concept as old as only a decade, according to a report by The Guardian.&amp;nbsp; Even so, bringing about legal changes does not translate into effective actions. In Sweden, women still earn about 5% less than their male counterparts and, globally, women earn 79 cents for every dollar paid to a man - which might not sound like a huge gap in theory but again, this is just a statistic which might not even reflect the actual situation flailing about in our system. It might not even consider the many women who are employed in the informal sectors of developing countries or are labouring away in the agricultural-sector without reaping any significant benefits out of it.&amp;nbsp; The wage gap exists for women of all educational backgrounds - from high school graduates to women with advanced degrees. According to a report by the Economic Policy Institute, this gap ranges from three dollars for women having an education level of less than high school to twelve dollars for women with advanced degrees. This is the opposite of what one would expect and a strong argument against how gender-wage-gap stems from the lower education levels of women. The gap only widens as the level of education increases, which is testament to the fact that the more literate and intelligent the woman, the more of a threat she is made out to be.&amp;nbsp; However, this bias is not limited to merely the pecuniary aspect of the work culture; it is deeply embedded in how women are treated in offices, always put on a rung lower than men, listened to but never heard or appreciated. From bearing the ‘motherhood penalty’ to being biologically ‘complicated’, women around the world are stifled at every step of their way to success. A recent American study deduced the average by which women’s future wages fall—at 4% per child, and 10% for the highest-earning, most skilled white women.&amp;nbsp; Women are considered assets as long as they do not ask for anything that lies outside the zone of anyone's convenience - be it providing maternity leaves or transportation for late work hours. And are also looked at like a nuisance for any lawsuits and uncomfortable conversations.&amp;nbsp; After the famous #MeToo movement, many companies and men in position suggested that hiring a woman nowadays can prove to be a risky investment because everything these days leads to lawsuits. Blaming the MeToo movement, many men claim that they are afraid to be alone with women in the workspace or hesitant to be around in their close vicinity - which is a complete rationalisation of the actions that are not okay in any workspace. And these men flagrantly choose to ignore that the issue doesn’t lie in women’s capability to live by the rules created by men but in men’s inability to treat them like human beings with boundaries that are to be respected.&amp;nbsp; Zomato, a food-delivery service was one of the first major-league companies in India to grant paid period leaves - an action heavily slated by men. Even so, only bringing a policy in place doesn't seem enough to provoke a change because most women might be hesitant to take those leaves due to the pronounced stigma around menstruation and being considered weak and fragile for going through with it. Menstruation is not given enough medical importance, contingent on how potent its symptoms can be- from nausea and backache to stomach cramps that can invalidate any healthy and strong person. The hope is that with policies like these there is wider acceptance towards the gravity of this issue without it being used as a pretext for inequality or inferiority in the workplace.&amp;nbsp; Even though women are more substantially employed now, occupying more positions in the workspace than before especially in developed countries, the proportion of women in managerial and top executive positions still remains abysmally low and according to the Enterprise Survey by the World Bank, only 18% of businesses had a female CEO. On the other hand in legislatures, the proportion of women is approximately 24%. Women, in their entirety, comprise less than one-fourth of the major domains of the working world.&amp;nbsp; The issue is not just gender-based discrimination but also discrimination against occupations that are majorly dominated by women. Professions of nurses, teachers, secretaries, child-care workers are found to be respected less and paid less too. According to a report by The Economist, Primary teachers in the OECD countries earn 81% of the average for graduate jobs. This issue leads to a polarity in the jobs pursued by men and women and thus demotivates and intimidates women to take up jobs in the field of law and litigation, engineering and the police force. It is found that only 3.5% of women are firefighters, which is one of the most heavily male-dominated industries next to male technicians and mechanics who dominate 99.19% of the industry. Even something as universal as religion is dominated by men, according to the Insider, only 17.6% of the clergy is female. And I am pretty sure this is not pertinent only to America but most of the world.&amp;nbsp; Thus, an important solution to gender-wage-gap is the migration of genders from female-dominated sectors to the male-dominated sectors and vice-versa. As important as it is for women to pursue fields that are considered too ambitious for them, it is equally imperative for men to be accepted in industries that are primarily governed by women. It is also important for the parental-care axle to shift from mothers, who drop out of the workforce or shift to less-intensive jobs to take care of their children to fathers, with a higher emphasis on the implementation of paternity leaves.&amp;nbsp; While discussing gender-based discrimination, to not consider the prejudice faced by trans people and other non-binary genders in the workplace would be unjust to the cause of equal wages for all. Trans people have even lesser representation and provisions to fall back on than women in the workplace and face persistent abuse and hiring-discrimination throughout the world, but more so in third-world and developing countries. Let alone provisions in the workplace, third-world countries like Kenya, Uganda, Senegal and Haiti do not even have basic anti-discriminatory laws for trans people. The transgender social acceptance rate, according to a report by Kimberly Tower is -2 whereas, in countries like India, Nepal and Argentina, it is positive yet wretchedly low, that is, 3, 2 and 1.5 respectively. Thus, there is still a long way to go for other genders to have equal remuneration and dignity as our patriarchal lords in the workplace.&amp;nbsp; These statistics and facts only substantiate the actuality of domination of men in most sectors of the world, which leads to the gender-wage-gap. This majority that men enjoy in legislation, business or the sciences, is what propagates ideas, policies and products fabricated by men, which more often than not are not gender-friendly. Representation is salient as it leads to better targeted economic and social policies which will help bridge this widening gap and actualise acceptance - thus ameliorating the social and economic status of minority genders.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?</title><link href="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, &lt;em&gt;during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with &lt;em&gt;rocks, &lt;/em&gt;we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: &lt;em&gt;“The world is watching, but will it do anything?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer. The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows. The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp; When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with rocks, we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp; The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp; Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: “The world is watching, but will it do anything?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Makeup Conundrum</title><link href="/The-Makeup-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Makeup Conundrum" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Makeup-Conundrum</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Makeup-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;Makeup is a very fascinating mode of self-expression. It is also a central part of many cultures across the globe. It is beautiful and is respected, but only within certain unspoken limits that are decided by the society in question.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often judge one’s personality by the amount and kind of makeup they are wearing. It can be either 'feminine’ and beautiful or unprofessional and frivolous. Not to mention, this is applicable only to one gender and everyone else is expected to not understand anything about it. In fact, they are expected to stay away from makeup, and when they do not follow this rule, they are seen as “unnatural”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Indians, like many other cultures, makeup is auspicious. A specific kind of makeup is reserved for each occasion or milestone in one’s life like engagement or wedding and of course, this varies from culture to culture. If you have, by any chance, come across an Indian TV serial or movie, you will know that more often than not, makeup is used to express certain character traits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, the female protagonist, who is shown to be a rather innocent and naive person, characteristics that we see being appreciated in female characters almost globally, has natural makeup on. On the other hand, the female antagonist tends to have very heavy makeup on, often playing with darker shades of red and black. This results in and is born out of an unconscious association of heavy or dark makeup with being promiscuous or a bad person.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moral policing in schools, especially in India, where I am from, is not rare. The administration and teachers often question the character of female students who choose to express themselves through different hairstyles or even just a simple eyeliner. It has been so ingrained in our psyche that most of us never even questioned it and in fact, were, to a large extent, in agreement with the policing. Makeup is simply a form of expression and associating it with not being serious about education is simply baseless and a way to control women. If a simple eyeliner is 'disruptive', we are definitely going wrong somewhere in our education system.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extension of this is the idea that women wear makeup solely to attract men. In fact, this is often used to shame girls in schools (at least, in India) who are found wearing anything that can be remotely associated with makeup. Honestly, if a little makeup distracts boys and men, they need to be taught to not sexualise anything and everything that is considered 'feminine' by society. Instead, school girls face punishment, sometimes to the extent of getting suspended.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When someone with authority suspends someone over wearing makeup, with the reason that it deviates attention from what is the main purpose of school, that is education, and more importantly, that it distracts the 'boys', it is a clear proclamation that they are unwilling to put an effort to teach boys to be respectful and are more satisfied with sending the person wearing makeup home, because their education is simply not as important as that of the boys.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of the matter is that makeup is simply a form of art. Neither should it be gendered nor should it be associated with a certain intention or personality trait. Some people wear makeup because of insecurities, some wear it because they enjoy it, some do it as a form of art and expression, some do it because it makes them feel confident - there is a myriad of reasons for wearing makeup.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This association of makeup with being frivolous or in other words, 'girly', a trait usually seen as negative and associated with not being serious, hardworking or trustworthy, has been around for a while now. In fact, many women who are victims of internalised misogyny fail to notice the problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, a young graphic designer, Katherine Young re-created the cover of &lt;em&gt;Girls’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum - articles on fashion and makeup, as well as other career choices?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and a fashion-forward outfit as less accomplished or not symbolic of an empowered woman, than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cultures, women are expected to wear heavy makeup to conform to a very restrictive standard of beauty. This is, more often than not, influenced by Western ideals: sharp nose, fair skin, straight hair, oval face, etc. Women face societal pressure to use makeup to live up to these standards, lest they be misunderstood as not being serious or worth listening to or, worst of all, ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cultures, women’s worth is defined by how easy it is to “marry her off” and being conventionally pretty helps the process. Yet, when they post their own pictures on social media looking absolutely gorgeous with makeup on, they are swarmed with messages about how she would look prettier without makeup or how a certain person prefers women who don't wear makeup. In male-dominated office spaces, women who dress up or wear makeup often find it difficult to be taken seriously and are repeatedly sexualised - makeup is seen as unprofessional. Yet, when they don’t, they are not seen as well put together or are questioned if they are sick. The double standards are quite frankly, astonishing and hilarious.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of Hollywood’s beloved movies with 'ugly duckling transformation' sequences continue to propagate the idea that someone who isn't wearing makeup, is not really taking care of themselves and so, is not taken seriously. Until of course, the transformation sequence takes place and suddenly, everything she says makes sense and is worth listening to. Yet, the same movie has a jealous female character, portrayed as someone who understands only clothes and makeup, hell-bent upon making the protagonist’s life miserable for no apparent reason. The amount of knowledge concerning makeup makes all the difference in the personalities in these movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In South Korea, beauty standards are very strict and this often pushes youngsters to opt for plastic surgery simply to make their lives easier by being able to conform to the unrealistic Korean beauty standards. Over the last couple of years, K-beauty has made a mark on the Western world. However, it is now facing backlash from within Korea’s borders. Influencers and commoners alike want to see a shift in the standards that pressurise women to go to extreme lengths to attain an unrealistic youthful look appreciated by society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Escape the Corset, #metoo and other similar feminist movements have seen Korean women openly expressing their dissatisfaction with the highly unequal and unfair societal norms through demonstrations like cutting their hair short and destroying makeup, among others. In June of 2018, Lina Bae, a former beauty Youtuber, posted a video titled 'I am not pretty'. The video concludes with her asking her audience to not compare themselves to what the media portrays as beautiful because they are special just the way they are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This message was appreciated by a large audience and the video went viral and was watched several million times. However, Korean media continues to worship a very specific look, a look that Korean idols continue to feel pressured to starve themselves and go under the knife to achieve. There are very few popular exceptions like Hwasa and Jessi, and they are treated as just that, exceptions in their place because idols are meant to be thin, tall and fair.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is more interesting is that society sometimes tends to have different expectations, in terms of beauty, from people of different races or ethnic backgrounds. For example, big lips and dark skin is not appreciated on black girls and yet, that seems to be the most appreciated 'look' on white women. Kim Kardashian and Kylie Jenner are frequently called out for their choices that are best described as blackfishing or black faces. However, the impact is short lived and the same mistakes are made over and over again. Blackface was a popular form of makeup used by white actors to portray a caricature of a black person for a long time. The portrayals were nowhere near accurate and were primarily meant to dehumanise and make fun of black people. So, you can see why people are not fond of such trends and rightfully so.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox eyes are all the rage right now, with Bella Hadid making several magazine covers and fashion shows with the look, while East Asians, with monolids and natural fox eyes are frequently attacked and criticised for their looks. The 'migraine pose' that these models often use to pull the eyes up to give a fox eye effect is identical to the racially charged gesture made to make fun of East Asians. It is important to remember that this is not a recent issue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1930's, Cecil Holland, a Hollywood makeup artist used various techniques to simulate East Asian fox eyes on white actors to portray Asian characters, often villains. This was practised for a very long time and gave us characters like Fu Manchu and I Y Yunioshi (&lt;em&gt;Breakfast at Tiffany’s&lt;/em&gt;), both played by white actors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to genders other than cis-females, makeup is treated very differently. It's very clear from Candance Owen’s remarks on Harry Styles’ &lt;em&gt;Vogue&lt;/em&gt; cover wearing traditionally feminine garments: “Bring back manly men”, that the conservative world is not very appreciative of makeup on men. They are often victims of homophobic slurs, when love for creative expression through makeup has absolutely nothing to do with one’s sexuality. Drag makeup is often criticised too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disagreement often comes in the form of a claim that makeup was meant to be feminine and thus, should be reserved for women. This is actually objectively false, because it was only in the mid-1800's when makeup started to be associated with a particular gender. Queen Victoria I of Britain and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination” resulting in a widespread and long-standing association of it with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”. These ideas were exported with imperialism and colonialism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, prior to that, men were often seen dawning makeup. In ancient Egypt, makeup was an integral part of the culture and had various religious connotations and so, makeup was worn, irrespective of gender. In ancient Rome, men often used makeup to cover up bald spots, lightened their skin using white powder, applied red pigment on their cheeks and so on and so forth. Even in Elizabethan England, makeup was popular among men. The influence of the Victorian age would start dying out only when Hollywood started using makeup on actors. However, they were still not mainstream. In the late 20th century, rock and roll artists started expressing themselves through makeup. Even today, as multiple male makeup gurus dominate the internet, many are wary of men wearing makeup in everyday life. However, this gendered aspect of makeup is clearly very new and for thousands of years, starting around 4000 BC to the mid-1800's, makeup was very common among men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, a lot of associations, often negative, made with makeup are baseless and are only an attempt to control women and demean those who do not agree with the modern societal interpretations of 'femininity' and 'masculinity'. Most of these are a result of internalised misogyny and perception of anything “girly” as frivolous and not serious. These have long-standing consequences in terms of forcing women to opt for extreme measures to adhere to beauty standards and to escape the constant scrutiny based on their looks, and alternatively, toning it down to be taken seriously in certain male-dominated spaces. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Makeup is a very fascinating mode of self-expression. It is also a central part of many cultures across the globe. It is beautiful and is respected, but only within certain unspoken limits that are decided by the society in question.&amp;nbsp; People often judge one’s personality by the amount and kind of makeup they are wearing. It can be either 'feminine’ and beautiful or unprofessional and frivolous. Not to mention, this is applicable only to one gender and everyone else is expected to not understand anything about it. In fact, they are expected to stay away from makeup, and when they do not follow this rule, they are seen as “unnatural”.&amp;nbsp; For Indians, like many other cultures, makeup is auspicious. A specific kind of makeup is reserved for each occasion or milestone in one’s life like engagement or wedding and of course, this varies from culture to culture. If you have, by any chance, come across an Indian TV serial or movie, you will know that more often than not, makeup is used to express certain character traits.&amp;nbsp; Generally, the female protagonist, who is shown to be a rather innocent and naive person, characteristics that we see being appreciated in female characters almost globally, has natural makeup on. On the other hand, the female antagonist tends to have very heavy makeup on, often playing with darker shades of red and black. This results in and is born out of an unconscious association of heavy or dark makeup with being promiscuous or a bad person.&amp;nbsp; Moral policing in schools, especially in India, where I am from, is not rare. The administration and teachers often question the character of female students who choose to express themselves through different hairstyles or even just a simple eyeliner. It has been so ingrained in our psyche that most of us never even questioned it and in fact, were, to a large extent, in agreement with the policing. Makeup is simply a form of expression and associating it with not being serious about education is simply baseless and a way to control women. If a simple eyeliner is 'disruptive', we are definitely going wrong somewhere in our education system.&amp;nbsp; An extension of this is the idea that women wear makeup solely to attract men. In fact, this is often used to shame girls in schools (at least, in India) who are found wearing anything that can be remotely associated with makeup. Honestly, if a little makeup distracts boys and men, they need to be taught to not sexualise anything and everything that is considered 'feminine' by society. Instead, school girls face punishment, sometimes to the extent of getting suspended.&amp;nbsp; When someone with authority suspends someone over wearing makeup, with the reason that it deviates attention from what is the main purpose of school, that is education, and more importantly, that it distracts the 'boys', it is a clear proclamation that they are unwilling to put an effort to teach boys to be respectful and are more satisfied with sending the person wearing makeup home, because their education is simply not as important as that of the boys.&amp;nbsp; The point of the matter is that makeup is simply a form of art. Neither should it be gendered nor should it be associated with a certain intention or personality trait. Some people wear makeup because of insecurities, some wear it because they enjoy it, some do it as a form of art and expression, some do it because it makes them feel confident - there is a myriad of reasons for wearing makeup.&amp;nbsp; This association of makeup with being frivolous or in other words, 'girly', a trait usually seen as negative and associated with not being serious, hardworking or trustworthy, has been around for a while now. In fact, many women who are victims of internalised misogyny fail to notice the problem.&amp;nbsp; In 2016, a young graphic designer, Katherine Young re-created the cover of Girls’ Life magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum - articles on fashion and makeup, as well as other career choices?&amp;nbsp; Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and a fashion-forward outfit as less accomplished or not symbolic of an empowered woman, than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated.&amp;nbsp; In some cultures, women are expected to wear heavy makeup to conform to a very restrictive standard of beauty. This is, more often than not, influenced by Western ideals: sharp nose, fair skin, straight hair, oval face, etc. Women face societal pressure to use makeup to live up to these standards, lest they be misunderstood as not being serious or worth listening to or, worst of all, ugly. In many cultures, women’s worth is defined by how easy it is to “marry her off” and being conventionally pretty helps the process. Yet, when they post their own pictures on social media looking absolutely gorgeous with makeup on, they are swarmed with messages about how she would look prettier without makeup or how a certain person prefers women who don't wear makeup. In male-dominated office spaces, women who dress up or wear makeup often find it difficult to be taken seriously and are repeatedly sexualised - makeup is seen as unprofessional. Yet, when they don’t, they are not seen as well put together or are questioned if they are sick. The double standards are quite frankly, astonishing and hilarious.&amp;nbsp; Many of Hollywood’s beloved movies with 'ugly duckling transformation' sequences continue to propagate the idea that someone who isn't wearing makeup, is not really taking care of themselves and so, is not taken seriously. Until of course, the transformation sequence takes place and suddenly, everything she says makes sense and is worth listening to. Yet, the same movie has a jealous female character, portrayed as someone who understands only clothes and makeup, hell-bent upon making the protagonist’s life miserable for no apparent reason. The amount of knowledge concerning makeup makes all the difference in the personalities in these movies. In South Korea, beauty standards are very strict and this often pushes youngsters to opt for plastic surgery simply to make their lives easier by being able to conform to the unrealistic Korean beauty standards. Over the last couple of years, K-beauty has made a mark on the Western world. However, it is now facing backlash from within Korea’s borders. Influencers and commoners alike want to see a shift in the standards that pressurise women to go to extreme lengths to attain an unrealistic youthful look appreciated by society.&amp;nbsp; The Escape the Corset, #metoo and other similar feminist movements have seen Korean women openly expressing their dissatisfaction with the highly unequal and unfair societal norms through demonstrations like cutting their hair short and destroying makeup, among others. In June of 2018, Lina Bae, a former beauty Youtuber, posted a video titled 'I am not pretty'. The video concludes with her asking her audience to not compare themselves to what the media portrays as beautiful because they are special just the way they are.&amp;nbsp; This message was appreciated by a large audience and the video went viral and was watched several million times. However, Korean media continues to worship a very specific look, a look that Korean idols continue to feel pressured to starve themselves and go under the knife to achieve. There are very few popular exceptions like Hwasa and Jessi, and they are treated as just that, exceptions in their place because idols are meant to be thin, tall and fair.&amp;nbsp; What is more interesting is that society sometimes tends to have different expectations, in terms of beauty, from people of different races or ethnic backgrounds. For example, big lips and dark skin is not appreciated on black girls and yet, that seems to be the most appreciated 'look' on white women. Kim Kardashian and Kylie Jenner are frequently called out for their choices that are best described as blackfishing or black faces. However, the impact is short lived and the same mistakes are made over and over again. Blackface was a popular form of makeup used by white actors to portray a caricature of a black person for a long time. The portrayals were nowhere near accurate and were primarily meant to dehumanise and make fun of black people. So, you can see why people are not fond of such trends and rightfully so.&amp;nbsp; Fox eyes are all the rage right now, with Bella Hadid making several magazine covers and fashion shows with the look, while East Asians, with monolids and natural fox eyes are frequently attacked and criticised for their looks. The 'migraine pose' that these models often use to pull the eyes up to give a fox eye effect is identical to the racially charged gesture made to make fun of East Asians. It is important to remember that this is not a recent issue.&amp;nbsp; In the 1930's, Cecil Holland, a Hollywood makeup artist used various techniques to simulate East Asian fox eyes on white actors to portray Asian characters, often villains. This was practised for a very long time and gave us characters like Fu Manchu and I Y Yunioshi (Breakfast at Tiffany’s), both played by white actors.&amp;nbsp; When it comes to genders other than cis-females, makeup is treated very differently. It's very clear from Candance Owen’s remarks on Harry Styles’ Vogue cover wearing traditionally feminine garments: “Bring back manly men”, that the conservative world is not very appreciative of makeup on men. They are often victims of homophobic slurs, when love for creative expression through makeup has absolutely nothing to do with one’s sexuality. Drag makeup is often criticised too.&amp;nbsp; The disagreement often comes in the form of a claim that makeup was meant to be feminine and thus, should be reserved for women. This is actually objectively false, because it was only in the mid-1800's when makeup started to be associated with a particular gender. Queen Victoria I of Britain and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination” resulting in a widespread and long-standing association of it with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”. These ideas were exported with imperialism and colonialism.&amp;nbsp; However, prior to that, men were often seen dawning makeup. In ancient Egypt, makeup was an integral part of the culture and had various religious connotations and so, makeup was worn, irrespective of gender. In ancient Rome, men often used makeup to cover up bald spots, lightened their skin using white powder, applied red pigment on their cheeks and so on and so forth. Even in Elizabethan England, makeup was popular among men. The influence of the Victorian age would start dying out only when Hollywood started using makeup on actors. However, they were still not mainstream. In the late 20th century, rock and roll artists started expressing themselves through makeup. Even today, as multiple male makeup gurus dominate the internet, many are wary of men wearing makeup in everyday life. However, this gendered aspect of makeup is clearly very new and for thousands of years, starting around 4000 BC to the mid-1800's, makeup was very common among men.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, a lot of associations, often negative, made with makeup are baseless and are only an attempt to control women and demean those who do not agree with the modern societal interpretations of 'femininity' and 'masculinity'. Most of these are a result of internalised misogyny and perception of anything “girly” as frivolous and not serious. These have long-standing consequences in terms of forcing women to opt for extreme measures to adhere to beauty standards and to escape the constant scrutiny based on their looks, and alternatively, toning it down to be taken seriously in certain male-dominated spaces.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital Yuan: The Start of the End for the US Dollar?</title><link href="/Digital-Yuan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Yuan: The Start of the End for the US Dollar?" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Digital-Yuan</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Digital-Yuan">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Crypto currency mania has gripped the world, as increasing acceptance of blockchain technology by major financial institutions has propelled the likes of Bitcoin into the mainstream. Whether you believe in crypto or not, the emergence of crypto currencies threatens to usurp fiat money. The Chinese government has identified the threat early, and has taken significant steps to ensure they have a meaningful head start on digitising their commercial sector and money supply. China’s long anticipated and recently released digital Yuan threatens to undermine the US dollar’s (USD) supremacy as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;China’s digital Yuan project is the first of its kind for any major global economy. It is a version of normal Chinese currency, deployed on a blockchain; the highly encrypted and secure online ledger technology that underpins digital coins like Bitcoin and Ethereum. The People’s Bank of China (PBOC) has led work on the digital Yuan project, which is classified as a central bank digital currency (CBDC) that aims to replace some of the cash in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;China has been trialling the digital currency since late 2020, and in 11 different regions since April, including in major cities such as Suzhou and Shenzhen, where the digital Yuan has been used for transport, food and retail. The digital Yuan bypasses the need for central banks in transaction processes, eliminating service fees and speeding up transaction times. China has plans for international use of the digital Yuan by 2024 or 2025, and has already established partnerships with the UAE, Hong Kong, and Thailand to promote international use of CBDCs. Given the vast extent of China’s bilateral trade relations globally, and the increasing likelihood of China overtaking the US as the world's largest economy, the internalisation of the digital Yuan is seeming inevitable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decline of the Dollar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The emergence of the digital Yuan coincides with a difficult period for the US dollar. The US dollar has become increasingly fragile of late, perhaps mirroring America’s decline within the international system, with its status as the ultimate reserve currency looking increasingly likely to be challenged in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US dollar has seen a steady fall since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is down about 10-12% relative to America’s major trading partners. Some have even suggested that the dollar will decline in value by 35% by the end of 2021. Ongoing political instability in the US has had a detrimental effect on global trust in the US dollar. The debasing of the US dollar through massive US government debt and central bank stimulus raises the question of the dollar’s long-term viability as the ultimate reserve currency.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To demonstrate this effect, we can look at the declining market of the US-China bilateral trade. The US imports from China dropped by $87.3 billion in 2019 from 2018, and continue to drop annually. The Chinese need for the US dollar is declining. The use of the US dollar in China-Russia transactions has declined from 90% in 2015 to less than 50% in the first quarter of 2020. At a rate of 10% annual decline, it will not be long before the US dollar is no longer used at all in China’s transactions. This vacuum left by the USD will allow for the growth of other currencies such as the digital Yuan. As more countries decide not to use the US dollar, the use of alternative currency reserves will increase. Given China’s extensive trade relations, the digital Yuan is well positioned to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China not Attempting to Replace USD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While it appears that the US dollar and digital Yuan are moving in opposite directions, Chinese officials have claimed that the development of the digital Yuan is not intended to ‘replace the USD’ as the ultimate reserve currency. Deputy governor of the PBOC Li Bo claimed that “efforts to create the digital Yuan are aimed at domestic use,” while Governor of the PBOC, Zhou Xiachuan, echoed that Beijing is not aiming to immediately take on the USD as a currency reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Regardless of China’s intentions for the digital Yuan, the reality is that the growth of the new digital currency will likely further contribute to the weakening and destabilisation of the USD. Much like when China developed paper currency in the 7th century during the Tang dynasty, China is today leading the way in a key transitional phase of the global financial system. The CBDC space certainly has potential to be a key battleground in the larger US-China struggle for global hegemony. Perhaps it is time for the US central bank to explore the implementation of a CBDC project more urgently. Should they fail to do so, there is a pressing possibility for the USD to get left behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-Noam Konyn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Noam Konyn is a graduate of the University of Bristol. He is currently pursuing an MA Government Specialisation in diplomacy and conflict at Interdisciplinary Centre Herzliya, Israel. He has previously worked in Elminda, a brain health medical device company in Tel Aviv, Israel.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guest</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Crypto currency mania has gripped the world, as increasing acceptance of blockchain technology by major financial institutions has propelled the likes of Bitcoin into the mainstream. Whether you believe in crypto or not, the emergence of crypto currencies threatens to usurp fiat money. The Chinese government has identified the threat early, and has taken significant steps to ensure they have a meaningful head start on digitising their commercial sector and money supply. China’s long anticipated and recently released digital Yuan threatens to undermine the US dollar’s (USD) supremacy as we know it. China’s digital Yuan project is the first of its kind for any major global economy. It is a version of normal Chinese currency, deployed on a blockchain; the highly encrypted and secure online ledger technology that underpins digital coins like Bitcoin and Ethereum. The People’s Bank of China (PBOC) has led work on the digital Yuan project, which is classified as a central bank digital currency (CBDC) that aims to replace some of the cash in circulation. China has been trialling the digital currency since late 2020, and in 11 different regions since April, including in major cities such as Suzhou and Shenzhen, where the digital Yuan has been used for transport, food and retail. The digital Yuan bypasses the need for central banks in transaction processes, eliminating service fees and speeding up transaction times. China has plans for international use of the digital Yuan by 2024 or 2025, and has already established partnerships with the UAE, Hong Kong, and Thailand to promote international use of CBDCs. Given the vast extent of China’s bilateral trade relations globally, and the increasing likelihood of China overtaking the US as the world's largest economy, the internalisation of the digital Yuan is seeming inevitable.&amp;nbsp; Decline of the Dollar The emergence of the digital Yuan coincides with a difficult period for the US dollar. The US dollar has become increasingly fragile of late, perhaps mirroring America’s decline within the international system, with its status as the ultimate reserve currency looking increasingly likely to be challenged in the long term. The US dollar has seen a steady fall since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is down about 10-12% relative to America’s major trading partners. Some have even suggested that the dollar will decline in value by 35% by the end of 2021. Ongoing political instability in the US has had a detrimental effect on global trust in the US dollar. The debasing of the US dollar through massive US government debt and central bank stimulus raises the question of the dollar’s long-term viability as the ultimate reserve currency.&amp;nbsp; To demonstrate this effect, we can look at the declining market of the US-China bilateral trade. The US imports from China dropped by $87.3 billion in 2019 from 2018, and continue to drop annually. The Chinese need for the US dollar is declining. The use of the US dollar in China-Russia transactions has declined from 90% in 2015 to less than 50% in the first quarter of 2020. At a rate of 10% annual decline, it will not be long before the US dollar is no longer used at all in China’s transactions. This vacuum left by the USD will allow for the growth of other currencies such as the digital Yuan. As more countries decide not to use the US dollar, the use of alternative currency reserves will increase. Given China’s extensive trade relations, the digital Yuan is well positioned to take over. China not Attempting to Replace USD While it appears that the US dollar and digital Yuan are moving in opposite directions, Chinese officials have claimed that the development of the digital Yuan is not intended to ‘replace the USD’ as the ultimate reserve currency. Deputy governor of the PBOC Li Bo claimed that “efforts to create the digital Yuan are aimed at domestic use,” while Governor of the PBOC, Zhou Xiachuan, echoed that Beijing is not aiming to immediately take on the USD as a currency reserve. Regardless of China’s intentions for the digital Yuan, the reality is that the growth of the new digital currency will likely further contribute to the weakening and destabilisation of the USD. Much like when China developed paper currency in the 7th century during the Tang dynasty, China is today leading the way in a key transitional phase of the global financial system. The CBDC space certainly has potential to be a key battleground in the larger US-China struggle for global hegemony. Perhaps it is time for the US central bank to explore the implementation of a CBDC project more urgently. Should they fail to do so, there is a pressing possibility for the USD to get left behind. -Noam Konyn Noam Konyn is a graduate of the University of Bristol. He is currently pursuing an MA Government Specialisation in diplomacy and conflict at Interdisciplinary Centre Herzliya, Israel. He has previously worked in Elminda, a brain health medical device company in Tel Aviv, Israel.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality</title><link href="/Transgenders-in-Sports" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality" /><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Transgenders-in-Sports</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Transgenders-in-Sports">&lt;p&gt;Throughout the U.S., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators&lt;/a&gt; that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Issue at Hand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's &lt;strong&gt;100 meters&lt;/strong&gt; lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.duke.edu/sports/sex-sport/comparative-athletic-performance/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds&lt;/a&gt;. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6391653/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges&lt;/a&gt; (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.olympic.org/the-ioc&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International Olympic Committee&lt;/a&gt; (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/01/sports/transgender-idaho-ban-sports.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ki.se/new-study-on-changes-in-muscle-mass-and-strength-after-gender-affirming-treatment-may-have-an&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-connecticut-girl-challenges-male-domination-of-female-sports-11562885421#&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year&lt;/a&gt;. Within just three years, girls across the state were &lt;a href=&quot;https://mspolicy.org/an-interview-with-selina-soule-a-brave-young-woman-standing-up-for-womens-sports/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/news/hsph-in-the-news/transgender-youth-at-risk-for-depression-suicide/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/trumps-plan-to-redefine-gender-makes-no-scientific-sense/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the limits of what science can offer&lt;/a&gt;, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions still unsolved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moving on, what about Intersex people?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eeshita Verma</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Throughout the U.S., roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about? Terminology Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand. The Issue at Hand The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’ To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly: Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's 100 meters lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp; Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories. So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp; One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the International Olympic Committee (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year.&amp;nbsp; But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (Source) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women. One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp; Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year. Within just three years, girls across the state were denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions. Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp; The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’ To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete. A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established. However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier. Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity. And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge. These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp; This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender? Possible Solutions One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp; For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against the limits of what science can offer, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp; Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels? Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task. If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions. Questions still unsolved To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders? Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago. Moving on, what about Intersex people? Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex. To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well. Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Indian Pharma Industry: Present and Future</title><link href="/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Pharma Industry: Present and Future" /><published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared the coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 to be a pandemic. More than a year after the outbreak, over three million people have lost their lives with approximately 152 million cases across the globe. The pandemic has managed to cause a complete upheaval in people’s lifestyle along with businesses running losses and workers losing their jobs. Amidst this scenario, it is the pharmaceutical industry that has taken centre stage in the fight against this menace, assisting world governments in fulfilling their population's needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The global pharmaceutical industry in 2019 achieved a market value of approximately $1,217 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 6.7%. This value is expected to decline to $1,209 billion in 2020 owing to the COVID-19 outbreak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pharmaceutical (or pharma) industry can be defined as a “&lt;em&gt;complex system of processes, operations, and organisations involved in the discovery, development, and manufacturing of drugs&lt;/em&gt;”. Firms functioning in the industry are responsible for research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities, development and manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients and manufacturing of drugs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, Germany occupied the top position in the pharma industry with a 14.5% share in the export of drugs and medicines. It was followed by Switzerland and Netherlands with a share of 12.2% and 7.9% respectively. Among other countries, Denmark, Netherlands and Italy are the fastest growing exporters of drugs and medicines since 2015. However, three countries have witnessed a decline in the exported drugs and medicines sales in the last five years. These are, namely, the United Kingdom (26.7%), Ireland (18.9%) and the United States (6.1%).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In recent years, growth patterns in developed economies have observed a flat trend which has induced firms to shift their focus to emerging markets, thus finding new sources of revenue and profitability. The same has been witnessed for the pharmaceutical industry. The pharmaceutical emerging markets, or 'pharmerging' markets hold the potential of an extraordinary growth story.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2016, emerging markets accounted for over 30% of the development in pharma markets. This shift has been attributed to the economic and demographic development in these economies with a rise in health expectancy, access to healthcare services and improved funding for the healthcare sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another major factor is the sharp decline in firms’ revenue as a result of the expiration of patents. This is known as the patent cliff, which is now affecting several branded drugs that have been in the market for years. The shift towards the use of generic drugs worldwide, increasing availability of biosimilar drugs, a significant differential in manufacturing costs and prices, and change in disease patterns in emerging countries are some of the other major reasons for the shift being observed in the pharmaceutical industry. These factors have induced the emerging economies into becoming the key drivers of the global pharmaceutical market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Among the emerging markets, five countries namely China, Brazil, Russia, India and South Africa are the ones in domination with their role becoming increasingly important in the coming decade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pharmaceutical Industry in India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the last fifty years, India’s pharmaceutical industry has grown by leaps and bounds. From having a 5% share of the total medicine consumption in India in 1969, Indian pharma holds an 85% share of the same in 2020. Today, India is not only able to meet its domestic needs but has also established itself as a leader in the global pharma landscape and is known as the ‘pharmacy of the world’. The industry today is recognised for the quality and cost-effectiveness of its products. Widely known as the ‘archetype of affordable healthcare’, the Indian industry has had a significant contribution towards the improvement of public health outcomes, both within India and across the globe.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With a market size of $41 billion in 2018-19 and a market growth rate of 10-12%, the Indian pharma industry exported $16.3 billion worth of bulk drugs, intermediates, drug formulations, herbal products, surgical equipment and other goods in 2019-20. Particularly, the industry contributes more than 20% by volume to the global generics market and 62% of the global demand for vaccines. Fourteenth largest in the world in terms of value and 3rd largest in terms of volume, the industry is expected to grow to $100 billion by 2025.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Within India, the industry plays an important role in India’s economic growth and is recognised as one of the top sectors attracting foreign direct investment (FDI) and reducing the trade deficit. The sector attracted a total of $16.54 billion worth of FDI inflow between April 2000 and June 2020. The sector’s importance is further underlined due to the amount of trade surplus generated with exports accounting for $20.7 billion and imports at $2.31 billion in the year 2020. The industry generates employment for over 2.7 million people, directly or indirectly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COVID-19 and Opportunity for India in Post-Pandemic World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The outbreak of the virus has challenged healthcare systems around the globe. From the United States, a country that undertakes the highest expenditure on its healthcare system, to the sophisticated European healthcare systems, each country is struggling to contain the spread. Despite the plethora of measures undertaken by countries, the massive inpouring of coronavirus infected patients has exceeded the existing infrastructure and resources in several countries, with the disease causing huge loss of life and human suffering. Additionally, there is a shortage of essential equipment, medicinal supplies and even medicines. The pandemic has also brought forth the existing inequalities in access to healthcare globally.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst these challenges, the global pharmaceutical markets are facing major discontinuities. For instance, there have been concerns regarding global over-dependence on China for active pharmaceutical ingredients (API), particularly in India, the US and Europe. As a result, in the past few months, several countries have been experiencing disruption in the pharma supply chain. The pandemic has also reinforced issues like re-shoring, nearshoring and shortening supply chains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Indian pharmaceutical industry has been a key contributor in improving the healthcare outcomes in the country with the pandemic presenting several opportunities and challenges for the industry. The growing distrust in China comes as an opportunity for India even so the economy will be facing increased competition from countries like Vietnam and Malaysia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To utilise the post-pandemic potential to the fullest, the industry has to build on its strength along with taking a giant leap towards innovation. The introduction of new capabilities is necessary to bring efficiencies to facilitate the industry to move up the value chain. A two-fold approach can be adopted to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, India needs to explore opportunities in complex generics, biosimilars, vaccines and preventives and other complex products. Having attained leadership in the generic market globally, India now needs to consolidate its position in other markets to move up the value chain. Focusing on complex products for this matter will help to achieve long-term sustained growth for the sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;These complex generics involve a comparatively more difficult production process, face less competition and involve higher margins. Similarly, biosimilars can play an equally important role in expanding India’s pharma sector. Domestically, India is leading in the world when it comes to launching biosimilars, however, only a few Indian companies are able to infiltrate US and European markets due to the non-alignment of India's regulatory guidelines with the regulations in these markets. In addition to the generics market, India has also established itself as a strong contender in the global vaccines market, with the country supplying 60% of the world's vaccine requirements. The step further is thus to develop new and complex vaccines, especially in times like these.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The second approach should be with respect to innovation. India needs to set up an environment conducive to innovation by bringing together academia, pharma companies, entrepreneurs and medical institutions. A look at the global scenario reveals that there is a concentration of research and development activities in the US and Europe, reflecting their dominance in innovation. India also does not compare well with its counterpart China which has twice the number of R&amp;amp;D sites and innovation centres. Therefore, there exists tremendous scope for India to establish itself as a global innovation hub.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In conclusion, the increasing shift of pharmaceutical firms from western economies to emerging economies presents India with a golden opportunity to enhance its pharma production along with emerging as a strong contender in the R&amp;amp;D sector. Even though the pandemic has resulted in innumerable challenges to the economy and the pharma industry in particular, it has also presented the industry with an opportunity to rise to the occasion and establish itself as a leading global player. Whether the country is able to perform on this front remains to be seen!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rajsi Sah</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared the coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 to be a pandemic. More than a year after the outbreak, over three million people have lost their lives with approximately 152 million cases across the globe. The pandemic has managed to cause a complete upheaval in people’s lifestyle along with businesses running losses and workers losing their jobs. Amidst this scenario, it is the pharmaceutical industry that has taken centre stage in the fight against this menace, assisting world governments in fulfilling their population's needs.&amp;nbsp; The global pharmaceutical industry in 2019 achieved a market value of approximately $1,217 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 6.7%. This value is expected to decline to $1,209 billion in 2020 owing to the COVID-19 outbreak.&amp;nbsp; The pharmaceutical (or pharma) industry can be defined as a “complex system of processes, operations, and organisations involved in the discovery, development, and manufacturing of drugs”. Firms functioning in the industry are responsible for research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities, development and manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients and manufacturing of drugs.&amp;nbsp; In 2019, Germany occupied the top position in the pharma industry with a 14.5% share in the export of drugs and medicines. It was followed by Switzerland and Netherlands with a share of 12.2% and 7.9% respectively. Among other countries, Denmark, Netherlands and Italy are the fastest growing exporters of drugs and medicines since 2015. However, three countries have witnessed a decline in the exported drugs and medicines sales in the last five years. These are, namely, the United Kingdom (26.7%), Ireland (18.9%) and the United States (6.1%).&amp;nbsp; In recent years, growth patterns in developed economies have observed a flat trend which has induced firms to shift their focus to emerging markets, thus finding new sources of revenue and profitability. The same has been witnessed for the pharmaceutical industry. The pharmaceutical emerging markets, or 'pharmerging' markets hold the potential of an extraordinary growth story.&amp;nbsp; In 2016, emerging markets accounted for over 30% of the development in pharma markets. This shift has been attributed to the economic and demographic development in these economies with a rise in health expectancy, access to healthcare services and improved funding for the healthcare sector.&amp;nbsp; Another major factor is the sharp decline in firms’ revenue as a result of the expiration of patents. This is known as the patent cliff, which is now affecting several branded drugs that have been in the market for years. The shift towards the use of generic drugs worldwide, increasing availability of biosimilar drugs, a significant differential in manufacturing costs and prices, and change in disease patterns in emerging countries are some of the other major reasons for the shift being observed in the pharmaceutical industry. These factors have induced the emerging economies into becoming the key drivers of the global pharmaceutical market.&amp;nbsp; Among the emerging markets, five countries namely China, Brazil, Russia, India and South Africa are the ones in domination with their role becoming increasingly important in the coming decade.&amp;nbsp; Pharmaceutical Industry in India In the last fifty years, India’s pharmaceutical industry has grown by leaps and bounds. From having a 5% share of the total medicine consumption in India in 1969, Indian pharma holds an 85% share of the same in 2020. Today, India is not only able to meet its domestic needs but has also established itself as a leader in the global pharma landscape and is known as the ‘pharmacy of the world’. The industry today is recognised for the quality and cost-effectiveness of its products. Widely known as the ‘archetype of affordable healthcare’, the Indian industry has had a significant contribution towards the improvement of public health outcomes, both within India and across the globe.&amp;nbsp; With a market size of $41 billion in 2018-19 and a market growth rate of 10-12%, the Indian pharma industry exported $16.3 billion worth of bulk drugs, intermediates, drug formulations, herbal products, surgical equipment and other goods in 2019-20. Particularly, the industry contributes more than 20% by volume to the global generics market and 62% of the global demand for vaccines. Fourteenth largest in the world in terms of value and 3rd largest in terms of volume, the industry is expected to grow to $100 billion by 2025.&amp;nbsp; Within India, the industry plays an important role in India’s economic growth and is recognised as one of the top sectors attracting foreign direct investment (FDI) and reducing the trade deficit. The sector attracted a total of $16.54 billion worth of FDI inflow between April 2000 and June 2020. The sector’s importance is further underlined due to the amount of trade surplus generated with exports accounting for $20.7 billion and imports at $2.31 billion in the year 2020. The industry generates employment for over 2.7 million people, directly or indirectly.&amp;nbsp; COVID-19 and Opportunity for India in Post-Pandemic World The outbreak of the virus has challenged healthcare systems around the globe. From the United States, a country that undertakes the highest expenditure on its healthcare system, to the sophisticated European healthcare systems, each country is struggling to contain the spread. Despite the plethora of measures undertaken by countries, the massive inpouring of coronavirus infected patients has exceeded the existing infrastructure and resources in several countries, with the disease causing huge loss of life and human suffering. Additionally, there is a shortage of essential equipment, medicinal supplies and even medicines. The pandemic has also brought forth the existing inequalities in access to healthcare globally.&amp;nbsp; Amidst these challenges, the global pharmaceutical markets are facing major discontinuities. For instance, there have been concerns regarding global over-dependence on China for active pharmaceutical ingredients (API), particularly in India, the US and Europe. As a result, in the past few months, several countries have been experiencing disruption in the pharma supply chain. The pandemic has also reinforced issues like re-shoring, nearshoring and shortening supply chains.&amp;nbsp; The Indian pharmaceutical industry has been a key contributor in improving the healthcare outcomes in the country with the pandemic presenting several opportunities and challenges for the industry. The growing distrust in China comes as an opportunity for India even so the economy will be facing increased competition from countries like Vietnam and Malaysia.&amp;nbsp; To utilise the post-pandemic potential to the fullest, the industry has to build on its strength along with taking a giant leap towards innovation. The introduction of new capabilities is necessary to bring efficiencies to facilitate the industry to move up the value chain. A two-fold approach can be adopted to achieve this. First, India needs to explore opportunities in complex generics, biosimilars, vaccines and preventives and other complex products. Having attained leadership in the generic market globally, India now needs to consolidate its position in other markets to move up the value chain. Focusing on complex products for this matter will help to achieve long-term sustained growth for the sector.&amp;nbsp; These complex generics involve a comparatively more difficult production process, face less competition and involve higher margins. Similarly, biosimilars can play an equally important role in expanding India’s pharma sector. Domestically, India is leading in the world when it comes to launching biosimilars, however, only a few Indian companies are able to infiltrate US and European markets due to the non-alignment of India's regulatory guidelines with the regulations in these markets. In addition to the generics market, India has also established itself as a strong contender in the global vaccines market, with the country supplying 60% of the world's vaccine requirements. The step further is thus to develop new and complex vaccines, especially in times like these.&amp;nbsp; The second approach should be with respect to innovation. India needs to set up an environment conducive to innovation by bringing together academia, pharma companies, entrepreneurs and medical institutions. A look at the global scenario reveals that there is a concentration of research and development activities in the US and Europe, reflecting their dominance in innovation. India also does not compare well with its counterpart China which has twice the number of R&amp;amp;D sites and innovation centres. Therefore, there exists tremendous scope for India to establish itself as a global innovation hub.&amp;nbsp; In conclusion, the increasing shift of pharmaceutical firms from western economies to emerging economies presents India with a golden opportunity to enhance its pharma production along with emerging as a strong contender in the R&amp;amp;D sector. Even though the pandemic has resulted in innumerable challenges to the economy and the pharma industry in particular, it has also presented the industry with an opportunity to rise to the occasion and establish itself as a leading global player. Whether the country is able to perform on this front remains to be seen!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Political Drama Worthy of Shakespeare: The Case of Malaysia</title><link href="/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Political Drama Worthy of Shakespeare: The Case of Malaysia" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare">&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Najib Razzak, who had become Prime Minister with the campaign promise of liberal politics, lost a general election to his former mentor, Mahathir Mohamad. The Barisan Nasional (BN) coalition, which had governed the country since its independence in 1957, was voted out of power. Following the downfall, Najib's properties were raided. Both he and his wife were charged with a string of offences and since then been found guilty on seven charges of corruption linked to the multibillion-dollar state investment fund 1MDB.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Najib’s history with corruption allegations is a long one. He has consistently denied the allegations and had been cleared by the country's authorities while still in office. During his tenure, he reformed strict laws on public gatherings and reinstated the controversial Internal Security Act in 2011 allowing detention without trial. The following year, he also went back on a pledge to repeal a controversial sedition law and instead strengthened it. Critics say the laws were a way for Najib to silence his political opponents and pander to the ethnic Malay-Muslim majority who formed his political party's most significant support base. In 2015, opposition leader and former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim was convicted of sodomy for the second time. In 2016, a security act aimed at combating terrorism was used to detain electoral reform activists. Ahead of the 2018 election, Najib's government set up a law against spreading &quot;fake news”, inadvertently used to silence campaigns by his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a string of numerous allegations, the real blight of Najib's political career has been his mismanagement of the state investment fund, 1Malaysia Development Berhad. The 1MDB fund was set up in 2009 to turn Kuala Lumpur into a financial hub and boost the economy through strategic investments. It began to draw negative attention in early 2015 after it missed payments due for some of the $11 billion it owed to banks and bondholders. The fund was then indicted for money laundering and sending hundreds of millions of dollars into private pockets to acquire assets globally, including yachts, paintings, jewellery and real estate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Department of Justice began investigating 1MDB, finding a diversion of $4.5 billion. Najib Razak was accused of pocketing nearly $700 million from the fund he set up. Ahead of the 2018 election, mass protests in Kuala Lumpur called on him to resign. The claims of corruption at 1MDB were a significant cause of Najib's election loss to Mahathir Mohamad, the world's oldest elected leader. Shortly after his victory, Malaysia's new Prime Minister reopened the 1MDB investigations and swore that Najib &quot;would face the consequences&quot; if he was guilty. Najib was forbidden from leaving the country, and properties linked to him were raided. Policemen state they recovered $273 million in luxury goods and cash, calling the seizure of valuables the biggest in Malaysian history.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US prosecutors had hinted that an anonymous individual dubbed &quot;Malaysian Official 1&quot; had received more than $1 billion from 1MDB, and that person is broadly believed to be Najib. Another target of the investigation is Malaysian businessman Low Taek Jho, who helped set up the fund, and is accused of diverting money to himself and his associates. He, too, has consistently rebuffed any wrongdoing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, Najib was arrested by anti-corruption authorities. He faces 21 counts of money laundering and 4 for abuse of power and negates all wrongdoing. The 12-year jail term for Malaysia's ex-Prime Minister serves as a warning that no matter how powerful one becomes, the sceptre of democracy hangs low over the heads of all public officials.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samakshi Garg</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 2018, Najib Razzak, who had become Prime Minister with the campaign promise of liberal politics, lost a general election to his former mentor, Mahathir Mohamad. The Barisan Nasional (BN) coalition, which had governed the country since its independence in 1957, was voted out of power. Following the downfall, Najib's properties were raided. Both he and his wife were charged with a string of offences and since then been found guilty on seven charges of corruption linked to the multibillion-dollar state investment fund 1MDB.&amp;nbsp; Najib’s history with corruption allegations is a long one. He has consistently denied the allegations and had been cleared by the country's authorities while still in office. During his tenure, he reformed strict laws on public gatherings and reinstated the controversial Internal Security Act in 2011 allowing detention without trial. The following year, he also went back on a pledge to repeal a controversial sedition law and instead strengthened it. Critics say the laws were a way for Najib to silence his political opponents and pander to the ethnic Malay-Muslim majority who formed his political party's most significant support base. In 2015, opposition leader and former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim was convicted of sodomy for the second time. In 2016, a security act aimed at combating terrorism was used to detain electoral reform activists. Ahead of the 2018 election, Najib's government set up a law against spreading &quot;fake news”, inadvertently used to silence campaigns by his opponents. Despite a string of numerous allegations, the real blight of Najib's political career has been his mismanagement of the state investment fund, 1Malaysia Development Berhad. The 1MDB fund was set up in 2009 to turn Kuala Lumpur into a financial hub and boost the economy through strategic investments. It began to draw negative attention in early 2015 after it missed payments due for some of the $11 billion it owed to banks and bondholders. The fund was then indicted for money laundering and sending hundreds of millions of dollars into private pockets to acquire assets globally, including yachts, paintings, jewellery and real estate.&amp;nbsp; The US Department of Justice began investigating 1MDB, finding a diversion of $4.5 billion. Najib Razak was accused of pocketing nearly $700 million from the fund he set up. Ahead of the 2018 election, mass protests in Kuala Lumpur called on him to resign. The claims of corruption at 1MDB were a significant cause of Najib's election loss to Mahathir Mohamad, the world's oldest elected leader. Shortly after his victory, Malaysia's new Prime Minister reopened the 1MDB investigations and swore that Najib &quot;would face the consequences&quot; if he was guilty. Najib was forbidden from leaving the country, and properties linked to him were raided. Policemen state they recovered $273 million in luxury goods and cash, calling the seizure of valuables the biggest in Malaysian history.&amp;nbsp; US prosecutors had hinted that an anonymous individual dubbed &quot;Malaysian Official 1&quot; had received more than $1 billion from 1MDB, and that person is broadly believed to be Najib. Another target of the investigation is Malaysian businessman Low Taek Jho, who helped set up the fund, and is accused of diverting money to himself and his associates. He, too, has consistently rebuffed any wrongdoing.&amp;nbsp; Eventually, Najib was arrested by anti-corruption authorities. He faces 21 counts of money laundering and 4 for abuse of power and negates all wrongdoing. The 12-year jail term for Malaysia's ex-Prime Minister serves as a warning that no matter how powerful one becomes, the sceptre of democracy hangs low over the heads of all public officials.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy</title><link href="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What seeds medical tourism?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Home Front&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, &lt;em&gt;atithi-devo-bhava &lt;/em&gt;(guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp; Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp; Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility. What seeds medical tourism? Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp; India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp; While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp; The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp; The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes. India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp; Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp; On the Home Front The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp; Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp; The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp; Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, atithi-devo-bhava (guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca</title><link href="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca">&lt;p&gt;When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Abhinav Gupta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guest</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products. Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp; Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp; The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp; Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&amp;nbsp;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp; If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production. The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp; The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market. Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology. LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp; The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp; While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp; The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp; There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp; The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp; The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp; LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp; -Abhinav Gupta Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A 23 on The Test</title><link href="/A-23-on-The-Test" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A 23 on The Test" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-23-on-The-Test</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-23-on-The-Test">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is not often that one gets to do what one enjoys the most, and I do. I get to announce to the world my life and web history. Unfortunately, the latter is almost always more exciting than the former and that is completely on me.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As an emotionally stunted child who wore the ugliest orange-brown clothes, I wondered which vehicle would zoom me out of my very own, personally customised hell. Turns out, it all begins with writing the lyrics of &lt;em&gt;Turning Page&lt;/em&gt; (from &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt;, duh) in a yellow, Winnie-the-Pooh diary. That and more, enveloped between multiple pages about overbearing mothers and underwhelming crushes can pave you the perfect path. My road to this pleasured life - wherein one learns to write like a jilted lover who married Freud’s second cousin, while may not have been easy, but it surely has been interesting to talk about. I may think I am all snark and sass, but underneath it all, I believe I am just an underdeveloped adult (read: kid) who barely has any control over herself and her relationships. Seldom have I ever given thought to who I would be if not me (not that I know who I am to begin with). A narcissistic go-getter? A quiet soul that fills everyone around them with peace? A bubbly know-it-all? Who!? Hold up, what if I am all of these or worse, none of them? What if I am just an unseasoned cardboard? Ah, the suspense.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Narcissism, come to think of it, is a word quite widely used and abused. Have you not called your ex one when he forgot your birthday? Or when your best friend buys that pair of jeans you had chosen for yourself? Often, the term is shrouded with the veil of self-love, and is even explained as vanity. But to be able to completely comprehend what it means, maybe we ought to step into the shoes of a narcissist. But first, should we test ourselves? How narcissistic are we? I have managed to find us all a risqué, not-all-that-legit &lt;a href=&quot;https://openpsychometrics.org/tests/NPI/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;test&lt;/a&gt;. If you tell me your scores, I will tell you mine (wink, wink), and then we can open a club!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The word ‘narcissism’ commonly describes someone who is excessively self-absorbed, selfish and egotistical, self-enhancing, arrogant, and shameless; but it is also used to explain individuals who are headstrong and may as well be used in a positive connotation. You see, before the Pandemic of Foreverland, they trended the idea of ‘Narcissism Epidemic’. It was based on the foundation of the ‘ME! ME! ME!’ life that many of us (us being Millennials and Gen Z) are leading. The social media influencers amidst us, have both literally and figuratively made a living out of just talking about and being concerned about oneself. From ‘OOTDs’ to ‘My Skincare Routine’- we’ve all been witnesses to the magic. I will watch Zendaya, or Harry Styles put on sunscreen any day, any time, no questions asked. And that may just be me with a keen level of fascination - but to each of them, the artists, they have to live with the idea of being famous for being ‘them’. This ‘Me’ culture quite vividly personifies the definition of Narcissism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This is not to say - any and every celebrity is a narcissist, just the ones who do not care about anyone else but them, such as Trump- (Melania, of course. Since the other Trump is irrelevant). It has been found that narcissistic traits afflict almost 10% of people in their 20s, compared to the 3% of people in their 60s, suggesting that as we grow older, our personalities are more settled and well-formed. I must say, this proves me right about how babies are just cute li’l narcissistic tiny-humans. All they care about is their milk and toys, the ‘me’ time never ends for them (oh the absolute joy!). I wonder if my suggestion of being a narcissist is also narcissistic. I wonder if we have made it so that anything but downgrading oneself beyond humility is how you prove you are not a narcissist. I wonder if only at the DSM’s criteria can we lay down the damage of narcissism and anything else is just immaculate fake news. The personality disorder of Narcissism is not something I’ve delved into, maybe due to the inconsistencies it may bring to our lives (self-fulfilling prophecy is real, people) or perhaps because no collection of symptoms is worth the trauma of self-diagnosis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Authority, self-sufficiency - a belief that one has achieved everything on their own, superiority, exhibitionism, exploitative-ness, vanity, and entitlement: these are the factoids used by the aforementioned risqué test, all quite all-encompassing, all traits of serial killers and great actors. All not all that bad sounding. Hitherto, the true problem that underlies narcissistic traits is not that they are problematic but that they are unrealistic. However much one is to believe otherwise, the belief in one’s own extraordinariness will sooner or later come to an end. Disillusionment is at bay. Now, one may choose to cross the bay, or stay stagnant and enjoy life while giving others’ plight - it's obviously a fair choice.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;You see, with a topic such as this, I can go on and on - hell, who am I kidding, I can go on and on about the most mundane of things - but today is special. I type all this knowing I might not get to do this again for some time now. Each time that I have penned down my thoughts, I have thought about how maybe it's just me and my editor who get a good chuckle out of these. Each time I tell myself my editor probably does not chuckle at all. Each time I am glad for the opportunity, upset about my own expectations and ecstatic over having been able to transfer my head-junk on paper. Narcissistic or not, I’m glad to be here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Disclaimer- I did score a 23 on the test, and if you did, too- please let’s form a Club! We can name it “Harshita’s”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><summary type="html">It is not often that one gets to do what one enjoys the most, and I do. I get to announce to the world my life and web history. Unfortunately, the latter is almost always more exciting than the former and that is completely on me.&amp;nbsp; As an emotionally stunted child who wore the ugliest orange-brown clothes, I wondered which vehicle would zoom me out of my very own, personally customised hell. Turns out, it all begins with writing the lyrics of Turning Page (from Twilight, duh) in a yellow, Winnie-the-Pooh diary. That and more, enveloped between multiple pages about overbearing mothers and underwhelming crushes can pave you the perfect path. My road to this pleasured life - wherein one learns to write like a jilted lover who married Freud’s second cousin, while may not have been easy, but it surely has been interesting to talk about. I may think I am all snark and sass, but underneath it all, I believe I am just an underdeveloped adult (read: kid) who barely has any control over herself and her relationships. Seldom have I ever given thought to who I would be if not me (not that I know who I am to begin with). A narcissistic go-getter? A quiet soul that fills everyone around them with peace? A bubbly know-it-all? Who!? Hold up, what if I am all of these or worse, none of them? What if I am just an unseasoned cardboard? Ah, the suspense.&amp;nbsp; Narcissism, come to think of it, is a word quite widely used and abused. Have you not called your ex one when he forgot your birthday? Or when your best friend buys that pair of jeans you had chosen for yourself? Often, the term is shrouded with the veil of self-love, and is even explained as vanity. But to be able to completely comprehend what it means, maybe we ought to step into the shoes of a narcissist. But first, should we test ourselves? How narcissistic are we? I have managed to find us all a risqué, not-all-that-legit test. If you tell me your scores, I will tell you mine (wink, wink), and then we can open a club! The word ‘narcissism’ commonly describes someone who is excessively self-absorbed, selfish and egotistical, self-enhancing, arrogant, and shameless; but it is also used to explain individuals who are headstrong and may as well be used in a positive connotation. You see, before the Pandemic of Foreverland, they trended the idea of ‘Narcissism Epidemic’. It was based on the foundation of the ‘ME! ME! ME!’ life that many of us (us being Millennials and Gen Z) are leading. The social media influencers amidst us, have both literally and figuratively made a living out of just talking about and being concerned about oneself. From ‘OOTDs’ to ‘My Skincare Routine’- we’ve all been witnesses to the magic. I will watch Zendaya, or Harry Styles put on sunscreen any day, any time, no questions asked. And that may just be me with a keen level of fascination - but to each of them, the artists, they have to live with the idea of being famous for being ‘them’. This ‘Me’ culture quite vividly personifies the definition of Narcissism.&amp;nbsp; This is not to say - any and every celebrity is a narcissist, just the ones who do not care about anyone else but them, such as Trump- (Melania, of course. Since the other Trump is irrelevant). It has been found that narcissistic traits afflict almost 10% of people in their 20s, compared to the 3% of people in their 60s, suggesting that as we grow older, our personalities are more settled and well-formed. I must say, this proves me right about how babies are just cute li’l narcissistic tiny-humans. All they care about is their milk and toys, the ‘me’ time never ends for them (oh the absolute joy!). I wonder if my suggestion of being a narcissist is also narcissistic. I wonder if we have made it so that anything but downgrading oneself beyond humility is how you prove you are not a narcissist. I wonder if only at the DSM’s criteria can we lay down the damage of narcissism and anything else is just immaculate fake news. The personality disorder of Narcissism is not something I’ve delved into, maybe due to the inconsistencies it may bring to our lives (self-fulfilling prophecy is real, people) or perhaps because no collection of symptoms is worth the trauma of self-diagnosis.&amp;nbsp; Authority, self-sufficiency - a belief that one has achieved everything on their own, superiority, exhibitionism, exploitative-ness, vanity, and entitlement: these are the factoids used by the aforementioned risqué test, all quite all-encompassing, all traits of serial killers and great actors. All not all that bad sounding. Hitherto, the true problem that underlies narcissistic traits is not that they are problematic but that they are unrealistic. However much one is to believe otherwise, the belief in one’s own extraordinariness will sooner or later come to an end. Disillusionment is at bay. Now, one may choose to cross the bay, or stay stagnant and enjoy life while giving others’ plight - it's obviously a fair choice.&amp;nbsp; You see, with a topic such as this, I can go on and on - hell, who am I kidding, I can go on and on about the most mundane of things - but today is special. I type all this knowing I might not get to do this again for some time now. Each time that I have penned down my thoughts, I have thought about how maybe it's just me and my editor who get a good chuckle out of these. Each time I tell myself my editor probably does not chuckle at all. Each time I am glad for the opportunity, upset about my own expectations and ecstatic over having been able to transfer my head-junk on paper. Narcissistic or not, I’m glad to be here.&amp;nbsp; Disclaimer- I did score a 23 on the test, and if you did, too- please let’s form a Club! We can name it “Harshita’s”.</summary></entry></feed>