<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-25T23:36:30+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge</title><link href="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge" /><published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge">&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan. The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF. India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp; This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma. However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere</title><link href="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere" /><published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere">&lt;p&gt;Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “&lt;em&gt;America First!&lt;/em&gt;”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp; Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp; From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond. But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp; In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “America First!”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp; In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp; Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War. What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modern Monetary Theory: The Solution to Developing Countries’ Problems?</title><link href="/Modern-Monetary-Theory" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Monetary Theory: The Solution to Developing Countries’ Problems?" /><published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Modern-Monetary-Theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Modern-Monetary-Theory">&lt;p&gt;Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is increasingly gaining traction in today’s public discourse. While there is huge literature available regarding MMT, it is often ridiculed by statements claiming to explain the theory, such as “&lt;em&gt;money printer gone brrrr&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; It is important to know that MMT doesn’t advocate for money printing. To borrow from L Randall Wray, a pioneer of the field, MMT argues that a sovereign government that issues its own “nonconvertible” currency cannot become insolvent (in terms of its own currency). It cannot be forced into involuntary default on its obligations denominated in its own currency. It can “afford” to buy anything for sale that is priced in its own currency. Here sovereignty is defined in monetary terms in that a state has monetary sovereignty when it issues its own currency, taxes its people in that currency, accepts that currency in payment of the imposed obligations, and issues debt in its own currency. Along with this, a fifth consideration, according to Wray, is to have a floating exchange rate regime (which is what “nonconvertible” currency means); so that it provides more fiscal space for the government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MMTers argue that their descriptions and prescriptions equally hold for the developing nations as for the developed nations. While this is largely true, there are however some constraints with regard to the developing countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first such constraint is the need for a developing country to accumulate foreign currency, especially the international reserve currency - the dollar. One major factor that leads to this accumulation is the necessity to import various types of goods (which could be for various reasons). So, with the accumulation of external debt, the demand for foreign currency also increases because it leads to higher debt service obligations and also because it increases risk perception as there is greater exposure to currency mismatch. The accumulation of foreign debt means that the balance of payments becomes a major limitation on the policy front for a developing country. In the current account of the balance of payments, a trade deficit (imports &amp;gt; exports) is compensated by positive capital inflows (which leads to a surplus in the capital account). That is, a current account deficit must be balanced by the sum of the capital account. Randal Wray once wrote that “&lt;em&gt;MMT makes no claim that floating rates eliminate current account deficits, indeed, MMT does not argue that elimination of current account deficits is even desirable”&lt;/em&gt;. But, the said balancing does not mean that a country can sustain any level of the current account deficit, over time. There is ample evidence available that the higher the current account deficit, the less likely that it can be sustained. What all this means is that the current account deficit chips away the monetary sovereignty of developing countries and thus the validity of MMT in such countries becomes uncertain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second issue, which is related here is that Wray suggests that in a floating exchange regime a government does not need to fear that it will run out of foreign currency reserves (or gold reserves) for the simple reason that it does not convert its domestic currency to foreign currency at a fixed exchange rate. Indeed, the government does not have to promise to make any conversions at all. But a developing country necessarily concerns itself with the capital flows not because of the issue of convertibility of currency, but because it needs to pay for its imports (or some sort of short-term obligation). All this is to say that a developing country may very well face the risk of foreign debt default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fadhel Kaboub, another MMT economist, identifies three broad areas from where a trade deficit arises. It arises because the developing country lacks food sovereignty, energy sovereignty and they essentially export low-value goods and import high-value goods. He says that this is a trap, in that a trade deficit leads a country to accumulate foreign currency. To do this, domestic resources are diverted from the areas of the government’s priority to areas that earn foreign exchange for the country. For instance, a government may prioritise the needs of foreign tourists as they spend the foreign currency or the government may announce tax concessions with the hope to attract foreign investors and end up losing revenue which could otherwise be used to develop local government. So, his advice to developing countries is to invest in sustainable agriculture to reach a level of self-sufficiency, to invest in renewable energy production that allows the countries to set their priorities, to invest in education, and to prepare an industrial strategy to move up the value chain from producing low-value-added goods to high-value-added goods. All these will provide resilience for a country from external shocks that a country may face.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third important constraint is inflation. MMT argues that while a sovereign can never default, there are limits as to how much it can spend; that is, there are certain limits on the fiscal deficit a sovereign runs. These limits are in the form of constraints on the part of real resources in an economy. If a government spends more than what these real resources could absorb, it risks the possibility of price hikes, i.e. inflation. MMT’s prescription to this problem is that the government could increase tax rates so that the purchasing power of the economy as a whole falls and thus inflation could be arrested (note that MMT also says tax revenue does not pay for anything but gives several other reasons for justifying the taxes). Now, in developing countries, there are two main problems with this. First, the tax base is lower in developing countries. Therefore, even when taxes are increased there might not be the desired effect of reducing purchasing power and thus controlling inflation. The prevalence of the informal economy on a large scale is also a constraint in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that developing economies face certain constraints that the MMT approach has not fully gauged. For instance, a developed country might not have constraints of fiscal space due to the current account of the balance of payments (and due to implications thereof). However, it can also be argued that it is precisely the understanding and the implementation of MMT that is required for the developing countries to overcome these constraints. The primary focus of MMT on real resources can be an important takeaway for developing economies because the development of real resources (in part) entails huge investments in developing human capital, green resources, and health resources. Despite many constraints, MMT also opens many doors for the developing economies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is increasingly gaining traction in today’s public discourse. While there is huge literature available regarding MMT, it is often ridiculed by statements claiming to explain the theory, such as “money printer gone brrrr”. It is important to know that MMT doesn’t advocate for money printing. To borrow from L Randall Wray, a pioneer of the field, MMT argues that a sovereign government that issues its own “nonconvertible” currency cannot become insolvent (in terms of its own currency). It cannot be forced into involuntary default on its obligations denominated in its own currency. It can “afford” to buy anything for sale that is priced in its own currency. Here sovereignty is defined in monetary terms in that a state has monetary sovereignty when it issues its own currency, taxes its people in that currency, accepts that currency in payment of the imposed obligations, and issues debt in its own currency. Along with this, a fifth consideration, according to Wray, is to have a floating exchange rate regime (which is what “nonconvertible” currency means); so that it provides more fiscal space for the government.&amp;nbsp; MMTers argue that their descriptions and prescriptions equally hold for the developing nations as for the developed nations. While this is largely true, there are however some constraints with regard to the developing countries.&amp;nbsp; The first such constraint is the need for a developing country to accumulate foreign currency, especially the international reserve currency - the dollar. One major factor that leads to this accumulation is the necessity to import various types of goods (which could be for various reasons). So, with the accumulation of external debt, the demand for foreign currency also increases because it leads to higher debt service obligations and also because it increases risk perception as there is greater exposure to currency mismatch. The accumulation of foreign debt means that the balance of payments becomes a major limitation on the policy front for a developing country. In the current account of the balance of payments, a trade deficit (imports &amp;gt; exports) is compensated by positive capital inflows (which leads to a surplus in the capital account). That is, a current account deficit must be balanced by the sum of the capital account. Randal Wray once wrote that “MMT makes no claim that floating rates eliminate current account deficits, indeed, MMT does not argue that elimination of current account deficits is even desirable”. But, the said balancing does not mean that a country can sustain any level of the current account deficit, over time. There is ample evidence available that the higher the current account deficit, the less likely that it can be sustained. What all this means is that the current account deficit chips away the monetary sovereignty of developing countries and thus the validity of MMT in such countries becomes uncertain.&amp;nbsp; A second issue, which is related here is that Wray suggests that in a floating exchange regime a government does not need to fear that it will run out of foreign currency reserves (or gold reserves) for the simple reason that it does not convert its domestic currency to foreign currency at a fixed exchange rate. Indeed, the government does not have to promise to make any conversions at all. But a developing country necessarily concerns itself with the capital flows not because of the issue of convertibility of currency, but because it needs to pay for its imports (or some sort of short-term obligation). All this is to say that a developing country may very well face the risk of foreign debt default. Fadhel Kaboub, another MMT economist, identifies three broad areas from where a trade deficit arises. It arises because the developing country lacks food sovereignty, energy sovereignty and they essentially export low-value goods and import high-value goods. He says that this is a trap, in that a trade deficit leads a country to accumulate foreign currency. To do this, domestic resources are diverted from the areas of the government’s priority to areas that earn foreign exchange for the country. For instance, a government may prioritise the needs of foreign tourists as they spend the foreign currency or the government may announce tax concessions with the hope to attract foreign investors and end up losing revenue which could otherwise be used to develop local government. So, his advice to developing countries is to invest in sustainable agriculture to reach a level of self-sufficiency, to invest in renewable energy production that allows the countries to set their priorities, to invest in education, and to prepare an industrial strategy to move up the value chain from producing low-value-added goods to high-value-added goods. All these will provide resilience for a country from external shocks that a country may face.&amp;nbsp; A third important constraint is inflation. MMT argues that while a sovereign can never default, there are limits as to how much it can spend; that is, there are certain limits on the fiscal deficit a sovereign runs. These limits are in the form of constraints on the part of real resources in an economy. If a government spends more than what these real resources could absorb, it risks the possibility of price hikes, i.e. inflation. MMT’s prescription to this problem is that the government could increase tax rates so that the purchasing power of the economy as a whole falls and thus inflation could be arrested (note that MMT also says tax revenue does not pay for anything but gives several other reasons for justifying the taxes). Now, in developing countries, there are two main problems with this. First, the tax base is lower in developing countries. Therefore, even when taxes are increased there might not be the desired effect of reducing purchasing power and thus controlling inflation. The prevalence of the informal economy on a large scale is also a constraint in this context. It is true that developing economies face certain constraints that the MMT approach has not fully gauged. For instance, a developed country might not have constraints of fiscal space due to the current account of the balance of payments (and due to implications thereof). However, it can also be argued that it is precisely the understanding and the implementation of MMT that is required for the developing countries to overcome these constraints. The primary focus of MMT on real resources can be an important takeaway for developing economies because the development of real resources (in part) entails huge investments in developing human capital, green resources, and health resources. Despite many constraints, MMT also opens many doors for the developing economies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scams &amp;amp; Frauds: Serial Killers of the Economy</title><link href="/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scams &amp; Frauds: Serial Killers of the Economy" /><published>2020-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy">&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy has been growing at an unprecedented rate in recent times. Various factors have culminated together to lead to such growth. No doubt, financial institutions are one of the most important aspects and thus referred to as the ‘backbones of the economy’. Banks, co-operatives, and other financial institutions look into the monetary affairs of a state, thus making their efficient functioning essential for an economy’s healthy growth. However, in recent times, these holy institutes have been marred by impious activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do face errors and issues due to a number of reasons but it is of no serious concern until it is taken care of. There have been times when these issues and errors slipped out of hand and created chaos among the public. These major errors can also be termed as ‘banking frauds’. Banking frauds are referred to the illegal and unethical means used by one party to extract or misuse funds, assets or even property owned by a financial institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India has seen a spike in these frauds recently and the reasons are still unknown. The cases of Vijay Mallya and Nirav Modi are two major examples of such frauds. Mallya is accused of fraud and money laundering and owes an estimated ₹90 billion to 17 Indian banks. The Nirav Modi-PNB scam is one of the largest in India’s banking history. It involves undertaking an estimated amount of ₹110 billion from the Punjab National Bank, Brady House branch located in Mumbai. Both accused escaped the country and the cases are still under trial. The money has not been returned yet and thus the banks had to lose out on such a huge amount that belongs to their account holders in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frauds are usually done by individuals for petty self-gains but the involvement of people within the banks is definite. It is possible to plan and execute a crime so huge only when you play around with the loopholes existing in the policies and thereby messing the entire functioning of the system. This usually requires help from the people working within the institution and in most cases of frauds, employees are involved. The advent of technology can also be one reason which facilitates these frauds. Other reasons can be concentration of power at certain levels or giving leeway during legal procedures. Ideally, accounts with huge exposures and capital need to be checked frequently with the use of forensic due diligence infrastructure. The decision making regarding huge loans should be done by a committee rather than a single person. Monitoring the trail of money will also reduce the risk of laundering cases.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question still remains: how do these frauds impact the public or even the economy?&amp;nbsp; They cause a slowdown in the growth of the economy which weakens the economy and discourages foreign investments. The money being stolen or laundered in these cases is the public fund. The minute public loses trust in a bank, it leads to even greater losses for the banks, and the bank might even go bankrupt. Banks play an important and integral part of the monetary system. They affect the cash flow, money demand, and various other factors. The moment their functioning is disturbed by these frauds, it definitely trickles down to other areas as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frauds and scams can surely be avoided at various levels and it is important that even governments provide guidelines to minimise the risks. Strict action against the offenders should be taken to set a precedence for the public. It is a huge task to maintain transparency at every step but at the same time, banks should come forward and take responsibility and accountability for the mishaps. The trust between the public and these financial institutions has to be maintained for the smooth functioning of the economy. Banking institutions are vital and thus a step towards more secure functioning needs to be taken to avoid these circumstances. It is tedious but definitely not impossible. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Indian economy has been growing at an unprecedented rate in recent times. Various factors have culminated together to lead to such growth. No doubt, financial institutions are one of the most important aspects and thus referred to as the ‘backbones of the economy’. Banks, co-operatives, and other financial institutions look into the monetary affairs of a state, thus making their efficient functioning essential for an economy’s healthy growth. However, in recent times, these holy institutes have been marred by impious activities. They do face errors and issues due to a number of reasons but it is of no serious concern until it is taken care of. There have been times when these issues and errors slipped out of hand and created chaos among the public. These major errors can also be termed as ‘banking frauds’. Banking frauds are referred to the illegal and unethical means used by one party to extract or misuse funds, assets or even property owned by a financial institution.&amp;nbsp; India has seen a spike in these frauds recently and the reasons are still unknown. The cases of Vijay Mallya and Nirav Modi are two major examples of such frauds. Mallya is accused of fraud and money laundering and owes an estimated ₹90 billion to 17 Indian banks. The Nirav Modi-PNB scam is one of the largest in India’s banking history. It involves undertaking an estimated amount of ₹110 billion from the Punjab National Bank, Brady House branch located in Mumbai. Both accused escaped the country and the cases are still under trial. The money has not been returned yet and thus the banks had to lose out on such a huge amount that belongs to their account holders in the first place. Frauds are usually done by individuals for petty self-gains but the involvement of people within the banks is definite. It is possible to plan and execute a crime so huge only when you play around with the loopholes existing in the policies and thereby messing the entire functioning of the system. This usually requires help from the people working within the institution and in most cases of frauds, employees are involved. The advent of technology can also be one reason which facilitates these frauds. Other reasons can be concentration of power at certain levels or giving leeway during legal procedures. Ideally, accounts with huge exposures and capital need to be checked frequently with the use of forensic due diligence infrastructure. The decision making regarding huge loans should be done by a committee rather than a single person. Monitoring the trail of money will also reduce the risk of laundering cases.&amp;nbsp; The question still remains: how do these frauds impact the public or even the economy?&amp;nbsp; They cause a slowdown in the growth of the economy which weakens the economy and discourages foreign investments. The money being stolen or laundered in these cases is the public fund. The minute public loses trust in a bank, it leads to even greater losses for the banks, and the bank might even go bankrupt. Banks play an important and integral part of the monetary system. They affect the cash flow, money demand, and various other factors. The moment their functioning is disturbed by these frauds, it definitely trickles down to other areas as well.&amp;nbsp; Frauds and scams can surely be avoided at various levels and it is important that even governments provide guidelines to minimise the risks. Strict action against the offenders should be taken to set a precedence for the public. It is a huge task to maintain transparency at every step but at the same time, banks should come forward and take responsibility and accountability for the mishaps. The trust between the public and these financial institutions has to be maintained for the smooth functioning of the economy. Banking institutions are vital and thus a step towards more secure functioning needs to be taken to avoid these circumstances. It is tedious but definitely not impossible.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Present Bias: Focus on the Now but maybe Not Always</title><link href="/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Present Bias: Focus on the Now but maybe Not Always" /><published>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always">&lt;p&gt;Many times we wonder, what is it that makes us procrastinate? Why do we spend the whole day scrolling through Instagram instead of finishing the assignment that is due tomorrow? Apart from the fact that social media is designed to distract us, procrastinating isn't as simple as just being lazy. It isn't only about not wanting to do the task at hand, but more about how we humans are wired.&amp;nbsp; Procrastination is in fact related to a cognitive bias called the &lt;em&gt;present bias&lt;/em&gt;. As the name in itself suggests, it is the tendency of humans to be biased towards the present. This means that we tend to go for short-term rewards that provide us instant gratification rather than choosing long-term benefits. Thus, even though the benefit of finishing that assignment is clearly more than simply being on Instagram, the sense of gratification is achieved faster in the latter. Therefore, our brain might as well trick us into choosing the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand why humans are actually biased towards the present. The answer lies in how our ancestors lived their lives. The times they lived in, it only made sense that they focused on the present. With the uncertainty of the future and the environment they lived in, they had no other option but to be short-sighted in their decision making. This present bias allowed them to survive and deal with the immediate threats that existed around them. Over the centuries, this outlook of theirs seems to have been so well engraved in our brains that even today we have a similar mindset. Despite us having a far more stable lifestyle and a future to actually look forward to, our brain still makes us biased towards our present. It still makes us believe that the future is a scary avenue that one shouldn't be focusing much on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of the present bias has been studied by many researchers over the years, in order to understand to what extent such a bias can affect the lives of individuals. An interesting experiment in this field was conducted by Walter Mischel. This experiment that goes by the name of &lt;em&gt;Marshmallow Test &lt;/em&gt;is a famous experiment which involved finding out whether children delayed gratification. It involved children being asked to either choose a marshmallow now or wait for 15-20 minutes to get two of them. This experiment, however, did not end here only. After a few years, these very children, who were by then adolescents, were traced and it was seen that the children who delayed gratification at a younger age were able to be more successful in the later period of their lives. Thus, shedding light on the connection between small decisions turning into a lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect of present bias is that it is not just limited to the field of psychology but also equally important for economics. Take for an example, if you were to choose between getting a job of ₹15,000/month now, or interning for free for a year and getting a job of ₹30,000/month. You are more likely to choose the former. But if you were asked to either complete your 3 years of Bachelor's and get a job starting at ₹15,000/month or to choose an integrated programme of 4 years that would allow you to get a package starting at ₹30,000/month, then you are most likely to choose the second option. Even though there isn’t a difference between these two cases other than the time periods, your choice would potentially differ. This is because our brain can only distinguish between the present and the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the future is three or four years down the lane, our brain fails to distinguish between them, because both are considered as far-sighted. Since our mind takes the future as uncertain it wants to make decisions for now, even though they might not be as beneficial. In economics, present bias is used when we talk about time inconsistency and discounting. Time inconsistency refers to the fact that individuals are inconsistent over time. That is, for instance, you decide to hit the gym next month, but when next month arrives, you are more likely to postpone it to another month. Thus, meaning that people aren't as rational in making decisions, but there are various social and psychological factors that govern their decisions. People have the tendency to change their choices, over different time periods even though the benefits remain the same. Richard H Thaler (a Nobel Prize Winner for his work in the field of behavioural economics) has conducted researches that show that economics and psychology are far more closely related than one can imagine, thus expanding the scope and importance of behavioural economics. He along with H M Shefrin wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;An Economic Theory of Self-control&lt;/em&gt; that introduced an economic model of self-control. This model explains that people aren't only lacking self-control when it comes to not buying new clothes, or when it comes to stopping with just another episode. But the lack of self-control can also be seen towards how people handle their finances, especially saving for their retirements before it gets late. To us, saving money seems more like a loss now even though it’ll benefit us in future, and thus people tend to postpone saving money. In fact, this research has led to various social policies to emerge to help people with saving their money from early days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it is wired into our system to focus on what could harm us immediately, rather than what could harm us in the long-term, present bias manifests itself in many of our actions. The concept of present bias explains why we humans tend to make self-harming choices that provide us instant gratification but clearly have harmful consequences in the future. It also explains why we tend to ignore the importance of climate change, since it doesn't seem like an instant harm to our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in the present is important, but it isn't all we should be focused on. In reality, our lives are a combination of the past, present and future and therefore it becomes equally important to realise that the present is only a small piece in the puzzle of life. Understanding what present bias is, and how strongly it can control our decision making, allows us to be more aware of our own selves. It makes us realise that our brains aren't always thinking what's best for us and can quite a few times make impulsive decisions that might not seem so right in the years to come. Clearly, our brains are guided by the fear of the future, because of all the uncertainty it brings. So it only makes sense that we continue to ignore the future, and be in a more comfortable zone, the present. And honestly, instant gratification, no matter for how little of a time, does feel good. But it also feels fulfilling to make decisions that'll help our future selves. This is the dilemma that present bias poses. Whether to choose the time that we know of or to choose the time that'll come. It isn't easy to break away from our habits, especially the ones that are so well engraved in our nerves. Self-control and will power aren't as easily attained as we are likely to believe. But what we can do is to be more aware of how our brains have a tendency of fooling our own selves, and maybe for once not trust whatever our brain has to say.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Priyanshi Mehra</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Many times we wonder, what is it that makes us procrastinate? Why do we spend the whole day scrolling through Instagram instead of finishing the assignment that is due tomorrow? Apart from the fact that social media is designed to distract us, procrastinating isn't as simple as just being lazy. It isn't only about not wanting to do the task at hand, but more about how we humans are wired.&amp;nbsp; Procrastination is in fact related to a cognitive bias called the present bias. As the name in itself suggests, it is the tendency of humans to be biased towards the present. This means that we tend to go for short-term rewards that provide us instant gratification rather than choosing long-term benefits. Thus, even though the benefit of finishing that assignment is clearly more than simply being on Instagram, the sense of gratification is achieved faster in the latter. Therefore, our brain might as well trick us into choosing the latter. It is important to understand why humans are actually biased towards the present. The answer lies in how our ancestors lived their lives. The times they lived in, it only made sense that they focused on the present. With the uncertainty of the future and the environment they lived in, they had no other option but to be short-sighted in their decision making. This present bias allowed them to survive and deal with the immediate threats that existed around them. Over the centuries, this outlook of theirs seems to have been so well engraved in our brains that even today we have a similar mindset. Despite us having a far more stable lifestyle and a future to actually look forward to, our brain still makes us biased towards our present. It still makes us believe that the future is a scary avenue that one shouldn't be focusing much on it. The idea of the present bias has been studied by many researchers over the years, in order to understand to what extent such a bias can affect the lives of individuals. An interesting experiment in this field was conducted by Walter Mischel. This experiment that goes by the name of Marshmallow Test is a famous experiment which involved finding out whether children delayed gratification. It involved children being asked to either choose a marshmallow now or wait for 15-20 minutes to get two of them. This experiment, however, did not end here only. After a few years, these very children, who were by then adolescents, were traced and it was seen that the children who delayed gratification at a younger age were able to be more successful in the later period of their lives. Thus, shedding light on the connection between small decisions turning into a lifestyle. An interesting aspect of present bias is that it is not just limited to the field of psychology but also equally important for economics. Take for an example, if you were to choose between getting a job of ₹15,000/month now, or interning for free for a year and getting a job of ₹30,000/month. You are more likely to choose the former. But if you were asked to either complete your 3 years of Bachelor's and get a job starting at ₹15,000/month or to choose an integrated programme of 4 years that would allow you to get a package starting at ₹30,000/month, then you are most likely to choose the second option. Even though there isn’t a difference between these two cases other than the time periods, your choice would potentially differ. This is because our brain can only distinguish between the present and the future. Whether the future is three or four years down the lane, our brain fails to distinguish between them, because both are considered as far-sighted. Since our mind takes the future as uncertain it wants to make decisions for now, even though they might not be as beneficial. In economics, present bias is used when we talk about time inconsistency and discounting. Time inconsistency refers to the fact that individuals are inconsistent over time. That is, for instance, you decide to hit the gym next month, but when next month arrives, you are more likely to postpone it to another month. Thus, meaning that people aren't as rational in making decisions, but there are various social and psychological factors that govern their decisions. People have the tendency to change their choices, over different time periods even though the benefits remain the same. Richard H Thaler (a Nobel Prize Winner for his work in the field of behavioural economics) has conducted researches that show that economics and psychology are far more closely related than one can imagine, thus expanding the scope and importance of behavioural economics. He along with H M Shefrin wrote a paper titled An Economic Theory of Self-control that introduced an economic model of self-control. This model explains that people aren't only lacking self-control when it comes to not buying new clothes, or when it comes to stopping with just another episode. But the lack of self-control can also be seen towards how people handle their finances, especially saving for their retirements before it gets late. To us, saving money seems more like a loss now even though it’ll benefit us in future, and thus people tend to postpone saving money. In fact, this research has led to various social policies to emerge to help people with saving their money from early days. Since it is wired into our system to focus on what could harm us immediately, rather than what could harm us in the long-term, present bias manifests itself in many of our actions. The concept of present bias explains why we humans tend to make self-harming choices that provide us instant gratification but clearly have harmful consequences in the future. It also explains why we tend to ignore the importance of climate change, since it doesn't seem like an instant harm to our minds. Living in the present is important, but it isn't all we should be focused on. In reality, our lives are a combination of the past, present and future and therefore it becomes equally important to realise that the present is only a small piece in the puzzle of life. Understanding what present bias is, and how strongly it can control our decision making, allows us to be more aware of our own selves. It makes us realise that our brains aren't always thinking what's best for us and can quite a few times make impulsive decisions that might not seem so right in the years to come. Clearly, our brains are guided by the fear of the future, because of all the uncertainty it brings. So it only makes sense that we continue to ignore the future, and be in a more comfortable zone, the present. And honestly, instant gratification, no matter for how little of a time, does feel good. But it also feels fulfilling to make decisions that'll help our future selves. This is the dilemma that present bias poses. Whether to choose the time that we know of or to choose the time that'll come. It isn't easy to break away from our habits, especially the ones that are so well engraved in our nerves. Self-control and will power aren't as easily attained as we are likely to believe. But what we can do is to be more aware of how our brains have a tendency of fooling our own selves, and maybe for once not trust whatever our brain has to say.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meraki and More</title><link href="/Meraki-and-More" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meraki and More" /><published>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Meraki-and-More</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Meraki-and-More">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;I’ve recently had the opportunity to travel to the city where my freedom lies and be back in all of 30 minus 1 hour, and let me tell you- the thrill of running away from an ill-fashioned mask wearer, who is munching on chips as he coughs, and to look at Starbucks with nostalgia, and think of times when you didn’t have to worry about how many people might have touched that straw? Mind-blowing. The question of my sanity lies in if the risk, the multiple masks, the shield, the gloves, the chaos, all of it was worth a total of 40 minutes spent in ecstasy garnered from a bubble tea and nachos, a well-lit room and comfy hotel bed, oh, and well, a well-timed fight with your may-be/may-not-be boyfriend. Well, so was it? I wouldn’t know, might have to come back to that.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the world that we live now, not much seems to be as it was, most of all, the things that are. Every stressor is either exaggerated or it exasperates you to think of your stressor in the face of others’ much bigger ones. No problem is big enough to hold in the face of a pandemic, and that is known - but every problem is definitely magnified in the face of a pandemic and if that’s not the truth, I don’t know what is. The other day, I got my results back from an entrance that I barely prepared for and upon announcing my failure to my friend, you know what I received? “&lt;em&gt;It is the pandemic, no one expects better.&lt;/em&gt;” Pure empathy, pure justification, pure ‘hello, new issue causing other issues’. I’ve rationalised most things in the last 7 months to be external, and that maybe the fundamental attribution at play but I’m not to be blamed. Am I trying to shroud the pain the world has been due to this hazard? Absolutely not. I couldn’t if I wanted to, know that.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Last time I sat down to write, Kanye was in his first phase of the breakdown and today, Biden has bagged the highest votes in Pennsylvania. No amount of stimulus has been able to stimulate me enough to go back to my Googling days, oh! The blessed days of me finding a new word and reaching out to it every chance I could get, complete Icarus to the sun. Which reminds me, (in my most moving voice) they say when you do something with all your creativity, love and passion - you do it with Meraki. A word I’m extremely fond and am slightly terrified of. Like every other beautiful, soul-filling word (well, in this case, soul shedding, (you’ll see)), it belongs to the Greeks and implies that &lt;em&gt;“every time one works on something one really loves, they put a part of themselves into it&lt;/em&gt;”. While the concept is beautiful and has no English counterpart, there lies enough truth in it to make it completely sound. In my little to no knowledge of the ‘worldly’ affairs, I could only bring myself to compare it to Cathexis - the psychic energy one puts into people, objects, things, a gift given to us by my all-time favourite, Mr Freud. A close second could be ardour, or well, ardour. Ah, here I am again, stuck in words, when what I need to do is be stressed by my stressors, and subsequently, others’ stressors, too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Is this the time to get back to the drama that folds in from my may-be/may-be-not boyfriend? How about my (n)ever engaged and lengthy enough to go around the sun once (maybe, twice) to-do list? Ah, the joys. All I hope for is that if and when you read this, if and when you are in a position where it seems that you’re not working with Meraki anymore, this could work as a reinforcement, perhaps an aversive one. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><summary type="html">I’ve recently had the opportunity to travel to the city where my freedom lies and be back in all of 30 minus 1 hour, and let me tell you- the thrill of running away from an ill-fashioned mask wearer, who is munching on chips as he coughs, and to look at Starbucks with nostalgia, and think of times when you didn’t have to worry about how many people might have touched that straw? Mind-blowing. The question of my sanity lies in if the risk, the multiple masks, the shield, the gloves, the chaos, all of it was worth a total of 40 minutes spent in ecstasy garnered from a bubble tea and nachos, a well-lit room and comfy hotel bed, oh, and well, a well-timed fight with your may-be/may-not-be boyfriend. Well, so was it? I wouldn’t know, might have to come back to that.&amp;nbsp; In the world that we live now, not much seems to be as it was, most of all, the things that are. Every stressor is either exaggerated or it exasperates you to think of your stressor in the face of others’ much bigger ones. No problem is big enough to hold in the face of a pandemic, and that is known - but every problem is definitely magnified in the face of a pandemic and if that’s not the truth, I don’t know what is. The other day, I got my results back from an entrance that I barely prepared for and upon announcing my failure to my friend, you know what I received? “It is the pandemic, no one expects better.” Pure empathy, pure justification, pure ‘hello, new issue causing other issues’. I’ve rationalised most things in the last 7 months to be external, and that maybe the fundamental attribution at play but I’m not to be blamed. Am I trying to shroud the pain the world has been due to this hazard? Absolutely not. I couldn’t if I wanted to, know that.&amp;nbsp; Last time I sat down to write, Kanye was in his first phase of the breakdown and today, Biden has bagged the highest votes in Pennsylvania. No amount of stimulus has been able to stimulate me enough to go back to my Googling days, oh! The blessed days of me finding a new word and reaching out to it every chance I could get, complete Icarus to the sun. Which reminds me, (in my most moving voice) they say when you do something with all your creativity, love and passion - you do it with Meraki. A word I’m extremely fond and am slightly terrified of. Like every other beautiful, soul-filling word (well, in this case, soul shedding, (you’ll see)), it belongs to the Greeks and implies that “every time one works on something one really loves, they put a part of themselves into it”. While the concept is beautiful and has no English counterpart, there lies enough truth in it to make it completely sound. In my little to no knowledge of the ‘worldly’ affairs, I could only bring myself to compare it to Cathexis - the psychic energy one puts into people, objects, things, a gift given to us by my all-time favourite, Mr Freud. A close second could be ardour, or well, ardour. Ah, here I am again, stuck in words, when what I need to do is be stressed by my stressors, and subsequently, others’ stressors, too.&amp;nbsp; Is this the time to get back to the drama that folds in from my may-be/may-be-not boyfriend? How about my (n)ever engaged and lengthy enough to go around the sun once (maybe, twice) to-do list? Ah, the joys. All I hope for is that if and when you read this, if and when you are in a position where it seems that you’re not working with Meraki anymore, this could work as a reinforcement, perhaps an aversive one.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Height of Oppression</title><link href="/The-Height-of-Oppression" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Height of Oppression" /><published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Height-of-Oppression</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Height-of-Oppression">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Heels are most often associated with femininity, and as a result, generally imposed on women for the sake of keeping up with the imagery. Multiple versions of the heel have been invented, such as pumps, stilettos, kitten heels and many more, and it is expected of women to wear heels to most places outside of the casual settings – their workspaces, fashion runways and extending, but not limited, to parties of differing natures. Multiple ceremonies and awards functions have a requirement that women must wear heels, the Cannes Film Festival in France is one of the biggest examples of this; one of their rules regarding the dress code stipulates that all women attendees must wear high heels in order to attend the ever so prestigious film festival. Over the years, several women celebrities have been stopped from attending the film festival for not wearing high heels. Not only such events but many companies, office places and restaurants require female employees to wear heels. There have been several instances of discrimination against women for their refusal to wear heels. For example, one such case of discrimination occurred when Nicola Thorp was fired by her manager for refusing to wear heels on her first day of work at an office job in London back in 2016. She was dressed in a suit and a pair of formal shoes. Shortly after she was fired, Thorp gained worldwide support for challenging the manager by filing a petition. The government concurred and felt that she had been discriminated against for not wearing heels, which is unlawful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Wearing heels has become common in this day and age, it is expected of women to wear exhaustingly high heels everywhere. But there is a question that arises, how much of this expectation to wear heels for formal occasions is justified? It is evident that women must have the freedom of choice to wear whichever footwear or clothing they feel most comfortable in. If a woman feels most comfortable while wearing heels, then that is a fully valid choice. But even in these progressive times, it is men who enjoy the very same freedom, i.e. the freedom of controlling what a woman has to wear in most situations. Most women do not expressly enjoy wearing heels every single day, the same footwear which can become extremely painful for a person to wear for a mere few hours. Aside from giving women a sense of authority and power while wearing heels, there seem to be no other evident benefits or signs of comfort for a woman to wear the same. The question arises, why do women continue wearing heels despite all the negative aspects, and there being no apparent need to? The answer to this lies in the oppression of women, which ultimately stems from the system of patriarchy which is persistent in remaining pervasive in society. In order to truly understand the reasons though, we must look at the history of the ‘heel,’ and the shift in society’s perspective regarding it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The history of heels can be traced back to the 3,500 BCE; where it was mostly the nobility who wore heels, as opposed to the common people who roamed around barefoot. Heels were also used for practical purposes, such as by butchers to ensure their feet did not come in contact with the blood or the meat of the animal. Heels were later on adopted by the Greeks and Romans to display the differences between different social classes, it is suggested that men belonging to the Middle East – who wore heels during wars while riding horses in order to get a better grip while shooting arrows – brought the concept of heels to Europe. Thus, European aristocracy soon thereafter realised that heels served a practical purpose of keeping their feet out of the mud. After all, it was mostly the higher classes who cared about protecting their feet from mud or dirt as a means to distinguish themselves from the lower classes whilst also serving a useful purpose at the same time. Both men and women had begun wearing heels around this time. Soon after the ‘chopines’ emerged, they were the first instance of platform heels that were invented. They were famous for being severely uncomfortable and hard to walk in, and often required the assistance of several men to help in walking. The chopines were the first heels that were specifically designed for women, but many feminists argue that they were invented to limit the movement of women and to ensure they do not leave their households as much. In addition to this, it became common practice to force Chinese concubines and Turkish odalisques to wear chopines in order to ensure that they would not flee. The very first example of men using heels to control the movement or freedom of women can be seen here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up and until the 17th century, heels were most commonly worn by men. In the 18th century, however, when the idea of imperialism had started to spread around the world, men started to abandon heels. By the 19th century, heels went on to be recognised as something inherently feminine. Post the Second World War, Christian Dior came up with ‘stilettos,’ in which he used steel rods, raising the height of the heels to three inches or more. Since then, a multitude of designers such as Manolo Blahnik, Jimmy Choo, Alexander Mcqueen, and Christian Louboutin have invented different versions of the heel – all men designers scrambled to create a more elevated and much more impractical version of the heel. Designers who are known for creating quality heels usually happen to be men; the irony of men creating such footwear meant especially for women cannot go unnoticed. High heels are known and are proven to be harmful for a woman’s posture and feet, yet there is a persistent buildup of undue pressure on women to continue wearing heels. Christian Louboutin, when asked to comment upon the fact that heels are uncomfortable to walk in and slow a woman down, said, “&lt;em&gt;What is the point of wanting to run?&lt;/em&gt;” he continued, “&lt;em&gt;I am all for the pace getting slower, and high heels are very good for that.&lt;/em&gt;” That's right, ‘no point of women moving at a fast pace in a man’s world’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to a study conducted by the &lt;em&gt;American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society&lt;/em&gt;, 50% of women experience daily pain from wearing their heels. Heels often put pressure on not only the feet but also the back, spines, knees and toes. High and tightly worn heels also cause blisters for a lot. Aside from this, heels can cause a myriad of other long-term problems as well, such as nerve damage and sciatica. Still, a majority of women continue wearing heels – either by their own choice or otherwise. In most parties or companies, men only feel obligated to wear suits with formal shoes; whereas women feel obligated to wear a dress and high heels as it shows ‘professional etiquette’, and many times dressing professionally can be mistaken with dressing uncomfortably just to please others. Although, women choose to wear heels most of the time as it may hand them a sense of ‘power’ and ‘authority,’ (heels are treated with a sense of hyper feminisation) but in most cases, women feel the need to abide by the invisible aura of the social construct.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nowadays, due to the influence of the fashion industry that has capitalised off of the social construct created by the existence of heels for women, there is a shift or a transition in the way heels have started to be perceived by women in general - earlier, heels used to be treated as modes that were used by a very limited number of people whose usage of heels usually did not allow for free movement or allow for any comfort. Now, due to high-end designers coming up with more innovative heel designs and popularising the usage of heels, women perceive heels to be footwear that, when worn, can be empowering, bold, sexy and fashionable instead of simply being uncomfortable and constrictive.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Louboutin told Vogue, “&lt;em&gt;It's almost three people who are different in terms of character. I never forget that shoes also have to please men. As a man, I totally understand looking at a girl and saying, “Darling, we're having dinner together tonight, so do you mind to change?” I understand that type of mentality from a man who loves his wife, his woman. He's concerned about the way you look. It's not an ugly thing. I understand also that a woman could not care. I like my design to please women, but also to please men.&lt;/em&gt;”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His own words make it sound like women are meant to wear heels for ‘the male gaze,’ which seems to be the only somewhat reasonable explanation behind a woman wearing heels. This can be interpreted as women not having to be overly concerned with the way they look while wearing heels, it only matters as long as a man likes what his wife or girlfriend might be wearing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has become extremely normal to see women wearing extremely high heels in their everyday lives – no matter how unbearable it may be to walk in them. There will most likely not be any shift in society regarding the same, women will continue wearing heels for a long time. What can be normalised though, is ensuring that women need not feel as though they need to adhere to a certain set of expectations from society. The shift from heels being used mostly by men to then being used solely by women is a drastic one; and before we all start feminising heels to such a large extent, we must remember where they originated from and which of the two sexes wore them in the beginning, and also helped in popularising them all around the world. Heels have had a sexist and controlling past, traces of which can be seen in today’s time as well. One can only hope that fashion does not aid in the widening of the gap between men and women. At the end of the day, we must remember that gendered clothing and footwear are not defined by which sex dons the piece the most, but it is defined by how people aside from that specific gender view it. Heels can be worn by any sex or gender, but it happens to be attached to femininity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pooja Bommareddy</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Heels are most often associated with femininity, and as a result, generally imposed on women for the sake of keeping up with the imagery. Multiple versions of the heel have been invented, such as pumps, stilettos, kitten heels and many more, and it is expected of women to wear heels to most places outside of the casual settings – their workspaces, fashion runways and extending, but not limited, to parties of differing natures. Multiple ceremonies and awards functions have a requirement that women must wear heels, the Cannes Film Festival in France is one of the biggest examples of this; one of their rules regarding the dress code stipulates that all women attendees must wear high heels in order to attend the ever so prestigious film festival. Over the years, several women celebrities have been stopped from attending the film festival for not wearing high heels. Not only such events but many companies, office places and restaurants require female employees to wear heels. There have been several instances of discrimination against women for their refusal to wear heels. For example, one such case of discrimination occurred when Nicola Thorp was fired by her manager for refusing to wear heels on her first day of work at an office job in London back in 2016. She was dressed in a suit and a pair of formal shoes. Shortly after she was fired, Thorp gained worldwide support for challenging the manager by filing a petition. The government concurred and felt that she had been discriminated against for not wearing heels, which is unlawful. Wearing heels has become common in this day and age, it is expected of women to wear exhaustingly high heels everywhere. But there is a question that arises, how much of this expectation to wear heels for formal occasions is justified? It is evident that women must have the freedom of choice to wear whichever footwear or clothing they feel most comfortable in. If a woman feels most comfortable while wearing heels, then that is a fully valid choice. But even in these progressive times, it is men who enjoy the very same freedom, i.e. the freedom of controlling what a woman has to wear in most situations. Most women do not expressly enjoy wearing heels every single day, the same footwear which can become extremely painful for a person to wear for a mere few hours. Aside from giving women a sense of authority and power while wearing heels, there seem to be no other evident benefits or signs of comfort for a woman to wear the same. The question arises, why do women continue wearing heels despite all the negative aspects, and there being no apparent need to? The answer to this lies in the oppression of women, which ultimately stems from the system of patriarchy which is persistent in remaining pervasive in society. In order to truly understand the reasons though, we must look at the history of the ‘heel,’ and the shift in society’s perspective regarding it.&amp;nbsp; The history of heels can be traced back to the 3,500 BCE; where it was mostly the nobility who wore heels, as opposed to the common people who roamed around barefoot. Heels were also used for practical purposes, such as by butchers to ensure their feet did not come in contact with the blood or the meat of the animal. Heels were later on adopted by the Greeks and Romans to display the differences between different social classes, it is suggested that men belonging to the Middle East – who wore heels during wars while riding horses in order to get a better grip while shooting arrows – brought the concept of heels to Europe. Thus, European aristocracy soon thereafter realised that heels served a practical purpose of keeping their feet out of the mud. After all, it was mostly the higher classes who cared about protecting their feet from mud or dirt as a means to distinguish themselves from the lower classes whilst also serving a useful purpose at the same time. Both men and women had begun wearing heels around this time. Soon after the ‘chopines’ emerged, they were the first instance of platform heels that were invented. They were famous for being severely uncomfortable and hard to walk in, and often required the assistance of several men to help in walking. The chopines were the first heels that were specifically designed for women, but many feminists argue that they were invented to limit the movement of women and to ensure they do not leave their households as much. In addition to this, it became common practice to force Chinese concubines and Turkish odalisques to wear chopines in order to ensure that they would not flee. The very first example of men using heels to control the movement or freedom of women can be seen here.&amp;nbsp; Up and until the 17th century, heels were most commonly worn by men. In the 18th century, however, when the idea of imperialism had started to spread around the world, men started to abandon heels. By the 19th century, heels went on to be recognised as something inherently feminine. Post the Second World War, Christian Dior came up with ‘stilettos,’ in which he used steel rods, raising the height of the heels to three inches or more. Since then, a multitude of designers such as Manolo Blahnik, Jimmy Choo, Alexander Mcqueen, and Christian Louboutin have invented different versions of the heel – all men designers scrambled to create a more elevated and much more impractical version of the heel. Designers who are known for creating quality heels usually happen to be men; the irony of men creating such footwear meant especially for women cannot go unnoticed. High heels are known and are proven to be harmful for a woman’s posture and feet, yet there is a persistent buildup of undue pressure on women to continue wearing heels. Christian Louboutin, when asked to comment upon the fact that heels are uncomfortable to walk in and slow a woman down, said, “What is the point of wanting to run?” he continued, “I am all for the pace getting slower, and high heels are very good for that.” That's right, ‘no point of women moving at a fast pace in a man’s world’. According to a study conducted by the American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society, 50% of women experience daily pain from wearing their heels. Heels often put pressure on not only the feet but also the back, spines, knees and toes. High and tightly worn heels also cause blisters for a lot. Aside from this, heels can cause a myriad of other long-term problems as well, such as nerve damage and sciatica. Still, a majority of women continue wearing heels – either by their own choice or otherwise. In most parties or companies, men only feel obligated to wear suits with formal shoes; whereas women feel obligated to wear a dress and high heels as it shows ‘professional etiquette’, and many times dressing professionally can be mistaken with dressing uncomfortably just to please others. Although, women choose to wear heels most of the time as it may hand them a sense of ‘power’ and ‘authority,’ (heels are treated with a sense of hyper feminisation) but in most cases, women feel the need to abide by the invisible aura of the social construct.&amp;nbsp; Nowadays, due to the influence of the fashion industry that has capitalised off of the social construct created by the existence of heels for women, there is a shift or a transition in the way heels have started to be perceived by women in general - earlier, heels used to be treated as modes that were used by a very limited number of people whose usage of heels usually did not allow for free movement or allow for any comfort. Now, due to high-end designers coming up with more innovative heel designs and popularising the usage of heels, women perceive heels to be footwear that, when worn, can be empowering, bold, sexy and fashionable instead of simply being uncomfortable and constrictive.&amp;nbsp; In 2013, Louboutin told Vogue, “It's almost three people who are different in terms of character. I never forget that shoes also have to please men. As a man, I totally understand looking at a girl and saying, “Darling, we're having dinner together tonight, so do you mind to change?” I understand that type of mentality from a man who loves his wife, his woman. He's concerned about the way you look. It's not an ugly thing. I understand also that a woman could not care. I like my design to please women, but also to please men.”&amp;nbsp; His own words make it sound like women are meant to wear heels for ‘the male gaze,’ which seems to be the only somewhat reasonable explanation behind a woman wearing heels. This can be interpreted as women not having to be overly concerned with the way they look while wearing heels, it only matters as long as a man likes what his wife or girlfriend might be wearing.&amp;nbsp; It has become extremely normal to see women wearing extremely high heels in their everyday lives – no matter how unbearable it may be to walk in them. There will most likely not be any shift in society regarding the same, women will continue wearing heels for a long time. What can be normalised though, is ensuring that women need not feel as though they need to adhere to a certain set of expectations from society. The shift from heels being used mostly by men to then being used solely by women is a drastic one; and before we all start feminising heels to such a large extent, we must remember where they originated from and which of the two sexes wore them in the beginning, and also helped in popularising them all around the world. Heels have had a sexist and controlling past, traces of which can be seen in today’s time as well. One can only hope that fashion does not aid in the widening of the gap between men and women. At the end of the day, we must remember that gendered clothing and footwear are not defined by which sex dons the piece the most, but it is defined by how people aside from that specific gender view it. Heels can be worn by any sex or gender, but it happens to be attached to femininity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Portrait of a Nation at War with Itself</title><link href="/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portrait of a Nation at War with Itself" /><published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;It has been like watching a train crash in slow motion.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Dino Mahtani, International Crisis Group, commenting upon the Ethiopian crisis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethiopia’s Federal Army is waging a war against the Tigray forces or more specifically the Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF). The grounds for this war lie in the accusation that the Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed &lt;em&gt;“has been trying to sideline.... and even criminalise”&lt;/em&gt; the TPLF. At the core of this predicament lies the nation of Eritrea, Ethiopia's northern neighbour sharing its border with the Tigray region. The Ethiopian Federal government has declared this unexpected war upon its Northern state which puts the stability of one of the world's most strategically important regions, Horn of Africa. This confrontation has prompted thousands of Ethiopians, who are no strangers to humanitarian disasters, to flee to Sudan in thousands. Axel Bisschop, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) representative in Sudan has estimated the figure to be at over 20,000 people, more than half of them constitute children. This might result in resource wars between the already existing refugees in Sudan and the newcomers. The ethnic groups are caught in the midst of a crossfire between the federal government aiming to secure a united Ethiopia and the Tigray rebels guarding their individual sovereignty. However, the culmination of the issues which has reached a tipping point is the outcome of a process and not a knee jerk reaction by the two ends of the spectrum. The roots of the present fragility are important to understand the reasons for the severity of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long Story Short&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The national governments of Ethiopia and Eritrea have been at loggerheads for decades. The fallouts included the Eritrean and Ethiopian War which began in May 1998 and ended in June 2000. The current Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad won the 2019 Nobel Peace Prize for successfully implementing the peace treaty between the two nations. The cause for the war may be understood as Eritrea breaking the international law and invading Eritrea and holding all the disputed territory and advancing into Eritrea. At the end of the war, the Eritrea-Ethiopia Boundary Commission, a UN body declared Badme, the disputed territory to Eritrean land. The internal dispute between the Federal government and the Tigrays which has pushed Africa's second most populous nation into the brink of a civil war too has its origins in the 1970’s. Tigray is located in the northernmost region of Ethiopia. Their total population is estimated to be at 110 million, constituting 6% of the Ethiopian population. They have been at the forefront of the struggle against the military dictatorship that ruled Ethiopia in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. The TPLF established itself as the leader of the coalition named as the Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) grasped power in the nation in 1991. A Tigrayan, Meles Zenawi, led Ethiopia in the years between 1991 and 2012. This period was marked by economic stability and regional prosperity in Northern Africa, albeit with a generous dose of repressing all political opposition. Abiy Ahmad, of the Oromo ethnicity, came to power riding on the tide of anti-government protests in 2018. Worst was yet to befall upon this community. Scores of Tigray’s were arrested in connection to corruption and security related crackdowns, removed from the positions of political authority. One of them was Getachew Asefa, who had evaded arrest and fled to Tigray, he continues to be a fugitive. This widened the gulf between the inhabitants of the Tigray region governed by TPLF and the federal government. This came after Abiy's proclamation that he aims at uniting the country by reducing the autonomy of the regional governments. It didn't sit well with the Tigray’s and invited resistance to this centralisation scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Current Military Offensive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abiy Ahmad dissolved the ruling coalition to form his new political party and has postponed the national elections which had been scheduled for August 2020 under the pretext of the coronavirus pandemic. However, in violation of the orders from Addis Ababa, Tigray held elections. This led to rapid deterioration of the status quo. Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad announced a military offensive after accusing the Tigrayan forces of attacking and seizing a military base in the regional capital of Mekelle on November 4, 2020. The Tigrayans have completely denied the accusation. Both governments now perceive each other as “illegitimate and unconstitutional”. In the first week of October, the Ethiopian federal government decided to sever ties with the Tigray region. The Upper house of Parliament voted to suspend budget aid to this region. The TPLF returned the “favour” by citing an article in the federal constitution that ensured “unconditional right to self-determination, including the right to secession”. The TPLF also resented the Prime Minister's “unprincipled” friendship with the Eritrean President Isais Afwerki as well as the 2018 peace agreement. It is no longer a domestic turmoil within the confines of Ethiopia as the current status of Badme remains unresolved, which is an improbability without the Ethiopian government’s cooperation in Tigray. The telecommunication network in Tigray has been cut, and airstrikes and ground offensives precede the involvement of constituencies of the neighbouring Amhara region. This raging battle involves the TPLF, who are often regarded as one of the best-armed forces led by experienced generals and hold the capacity to deflect equipment from the grip of the Northern Command. The paramilitary and a local militia are estimated to consist of about 250,000 troops. Abiy had plainly accused the Tigrayan leaders of committing “criminal hubris and intransigence”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is There a Civil War in Sight?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest update to spill out of the borders is that Abiy Ahmed had proclaimed on November 15, 2020, that his federal forces had captured another town in the northern Tigray region. This comes after two weeks of fighting. Alberta lies in the control of the federal government. The end of this bloody civil war, many observers predict, may result in the secession of a united Ethiopia. Considering that both sides are evenly matched, the increase in the involvement of&amp;nbsp; Ethiopia’s neighbours, regional partners, and international actors- an escalation would not be a surprise. Though the Eritrean Foreign Minister, Osman Saleh Mohammed had rejected claims of Eritrean involvement, terming the issue as an internal conflict. Concerns remain about the refugee influx into Sudan. The humanitarian concern can be justified when one studies the impact of the war upon the regional capital Mekelle, which houses half a million people. Power and water have been cut. 150,000 soldiers have been forcefully taken over or defected to the Tigrayan side. War crimes include the gruesome killing of hundreds of citizens- slashed by machetes in the town of Mai-Kendra on November 9, 2020. Sudan too has its own skeletons in the cupboard. The Sudanese government was responsible for the Darfur genocide in 2003, which in turn led to a forced displacement of 2.4 million Sudanese. Sudan too can be a perilous nation for the refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic hardships are on the rise, furthered by COVID-19. Banking services have halted thereby resulting in a lack of cash. A refugee from war-torn Ethiopia, with an uncertain future, has perhaps best articulated the tale of a nation at war with itself- “&lt;em&gt;We are in need of everything- food, fresh water, masks. Everything.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize a year before now stands at the risk of being remembered as a man who slashed civilians in his ardour to relinquish the ethnic dissenters. Irony much?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“It has been like watching a train crash in slow motion.&quot; -Dino Mahtani, International Crisis Group, commenting upon the Ethiopian crisis Ethiopia’s Federal Army is waging a war against the Tigray forces or more specifically the Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF). The grounds for this war lie in the accusation that the Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed “has been trying to sideline.... and even criminalise” the TPLF. At the core of this predicament lies the nation of Eritrea, Ethiopia's northern neighbour sharing its border with the Tigray region. The Ethiopian Federal government has declared this unexpected war upon its Northern state which puts the stability of one of the world's most strategically important regions, Horn of Africa. This confrontation has prompted thousands of Ethiopians, who are no strangers to humanitarian disasters, to flee to Sudan in thousands. Axel Bisschop, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) representative in Sudan has estimated the figure to be at over 20,000 people, more than half of them constitute children. This might result in resource wars between the already existing refugees in Sudan and the newcomers. The ethnic groups are caught in the midst of a crossfire between the federal government aiming to secure a united Ethiopia and the Tigray rebels guarding their individual sovereignty. However, the culmination of the issues which has reached a tipping point is the outcome of a process and not a knee jerk reaction by the two ends of the spectrum. The roots of the present fragility are important to understand the reasons for the severity of the crisis. Long Story Short The national governments of Ethiopia and Eritrea have been at loggerheads for decades. The fallouts included the Eritrean and Ethiopian War which began in May 1998 and ended in June 2000. The current Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad won the 2019 Nobel Peace Prize for successfully implementing the peace treaty between the two nations. The cause for the war may be understood as Eritrea breaking the international law and invading Eritrea and holding all the disputed territory and advancing into Eritrea. At the end of the war, the Eritrea-Ethiopia Boundary Commission, a UN body declared Badme, the disputed territory to Eritrean land. The internal dispute between the Federal government and the Tigrays which has pushed Africa's second most populous nation into the brink of a civil war too has its origins in the 1970’s. Tigray is located in the northernmost region of Ethiopia. Their total population is estimated to be at 110 million, constituting 6% of the Ethiopian population. They have been at the forefront of the struggle against the military dictatorship that ruled Ethiopia in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. The TPLF established itself as the leader of the coalition named as the Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) grasped power in the nation in 1991. A Tigrayan, Meles Zenawi, led Ethiopia in the years between 1991 and 2012. This period was marked by economic stability and regional prosperity in Northern Africa, albeit with a generous dose of repressing all political opposition. Abiy Ahmad, of the Oromo ethnicity, came to power riding on the tide of anti-government protests in 2018. Worst was yet to befall upon this community. Scores of Tigray’s were arrested in connection to corruption and security related crackdowns, removed from the positions of political authority. One of them was Getachew Asefa, who had evaded arrest and fled to Tigray, he continues to be a fugitive. This widened the gulf between the inhabitants of the Tigray region governed by TPLF and the federal government. This came after Abiy's proclamation that he aims at uniting the country by reducing the autonomy of the regional governments. It didn't sit well with the Tigray’s and invited resistance to this centralisation scheme. The Current Military Offensive Abiy Ahmad dissolved the ruling coalition to form his new political party and has postponed the national elections which had been scheduled for August 2020 under the pretext of the coronavirus pandemic. However, in violation of the orders from Addis Ababa, Tigray held elections. This led to rapid deterioration of the status quo. Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad announced a military offensive after accusing the Tigrayan forces of attacking and seizing a military base in the regional capital of Mekelle on November 4, 2020. The Tigrayans have completely denied the accusation. Both governments now perceive each other as “illegitimate and unconstitutional”. In the first week of October, the Ethiopian federal government decided to sever ties with the Tigray region. The Upper house of Parliament voted to suspend budget aid to this region. The TPLF returned the “favour” by citing an article in the federal constitution that ensured “unconditional right to self-determination, including the right to secession”. The TPLF also resented the Prime Minister's “unprincipled” friendship with the Eritrean President Isais Afwerki as well as the 2018 peace agreement. It is no longer a domestic turmoil within the confines of Ethiopia as the current status of Badme remains unresolved, which is an improbability without the Ethiopian government’s cooperation in Tigray. The telecommunication network in Tigray has been cut, and airstrikes and ground offensives precede the involvement of constituencies of the neighbouring Amhara region. This raging battle involves the TPLF, who are often regarded as one of the best-armed forces led by experienced generals and hold the capacity to deflect equipment from the grip of the Northern Command. The paramilitary and a local militia are estimated to consist of about 250,000 troops. Abiy had plainly accused the Tigrayan leaders of committing “criminal hubris and intransigence”. Is There a Civil War in Sight? The latest update to spill out of the borders is that Abiy Ahmed had proclaimed on November 15, 2020, that his federal forces had captured another town in the northern Tigray region. This comes after two weeks of fighting. Alberta lies in the control of the federal government. The end of this bloody civil war, many observers predict, may result in the secession of a united Ethiopia. Considering that both sides are evenly matched, the increase in the involvement of&amp;nbsp; Ethiopia’s neighbours, regional partners, and international actors- an escalation would not be a surprise. Though the Eritrean Foreign Minister, Osman Saleh Mohammed had rejected claims of Eritrean involvement, terming the issue as an internal conflict. Concerns remain about the refugee influx into Sudan. The humanitarian concern can be justified when one studies the impact of the war upon the regional capital Mekelle, which houses half a million people. Power and water have been cut. 150,000 soldiers have been forcefully taken over or defected to the Tigrayan side. War crimes include the gruesome killing of hundreds of citizens- slashed by machetes in the town of Mai-Kendra on November 9, 2020. Sudan too has its own skeletons in the cupboard. The Sudanese government was responsible for the Darfur genocide in 2003, which in turn led to a forced displacement of 2.4 million Sudanese. Sudan too can be a perilous nation for the refugees. Economic hardships are on the rise, furthered by COVID-19. Banking services have halted thereby resulting in a lack of cash. A refugee from war-torn Ethiopia, with an uncertain future, has perhaps best articulated the tale of a nation at war with itself- “We are in need of everything- food, fresh water, masks. Everything.” The man who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize a year before now stands at the risk of being remembered as a man who slashed civilians in his ardour to relinquish the ethnic dissenters. Irony much?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are Economists Evolving to be Engineers?</title><link href="/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Economists Evolving to be Engineers?" /><published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers">&lt;p&gt;The opening match of the Indian Premier League 2020 was viewed by over 200 million people. A record-breaking viewership figure for the opening-day of a sports event in any country. This shows the buzz among viewers for this annually conducted India-based event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes the show more breathtaking is the custom of the auction of players that takes place months prior to the final episode. Cricket admirers would also be aware of the most tragic bids of cricket history. Recall Tymal Mills, one of the players auctioned, was one of the most expensive purchases of season 10. Consequently, he struggled to find a purchaser in the following season because of his disappointing performance in the former season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did the team pay an exorbitantly high sum of ₹120 million for such a player? What could be the reason behind the faulty valuation of Tymal Mills? The truth is that such glitches and miscalculations in auctions are not uncommon as the modern form of auctions is not just restricted to the disposal of a bankrupt’s property. It is a lot more than that. Auctioning telecom spectrums, oil wells, airport landing slots - it is indeed a mind boggling process. And a solution to such a process fetched the Nobel Prize 2020 for economics to Paul R Milgrom and Robert B Wilson. These researchers tried to evaluate the outcomes of different rules of bidding and final prices and devised a framework “&lt;em&gt;for improvements to auction theory and invention of new auction formats.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story dates back to the times when the telecom spectrum was sold to companies in the form of beauty contests. Basically, the one with the best plan was the winner. However, it was subject to lobbying. Approaches like political markets and lotteries were also adopted though both of these approaches were biased and led to unjustified distribution. As a resort, in 1994, the laureates introduced ‘simultaneous multiple round auctions’ for radio spectrum sale. This arrangement helped governments to sell the commodity rights at a competitive price - a price not too trivial which could result in losses and not too high. It ultimately helped the sellers find the buyer who values his product most. This format initially adopted by the USA’s Federal Communications Commission (FCC) is now used throughout the world for the allocation of natural resources.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auction theory sounds simple considering that the buyer’s motive is to be able to purchase something at the lowest possible price. Economists also try their hands at game theory to find out all the predictions that could be made by bidders before quoting a price. However, in real life auctions, this prognosis won’t be a smooth ride. As bidders with little information available about the product struggle to find out its worth. At the same time, sellers face problems executing the sale of a bunch of items at the same time. They have to protect the auction from purchasers who might collaborate amongst themselves behind the scenes hence hampering the dignity of the auction. The auction theory of these Stanford University-affiliated economists aided in implementing the sale of complex goods. Their thesis is based on the following three factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;They explained how rules of auction affect the behaviour of bidders and revenues brought in for sellers hence defying the ‘revenue equivalence theorem’. Are the bids open or closed? How many times can a participant bid? What amount shall the winner be liable to pay? All such statutes cause changes in the bidders’ attitude. The most suitable example of such a situation was quoted in a case study by &lt;em&gt;The Hindu&lt;/em&gt; which narrated a spectrum auction of New Zealand which took place in 1990. The auction was a Vickrey auction. Here, the winner was liable to pay the second-highest bid. Due to this, a company that actually bid NZ$100,000 ultimately ended up paying just NZ$6. Hence a difference in guidelines brought a major transformation in the amount the seller would have earned if the rules were slightly different.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The commodity or service that is being put to sale. The circumstances of a painting being auctioned shall enormously vary from telecom auctions.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What are the uncertainties involved in the sale? What is the information available to a bidder about the product? A bidder is aware of the royal history of a mansion might view it differently from one unaware of it.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilson, according to the prize committee devised that the auction of objects with a common value which is uncertain earlier becomes common for everyone at the end and that winners should bid below the common value of a product to eschew the winner’s curse. For a more extensive understanding let’s find out what is this common value, private value, and the winner’s curse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winner’s curse refers to a situation when the intrinsic value of a product is lower than its estimated value. This is a phenomenon that usually arises when bidders have no way of evaluating the exact intrinsic value of a product and offer a price as per their own assessment of the object. As happened in the case of Tymal Mills stated above - the team overestimated the performance of this player ending up winning the bid but losing the game. The winner is usually the one with the most optimistic estimation of the product while he may later realise that valuation by him was way higher in comparison to other bidders. This paradox was quoted by the 2017 Economics Nobel prize winner, Richard Thaler in &lt;em&gt;Misbehaving: The making of behavioural economics&lt;/em&gt; as “&lt;em&gt;When many bidders compete for the same object, the winner of the auction is often the bidder who most overvalues the product being sold&lt;/em&gt;”. This phenomenon even poses a question to the hypothesis of efficient markets. If the markets would have been efficient then there wouldn’t be such variation in the valuation by different bidders as all shall possess symmetric information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another deciding factor for the price is the private value of the commodity. It is an individual’s outlook towards a product based on the personal information he possesses. For instance, in the auction of a painting, the private value of that art shall be the pleasure that the bidder is seeking from it for his own sake. However, when he would like to sell that painting in the future then what shall matter to him is the common value which is based on what others think will be the possible price. It is due to the private value of an object that bidders might have massive variations in their bids depending on their own circumstances. For instance, a company with an ability to sell oil at higher prices or process it at a lower price might be ready to bid higher for crude oil.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering this, Wilson studied the buyers who overpaid for US oil leases in the 1970's and earned lower returns due to the winner’s curse. He argued that the most rational approach is to place a bid below the perceived common value of resources. Milgrom nonetheless focused on a more general theory of auction and analysed different bidding strategies in a plethora of auction formats and concluded that it shall be the most profitable deal for the seller when they share more information with potential buyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, these laureates have made a major contribution to society by devising a theory that has practical engineering applications. This new auction format is a more sorted approach to sell complex goods and is a well-designed system for both private and public sellers to design their auctions proficiently. With this theory, the researchers advocate that like physics and chemistry, economic theories can also create useful technologies for both companies and the government. This even justifies how economists who earlier only acted as advisors to government now play an indispensable role in corporate companies too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pragati Agrawal</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The opening match of the Indian Premier League 2020 was viewed by over 200 million people. A record-breaking viewership figure for the opening-day of a sports event in any country. This shows the buzz among viewers for this annually conducted India-based event. What makes the show more breathtaking is the custom of the auction of players that takes place months prior to the final episode. Cricket admirers would also be aware of the most tragic bids of cricket history. Recall Tymal Mills, one of the players auctioned, was one of the most expensive purchases of season 10. Consequently, he struggled to find a purchaser in the following season because of his disappointing performance in the former season. So why did the team pay an exorbitantly high sum of ₹120 million for such a player? What could be the reason behind the faulty valuation of Tymal Mills? The truth is that such glitches and miscalculations in auctions are not uncommon as the modern form of auctions is not just restricted to the disposal of a bankrupt’s property. It is a lot more than that. Auctioning telecom spectrums, oil wells, airport landing slots - it is indeed a mind boggling process. And a solution to such a process fetched the Nobel Prize 2020 for economics to Paul R Milgrom and Robert B Wilson. These researchers tried to evaluate the outcomes of different rules of bidding and final prices and devised a framework “for improvements to auction theory and invention of new auction formats.” The story dates back to the times when the telecom spectrum was sold to companies in the form of beauty contests. Basically, the one with the best plan was the winner. However, it was subject to lobbying. Approaches like political markets and lotteries were also adopted though both of these approaches were biased and led to unjustified distribution. As a resort, in 1994, the laureates introduced ‘simultaneous multiple round auctions’ for radio spectrum sale. This arrangement helped governments to sell the commodity rights at a competitive price - a price not too trivial which could result in losses and not too high. It ultimately helped the sellers find the buyer who values his product most. This format initially adopted by the USA’s Federal Communications Commission (FCC) is now used throughout the world for the allocation of natural resources.&amp;nbsp; Auction theory sounds simple considering that the buyer’s motive is to be able to purchase something at the lowest possible price. Economists also try their hands at game theory to find out all the predictions that could be made by bidders before quoting a price. However, in real life auctions, this prognosis won’t be a smooth ride. As bidders with little information available about the product struggle to find out its worth. At the same time, sellers face problems executing the sale of a bunch of items at the same time. They have to protect the auction from purchasers who might collaborate amongst themselves behind the scenes hence hampering the dignity of the auction. The auction theory of these Stanford University-affiliated economists aided in implementing the sale of complex goods. Their thesis is based on the following three factors: They explained how rules of auction affect the behaviour of bidders and revenues brought in for sellers hence defying the ‘revenue equivalence theorem’. Are the bids open or closed? How many times can a participant bid? What amount shall the winner be liable to pay? All such statutes cause changes in the bidders’ attitude. The most suitable example of such a situation was quoted in a case study by The Hindu which narrated a spectrum auction of New Zealand which took place in 1990. The auction was a Vickrey auction. Here, the winner was liable to pay the second-highest bid. Due to this, a company that actually bid NZ$100,000 ultimately ended up paying just NZ$6. Hence a difference in guidelines brought a major transformation in the amount the seller would have earned if the rules were slightly different.The commodity or service that is being put to sale. The circumstances of a painting being auctioned shall enormously vary from telecom auctions.What are the uncertainties involved in the sale? What is the information available to a bidder about the product? A bidder is aware of the royal history of a mansion might view it differently from one unaware of it. Wilson, according to the prize committee devised that the auction of objects with a common value which is uncertain earlier becomes common for everyone at the end and that winners should bid below the common value of a product to eschew the winner’s curse. For a more extensive understanding let’s find out what is this common value, private value, and the winner’s curse.&amp;nbsp; Winner’s curse refers to a situation when the intrinsic value of a product is lower than its estimated value. This is a phenomenon that usually arises when bidders have no way of evaluating the exact intrinsic value of a product and offer a price as per their own assessment of the object. As happened in the case of Tymal Mills stated above - the team overestimated the performance of this player ending up winning the bid but losing the game. The winner is usually the one with the most optimistic estimation of the product while he may later realise that valuation by him was way higher in comparison to other bidders. This paradox was quoted by the 2017 Economics Nobel prize winner, Richard Thaler in Misbehaving: The making of behavioural economics as “When many bidders compete for the same object, the winner of the auction is often the bidder who most overvalues the product being sold”. This phenomenon even poses a question to the hypothesis of efficient markets. If the markets would have been efficient then there wouldn’t be such variation in the valuation by different bidders as all shall possess symmetric information.&amp;nbsp; Another deciding factor for the price is the private value of the commodity. It is an individual’s outlook towards a product based on the personal information he possesses. For instance, in the auction of a painting, the private value of that art shall be the pleasure that the bidder is seeking from it for his own sake. However, when he would like to sell that painting in the future then what shall matter to him is the common value which is based on what others think will be the possible price. It is due to the private value of an object that bidders might have massive variations in their bids depending on their own circumstances. For instance, a company with an ability to sell oil at higher prices or process it at a lower price might be ready to bid higher for crude oil.&amp;nbsp; Considering this, Wilson studied the buyers who overpaid for US oil leases in the 1970's and earned lower returns due to the winner’s curse. He argued that the most rational approach is to place a bid below the perceived common value of resources. Milgrom nonetheless focused on a more general theory of auction and analysed different bidding strategies in a plethora of auction formats and concluded that it shall be the most profitable deal for the seller when they share more information with potential buyers. Hence, these laureates have made a major contribution to society by devising a theory that has practical engineering applications. This new auction format is a more sorted approach to sell complex goods and is a well-designed system for both private and public sellers to design their auctions proficiently. With this theory, the researchers advocate that like physics and chemistry, economic theories can also create useful technologies for both companies and the government. This even justifies how economists who earlier only acted as advisors to government now play an indispensable role in corporate companies too.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Anecdote of Blocked-up Capital: The Code of Bilateral Netting and the Art of Simplification</title><link href="/An-Anecdote-of-Blocked-up-Capital" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Anecdote of Blocked-up Capital: The Code of Bilateral Netting and the Art of Simplification" /><published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/An-Anecdote-of-Blocked-up-Capital</id><content type="html" xml:base="/An-Anecdote-of-Blocked-up-Capital">&lt;p&gt;Here follows a conversation from one of the greatest books of the 20th century, &lt;em&gt;The Catcher in the Rye&lt;/em&gt; by JD Salinger:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man: One short, faintly stuffy, pedagogical question. Don't you think there's a time and place for everything? Don't you think if someone starts to tell you about his father's farm, he should stick to his guns, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; get around to telling you about his uncle's brace? &lt;em&gt;Or&lt;/em&gt;, if his uncle's brace is such a provocative subject, shouldn't he have selected it in the first place as his subject—not the farm?'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holden: “Yes—I don't know. I guess he should. I mean I guess he should've picked his uncle as a subject, instead of the farm, if that interested him most. But what I mean is, lots of time you don't &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what interests you most till you start talking about something that &lt;em&gt;doesn't&lt;/em&gt; interest you most. I mean you can't help it sometimes. You don't know my old teacher, Mr Vinson. He could drive you crazy sometimes, him and the goddamn class. I mean he'd keep telling you to &lt;em&gt;unify&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;simplify&lt;/em&gt; all the time. Some things you just can't &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;. I mean you can't hardly ever simplify and unify something just because somebody &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; you to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here’s the catch, this is the year of exceptional happenings, and so you wouldn’t be surprised if you found out that there has been an introduction of elements of unification &amp;amp; simplification in the way say, qualified financial transactions are carried out. Yes, I’m talking about the recent bill on Bilateral Netting, introduced by Indian Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman, after arguing that it would help big banks and other financial intermediaries to save costs and transact more efficiently. Puzzled? Let’s take it from the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Act&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Government of India on October 1, 2020, passed the Bilateral Netting of Qualified Financial Contracts Act, 2020. The Act promises to provide a regulatory framework for offsetting claims between two parties to a financial contract to determine a single net payment obligation due from one counterparty to the other. How does it have anything to do with what Mr Holden just concluded? Well, bilateral netting in very simple terms is a method of reducing credit, settlement, and other risks of financial contracts by unifying two or more obligations to achieve a more simplified reduced net obligation. As a result, bilateral netting reduces the number of overall transactions between the two counterparties, thereby reducing the actual volume of transactions, accounting activity, along with costs and fees associated with an increased number of trades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act covers bilateral contracts notified as Qualified Financial Contracts (QFCs) by a relevant authority such as Reserve Bank of India (RBI), Securities Exchange Board of India (SEBI), Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority of India (IRDAI), Pension Fund Regulatory and Development Authority (PFRDA), and International Financial Services Centres Authority (IFSCA). The QFC definition is very broad and includes any securities contract, commodity contract, forward contract, repurchase agreement, swap agreement, and any similar agreement that the aforementioned authorities determine by regulation, resolution, or order to be a QFC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that you are an investment trust and you own a $1 million corporate bond issued by a private housing firm. You think that there is a risk in the event the housing firm defaults on repayment, so you decide to buy a Credit Default Swap (CDS) worth $1 million from a hedge fund. You have agreed to pay interest on this credit default swap of say 5%, which amounts to $50,000 a year. If the housing firm defaults, you get the compensation equal to the value of the CDS from the hedge fund in exchange for the pre-decided interest amount. On the other hand, if the housing firm doesn’t default, you end up losing the interest amount, kind of like sunk cost. In either case, you hedge the loan amount against the risk of default. While you are at it, you need to set aside some amount depending upon the terms of the contract because the Central Bank mandates you to keep a fraction of the loan amount as a reserve to protect yourself in case the loan gets bad or subprime. The hedge fund will have to keep a certain percentage of the amount that it has promised to make good for the same reasons as you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine that the hedge fund that sold you CDS enters into a completely new qualified financial contract with you to downsize its risk on a different contract and you agree to invest in it because you think it can work out in your favour and you can end up earning a bounty. By law, you are both required (yet again) to keep aside a certain sum of money. The problem is, you may enter into a lot of swap agreements with the counterparty, and each that happens, you both block in a certain sum of money to honour your other commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you get the problem now? This act allows the parties to the qualified financial contracts to release the large amounts of locked-up capital in the banking system for the onward lending by employing a tool called “bilateral netting” which is nothing but offsetting the claims arising from dealings between the two parties to determine the net amount payable or receivable from one party to another. These QFCs take place directly between the two parties without involving any regulatory authority like SEBI or RBI; in finance, we call them Over-the-Counter (OTC) transactions. The thing about OTC transactions is that they are less transparent &amp;amp; are subject to fewer regulations, which increases the chances of default without any Clearinghouse in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while India allows netting of multilateral over-the-counter financial derivative contracts, the same wasn’t allowed for bilateral contracts until now. And to my surprise, as per RBI, the value of bi-lateral contracts as estimated by Clearing Corporation of India amounts to ₹5,633,257 crores as of March 2018. And if bilateral netting was made available in FY 2017-18, the banks could have freed up around 2.14 lakh crore till 2020 which could have been made available for lending. So, by introducing this act, not only banks get to reduce their regulatory capital burden, but it also enables a reduction in hedging costs and liquidity needs for banks, primary dealers, and other market-makers, thereby encouraging participation in the OTC derivatives market to hedge against risk, and the added bonus is better employment of the blocked-up capital. From that point of view, allowing netting of financial contracts is a very important milestone that will reduce the cost of market players who are consistently entering into contracts to hedge against risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilateral netting of QFCs is a common practice in economies like the USA, UK, Europe, Japan, etc. and has been proposed in India by the Ministry of Finance several times over the past few decades. Nirmala Sitharaman said that this particular legislation is extremely necessary for the stability of the financial market. Money locked up in banks is not available when the economy is starved for funds. This will enhance liquidity and the economy will get lubrication and I think we can all agree with that. This bill has been brought in to address the lessons learned from the 2008 global financial crisis; it took us a lot of time to get here, some might even say a worldwide pandemic and yet another global crisis, but we are here nonetheless, and it’s a win-win for everybody. Perhaps, we can &lt;em&gt;simplify &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;unify &lt;/em&gt;things, after all, just because somebody (here, the nation) wants us to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anjali Harjani</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Here follows a conversation from one of the greatest books of the 20th century, The Catcher in the Rye by JD Salinger: Man: One short, faintly stuffy, pedagogical question. Don't you think there's a time and place for everything? Don't you think if someone starts to tell you about his father's farm, he should stick to his guns, then get around to telling you about his uncle's brace? Or, if his uncle's brace is such a provocative subject, shouldn't he have selected it in the first place as his subject—not the farm?' Holden: “Yes—I don't know. I guess he should. I mean I guess he should've picked his uncle as a subject, instead of the farm, if that interested him most. But what I mean is, lots of time you don't know what interests you most till you start talking about something that doesn't interest you most. I mean you can't help it sometimes. You don't know my old teacher, Mr Vinson. He could drive you crazy sometimes, him and the goddamn class. I mean he'd keep telling you to unify and simplify all the time. Some things you just can't do. I mean you can't hardly ever simplify and unify something just because somebody wants you to.” But here’s the catch, this is the year of exceptional happenings, and so you wouldn’t be surprised if you found out that there has been an introduction of elements of unification &amp;amp; simplification in the way say, qualified financial transactions are carried out. Yes, I’m talking about the recent bill on Bilateral Netting, introduced by Indian Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman, after arguing that it would help big banks and other financial intermediaries to save costs and transact more efficiently. Puzzled? Let’s take it from the top. The Act The Government of India on October 1, 2020, passed the Bilateral Netting of Qualified Financial Contracts Act, 2020. The Act promises to provide a regulatory framework for offsetting claims between two parties to a financial contract to determine a single net payment obligation due from one counterparty to the other. How does it have anything to do with what Mr Holden just concluded? Well, bilateral netting in very simple terms is a method of reducing credit, settlement, and other risks of financial contracts by unifying two or more obligations to achieve a more simplified reduced net obligation. As a result, bilateral netting reduces the number of overall transactions between the two counterparties, thereby reducing the actual volume of transactions, accounting activity, along with costs and fees associated with an increased number of trades. The act covers bilateral contracts notified as Qualified Financial Contracts (QFCs) by a relevant authority such as Reserve Bank of India (RBI), Securities Exchange Board of India (SEBI), Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority of India (IRDAI), Pension Fund Regulatory and Development Authority (PFRDA), and International Financial Services Centres Authority (IFSCA). The QFC definition is very broad and includes any securities contract, commodity contract, forward contract, repurchase agreement, swap agreement, and any similar agreement that the aforementioned authorities determine by regulation, resolution, or order to be a QFC. Let’s assume that you are an investment trust and you own a $1 million corporate bond issued by a private housing firm. You think that there is a risk in the event the housing firm defaults on repayment, so you decide to buy a Credit Default Swap (CDS) worth $1 million from a hedge fund. You have agreed to pay interest on this credit default swap of say 5%, which amounts to $50,000 a year. If the housing firm defaults, you get the compensation equal to the value of the CDS from the hedge fund in exchange for the pre-decided interest amount. On the other hand, if the housing firm doesn’t default, you end up losing the interest amount, kind of like sunk cost. In either case, you hedge the loan amount against the risk of default. While you are at it, you need to set aside some amount depending upon the terms of the contract because the Central Bank mandates you to keep a fraction of the loan amount as a reserve to protect yourself in case the loan gets bad or subprime. The hedge fund will have to keep a certain percentage of the amount that it has promised to make good for the same reasons as you. Now, imagine that the hedge fund that sold you CDS enters into a completely new qualified financial contract with you to downsize its risk on a different contract and you agree to invest in it because you think it can work out in your favour and you can end up earning a bounty. By law, you are both required (yet again) to keep aside a certain sum of money. The problem is, you may enter into a lot of swap agreements with the counterparty, and each that happens, you both block in a certain sum of money to honour your other commitments. Do you get the problem now? This act allows the parties to the qualified financial contracts to release the large amounts of locked-up capital in the banking system for the onward lending by employing a tool called “bilateral netting” which is nothing but offsetting the claims arising from dealings between the two parties to determine the net amount payable or receivable from one party to another. These QFCs take place directly between the two parties without involving any regulatory authority like SEBI or RBI; in finance, we call them Over-the-Counter (OTC) transactions. The thing about OTC transactions is that they are less transparent &amp;amp; are subject to fewer regulations, which increases the chances of default without any Clearinghouse in action. And while India allows netting of multilateral over-the-counter financial derivative contracts, the same wasn’t allowed for bilateral contracts until now. And to my surprise, as per RBI, the value of bi-lateral contracts as estimated by Clearing Corporation of India amounts to ₹5,633,257 crores as of March 2018. And if bilateral netting was made available in FY 2017-18, the banks could have freed up around 2.14 lakh crore till 2020 which could have been made available for lending. So, by introducing this act, not only banks get to reduce their regulatory capital burden, but it also enables a reduction in hedging costs and liquidity needs for banks, primary dealers, and other market-makers, thereby encouraging participation in the OTC derivatives market to hedge against risk, and the added bonus is better employment of the blocked-up capital. From that point of view, allowing netting of financial contracts is a very important milestone that will reduce the cost of market players who are consistently entering into contracts to hedge against risk. Bilateral netting of QFCs is a common practice in economies like the USA, UK, Europe, Japan, etc. and has been proposed in India by the Ministry of Finance several times over the past few decades. Nirmala Sitharaman said that this particular legislation is extremely necessary for the stability of the financial market. Money locked up in banks is not available when the economy is starved for funds. This will enhance liquidity and the economy will get lubrication and I think we can all agree with that. This bill has been brought in to address the lessons learned from the 2008 global financial crisis; it took us a lot of time to get here, some might even say a worldwide pandemic and yet another global crisis, but we are here nonetheless, and it’s a win-win for everybody. Perhaps, we can simplify and unify things, after all, just because somebody (here, the nation) wants us to.</summary></entry></feed>