<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-11T22:04:37+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Indo-British Empire: How Indians Built the Raj</title><link href="/The-Indo-British-Empire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indo-British Empire: How Indians Built the Raj" /><published>2023-05-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Indo-British-Empire</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indo-British-Empire">&lt;p&gt;The Indian independence movement was built on the supposed axiom that the British Empire in India was singularly evil. According to India's first Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru, India's long-suppressed soul found utterance after it was freed from the colonial yoke. Every Indian is taught that the Republic's Founding Fathers, despite their flaws, were fighting the good fight against the white man. In fact, figures like Gandhi and even Shubhas Chandra Bose are accorded a semi-divine status in the narrative of the Indian Freedom Struggle.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, any narrative that portrays one set of people as unequivocally 'good' and another as 'bad' is bound to be far from the truth. The question is: to what extent is the narrative of the evil British Empire in India, a false one? I venture to say that it is gravely so, not because I buy the imperial propaganda of the White Man's Burden but because I find that history shows that the British Empire in India was truly, as Enoch Powell stated in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/VsC6GBw9zew&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt;, the &quot;Indo-British Empire&quot; in India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Raj formally began after the Government of India Act 1858 and the Queen's Proclamation. This was right after the uprising of 1857 which led to the defeat of the last Mughal Emperor (a mere figurehead at the time) at the hands of the East India Company. The said Government of India Act replaced the rule of the East India Company with the direct rule of the British Crown. The rule of the Company, for all practical purposes, began in 1757, when the Company defeated the forces of the &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt; of Bengal (equivalent to a British Duke) and had a puppet installed in his stead.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Company had very little actual power prior to this point, apart from having trading privileges granted by the fourth Mughal Emperor. In fact, from 1686-1690, the East India Company had tried to carry out a blockade of Mughal ports with the intent of capturing Bengal when they were denied higher trading rights. His Majesty King James II had sent a formidable fleet of ships to assist in this regard. But the forces of the infamous Emperor Alamgir I (or Aurangzeb as he is better known) brought the Company to its knees, literally. The Company's envoys had to prostrate themselves before the last Great Khan, the Refuge of Allah, the Conqueror of Kings (the Mughals had comically grand imperial titles) and pay him a fine amounting to ₹150,000, which was a huge sum at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Alamgir I died in 1707, and the largest political economy of the time slowly descended into chaos and in-fighting. By 1756, the young Siraj ud-Daulah became the &lt;em&gt;Nawab &lt;/em&gt;of Bengal. The brash &lt;em&gt;Nawab &lt;/em&gt;was, to say the least, indelicate and prone to making enemies in the conduct of statecraft. He passed over many influential members of his family and the aristocracy when making official appointments. He also had his aunt's palaces raided to neutralise the threat posed by her. The &lt;em&gt;Nawab &lt;/em&gt;had no understanding of the day-to-day troubles of running a government and trusted a group of Hindu merchants led by one Jagat Seth to manage the treasury. Siraj threatened to have Jagat Seth (literally 'Banker to the World') circumcised upon learning that due to the deep debts of the &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt;, there was not enough money to pay the salaries of the army.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not a good move. As Aakar Patel, an eminent journalist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/amp/s/www.livemint.com/Opinion/zgaDxyMuIrH3QWHElwkX3M/Blame-the-British-Raj-on-bankers.html%3ffacet=amp&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt;, &quot;Jagat Seth ran the economy for Siraj ud Daulah, Mir Jafar, and later for Mir Qasim. It is recorded that&amp;nbsp;₹&amp;nbsp;3 out of&amp;nbsp;₹&amp;nbsp;4 collected as revenue in the state went straight to Jagat Seth, against loans he had already advanced to the nawabs.&quot; Jagat Seth and his group of merchants did not take slights such as these and the general mismanagement of the province lightly. They plotted with the young &lt;em&gt;Nawab'&lt;/em&gt;s rivals, chiefly one Mir Jafar, to have the young &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt; removed. In this plot, the British were the natural allies of the shrewd &lt;em&gt;Bania&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the British had many grouses against the &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt;, such as the alleged Black Hole of Calcutta incident, the real point of synergy between the Seth and the Company was the Company's adherence to the rules of good business. As pointed out by Patel once again, the Indian merchants of Bengal stored their commercial paper and cash in Calcutta. This was because the British could be trusted with keeping their end of the bargain. The British system of justice, the rule of law, ensured that contractual obligations were enforced and honoured. For a betting banker, the chances of getting a return on his investment from a capitalist force like the Company was far greater than an immature and whimsical aristocrat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus in 1757, after recapturing Fort William, Robert Clive, a mentally unstable military genius won the Battle of Plassey against Siraj ud-Daulah, pursuant to a secret treaty between himself and Mir Jafar which was brokered by an agent of Jagat Seth, who operated in the shadows. Clive recognised Mir Jafar as the &lt;em&gt;Nawab &lt;/em&gt;and it was decided that a compensation of 22 million rupees would be made over to the Company by the treasury of the &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt;. Jagat Seth hastened to the Mughal court in Delhi and succeeded in persuading the Mughal Emperor to give his rubber stamp of approval to the English victory and to the appointment of the new &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When these facts are taken cognisance of, the beginning of the Empire looks more like a corporate takeover, as William Dalrymple suggests in &lt;em&gt;The Anarchy&lt;/em&gt;, rather than a true subjugation of an indigenous people by an imperialistic force. In fact, the complicity of the indigenous in this corporate takeover seems far greater than that of the imperialists. The Company could not have defeated Siraj in a fair battle. It could not have won without the support of a shrewd banker and a disgruntled relative of Siraj. Even the Company's foot soldiers or &lt;em&gt;sepoys&lt;/em&gt;, as they were called, were not European, but low-caste Indians on the Company's payroll.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of the British Empire in India would have been impossible without Indians facilitating the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cultural developments of the time give further evidence of this. To congratulate Clive on his victory, a certain &lt;em&gt;zamindar &lt;/em&gt;or landlord by the name of &lt;em&gt;Raja &lt;/em&gt;(or 'King') Naba Krishna Dawn organised a grand festival in honour of the Hindu Goddess Durga. This was not strictly in accordance with scripture since the invocation of Durga was usually associated with spring. However, the celebration took hold of the imagination of the new aristocracy under the new masters of Bengal. It became ubiquitous and continued to grow in both scale and splendour. In fact, it has now become Bengal's most important festival and it is now rare to see Durga worship in spring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India's native elites were happy to give up power for the centralisation that was brought about by the British. A patent example is the doctrine of subsidiary alliance formulated by Lord Wellesley - who was appointed Governor-General of India in 1798. This doctrine capitalised on the existence of the many bitter warring nobles in the subcontinent - who had grown in power and independence due to the decline of the Mughal Empire - but were deeply insecure due to the anarchy that was prevalent in those times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British offered protection to these nobles from the threats posed by their rivals and other colonising forces such as the French. In exchange, these nobles were required to maintain an army of the East India Company stationed permanently in their territory. More importantly, the Company would place an agent in the court of the noble as the point of contact and as a check on any potential betrayals by the nobles.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this was an enticing deal for the near-independent vassals of the Mughals: They wouldn't really have to maintain their own armies to fight off constant threats, and business with the Company would ensure that the riches would keep flowing. The powerful and wealthy Nizam of Hyderabad, the region where the Kohinoor diamond was mined, was the first to sign up to the doctrine. After the defeat of Tipu Sultan, the Wodeyar rulers of the area of Mysore signed up. With the defeat of the Marathas in 1817-1819, the &lt;em&gt;Peshwa&lt;/em&gt; or Prime Minister of the Marathas accepted the doctrine as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, war and conquest were necessary in many cases, but the doctrine of subsidiary alliances was a success. India's ruling class was too selfish and too narrow-minded to resist British paramountcy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian kings were handsomely rewarded for giving up some of their powers. The riches of the Kings of Patiala, i.e. the successors to the Kings who gave up the Kohinoor to Her Majesty Empress Victoria - grew immensely during the Raj, with lavish parties and Rolls Royces characterising their rule. The Marathas and Rajputs who are upheld as the paragons of nationalism by Hindu Nationalists built palaces, held grand &lt;em&gt;darbars&lt;/em&gt;, and bathed themselves in decadence as junior partners of the Raj.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the establishment of the Empire was a consequence of Indian acquiescence, its continuation, especially during its heyday, was due to a special partnership. A partnership that had no parallel in any other part of the Empire. While the nobility ushered in the British Raj, the Hindu and Muslim landed elite, the Pandit and the Ashraf, made it the envy of the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Brahmins and other upper castes (both Hindu and Muslim) of East India pursuant to the Permanent Settlement of 1793 were given ownership of the lands of which they were mere tax collectors under the Mughal regime. These aristocrats thus became the backbone of the Company's rule and the British Raj, they ensured that the flow of money extracted from the fertile lands of India to the coloniser remained undiminished. According to a research &lt;a href=&quot;https://egrove.olemiss.edu/hon_thesis/1886&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, the collection of land revenue never really declined when famines broke out in North India where the &lt;em&gt;zamindars&lt;/em&gt; were dominant. In fact, during the 200 years of the Raj, which was afflicted by 17 major famines, land revenue collection only ever grew.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;zamindar&lt;/em&gt;, as the plinth of the Raj's revenue extraction infrastructure, grew very rich by exploiting the peasant. In fact, the Famine Commission of the British Raj itself remarked in 1880 that the objective of the feudal landlord was &quot;to harass the tenant and to diminish the value of his occupancy rights, by bringing suit after suit for enhancement of the rent.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If cultivators left their villages for relief work during a famine, the landlords would ruthlessly take over &lt;a href=&quot;https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:431f85b3-e454-4faa-9718-4c49cee32460/files/m71b80352b972c86747a7a64c00af818a&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;their lands&lt;/a&gt;, even if they had left women and children behind. British officials, when dealing with a famine in the United Provinces (present-day Uttar Pradesh), observed in 1879 that &quot;If&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this famine lasts for a year there will not be an occupancy right left in the whole of&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moradabad&quot; due to the &lt;em&gt;zamindar&lt;/em&gt; of Moradabad remorselessly taking over the lands of his tenant farmers who had left for relief work. The famine became a tool for the upper caste &lt;em&gt;zamindar&lt;/em&gt; to advance profitability. He would hoard grain whenever the symptoms of famine became apparent instead of advancing any loans to his farmers. This hoarded grain would then be sold at extortionate prices, giving the &lt;em&gt;zamindar&lt;/em&gt; a windfall gain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering all this, it should come as no surprise that India was ruled by a handful of British officials. Even as late as 1931, when India had a population of 300 million, there were only 60,000 Britons in the armed forces of India and a meagre 4,000 of them in the Indian civilian administration! The British did not need to actually do the dirty work of subjugating &quot;the bloody natives&quot; and extracting an estimated $45 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/opinions/2018/12/19/how-britain-stole-45-trillion-from-india&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;trillion&lt;/a&gt; from their lands, they could rely on India's pre-existing social and economic upper-crust to do it for them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, while it is all good fun for Indians to marvel at Shashi Tharoor's lambasting of the British Empire, it is extremely hard but extremely necessary to look within and ask ourselves whether we (or perhaps a section of us) are the ones responsible for our historic oppression.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="main" /><category term="featured" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The Indian independence movement was built on the supposed axiom that the British Empire in India was singularly evil. According to India's first Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru, India's long-suppressed soul found utterance after it was freed from the colonial yoke. Every Indian is taught that the Republic's Founding Fathers, despite their flaws, were fighting the good fight against the white man. In fact, figures like Gandhi and even Shubhas Chandra Bose are accorded a semi-divine status in the narrative of the Indian Freedom Struggle.&amp;nbsp; Naturally, any narrative that portrays one set of people as unequivocally 'good' and another as 'bad' is bound to be far from the truth. The question is: to what extent is the narrative of the evil British Empire in India, a false one? I venture to say that it is gravely so, not because I buy the imperial propaganda of the White Man's Burden but because I find that history shows that the British Empire in India was truly, as Enoch Powell stated in an interview, the &quot;Indo-British Empire&quot; in India.&amp;nbsp; The Raj formally began after the Government of India Act 1858 and the Queen's Proclamation. This was right after the uprising of 1857 which led to the defeat of the last Mughal Emperor (a mere figurehead at the time) at the hands of the East India Company. The said Government of India Act replaced the rule of the East India Company with the direct rule of the British Crown. The rule of the Company, for all practical purposes, began in 1757, when the Company defeated the forces of the Nawab of Bengal (equivalent to a British Duke) and had a puppet installed in his stead.&amp;nbsp; The Company had very little actual power prior to this point, apart from having trading privileges granted by the fourth Mughal Emperor. In fact, from 1686-1690, the East India Company had tried to carry out a blockade of Mughal ports with the intent of capturing Bengal when they were denied higher trading rights. His Majesty King James II had sent a formidable fleet of ships to assist in this regard. But the forces of the infamous Emperor Alamgir I (or Aurangzeb as he is better known) brought the Company to its knees, literally. The Company's envoys had to prostrate themselves before the last Great Khan, the Refuge of Allah, the Conqueror of Kings (the Mughals had comically grand imperial titles) and pay him a fine amounting to ₹150,000, which was a huge sum at the time. But Alamgir I died in 1707, and the largest political economy of the time slowly descended into chaos and in-fighting. By 1756, the young Siraj ud-Daulah became the Nawab of Bengal. The brash Nawab was, to say the least, indelicate and prone to making enemies in the conduct of statecraft. He passed over many influential members of his family and the aristocracy when making official appointments. He also had his aunt's palaces raided to neutralise the threat posed by her. The Nawab had no understanding of the day-to-day troubles of running a government and trusted a group of Hindu merchants led by one Jagat Seth to manage the treasury. Siraj threatened to have Jagat Seth (literally 'Banker to the World') circumcised upon learning that due to the deep debts of the Nawab, there was not enough money to pay the salaries of the army.&amp;nbsp; This was not a good move. As Aakar Patel, an eminent journalist noted, &quot;Jagat Seth ran the economy for Siraj ud Daulah, Mir Jafar, and later for Mir Qasim. It is recorded that&amp;nbsp;₹&amp;nbsp;3 out of&amp;nbsp;₹&amp;nbsp;4 collected as revenue in the state went straight to Jagat Seth, against loans he had already advanced to the nawabs.&quot; Jagat Seth and his group of merchants did not take slights such as these and the general mismanagement of the province lightly. They plotted with the young Nawab's rivals, chiefly one Mir Jafar, to have the young Nawab removed. In this plot, the British were the natural allies of the shrewd Bania.&amp;nbsp; While the British had many grouses against the Nawab, such as the alleged Black Hole of Calcutta incident, the real point of synergy between the Seth and the Company was the Company's adherence to the rules of good business. As pointed out by Patel once again, the Indian merchants of Bengal stored their commercial paper and cash in Calcutta. This was because the British could be trusted with keeping their end of the bargain. The British system of justice, the rule of law, ensured that contractual obligations were enforced and honoured. For a betting banker, the chances of getting a return on his investment from a capitalist force like the Company was far greater than an immature and whimsical aristocrat.&amp;nbsp; Thus in 1757, after recapturing Fort William, Robert Clive, a mentally unstable military genius won the Battle of Plassey against Siraj ud-Daulah, pursuant to a secret treaty between himself and Mir Jafar which was brokered by an agent of Jagat Seth, who operated in the shadows. Clive recognised Mir Jafar as the Nawab and it was decided that a compensation of 22 million rupees would be made over to the Company by the treasury of the Nawab. Jagat Seth hastened to the Mughal court in Delhi and succeeded in persuading the Mughal Emperor to give his rubber stamp of approval to the English victory and to the appointment of the new Nawab.&amp;nbsp; When these facts are taken cognisance of, the beginning of the Empire looks more like a corporate takeover, as William Dalrymple suggests in The Anarchy, rather than a true subjugation of an indigenous people by an imperialistic force. In fact, the complicity of the indigenous in this corporate takeover seems far greater than that of the imperialists. The Company could not have defeated Siraj in a fair battle. It could not have won without the support of a shrewd banker and a disgruntled relative of Siraj. Even the Company's foot soldiers or sepoys, as they were called, were not European, but low-caste Indians on the Company's payroll.&amp;nbsp; The foundation of the British Empire in India would have been impossible without Indians facilitating the same.&amp;nbsp; The cultural developments of the time give further evidence of this. To congratulate Clive on his victory, a certain zamindar or landlord by the name of Raja (or 'King') Naba Krishna Dawn organised a grand festival in honour of the Hindu Goddess Durga. This was not strictly in accordance with scripture since the invocation of Durga was usually associated with spring. However, the celebration took hold of the imagination of the new aristocracy under the new masters of Bengal. It became ubiquitous and continued to grow in both scale and splendour. In fact, it has now become Bengal's most important festival and it is now rare to see Durga worship in spring.&amp;nbsp; India's native elites were happy to give up power for the centralisation that was brought about by the British. A patent example is the doctrine of subsidiary alliance formulated by Lord Wellesley - who was appointed Governor-General of India in 1798. This doctrine capitalised on the existence of the many bitter warring nobles in the subcontinent - who had grown in power and independence due to the decline of the Mughal Empire - but were deeply insecure due to the anarchy that was prevalent in those times.&amp;nbsp; The British offered protection to these nobles from the threats posed by their rivals and other colonising forces such as the French. In exchange, these nobles were required to maintain an army of the East India Company stationed permanently in their territory. More importantly, the Company would place an agent in the court of the noble as the point of contact and as a check on any potential betrayals by the nobles.&amp;nbsp; Naturally, this was an enticing deal for the near-independent vassals of the Mughals: They wouldn't really have to maintain their own armies to fight off constant threats, and business with the Company would ensure that the riches would keep flowing. The powerful and wealthy Nizam of Hyderabad, the region where the Kohinoor diamond was mined, was the first to sign up to the doctrine. After the defeat of Tipu Sultan, the Wodeyar rulers of the area of Mysore signed up. With the defeat of the Marathas in 1817-1819, the Peshwa or Prime Minister of the Marathas accepted the doctrine as well.&amp;nbsp; Indeed, war and conquest were necessary in many cases, but the doctrine of subsidiary alliances was a success. India's ruling class was too selfish and too narrow-minded to resist British paramountcy.&amp;nbsp; The Indian kings were handsomely rewarded for giving up some of their powers. The riches of the Kings of Patiala, i.e. the successors to the Kings who gave up the Kohinoor to Her Majesty Empress Victoria - grew immensely during the Raj, with lavish parties and Rolls Royces characterising their rule. The Marathas and Rajputs who are upheld as the paragons of nationalism by Hindu Nationalists built palaces, held grand darbars, and bathed themselves in decadence as junior partners of the Raj. If the establishment of the Empire was a consequence of Indian acquiescence, its continuation, especially during its heyday, was due to a special partnership. A partnership that had no parallel in any other part of the Empire. While the nobility ushered in the British Raj, the Hindu and Muslim landed elite, the Pandit and the Ashraf, made it the envy of the world.&amp;nbsp; The Brahmins and other upper castes (both Hindu and Muslim) of East India pursuant to the Permanent Settlement of 1793 were given ownership of the lands of which they were mere tax collectors under the Mughal regime. These aristocrats thus became the backbone of the Company's rule and the British Raj, they ensured that the flow of money extracted from the fertile lands of India to the coloniser remained undiminished. According to a research paper, the collection of land revenue never really declined when famines broke out in North India where the zamindars were dominant. In fact, during the 200 years of the Raj, which was afflicted by 17 major famines, land revenue collection only ever grew.&amp;nbsp; The zamindar, as the plinth of the Raj's revenue extraction infrastructure, grew very rich by exploiting the peasant. In fact, the Famine Commission of the British Raj itself remarked in 1880 that the objective of the feudal landlord was &quot;to harass the tenant and to diminish the value of his occupancy rights, by bringing suit after suit for enhancement of the rent.&quot;&amp;nbsp; If cultivators left their villages for relief work during a famine, the landlords would ruthlessly take over their lands, even if they had left women and children behind. British officials, when dealing with a famine in the United Provinces (present-day Uttar Pradesh), observed in 1879 that &quot;If&amp;nbsp; this famine lasts for a year there will not be an occupancy right left in the whole of&amp;nbsp; Moradabad&quot; due to the zamindar of Moradabad remorselessly taking over the lands of his tenant farmers who had left for relief work. The famine became a tool for the upper caste zamindar to advance profitability. He would hoard grain whenever the symptoms of famine became apparent instead of advancing any loans to his farmers. This hoarded grain would then be sold at extortionate prices, giving the zamindar a windfall gain.&amp;nbsp; Considering all this, it should come as no surprise that India was ruled by a handful of British officials. Even as late as 1931, when India had a population of 300 million, there were only 60,000 Britons in the armed forces of India and a meagre 4,000 of them in the Indian civilian administration! The British did not need to actually do the dirty work of subjugating &quot;the bloody natives&quot; and extracting an estimated $45 trillion from their lands, they could rely on India's pre-existing social and economic upper-crust to do it for them.&amp;nbsp; So, while it is all good fun for Indians to marvel at Shashi Tharoor's lambasting of the British Empire, it is extremely hard but extremely necessary to look within and ask ourselves whether we (or perhaps a section of us) are the ones responsible for our historic oppression.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choose France Tour 2022</title><link href="/Choose-France-Tour-2022" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choose France Tour 2022" /><published>2022-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Choose-France-Tour-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Choose-France-Tour-2022">&lt;p&gt;As one graduates from school, they are already faced with one of the most important decisions of their lives, the inevitable: “What do I want to do after school?” In most cases, Indian students start looking for universities to apply to, to study further. A majority of these students stay in India to obtain a degree, some prefer to go abroad. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While an education abroad, like most other things, has its pros and cons, it is a fairly popular proposition that attracts millions of Indian students each year. People are willing to pay the high tuition fees and endure the expensive costs of living for the promise of a world-class education, a better quality of life, and the possibility of employment in a developed country. For these students, the first few countries on the list are always the US, Canada, the UK and Australia. It isn’t hard for one to understand why these would be the preferred options for Indians, these are English-speaking developed countries that have hosted Indian students for several decades now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the Choose France Tour 2022 comes in. It is an attempt by the French government to make France a solid option in the future for Indian students that are looking to pursue higher studies abroad. With a surprising three-fourths of all French University courses being taught in English, the assurance of lower economic commitment for the students (compared to other options abroad), and a vague but positive chance of employment opportunities post-graduation makes it sound like a lucrative offering. The eleven-crore-rupee sponsorship that the French government is offering as a stimulus for the initiative is also a great starting point. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, Indian students would have a hard time ignoring the fact that English is not France's primary language. Although 75% of the courses are in English, that is only restricted to the lectures and the curriculum material. A significant part of the university experience is outside the campus in the sphere of networking. Indians may feel disadvantaged compared to their French counterparts in these situations. However, the launch of the France Alumni India Chapter in 2016 provides Indian students who have studied in France with a unique channel for networking. Despite English being taught in French primary schools to children from as young as five years old, the language barrier will undoubtedly be felt in simple everyday life, socialising and interacting with locals. The French are certainly known to be very proud of their language, and rightfully so. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An optimist, however, would not view this as an obstacle but rather as an opportunity to learn the language. When you are in a foreign land, the cultural experience is much more enriching when you know the language. How cool would it be to be able to read Dumas’ original&lt;em&gt; Les Trois Mousquetaires&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;The Three Musketeers&lt;/em&gt;! Besides, being fluent in French can accelerate a student’s career. According to the &lt;em&gt;Business Standard&lt;/em&gt;, there are over 200 Indian companies, ranging from Tata Consultancy Services to United Phosphorus Limited, with offices all over France, and this number has been on the rise in recent years. Furthermore, top European firms heavily value fluency in an additional European language. Apart from the obvious social and occupational benefits, French is also known to be an analytical language that structures thought and develops critical thinking. It is no wonder that there are so many great French philosophers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question remains, why do the French even want to invest in Indian students? They could just focus on their own population instead. The truth is, France wants to tap into hot talent from a culture that values conscientiousness in education. Something that English-speaking developed countries have been doing for decades. Indian students’ GPAs are consistently above average in foreign universities. Today, the largest corporations in the world are run by Indians. What’s more, universities seek a diverse culture and an influx of Indian students would be another step in that direction for French universities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the pandemic, in 2019, there were 10,000 Indian students pursuing higher education in France. The former French&amp;nbsp;Foreign Minister, Jean-Yves Le Drian&amp;nbsp;had set a target to double this number by 2025. Indian students currently enrolled in French universities appreciate the practical programme structure and the international outlook of these universities. Also very appealing is the option offered by the French government for international students after graduation to look for employment for a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things considered, the Indo-French economic connection is already on the rise and this is certainly the beginning of a win-win situation that could benefit both the Indian student and the French government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Raghav Dhariwal</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="main" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">As one graduates from school, they are already faced with one of the most important decisions of their lives, the inevitable: “What do I want to do after school?” In most cases, Indian students start looking for universities to apply to, to study further. A majority of these students stay in India to obtain a degree, some prefer to go abroad. While an education abroad, like most other things, has its pros and cons, it is a fairly popular proposition that attracts millions of Indian students each year. People are willing to pay the high tuition fees and endure the expensive costs of living for the promise of a world-class education, a better quality of life, and the possibility of employment in a developed country. For these students, the first few countries on the list are always the US, Canada, the UK and Australia. It isn’t hard for one to understand why these would be the preferred options for Indians, these are English-speaking developed countries that have hosted Indian students for several decades now. This is where the Choose France Tour 2022 comes in. It is an attempt by the French government to make France a solid option in the future for Indian students that are looking to pursue higher studies abroad. With a surprising three-fourths of all French University courses being taught in English, the assurance of lower economic commitment for the students (compared to other options abroad), and a vague but positive chance of employment opportunities post-graduation makes it sound like a lucrative offering. The eleven-crore-rupee sponsorship that the French government is offering as a stimulus for the initiative is also a great starting point. Even so, Indian students would have a hard time ignoring the fact that English is not France's primary language. Although 75% of the courses are in English, that is only restricted to the lectures and the curriculum material. A significant part of the university experience is outside the campus in the sphere of networking. Indians may feel disadvantaged compared to their French counterparts in these situations. However, the launch of the France Alumni India Chapter in 2016 provides Indian students who have studied in France with a unique channel for networking. Despite English being taught in French primary schools to children from as young as five years old, the language barrier will undoubtedly be felt in simple everyday life, socialising and interacting with locals. The French are certainly known to be very proud of their language, and rightfully so. An optimist, however, would not view this as an obstacle but rather as an opportunity to learn the language. When you are in a foreign land, the cultural experience is much more enriching when you know the language. How cool would it be to be able to read Dumas’ original Les Trois Mousquetaires instead of The Three Musketeers! Besides, being fluent in French can accelerate a student’s career. According to the Business Standard, there are over 200 Indian companies, ranging from Tata Consultancy Services to United Phosphorus Limited, with offices all over France, and this number has been on the rise in recent years. Furthermore, top European firms heavily value fluency in an additional European language. Apart from the obvious social and occupational benefits, French is also known to be an analytical language that structures thought and develops critical thinking. It is no wonder that there are so many great French philosophers. The question remains, why do the French even want to invest in Indian students? They could just focus on their own population instead. The truth is, France wants to tap into hot talent from a culture that values conscientiousness in education. Something that English-speaking developed countries have been doing for decades. Indian students’ GPAs are consistently above average in foreign universities. Today, the largest corporations in the world are run by Indians. What’s more, universities seek a diverse culture and an influx of Indian students would be another step in that direction for French universities. Before the pandemic, in 2019, there were 10,000 Indian students pursuing higher education in France. The former French&amp;nbsp;Foreign Minister, Jean-Yves Le Drian&amp;nbsp;had set a target to double this number by 2025. Indian students currently enrolled in French universities appreciate the practical programme structure and the international outlook of these universities. Also very appealing is the option offered by the French government for international students after graduation to look for employment for a year. All things considered, the Indo-French economic connection is already on the rise and this is certainly the beginning of a win-win situation that could benefit both the Indian student and the French government.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sri Lanka’s Economic Crisis: What Led to Such a Disaster</title><link href="/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sri Lanka’s Economic Crisis: What Led to Such a Disaster" /><published>2022-05-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Sri Lanka is currently facing its worst economic crisis in decades in the form of a combined &lt;strong&gt;balance of payment and sovereign debt crisis&lt;/strong&gt;. The Mahinda Rajapaksa government is finding it difficult to pay for essential imports after a 70% drop in foreign exchange reserves over two years which triggered a currency devaluation. Prices of food and essential goods have increased tremendously, fuel is in short supply and protests have broken out. With a population of 2.19 crore, Sri Lanka has announced its decision to &lt;em&gt;default on its foreign debt of $51 billion &lt;/em&gt;as of April 12. As per the data, Sri Lanka's primary creditors include China and the Asian Development Bank (ADB). 36.4% of Sri Lanka's debt is in international sovereign bonds, with ADB accounting for 14.6%, Japan 10.9% and China 10.8%. India has already extended a $1 billion line of credit to help Sri Lanka buy fuel, food and medicine but some analysts warned that this assistance might prolong the crisis rather than solve it. Sri Lanka is now seeking financial help from the IMF and Sri Lanka finance minister Basil Rajapaksa will also meet with World Bank officials next month to seek support from the United States-headquartered agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What really happened to the Sri Lankan economy?&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The crisis in Sri Lanka is broadly seen as a result of &lt;em&gt;mismanagement of government finances and ill-timed tax cuts, in addition to the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic&lt;/em&gt;. Post-independence in 1948, Sri Lanka's agriculture was dominated by export-oriented crops such as tea, coffee, rubber and spices. But a decline in exports put foreign exchange reserves under strain. Therefore, from 1965 onwards, Sri Lanka obtained 16 loans from the IMF. To make matters worse in April 2021, the government &lt;em&gt;banned the import of fertilizer&lt;/em&gt; which affected the production of tea and rubber. Though in November 2021 the ban was lifted, the earnings from agriculture had declined significantly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A gloomy situation turned worse with two economic shocks in 2019&lt;/em&gt;. First, there was a series of bomb blasts in churches and hotels in Colombo in April 2019. This led to an 80% decline in tourist arrivals. At the same time, the world was struck by an unprecedented pandemic. Being a tourism dependent country, its situation got worse due to the pandemic. According to the IMF recent report, COVID-19 has severely hit the Sri Lankan economy. The annual GDP growth rate of 2.3% in 2019 declined to -3.6% in 2020. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, the Rajapaksa government introduced populist tax cuts prior to the pandemic, limiting the government’s revenue options from corporate tax revenue. Value added tax rates were cut from 15% to 8%, whereas the government reduced the corporate tax rates from 28% to 24%. Foreign remittances from Sri Lankan workers abroad were drying up already. With a weak revenue base, the adverse impact of COVID-19 and the announced relief spending measures led to higher government expenditure which made fiscal deficits to be larger than 10% of GDP in 2020 and 2021, while the economy witnessed a rapid expansion in public debt to 119% of GDP in 2021, i.e., it has borrowed more money than it can produce via goods and services.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2020, Sri Lanka lost its access to international capital markets, leading to a decline of international reserves to critically low levels and large-scale direct lending to the government by the Central Bank of Sri Lanka (CBSL). A widening current account deficit and huge external debt repayments led to foreign exchange (FX) shortages, while the official exchange rate remained de facto &lt;em&gt;fixed since&lt;/em&gt; April 2021. All these impacted imports of fuel and other essential goods which sent prices soaring. The war in Ukraine hasn't helped either; the cost of fuel surged by 40% within a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lives of people in Sri Lanka&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;For Sri Lankans, the crisis has turned their daily lives into an endless cycle of waiting in queues for essential goods, many of which are being rationed. Soldiers are stationed at gas stations to calm customers, who line up for hours in the searing heat to fill their tanks. Life of Sri Lankans is made more difficult by frequent power cuts that plunge Colombo into darkness, sometimes for more than 10 hours at a time. Shops have been forced to shut just because they can't run fridges, air conditioners, or fans. Hospitals have refused to do any surgeries because of shortage of medical supplies. People have to wait for hours for propane gas to cook food for their families. The situation in Sri Lanka is so bad that people have now started to flee out of the country. According to experts, bad macroeconomic policy management further accentuated the economic crisis making the common citizenry suffer. Public frustration and anger erupted on April 1, when thousands of people came out on the streets to protest the crippling power cuts and shortages of essential commodities caused by the country’s economic meltdown. Consequently, Sri Lanka’s President Gotabaya Rajapaksa &lt;strong&gt;declared an Emergency on April 1.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What should Sri Lanka do now ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to some experts, Sri Lanka should establish a &lt;em&gt;three-year repayment structure&lt;/em&gt;. They believe that doing so would reduce the burden on citizens of Sri Lanka. As per the Verité Research Executive Director and Economist Dr Nishan de Mel, &quot;&lt;em&gt;Sri Lanka is unreasonably committed to repaying its debt. It is more important to press pause on debt repayment and take care of critical economic needs&lt;/em&gt;”. The Lankan economy would need a robust path towards revenue based fiscal consolidation. Reforms must focus on strengthening value added taxes, income and corporate taxes, through gradual rate increases and base broadening measures. In order to reduce fiscal risks from loss-making public enterprises, fiscal adjustment would need to be accompanied by energy pricing reforms.  Short-term monetary contractionary policy is needed to reduce the inflation. As the IMF report suggests institution building reforms, such as revamping the fiscal rule, would also help ensure the credibility of the strategy. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Other longer-term reforms include establishing a flexible exchange rate policy and a medium-to-long-term debt reduction strategy, while ensuring that most of government spending is in targeted social areas for developmental objectives such as in areas of healthcare, education and social security goals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cheshta Sharma</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="main" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Sri Lanka is currently facing its worst economic crisis in decades in the form of a combined balance of payment and sovereign debt crisis. The Mahinda Rajapaksa government is finding it difficult to pay for essential imports after a 70% drop in foreign exchange reserves over two years which triggered a currency devaluation. Prices of food and essential goods have increased tremendously, fuel is in short supply and protests have broken out. With a population of 2.19 crore, Sri Lanka has announced its decision to default on its foreign debt of $51 billion as of April 12. As per the data, Sri Lanka's primary creditors include China and the Asian Development Bank (ADB). 36.4% of Sri Lanka's debt is in international sovereign bonds, with ADB accounting for 14.6%, Japan 10.9% and China 10.8%. India has already extended a $1 billion line of credit to help Sri Lanka buy fuel, food and medicine but some analysts warned that this assistance might prolong the crisis rather than solve it. Sri Lanka is now seeking financial help from the IMF and Sri Lanka finance minister Basil Rajapaksa will also meet with World Bank officials next month to seek support from the United States-headquartered agency. What really happened to the Sri Lankan economy?&amp;nbsp; The crisis in Sri Lanka is broadly seen as a result of mismanagement of government finances and ill-timed tax cuts, in addition to the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. Post-independence in 1948, Sri Lanka's agriculture was dominated by export-oriented crops such as tea, coffee, rubber and spices. But a decline in exports put foreign exchange reserves under strain. Therefore, from 1965 onwards, Sri Lanka obtained 16 loans from the IMF. To make matters worse in April 2021, the government banned the import of fertilizer which affected the production of tea and rubber. Though in November 2021 the ban was lifted, the earnings from agriculture had declined significantly.&amp;nbsp; A gloomy situation turned worse with two economic shocks in 2019. First, there was a series of bomb blasts in churches and hotels in Colombo in April 2019. This led to an 80% decline in tourist arrivals. At the same time, the world was struck by an unprecedented pandemic. Being a tourism dependent country, its situation got worse due to the pandemic. According to the IMF recent report, COVID-19 has severely hit the Sri Lankan economy. The annual GDP growth rate of 2.3% in 2019 declined to -3.6% in 2020. &amp;nbsp; Second, the Rajapaksa government introduced populist tax cuts prior to the pandemic, limiting the government’s revenue options from corporate tax revenue. Value added tax rates were cut from 15% to 8%, whereas the government reduced the corporate tax rates from 28% to 24%. Foreign remittances from Sri Lankan workers abroad were drying up already. With a weak revenue base, the adverse impact of COVID-19 and the announced relief spending measures led to higher government expenditure which made fiscal deficits to be larger than 10% of GDP in 2020 and 2021, while the economy witnessed a rapid expansion in public debt to 119% of GDP in 2021, i.e., it has borrowed more money than it can produce via goods and services.&amp;nbsp; In 2020, Sri Lanka lost its access to international capital markets, leading to a decline of international reserves to critically low levels and large-scale direct lending to the government by the Central Bank of Sri Lanka (CBSL). A widening current account deficit and huge external debt repayments led to foreign exchange (FX) shortages, while the official exchange rate remained de facto fixed since April 2021. All these impacted imports of fuel and other essential goods which sent prices soaring. The war in Ukraine hasn't helped either; the cost of fuel surged by 40% within a week. Lives of people in Sri Lanka For Sri Lankans, the crisis has turned their daily lives into an endless cycle of waiting in queues for essential goods, many of which are being rationed. Soldiers are stationed at gas stations to calm customers, who line up for hours in the searing heat to fill their tanks. Life of Sri Lankans is made more difficult by frequent power cuts that plunge Colombo into darkness, sometimes for more than 10 hours at a time. Shops have been forced to shut just because they can't run fridges, air conditioners, or fans. Hospitals have refused to do any surgeries because of shortage of medical supplies. People have to wait for hours for propane gas to cook food for their families. The situation in Sri Lanka is so bad that people have now started to flee out of the country. According to experts, bad macroeconomic policy management further accentuated the economic crisis making the common citizenry suffer. Public frustration and anger erupted on April 1, when thousands of people came out on the streets to protest the crippling power cuts and shortages of essential commodities caused by the country’s economic meltdown. Consequently, Sri Lanka’s President Gotabaya Rajapaksa declared an Emergency on April 1. What should Sri Lanka do now ? According to some experts, Sri Lanka should establish a three-year repayment structure. They believe that doing so would reduce the burden on citizens of Sri Lanka. As per the Verité Research Executive Director and Economist Dr Nishan de Mel, &quot;Sri Lanka is unreasonably committed to repaying its debt. It is more important to press pause on debt repayment and take care of critical economic needs”. The Lankan economy would need a robust path towards revenue based fiscal consolidation. Reforms must focus on strengthening value added taxes, income and corporate taxes, through gradual rate increases and base broadening measures. In order to reduce fiscal risks from loss-making public enterprises, fiscal adjustment would need to be accompanied by energy pricing reforms.  Short-term monetary contractionary policy is needed to reduce the inflation. As the IMF report suggests institution building reforms, such as revamping the fiscal rule, would also help ensure the credibility of the strategy. &amp;nbsp; Other longer-term reforms include establishing a flexible exchange rate policy and a medium-to-long-term debt reduction strategy, while ensuring that most of government spending is in targeted social areas for developmental objectives such as in areas of healthcare, education and social security goals.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parenting the Internet Generation</title><link href="/Parenting-the-Internet-Generation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parenting the Internet Generation" /><published>2022-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Parenting-the-Internet-Generation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Parenting-the-Internet-Generation">&lt;p&gt;The modern world is changing at an unprecedented rate. The challenges faced by today’s parents are no exception. With the rise of technologies such as the internet and social media, how will this affect new generations of children who never knew a world before these became quintessential parts of our everyday lives? How will this affect their parents?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, we discuss with our guest, Tracy Ho. She is the principal of Hils Learning, a centre that specialises in the development and learning support of children with special needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to the full session here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-2&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/2022-04-07-Parenting-the-Internet-Generation.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Or watch it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9XXjIG1cGNo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;*This session was recorded at Qworky Academy on 11th September 2021 and moderated by &lt;a href=&quot;/author/avinash.naidu/&quot;&gt;Avinash Naidu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Avinash Naidu</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="featured" /><category term="the-faraday-corner" /><category term="podcast" /><summary type="html">The modern world is changing at an unprecedented rate. The challenges faced by today’s parents are no exception. With the rise of technologies such as the internet and social media, how will this affect new generations of children who never knew a world before these became quintessential parts of our everyday lives? How will this affect their parents?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All Talk and No Action: A Common Thread</title><link href="/All-Talk-and-No-Action-A-Common-Thread" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All Talk and No Action: A Common Thread" /><published>2022-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/All-Talk-and-No-Action-A-Common-Thread</id><content type="html" xml:base="/All-Talk-and-No-Action-A-Common-Thread">&lt;p&gt;It seems like only yesterday that we ushered in the new year, and now we are well into the third month. Although the last year was largely overshadowed by the havoc wreaked by COVID-19, one event that arguably stood out was COP26. Whether it was a success or not is another matter, but it did highlight the emergency in some ways: Sir David Attenborough’s&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o7EpiXViSIQ&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o7EpiXViSIQ&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;passionate call to action&lt;/a&gt;, for example. In that backdrop, it is essential to see where we as a people are headed. Some may question waiting this far along into the new year to decipher directions, but recent events have put things in perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, the budget for 2022-23 was presented. While there were some things to be optimistic about, the general consensus, depending on where you stand obviously, is that it hasn’t hit the mark, nor does it realise the seriousness of the environmental problems we are meant to tackle with the utmost sense of urgency. There is an increase in allocations for the environment ministry, the &lt;em&gt;Jal Jeevan &lt;/em&gt;Mission (Water is life mission) and some other programmes, such as, the Save the Tiger and Deep Ocean Missions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increase in the budget for production-linked incentives (PLI) had already been announced in November, but was reiterated here as well. The transition to clean energy is where the half-baked good news pretty much comes to a halt and the problems with the usual lopsided approach begin.&amp;nbsp; While the increased allocation for the environment ministry is ₹5.1 billion, the allocation for the Climate Change Action Plan is a mere ₹300 million! Additionally, mining got a boost of ₹26.74 billion. This shows the government totally missing the bus on climate resilience and adaptation, and further, despite what it may look like on the face of it, the predisposition towards industry and ‘development’ is very clear.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;If anyone needs more convincing, do take a look at the proposed expansion of highways: a whopping 25,000 km, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://thewire.in/environment/union-budget-2022-environment-india-climate-action-pollution-clean-energy&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;experts&lt;/a&gt; opine will put the final nails into India’s ecological coffin. Moreover, five more river-linking projects other than the already controversial Ken-Betwa project have been planned. It is important to remember that the controversy and disputes in relation to the Ken-Betwa project had led the Indian Supreme Court to appoint a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/sci-tech/energy-and-environment/the-ken-betwa-project-reflects-the-ill-conceived-rationale-behind-river-linking/article34335304.ece&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Central Empowered Committee&lt;/a&gt;, which had thoroughly doubted the viability of the project, stating that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“No amount of mitigating measures can create this kind of unique ecosystem which has evolved over millions of years to reach the present level of biodiversity.”&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that is not all. A bill has been tabled in the winter session of Indian Parliament that proposes to once again legalise the commercial trade of elephants, after the same had been banned for the last five decades. There was a time when India was known as one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.downtoearth.org.in/coverage/in-dubious-battle-24137&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;staunchest supporters&lt;/a&gt; of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora, consistently raising its voice against the downgrading of any species, and itself placing the Indian as well as the Asian Elephant in List I. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.downtoearth.org.in/coverage/in-dubious-battle-24137&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; going back a quarter of a century from 1997 suggest that even then the country wasn't doing well; and despite that &lt;a href=&quot;https://scroll.in/article/1016272/indias-elephants-will-suffer-huge-setback-if-proposed-changes-to-wildlife-protection-act-are-passed&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;still being true&lt;/a&gt;, it now wants to ‘manage’ wildlife instead of conserving it. If this isn’t pandering blindly to commercial interests, what is?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then there is yet more that puts the stand of those meant to ‘protect’ the environment in perspective. The government has also introduced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://theprint.in/theprint-essential/these-are-the-7-criteria-modi-govt-will-use-for-ranking-states-on-environment-clearance/808592/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ranking system &lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;which is to be employed to ‘increase efficiency’ and facilitate the ‘ease of doing business.’ It ‘streamlines’ the environmental clearance (EC) process and puts a points system in place to see how quickly the permits are granted, ‘without diluting any regulatory safeguards’ and it is also reported that Indian States which take time in granting the clearance will not be ‘penalised’. Let us break that down to what it really is. Streamlining is a polite way of saying that requirements are going to be watered down, not being ‘penalised’ suggests a clear, unabashed pro-business outlook at the cost of the environment, and the no dilution-bit is clearly false because points are also allocated for the number of visits made by the authorities and the number of times documents are sought.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is safe to assume that there are more blows in the pipeline , given the relentless pursuit of a $5 trillion economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But India is not the only one which causes sleepless flights to those fretting over the climate crisis. India’s northern neighbour, and one of the biggest economies of the world as well is, by far, the largest emitter of greenhouse gases. China, while it has made certain efforts and announcements to do its rather large bit to tackle the climate crisis, is yet &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/chinas-climate-change-record-beijing-tends-to-meet-its-targets-but-sets-the-bar-too-low-172138&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;not carrying its weight&lt;/a&gt;. It sets the bar too low for itself. It must also be noted that while encouraging statements were being made on the one hand, on the other, coal production hit&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2022/jan/17/chinas-coal-production-hit-record-levels-in-2021&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; record levels&lt;/a&gt; in 2021, and in the year preceding that, China was noted to be the only country whose greenhouse gas emissions&lt;a href=&quot;https://rhg.com/research/preliminary-2020-greenhouse-gas-emissions-estimates-for-china/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; increased&lt;/a&gt; in 2020. It is in this dark light that Premier Xi’s statements like &quot;low carbon emissions should &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/jan/26/xi-jinping-warns-chinas-low-carbon-ambitions-must-not-interfere-with-normal-life&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;not interfere &lt;/a&gt;with normal life&quot;, and that China will begin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/world/china/chinas-xi-says-china-will-phase-down-coal-consumption-over-2026-2030-2021-04-22/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;phasing out&lt;/a&gt; the use of coal in 2026 becomes deeply problematic. This 'normal life' is, in other words, the race for development, because normal is an expanding concept, where people and their betterment is measured solely in economic terms. Till the time the understanding of this ‘normal’ doesn’t change, do we have a chance at survival?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this common thread, we look at the second biggest emitter, the US, as well.&amp;nbsp; It is not an exaggeration that the term of the 45th President was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02800-9&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;disastrous&lt;/a&gt; in terms of the environment, and the multitude of effects that it had on the world at large is yet to be understood. Number 46 as well, while infinitely better, has not been able to and has not been allowed to achieve what is needed, repair the damage, chart the future, and take action. In what has been termed as a year of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/04/climate/biden-climate-change.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;over-promising and under-delivering&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp; just shortly after COP26, the US government auctioned 80 million acres for offshore drilling in the Gulf of Mexico, which is a record for that area. With a version of reality entirely possible where President Biden’s party doesn’t control the legislature, the world’s climate future just turned a few shades bleaker.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this is the picture presented by three of the world’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldpopulationreview.com/country-rankings/greenhouse-gas-emissions-by-country&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;largest&lt;/a&gt; GHG emitters, then what does the future hold for the young people led by Greta Thumberg, Disha Ravi and those of us who are maybe a few years older? How are we to go about our ‘normal lives’, as Premier Xi puts it, knowing that people like him have put us and continue to put us in even graver danger? With the systematic dismantling of protection mechanisms or lopsided monetary allocations as highlighted in India, how do we prepare for the massive, impending displacement that is to be brought on by rising sea levels threatening the very existence of nine major Indian cities? With there being less than eight years to stop ourselves from going over the tipping point, how do we convince China that phasing out, beginning 2026 is not enough? How do we get the American political establishment to understand that there is much more at stake, for their own children and grandchildren, than mere maintenance of the Empire?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The direction in which these three countries can be seen as heading, is one of too little, too slow.&amp;nbsp; 2022 marks the 50th year of the Stockholm Declaration and a stark truth is that we have still not realised its principles, even in their most anthropocentric form. In a time where opportunism, self- interest and the hunger for money are masters of the game, even that seems unlikely.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can this common thread, currently slated to spell doom (that may seem alarmist to a few, and they would be right, it is, justifiably so) be turned around instead to be one of realisation, planning and execution or is the quest for normal far too enticing to give up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-Ishan Chauhan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ishan Chauhan is an Independent Researcher, with keen interests in environmental law and policy. His work has appeared in The Hindu, Navhind Times, The Orissa Post, Deshbandhu etc. He is the writer of two and editor of one volume of fiction/non-fiction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>trending guest</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">It seems like only yesterday that we ushered in the new year, and now we are well into the third month. Although the last year was largely overshadowed by the havoc wreaked by COVID-19, one event that arguably stood out was COP26. Whether it was a success or not is another matter, but it did highlight the emergency in some ways: Sir David Attenborough’s passionate call to action, for example. In that backdrop, it is essential to see where we as a people are headed. Some may question waiting this far along into the new year to decipher directions, but recent events have put things in perspective. In India, the budget for 2022-23 was presented. While there were some things to be optimistic about, the general consensus, depending on where you stand obviously, is that it hasn’t hit the mark, nor does it realise the seriousness of the environmental problems we are meant to tackle with the utmost sense of urgency. There is an increase in allocations for the environment ministry, the Jal Jeevan Mission (Water is life mission) and some other programmes, such as, the Save the Tiger and Deep Ocean Missions.&amp;nbsp; The increase in the budget for production-linked incentives (PLI) had already been announced in November, but was reiterated here as well. The transition to clean energy is where the half-baked good news pretty much comes to a halt and the problems with the usual lopsided approach begin.&amp;nbsp; While the increased allocation for the environment ministry is ₹5.1 billion, the allocation for the Climate Change Action Plan is a mere ₹300 million! Additionally, mining got a boost of ₹26.74 billion. This shows the government totally missing the bus on climate resilience and adaptation, and further, despite what it may look like on the face of it, the predisposition towards industry and ‘development’ is very clear.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;If anyone needs more convincing, do take a look at the proposed expansion of highways: a whopping 25,000 km, which experts opine will put the final nails into India’s ecological coffin. Moreover, five more river-linking projects other than the already controversial Ken-Betwa project have been planned. It is important to remember that the controversy and disputes in relation to the Ken-Betwa project had led the Indian Supreme Court to appoint a Central Empowered Committee, which had thoroughly doubted the viability of the project, stating that: “No amount of mitigating measures can create this kind of unique ecosystem which has evolved over millions of years to reach the present level of biodiversity.”&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, that is not all. A bill has been tabled in the winter session of Indian Parliament that proposes to once again legalise the commercial trade of elephants, after the same had been banned for the last five decades. There was a time when India was known as one of the staunchest supporters of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora, consistently raising its voice against the downgrading of any species, and itself placing the Indian as well as the Asian Elephant in List I. However, reports going back a quarter of a century from 1997 suggest that even then the country wasn't doing well; and despite that still being true, it now wants to ‘manage’ wildlife instead of conserving it. If this isn’t pandering blindly to commercial interests, what is?&amp;nbsp; But then there is yet more that puts the stand of those meant to ‘protect’ the environment in perspective. The government has also introduced a ranking system &amp;nbsp;which is to be employed to ‘increase efficiency’ and facilitate the ‘ease of doing business.’ It ‘streamlines’ the environmental clearance (EC) process and puts a points system in place to see how quickly the permits are granted, ‘without diluting any regulatory safeguards’ and it is also reported that Indian States which take time in granting the clearance will not be ‘penalised’. Let us break that down to what it really is. Streamlining is a polite way of saying that requirements are going to be watered down, not being ‘penalised’ suggests a clear, unabashed pro-business outlook at the cost of the environment, and the no dilution-bit is clearly false because points are also allocated for the number of visits made by the authorities and the number of times documents are sought.&amp;nbsp; It is safe to assume that there are more blows in the pipeline , given the relentless pursuit of a $5 trillion economy.&amp;nbsp; But India is not the only one which causes sleepless flights to those fretting over the climate crisis. India’s northern neighbour, and one of the biggest economies of the world as well is, by far, the largest emitter of greenhouse gases. China, while it has made certain efforts and announcements to do its rather large bit to tackle the climate crisis, is yet not carrying its weight. It sets the bar too low for itself. It must also be noted that while encouraging statements were being made on the one hand, on the other, coal production hit record levels in 2021, and in the year preceding that, China was noted to be the only country whose greenhouse gas emissions increased in 2020. It is in this dark light that Premier Xi’s statements like &quot;low carbon emissions should not interfere with normal life&quot;, and that China will begin phasing out the use of coal in 2026 becomes deeply problematic. This 'normal life' is, in other words, the race for development, because normal is an expanding concept, where people and their betterment is measured solely in economic terms. Till the time the understanding of this ‘normal’ doesn’t change, do we have a chance at survival? In this common thread, we look at the second biggest emitter, the US, as well.&amp;nbsp; It is not an exaggeration that the term of the 45th President was disastrous in terms of the environment, and the multitude of effects that it had on the world at large is yet to be understood. Number 46 as well, while infinitely better, has not been able to and has not been allowed to achieve what is needed, repair the damage, chart the future, and take action. In what has been termed as a year of over-promising and under-delivering,&amp;nbsp; just shortly after COP26, the US government auctioned 80 million acres for offshore drilling in the Gulf of Mexico, which is a record for that area. With a version of reality entirely possible where President Biden’s party doesn’t control the legislature, the world’s climate future just turned a few shades bleaker.&amp;nbsp; When this is the picture presented by three of the world’s largest GHG emitters, then what does the future hold for the young people led by Greta Thumberg, Disha Ravi and those of us who are maybe a few years older? How are we to go about our ‘normal lives’, as Premier Xi puts it, knowing that people like him have put us and continue to put us in even graver danger? With the systematic dismantling of protection mechanisms or lopsided monetary allocations as highlighted in India, how do we prepare for the massive, impending displacement that is to be brought on by rising sea levels threatening the very existence of nine major Indian cities? With there being less than eight years to stop ourselves from going over the tipping point, how do we convince China that phasing out, beginning 2026 is not enough? How do we get the American political establishment to understand that there is much more at stake, for their own children and grandchildren, than mere maintenance of the Empire? The direction in which these three countries can be seen as heading, is one of too little, too slow.&amp;nbsp; 2022 marks the 50th year of the Stockholm Declaration and a stark truth is that we have still not realised its principles, even in their most anthropocentric form. In a time where opportunism, self- interest and the hunger for money are masters of the game, even that seems unlikely.&amp;nbsp; Can this common thread, currently slated to spell doom (that may seem alarmist to a few, and they would be right, it is, justifiably so) be turned around instead to be one of realisation, planning and execution or is the quest for normal far too enticing to give up? -Ishan Chauhan Ishan Chauhan is an Independent Researcher, with keen interests in environmental law and policy. His work has appeared in The Hindu, Navhind Times, The Orissa Post, Deshbandhu etc. He is the writer of two and editor of one volume of fiction/non-fiction.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NFTs: Desperate for Utility</title><link href="/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NFTs: Desperate for Utility" /><published>2022-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility</id><content type="html" xml:base="/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It could be really difficult for one to understand why someone would pay $69 million for a digital image that can be easily copied and pasted for free. What one needs to understand is that the value of such an item is not in its utility but in its value itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What are Non-Fungible Tokens? The first part of the term is 'non-fungible' which means unique, and that such a token cannot be traded or replaced with another one of itself. Fungible items are non-unique and divisible items such as fiat currencies like the US Dollar, a lot of them exist and the one in your pocket is worth the same as the one in Donald Trump’s dollar. NFTs are on blockchains with most of them being on the Ethereum blockchain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As most things do, status symbols have evolved over the centuries from Mayans pressing their children’s skulls into a variety of shapes to reflect their place in society to fancy watches and rare sneakers. As has been the case with most aspects of humankind, status symbols are getting digitised.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;If, like many others including me, you have failed to understand the utility of NFTs, in most cases, there isn’t any. Just like the tulips in Amsterdam in the 1600's or the Beanie Babies of the 1980’s. If you own any expensive NFTs at the moment, the two aforementioned examples must be ringing alarm bells in your head, or if they aren’t, then they should. The Dutch Tulip Mania of the 1600’s saw prices of tulips (the flowers that are now very common in the Netherlands) shoot up to US$ 750,000 per piece in today’s money before crashing completely.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A similar narrative played out for Beanie Babies. These two stories illustrate the inevitable disaster that follows the brewing of a financial bubble of a relatively meaningless asset class. In other words, when people buy utterly useless stuff only with the motive of flipping it for profit, the buying spree ends eventually and dramatically. Gary Vaynerchuk’s NFT restaurant located in New York City perfectly demonstrates the desperation of stakeholders in the NFT market to add utility to them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Although the signs are there, it would be hard to say with the utmost certainty that NFTs are going to go down the same path as the other assets mentioned above. NFTs are still quite new from a global perspective with only a very small group of people truly understanding them. Twitter’s verified NFT profile picture is a positive sign towards widespread acceptance but there’s still a long road ahead for it to compete with more conventional symbols like fast cars or designer clothes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Since NFTs can be easily copied and pasted, it makes their apparent utility almost zero. Hence, it is easy for one to conclude that a person only possesses the NFT for either (1) flipping it for profit or (2) to flex. Unfortunately, both scenarios are problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The former points to a classic financial bubble, overinflated rates for little-to-no utility assets being held just for the sake of flipping. While the latter fuels the bubble, it also has its own limitations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Anybody that has enough money can buy an NFT, there are not many barriers to entry into the NFT game apart from possession of money. This makes NFTs a very limited status symbol as there is no exclusivity attached to them. Although money and status have a strong correlation, money does not guarantee status, hence the sheer ownership of NFTs only guarantees an abundance of money but does not guarantee status or honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Unlike overly expensive clothes whose purchase can be justified by vastly exaggerating their additional comfort and style quotient compared to regular clothes, NFTs do not have an alibi for purchase. They are very loud and clear status symbols that are bought in an attempt to motion status. However, purposefully motioning status is a low-status action itself. Successful status symbols require alibis, their consumption needs to be legitimised by their progressed utility. To this end, extravagant brands talk unendingly about extraordinary craftsmanship, splendid planning or designing ability - to sell a facade of functionalism that conceals crude positional stamping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While indicative expenses and vindications are crucial, the most basic part of a status symbol is a cachet, a clear marker of a relationship with existing high-status gatherings. Both Ferraris and metropolitan waste vehicles are pricey, yet just Ferraris fill in as status symbols since rich individuals don't drive dump trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;NFTs clear the principal bar of status symbols: they are extremely expensive. Steph Curry just paid $180,000 for Bored Ape #7990. For the people who got in ahead of schedule, time turns into the flagging expense. It may seem that the expenses of faking an NFT are incredibly low - screenshotting a Bored Ape is free - however, with the assurance of provenance in Blockchain, fake use can be uncovered right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Then, do NFTs have any myth of utility? One cannot find anything more than the flimsiest common sense utility of &quot;workmanship&quot; (as Roose says, Pudgy Penguins are &quot;in a general sense inconsequential&quot;). In any case, there is a more essential issue: there is no real way to possess and show NFTs without aim. They aren't ‘normal’ portions of a high-status way of life. Each NFT recounts the narrative of a person taking the time and cash to get an NFT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Be that as it may, this is the place where things get extremely confusing. The best vindication for NFTs is that they are a venture. Steph Curry didn't squander $180,000 on a jpeg - he got it to sell it for a profit later. Simultaneously, the whole superficial point of interest story itself fills in as a vindication for the presence of NFTs: Without them being used in individual self-articulation, they are just unstable and speculative monetary vehicles. There is a circle, where NFTs are acting like status symbols acting like speculations. In any event, the way that individuals with such ease wield their speculation properties to exhibit taste says a great deal regarding our age. Most likely nobody in the 70's conveyed receipts for corn fates as their vacation cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In regards to cachet, NFTs right now offer no unambiguous relationship with high-status networks. Gary Vaynerchuk, Steve Aoki, Mike Tyson, and numerous renowned crypto-evangelists use NFT symbols, however, so do mysterious nobodies. Any individual who peruses a couple of bulletin articles can sort out some way to get one. That being said, aggregate proprietorship makes a ‘symbol club’. For Kyle, they are a &quot;weird blend of gated web-based local area, stock-shareholding gathering, and workmanship appreciation society.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;NFTs hence fill in as section level status symbols to join these gatherings. Once inside the ‘swamp club for chimps’, Bored Ape proprietors can partake in the warm sparkle of acknowledgement from outsiders. Kevin Roose, after purchasing a Pudgy Penguin, noticed, &quot;My notices were spilling over with bulbous and angled intruders, all praising me…&quot; But NFT groups have people of both low- and high-status positions, making them generally not quite the same as national clubs or VIP lounges. Anybody can join, assuming they have the cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, many NFTs fill in as brilliant passes to these clubs. Right now, NFTs are just compelling for the individuals who wish to join the envisioned networks around NFTs. In the best-case scenario, NFTs might motion toward ordinary individuals’ profound information in crypto, speculation ability, and experience with state of the art mainstream society. Be that as it may, in our pre-metaverse world, NFTs draw no worth from being important to a high-status way of life; they just point out the cash expected to purchase them. This conspicuousness checks their viability. To be better status symbols, they should turn out to be more casual, like fine Swiss watches, they must be something worth acquiring as part of an attempt to symbolise aspirations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Raghav Dhariwal</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">It could be really difficult for one to understand why someone would pay $69 million for a digital image that can be easily copied and pasted for free. What one needs to understand is that the value of such an item is not in its utility but in its value itself.&amp;nbsp; What are Non-Fungible Tokens? The first part of the term is 'non-fungible' which means unique, and that such a token cannot be traded or replaced with another one of itself. Fungible items are non-unique and divisible items such as fiat currencies like the US Dollar, a lot of them exist and the one in your pocket is worth the same as the one in Donald Trump’s dollar. NFTs are on blockchains with most of them being on the Ethereum blockchain.&amp;nbsp; As most things do, status symbols have evolved over the centuries from Mayans pressing their children’s skulls into a variety of shapes to reflect their place in society to fancy watches and rare sneakers. As has been the case with most aspects of humankind, status symbols are getting digitised.&amp;nbsp; If, like many others including me, you have failed to understand the utility of NFTs, in most cases, there isn’t any. Just like the tulips in Amsterdam in the 1600's or the Beanie Babies of the 1980’s. If you own any expensive NFTs at the moment, the two aforementioned examples must be ringing alarm bells in your head, or if they aren’t, then they should. The Dutch Tulip Mania of the 1600’s saw prices of tulips (the flowers that are now very common in the Netherlands) shoot up to US$ 750,000 per piece in today’s money before crashing completely.&amp;nbsp; A similar narrative played out for Beanie Babies. These two stories illustrate the inevitable disaster that follows the brewing of a financial bubble of a relatively meaningless asset class. In other words, when people buy utterly useless stuff only with the motive of flipping it for profit, the buying spree ends eventually and dramatically. Gary Vaynerchuk’s NFT restaurant located in New York City perfectly demonstrates the desperation of stakeholders in the NFT market to add utility to them.&amp;nbsp; Although the signs are there, it would be hard to say with the utmost certainty that NFTs are going to go down the same path as the other assets mentioned above. NFTs are still quite new from a global perspective with only a very small group of people truly understanding them. Twitter’s verified NFT profile picture is a positive sign towards widespread acceptance but there’s still a long road ahead for it to compete with more conventional symbols like fast cars or designer clothes.&amp;nbsp; Since NFTs can be easily copied and pasted, it makes their apparent utility almost zero. Hence, it is easy for one to conclude that a person only possesses the NFT for either (1) flipping it for profit or (2) to flex. Unfortunately, both scenarios are problematic. The former points to a classic financial bubble, overinflated rates for little-to-no utility assets being held just for the sake of flipping. While the latter fuels the bubble, it also has its own limitations.&amp;nbsp; Anybody that has enough money can buy an NFT, there are not many barriers to entry into the NFT game apart from possession of money. This makes NFTs a very limited status symbol as there is no exclusivity attached to them. Although money and status have a strong correlation, money does not guarantee status, hence the sheer ownership of NFTs only guarantees an abundance of money but does not guarantee status or honour. Unlike overly expensive clothes whose purchase can be justified by vastly exaggerating their additional comfort and style quotient compared to regular clothes, NFTs do not have an alibi for purchase. They are very loud and clear status symbols that are bought in an attempt to motion status. However, purposefully motioning status is a low-status action itself. Successful status symbols require alibis, their consumption needs to be legitimised by their progressed utility. To this end, extravagant brands talk unendingly about extraordinary craftsmanship, splendid planning or designing ability - to sell a facade of functionalism that conceals crude positional stamping. While indicative expenses and vindications are crucial, the most basic part of a status symbol is a cachet, a clear marker of a relationship with existing high-status gatherings. Both Ferraris and metropolitan waste vehicles are pricey, yet just Ferraris fill in as status symbols since rich individuals don't drive dump trucks. NFTs clear the principal bar of status symbols: they are extremely expensive. Steph Curry just paid $180,000 for Bored Ape #7990. For the people who got in ahead of schedule, time turns into the flagging expense. It may seem that the expenses of faking an NFT are incredibly low - screenshotting a Bored Ape is free - however, with the assurance of provenance in Blockchain, fake use can be uncovered right away. Then, do NFTs have any myth of utility? One cannot find anything more than the flimsiest common sense utility of &quot;workmanship&quot; (as Roose says, Pudgy Penguins are &quot;in a general sense inconsequential&quot;). In any case, there is a more essential issue: there is no real way to possess and show NFTs without aim. They aren't ‘normal’ portions of a high-status way of life. Each NFT recounts the narrative of a person taking the time and cash to get an NFT. Be that as it may, this is the place where things get extremely confusing. The best vindication for NFTs is that they are a venture. Steph Curry didn't squander $180,000 on a jpeg - he got it to sell it for a profit later. Simultaneously, the whole superficial point of interest story itself fills in as a vindication for the presence of NFTs: Without them being used in individual self-articulation, they are just unstable and speculative monetary vehicles. There is a circle, where NFTs are acting like status symbols acting like speculations. In any event, the way that individuals with such ease wield their speculation properties to exhibit taste says a great deal regarding our age. Most likely nobody in the 70's conveyed receipts for corn fates as their vacation cards. In regards to cachet, NFTs right now offer no unambiguous relationship with high-status networks. Gary Vaynerchuk, Steve Aoki, Mike Tyson, and numerous renowned crypto-evangelists use NFT symbols, however, so do mysterious nobodies. Any individual who peruses a couple of bulletin articles can sort out some way to get one. That being said, aggregate proprietorship makes a ‘symbol club’. For Kyle, they are a &quot;weird blend of gated web-based local area, stock-shareholding gathering, and workmanship appreciation society.&quot; NFTs hence fill in as section level status symbols to join these gatherings. Once inside the ‘swamp club for chimps’, Bored Ape proprietors can partake in the warm sparkle of acknowledgement from outsiders. Kevin Roose, after purchasing a Pudgy Penguin, noticed, &quot;My notices were spilling over with bulbous and angled intruders, all praising me…&quot; But NFT groups have people of both low- and high-status positions, making them generally not quite the same as national clubs or VIP lounges. Anybody can join, assuming they have the cash. However, many NFTs fill in as brilliant passes to these clubs. Right now, NFTs are just compelling for the individuals who wish to join the envisioned networks around NFTs. In the best-case scenario, NFTs might motion toward ordinary individuals’ profound information in crypto, speculation ability, and experience with state of the art mainstream society. Be that as it may, in our pre-metaverse world, NFTs draw no worth from being important to a high-status way of life; they just point out the cash expected to purchase them. This conspicuousness checks their viability. To be better status symbols, they should turn out to be more casual, like fine Swiss watches, they must be something worth acquiring as part of an attempt to symbolise aspirations.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Economic Sanctions: A Silent Weapon of War</title><link href="/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economic Sanctions: A Silent Weapon of War" /><published>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The United States has imposed severe sanctions over the state of North Korea for their new ballistic missile test.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This is how a typical headline in global politics looks like when a jaw-dropping geopolitically motivated event occurs. At first glance, one might wonder why a country such as the US is so vested in the fund allocation of the North Korean treasury. It all essentially boils down to the degree of influence that a superpower (assumption being that the US is the lone superpower) has over nation states when it comes to their economy and people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US does so in the larger interest of the world, and considers itself to be the saviour of our generation when it comes to averting a nuclear catastrophe. Since it cannot (and must not) threaten war on many already poverty stricken and poor states, it imposes a series of Keynesian tool-based economic sanctions that prohibit the economic growth of the nation state, as they directly affect the demand and supply chains of the economy and tend to cut them off from more states that are members of ‘the bloc’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The unsettling reality is that disasters similar to Hiroshima and Nagasaki continue to occur in Middle Eastern countries, where war has been raging for decades, and yet we've been so oblivious to their occurrences when we accidentally switch to &lt;em&gt;BBC International&lt;/em&gt; after cheering for our football team on the previous channel. But beneath the thick glorious boasts of killing ISIS leaders, annihilating Sanaa (again), and killing millions, there is the far more destructive layer of economic sanctions imposed on seemingly rogue states that disagree with the ideology of the world's leading nation state. The inconvenient reality is that those sanctions, in a roundabout way, have an effect on the health of citizens and frequently bring about devastating consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economic sanctions are of three types: (1) suspension of loans or aid withdrawal by the sender; (2) denial of access to international financial markets; and (3) bans on capital investment in the targeted state. They often involve a sector-specific ban such as an oil ban, textile ban, a ban on using a particular currency or engaging with particular financial operators (such as banks). Intended to impose constraints on the economic activities of the targeted state, economic sanctions aim to prevent a state from importing certain goods or services. They may also prevent a state from exporting its natural resources, agricultural, or manufactured products.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another type of economic sanction specifically targets the banking and financial sectors. Overseas assets, for example, can be frozen or transactions put on hold. Foreign aid may be withheld as well. Economic sanctions are most likely to be detrimental to a country. Refusing to import goods or services from a country can act as a kind of protectionist policy for the target country. This can create a constituency for such policies, making them difficult to repeal. A ban on exporting certain goods and services to a country, such as agricultural products, on the other hand, can harm influential sectors of the target country and make it difficult to impose or sustain such measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to Farrokh Habibzadeh's paper &lt;em&gt;Economic sanction: a weapon of mass destruction&lt;/em&gt;, the UN Security Council Resolution 661-3 imposed a multilateral sanction on Iraq in 1990, prohibiting the import of all substances other than those intended for scientific purposes, food, and various humanitarian items. The sanction killed approximately 1.5 million people (including more than half a million children) in Iraq - more than the number of people killed in Hiroshima in the aftermath of the nuclear bomb detonation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Many critical life-saving tablets become unavailable due to the imposition of sanctions. Even the production of a few drugs is reduced, if not halted, due to a scarcity of basic substances or spare device components required for drug production. The cost of medicines rises to a point that people with low incomes can only afford a small portion of it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This results in growth of black markets as locations where medicines (occasionally forged) are illegally traded. Additionally, the lack of spare components tends to affect not only medical devices, but also different critical infrastructures such as electric powered generators. Consequently, frequent power outages result in severe problems such as lack of vaccines, tablets, ventilators, monitors, etc. Thus, hundreds of thousands of people die in silence as a result of diseases.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This quiet mass homicide in a tumultuous sector is not always noticed, and may even be overlooked. The same can be said about the current COVID crisis, in which the US refused to lift sanctions against Iran despite the fact that it was dealing with COVID-19 and low vaccination rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Seen in this light, sanctions act as a terrifying mechanism for bringing a country to its knees. There are many ways to deal with 'rogue' states, but depriving people of their humanity is not one of them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shreyansh Verma</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">‘The United States has imposed severe sanctions over the state of North Korea for their new ballistic missile test.’ This is how a typical headline in global politics looks like when a jaw-dropping geopolitically motivated event occurs. At first glance, one might wonder why a country such as the US is so vested in the fund allocation of the North Korean treasury. It all essentially boils down to the degree of influence that a superpower (assumption being that the US is the lone superpower) has over nation states when it comes to their economy and people.&amp;nbsp; The US does so in the larger interest of the world, and considers itself to be the saviour of our generation when it comes to averting a nuclear catastrophe. Since it cannot (and must not) threaten war on many already poverty stricken and poor states, it imposes a series of Keynesian tool-based economic sanctions that prohibit the economic growth of the nation state, as they directly affect the demand and supply chains of the economy and tend to cut them off from more states that are members of ‘the bloc’. The unsettling reality is that disasters similar to Hiroshima and Nagasaki continue to occur in Middle Eastern countries, where war has been raging for decades, and yet we've been so oblivious to their occurrences when we accidentally switch to BBC International after cheering for our football team on the previous channel. But beneath the thick glorious boasts of killing ISIS leaders, annihilating Sanaa (again), and killing millions, there is the far more destructive layer of economic sanctions imposed on seemingly rogue states that disagree with the ideology of the world's leading nation state. The inconvenient reality is that those sanctions, in a roundabout way, have an effect on the health of citizens and frequently bring about devastating consequences. Economic sanctions are of three types: (1) suspension of loans or aid withdrawal by the sender; (2) denial of access to international financial markets; and (3) bans on capital investment in the targeted state. They often involve a sector-specific ban such as an oil ban, textile ban, a ban on using a particular currency or engaging with particular financial operators (such as banks). Intended to impose constraints on the economic activities of the targeted state, economic sanctions aim to prevent a state from importing certain goods or services. They may also prevent a state from exporting its natural resources, agricultural, or manufactured products.&amp;nbsp; Another type of economic sanction specifically targets the banking and financial sectors. Overseas assets, for example, can be frozen or transactions put on hold. Foreign aid may be withheld as well. Economic sanctions are most likely to be detrimental to a country. Refusing to import goods or services from a country can act as a kind of protectionist policy for the target country. This can create a constituency for such policies, making them difficult to repeal. A ban on exporting certain goods and services to a country, such as agricultural products, on the other hand, can harm influential sectors of the target country and make it difficult to impose or sustain such measures. According to Farrokh Habibzadeh's paper Economic sanction: a weapon of mass destruction, the UN Security Council Resolution 661-3 imposed a multilateral sanction on Iraq in 1990, prohibiting the import of all substances other than those intended for scientific purposes, food, and various humanitarian items. The sanction killed approximately 1.5 million people (including more than half a million children) in Iraq - more than the number of people killed in Hiroshima in the aftermath of the nuclear bomb detonation.&amp;nbsp; Many critical life-saving tablets become unavailable due to the imposition of sanctions. Even the production of a few drugs is reduced, if not halted, due to a scarcity of basic substances or spare device components required for drug production. The cost of medicines rises to a point that people with low incomes can only afford a small portion of it.&amp;nbsp; This results in growth of black markets as locations where medicines (occasionally forged) are illegally traded. Additionally, the lack of spare components tends to affect not only medical devices, but also different critical infrastructures such as electric powered generators. Consequently, frequent power outages result in severe problems such as lack of vaccines, tablets, ventilators, monitors, etc. Thus, hundreds of thousands of people die in silence as a result of diseases.&amp;nbsp; This quiet mass homicide in a tumultuous sector is not always noticed, and may even be overlooked. The same can be said about the current COVID crisis, in which the US refused to lift sanctions against Iran despite the fact that it was dealing with COVID-19 and low vaccination rates. Seen in this light, sanctions act as a terrifying mechanism for bringing a country to its knees. There are many ways to deal with 'rogue' states, but depriving people of their humanity is not one of them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dark Disney: Use of Mature Themes in Children’s Animation</title><link href="/Dark-Disney-Use-of-Mature-Themes-in-Children-s-Animation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dark Disney: Use of Mature Themes in Children’s Animation" /><published>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Dark-Disney-Use-of-Mature-Themes-in-Children-s-Animation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dark-Disney-Use-of-Mature-Themes-in-Children-s-Animation">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Disney’s &lt;em&gt;Encanto&lt;/em&gt; has been the talk of the town for several months now. Apart from featuring multiple incredible songs with relatable lyrics like &lt;em&gt;Surface Pressure&lt;/em&gt;, the movie has numerous other factors working in its favour. One of them is the incorporation of 'heavy themes' like intergenerational trauma, neglect and so on. However, this isn’t the first time that Disney has successfully incorporated a more mature theme in a children’s movie. In fact, several other such animated movies, though severely underrated, exist and are a great watch for audiences of all ages because of their art, stories and themes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lilo &amp;amp; Stitch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This movie is perhaps among the best animated movies to ever exist. It is a truly unique story about two Hawaiian orphans, the antisocial six-year-old Lilo Pelekai and her older sister, Nani. After the death of their parents in a car accident, Nani is forced to take up the responsibility of her sister, even though she herself is only a young adult. Lilo adopts Stitch, a genetically engineered alien that distantly resembles a blue koala. Released in 2002, the movie stands out among its contemporaries because of its storyline and themes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Bechdel-Wallace test is a popular measure used to check for female representation in various productions. It is easy to pass the test: the production must have at least two female characters, who have names and converse with each other about anything but a man. Unfortunately, most movies fail this test even today. “Lilo and Stitch” stands out in this regard because not only does it pass the test, but also one of its central themes is the relationship between the two sisters. Such a theme was extremely rare back then and the scene hasn’t changed much since. There are some exceptions of course. Most notably, “Frozen” features two royal sisters- the first of its kind in the Disney princess lineup.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Lilo is often misunderstood as a bratty child by the audience as she often misbehaves and lashes out at Nani. However, acting out is common in those who have had deeply traumatic experiences as the two sisters have. Unlike most Disney movies, where the character would most likely be grateful to the older sister, this is a more realistic depiction of the consequences of a tragedy. Lilo also articulates the reason for her anger: “I like you better as a sister than a mom&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;” and the realisation: “We’re a broken family, aren’t we?”. The story also explores their economic hardships and other struggles that come with their kind of family dynamic, including Nani trying to prove to a rightfully tough social worker named Cobra Bubbles that she is a responsible caregiver. At one point, even after giving Nani a chance to prove herself, Cobra Bubbles realises that Lilo is not safe in the household and that her sister is not a suitable guardian because of her temper and immaturity. The sisters come very close to separation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The art is yet another thing that deserves a lot of praise. Nani, unlike most animated young women, is dark-skinned, pug-nosed and has a curvy figure. Also, the story does not make a big deal out of this. That is to say, her not being pretty in terms of the West’s definition of the word is not a central theme and quite unlike most of its contemporary movies, there is no ugly duckling to swan transformation. She is strong and real, and certainly not a damsel in distress. We also get a glimpse of her budding romance with David, her coworker.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another important theme is love and redemption. Lilo’s need for companionship and Stitch’s desire for a sense of belonging defines their relationship. Stitch was originally a mere experiment (Experiment 626) aimed to cause destruction. However, the love and kindness that Lilo shows helps Stitch make revelations about humanity and opt for a path of change. The film features some of the most iconic Disney dialogues including Lilo’s “Ohana means family, family means no one gets left behind or forgotten. But if you want to leave, you can. I'll remember you though. I remember everyone that leaves.” and Stitch’s “This is my family. I found it all on my own. It is little and broken but still good. Yeah…”. At the end of the movie, Stitch, Jumba and Pleakley become a part of Nani and Lilo’s family, relieving some of Nani’s burdens and creating a better environment for Lilo to grow up in.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Hunchback of Notre Dame&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A strong competition for the crown of the best animated film ever is &lt;em&gt;The Hunchback of the Notre Dame&lt;/em&gt; based on the Victor Hugo novel of the same name. Now, for those who have read the novel before, the title itself raises some red flags considering the fact that the movie is meant for children. An uninitiated child might not be able to notice the themes in play in the movie, but as an adult, watching it again, the messaging is clear and very important.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The story revolves around Claude Frollo, who is extremely prejudiced against gypsies. He calls them “sinful, invading gypsies” and is consumed by the desire to rid Paris of them, by any means necessary. Frollo’s abuse of power and rhetoric that aims to “other” the gipsies is one that we hear often even today, especially in the context of immigrants. Songs like “God Help the Outcasts” sung by the female protagonist and an outspoken gypsy woman, Esmeralda really leaves no space for doubt regarding what the story is about. She begs God, whom she confesses might not be the kind to pay heed to a meer gypsy’s prayer, to help her people, the “The poor and downtrodden”. She knows that there are those who are “Less lucky than I” and insists that God should help them because all of them, even though outcasts from society, are the “children of God”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another victim of Frollo’s beliefs is the male protagonist Quasimodo. The film begins with Frollo pursuing some gypsies. Quasimodo’s mother is among them and she dies on the steps of the Notre Dame Cathedral during the pursuit. The Archdeacon, a clergyman of the cathedral, witnesses her death when he walks out to respond to her call for sanctuary. He is presented as a positive character, antithetical to Frollo’s character and ways. In the book, however, Frollo was the Archdeacon. Keeping it that way would have caused issues with the Church, which is probably why this change was made. The Archdeacon insists that Frollo take up the guardianship of Quasimodo to make up for his sin of killing his mother.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Quasi is physically deformed and his guardian is utterly repulsed by him. He is constantly told that he is a monster that even his own birth mother did not want, and that what little Frollo does for him is a great act of mercy. Quasi spends his life in the Notre Dame, hidden from everyone else, resenting the way he looks and with a job to ring the bells of the cathedral as required. His self-respect is severely damaged and he is left afraid of the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The story also provides a commentary on the mob mentality that results in Quasi’s public humiliation during the Festival of Fools and towards the end of the film, the burning of the city of Paris. Much like Esmeralda, Quasi is an outcast looking for a sense of safety and belonging. However, not only does she not see the reason to make him an outcast because of his looks, Esmeralda stands up for him during the Festival of Fools. These are among the reasons that he falls for her. However, Esmeralda falls in love with Phoebus. At the end of the movie, we see Quasimodo accept the fact that Esmeralda is in love with someone else (which is in contrast with Frollo’s actions, as discussed in the following paragraphs). It is common to have characters in a similar situation take this as a challenge and pursue the woman relentlessly or get mad at the world for being “friend-zoned”. This protagonist, on the other hand, takes a more realistic and healthy approach to the situation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The most shocking aspect of the film is the representation of Judge Frollo as a lascivious character. It is his lust for Esmeralda that makes him burn down Paris. In one scene, he sniffs her hair and the following exchange takes place:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Esmeralda: &quot;What are you doing?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Frollo: &quot;I was just imagining a rope around your neck&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Esmeralda: &quot;I know what you were imagining!&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Frollo even blames her for pushing him to commit a sin in his song &lt;em&gt;Hellfire&lt;/em&gt; (the lyrics showcasing Frollo’s lust for Esmeralda is in stark contrast with the lyrics of &lt;em&gt;Heaven’s Light&lt;/em&gt; that Quasimodo sings moments prior, confessing his love for Esmeralda). The lyrics go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Like fire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Hellfire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This fire in my skin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This burning&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Desire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Is turning me to sin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It's not my fault&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;(Mea culpa)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;I'm not to blame&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;(Mea culpa)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is the gypsy girl&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The witch who set this flame&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;(Mea maxima culpa)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It’s not my fault&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;(Mea culpa)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It in God’s plan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;(Mea culpa)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;He made the devil so much stronger than a man&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;'Mea Culpa' translates to 'my fault'. You can literally see him arguing with himself- whether he wants an answer from Beata Maria (Virgin Mary) or Hell’s fire (he spends most of the time looking at and addressing the fire). Unlike other Disney villains, he is not having the time of his life, he is conflicted. The song is accompanied by some of the darkest visuals and symbolism to exist in any Disney movie: of hellfire and Esmeralda dancing provocatively in the fire. He wants her to be “mine and mine alone” and towards the end of the scene he gives her an ultimatum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Now gypsy, it's your turn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Choose me or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Your pyre&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Be mine or you will burn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;(Kyrie Eleison)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;God have mercy on her&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;(Kyrie Eleison)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;God have mercy on me&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;(Kyrie Eleison)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;But she will be mine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;or she will burn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Frollo is probably the only Disney villain which can and has existed in the past in real life. This only makes him scarier. So, if you did not enjoy the movie as a kid, it's time to watch it again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There are, of course, several other Disney animated movies that are very sophisticated in the themes that they present: &lt;em&gt;Big Hero 6&lt;/em&gt; talks about depression caused by loss, &lt;em&gt;Mulan&lt;/em&gt; talks about misogyny, &lt;em&gt;Luca&lt;/em&gt; talks about fear-mongering and othering, &lt;em&gt;Lion King&lt;/em&gt; talks about familial betrayal, &lt;em&gt;Coco&lt;/em&gt; talks about death, betrayal and familial love, and so on and so forth. These themes make the movies, not only fun for people of all ages to watch, but also introspective and educational, especially for a slightly older audience than the one we usually associate with 'cartoons'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Disney’s Encanto has been the talk of the town for several months now. Apart from featuring multiple incredible songs with relatable lyrics like Surface Pressure, the movie has numerous other factors working in its favour. One of them is the incorporation of 'heavy themes' like intergenerational trauma, neglect and so on. However, this isn’t the first time that Disney has successfully incorporated a more mature theme in a children’s movie. In fact, several other such animated movies, though severely underrated, exist and are a great watch for audiences of all ages because of their art, stories and themes.&amp;nbsp; Lilo &amp;amp; Stitch This movie is perhaps among the best animated movies to ever exist. It is a truly unique story about two Hawaiian orphans, the antisocial six-year-old Lilo Pelekai and her older sister, Nani. After the death of their parents in a car accident, Nani is forced to take up the responsibility of her sister, even though she herself is only a young adult. Lilo adopts Stitch, a genetically engineered alien that distantly resembles a blue koala. Released in 2002, the movie stands out among its contemporaries because of its storyline and themes.&amp;nbsp; The Bechdel-Wallace test is a popular measure used to check for female representation in various productions. It is easy to pass the test: the production must have at least two female characters, who have names and converse with each other about anything but a man. Unfortunately, most movies fail this test even today. “Lilo and Stitch” stands out in this regard because not only does it pass the test, but also one of its central themes is the relationship between the two sisters. Such a theme was extremely rare back then and the scene hasn’t changed much since. There are some exceptions of course. Most notably, “Frozen” features two royal sisters- the first of its kind in the Disney princess lineup.&amp;nbsp; Lilo is often misunderstood as a bratty child by the audience as she often misbehaves and lashes out at Nani. However, acting out is common in those who have had deeply traumatic experiences as the two sisters have. Unlike most Disney movies, where the character would most likely be grateful to the older sister, this is a more realistic depiction of the consequences of a tragedy. Lilo also articulates the reason for her anger: “I like you better as a sister than a mom.” and the realisation: “We’re a broken family, aren’t we?”. The story also explores their economic hardships and other struggles that come with their kind of family dynamic, including Nani trying to prove to a rightfully tough social worker named Cobra Bubbles that she is a responsible caregiver. At one point, even after giving Nani a chance to prove herself, Cobra Bubbles realises that Lilo is not safe in the household and that her sister is not a suitable guardian because of her temper and immaturity. The sisters come very close to separation.&amp;nbsp; The art is yet another thing that deserves a lot of praise. Nani, unlike most animated young women, is dark-skinned, pug-nosed and has a curvy figure. Also, the story does not make a big deal out of this. That is to say, her not being pretty in terms of the West’s definition of the word is not a central theme and quite unlike most of its contemporary movies, there is no ugly duckling to swan transformation. She is strong and real, and certainly not a damsel in distress. We also get a glimpse of her budding romance with David, her coworker.&amp;nbsp; Another important theme is love and redemption. Lilo’s need for companionship and Stitch’s desire for a sense of belonging defines their relationship. Stitch was originally a mere experiment (Experiment 626) aimed to cause destruction. However, the love and kindness that Lilo shows helps Stitch make revelations about humanity and opt for a path of change. The film features some of the most iconic Disney dialogues including Lilo’s “Ohana means family, family means no one gets left behind or forgotten. But if you want to leave, you can. I'll remember you though. I remember everyone that leaves.” and Stitch’s “This is my family. I found it all on my own. It is little and broken but still good. Yeah…”. At the end of the movie, Stitch, Jumba and Pleakley become a part of Nani and Lilo’s family, relieving some of Nani’s burdens and creating a better environment for Lilo to grow up in.&amp;nbsp; The Hunchback of Notre Dame A strong competition for the crown of the best animated film ever is The Hunchback of the Notre Dame based on the Victor Hugo novel of the same name. Now, for those who have read the novel before, the title itself raises some red flags considering the fact that the movie is meant for children. An uninitiated child might not be able to notice the themes in play in the movie, but as an adult, watching it again, the messaging is clear and very important.&amp;nbsp; The story revolves around Claude Frollo, who is extremely prejudiced against gypsies. He calls them “sinful, invading gypsies” and is consumed by the desire to rid Paris of them, by any means necessary. Frollo’s abuse of power and rhetoric that aims to “other” the gipsies is one that we hear often even today, especially in the context of immigrants. Songs like “God Help the Outcasts” sung by the female protagonist and an outspoken gypsy woman, Esmeralda really leaves no space for doubt regarding what the story is about. She begs God, whom she confesses might not be the kind to pay heed to a meer gypsy’s prayer, to help her people, the “The poor and downtrodden”. She knows that there are those who are “Less lucky than I” and insists that God should help them because all of them, even though outcasts from society, are the “children of God”. Another victim of Frollo’s beliefs is the male protagonist Quasimodo. The film begins with Frollo pursuing some gypsies. Quasimodo’s mother is among them and she dies on the steps of the Notre Dame Cathedral during the pursuit. The Archdeacon, a clergyman of the cathedral, witnesses her death when he walks out to respond to her call for sanctuary. He is presented as a positive character, antithetical to Frollo’s character and ways. In the book, however, Frollo was the Archdeacon. Keeping it that way would have caused issues with the Church, which is probably why this change was made. The Archdeacon insists that Frollo take up the guardianship of Quasimodo to make up for his sin of killing his mother.&amp;nbsp; Quasi is physically deformed and his guardian is utterly repulsed by him. He is constantly told that he is a monster that even his own birth mother did not want, and that what little Frollo does for him is a great act of mercy. Quasi spends his life in the Notre Dame, hidden from everyone else, resenting the way he looks and with a job to ring the bells of the cathedral as required. His self-respect is severely damaged and he is left afraid of the world.&amp;nbsp; The story also provides a commentary on the mob mentality that results in Quasi’s public humiliation during the Festival of Fools and towards the end of the film, the burning of the city of Paris. Much like Esmeralda, Quasi is an outcast looking for a sense of safety and belonging. However, not only does she not see the reason to make him an outcast because of his looks, Esmeralda stands up for him during the Festival of Fools. These are among the reasons that he falls for her. However, Esmeralda falls in love with Phoebus. At the end of the movie, we see Quasimodo accept the fact that Esmeralda is in love with someone else (which is in contrast with Frollo’s actions, as discussed in the following paragraphs). It is common to have characters in a similar situation take this as a challenge and pursue the woman relentlessly or get mad at the world for being “friend-zoned”. This protagonist, on the other hand, takes a more realistic and healthy approach to the situation.&amp;nbsp; The most shocking aspect of the film is the representation of Judge Frollo as a lascivious character. It is his lust for Esmeralda that makes him burn down Paris. In one scene, he sniffs her hair and the following exchange takes place: Esmeralda: &quot;What are you doing?&quot;Frollo: &quot;I was just imagining a rope around your neck&quot;Esmeralda: &quot;I know what you were imagining!&quot; Frollo even blames her for pushing him to commit a sin in his song Hellfire (the lyrics showcasing Frollo’s lust for Esmeralda is in stark contrast with the lyrics of Heaven’s Light that Quasimodo sings moments prior, confessing his love for Esmeralda). The lyrics go: Like fireHellfireThis fire in my skinThis burningDesireIs turning me to sinIt's not my fault(Mea culpa)I'm not to blame(Mea culpa)It is the gypsy girlThe witch who set this flame(Mea maxima culpa)It’s not my fault(Mea culpa)It in God’s plan(Mea culpa) He made the devil so much stronger than a man 'Mea Culpa' translates to 'my fault'. You can literally see him arguing with himself- whether he wants an answer from Beata Maria (Virgin Mary) or Hell’s fire (he spends most of the time looking at and addressing the fire). Unlike other Disney villains, he is not having the time of his life, he is conflicted. The song is accompanied by some of the darkest visuals and symbolism to exist in any Disney movie: of hellfire and Esmeralda dancing provocatively in the fire. He wants her to be “mine and mine alone” and towards the end of the scene he gives her an ultimatum: Now gypsy, it's your turnChoose me orYour pyreBe mine or you will burn(Kyrie Eleison)God have mercy on her(Kyrie Eleison)God have mercy on me(Kyrie Eleison)But she will be mineor she will burn! Frollo is probably the only Disney villain which can and has existed in the past in real life. This only makes him scarier. So, if you did not enjoy the movie as a kid, it's time to watch it again.&amp;nbsp; There are, of course, several other Disney animated movies that are very sophisticated in the themes that they present: Big Hero 6 talks about depression caused by loss, Mulan talks about misogyny, Luca talks about fear-mongering and othering, Lion King talks about familial betrayal, Coco talks about death, betrayal and familial love, and so on and so forth. These themes make the movies, not only fun for people of all ages to watch, but also introspective and educational, especially for a slightly older audience than the one we usually associate with 'cartoons'.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Policy Framework for Effective Immunization Coverage of the Indian Population</title><link href="/A-Policy-Framework-for-Effective-Immunization-Coverage-of-the-Indian-Population" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Policy Framework for Effective Immunization Coverage of the Indian Population" /><published>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Policy-Framework-for-Effective-Immunization-Coverage-of-the-Indian-Population</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Policy-Framework-for-Effective-Immunization-Coverage-of-the-Indian-Population">&lt;p&gt;Despite the widespread availability of safe and effective vaccines, disease outbreaks and deaths from vaccine-preventable diseases continue to occur due to poor coverage at all ages, especially in times of COVID-19. Immunization is the most cost-effective way that prevents suffering through sickness, disability and death. India has made significant progress on sustainable and inclusive growth in the past three decades. There is now a greater sense of awareness and expectations from the citizens as the country makes further social and economic progress. But still, there exist significant inequities in vaccination coverage across states based on various factors related to the individual (gender, birth order), family (area of residence, wealth, and parental education), demography structure (religion, caste) and community (access to health care, community literacy level) characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons for Low Immunization Coverage&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to multiple reasons, overall immunization coverage levels are low in India. According to the National Coverage Evaluation Survey of 2009, the reasons for low immunization coverage pertain to issues on the demand and supply side (as given in the figure below). Formative research carried out in 2015 in Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, and Tamil Nadu showed that parents lacked awareness and did not understand the role of immunization in preventing diseases. The perceived threat of vaccine-preventable diseases was overall low. Lack of knowledge of the immunization schedule (the what, when and why), lack of urgency, and prioritization of vaccination are responsible for the low service demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2022-02-27-A-Policy-Framework-for-Effective-Immunization-Coverage-of-the-Indian-Population-image1.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 1: Reasons for low immunization coverage in India (Source: UNICEF CES 2009)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Addressing Immunization Coverage Gaps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In remote areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Planning predictable outreach services&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Leveraging new innovations in supply chain and mapping technology&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Conducting multi-sectoral engagement to address transport challenges&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Designing appropriate service delivery&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In urban areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mapping the urban unimmunized and their numbers&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Overcoming legal obstacles&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Deciding fixed service delivery schedules&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Align and coordinate between overlapping governance systems&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use of innovative data to better account for urban mobility&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Engage strategically with private health care providers&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop and expand mechanisms for registration and reminders, including harnessing the potential of new technology and mobile systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conflict-affected/insecure areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Engaging With non-traditional partners&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Security assessments&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Close community engagement&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Coordination with other humanitarian relief activities&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Flexibility around vaccine scheduling and dosing options&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Promoting&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;fixed-day, fixed time, and fixed-site strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;is effective in delivering immunisation services to ensure that communities are aware of the immunisation day. Anganwadi centres, schools, panchayat grounds and dispensaries can better serve as immunisation sites. Specific days can be fixed for each month as Village Health and Nutrition Days to maximise the opportunity for community mobilisation and service delivery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encouraging&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;catch-up campaigns&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;for all interrupted vaccine schedules (adolescent, college, travel, adults and the elderly), is the need of the hour. Similarly, intensified campaigns for boosting coverage in low performing areas and vulnerable populations need to be implemented. This will be beneficial in increasing demand and building vaccine confidence through communication strategy and stress on preventive health care than curative to prevent the spread of diseases, especially COVID these days.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immunisation sessions&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;may be held with flexible timings. Their reach can be expanded through mobile sessions and mobilisation by other departments. An online portal can be used for timely reporting and supervision.&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;Performance incentives&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;for achievement in immunisation coverage at household, panchayat, block, district and state levels can be given. Promotion of inter-sectoral synergies between organisations, communities and individuals on spreading immunisation. &lt;strong&gt;Strengthening collaborations&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;with ministries, educational bodies, and NGOs need to be taken up to transform the public perceptions and attitudes and to mobilise human and available platforms for immunisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuous&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;skill-building of health workers&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;associated with routine immunisation programs is required to achieve and sustain quality coverage of immunisation. Training modules for front line health workers, medical officers, cold chain and vaccine supply staff need to be prepared and updated periodically to train the staff.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;School health programs&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;need to be stressed as well. The ANMs and other frontline workers’ visits to schools should be mandated at least once a year with vaccines to assess the immunisation status of children. Use of Due List by frontline health workers for tracking beneficiaries is needed and improvement of communication with parents is important to reduce dropouts, which can take place during Parent-Teacher Meetings (PTMs).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing demand and reducing barriers for people to access immunisation services can be very effectively done through improved&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;social mobility&lt;/strong&gt;. ASHA driven mechanisms, such as the mother’s meetings, need to be utilised to promote immunisation messages, discuss how children become vulnerable to diseases, and the various risks involved with lower child immunity. It can educate them on the importance of routine immunisation. Recognising the critical role men play in immunisation decision making and uptake is important. New platforms can be created, such as father’s meetings, to sensitize and orient men on these issues as well. Community and religious male influencers need to be identified to support frontline workers in reaching out to hesitant/resistant male members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensuring&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;adequate funds&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;for communication interventions and activities related to immunisation programs is needed. The available funds can be supplied to dispensaries or government hospitals that can be used by Anganwadi workers, ASHA workers and ANM for these communication efforts and to avoid temporary cash flow issues.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The community members, NGOs and interest groups in immunisation like&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;women’s self-help groups&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;should be involved in advocacy for implementation and increasing demand for services. Where-ever the reports of mistrust towards immunisation by community members are noticed, these should be studied and appropriate corrective actions need to be taken. &lt;strong&gt;New communication material&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;on immunisation should be developed and disseminated widely. New audio-visual communication messages for TV and radio, along with print material needs to be developed. The government can also use social media platforms as a parallel communication channel to increase visibility with multiple target audiences. Institutions like NSS, NCC, etc., can also be mobilised to reach out to school youth and eligible children in hard-to-reach population areas to spread awareness.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High quality and timely&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;immunisation data&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;are vital for immunisation tracking to make informed decisions at local, national, and global levels about better reach. The introduction of new vaccines, documenting and monitoring the impact, and improving the immunisation systems performance by prioritising resources and activities should be of utmost importance. The use of technology for tracking the beneficiaries is extremely helpful. Application-based records, instead of or along with the immunisation cards will help in tracking the number of children, females and other age group people vaccinated at a given point in time. The data will be sent directly to the Department/ ministry that can track the progress and form reports to address the lagging issues and areas. This also solves frontline workers’ issues as their performance will be tracked alongside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vaccination Tracking System&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;should be used to help reduce the gap between reported and evaluated coverage of vaccines. It has to be designed to collate information of all pregnant women and infants into a central database and the database will enable functions like data analysis, report generation, and thus, will contribute to better decision-making and timely and effective allocation of resources. It will act as a feedback system for health workers like nurses, midwives, ASHAs, etc., and will enable better health service delivery by drawing out action plans for health workers for antenatal care, prenatal care and child immunisation. Under this system, SMS alerts and phone calls can also be made to pregnant women, who are nearing the delivery date to remind them of the need to visit the health care centre for prenatal check-up and delivery, and to mothers about their child’s immunisation due dates. Audio-video counselling can also be done using the system to support immunisation activities and create awareness.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New technologies&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;such as the Internet of Things, Artificial Intelligence, and Blockchain can be used track all products in the supply chain and gather data about each product through innovative and cost effective methods. This kind of access to data helps in ensuring proper distribution, prediction of the demand and supply levels, and reducing the cost and wastage of all limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The governments must reduce access barriers to vaccines and vaccination to recover from the negative impacts of the pandemic on routine vaccination coverage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;Vaccine delivery channels&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;can be expanded to include pharmacy-based, community-based, employer-based, residential-care-based, and school-based delivery of vaccinations, to support successful implementation of life-course immunisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ‘one-size-fits-all’ approach is no longer appropriate in this changing world. The diverse dynamics must be addressed at sub-national levels to achieve better immunisation coverage. Immunisation programmes require continued nurturing and attention to remain as a resilient service delivery platform for primary health care and to take advantage of and harness new technologies to reach unimmunised children in the remotest parts of the country.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swati Solanki</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Despite the widespread availability of safe and effective vaccines, disease outbreaks and deaths from vaccine-preventable diseases continue to occur due to poor coverage at all ages, especially in times of COVID-19. Immunization is the most cost-effective way that prevents suffering through sickness, disability and death. India has made significant progress on sustainable and inclusive growth in the past three decades. There is now a greater sense of awareness and expectations from the citizens as the country makes further social and economic progress. But still, there exist significant inequities in vaccination coverage across states based on various factors related to the individual (gender, birth order), family (area of residence, wealth, and parental education), demography structure (religion, caste) and community (access to health care, community literacy level) characteristics. Reasons for Low Immunization Coverage&amp;nbsp; Due to multiple reasons, overall immunization coverage levels are low in India. According to the National Coverage Evaluation Survey of 2009, the reasons for low immunization coverage pertain to issues on the demand and supply side (as given in the figure below). Formative research carried out in 2015 in Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, and Tamil Nadu showed that parents lacked awareness and did not understand the role of immunization in preventing diseases. The perceived threat of vaccine-preventable diseases was overall low. Lack of knowledge of the immunization schedule (the what, when and why), lack of urgency, and prioritization of vaccination are responsible for the low service demand. Figure 1: Reasons for low immunization coverage in India (Source: UNICEF CES 2009) Addressing Immunization Coverage Gaps In remote areas Planning predictable outreach services&amp;nbsp;Leveraging new innovations in supply chain and mapping technology&amp;nbsp;Conducting multi-sectoral engagement to address transport challenges&amp;nbsp;Designing appropriate service delivery In urban areas Mapping the urban unimmunized and their numbers&amp;nbsp;Overcoming legal obstacles&amp;nbsp;Deciding fixed service delivery schedulesAlign and coordinate between overlapping governance systems&amp;nbsp;Use of innovative data to better account for urban mobilityEngage strategically with private health care providersDevelop and expand mechanisms for registration and reminders, including harnessing the potential of new technology and mobile systems.&amp;nbsp; In conflict-affected/insecure areas Engaging With non-traditional partnersSecurity assessmentsClose community engagement&amp;nbsp;Coordination with other humanitarian relief activitiesFlexibility around vaccine scheduling and dosing options Promoting&amp;nbsp;fixed-day, fixed time, and fixed-site strategies&amp;nbsp;is effective in delivering immunisation services to ensure that communities are aware of the immunisation day. Anganwadi centres, schools, panchayat grounds and dispensaries can better serve as immunisation sites. Specific days can be fixed for each month as Village Health and Nutrition Days to maximise the opportunity for community mobilisation and service delivery.&amp;nbsp; Encouraging&amp;nbsp;catch-up campaigns&amp;nbsp;for all interrupted vaccine schedules (adolescent, college, travel, adults and the elderly), is the need of the hour. Similarly, intensified campaigns for boosting coverage in low performing areas and vulnerable populations need to be implemented. This will be beneficial in increasing demand and building vaccine confidence through communication strategy and stress on preventive health care than curative to prevent the spread of diseases, especially COVID these days.&amp;nbsp; Immunisation sessions&amp;nbsp;may be held with flexible timings. Their reach can be expanded through mobile sessions and mobilisation by other departments. An online portal can be used for timely reporting and supervision.&amp;nbsp;Performance incentives&amp;nbsp;for achievement in immunisation coverage at household, panchayat, block, district and state levels can be given. Promotion of inter-sectoral synergies between organisations, communities and individuals on spreading immunisation. Strengthening collaborations&amp;nbsp;with ministries, educational bodies, and NGOs need to be taken up to transform the public perceptions and attitudes and to mobilise human and available platforms for immunisation.&amp;nbsp; Continuous&amp;nbsp;skill-building of health workers&amp;nbsp;associated with routine immunisation programs is required to achieve and sustain quality coverage of immunisation. Training modules for front line health workers, medical officers, cold chain and vaccine supply staff need to be prepared and updated periodically to train the staff.&amp;nbsp; School health programs&amp;nbsp;need to be stressed as well. The ANMs and other frontline workers’ visits to schools should be mandated at least once a year with vaccines to assess the immunisation status of children. Use of Due List by frontline health workers for tracking beneficiaries is needed and improvement of communication with parents is important to reduce dropouts, which can take place during Parent-Teacher Meetings (PTMs).&amp;nbsp; Increasing demand and reducing barriers for people to access immunisation services can be very effectively done through improved&amp;nbsp;social mobility. ASHA driven mechanisms, such as the mother’s meetings, need to be utilised to promote immunisation messages, discuss how children become vulnerable to diseases, and the various risks involved with lower child immunity. It can educate them on the importance of routine immunisation. Recognising the critical role men play in immunisation decision making and uptake is important. New platforms can be created, such as father’s meetings, to sensitize and orient men on these issues as well. Community and religious male influencers need to be identified to support frontline workers in reaching out to hesitant/resistant male members. Ensuring&amp;nbsp;adequate funds&amp;nbsp;for communication interventions and activities related to immunisation programs is needed. The available funds can be supplied to dispensaries or government hospitals that can be used by Anganwadi workers, ASHA workers and ANM for these communication efforts and to avoid temporary cash flow issues.&amp;nbsp; The community members, NGOs and interest groups in immunisation like&amp;nbsp;women’s self-help groups&amp;nbsp;should be involved in advocacy for implementation and increasing demand for services. Where-ever the reports of mistrust towards immunisation by community members are noticed, these should be studied and appropriate corrective actions need to be taken. New communication material&amp;nbsp;on immunisation should be developed and disseminated widely. New audio-visual communication messages for TV and radio, along with print material needs to be developed. The government can also use social media platforms as a parallel communication channel to increase visibility with multiple target audiences. Institutions like NSS, NCC, etc., can also be mobilised to reach out to school youth and eligible children in hard-to-reach population areas to spread awareness.&amp;nbsp; High quality and timely&amp;nbsp;immunisation data&amp;nbsp;are vital for immunisation tracking to make informed decisions at local, national, and global levels about better reach. The introduction of new vaccines, documenting and monitoring the impact, and improving the immunisation systems performance by prioritising resources and activities should be of utmost importance. The use of technology for tracking the beneficiaries is extremely helpful. Application-based records, instead of or along with the immunisation cards will help in tracking the number of children, females and other age group people vaccinated at a given point in time. The data will be sent directly to the Department/ ministry that can track the progress and form reports to address the lagging issues and areas. This also solves frontline workers’ issues as their performance will be tracked alongside. Vaccination Tracking System&amp;nbsp;should be used to help reduce the gap between reported and evaluated coverage of vaccines. It has to be designed to collate information of all pregnant women and infants into a central database and the database will enable functions like data analysis, report generation, and thus, will contribute to better decision-making and timely and effective allocation of resources. It will act as a feedback system for health workers like nurses, midwives, ASHAs, etc., and will enable better health service delivery by drawing out action plans for health workers for antenatal care, prenatal care and child immunisation. Under this system, SMS alerts and phone calls can also be made to pregnant women, who are nearing the delivery date to remind them of the need to visit the health care centre for prenatal check-up and delivery, and to mothers about their child’s immunisation due dates. Audio-video counselling can also be done using the system to support immunisation activities and create awareness.&amp;nbsp; New technologies&amp;nbsp;such as the Internet of Things, Artificial Intelligence, and Blockchain can be used track all products in the supply chain and gather data about each product through innovative and cost effective methods. This kind of access to data helps in ensuring proper distribution, prediction of the demand and supply levels, and reducing the cost and wastage of all limited resources. The governments must reduce access barriers to vaccines and vaccination to recover from the negative impacts of the pandemic on routine vaccination coverage.&amp;nbsp;Vaccine delivery channels&amp;nbsp;can be expanded to include pharmacy-based, community-based, employer-based, residential-care-based, and school-based delivery of vaccinations, to support successful implementation of life-course immunisation. A ‘one-size-fits-all’ approach is no longer appropriate in this changing world. The diverse dynamics must be addressed at sub-national levels to achieve better immunisation coverage. Immunisation programmes require continued nurturing and attention to remain as a resilient service delivery platform for primary health care and to take advantage of and harness new technologies to reach unimmunised children in the remotest parts of the country.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bitcoin: The 21st Century Dutch Tulip Mania</title><link href="/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitcoin: The 21st Century Dutch Tulip Mania" /><published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Amsterdam Stock Exchange (AEX), regarded as the predecessor of contemporary investing, paved the way for modern stock exchanges. However, it was also responsible for facilitating the first financial bubble in history, namely, the ‘Dutch tulip bulb market bubble’. It happened in Holland during the early 1600’s when speculation drove the value of tulip bulbs to extremes. At the market’s peak, the rarest tulip bulbs were traded for as much as six times the average person's annual salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Tulips first arrived in Western Europe from native Turkey in the late 1500’s. Initially purchased as a status symbol by the wealthy, they attracted the attention of the middle class. In 1634, tulip mania swept through Holland. Charles Mackay stated: &quot;The rage among the Dutch to possess (tulip bulbs) was so great that the ordinary industry of the country was neglected, and the population, even to its lowest dregs, embarked in the tulip trade.&quot; According to McKay, a single bulb could be worth as much as 4,000 or even 5,500 florins. In today's monetary terms, the best tulips would cost upwards of $750,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By 1636, the demand for the tulip trade was so high that regular marts for their sale were established on the Stock Exchange of Amsterdam, in Rotterdam, Haarlem, and other towns. Professional traders joined in at that time, and everyone seemed to be making money just by purchasing these rare bulbs. The price of tulips seemed to only go up. People began buying tulips with leverage, using derivatives contracts to acquire more than they could afford. Despite the promising start, confidence got quickly shattered.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By the end of the year 1637, prices began to decline and then never really went up. The rapid decline was largely caused by people purchasing bulbs on credit in the hope of repaying their loans when they sold them for a profit. As prices fell, the bulb holders were forced to liquidate and declare bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; By 1638, tulip bulb prices had crashed, returning to the price levels they had once commanded upon their arrival in Holland. As a result of the Dutch tulip mania, the economy slowed down in the Dutch Golden Age. As the prices fell, demand decreased along with household spending, resulting in a shrinking economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, the actual impact of the incident is often questioned by cynics. Irrespective of the scale of the event, it does teach us an important lesson in investing: be wary of financial bubbles. Bubbles occur when market value erupts rapidly, particularly in the price of assets. Following this rapid inflation, a subsequent contraction occurs. A bubble usually forms when asset prices surge due to exuberant market behaviour. During a bubble, assets typically trade at prices that exceed their intrinsic value by a significant margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Several such economic bubbles have occurred throughout history, such as the South Sea Bubble of 1720, Japan's Asset Price Bubble of the 1980's, the Dotcom bubble, and the 2008 US Housing Bubble. These are some of history's largest financial bubbles, but in recent times, Michael Hartnett, Chief Investment Strategist at Bank of America, has dubbed Bitcoin &quot;the mother of all bubbles.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The scenario around Bitcoin has almost all of the signs of a financial bubble. Bitcoin was launched in 2009 and took two years to reach the price of $1 in February, 2011. However, ten years later, in 2021, at one point it was worth just under $45,000. Hence, it has grown a staggering 45,000 times in ten years, a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 191.16%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even now, when Bitcoin has become culturally mainstream, it continues to be volatile. It doubled investors’ wealth in 2020, but it also halved in 30 days from mid-April to mid-May in 2021. These fluctuations have started to have major impacts on conventional markets such as the stock markets. Bitcoin reached a market cap of over $1 trillion in May of 2021, which is more than the combined market cap of Visa and JPMorgan. Due to its sheer size and the amount of money tied up in this cryptocurrency, when the bubble bursts and Bitcoin hits near-zero, it will be the 'mother of all financial bubbles'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Besides the inexplicable astronomical rise in value, there are numerous other indicators that point to Bitcoin being a quintessential financial bubble. Bitcoin has been labelled as a speculative bubble by eight winners of the Nobel Prize in Economics namely, Paul Krugman, Robert J Shiller, Joseph Stiglitz, Richard Thaler, James Heckman, Thomas Sargent, Angus Deaton, and Oliver Hart. While these economists have discussed a variety of issues concerning Bitcoin and cryptocurrency, the following are the primary reasons for classifying it as a speculative bubble:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lack of Intrinsic Value:&lt;/em&gt; While fiat currencies, which have been in use for as long as one can remember, have no intrinsic value and are backed by faith in the government, they work as a store of value because they can be used to trade almost anywhere and anytime. Furthermore, fluctuations in these currencies are effectively monitored by governments in order to avoid excessive volatility and protect people from unwarranted losses. It is in this regard that Bitcoin completely fails. According to Maddie Shepherd of Fundera, out of an estimated 582 million entrepreneurs in the world, only 15,174 businesses accept Bitcoin as of December 2020. Since it is not an effective medium of exchange, it also fails as a real store of value since it lacks real utility. Furthermore, its volatility is another reason why it is not a reliable store of value. As a result, it is not a real asset and has no intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Susceptibility to market manipulation: &lt;/em&gt;Bitcoin has been artificially driven by tweets from eminent personalities such as Tesla CEO Elon Musk, demonstrating how fickle this market is. The Tesla boss initially supported Bitcoin. In February, he purchased $1.5 billion in Bitcoin for Tesla's balance sheet, and a month later, he announced that the company would begin accepting Bitcoin for electric vehicle purchases. After 49 days, he tweeted that Tesla would no longer accept Bitcoin due to the adverse environmental impact of mining it and subsequently turned his attention to Dogecoin. Thus, tweets with little or no substance are creating and erasing hundreds of billions of dollars in Bitcoin market value. This is a clear indication that a bubble has been brewing for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Price is driven by momentum and attention from retail investors: &lt;/em&gt;Two factors that are behind the soaring price of Bitcoin are momentum and the attention that people pay to it. Momentum means that if Bitcoin goes up more than usual, it will, on average, continue to rise. The fear of missing out on this supposed ‘get rich quick scheme’ keeps the prices high. Similarly, if there are more Google searches for the word Bitcoin, for example, Bitcoin prices tend to go up. Hence, a large proportion of Bitcoin's gains are due to hype, as Bitcoin seems to be at the ‘Peak of Inflated Expectations’ phase on Gartner’s Hype Cycle for Emerging Technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another noteworthy point is that there are no readily identifiable real-world correlations. For example, it is well-known that gold and the US dollar have an inverse relationship. When the dollar is declining in value, gold is likely rising in value. This is a correlation that's been established over a long period. Enthusiasts have pointed out how Bitcoin is a hedge against inflation, but they forget that Bitcoin has both risen and fallen when the money supply expanded rapidly or slowly. Cryptocurrency is driven by emotion and technical analysis, primarily because it has no real-world correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Due to its monumental returns and growing popularity, Bitcoin has gone from being a relatively small niche of the tech industry to a cheat code for institutional investors to boost fund returns at the expense of ignorant retail investors. While the arrival of these investors triggers a spurt in prices, it also marks the beginning of the end for most financial bubbles. There is very little contrast between the Tulip Mania of 400 years ago and the current Bitcoin situation. Both started insignificantly, only to become public frenzies very soon. And in the pursuit of making an easy profit, the Tulip Bulbs imploded, which points to what is inevitably coming for Bitcoin. The bubble will eventually burst.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Raghav Dhariwal</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The Amsterdam Stock Exchange (AEX), regarded as the predecessor of contemporary investing, paved the way for modern stock exchanges. However, it was also responsible for facilitating the first financial bubble in history, namely, the ‘Dutch tulip bulb market bubble’. It happened in Holland during the early 1600’s when speculation drove the value of tulip bulbs to extremes. At the market’s peak, the rarest tulip bulbs were traded for as much as six times the average person's annual salary. Tulips first arrived in Western Europe from native Turkey in the late 1500’s. Initially purchased as a status symbol by the wealthy, they attracted the attention of the middle class. In 1634, tulip mania swept through Holland. Charles Mackay stated: &quot;The rage among the Dutch to possess (tulip bulbs) was so great that the ordinary industry of the country was neglected, and the population, even to its lowest dregs, embarked in the tulip trade.&quot; According to McKay, a single bulb could be worth as much as 4,000 or even 5,500 florins. In today's monetary terms, the best tulips would cost upwards of $750,000. By 1636, the demand for the tulip trade was so high that regular marts for their sale were established on the Stock Exchange of Amsterdam, in Rotterdam, Haarlem, and other towns. Professional traders joined in at that time, and everyone seemed to be making money just by purchasing these rare bulbs. The price of tulips seemed to only go up. People began buying tulips with leverage, using derivatives contracts to acquire more than they could afford. Despite the promising start, confidence got quickly shattered.&amp;nbsp; By the end of the year 1637, prices began to decline and then never really went up. The rapid decline was largely caused by people purchasing bulbs on credit in the hope of repaying their loans when they sold them for a profit. As prices fell, the bulb holders were forced to liquidate and declare bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; By 1638, tulip bulb prices had crashed, returning to the price levels they had once commanded upon their arrival in Holland. As a result of the Dutch tulip mania, the economy slowed down in the Dutch Golden Age. As the prices fell, demand decreased along with household spending, resulting in a shrinking economy. However, the actual impact of the incident is often questioned by cynics. Irrespective of the scale of the event, it does teach us an important lesson in investing: be wary of financial bubbles. Bubbles occur when market value erupts rapidly, particularly in the price of assets. Following this rapid inflation, a subsequent contraction occurs. A bubble usually forms when asset prices surge due to exuberant market behaviour. During a bubble, assets typically trade at prices that exceed their intrinsic value by a significant margin. Several such economic bubbles have occurred throughout history, such as the South Sea Bubble of 1720, Japan's Asset Price Bubble of the 1980's, the Dotcom bubble, and the 2008 US Housing Bubble. These are some of history's largest financial bubbles, but in recent times, Michael Hartnett, Chief Investment Strategist at Bank of America, has dubbed Bitcoin &quot;the mother of all bubbles.&quot; The scenario around Bitcoin has almost all of the signs of a financial bubble. Bitcoin was launched in 2009 and took two years to reach the price of $1 in February, 2011. However, ten years later, in 2021, at one point it was worth just under $45,000. Hence, it has grown a staggering 45,000 times in ten years, a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 191.16%.&amp;nbsp; Even now, when Bitcoin has become culturally mainstream, it continues to be volatile. It doubled investors’ wealth in 2020, but it also halved in 30 days from mid-April to mid-May in 2021. These fluctuations have started to have major impacts on conventional markets such as the stock markets. Bitcoin reached a market cap of over $1 trillion in May of 2021, which is more than the combined market cap of Visa and JPMorgan. Due to its sheer size and the amount of money tied up in this cryptocurrency, when the bubble bursts and Bitcoin hits near-zero, it will be the 'mother of all financial bubbles'. Besides the inexplicable astronomical rise in value, there are numerous other indicators that point to Bitcoin being a quintessential financial bubble. Bitcoin has been labelled as a speculative bubble by eight winners of the Nobel Prize in Economics namely, Paul Krugman, Robert J Shiller, Joseph Stiglitz, Richard Thaler, James Heckman, Thomas Sargent, Angus Deaton, and Oliver Hart. While these economists have discussed a variety of issues concerning Bitcoin and cryptocurrency, the following are the primary reasons for classifying it as a speculative bubble: Lack of Intrinsic Value: While fiat currencies, which have been in use for as long as one can remember, have no intrinsic value and are backed by faith in the government, they work as a store of value because they can be used to trade almost anywhere and anytime. Furthermore, fluctuations in these currencies are effectively monitored by governments in order to avoid excessive volatility and protect people from unwarranted losses. It is in this regard that Bitcoin completely fails. According to Maddie Shepherd of Fundera, out of an estimated 582 million entrepreneurs in the world, only 15,174 businesses accept Bitcoin as of December 2020. Since it is not an effective medium of exchange, it also fails as a real store of value since it lacks real utility. Furthermore, its volatility is another reason why it is not a reliable store of value. As a result, it is not a real asset and has no intrinsic value. Susceptibility to market manipulation: Bitcoin has been artificially driven by tweets from eminent personalities such as Tesla CEO Elon Musk, demonstrating how fickle this market is. The Tesla boss initially supported Bitcoin. In February, he purchased $1.5 billion in Bitcoin for Tesla's balance sheet, and a month later, he announced that the company would begin accepting Bitcoin for electric vehicle purchases. After 49 days, he tweeted that Tesla would no longer accept Bitcoin due to the adverse environmental impact of mining it and subsequently turned his attention to Dogecoin. Thus, tweets with little or no substance are creating and erasing hundreds of billions of dollars in Bitcoin market value. This is a clear indication that a bubble has been brewing for some time. Price is driven by momentum and attention from retail investors: Two factors that are behind the soaring price of Bitcoin are momentum and the attention that people pay to it. Momentum means that if Bitcoin goes up more than usual, it will, on average, continue to rise. The fear of missing out on this supposed ‘get rich quick scheme’ keeps the prices high. Similarly, if there are more Google searches for the word Bitcoin, for example, Bitcoin prices tend to go up. Hence, a large proportion of Bitcoin's gains are due to hype, as Bitcoin seems to be at the ‘Peak of Inflated Expectations’ phase on Gartner’s Hype Cycle for Emerging Technologies. Another noteworthy point is that there are no readily identifiable real-world correlations. For example, it is well-known that gold and the US dollar have an inverse relationship. When the dollar is declining in value, gold is likely rising in value. This is a correlation that's been established over a long period. Enthusiasts have pointed out how Bitcoin is a hedge against inflation, but they forget that Bitcoin has both risen and fallen when the money supply expanded rapidly or slowly. Cryptocurrency is driven by emotion and technical analysis, primarily because it has no real-world correlations. Due to its monumental returns and growing popularity, Bitcoin has gone from being a relatively small niche of the tech industry to a cheat code for institutional investors to boost fund returns at the expense of ignorant retail investors. While the arrival of these investors triggers a spurt in prices, it also marks the beginning of the end for most financial bubbles. There is very little contrast between the Tulip Mania of 400 years ago and the current Bitcoin situation. Both started insignificantly, only to become public frenzies very soon. And in the pursuit of making an easy profit, the Tulip Bulbs imploded, which points to what is inevitably coming for Bitcoin. The bubble will eventually burst.</summary></entry></feed>