<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-29T20:45:29+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up</title><link href="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up" /><published>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up</id><content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up">&lt;p&gt;Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 237&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated UFC 237 saw a Brazilian takeover in the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, with the Fight of the Night being awarded to the epic war between then Strawweight Champion Rose Namajunas and ‘Bate Estaca’ (Pile Driver) Jessica Andrade, who demonstrated her superb strength with a vicious slam knockout to claim the Strawweight belt much to the delight of the Brazilian fans, who all together had enjoyed a torrid evening full of disappointment, with Andrade being one of only four Brazilians to taste victory on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil has always been notorious for showcasing undoubtedly the most hostile fans in MMA. Their unwelcoming spirit to any competitor from outside Brazil was exemplified best in Jared Cannonier’s victory over Anderson Silva in the frustrating co-main event. A leg kick from Cannonier to the knee of Silva ended the fight in unfortunate fashion in the first round, much to the displeasure of the Brazilian fans, who proceeded to boo Cannonier throughout his post-fight interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the match-up between Australia’s Alexander ‘The Great’ Volkanovski and the hometown hero José Aldo did not disappoint. With the crowd expecting the -145 betting favourite José Aldo to pull off a victory that would put him back in title contention, Volkanovski came into the cage relaxed and confident. ‘The Great’ Volkanovski quickly demonstrated why he is considered the Number 1 contender, dominating Aldo for all three rounds with leg kicks and strikes, earning himself a unanimous decision victory, extending his fight win streak to sixteen, and his record in MMA to 19-1-0. This leaves Volkanovski waiting to face the winner of Max Holloway versus Frankie Edgar at UFC 240, whilst José Aldo drops down the rankings to Number 3 in the division, potentially opening up a window for a fight with Number 2 ranked Brian Ortega.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event of UFC 237 saw ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas take on Jessica ‘Bate Estaca’ Andrade in a title showdown for the Women’s Strawweight Title. With Namajunas returning to the Octagon for the first time in over a year after recovering from neck surgery, many expected her not to perform to the same level as her incredible two previous victories over former Strawweight champion Joanna Jedrzejczyk. However, it appeared that Rose was as sharp as ever in the first round, completely out-striking and dominating Andrade for the first five minutes. An attempted but unsuccessful arm-bar submission from Namajunas exemplified the narrative of the first round, with the victory appearing to be merely a formality and an inevitability for the American. Nevertheless, with the backing of her hometown fans, Andrade showed her endurance and determination coming out in the second round pressing Namajunas up to the fence and working for the clinch in order to utilise her far superior strength. Once Andrade secured the clinch, she was able to perform a High Crotch Slam, living up to her nickname ‘Pile Driver’, dumping Namajunas onto the canvas and gaining the KO victory. Andrade’s knockout of Namajunas was only the fourth ever slam KO performed in a UFC title fight, and the first slam KO since Matt Hughes defeated Carlos Newton at UFC 34 in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fight, Namajunas cast doubt over her future in the organisation, hinting at a potential retirement due to the strain it was placing on her life and relationship with husband and coach Pat Barry. All MMA fans hope that this won’t be the end of ‘Thug’ Rose’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Andrade, she will now wait to see whether a rematch with Namajunas is the next step or whether she will face the likes of undefeated contender Tatiana Suarez, who holds massive potential and has been likened to current Men’s Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov due to her superior wrestling ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 238&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prelims saw wins for rising stars such as Tatiana Suarez, Aljamain Sterling and Calvin Kattar. Sterling, who is currently ranked third in the bantamweight division, defeated Pedro Munhoz via unanimous decision, with Munhoz riding high after his KO win over former champion Cody Garbrandt. Sterling controlled the fight with ease, utilising his striking and unique style to win the fight 30-27 on all score cards. This should set Sterling up for a shot at the title, unless Moraes is granted a rematch with Cejudo, in which case it is likely Sterling will face Number 2 ranked Raphael Assuncao.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calvin Kattar showcased exactly why MMA fans are so excited about him with a beautiful first round knockout of Ricardo Lamas. A clean lead left hook followed by a precise and brutal straight right hand ended the fight and catapulted Kattar within touching distance of the top ten of the division. There is certainly a lot on the horizon for the 31 year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tatiana Suarez displayed her talent despite a late rally from opponent Nina Ansaroff to earn a unanimous decision victory and set herself up for a potential title shot against champion Jessica Andrade. Suarez showed persistence and perseverance to secure a takedown early in the first, and proceeded to demonstrate superb top control during the 15 minutes to secure the victory, despite Ansaroff showing great heart in the third round with a great striking game on the feet, winning her the round albeit in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main card began with a heavyweight slugfest between Australia’s Tai Tuivasa and Bulgaria’s Blagoy Ivanov. Ivanov took the fight via unanimous decision. The Bulgarian dropped ‘Bam Bam’ Tuivasa in the first with a fantastic combination and would have won the fight via guillotine choke in the second had the bell not sounded. Despite huge shots from ‘Bam Bam’ threatening throughout the third round, Ivanov saw off Tuivasa to earn the victory with a confident performance that could see him potentially enter the top ten in the Heavyweight division.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petr Yan continued to show why he should be taken seriously at Bantamweight as he defeated Jimmie Rivera, dropping him twice, once in the first and then again in the second round. Rivera rallied to muster the performance he needed in the third round, however the knockdowns gifted Yan two 10-8 rounds, so only a stoppage would have given Rivera the victory. Despite landing shots on Yan in the final round, it was ineffectual as Yan claimed the unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aptly titled People’s Main Event saw two savages in Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson and Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone go to war at Lightweight. The opening round saw the two men stand and trade shots in the centre of the octagon, with Ferguson edging the round by outlanding Cowboy with significant strikes to the head and body. Ferguson’s endurance and pressure fighting style began to pay dividends in the second round, with Cerrone appearing to be slowly broken down by the accuracy of Ferguson’s punches and kicks. The end of the fight came shortly after the bell to end round 2, after Ferguson landed a late blow on Cowboy. Cerrone’s right eye was swollen shut. In an effort to clear the swelling he blew his nose, however, this only worsened the swelling and caused the doctor to call off the fight, awarding Ferguson the TKO victory. Whilst the fight did not end the way many had wished, it was in my opinion a correct decision for the bout to be ended despite protests from Cerrone. Ferguson was visibly upset by the way the fight ended, evidently disappointed in himself for landing the late strike. However, in his post-fight interview with Joe Rogan, Cerrone insisted that his injury was not a result of the strike. An anticlimactic ending but without a doubt one of the most entertaining fights of the night. ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson proved that he deserves a shot against the Lightweight champion Khabib Nurmagomedov by defeating Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone to confirm his position as the man to take on the winner of Khabib versus Dustin Poirier at UFC 242.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The co-main and main event did not hold such disappointment. Here we saw Valentina ‘Bullet’ Shevchenko cement her status as one of the most terrifying female competitors in MMA after defending her Flyweight title in style. Number 1 contender Jessica ‘Evil’ Eye was Shevchenko’s opponent in the Kyrgyzstani’s first defence of the title. Shevchenko showed exactly why she is one of the most devastating and feared fighters in women’s MMA, finishing the fight with a right head-kick that left Eye unconscious and twitching on the canvas for several minutes. In my opinion, Shevchenko has truly reached her peak, and produced one of the scariest KO’s in all of MMA history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Cejudo has arguably experienced the most meteoric rise in success in recent times. This success was furthered by his performance in the main event of UFC 238 at the United Centre in Chicago against Marlon Moraes. Cejudo looked to make history by becoming the first fighter to win an Olympic gold medal and be a 2 division UFC champion. In his way was Brazilian Marlon Moraes, who had been on a 4 fight win streak, finishing the likes of Jimmie Rivera and Raphael Assuncao prior to his title shot. With the vacant bantamweight title up for grabs, both men were plenty fired up in the build up, trading trash talk since the bout was announced. Having beaten TJ Dillashaw in his last fight, Cejudo leapt at the opportunity to become Champ Champ once Dillashaw vacated the title due to him testing positive for EPO in his fight with Cejudo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round saw Moraes take the early initiative, peppering Cejudo with hard leg kicks and strikes, easily winning the round. Moraes was on track to make the fight a one-sided contest, however Cejudo had other plans. ‘The Messenger’ came out in round 2 throwing hard right hands that effectively halted Moraes’ progress and Cejudo was also able to land some hard knees in the clinch, awarding him the second round. The third round showed just how determined and driven Cejudo was to become a double champion. Gaining top position on the ground, Cejudo landed devastating elbows and hammer fists on the visibly broken Moraes, which led to the referee stepping in and ending the fight as Cejudo became the 4th UFC fighter to hold belts in multiple divisions, following in the footsteps of the likes of Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Amanda Nunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This victory undoubtedly puts Cejudo in the conversation for the pound for pound best fighter at this moment in time. Certainly, the likes of Jon Jones and Khabib Nurmagomedov cannot be discounted due to the number of title defences from Jones and Khabib’s phenomenal 27-0 record. However, as Cejudo is the only athlete to have an Olympic gold medal on his resume, he has to, in my opinion, be included within the top 3 or at least the top 5 pound for pound greats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up on the calendar is perhaps the most anticipated card of the year. On July 6th in Las Vegas, UFC 239 sees Jon Jones look to defend his Light Heavyweight title against Thiago Santos, on a card that contains the likes of Amanda Nunes, Ben Askren, Jorge Masvidal, Luke Rockhold and many more. This card promises to be explosive and I believe it will be one of the best events of 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Eakin</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="mma" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League</title><link href="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League" /><published>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</updated><id>/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola">&lt;p&gt;A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for
the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition
in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning
whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically,
whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his
contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition
in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of
all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola
despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions
of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders
such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower
win rate in the competition than Guardiola.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manager&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;UEFA Champions League Finals &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;loss&lt;/span&gt; record (year)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL semi-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL quarter-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of seasons managed in CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL win percentage (%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luis Enrique&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jupp Heynckes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 -1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;98&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zinedine Zidane&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louis Van Gaal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;95&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;96&lt;/span&gt;, 10)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diego Simeone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carlo Ancelotti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Alex Ferguson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;99&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Mourinho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jürgen Klopp&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners
medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and
Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high
standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team
capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a
victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of
having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble
(Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had
sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of
the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester
United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force
that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively
starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first
leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal,
the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the
penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their
‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were
trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a
breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and
the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by
the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever,
again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s
former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with
Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to
play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the
defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to
pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper
Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this
tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg
out of reach for Guardiola’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria
as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time
losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74%
possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled
at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style
being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter
attacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the
understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize.
But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the
semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League
on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which
included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo
Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score
6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering
Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to
an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael
Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club,
were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the
young French side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120
million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these
costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at
Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s
premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham
Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming
performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy
Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical
decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City
largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals
stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a
fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal
could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was
ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning
that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year
of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third
season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals,
having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s
Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable
decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg
between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were
unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with
their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as
Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the
ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading
Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to
win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from
questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta
was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed
them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in
Madrid was incorrectly ruled out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s
success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A
plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way
or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John
Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only
one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped
mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply
luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the
woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only
have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches
higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty
in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have
been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired
straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no
control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end
results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to
be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and
whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade,
he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager
that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions
League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the
trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season).
Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European
campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those
expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City
have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that
has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time
for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League
with multiple clubs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>samuel.hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically, whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team. When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower win rate in the competition than Guardiola. Manager UEFA Champions League Finals win/loss record (year) CL semi-finals reached CL quarter-finals reached Number of seasons managed in CL CL win percentage (%) Luis Enrique 1-0 (15) 1 3 3 73 Jupp Heynckes 2 -1 (98, 12, 13) 4 4 4 70 Zinedine Zidane 3-0 (16, 17, 18) 3 3 4 70 Pep Guardiola 2-0 (09, 11) 7 9 10 61 Louis Van Gaal 1-2 (95, 96, 10) 5 6 10 60 Diego Simeone 0-2 (14, 16) 3 4 6 56 Carlo Ancelotti 3-1 (03, 05, 07, 14) 8 12 17 55 Sir Alex Ferguson 2-2 (99, 08, 09, 11) 7 12 19 54 José Mourinho 2-0 (04, 10) 8 8 16 53 Jürgen Klopp 0-2 (13, 18) 3* 4 6 51 Arsène Wenger 0-1 (06) 3 7 20 47 On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble (Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure.  After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal, the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their ‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo. Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever, again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg out of reach for Guardiola’s side. More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74% possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter attacking. Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize. But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final.  In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score 6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club, were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the young French side. Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120 million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals, having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition.  Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in Madrid was incorrectly ruled out. Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match. Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade, he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season). Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League with multiple clubs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review: The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and His Empire of Truth</title><link href="/The-Calling-of-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and His Empire of Truth" /><published>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Calling-of-History</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Calling-of-History">&lt;p&gt;The first thought that would possibly flash through a person’s mind, after reading Dipesh Chakrabarty’s &lt;em&gt;The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and his Empire of Truth&lt;/em&gt;, is the precision of the title—it effortlessly sums it all up. The book narrates the coming into being of ‘History’  as a discipline in colonial India. This is done beautifully through the character of Jadunath Sarkar – India’s preeminent historian – and his fixation with facts. Spread over a meticulously penned introduction and eight insightful chapters, it is a journey that concerns itself with historical research, and in itself is not a biography of Jadunath Sarkar. But it is based on about 250 private letters, exchanged from 1907 to 1952, between Sarkar and his comrade-in-arms, Govindrao Sakharam Sardesai. The book poignantly recounts the anxieties, struggles and tests of these two historians concerning the craft of historical writing during the initial days of ‘History’ in India. Chakrabarty draws from other archival sources and refers to anecdotes to project a very balanced assessment of Sarkar’s character, which is essential for the purpose of the book. I’m tempted to point out here that, interestingly, in doing so Chakrabarty adopts Sarkar’s technique of constructing characters of historical figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While mapping the birth of History, which was undeniably troubled, Chakrabarty draws attention to the interactions between its ‘public’ and ‘cloistered’ lives, and how each patterned the other. Such interactions concerned Sarkar and Sardesai who called for a ‘scientific’ approach based on &lt;em&gt;facts&lt;/em&gt; to overcome the limitations of histories emerging from the public domain. They adopted the Rankean model where truth is held sacred and history is to be written without compromising on facts. Chakrabarty identifies this as the most contentious issue between Sarkar, Sardesai et al, on the one hand, and the scholars of the &lt;em&gt;Bharat Itihas Samshodhak Mandal&lt;/em&gt; (Indian Historical Records Commission) on the other. There were clashes of ideas, bitter debates, personal condemnations and struggles for control over the Indian Historical Records Commission that, according to Chakrabarty, eventually charted the trajectory of the discipline of History and the institutions associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his lifetime, Sarkar’s positivism and dedication to truth made him resolute enough to accurately document the past - even the unpleasant things that could put one to shame. In fact, Chakrabarty observes, Sarkar was against any form of identity politics of nationalism that compromised on truth, leading to many intellectual skirmishes which earned him the wrath of anti-colonial nationalist historians. Chakrabarty rescues Sarkar from this ignominy though and sets forth to bring out the patriot in him. Sarkar was no doubt a patriot, but not an anti-colonial nationalist. Chakrabarty elaborates, if Ranke intended to serve God, Sarkar’s mission was to serve his nation by writing ‘scientific’ history. Sarkar believed such history writing was the first step towards national development. He recognised not only the glories but also the tragedies and unpleasant facts of the past that would facilitate the building of a strong nation. And for this, Sarkar was of the opinion that the historians needed to be of ‘strong character’. Here, Chakrabarty makes an interesting intervention. He identifies ‘strong character’ as a crucial component of Sarkar’s historical method and notes that, undeniably a man of strong character, Sarkar himself was a part of his method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter deserves a special mention as it is distinct in style as compared to the rest of the book. It is in the form of an imaginary dialogue between Sarkar and the author. It is an imaginary conversation between two historians of two generations having distinct understandings of History. What Chakrabarty does brilliantly is, by staging a dialogue between the two, he reconstructs the character of Sarkar and clarifies Sarkar’s method of history writing and patriotism. The chapter is masterfully crafted and one feels as if a live interview of Sarkar is being taken by the author. Though the two do not see eye-to-eye during the course of this imagined conversation, one feels that there is an attempt to resurrect Sarkar as a historian, and herein lies the skill of the author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final analysis, it seems, the spirit of Sarkar hovers over Chakrabarty who adopts Sarkar’s method of history writing in this book. Drawing from archival sources and remaining faithful to facts, both pleasant and unpleasant, the author sketches a balanced character of Sarkar to tell a larger story—a technique Sarkar fought for throughout his life. While doing so, the author emphasises that Sarkar was a child of the Empire and many of its abstract ideals shaped his ideas. But one wonders whether it would have been more helpful for the readers to conjure a clearer image of Sarkar and understand his ideas better, if Chakrabarty took recourse to the category of class, delving more into Sarkar’s Bengali middle-class location rather than making a couple of passing references. This absence, intentional or otherwise, strikes one particularly when he recalls Chakrabarty’s use of what he classifies as Bengali middle-class material in his more famous &lt;em&gt;*Provincializing Europe&lt;/em&gt;: Postcolonial Thought and Historical Difference&lt;em&gt;, and when one reads his article ‘Limits of Bourgeois Model?’ in Sanjay Joshi’s *The Middle Class in Colonial India&lt;/em&gt;. The point here is not to relate these works of Chakrabarty with the book, but to remind the readers of his authoritative understanding of the Bengali middle-class psyche, as evident from most of his works, and emphasise that they would have benefited more had Chakrabarty elaborated on Jadunath Sarkar’s Bengali middle-class position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before concluding this review let us not miss out on something interesting. Two eminent scholars of South Asian origin, namely Dipesh Chakrabarty and Bhikhu Parekh came up with two fascinating books in 2015. Chakrabarty’s book is the one being reviewed here and Bhikhu Parekh’s is &lt;em&gt;Debating India: Essays on Indian Political Discourse&lt;/em&gt;, a collection of essays written over a span of twenty years. The two books have undoubtedly different themes yet after reading these, one will be compelled to locate commonalities. Both these books focus on debates from the past taking place in India while strongly reflecting on the idea of truth. Also, Chakrabarty’s work, based primarily on letters exchanged privately between two friends, gives us a glimpse of the nature of their friendship, and Parekh’s book has an exclusive chapter on friendship and its different levels and forms. Furthermore, both have taken recourse to a not so common technique of writing dialogically in a chapter in their respective books—Chakrabarty has a chapter in the form of an interview and Parekh has one in the form of letters. It leaves one wondering whether these two scholars were themselves in conversation with each other while working on their respective books! Even if history may not repeat itself, historians certainly seem to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The first thought that would possibly flash through a person’s mind, after reading Dipesh Chakrabarty’s The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and his Empire of Truth, is the precision of the title—it effortlessly sums it all up. The book narrates the coming into being of ‘History’ as a discipline in colonial India. This is done beautifully through the character of Jadunath Sarkar – India’s preeminent historian – and his fixation with facts. Spread over a meticulously penned introduction and eight insightful chapters, it is a journey that concerns itself with historical research, and in itself is not a biography of Jadunath Sarkar. But it is based on about 250 private letters, exchanged from 1907 to 1952, between Sarkar and his comrade-in-arms, Govindrao Sakharam Sardesai. The book poignantly recounts the anxieties, struggles and tests of these two historians concerning the craft of historical writing during the initial days of ‘History’ in India. Chakrabarty draws from other archival sources and refers to anecdotes to project a very balanced assessment of Sarkar’s character, which is essential for the purpose of the book. I’m tempted to point out here that, interestingly, in doing so Chakrabarty adopts Sarkar’s technique of constructing characters of historical figures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discussing The Impact of Sabermetrics on Baseball</title><link href="/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discussing The Impact of Sabermetrics on Baseball" /><published>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball">&lt;p&gt;Advancement in sabermetrics, the application of statistical analysis to baseball records, has become more apparent than ever in the game of baseball today. Major league front offices have adopted a new mindset when it comes to baseball operations and player evaluation. New strategies are being implemented by teams all over the playing field - the most notable among them being the defensive shift. In addition, Major League Baseball itself has dove into sabermetrics by altering some rules and aspects of the game to engage and grow a younger fanbase. With these rapid changes to a traditionally “old-school” game, there has been much controversy as to whether sabermetrics is leading baseball away from its roots and into a money-making machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A baseball fan that turns on the T.V. today would see a shortstop playing behind the second base bag, an outfielder shaded a certain direction based off of a hitter’s tendencies, and pitchers hurrying to get set due to the new pitch clock. All of these small, yet noticeable changes in how the game is played have their root the influx of data-driven observations, suggestions and strategies.The game has never before seen this many changes at a single time. Are these rapid changes too much at once for our historic game? Are these changes coming at a time when baseball is turning into its most vulnerable state? Only time will tell how analytics will affect the state and integrity of our game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, we can only examine how analytics has affected our game in the short-term. Looking back on the 2018 baseball season, many of us were shocked by the success of the Milwaukee Brewers - they advanced to the National League Championship Series against the Los Angeles Dodgers. Much can be attributed to the 2018 NL MVP, Christian Yelich, as the X-Factor to this surprising success. Despite this, many have overlooked the Brewers’ underrated starting rotation, comprised of injury-plagued “no-names”. Yet, this scrappy rotation elevated the Brewers’ team ERA into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fangraphs.com/leaders.aspx?pos=all&amp;amp;stats=sta&amp;amp;lg=all&amp;amp;qual=0&amp;amp;type=8&amp;amp;season=2018&amp;amp;month=0&amp;amp;season1=2018&amp;amp;ind=0&amp;amp;team=0,ts&amp;amp;rost=0&amp;amp;age=0&amp;amp;filter=&amp;amp;players=0&amp;amp;sort=15,d&quot;&gt;top third&lt;/a&gt; of the league last season. A rotation of Chase Anderson, Zach Davies, Jhoulys Chacin, Brent Suter, and Jimmy Nelson combined for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fangraphs.com/leaders.aspx?pos=all&amp;amp;stats=sta&amp;amp;lg=all&amp;amp;qual=0&amp;amp;type=8&amp;amp;season=2018&amp;amp;month=0&amp;amp;season1=2018&amp;amp;ind=0&amp;amp;team=0,ts&amp;amp;rost=0&amp;amp;age=0&amp;amp;filter=&amp;amp;players=0&amp;amp;sort=15,d&quot;&gt;3.92&lt;/a&gt; ERA. A rotation that made an annual combined salary of just over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotrac.com/mlb/milwaukee-brewers/payroll/2018/&quot;&gt;$17 million&lt;/a&gt;. To put this in perspective, Cincinnati Reds starting pitcher &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotrac.com/mlb/rankings/2018/average/starting-pitcher/&quot;&gt;Homer Bailey&lt;/a&gt; makes just over this mark. The small-market Milwaukee Brewers used data-driven analytics to allocate their money and invest it in underrated pitchers that, when used properly, found success as a collective unit. Many teams are following the model that the Brewers followed from the Moneyball Oakland Athletics. This new application of player evaluation has given small-market teams such as the Milwaukee Brewers, Oakland Athletics, and Cleveland Indians, to name a few, a chance for success. Prepare yourselves: the age of sabermetrics is just getting underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, sabermetrics has its cons. One smaller controversial topic that fits under this larger umbrella debate is the role of scouts due to the emergence of Big Data and baseball analysts. Aside from how sabermetrics is affecting the heart of the game, I was also very interested in how it would affect the role of the scout. The role of the scout in today’s game is to be the visual component, the “eyes” of the organization, and to take an initial glance, to decide whether the player is worth a more in-depth look from an analytical perspective. This results in friction between the two sides as scouts are fighting for more power and influence in organizational decisions. One American League West scout described the relationship between the two sides of player evaluation, analytics vs. traditional scouting, when asked if there is ever a “battle” between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“’&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baseballprospectus.com/prospects/article/27318/some-projection-left-ask-the-industry-scouts-on-stats/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wouldn’t call it a battle, but sometimes I think those two sides butt heads. They’re all on the same team but depending on the GM, one side is going to be heard more often than not. When it’s not your side, that’s not a lot of fun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many scouts are worried that their diminished role in player evaluation could eventually lead to an extinction of scouts in our game. 60 scouts have been released by Major League teams in the last year. The Houston Astros Organization released 34 scouts in the last year, double that of the next team behind them. If other teams follow the Houston Astros in their analytically-stricken mindset, baseball will turn into a purely number-based sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a personal point of view, advancement in analytics has helped today’s game without stripping it of its heart and soul. Sabermetrics has not only provided front offices with more information than ever before about player attributes, but has also impacted baseball fan experience. Adding Statcast, an analytical tool that can measure play-by-play metrics live, to the fan perspective has added a new element of entertainment and interest to, as many would say, a dying sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://kwhs.wharton.upenn.edu/2019/03/baseball-big-data-statistics-analytics-changing-game/&quot;&gt;https://kwhs.wharton.upenn.edu/2019/03/baseball-big-data-statistics-analytics-changing-game/&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baseballamerica.com/stories/a-concerning-future-for-traditional-mlb-scouting/&quot;&gt;https://www.baseballamerica.com/stories/a-concerning-future-for-traditional-mlb-scouting/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jacob.benabou</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="baseball" /><summary type="html">Advancement in sabermetrics, the application of statistical analysis to baseball records, has become more apparent than ever in the game of baseball today. Major league front offices have adopted a new mindset when it comes to baseball operations and player evaluation. New strategies are being implemented by teams all over the playing field - the most notable among them being the defensive shift. In addition, Major League Baseball itself has dove into sabermetrics by altering some rules and aspects of the game to engage and grow a younger fanbase. With these rapid changes to a traditionally “old-school” game, there has been much controversy as to whether sabermetrics is leading baseball away from its roots and into a money-making machine.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Tale of Two Brothers</title><link href="/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Brothers" /><published>2019-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CHINA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wedged between the Eastern Coast and the mainland of China, lies the ancient province of Zhongyuan. Historically renowned as the birthplace of the Chinese civilisation, it is home to a multitude of heritage sites ranging from the ruins of the Shang dynasty to the Eight Great Ancient Capitals of the nation. Its nearly-bygone eminence, in part, can be attributed to its fertile mainland, to the river Huang-He that runs through its veins, and perhaps, even to some of its women, like Lady Fu Hao who managed to bloom through the misogynistic past of the nation. Skip ahead a thousand years to the current millennium, and we find that much like the Ancient Greece, Zhongyuan is a graveyard of distant and glorious memories. Although it is now a set of vast agricultural lands with a reasonably efficient productivity level, it’s the demographic structure is quite the disaster. The sex ratio of the province, much more skewed than that of the entire nation, is at a startling 118 men for every 100 women. This implies that nearly one-fifth of the men may not find even a match for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ancient Chinese philosophy of contrasting a passive female principle (Yin) to an active male principle (Yang) for creating a complementary match is the base for the patriarchy that has dominated the traditional family structures in China, which must ideally be patrilineal and prescriptively virilocal. Despite the nation being colonised and later having been through a long regime of Communism, these basic traditions never changed for the common people. Mao Zedong’s antipathy to religion reshaped private beliefs but these traditions were so deep-rooted that they remained unscathed. And so, when the ‘One Child Policy’ was introduced in 1979 (or a decade prior for some parts of the nation), a natural preference for boys arose more predominantly in the countryside areas like Zhongyuan. This gave rise to the current situation of numerous Gen-Y ‘Bachelor Towns’ where men struggle to find wives, not only because there simply aren’t enough women but also because they’re being subjected to societal shaming, such as by being called ‘&lt;em&gt;guanggun&lt;/em&gt;’ or dead branches. On the other hand, the women have to both endure increasing sexual crimes, and take advantage of natural selection, which drives them to marry the higher educated men in the cities. The disparity, after two generations ageing without cousins and siblings, is so vast that many economists believe that retracting the policy in 2015 was a little too late to reestablish balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With hopes of a higher income, and a greater chance at finding a match, thousands of men move to the Pearl River Delta each day, which has nearly 60,000 factories employing 3-4 million people and has much role in making China &lt;em&gt;The World’s Factory&lt;/em&gt;. The Pearl Delta is primarily where all the rapid growth of China came from and where all its FDI went. The workforce is gender-neutral, and even though the balance has shifted from 70-30 in favour of women, to nearly 50-50 now, it still leaves sufficient room for couples to make and breakup at the assembly line each morning. The region additionally includes Shenzhen, the tech hub where the nation’s second stock exchange is situated. Shenzhen acts as an outlet for the labour to cater to the foreign investment projects that have recently been undertaken by China, with an increasing frequency, primarily in poor and middle-income nations of Southeast Asia and Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government’s ambitious programme to create the modern maritime silk route under the Belt and Road Initiative has been met by skepticism in the West, who have resorted to calling it ‘chequebook diplomacy’. But for China, these projects have rendered both a macroeconomic dominance and an unconventional solution to the gender problem, since the projects have eased not only China’s international relations, but also the visa requirements for its citizens to travel to these nations. Thus, many men from Zhongyuan, take on the months’ long journey to nations like Myanmar, Philippines, Indonesia and, recently, Pakistan, to set up a deal with local traffickers who can easily arrange for young women―whose parents willingly participate in such international betrothals in exchange for some money―and the hope for a better future for their daughters. An approximate cost of $10,000 is all it takes for these men to conform to the societal script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PAKISTAN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warmed by the wrath of the 1962 Sino-Indian War and the Cold War, the diplomatic relations between China and Pakistan bolstered through the years, and lately they come to be known as the ‘Iron Brothers’. Metaphorically speaking, both the brothers have grown in different directions, but factually, only one has moved for what we could call ‘growth’, while the other, i.e. Pakistan is struggling in a slough of debt. But China, being the generous brother that it is, has interceded to the rescue of Pakistan by making its international commercial initiative more inclusive through the China Pakistan Economic Corridor (CPEC). It is a project whose combined value was recently estimated to be $62 billion, which is greater than the total amount of FDI in Pakistan since 1970. The two-armed project will connect pipelines, roads and bridges via a 2700 km stretch to the deepwater ports at Karachi and Gwadar, where the latter will be redesigned to increase its cargo capacity from 1 million tonnes to 400 million tonnes, making it one of the most sophisticated ports to ever exist. It will additionally simulate much-needed growth in Pakistan. In fact, nearly $30 billion is dedicated to energy projects, which will generate 7000 MW of energy, contributing to 3% of Pakistan’s GDP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China too has much to gain from this brotherly affection, however. The most prominent underlying advantage being that it will be able to systematically bypass the maritime chokepoints of the South China Sea, and gain control of other strategic hotspots. This is why it is willing to risk venturing into the politically unstable regions of Baloch, Sindh and Khyber-Pakhtunkhwa, while the elite of Islamabad want to systematically cut Baloch out of the Gwadar equation. This marginalisation has partially fueled the rise of Balochi separatists, who recently attacked a bus full of Chinese engineers, prompting China to consider deploying its own troops in Pakistan for the protection of its workers. Considering the fragile situation of the Pakistani economy, with their Rupee falling by over 20% last year, paying off the debt has become even harder, while the forex reserves are below the $10 billion mark. An IMF bailout would pose conditions of coming clean with the CPEC books, and would compel Pakistan to expose the chequebook diplomacy, which is quite unlikely. So, in the foreseeable future, this ‘brotherhood’ is bound to strengthen, as more loans are lent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rising influx of Chinese men, who may not necessarily have a job, is owed to the visa-on-arrival policy for the ease of the Chinese people. Last year alone, over 91,000 Chinese people visited the country and 32,000 visas of Chinese nationals were extended. This has threatened the safety of the women in villages. Trafficking is a profitable business and the minorities, like the Christian community, are specifically targeted, since the Pakistani government is visibly unconcerned about them, as is reflected in the escape of Asia Bibi, the Christian woman who fled the nation after fearing death threats from ordinary citizens, even after she had been aquitted of blasphemy charges. The minorities also appeal to the Chinese men due to their ethnocentrist approach to the Muslim community, the proof being their tyrannical crackdowns on the local Uighur Muslim minority of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan’s Federal Investigation Agency (FIA) approximated that nearly 700 Christian and 300 Muslim women, many underage, were at risk of sexual slavery after falling for the pretext of marriage, as of 2018. Recently, Natasha Robin, 22, who was promised a life free of destitution, had agreed to marry a Chinese suitor whom she had met through an unlawful matchmaking agency. After twelve days of being subjected to the mental and physical torment of sex slavery, she managed to escape. Others have not been so lucky. This callousness of Pakistan towards its women may pose demographic threats to its own environment, since female infanticide is already prevalent and trafficking might further aggravate the sex ratio, which is already at a worrying 106 men per 100 women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggressive policy measures, for adherence to economic indicators, have often put the well being of the population at stake, China made this mistake and has ended up destabilising the sex ratio for the sake of ameliorating the demographic pressure. Pakistan is in pursuit of a disaster if doesn’t curb the illegal activities that accompany China’s growth agenda. It must reconsider if this brotherhood is in fact as mutually beneficial as China claims it to be. As for the people of Zhongyuan, who adulate their Supreme Leader Mao, it’s high time they act on one of his rare rational beliefs: ‘&lt;em&gt;Women hold up half the sky&lt;/em&gt;’. The next few months are crucial to see how the situation pans out further, whether in favour of the local population of the remote Pakistani areas, or the elite of Islamabad who concern themselves with fairly active policy measures to rebuild the economy whilst neglecting the ground-level work towards ensuring a safe and secure environment for their own people.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">CHINA</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Jihad</title><link href="/Understanding-Jihad" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Jihad" /><published>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Understanding-Jihad</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-Jihad">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jihad&lt;/em&gt;; possibly the most polarising word in the Arabic language. It provokes a range of varied reactions, depending on the perspective through which one looks at it. And it is true to say that the word has largely been misunderstood in non-Muslim circles. So before I even begin said analysis, I must make a series of clarifications and preliminary disclaimers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, my article is not intended to be an attack upon the Muslim community. Nor is it meant to be a criticism of individual Muslims. Some of the most kind, brotherly and loving people I have met are devout practicing Muslims and I am grateful to God for their friendship. I also recognise that there are countless members of the Islamic &lt;em&gt;ummah&lt;/em&gt; who are peaceful and humane people, truly worthy of our respect as fellow human beings. My article is not meant to be an indictment of the entire Muslim people. Rather, my goal is to analyse the concept of &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;, and how it has been understood by most of the mainstream Islamic schools of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I recognise and mourn the tragedies and persecutions which Muslim people have had to endure. I condemn in no uncertain terms the attacks upon innocent Muslims that have taken place on account of their faith. No one should ever be harmed or attacked or despised or be held in suspicion simply for being a Muslim. Indeed, my goal is not to spread suspicion against Muslims. I invite all people to extend their arms wide open in welcome for their Muslim friends, neighbours and fellow human beings, especially to Muslim refugees in need, and to give them the love and the affection that we indeed owe them as fellow citizens of this Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, my criticisms will not apply to quite a few schools of thought in Islam. They do not apply, for example, to the Ahmadi Muslim Community, which I consider to be the most peaceful sect of Islam. Nor do they apply to the Ibadis, who have proven themselves to be very tolerant and welcoming, and regarding their theology I have little knowledge and have no wish to pontificate. My criticisms mostly apply to Sunni and Shia schools of thought, but even among them there are exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I do not pretend to be a scholar of Islam. I am merely an interested layperson. So take all my claims with a grain of salt. Fact-check them and see if they are correct. I write with little formal authority on the subject, but with the firmest of convictions that I am right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, please don’t be surprised that the views I document, describe and criticise in this article are not held by many of the average Muslims. Laypeople of all religions are known to have a poor track record of understanding what their religion actually teaches, and it is not uncommon to see that at times the views of laypeople are significantly at variance with the views of their own religious leaders. A good example is seen among some ‘Catholics’ in North America, many of whom practice contraception and have no problem with abortion, both of which are strongly condemned by the leaders of the Church they belong to and claim to profess faith in. Similarly, many ‘Protestants’ in England and Northern Europe don’t even believe in a physical Resurrection anymore, a belief which is absolutely central to historic Protestant orthodoxy. The views of laypeople are rarely barometers for the beliefs of the religion they follow, though, of course, there are exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that said, let us press on the main subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you are me and you hail from a liberal background and you’ve had the same experience I’ve had, one of the first things you would have heard about Islam – especially from Westernised non-Muslim liberals – is how wonderful it truly is. You would have been told that Islam promotes peace, harmony, cultural diversity, coexistence and the emancipation of women. You would even have been informed that the word ‘Islam’ has its roots in a word which means ‘peace’. And, of course, you would have been told that the word ‘jihad’ does not mean ‘terrorism’ or ‘holy war’ but rather ‘struggle’. And don’t we all struggle against something or the other, especially against the faults in our own personality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, much of these claims are true, to some degree or the other. However, the problem is that this narrative, although it certainly has a grain of truth, does not tell the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that ‘jihad’ does not mean ‘terrorism’ or ‘violence’ but ‘struggle’. But what many people aren’t told is that the ‘struggle’ in Islam is not merely against personal faults, but also against injustice in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some of you might be wondering, “Well, what’s wrong with that? Surely, we all have a duty to fight injustice?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is not that Islam exhorts war against injustice. The issue, however, is how Islam defines injustice. And injustice, in the Islamic context, is quite different from the SJW conception of ‘injustice’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Islamic word for this is &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;. It literally means ‘corruption’ or ‘rottenness’. Consider, for instance, the following passage from the Quran, which talks about people who promote &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;When they are told, ‘Do not cause corruption on the earth,’ they say, ‘We are only reformers!’
Look! They are themselves the agents of corruption, but they are not aware.”&lt;/em&gt; (Quran 2:11-12).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To whom does this passage refer? To corruption in general? To things like stealing, murder, adultery, etc., which most human beings would agree are corrupt deeds? No doubt, in Islam, these things are certainly sinful and are also part of corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the context of this particular passage, the corruption refers not to sin in general, but very specifically to the sin of unbelief. Here’s what the preceding five verses say. I have added some emphasis to bring out the major themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As for the &lt;strong&gt;faithless&lt;/strong&gt;, it is the same to them whether you warn them or do not warn them, &lt;strong&gt;they will not have faith&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allah has set a seal on their hearts and their hearing, and there is a blindfold on their sight, and there is a great punishment for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And among the people are those who say, ‘We have faith in Allah and the Last Day,’ but &lt;strong&gt;they have no faith&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They seek to deceive Allah and those who have faith, yet they deceive no one but themselves, but they are not aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sickness in their hearts; then Allah increased their sickness, and there is a painful punishment for them &lt;strong&gt;because of the lies they used to tell.&lt;/strong&gt;” (Quran 2:6-10)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this passage is condemning a very specific form of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt; – the sin of &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; or unbelief, and the telling of lies based upon this &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt;. The word &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; is the one from which comes the word &lt;em&gt;kafir&lt;/em&gt; or non-believer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the point even clearer, here is what the Quranic passage says right after verse 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;And when they are told, ‘Believe like the people who have believed,’ they say, &lt;strong&gt;‘Shall we believe like the fools who have believed?’&lt;/strong&gt; Look! They are themselves the fools, but they do not know.
When they meet the faithful, they say, ‘We believe,’ &lt;strong&gt;but when they are alone with their devils, they say, ‘We are with you; we were only deriding [them].&lt;/strong&gt;’
It is Allah who derides them, and leaves them bewildered in their rebellion.&lt;/em&gt;” (Quran 2:13-15).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So not only is the passage condemning a particular form of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt; (corruption) – &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; (unbelief) – it is condemning a very specific kind of &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt;: the sin of pretending to be a Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted before, Islam places a lot of emphasis upon justice (&lt;em&gt;adl&lt;/em&gt;). Striving to achieve justice is a virtue in Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, once more, the simple fact is that justice is defined very differently in Islam from the way a liberal might understand justice. Justice in Islam is, to put it simply, &lt;em&gt;Islam itself&lt;/em&gt;, and anything which detracts from Islam or diverges from Islam is, in some sense, to varying degrees, injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the struggle (&lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;) against corruption (&lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;) in order to achieve justice (&lt;em&gt;adl&lt;/em&gt;) is nothing more and nothing less than a struggle to achieve the triumph of Islam, in every sphere of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there are different kinds of &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; in Islam. And there are many interpretations of jihad. Hardly any of these interpretations are pacifistic, but not all of them are hyper-militaristic. Let’s stop there for a moment and consider some important facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic theology and jurisprudence are based upon the Quran (believed to be the Word of God) and the Sunnah (the path of the Prophet). The latter is known from the various &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt;. These are narrations, orally transmitted across several centuries, which relate stories about or quotations from the Prophet and/or his family (the &lt;em&gt;Ahlul Bayt&lt;/em&gt;) and/or his companions. Sunnis and Shias have different Hadith collections. The Sunnis have the six books, chief among them being Sahih Bukhari and Sahih Muslim. The Shias have the Kitab-al-Kafi and three others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all hadith are uncritically accepted. Some are strong (that is, believed to be reliable narrations). Others are thought weak and unreliable. And contradictions among them abound, thereby producing a variety of schools of thought and interpretations thereof. Generally speaking, however, there are three main classifications of &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;sahih&lt;/em&gt; (authentic), &lt;em&gt;hasan&lt;/em&gt; (good) and &lt;em&gt;da’if&lt;/em&gt; (weak). &lt;em&gt;Sahih&lt;/em&gt; is the highest epithet that can be applied to a hadith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic theology about &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; comes from the Quran. But the Quran is not written like other books. For one, it is not arranged chronologically in the order in which it was written. The first chapter of the Quran that was allegedly revealed to Muhammad was Chapter 96, &lt;em&gt;Surah Al-Alaq&lt;/em&gt;. Even the different passages in the Quran were sometimes revealed at different times and in very specific contexts. All of these are haphazard in arrangement. This can be seen especially in &lt;em&gt;Surah Maryam&lt;/em&gt;, in which several Biblical prophets are mentioned, but in a mixed up order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why on the one hand you have passages which seem to call for peace and others which seem to urge violence. Unless we want to affirm that the author(s) of the Quran was/were confused, we must realise that there is great ambiguity in understanding the intent, purposes and context of these conflicting verses. Some scholars even say that if commands in the Quran contradict, the one which was revealed later repeals the one which came before. This interpretation is quite common and well-known among scholars in the Muslim world (though not, thankfully, universally accepted) and is itself based upon a Quranic verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Whatever communications We abrogate or cause to be forgotten, We bring one better than it or like it. Do you not know that Allah has power over all things?&lt;/em&gt;” (Quran 2:106)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this interpretation, of course, is that many of the violent passages seem to have popped up at a later date than the more peaceful ones, according to Islam’s own sources! If this interpretation is to be followed, we would perhaps have to adopt a more violent form of Islam, because the more militaristic-sounding verses would then repeal the more peaceful and tolerant-sounding ones and become, as David Wood says, “the final marching orders” of that religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, of course, interpretations are manifold and varied. As stated before, while &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; is an integral part of Islam, it is certainly true that not every school of thought takes a hyper-militaristic view of it. In many schools, &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; is non-violent for the most part. However, once &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; becomes successful and Islam gains dominance in society, a different picture emerges. Most of the mainstream Islamic schools of jurisprudence affirm that if Islam manages to take hold of a society, it should become the state religion and the entire country – both Muslims and non-Muslims - should be governed according to the law of Allah. It is now that the persecution of minorities becomes almost inescapable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider for instance what is considered one of the most peaceful verses in the Quran:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;On that account: We ordained for the Children of Israel that if any one slew a person - unless it be for murder or for spreading mischief in the land - it would be as if he slew the whole people: and if any one saved a life, it would be as if he saved the life of the whole people.&lt;/em&gt;” (Qur’an 5:32)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberals often cite this verse as an evidence of the peaceful and tolerant nature of Islam, but what they fail to understand is that “spreading mischief in the land” (the word originally used in Arabic, again, is &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;) means a whole host of things in Islam, and many Islamic scholars and theologians would gladly agree that insulting the religion, mocking the prophet or preaching other religions to Muslims is a part of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, rather than being an exhortation to promote equality and egalitarianism as some silly liberals vainly imagine, the exhortation would actually justify the killing and/or incarceration of Christian missionaries who preach Christianity in Muslim lands!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good example is the case of apostasy. What if there is a Muslim who has lost faith and wishes to leave the &lt;em&gt;ummah&lt;/em&gt;? Here again, the Islamic testimony seems contradictory. Qur’an 2:256 literally states that there is ‘no compulsion in religion’. For many ears, this sounds pretty peaceful. However, can this text be applied to apostates, or does it refer only to the non-Muslim embracing Islam (for the first time)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; seem to indicate that it is the latter. Consider for instance the following citation from Sahih Bukhari, one of the most respected Sunni Hadith collections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Narrated Abdullah:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allah’s Messenger said, “The blood of a Muslim who confesses that none has the right to be worshipped but Allah and that I am His Apostle, cannot be shed except in three cases: In Qisas for murder, a married person who commits illegal sexual intercourse and the one who reverts from Islam (apostate) and leaves the Muslims.” Sahih Bukhari 9:83:17&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar Hadith are also found in Sahih Muslim 16:4152 and 4154. And all three of these &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; are considered authentic (&lt;em&gt;sahih&lt;/em&gt;) which, as stated earlier, is the highest epithet that can be given to a &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted before, the evidence seems ambiguous and difficult to interpret. However, historically, most of the major Islamic schools of jurisprudence have indeed advocated the death penalty for apostasy. Even a peaceful liberal Muslim who interprets the texts in a different way cannot deny this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once one understands this, one will realise why Muslim countries tend to be more religiously intolerant than non-Muslim countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that many Muslim scholars and theologians advocate a non-violent form of Jihad which mostly involves prayer, memorising the Quran, fasting and preaching Islam in a peaceful, non-coercive manner. However, once Islam gains dominance and a large portion of the population has embraced the faith, most schools of jurisprudence would gladly advocate the setting up of an Islamic state. And one need only look at the Middle East to see what that would be like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One must also realise that Islam is quite stringently theocratic. Except in certain less influential schools of thought, setting up a religious state is always considered the ideal. The only thing is, setting up an Islamic state is not always possible for Muslims, especially in lands where Islam has little influence. It is only in these settings that puritanical Muslims advocate secularism. The separation of mosque and state is always considered a compromise by the mainstream schools of jurisprudence, never the ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal is always an Islamic state. And all jihad – even the most peaceful forms of it – is ultimately meant to accomplish the ideal. And I will only leave the reader to contemplate the ominous implications that entails.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Jihad; possibly the most polarising word in the Arabic language. It provokes a range of varied reactions, depending on the perspective through which one looks at it. And it is true to say that the word has largely been misunderstood in non-Muslim circles. So before I even begin said analysis, I must make a series of clarifications and preliminary disclaimers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Robust Political Economy</title><link href="/Robust-Political-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robust Political Economy" /><published>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Robust-Political-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Robust-Political-Economy">&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest criticisms of classical liberalism has always been its reliance on the “idealised theoretical conditions”. Perfect knowledge among buyers and sellers, perfect competition, perfect mobility of factors of production, absence of externalities and transaction fees: the examples are countless. Similarly, the benevolence of agents, that is, the tendency to act towards societal welfare, rather than self-interest, was one of the governing “idealised theoretical conditions” of socialism and even classical liberalism. Under these mirage-like ideal conditions, both communism and capitalism could theoretically prove that they were extremely efficient in maximising social welfare. Similarly, under constraints, anarchies and authoritarian regimes proved to be more effective in imparting social and economic justice than a democracy ever could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of political economic systems, ‘robustness’ refers to a political economy’s ability to produce social welfare-enhancing outcomes especially in the face of deviations from the ideal assumptions about individuals’ motivations and information. Essentially, a political and economic system becomes ‘robust’ if it can withstand the realities and imperfections of human behaviour. Robust political economy requires that both the assumptions of agent’s benevolence and omniscience be relaxed. Such that the incentive issues and knowledge problems can be adequately addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two significant deviations that any theoretical robust political economy creates from a classical or socialist theory, is in the following respects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perfect Rationality: As opposed to the assumption, human beings are not fully rational agents—they also are not omniscient beings. Whenever they make decisions, they do so in a context of considerable uncertainty and there is always imperfect information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Benevolence: The second human imperfection is the problem of ‘limited benevolence’. People may, under certain circumstances, act out of self-interested motivations. They may be opportunistic. Therefore, we need to evaluate institutions in terms of the incentives they provide to channel potentially opportunistic actors to behave in a way that increases the overall well-being in society—that generates positive rather than negative sum gains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A robust political economy deals adequately with both of these issues. When information is costly, imperfect, and asymmetric, a robust political economy can still produce rational allocation. Likewise, when men are selfish knaves, a robust political economy nevertheless produces socially beneficial outcomes. In short, conditions shy of omniscience and benevolence do not cause the system to falter. Even in the face of these problematic imperfections, a robust political economy performs well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first easy case to deal with is the combination of self-interested individuals and classical liberalism. The classical economists sought out to show that even in the worst-case scenario of a society, populated by completely self-interested individuals, the market would ensure that the desires of men would be satisfied without any problem. Adam Smith’s famous invisible-hand postulate illustrated how the process of selfish individuals, each pursuing his or her own interests, leads to the promotion of society’s interests as a whole. His most famous quote from the &lt;em&gt;Wealth of Nations&lt;/em&gt; summarises this point nicely: “It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker, that we expect our dinner but from their regard to their own interest. We address ourselves, not to their humanity but to their self-love.” Indeed, he argued that liberalism could not only deal with a world of selfish individuals but also harnesses each man’s self-interested motivation for the benefit of everyone. This is because of the fundamental principles of exchange and private property, which would serve to guide the actions of both parties, and lead to a steady flow of resources and shifts in commodities according to changes in preferences of the consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a tougher question to ask is: Can classical liberalism thrive in imperfect knowledge? Hayek’s famous 1945 essay, &lt;em&gt;The Use of Knowledge in Society&lt;/em&gt; addressed this very question. Hayek pointed out that analogous to the division of labour, there exists an equally important division of knowledge in the market. No one person has all the knowledge necessary to make the market function effectively. However, precisely because knowledge is dispersed among the millions of individuals who comprise society, through the price system, the market is able to effectively coordinate the disparate plans of all market participants. Prices enable producers to evaluate the past successes or failures of market actors to determine whether they have adequately satisfied the desires of consumers. The price system, built on the diverse and decentralised knowledge of the individuals who compose the market, allows all market participants to economise on costly information. Therefore, in a way price becomes the indicator of knowledge and information in the market. The price of a particular commodity is eventually set depending upon the amalgamation of knowledge of all the players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hayek showed that by way of the price system, markets are able to cope with radically dispersed information and individual ignorance. By assuming the worst case about the information held by actors under liberalism and by showing liberalism’s ability to thrive on this ‘imperfection,’ Hayek demonstrated the robustness of liberal political economy. Hayek broadened his argument for the robustness of liberalism in the &lt;em&gt;Constitution of Liberty&lt;/em&gt; and later in &lt;em&gt;Law, Legislation, and Liberty&lt;/em&gt; where he developed the idea of the importance of particular institutions as the backdrop against which, erring and ignorant agents can learn to adapt their behaviour so as to coordinate their activities with those of others. According to Hayek, the institutions of private property, contract and consent, embedded in a system of general rules that protect these institutions, are crucial in ensuring that economic actors are able to utilise their individual knowledge of time and place in making decisions in such a way that their plans may be realised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although after the fall of the Soviet Union and the communist bloc in the early 1990’s, classical liberalism has proven to be the more robust system of the two, yet, during the Cold War, these ideological differences rested at the heart of the conflict between the United States and Soviet Union. Proponents of socialism often argued that without assumptions of perfect knowledge and benevolence, classical liberalism became so flawed that decentralised decision-making could not be trusted. They contended that the real world deviates so strongly from these idealised theories that the government’s role in the central planning and forcefully deciding the combination of goods and services to be produced was vital to maximise welfare. The central reasoning for this proposition was that the robustness of classical liberalism is based on the “invisible hand” of Adam Smith, which neither relies on benevolence nor on perfect knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hayek and Mises believed in disproving the socialism theory under the best-case scenario. They didn’t focus on the incentive problem of the people at the various positions of the hierarchical structure. Thus, they took benevolence as a given assumption. However, the imperfect information problem was wide open to be attacked. They contested the information available with the authority, and went on to say that due to delays in receiving the information or stagnancy of decision in the market, there would be extreme mismanagement between the wants of the consumers and resource allocation of the producers. Thus, the theory of socialism would lead to a most definite market failure, which is inevitable in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, we can clearly see, in governance systems across the globe, that classical liberalism with its minimal interference by the government and unprecedented decentralised decision-making is not followed in its crude format. A stronger role for the government, in sectors like education, healthcare and public services is widely practiced and argued for. Managing a political economy, in some terms, is truly a balancing act. Whenever dogma prevails over practicality, robustness diminishes, be it the 1991 fall of the USSR or the 2008 financial crash. At the end, “robustness” is vastly dependent on adaptability and as long as governments and communities show greater adaptability to newer challenges, more real and robust political economies will continue to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">One of the greatest criticisms of classical liberalism has always been its reliance on the “idealised theoretical conditions”. Perfect knowledge among buyers and sellers, perfect competition, perfect mobility of factors of production, absence of externalities and transaction fees: the examples are countless. Similarly, the benevolence of agents, that is, the tendency to act towards societal welfare, rather than self-interest, was one of the governing “idealised theoretical conditions” of socialism and even classical liberalism. Under these mirage-like ideal conditions, both communism and capitalism could theoretically prove that they were extremely efficient in maximising social welfare. Similarly, under constraints, anarchies and authoritarian regimes proved to be more effective in imparting social and economic justice than a democracy ever could.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Celebrating Darkness Through Style: Yami Kawaii</title><link href="/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating Darkness Through Style: Yami Kawaii" /><published>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style">&lt;p&gt;The streets of Harajuku have witnessed it all; the shifts, blends and twists that have gone into making Japan’s street fashion what it is today. As part of one of the world’s most exciting fashion capitals, Tokyo, Harajuku’s streets have given birth to diverse fashion trends, which stem from an interplay of western elements and unique individual tastes. With a splendid array of authentic styles, characterised by heavy accessorisation and experimentation, Harajuku has garnered attention from designers worldwide. The youth of Harajuku, in particular, has begun creating a free space of expression for themselves through the clothes they don. Vibrant and quirky, the Harajuku youth culture, both as a trend in fashion and a lifestyle reflects the constant struggle to break free from mainstream culture, which is marked by order and discipline and leaves little space for people to play with their style and fashion choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world’s obsession with &lt;em&gt;kawaii&lt;/em&gt; (meaning cute) is not new and with growing fame, &lt;em&gt;kawaii&lt;/em&gt; has expanded beyond Hello Kitty products and plushies (which as a matter of fact draw their inspiration from fierce beasts!) to enter the world of fashion. As phrases like “&lt;em&gt;that’s so kawaii!&lt;/em&gt;” emerged, adolescents embraced styles that gave them an innocent, childlike air. Against the backdrop of Japan’s mental health crisis and a cultural unwillingness to speak about it, some even went a step ahead to give their own twist to the idea of kawaii. Thus emerged a new look in the streets of Harajuku, called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;yami kawaii&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Literally translating to ‘sick cute’, yami kawaii wasn’t the normal, conventional kawaii. Something dark and profound pervaded it. It dealt with sickness, a sickness that even though plagued the whole of Japan was one that nobody was and is still ready to talk about. It dealt with depression and suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By fusion of the cute and the dark, yami kawaii produced fashion of a freakish nature, involving soft pastels and anime juxtaposed with guns, syringes, bandages. Underneath the facade of kawaii, the tshirts illustrated chilling messages such as ‘Kill You’, ‘I want to die’ and ‘F*ck You’. What makes such fashion intense is not the frightening imagery that it employs but the implication that underlies that imagery; these clothes were a desperate last resort for people to express themselves, an attempt at catharsis of a deep, deep pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Menhera Chan, a manga character, came to be seen as an important figure in the yami kawaii movement. This is primarily because Menhera chan is different from other manga characters. She has a dark cynical vibe to her, her arms are bandaged, she carries a blade with her and harms herself, she is anxious and depressed. Her despair and agony are what make her a strangely relatable figure to countless others, who experience a similar pain but have to shroud it with their silence. They see her as the personification of the feelings and desires buried in the depths of their hearts, a therapeutic mechanism to pour out the pain of hiding the miserable state they’re in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncannily enough, yami kawaii has opened doors for a healthy dialogue in a society where profession and education overwhelmingly dictate every aspect of an individual’s life, where seeking help in order to tackle mental illness is still labelled a weakness. In the difficulty of having to reshape one’s life during the hard times, expression seems the only recourse, something that yami kawaii offers as a style. This, however, is not to be misunderstood as the glorification of suicide or depression. Personally, I find this style to be emboldening, simply because it marks a dissent from the ongoing discourse that reeks of bigotry and seeks to forbid individuals from expressing what they truly feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With negativity looming over the topic of mental health (which again, is partly responsible for the lack of dialogue) one remains fettered to live a life of lies. Constantly in the shackles of keeping up appearances, one has to project oneself as something they’re not. Those unable to take it anymore, seek their emancipation in suicide. Against the stifling expectations of society, where abiding by rules and etiquette are a must, yami kawaii offers a way out to people, in the form of catharsis. Yami kawaii gives a release to the inner turbulence they experience while helping one connect with others who feel the same way. It possesses a healing power of sorts, alleviating all those enduring the pain of masking their true feelings and enabling their style to speak for them. This makes yami kawaii empowering, fostering a new hope in the world for greater acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using fashion as an instrument of their liberation, the youngsters of Harajuku have certainly begun to lay down the foundations of change, to break silence against this raging catastrophe. By providing an outlet to vent complex emotions through style, an embodiment of the self, they seek to urge others who are suffering like them to join this movement towards self-love. Yami kawaii tells one and all that they have nothing to hide and nothing to fear. Bold and beautiful, these youths, go about announcing their identity in the streets of Harajuku.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">The streets of Harajuku have witnessed it all; the shifts, blends and twists that have gone into making Japan’s street fashion what it is today. As part of one of the world’s most exciting fashion capitals, Tokyo, Harajuku’s streets have given birth to diverse fashion trends, which stem from an interplay of western elements and unique individual tastes. With a splendid array of authentic styles, characterised by heavy accessorisation and experimentation, Harajuku has garnered attention from designers worldwide. The youth of Harajuku, in particular, has begun creating a free space of expression for themselves through the clothes they don. Vibrant and quirky, the Harajuku youth culture, both as a trend in fashion and a lifestyle reflects the constant struggle to break free from mainstream culture, which is marked by order and discipline and leaves little space for people to play with their style and fashion choices.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Martin Scorsese and The American Dream</title><link href="/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martin Scorsese and The American Dream" /><published>2019-06-16T23:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-16T23:13:00+00:00</updated><id>/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream">&lt;p&gt;(Spoilers ahead for &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day, I was looking at reviews of &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, a film
that I love a lot. Upon noticing a lot of negative comments I decided to rewatch
it and watching it reminded me of why I loved that film so much; not because of
how the film manages to spill excess into every scene, but because of how in the
midst of it all, a message lies hidden. The same message that Martin Scorsese
has always tried to illustrate throughout his filmography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scorsese loves to show the downfall of the Man in the high castle. Be it
&lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;The Aviator&lt;/em&gt;, and this 3-hour debauchery act
that I’ll be focusing on primarily, Scorsese focuses quite a lot on male ego.
What ties his stories together is how his characters’ life choices are
influenced by their dreamland. In other words, the protagonists in all of his
movies and shows wanted to live the &lt;em&gt;American Dream&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America has always been seen as a land of opportunity. Throughout the history of
the USA, one can observe immigrants from various European countries finding a
place in this glorious nation to make a living. It continues even today, as seen
in students coming from all over the world to America to study or in Silicon
Valley, where a sizeable percentage of the workforce is of quasi-American
heritage, that too only by a generation or so. The immigrants’ aim to get a
coveted degree, a top job at a quant firm or under a tech mogul, or to kickstart
their venture into a high-life which they always wanted. Microsoft is headed by
an Indian today, Facebook was founded by multiple Jewish-Americans with other
mixed heritages, and these are just the biggest examples in a vast sea of such
cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the kicker: America hasn’t necessarily been kind to a lot of outsiders.
The cases in the limelight were stories of success that create a narrative that
you could be anyone, you could be dirt poor, but you’ll always find a way to
make something out of the land of the brave and the free. But in reality, one’s
likelihood to succeed is rigged by factors such as race and appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 20th century, there was mass immigration of Italians to America.
Many of them were very poor and lived in neighbourhoods characterised by
poverty. Gradually, they grew out of it but, initially, life was rather too
hard. They were involved in low-paying blue-collar jobs, had difficulty
adjusting to their surroundings as they faced issues like the inability to speak
English and considerable discrimination during World War II by the US
government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of such adversity, the definition of the American Dream had become
slightly skewed. It became an end in itself and the means to attain it was left
open to a fair extent. This is where my example of Italian-Americans comes in
(I’m well aware that this could be advancing a stereotypical narrative about
them which is not my intention, but nonetheless, it surely is a sociological
factor). In Italy, the institution of family was very important, to the extent
that they would do anything to protect and advance the interests of their own
kind. Italian-Americans organized themselves in places like New York, and
created communities around them where they had control over the socio-economic
conditions of their people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular example of Italian-Americans is pertinent because of Scorsese’s
focus on it. &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; is a movie about how Italian gangsters in New York
made their profession look cool and aspirational around their neighbourhood;
their display of power enticed anybody who wanted to make the American Dream a
reality. The idea of a family also becomes important here; Henry Hill had said
that being an Italian mobster was better than being the President of the United
States of America because of how relaxed these mobsters are. They have shady but
steady sources of income, and no one to trouble them. The reason I can see
behind this is that the Italian mobster feels no responsibility towards others.
With this, the idea of the American Dream shifted from making use of the
opportunity to succeed in the land of the American Dream without responsibility
towards anyone or anything at all, at least for those who feel the need to
resort to illegitimate means, even if in limited quantities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; exemplifies that philosophy to perfection. Leading a
normal life is a frustrating ordeal for Jordan Belfort. It all begins with one
morally ambiguous choice. Jordan Belfort started selling stocks of companies
that were not financially sound enough to get themselves listed on a legitimate
stock exchange. He overlooked the fact that consumers might be adversely
affected by such a deal with the misguided assurance that every company makes
profits in the long run! Belfort has sex with everyone but his wife. She won’t
find out, problem sorted! &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; advances its story in the same vein;
let’s bribe the cops, so everyone is happy. People get what they want, if only
they put in the ‘effort’ to acquire it. So, everything could be hacked. But all
of it becomes a problem when you want more, or when you find the need to sustain
that lifestyle. You get sucked in, and you can’t find a way out. Stockbroking
was a highly focused job that requires one to remain calm at all times.
Substance usage provided that enhanced ability. Promiscuous sex provided the
relief after. Home life provided the anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, this conception of the American Dream was most
magnified when money-crazed kids read a &lt;em&gt;Forbes&lt;/em&gt; piece that was actually critical
of Jordan Belfort and decided to join his firm, Stratton Oakmont. Drugs, women,
capital, a need for the high life. It was everything that an average American
male needed; a break from the monotony of merely existing and working an
unexciting job to feel larger than life. The middle-class could now profit off
of the impulsiveness of the 1%, which was what Leonardo DiCaprio’s character
initially set out to do. In part, this obsession can be attributed to the huge
amounts of investment flowing through the economy, and mass media like the
Michael Douglas-starrer &lt;em&gt;Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; glorifying the “greed is good” image. With
corporate raiders gaining infamy on the scene, the market being generally
bullish, and huge leveraged buyouts being made (case in point being RJR
Nabisco), Wall Street was a party. What is more interesting is that you could be
a college dropout, an illiterate beggar, and Wall Street will still let you make
your own fortune. That was where the appeal lay; selling is an art that can be
learned irrespective of where you are in life. It primarily became a game of
convincing American citizens that they wanted to shift their capital elsewhere,
without holding any responsibility for their investments in the future. And why
not this game? It was a comparatively easy and a quick way to make money. “Sell
me a pen” became quotable as a line later on, because it was an exhibition of
the idea that doing this much was enough to signify one’s potential for success,
the main determinant of which was wealth. The product was not necessarily the
seller’s own, he/she was just a middleman who won a fat commission on each sale.
No responsibility, no accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He did not just have this art of selling people things they didn’t want. What
Jordan Belfort was most successful at was selling the perfect life to his
employees. In the scene where he makes the motivational speech before the Steve
Madden IPO, he draws a contrast between the women that men desire (“with big
voluptuous tits”), and the women that are “disgusting wildebeests with three
days of razor stubble”. That was his best sale ever, not the penny stocks that
were essentially scams. What Scorsese really wanted to show here was how toxic
masculinity began to shape the American Dream, mainly by saying that money can
buy everything, including your happiness. One may argue that Belfort knew that
it was all a crime, so he could have backed out by striking a deal with the FBI
when they offered him a back door. But no, he felt too attached to this baby of
his; this company that he had started from scratch after a disastrous stock
market crash had left him unemployed. A parallel to this could be how attached
&lt;em&gt;Breaking Bad’s&lt;/em&gt; Walter White felt for his Baby Blue - his meth empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Departed&lt;/em&gt; contains streaks of this American Dream. The opening lines of
Jack Nicholson’s crazed, senile Irish gangster character says that he wants his
environment to be a product of him, and not the other way round. He criticises
the Afro-American community, calling them the N-word, saying that they were
where they were because they could never “take it”. Nobody would give it to
them. This idea of carving out your own environment to survive, no matter how
illegitimate, defined the American Dream as presented in Scorsese’s films. It is
safe to say that as the son of Americans with Italian heritage himself, he has
seen the dream suck people into an abyss. This is not to say he doesn’t thank
America for being so kind to him; &lt;em&gt;Gangs of New York&lt;/em&gt; was a celebration of that.
However, the thought of taking matters into one’s own hands became such an
obsession for Americans that it eventually led to the downfall of prominent,
wealthy people. They may have started from the bottom, but they definitely
forgot their roots because that was always their intention. No one wants to
remember painful beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martin Scorsese has always evoked extreme reactions from his viewers. The
surface viewer might just think that &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; was a 3-hour
grossed-out porno-comedy without any message. That person misses a lot of the
important shots that convey a deeper meaning, like that of the federal agent
tasked with bringing Belfort to justice or shots of dull-faced middle-class
people in a metro train. According to the film, the federal agent wanted to be a
broker sometime in the past. And despite nailing such a huge arrest, he felt
empty inside. He could never live the life Belfort did, even when he had the
choice to. All it remained for him was a dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Pranav Manie</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">(Spoilers ahead for The Wolf of Wall Street). The other day, I was looking at reviews of The Wolf of Wall Street, a film that I love a lot. Upon noticing a lot of negative comments I decided to rewatch it and watching it reminded me of why I loved that film so much; not because of how the film manages to spill excess into every scene, but because of how in the midst of it all, a message lies hidden. The same message that Martin Scorsese has always tried to illustrate throughout his filmography. Scorsese loves to show the downfall of the Man in the high castle. Be it Goodfellas, Raging Bull or The Aviator, and this 3-hour debauchery act that I’ll be focusing on primarily, Scorsese focuses quite a lot on male ego. What ties his stories together is how his characters’ life choices are influenced by their dreamland. In other words, the protagonists in all of his movies and shows wanted to live the American Dream. America has always been seen as a land of opportunity. Throughout the history of the USA, one can observe immigrants from various European countries finding a place in this glorious nation to make a living. It continues even today, as seen in students coming from all over the world to America to study or in Silicon Valley, where a sizeable percentage of the workforce is of quasi-American heritage, that too only by a generation or so. The immigrants’ aim to get a coveted degree, a top job at a quant firm or under a tech mogul, or to kickstart their venture into a high-life which they always wanted. Microsoft is headed by an Indian today, Facebook was founded by multiple Jewish-Americans with other mixed heritages, and these are just the biggest examples in a vast sea of such cases. Here’s the kicker: America hasn’t necessarily been kind to a lot of outsiders. The cases in the limelight were stories of success that create a narrative that you could be anyone, you could be dirt poor, but you’ll always find a way to make something out of the land of the brave and the free. But in reality, one’s likelihood to succeed is rigged by factors such as race and appearance. In the early 20th century, there was mass immigration of Italians to America. Many of them were very poor and lived in neighbourhoods characterised by poverty. Gradually, they grew out of it but, initially, life was rather too hard. They were involved in low-paying blue-collar jobs, had difficulty adjusting to their surroundings as they faced issues like the inability to speak English and considerable discrimination during World War II by the US government. In the face of such adversity, the definition of the American Dream had become slightly skewed. It became an end in itself and the means to attain it was left open to a fair extent. This is where my example of Italian-Americans comes in (I’m well aware that this could be advancing a stereotypical narrative about them which is not my intention, but nonetheless, it surely is a sociological factor). In Italy, the institution of family was very important, to the extent that they would do anything to protect and advance the interests of their own kind. Italian-Americans organized themselves in places like New York, and created communities around them where they had control over the socio-economic conditions of their people. This particular example of Italian-Americans is pertinent because of Scorsese’s focus on it. Goodfellas is a movie about how Italian gangsters in New York made their profession look cool and aspirational around their neighbourhood; their display of power enticed anybody who wanted to make the American Dream a reality. The idea of a family also becomes important here; Henry Hill had said that being an Italian mobster was better than being the President of the United States of America because of how relaxed these mobsters are. They have shady but steady sources of income, and no one to trouble them. The reason I can see behind this is that the Italian mobster feels no responsibility towards others. With this, the idea of the American Dream shifted from making use of the opportunity to succeed in the land of the American Dream without responsibility towards anyone or anything at all, at least for those who feel the need to resort to illegitimate means, even if in limited quantities. The Wolf of Wall Street exemplifies that philosophy to perfection. Leading a normal life is a frustrating ordeal for Jordan Belfort. It all begins with one morally ambiguous choice. Jordan Belfort started selling stocks of companies that were not financially sound enough to get themselves listed on a legitimate stock exchange. He overlooked the fact that consumers might be adversely affected by such a deal with the misguided assurance that every company makes profits in the long run! Belfort has sex with everyone but his wife. She won’t find out, problem sorted! Goodfellas advances its story in the same vein; let’s bribe the cops, so everyone is happy. People get what they want, if only they put in the ‘effort’ to acquire it. So, everything could be hacked. But all of it becomes a problem when you want more, or when you find the need to sustain that lifestyle. You get sucked in, and you can’t find a way out. Stockbroking was a highly focused job that requires one to remain calm at all times. Substance usage provided that enhanced ability. Promiscuous sex provided the relief after. Home life provided the anxiety. In The Wolf of Wall Street, this conception of the American Dream was most magnified when money-crazed kids read a Forbes piece that was actually critical of Jordan Belfort and decided to join his firm, Stratton Oakmont. Drugs, women, capital, a need for the high life. It was everything that an average American male needed; a break from the monotony of merely existing and working an unexciting job to feel larger than life. The middle-class could now profit off of the impulsiveness of the 1%, which was what Leonardo DiCaprio’s character initially set out to do. In part, this obsession can be attributed to the huge amounts of investment flowing through the economy, and mass media like the Michael Douglas-starrer Wall Street glorifying the “greed is good” image. With corporate raiders gaining infamy on the scene, the market being generally bullish, and huge leveraged buyouts being made (case in point being RJR Nabisco), Wall Street was a party. What is more interesting is that you could be a college dropout, an illiterate beggar, and Wall Street will still let you make your own fortune. That was where the appeal lay; selling is an art that can be learned irrespective of where you are in life. It primarily became a game of convincing American citizens that they wanted to shift their capital elsewhere, without holding any responsibility for their investments in the future. And why not this game? It was a comparatively easy and a quick way to make money. “Sell me a pen” became quotable as a line later on, because it was an exhibition of the idea that doing this much was enough to signify one’s potential for success, the main determinant of which was wealth. The product was not necessarily the seller’s own, he/she was just a middleman who won a fat commission on each sale. No responsibility, no accountability. He did not just have this art of selling people things they didn’t want. What Jordan Belfort was most successful at was selling the perfect life to his employees. In the scene where he makes the motivational speech before the Steve Madden IPO, he draws a contrast between the women that men desire (“with big voluptuous tits”), and the women that are “disgusting wildebeests with three days of razor stubble”. That was his best sale ever, not the penny stocks that were essentially scams. What Scorsese really wanted to show here was how toxic masculinity began to shape the American Dream, mainly by saying that money can buy everything, including your happiness. One may argue that Belfort knew that it was all a crime, so he could have backed out by striking a deal with the FBI when they offered him a back door. But no, he felt too attached to this baby of his; this company that he had started from scratch after a disastrous stock market crash had left him unemployed. A parallel to this could be how attached Breaking Bad’s Walter White felt for his Baby Blue - his meth empire. The Departed contains streaks of this American Dream. The opening lines of Jack Nicholson’s crazed, senile Irish gangster character says that he wants his environment to be a product of him, and not the other way round. He criticises the Afro-American community, calling them the N-word, saying that they were where they were because they could never “take it”. Nobody would give it to them. This idea of carving out your own environment to survive, no matter how illegitimate, defined the American Dream as presented in Scorsese’s films. It is safe to say that as the son of Americans with Italian heritage himself, he has seen the dream suck people into an abyss. This is not to say he doesn’t thank America for being so kind to him; Gangs of New York was a celebration of that. However, the thought of taking matters into one’s own hands became such an obsession for Americans that it eventually led to the downfall of prominent, wealthy people. They may have started from the bottom, but they definitely forgot their roots because that was always their intention. No one wants to remember painful beginnings. Martin Scorsese has always evoked extreme reactions from his viewers. The surface viewer might just think that The Wolf of Wall Street was a 3-hour grossed-out porno-comedy without any message. That person misses a lot of the important shots that convey a deeper meaning, like that of the federal agent tasked with bringing Belfort to justice or shots of dull-faced middle-class people in a metro train. According to the film, the federal agent wanted to be a broker sometime in the past. And despite nailing such a huge arrest, he felt empty inside. He could never live the life Belfort did, even when he had the choice to. All it remained for him was a dream.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Indian Elections, A Hindu Zeitgeist and ‘Pattanaikism’</title><link href="/The-Indian-Elections-A-Hindu-Zeitgeist-and-Pattanaikism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Elections, A Hindu Zeitgeist and 'Pattanaikism'" /><published>2019-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Indian-Elections-A-Hindu-Zeitgeist-and-Pattanaikism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Elections-A-Hindu-Zeitgeist-and-Pattanaikism">&lt;p&gt;It is now a truism that faith divides people, engenders identities, perpetuates meaningless violence and places stupid restrictions on human behaviour. Whether it be Islamophobic attacks or the rise of the Islamic State, religion, rather than making us better human beings, can drive us towards all kinds of mindless evil. So it is no wonder that people think religion is (or ought to be) a dying institution or social phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the fight it is putting up by seeking to tie-up with politics means that it is not going away anytime soon. Nowhere is this more apparent than in the Indian general election results of 2019, which saw India’s Hindu Nationalist party being swept back into power after a fiery, divisive and communally-charged campaign. But to say that this election result is the endorsement of a militant, monolithic kind of Hinduism would be disingenuous. Hinduism is, ultimately, a complex and chaotic faith that has multiple aspects and ever-changing dialectics in every age. And the Hindu Nationalist’s victory is countered by numerous different perspectives, both correct and incorrect. These narratives serve to show us a faith that is alive, and, more importantly, learning to find a sweet spot in a modern world that may see religion as a relic of human stupidity. The zeitgeist of Hinduism today lies not in the polarising voices of Prime Minister Modi and his minions, but in the vast extent of all the different ideas that dominate Hinduism’s current cultural landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an animistic, possibly agnostic faith that was centred around animal sacrifice and elaborate fire rituals over 3,000 years ago, Hinduism has come a long way. It now has an organised chaos, in every sense of the phrase, with multiple strands of theistic and atheistic philosophies, grand epics, a notorious caste system and 330 million ‘gods’. Prima facie, one can see how the &lt;em&gt;Sanatan Dharma&lt;/em&gt; (or The Eternal Faith, as so many Hindus call it) is ever so different from Christianity, Islam or Judaism. However, given Hinduism’s openness to new ideas, an analysis of some of the broad socio-political strands currently prevailing within (and without) the faith reveals many similarities with Abrahamic religions. In fact, it is the “Hindu revivalism” championed by (what can only be called) India’s Hindu Nationalists that seems to have the strongest resemblance to Abrahamic faiths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu Nationalist organisations, collectively known as the “&lt;em&gt;Sangh Parivar&lt;/em&gt;” (Family of Associations), which form the ideological bedrock of PM Modi’s party, explicitly subscribe to a kind of “Hindu Zionism”. They believe that, like Israel, the glue that should bind India is the idea of a Hindu motherland, where a great Temple is built (in place of an existing mosque) that is dedicated to Lord Ram. Lord Ram is a Hindu god king from the epic &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, and his rule is seen as the most perfect model for good governance and nation-building. Hindu Nationalists paint Lord Ram and the idea of India with brushstrokes that evidently transplant ideas from the Christian, Islamic or Israeli far right. They have major problems with the presence of another faith in their own ‘backyard’, they rely heavily on spiritual ‘gurus’ and religious leadership to spread their message, and they cling on to “older, truer” values like an opposition to the LGBTQ movement. While these groups have usually been a noisy minority with a record of some major violence like the vandalism of the mosque which allegedly stood in Lord Ram’s birthplace, they are now a formidable force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all their faults, the Hindu Nationalists have sparked a true debate on the nature of Hinduism. They have forced people to ask: What makes Hinduism ‘different’? What is the difference between the ‘right’ or ‘wrong’ kind of Hinduism? How important is it for a Hindu to not consume beef? Should Hinduism seek some level of organisation like Abrahamic faiths? Is the idea of India inextricably linked to a fundamentally “Hindu identity”? The import of these questions extends far beyond their relevance to Hindu dogma (if there is one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not from a strictly Hindu perspective, the political criticism of Hindu Nationalism comes from India’s broad cross-section of left-wing intellectuals and politicians. Their first major criticism being that PM Modi and his coterie of fanatic backers have perpetuated greater communal violence and intolerance. This is certainly not untrue. In a country which prides itself on having a composite culture, the recent increase in lynchings of people belonging to minority faiths is a complete and utter travesty. If there’s one thing a faith or ideology should not have is a penchant for violence. If the Hinduism of tomorrow or the India of tomorrow is run by people who resemble the Taliban, then Hinduism must rightly die as a faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, the second major criticism hurled at the Hindu Nationalist is more ideological than factual. The Indian left-wing sees Hindu Nationalism as contrary both to the idea of India and the demands of a more modern world. The idea of India put forward by the Indian Left is very significantly influenced by the ideas of Jawaharlal Nehru, India’s first Prime Minister. Nehru argues that India is a composite culture that has forever lived in harmony verily because of the immense spiritual diversity of Hinduism. Consequently, the Nehruvian vision of India dreams of a secular Indian state that stands in support of all faiths and respects all minorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are great internal flaws in these ideas. It is completely counterfactual to suggest that India has ever had true harmony in its history. The histories are replete with examples of Islamic rulers exploiting their Hindu subjects and vice versa. And it is undeniably a cheap political lie to suggest that Hinduism has, historically, been a tolerant faith that has always accepted outsiders. The history of Hinduism is plagued both by strands of profound pluralism and horrific clashes. For instance, the burning and pillaging of Buddhist monasteries has been a feature of Hinduism since the rise of the former as an alternative to a faith that thinks it’s okay (desirable, even) to label someone an ‘Untouchable’. The works of Dr B.R. Ambedkar, the architect of India’s Constitution are filled with examples of Hinduism terrorising all kinds of people―especially those who are untouchable. I fail to see how a faith that has denied ‘lower’ people the right to share clean water with some ‘higher’ people on the basis of birthright can be considered tolerant, especially when it ironically says each person possesses an immanent, infinite and transcendental soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian left-wing seems to always ignore these truths, taking refuge instead in the apologetic argument that Hindu Nationalist ideology is a hangover from a colonial past or that it is a high caste conspiracy. While this argument makes sense in part, its implications are far more problematic. Yes, it is true that the coloniser’s view of Hinduism’s fearsome, naked goddesses and shamanic traditions drove it to embrace more Victorian trends like prudishness about sex or LGBTQ people (in the land of the &lt;em&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/em&gt;!). But that ominously suggests that if Hinduism were rid of colonial influences then it could return to some kind of earlier purity. Quite obviously, that ignores what Hinduism was before colonisation―a religion that burned widows alive. And, moreover, it implies that cultures can reverse history, which quite clearly is impossible. Faiths today cannot rely on the smokescreen of a heyday of yesteryear to redeem themselves, they must seek to move forward, not backwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as blaming the higher castes for Hinduism’s social evils is concerned, that argument seems both malicious and futile. No one can deny that the Brahmins played an active role in engendering the dehumanising aspects of the caste system. And, of course, ex post rationalisations of caste as a division of labour are deeply troublesome. But to confuse fighting against the caste system with fighting against the Brahmins entails a society that is fraught with acrimonious divisions. Nowhere is this truer than in South India, where movements led by the late thinker Periyar have created an environment that is hostile to Brahmins–leading to a slow death of their culture. The Left’s view of the caste system as a symptom of Brahmin hegemony, rather than the other way around, blames a group of people following Hinduism over the religion itself―which is the source of this rot. Instead of finding positive solutions it only presents arguments on whom to blame, making it extremely unhelpful to those who actually require emancipation and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, the back and forth between India’s Hindu Right and Secular Left seems very poor in providing either a vision of Hinduism that is ready for a modern age or an idea of India that is historically accurate. While one side sees Hinduism as the be-all and end-all of 1.3 billion people, the other trivialises it by white-washing the faith to provide a rather deceptive vision. The Hindu Indian voter in the 2019 election was forced to stand between a rock and a hard place. And the predicament of the Indian voter reveals the confusion that animates all of society today in regards to religion. The Hindu may have chosen the Hindu Nationalists, but they did so only because the other parties didn’t really give two hoots about their faith, which obviously defines their identity. Like the American Evangelical, the Hindu voter knows that Modi, like Trump, doesn’t actually care about faith and god. After all, to the Hindu Nationalist, Lord Ram isn’t a god who provides deep spiritual enhancement, he’s a political tool. To the Indian Secularist, Hinduism is only relevant or important in so far as it helps their idea of India. All movements that seem to use religion for politics, seem to do verily that, use it for politics. And to think the Hindu Indian voter doesn’t know that, or that he’s going to let the Hindu Nationalist define his faith post this election victory reeks of naivety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for the Hindu Indian voter, a new, more philosophical movement seems emergent amidst all of these political debates. While no movement of this kind is attributable to a single person, this “new age Hinduism” does have an unofficial leader: Devdutt Pattanaik. Pattanaik has written over forty books and hundreds of columns on Hinduism and has been a management consultant to many large corporates―where he has ingeniously combined mythology to put forth &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/I7QwxbImhZI&quot;&gt;new ideas&lt;/a&gt; on management. His writings provide both scathing critiques and poignant praise of all that is found in Hinduism, unravelling how the mythology of Indian culture shapes its people. Most radically, the Pattanaikist worldview &lt;a href=&quot;https://mumbaimirror.indiatimes.com/others/sunday-read/defining-hinduism/articleshow/60897762.cms&quot;&gt;shatters&lt;/a&gt; the illusion that Hinduism can provide any singular answer to what it is and what it should be. Instead, it suggests that Hinduism is truly about embracing the diversity of opinions it allows and accepting that the Eternal Faith is so because &lt;a href=&quot;https://devdutt.com/articles/applied-mythology/society/who-is-a-hindu-hinduisms-diy-kit.html&quot;&gt;nothing in it is eternally true&lt;/a&gt;. Pattanaik illustrates this by contrasting the two versions of the same god Vishnu in his books &lt;em&gt;Sita&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jaya&lt;/em&gt;, which are his takes on the Hindu epics the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt;. In one age, Vishnu, the preserver of &lt;em&gt;Dharma&lt;/em&gt; (that which is right) is Lord Ram, who is the perfect man because he upholds social rules, no matter how distasteful they are. While, in another age, Vishnu is Lord Krishna, who is the perfect man because he upholds what is right by disregarding social rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not readily apparent, Pattanaik’s philosophy has certain very optimistic implications for the plight of the Hindu post the 2019 Indian general elections. Firstly, it serves to remind the Hindu that his faith is richer than shibboleths like beef bans and Ram Temples. Of course, this doesn’t mean that the Pattnaikist view provides any political clarion call against India’s Hindu Nationalists. Rather, it does something far more impactful: it brings the devoted Hindu a way of psychologically divorcing his faith from those who would claim a monopoly on it in the name of nationalism or politics. The Hindu, being enlightened by the multilayered and complex nature of his religion, is able to rise above the politics of the Hindu Nationalist to worship Lord Ram for who he is: a perfect god, instead of some pithy political totem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Pattanaik worldview, quite counterintuitively, provides what I think is a truer understanding of Hinduism and its place in the “idea of India”. It recognises where Hinduism must change to fit a secular Indian society while continuing to grow. Instead of the Indian Left’s apologetic or misleading narratives, Pattanaik provides a very positive but limited argument. And unlike the Hindu Nationalist’s strident dogmatism, his view entails a very comforting kind of ambiguity. Pattanaik writes in in the Introduction to Jaya: “Within infinite lies, lies a truth. Who sees it all? Varuna [the god of the waters] has but a thousand eyes, Indra [the god of rain], a hundred, you and I, only two.” The liberating quality of this short mantra cannot be emphasised enough, stemming from the depths of Upanishadic Hindu philosophy. It reminds Hindus and, more broadly, Indians that it is difficult to always see the truth. So, to blame anyone for what we consider different, or misguided, or, perhaps, plain wrong is rather hypocritical. This means that Hindus and India must learn, as part of kind of national introspection, to not only tolerate differences, but to accept them as alternative truths one may not be able to fully see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this doesn’t mean that Hinduism ought to be a ‘lolbertarian’ religion. But it does mean that Hinduism in the age of Kali must learn to live with other religions and with the variations in its own nature. And that applies, contrary to Popperian ‘mythologies’, even if it is found that there is a view that opposes that very truth―as Hindu Nationalism ostensibly does. To put it in Pattanaik’s own &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/sNCpWECSGR4&quot;&gt;words&lt;/a&gt;, “Everybody has beliefs, and most beliefs are stupid”, and that clearly means no one is really in the position to evaluate if another’s belief is based on falsehoods or not. We are simply not that wise. A Hindu by definition is supposed to believe that he has not the moral or epistemic authority to disrespect anyone’s views. And that makes for an undeniably marvellous faith that is willing to coexist with others, with more than just tolerance, even if there is disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas of Pattanaik and their growing popularity offer respite to anyone who thinks this Indian election has set Hinduism on a course towards fanaticism. It provides a template for how religions, by having both a healthy measure of empathy towards all those who ‘twist’ its tenets and trivialise its significance, can survive in a modern world. Religions have lost much due to their inability to adapt and put forward a zeitgeist that is brimming with new ideas. Pattanaik’s view gives us a Hinduism whose true zeitgeist today, far from being restricted to Modi’s Lotus flags (even if inclusive of it), is animated by a hotbed of new ideas. And all these ideas are rising up to the challenge of making the Hindu life more meaningful and enriching at a very interesting time. Pattanaik’s view of Hinduism gives us more than a reason to believe that Hinduism shall continue to be rich and complex, it tells us why that’s a very good thing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It is now a truism that faith divides people, engenders identities, perpetuates meaningless violence and places stupid restrictions on human behaviour. Whether it be Islamophobic attacks or the rise of the Islamic State, religion, rather than making us better human beings, can drive us towards all kinds of mindless evil. So it is no wonder that people think religion is (or ought to be) a dying institution or social phenomenon.</summary></entry></feed>