<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-26T13:02:34+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Lost Votes *A call to first-time voters*</title><link href="/Lost-Votes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost Votes *A call to first-time voters*" /><published>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Lost-Votes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Lost-Votes">&lt;p&gt;The elections are, literally speaking, a celebration in India. The Indian Election Commission in its campaign to encourage citizens to turn up and vote calls them ‘&lt;em&gt;Desh ka Tyohar&lt;/em&gt;’ ( The National Festival). And why not? After all, this is the only time when politicians are knocking on the doors of 900 million eligible voters and not the other way round. For Indians, elections are about debating a host of complex and not-so-complex issues, and then choosing whosoever will deliver the highest standards of living to them. For the rest of the world, Indian elections are about their awe-inspiring size and the grandeur (much like any big Indian wedding). For the Indians living abroad, it is somewhere in between…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a young country when compared to its more developed Asian peers like China, Japan and Singapore. In the last general elections in 2014, 24 million first-time voters were added to the electoral list. If this number is astounding enough for you, what about the 45 million first-time voters in 2019? This number is larger than the populations of 200 countries (not even kidding). Most of these 45 million voters are aged between 18 to 24. No wonder a lot of campaign issues like unemployment, nationalism under the garb of national security, income guarantees try to capture the imagination of these voters. Politicians are bearing the hot Indian summer, campaigning incessantly, using social media, releasing music videos, and whatnot, to get the youth to their side. What a waste of effort will it be to see many of the youth not voting at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you talk to students in Delhi University (which has the youth coming to study from across India), many are not going to vote for two reasons: one is stupid, and the other is sensible, but not sufficient enough to not vote. Talking about the sensible reason first, the trouble is that of travelling back to their hometowns to vote. Most first-time voters are studying in places far away from their hometowns. For them, travelling back for &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; one day for &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; a single vote which ‘&lt;em&gt;won’t even matter&lt;/em&gt;’ is not worth it. Add on to this their stupid reason: they &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; don’t see a suitable candidate to vote for. They dislike the incumbent, they hate the alternatives. You combine these two reasons: of having to travel all way back to your hometown (India is a big country, geographically speaking) only to vote for someone you do not support, and you become sympathetic to their case of not voting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem here is that everything is problematic. Voting is NOT a privilege which can be compromised at the cost of personal comfort. There are voters participating in the festival of democracy by braving the gunshots and IED bombs of Maoists. These villagers are warned by local Naxalites to vote only at the expense of losing their lives, not to mention the election officials and security personnel who facilitate the voting in these remote areas, often at the cost of their lives. The State is making attempts to make sure every eligible citizen votes in the elections. Their work has stretched from setting up a polling booth specifically for one person in the middle of the Gir forest in western India amongst Asiatic Lions to election officials walking through knee-deep snow for 45 kilometers in the Himalayas with their election equipment for a meagre 37 voters. Oppressed women and Dalits fight their oppressors to exercise their franchise independently, every time they are asked to not vote or vote for a particular political party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these examples do not hit the young Indian’s “Lutyens’ Delhi” conscience, then the idea of voting should. A vote is an expression of freedom. It symbolises a free people living in a free land - a luxury not all human beings can enjoy. From being labelled “unfit to govern ourselves” by the British (White Man’s Burden, remember?), which became an excuse to oppress millions of people before independence to doomsayers predicting our Balkanisation after independence, an Indian’s vote is a slap to every coloniser or India-skeptic who ever questioned our right to nationhood. It is not, I repeat, a luxury. Lastly, young India’s vote determines India’s future. But, who cares? Saving a few Rupees on travel cost and having ‘exam prep’ is more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the young, educated Indian’s attitude brings with it ironies which should be pointed out. How can we complain of the lack of young politicians when the youth does not prioritise engaging in democratic practices? How can we complain of lack of alternatives (the stupid excuse to not vote) when the youth does not care about the nation’s future? Aren’t our politicians a reflection of the society, no matter how skewed the reflection is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, 281 million registered voters did not vote. To give you some perspective, ‘only’ 183 million voters are registered in the US- the world’s second largest democracy. It is as if a whole nation did not vote. 2014 was a wave election when the country was inspired by an ambitious leader. Voters also, for the first time, had the option to vote NOTA (None of the Above). Hence, the number of people opting not to exercise their franchise, in 2019, is expected to be larger. While high voter turnouts in percentage terms show how much faith Indians have in democracy, what is being argued here is the reason(s) to not vote of a very important section of the society is deplorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a young democracy. As we mature, we are bringing more reforms to our democratic setup. NOTA was one such reform. NOTA gives the ‘frustrated’ voter to register his anti-establishment sentiment in an established way. How many countries can take pride in this? While NOTA has been criticised for its ‘impotence’ (even if NOTA has most votes in a constituency, the candidate with highest votes still gets elected), it is a step in the right direction. Reform does not come in one go, but only gradually. If NOTA’s vote share keeps on rising, as it has since being introduced, policymakers might be tempted to give it its due potency a few general elections down the line. There are still more reforms which can be discussed but won’t be due to lack of space, like the Right to Recall or the introduction of a ‘Proportionate Representation System’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the above-mentioned reforms, ideas like proxy voting, postal ballots, online voting and setting up ‘voting centers’ to enable those who live away from their hometowns to vote in their city of stay are being floated around. In fact, the &lt;em&gt;Times of India&lt;/em&gt; has started a petition called ‘Lost Votes’ to bring to the government’s notice the need to enable voting from the place of residence. Change will come but who will bring the change? &lt;em&gt;The leaders of tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. What are &lt;em&gt;the leaders of tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; doing? Thinking of the &lt;em&gt;Right to Vote&lt;/em&gt; to be a &lt;em&gt;privilege&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an appeal to all those first-time voters who have been caught in the inertia of everyday life. Remember, if we don’t change anything, then nothing will change. It is time we change the system &lt;em&gt;by being a part of it&lt;/em&gt; rather than being a part of it &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the system reforms itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidyarthi</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The elections are, literally speaking, a celebration in India. The Indian Election Commission in its campaign to encourage citizens to turn up and vote calls them ‘Desh ka Tyohar’ ( The National Festival). And why not? After all, this is the only time when politicians are knocking on the doors of 900 million eligible voters and not the other way round. For Indians, elections are about debating a host of complex and not-so-complex issues, and then choosing whosoever will deliver the highest standards of living to them. For the rest of the world, Indian elections are about their awe-inspiring size and the grandeur (much like any big Indian wedding). For the Indians living abroad, it is somewhere in between…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jadis the Bells: The Pyres of Notre Dame</title><link href="/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jadis the Bells: The Pyres of Notre Dame" /><published>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame">&lt;p&gt;Jadis, the bells. Paris is in flames. Notre de Dame de Paris, my dearest, most
cherished Cathedral, our Lady of Paris, is burning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or certainly, it was when I began writing. Now it sits, an exhausted carcass,
divested of that eldest of jewels from the Parisian skyline. Much of the stained
glass is ruined. And the windows have been blinded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly painful for all French people. I, like many of them, have a
long, difficult and passionate relationship with Notre Dame, mostly because of
how much I have sung about it. I remember the first time I saw the Cathedral
itself depicted, in the Disney film, &lt;em&gt;The Hunchback of Notre Dame&lt;/em&gt;. The most
gothic, the darkest piece in the mouse’s repertoire, it marked me as a child.
The first time I heard those voices, coupled with those spires, stabbing into
that sky, I was terrified, I was exhilarated, I was amazed at the power of the
artistic and dark marvel. It stayed with me forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passion people can have for something so immortal as a building can truly
show how they can bring out the personhood within our creations, the moral in
the static. Anthropology has much to say about such things, particularly in the
works of Michel Foucault, especially on how architecture affects peoples’
feelings; how their surroundings affect their moods; how buildings can be so
evocative, purely because of this integral intransitive nature of the human
spirit, because of this very ghost within the shell. And what ghosts do haunt
our cities now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victor Hugo knew this, in fact he published that famous hunchback’s tale in an
effort to generate public interest in the Cathedral, which was at the time
Paris’s local, dilapidated and forgotten ruin. His book, in time, helped garner
enough interest to pay for the restorations we saw crumble and part into dust
and smoke in the wind. And so that spirit passes. And so passes the old Europe,
into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I ever sang a solo in our rural town’s music conservatoire young
choir, at say 12 or 13, I knew what I would sing about. I still remember my name
being called, as I stepped out from behind the curtain to expectant applause,
and the bells shook, and the voices did swell, until my queue, on a little
accordion…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Morning in Paris, the city awakes to the Bells of Notre Dame. The fisherman
fishes, the bakerman bakes, to the Bells of Notre Dame. From the big bells as
LOUD as the Thunder, to the little bells as -soft- as a psalm, and SOME say the
SOUL of the city’s the TOLL of the bells… The Bells of Notre Dame. Kyrie
eleison…”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was never the same for me again. I still remember sitting in the cellar
of our old 15th century house, in France, intermittently watching the musical
Notre Dame de Paris, waiting for my calls to help with the dinners we would host
at the Manor. I sat in awe as Bruneau Pelletier sang away about “a time of
Cathedrals”, becoming one of my vocal heroes, the song becoming one of my go-to
standards. That famous song of the successful musical show touches on the advent
of the Cathedral as a symbol of man’s growing ambition in Europe, heralded by
the Gothic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the passage from Romanesque to Gothic architecture, in making the buildings
bigger, European architecture had looked to nature to make the inside of
churches resemble the outside world and was inspired by the natural landscape
for decoration and adaptation of space. The very term ‘gothic’ itself was used
derogatively by writers like Molière to criticise a barbarous, pagan style
called monstrous by association with a less ‘civilised’ age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By very virtue of worshipping a ‘pagus’, a local spirit of nature, the earlier
pagans venerated nature, and medieval Christian churches began to take on
aspects emulative of the ‘nemetons’, sacred groves of the heathens from Europe
of yore. Greeks and Romans themselves had their ‘tenemos’, areas of vegetation
or clearings separated from public use, for a religious purpose (associated with
the female Oracle at Delphi; perhaps related to the Greek &lt;em&gt;delphus&lt;/em&gt;, ‘womb’).
The Norse Poetic &lt;em&gt;Edda&lt;/em&gt; features the open-air ‘hörgr’ (harrow, etymologically
related to ‘heathen’). D. Wilson notes that for the Anglo-Saxons, the hörgr is
specifically a “special type of religious site, that occupied a prominent
position on high land and was a communal place of worship for a specific group
of people”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, almost as if inspired by a divine, pagan purpose sleeping within them, as
if it had been dictated to them by an ancestral wisdom, the medieval European
builders of gothic churches beheld the truly sacred, the natural world, and made
of it a cold, stone creation. They took the magical outside, brought it inside,
and made of it the prerogative of their one god and the possession of the mortal
man. All of this, in simple architecture, in ancient stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the veneration of fertility in the form of resplendent, beautiful goddesses
was retained somehow by the Europeans of old Paris, for though referring to the
Virgin Mary, they made of this now presently wounded cathedral, ‘Our Lady’, of
the city.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I saw the place in person was in 2017 on a much belated visit to
the capital, I was shy and nervous about the city, like an estranged friend,
like a lost lover, but when I arrived with a companion acting as guide at the
station of the Isle de la Cité, then I knew. Then I felt it. The soul of Paris.
It was about time. It was about the enduring, deepest European aspect. And then
we went upstairs, and to the street. And I heard it. I heard them. The bells of
Notre Dame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally did go inside, it was a deeply spiritual experience, but not for
Christian reasons. For only then did I feel and know Paris. The high ceilings
and high halls, evoking Europe’s ancient sacred groves of tall trees, oak, pine
and poplar. The Cathedral’s small park by the Seine, watching the people of the
city go by, young people, young students, people from intelligent cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People love their cities, and they love the buildings which they and their kin
have woken up to and walked past for centuries. Such a paysage of human
construction acts to support a sort of consistency of a nation’s spirit. These
buildings are a skeleton, they are the frameworks which contain and maintain the
very culture of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so everywhere, on our social media platforms, on our video-streaming
services, all that can be heard is that “Europe is dying!”. It is not the first
time a great fire having devastated a great edifice of cultural import has
prompted reactions of national significance. Most significantly, comparisons can
be drawn to the 1933 Reichstag Fire, when the burning of the historic German
Parliament building in Berlin allowed Adolf Hitler to put the country into a
state of national alert. This was the first and most conclusive step towards
seizing power on a national scale for Hitler, and it sealed Germany’s future
forever.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracies have abounded for decades and ever will as to the cause of such
fires. But the consequences of such fires are inarguable: grim, dejected locals,
suddenly feeling a great need to protect what is theirs for pride and for
sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, poor Notre Dame. If her bells do not sound, Paris is made mute. If her
glass does not shine, Paris is blinded. But we must not forget that as long as
her children live, Our Lady of Paris survives. And so we must look to future
truth, and future Europeans. If their spirit built her, their spirit can do and
ought to do so much more than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jadis, les cloches. Adieux Notre Dame. Adieux Paris. I owe you the letters after
my name. And I hear you forever in my heart. Jadis, the bells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this comes now, when we see ourselves go mad, when a black hole is seen for
the first time, and we stare into it; the abyss stares back, and smiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw fire, and as it presides over us now, the black hole sun dawns. A vile
rictus upon us. How destiny does smile, sickeningly. How the fates, as the
vates, do seem to have a sense of humour. Clown World begins. A Circle of fire
forms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Morgan Black</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Jadis, the bells. Paris is in flames. Notre de Dame de Paris, my dearest, most cherished Cathedral, our Lady of Paris, is burning. Or certainly, it was when I began writing. Now it sits, an exhausted carcass, divested of that eldest of jewels from the Parisian skyline. Much of the stained glass is ruined. And the windows have been blinded. This is particularly painful for all French people. I, like many of them, have a long, difficult and passionate relationship with Notre Dame, mostly because of how much I have sung about it. I remember the first time I saw the Cathedral itself depicted, in the Disney film, The Hunchback of Notre Dame. The most gothic, the darkest piece in the mouse’s repertoire, it marked me as a child. The first time I heard those voices, coupled with those spires, stabbing into that sky, I was terrified, I was exhilarated, I was amazed at the power of the artistic and dark marvel. It stayed with me forever. The passion people can have for something so immortal as a building can truly show how they can bring out the personhood within our creations, the moral in the static. Anthropology has much to say about such things, particularly in the works of Michel Foucault, especially on how architecture affects peoples’ feelings; how their surroundings affect their moods; how buildings can be so evocative, purely because of this integral intransitive nature of the human spirit, because of this very ghost within the shell. And what ghosts do haunt our cities now. Victor Hugo knew this, in fact he published that famous hunchback’s tale in an effort to generate public interest in the Cathedral, which was at the time Paris’s local, dilapidated and forgotten ruin. His book, in time, helped garner enough interest to pay for the restorations we saw crumble and part into dust and smoke in the wind. And so that spirit passes. And so passes the old Europe, into oblivion. The first time I ever sang a solo in our rural town’s music conservatoire young choir, at say 12 or 13, I knew what I would sing about. I still remember my name being called, as I stepped out from behind the curtain to expectant applause, and the bells shook, and the voices did swell, until my queue, on a little accordion… “Morning in Paris, the city awakes to the Bells of Notre Dame. The fisherman fishes, the bakerman bakes, to the Bells of Notre Dame. From the big bells as LOUD as the Thunder, to the little bells as -soft- as a psalm, and SOME say the SOUL of the city’s the TOLL of the bells… The Bells of Notre Dame. Kyrie eleison…”. And it was never the same for me again. I still remember sitting in the cellar of our old 15th century house, in France, intermittently watching the musical Notre Dame de Paris, waiting for my calls to help with the dinners we would host at the Manor. I sat in awe as Bruneau Pelletier sang away about “a time of Cathedrals”, becoming one of my vocal heroes, the song becoming one of my go-to standards. That famous song of the successful musical show touches on the advent of the Cathedral as a symbol of man’s growing ambition in Europe, heralded by the Gothic. In the passage from Romanesque to Gothic architecture, in making the buildings bigger, European architecture had looked to nature to make the inside of churches resemble the outside world and was inspired by the natural landscape for decoration and adaptation of space. The very term ‘gothic’ itself was used derogatively by writers like Molière to criticise a barbarous, pagan style called monstrous by association with a less ‘civilised’ age. By very virtue of worshipping a ‘pagus’, a local spirit of nature, the earlier pagans venerated nature, and medieval Christian churches began to take on aspects emulative of the ‘nemetons’, sacred groves of the heathens from Europe of yore. Greeks and Romans themselves had their ‘tenemos’, areas of vegetation or clearings separated from public use, for a religious purpose (associated with the female Oracle at Delphi; perhaps related to the Greek delphus, ‘womb’). The Norse Poetic Edda features the open-air ‘hörgr’ (harrow, etymologically related to ‘heathen’). D. Wilson notes that for the Anglo-Saxons, the hörgr is specifically a “special type of religious site, that occupied a prominent position on high land and was a communal place of worship for a specific group of people”. Soon, almost as if inspired by a divine, pagan purpose sleeping within them, as if it had been dictated to them by an ancestral wisdom, the medieval European builders of gothic churches beheld the truly sacred, the natural world, and made of it a cold, stone creation. They took the magical outside, brought it inside, and made of it the prerogative of their one god and the possession of the mortal man. All of this, in simple architecture, in ancient stone. Even the veneration of fertility in the form of resplendent, beautiful goddesses was retained somehow by the Europeans of old Paris, for though referring to the Virgin Mary, they made of this now presently wounded cathedral, ‘Our Lady’, of the city.   The first time I saw the place in person was in 2017 on a much belated visit to the capital, I was shy and nervous about the city, like an estranged friend, like a lost lover, but when I arrived with a companion acting as guide at the station of the Isle de la Cité, then I knew. Then I felt it. The soul of Paris. It was about time. It was about the enduring, deepest European aspect. And then we went upstairs, and to the street. And I heard it. I heard them. The bells of Notre Dame. When I finally did go inside, it was a deeply spiritual experience, but not for Christian reasons. For only then did I feel and know Paris. The high ceilings and high halls, evoking Europe’s ancient sacred groves of tall trees, oak, pine and poplar. The Cathedral’s small park by the Seine, watching the people of the city go by, young people, young students, people from intelligent cities. People love their cities, and they love the buildings which they and their kin have woken up to and walked past for centuries. Such a paysage of human construction acts to support a sort of consistency of a nation’s spirit. These buildings are a skeleton, they are the frameworks which contain and maintain the very culture of the people. And so everywhere, on our social media platforms, on our video-streaming services, all that can be heard is that “Europe is dying!”. It is not the first time a great fire having devastated a great edifice of cultural import has prompted reactions of national significance. Most significantly, comparisons can be drawn to the 1933 Reichstag Fire, when the burning of the historic German Parliament building in Berlin allowed Adolf Hitler to put the country into a state of national alert. This was the first and most conclusive step towards seizing power on a national scale for Hitler, and it sealed Germany’s future forever.    Conspiracies have abounded for decades and ever will as to the cause of such fires. But the consequences of such fires are inarguable: grim, dejected locals, suddenly feeling a great need to protect what is theirs for pride and for sovereignty. And so, poor Notre Dame. If her bells do not sound, Paris is made mute. If her glass does not shine, Paris is blinded. But we must not forget that as long as her children live, Our Lady of Paris survives. And so we must look to future truth, and future Europeans. If their spirit built her, their spirit can do and ought to do so much more than this. Jadis, les cloches. Adieux Notre Dame. Adieux Paris. I owe you the letters after my name. And I hear you forever in my heart. Jadis, the bells. And this comes now, when we see ourselves go mad, when a black hole is seen for the first time, and we stare into it; the abyss stares back, and smiles. I saw fire, and as it presides over us now, the black hole sun dawns. A vile rictus upon us. How destiny does smile, sickeningly. How the fates, as the vates, do seem to have a sense of humour. Clown World begins. A Circle of fire forms.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Talk About Islam</title><link href="/How-to-Talk-about-Islam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Talk About Islam" /><published>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</updated><id>/How-to-Talk-about-Islam</id><content type="html" xml:base="/How-to-Talk-about-Islam">&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that Islam is by far the most powerful religion in the world
today. With a presence on almost every continent inhabited by man, a powerful
theocratic political influence in countries dominated by its adherents, a
rapidly increasing immigrant population in post-Christian European countries, an
ever-strengthening missionary influence, and a global following of more than a
billion people, it has come to influence much of the modern world. In 2008, the
Vatican revealed that Muslims have overtaken Catholics as far as the number of
members is concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, it is no longer possible for people to simply ignore the Islamic
phenomenon, no matter what their opinion of it might be. The reason is that
Islam is quite unavoidable. There is hardly a place on earth when the &lt;em&gt;adhan&lt;/em&gt;
cannot be heard. There is a hardly a skyline which does not have a minaret
reaching up to the heavens. No matter where you go, Islam is there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a convert from Hinduism to orthodox Catholicism, there is much in Islam that
I admire, despite the deeply troubled history that my Church has shared with the
followers of Muhammad. I deeply admire, for instance, Islam’s teachings on
modesty. I am appreciative of many of the values which Islam inculcates in its
adherents – the devotion to one’s parents and the respect for elders.
Catholicism and Islam both profess to be monotheistic and eschew the joining of
partners with Almighty God, although our views about the nature of Almighty God
are radically different. And it goes without saying that I condemn any and all
forms of violence, hatred, and bigotry towards Muslims on the basis of their
religious affiliation as unethical, immoral and – above all – un-Christian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are also elements in Islam that I find deeply troubling. Now,
notice that I use the word “elements in Islam”, rather than simply “Islam”.
After all, there are many different groups that profess to be Muslim and which
have different interpretations of Islam. For instance, the Ahmadiyya Muslim
Community is entirely pacifistic in nature and condemns any and all forms of
religious terrorism. There are also many Sufis, Salafis, and mainstream Sunnis
who have condemned violence against non-Muslims and advocate a more apolitical
form of Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I acknowledge and respect the fact that the texts which &lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt; to call for
violence – in the Quran and the Hadith – are open to interpretation. As such, it
is not my intention to paint all Muslims with a broad brush, or to pretend that
Islam is monolithic. Just as it would be disingenuous for someone to paint my
faith or any other faith with gross overgeneralizations, so would be to do the
same with Islam. However, there are certainly some trends in the modern media
that are problematic and need to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a tendency (among many secularists, liberals and the left-leaning) to
classify all critics of Islam as part of the far-right. This is not only
inaccurate, but also extremely dangerous, and contrary to the principle of the
freedom of expression. The act of criticising a particular
ideology/proposition/belief system is not the same as advocating violence,
hatred, discrimination or bigotry against proponents of that
ideology/proposition/belief system&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that all those who advocate violence against proponents of a
particular ideology/proposition/belief system also happen to be critics of that
particular ideology/proposition/belief system. But not all who criticise the
ideology/proposition/belief system are calling for violence against proponents
of that ideology/proposition/belief system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give an example from everyday life: all oranges are fruits, but not all
fruits are oranges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oranges might be bad, and all oranges might be fruits, but the fact that all
oranges are bad does not imply that all fruits are bad, even though all oranges
are fruits. This is because of the very simple fact that there are some fruits
which are not oranges. In other words, all anti-Muslim bigots are critics of
Islam, but not all critics of Islam are anti-Muslim bigots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider, for example, the case of David Wood, a convert from atheism to
Christianity. Wood is a fairly prominent critic of Islam. He has criticised the
teachings of Islam as inherently violent, the founder of Islam as an immoral
man, and the claims of Islam as intellectually deficient. However, I am yet to
come across a single video in which he has called for hatred against Muslims. On
the contrary, I follow him regularly and can testify that, as far as I can see,
he has nothing in his heart but love for Muslims, whom he believes to be in
error. This he has demonstrated on numerous occasions in many ways. One of the
best examples I can give is when he actually attempted to meet with someone who
had threatened to kill him. He recorded the occasion on camera when he visited
the agreed-upon venue and found that his would-be assassin hadn’t turned up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a professed Christian evangelist, Wood’s goal is not to spread bigotry
against Muslims, but to show Muslims (what he considers to be) the defects in
Islam, and to invite them to (what he believes to be) a better way:
Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what has been the response to his criticism? Intelligent, counter-critiques
from Muslims? On occasion, yes, as we see in the case of the Islamic scholar
(and gentleman) Shabir Ally who has debated him on numerous occasions and who
has always treated him with dignity, respect, and goodwill. However, much of the
backlash against his work has been neither intelligent, nor reasoned, nor
humane. Much of the responses to his criticism include death threats and the
mockery of his disabled children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not every Muslim has responded in this manner. Of course, there are
many Muslims who would consider such barbaric behaviour to be un-Islamic. Of
course, such aforementioned peaceful Muslims may (and probably do) have peaceful
interpretations of Islam. But what we must realise is that there is a powerful
party within the religion of Islam which is violent, intolerant of criticism,
aggressively imperialist and which bases their beliefs not on political
convictions but on religiously motivated interpretations of Quranic and Hadithic
texts. And it is these hyper-fundamentalists who are making use of the
atmosphere of ‘tolerance’ and political correctness to advance an agenda that is
diabolical and toxic. Attempts to suppress peaceful, intelligent critics of
Islam is not ‘tolerance’. It is intolerance. And such attempts play right into
the hands of the Islamists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing that we see in the case of Wood is that a number of these
internet jihadis have started false-flagging his content. The shocking result
has been that Facebook has notified him that some of his posts “go against”
their community guidelines. These include posts in which Wood simply informed
his audiences of the most recent threats he had gotten from jihadis! Not a
single one of them included a call to violence, but only an appeal to keep-up
the criticism and satire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems, at times, that the people running Facebook have an extremely warped
idea of what hate speech is. Criticising an ideology as intellectually and
morally deficient is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; hate speech, but threatening someone for making those
criticisms certainly is. Indeed, as I have been at pains to emphasise: we have
to love our Muslim friends, condemn acts of violence against Muslims and fight
anti-Muslim discrimination. But that doesn’t mean we must be naïve and pretend
that Islam is a wholly pacifistic religion and that all the IS terrorists are
merely politically-motivated people using religion as a cover to gain support
for their cause. Such an analysis is not only painfully ignorant of the facts,
but is also dangerous since it encourages complacency against what is clearly a
rising tide of religiously-motivated Islamic fundamentalism in the world today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we similarly pretend that the founder of Islam was a feminist and a
pacifist? No. If the historical evidence does not indicate that he was such, we
should not pretend that he was such. We should portray him in as historically
accurate a manner as possible – even if that portrayal is deemed offensive and
blasphemous by violent cyber-jihadists who have only one goal: the violent
promulgation of a religious system and the suppression of all criticism of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many peaceful, kind, gentlemanly and dignified people in the Muslim
community who would consider themselves orthodox and who would, in fact, agree
with what I am saying today. Yet, that still begs the question: how &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; we
talk about Islam? We should seek to honestly evaluate the religion itself. But
how should we judge what the religion is? There are peaceful Muslims and violent
Muslims, just as there are peaceful Christians and violent Christians. Which are
the true followers, and which are more influenced by other ideologies rather
than the doctrine itself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience (having extensively and intensively studied religion for around
ten years now), we should always judge a religion on the basis of its &lt;em&gt;Sources&lt;/em&gt;
and its &lt;em&gt;Heroes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Sources&lt;/em&gt; of a religion are essentially its authorities and/or sources of
doctrine. In Protestant Christianity, the &lt;em&gt;Source&lt;/em&gt; is Scripture alone, and its
plain perspicuous teaching. In Catholic Christianity, the source is Scripture
and Apostolic Tradition as received and interpreted by the Magisterium (i.e.,
the Church itself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Heroes&lt;/em&gt; of a religion are those figures which have been deemed by the
Sources/Authorities as having followed the religion well (though not necessarily
perfectly, and there are different grades of heroes in every religion). The
ultimate Hero of all Christianity is Jesus Himself, who is believed to be the
perfect man. In Catholicism, the heroes are (to a certain degree) the saints.
Although it is generally agreed that the canonisation process only grants us
certainty that the deceased is in heaven, not that the person always lived an
exemplary life. This gives room for the believing Catholic to criticise even the
acts of saints, as many traditionalists have done with St. Mother Teresa, to
give an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Islam, the greatest hero is Muhammad himself, who is considered to be the
perfect example for all mankind. In Sunni Islam, Muhammad is closely followed by
the Four Rightly Guided Caliphs, whereas in Shia Islam, Muhammad is but one of
Fourteen Infallibles, which include – besides the founder himself – Fatima and
the Twelve Imams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when we judge Islam, we should first distinguish between the various schools
of Islam. Sunni Islam is not the same as Shia Islam or Ibadi Islam or Ahmadi
Islam. There are, so to speak, quite a few ‘Islams’, just as there are different
interpretations of Marxism, democracy, libertarianism, capitalism, feminism and
just about everything else. In other words, the next time you see some act of
violence perpetrated by fundamentalists of any religion or sect, ask yourself
the question: is this act of violence commanded by the Sources of the faith in
question? Is there any precedent for this sort of terror in the behaviour of its
heroes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should ask the same question when it comes to the good actions of peaceful
adherents. When you see followers of a religion endorsing pacifism or separation
of religion and state, are they acting faithfully according to their Sources and
Heroes? Or are there more influenced by other ideologies, in light of which they
interpret their religion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I end this article with a comparison between the Christian Crusades and the
Islamic Mujahideen. The Crusades were an administrative decision, in part made
by the Pope. Catholicism does not require its adherents to consider Papal
administrative decisions as infallible – the only infallible things coming out
of the Pope are his ratifications of ecumenical councils and ex-cathedra
statements; that is to say, matters which &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; concern doctrine and dogma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Administrative decisions, as per Catholic ecclesiology, are &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; fallible.
As a matter of fact, it is the conservatives in the Church who are very loud in
criticising the administrative decisions of recent Popes, such as the decision
of Pope Paul VI to allow the priest to celebrate the Mass facing the
congregation (&lt;em&gt;versus populum&lt;/em&gt;) rather than the East (&lt;em&gt;ad orientem&lt;/em&gt;) as has
traditionally been practised. So, largely, the Crusades are not part of Catholic
doctrine, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not say this in order to “wash my hands clean” of the Crusades, so to
speak. Personally, I think the Crusades had a noble intent in &lt;em&gt;theory&lt;/em&gt; (i.e.,
that of defending Christendom), but I lament the fact that in &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; many of
the Crusaders became too extreme. Rather than simply defeating enemy military
forces, they committed unspeakable atrocities upon civilians which are
horrendous, lamentable and condemnable. As a traditional and orthodox Catholic,
I am &lt;em&gt;ashamed&lt;/em&gt; of the misdeeds that were perpetrated in the name of the
Crusades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing: my religion gives me the liberty to say this. My faith
does not compel me to believe that the Crusaders were “inspired by God”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you study the early Muslim invasions of neighbouring civilisations, ask
yourself the question: can we say the same about Islam? Who led these invasions?
Were these figures deemed by Islam to be inspired by God in their acts and to
be, in some sense, infallible? Do the chief sources command its adherents to
consider their acts of war as virtuous on the part of a ruler? Our judgment of
Islam should be based on these facts. I will leave you to make up your own mind.
It may turn out that, in fact, Islam is an extremely peaceful and humane
religion. Or it may turn out another way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only ask you to use sound judgment in your study and to not be afraid of the
truth, however hard it may turn out to be. However, in all our critique or
appraisal, we must remember that our analysis of a doctrine should not seep into
a generalisation of the moral character of the adherents of that doctrine. This
attitude allows me to be extremely kind and respectful to my Muslim friends
while, at the same time, giving me total liberty to analyse and evaluate the
religion as my conscience commands me. And that is how we should talk about
Islam today, condemning it where we see condemnation due, fighting for and
respecting its adherents when they so require, and accepting or rejecting it for
what it is when truth so demands.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">There is no doubt that Islam is by far the most powerful religion in the world today. With a presence on almost every continent inhabited by man, a powerful theocratic political influence in countries dominated by its adherents, a rapidly increasing immigrant population in post-Christian European countries, an ever-strengthening missionary influence, and a global following of more than a billion people, it has come to influence much of the modern world. In 2008, the Vatican revealed that Muslims have overtaken Catholics as far as the number of members is concerned. As such, it is no longer possible for people to simply ignore the Islamic phenomenon, no matter what their opinion of it might be. The reason is that Islam is quite unavoidable. There is hardly a place on earth when the adhan cannot be heard. There is a hardly a skyline which does not have a minaret reaching up to the heavens. No matter where you go, Islam is there. As a convert from Hinduism to orthodox Catholicism, there is much in Islam that I admire, despite the deeply troubled history that my Church has shared with the followers of Muhammad. I deeply admire, for instance, Islam’s teachings on modesty. I am appreciative of many of the values which Islam inculcates in its adherents – the devotion to one’s parents and the respect for elders. Catholicism and Islam both profess to be monotheistic and eschew the joining of partners with Almighty God, although our views about the nature of Almighty God are radically different. And it goes without saying that I condemn any and all forms of violence, hatred, and bigotry towards Muslims on the basis of their religious affiliation as unethical, immoral and – above all – un-Christian. However, there are also elements in Islam that I find deeply troubling. Now, notice that I use the word “elements in Islam”, rather than simply “Islam”. After all, there are many different groups that profess to be Muslim and which have different interpretations of Islam. For instance, the Ahmadiyya Muslim Community is entirely pacifistic in nature and condemns any and all forms of religious terrorism. There are also many Sufis, Salafis, and mainstream Sunnis who have condemned violence against non-Muslims and advocate a more apolitical form of Islam. I acknowledge and respect the fact that the texts which seem to call for violence – in the Quran and the Hadith – are open to interpretation. As such, it is not my intention to paint all Muslims with a broad brush, or to pretend that Islam is monolithic. Just as it would be disingenuous for someone to paint my faith or any other faith with gross overgeneralizations, so would be to do the same with Islam. However, there are certainly some trends in the modern media that are problematic and need to be addressed. There is a tendency (among many secularists, liberals and the left-leaning) to classify all critics of Islam as part of the far-right. This is not only inaccurate, but also extremely dangerous, and contrary to the principle of the freedom of expression. The act of criticising a particular ideology/proposition/belief system is not the same as advocating violence, hatred, discrimination or bigotry against proponents of that ideology/proposition/belief system Yes, it is true that all those who advocate violence against proponents of a particular ideology/proposition/belief system also happen to be critics of that particular ideology/proposition/belief system. But not all who criticise the ideology/proposition/belief system are calling for violence against proponents of that ideology/proposition/belief system. To give an example from everyday life: all oranges are fruits, but not all fruits are oranges. Oranges might be bad, and all oranges might be fruits, but the fact that all oranges are bad does not imply that all fruits are bad, even though all oranges are fruits. This is because of the very simple fact that there are some fruits which are not oranges. In other words, all anti-Muslim bigots are critics of Islam, but not all critics of Islam are anti-Muslim bigots. Consider, for example, the case of David Wood, a convert from atheism to Christianity. Wood is a fairly prominent critic of Islam. He has criticised the teachings of Islam as inherently violent, the founder of Islam as an immoral man, and the claims of Islam as intellectually deficient. However, I am yet to come across a single video in which he has called for hatred against Muslims. On the contrary, I follow him regularly and can testify that, as far as I can see, he has nothing in his heart but love for Muslims, whom he believes to be in error. This he has demonstrated on numerous occasions in many ways. One of the best examples I can give is when he actually attempted to meet with someone who had threatened to kill him. He recorded the occasion on camera when he visited the agreed-upon venue and found that his would-be assassin hadn’t turned up. As a professed Christian evangelist, Wood’s goal is not to spread bigotry against Muslims, but to show Muslims (what he considers to be) the defects in Islam, and to invite them to (what he believes to be) a better way: Christianity. But what has been the response to his criticism? Intelligent, counter-critiques from Muslims? On occasion, yes, as we see in the case of the Islamic scholar (and gentleman) Shabir Ally who has debated him on numerous occasions and who has always treated him with dignity, respect, and goodwill. However, much of the backlash against his work has been neither intelligent, nor reasoned, nor humane. Much of the responses to his criticism include death threats and the mockery of his disabled children. Of course, not every Muslim has responded in this manner. Of course, there are many Muslims who would consider such barbaric behaviour to be un-Islamic. Of course, such aforementioned peaceful Muslims may (and probably do) have peaceful interpretations of Islam. But what we must realise is that there is a powerful party within the religion of Islam which is violent, intolerant of criticism, aggressively imperialist and which bases their beliefs not on political convictions but on religiously motivated interpretations of Quranic and Hadithic texts. And it is these hyper-fundamentalists who are making use of the atmosphere of ‘tolerance’ and political correctness to advance an agenda that is diabolical and toxic. Attempts to suppress peaceful, intelligent critics of Islam is not ‘tolerance’. It is intolerance. And such attempts play right into the hands of the Islamists. The interesting thing that we see in the case of Wood is that a number of these internet jihadis have started false-flagging his content. The shocking result has been that Facebook has notified him that some of his posts “go against” their community guidelines. These include posts in which Wood simply informed his audiences of the most recent threats he had gotten from jihadis! Not a single one of them included a call to violence, but only an appeal to keep-up the criticism and satire. It seems, at times, that the people running Facebook have an extremely warped idea of what hate speech is. Criticising an ideology as intellectually and morally deficient is not hate speech, but threatening someone for making those criticisms certainly is. Indeed, as I have been at pains to emphasise: we have to love our Muslim friends, condemn acts of violence against Muslims and fight anti-Muslim discrimination. But that doesn’t mean we must be naïve and pretend that Islam is a wholly pacifistic religion and that all the IS terrorists are merely politically-motivated people using religion as a cover to gain support for their cause. Such an analysis is not only painfully ignorant of the facts, but is also dangerous since it encourages complacency against what is clearly a rising tide of religiously-motivated Islamic fundamentalism in the world today. Should we similarly pretend that the founder of Islam was a feminist and a pacifist? No. If the historical evidence does not indicate that he was such, we should not pretend that he was such. We should portray him in as historically accurate a manner as possible – even if that portrayal is deemed offensive and blasphemous by violent cyber-jihadists who have only one goal: the violent promulgation of a religious system and the suppression of all criticism of it. There are many peaceful, kind, gentlemanly and dignified people in the Muslim community who would consider themselves orthodox and who would, in fact, agree with what I am saying today. Yet, that still begs the question: how should we talk about Islam? We should seek to honestly evaluate the religion itself. But how should we judge what the religion is? There are peaceful Muslims and violent Muslims, just as there are peaceful Christians and violent Christians. Which are the true followers, and which are more influenced by other ideologies rather than the doctrine itself? In my experience (having extensively and intensively studied religion for around ten years now), we should always judge a religion on the basis of its Sources and its Heroes. What do I mean by this? The Sources of a religion are essentially its authorities and/or sources of doctrine. In Protestant Christianity, the Source is Scripture alone, and its plain perspicuous teaching. In Catholic Christianity, the source is Scripture and Apostolic Tradition as received and interpreted by the Magisterium (i.e., the Church itself). The Heroes of a religion are those figures which have been deemed by the Sources/Authorities as having followed the religion well (though not necessarily perfectly, and there are different grades of heroes in every religion). The ultimate Hero of all Christianity is Jesus Himself, who is believed to be the perfect man. In Catholicism, the heroes are (to a certain degree) the saints. Although it is generally agreed that the canonisation process only grants us certainty that the deceased is in heaven, not that the person always lived an exemplary life. This gives room for the believing Catholic to criticise even the acts of saints, as many traditionalists have done with St. Mother Teresa, to give an example. In Islam, the greatest hero is Muhammad himself, who is considered to be the perfect example for all mankind. In Sunni Islam, Muhammad is closely followed by the Four Rightly Guided Caliphs, whereas in Shia Islam, Muhammad is but one of Fourteen Infallibles, which include – besides the founder himself – Fatima and the Twelve Imams. So, when we judge Islam, we should first distinguish between the various schools of Islam. Sunni Islam is not the same as Shia Islam or Ibadi Islam or Ahmadi Islam. There are, so to speak, quite a few ‘Islams’, just as there are different interpretations of Marxism, democracy, libertarianism, capitalism, feminism and just about everything else. In other words, the next time you see some act of violence perpetrated by fundamentalists of any religion or sect, ask yourself the question: is this act of violence commanded by the Sources of the faith in question? Is there any precedent for this sort of terror in the behaviour of its heroes? You should ask the same question when it comes to the good actions of peaceful adherents. When you see followers of a religion endorsing pacifism or separation of religion and state, are they acting faithfully according to their Sources and Heroes? Or are there more influenced by other ideologies, in light of which they interpret their religion? I end this article with a comparison between the Christian Crusades and the Islamic Mujahideen. The Crusades were an administrative decision, in part made by the Pope. Catholicism does not require its adherents to consider Papal administrative decisions as infallible – the only infallible things coming out of the Pope are his ratifications of ecumenical councils and ex-cathedra statements; that is to say, matters which solely concern doctrine and dogma. Administrative decisions, as per Catholic ecclesiology, are entirely fallible. As a matter of fact, it is the conservatives in the Church who are very loud in criticising the administrative decisions of recent Popes, such as the decision of Pope Paul VI to allow the priest to celebrate the Mass facing the congregation (versus populum) rather than the East (ad orientem) as has traditionally been practised. So, largely, the Crusades are not part of Catholic doctrine, if at all. I do not say this in order to “wash my hands clean” of the Crusades, so to speak. Personally, I think the Crusades had a noble intent in theory (i.e., that of defending Christendom), but I lament the fact that in practice many of the Crusaders became too extreme. Rather than simply defeating enemy military forces, they committed unspeakable atrocities upon civilians which are horrendous, lamentable and condemnable. As a traditional and orthodox Catholic, I am ashamed of the misdeeds that were perpetrated in the name of the Crusades. But here’s the thing: my religion gives me the liberty to say this. My faith does not compel me to believe that the Crusaders were “inspired by God”. But when you study the early Muslim invasions of neighbouring civilisations, ask yourself the question: can we say the same about Islam? Who led these invasions? Were these figures deemed by Islam to be inspired by God in their acts and to be, in some sense, infallible? Do the chief sources command its adherents to consider their acts of war as virtuous on the part of a ruler? Our judgment of Islam should be based on these facts. I will leave you to make up your own mind. It may turn out that, in fact, Islam is an extremely peaceful and humane religion. Or it may turn out another way. I only ask you to use sound judgment in your study and to not be afraid of the truth, however hard it may turn out to be. However, in all our critique or appraisal, we must remember that our analysis of a doctrine should not seep into a generalisation of the moral character of the adherents of that doctrine. This attitude allows me to be extremely kind and respectful to my Muslim friends while, at the same time, giving me total liberty to analyse and evaluate the religion as my conscience commands me. And that is how we should talk about Islam today, condemning it where we see condemnation due, fighting for and respecting its adherents when they so require, and accepting or rejecting it for what it is when truth so demands.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CLO’s - The New Danger to Financial Markets?</title><link href="/CLO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CLO’s - The New Danger to  Financial Markets?" /><published>2019-04-25T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-25T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/CLO</id><content type="html" xml:base="/CLO">&lt;p&gt;It’s funny to see the people who run financial markets so eagerly rushing into
committing the same mistake. Rushing for what? The same old, usual story. The
enticement of higher profits by undertaking higher risks provides the same high
to these investors as drugs do to teens. The global financial markets, which had
a near-death experience with CDOs just a decade ago, face a new product ready to
facilitate its total obliteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product in question this time is CLOs, or Collateralized Loan Obligations.
Believed to be a safer version of the infamous CDOs, or Collateralized Debt
Obligations, which was one of the main culprits of the 2008 Financial Crisis,
CLOs are already raising eyebrows all around the world. With the Governor of The
Bank of England Mark Carney and the former Fed Chairman Janet Yellen warning
about the potential risks, governments and the public are becoming wary.
However, it looks like these warnings are having no effect on banks and
institutional investors, for whom it was intended, as they continue buying CLOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A CLO is very similar to a CDO which, as mentioned earlier, was the main reason
for the downfall of the financial markets in 2008. A CLO is basically a huge
collection of loans given out by a bank for sale to banks and institutional
investors in small tranches or groups. The benefit that an investor gains from
buying a CLO is that he gets to earn the entire interest from the loans in his
group or “tranche”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the amount of CLOs currently outstanding in the world crossing  $700
billion, and with $100 billion being added each year, the amount of CLOs has
already reached the levels of CDOs before the Financial Crisis of 2008. The
structuring of a CLO is the same as a CDO. The groups of CLOs are rated by
rating agencies on the basis of the overall creditworthiness and mortgaged
assets. The CLO groups are majorly rated into AA, BBB+, BBB- and so on. Within
each individual group, each specific tranche is also rated. Hence, in an AA
class group, there are tranches rated AA, BBB+, BBB- and so forth. The same goes
for the BBB+ class group and all the other groups which follow. The highest
tranche of the highest group is paid first, followed by all the tranches in the
highest group, which is followed by all the groups and their respective
tranches. Hence, the lowest class tranche of the lowest group is the riskiest,
and promises the highest return, whereas, the highest class tranche of the
highest group is the safest and promises least return. This allows investors to
invest in groups and tranches according to their risk appetite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way in which CLOs have differed from CDOs have been stricter banking
regulations and the type of loans which are being put into the groups. Instead
of having only housing loans, CLOs offer a wide variety of loans such as
automobiles, housing, retail and so on. Moreover, stricter regulations demand
that banks hold some proportion of each group of CLOs in order to ensure that to
earn a riskless profit, the banks are not just giving loans to any individual
they meet, which happened in the case of CDOs during the Financial Crisis of
2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proponents of CLOs point towards the double-digit returns, low default rates and
resilience to rising interest rates. With banks such as Credit Suisse, Nomura,
Barclays and JP Morgan Chase showing confidence in CLOs due to its high returns
and substantially low risks, the demand for CLOs is rising in international
markets. The industry is stressing the fact that CLOs are not as vulnerable to
rising interest rates as CDOs were a decade ago. They also stress the fact that
only 36 tranches among the 1500 plus CLOs rated by S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings have
defaulted since 1994.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are downfalls. Investors assume that the portfolios are safer as
they are better diversified. But, diversification of portfolios has led to them
being made of fewer and larger loans, which increases concentration risk. These
leveraged loans are highly sensitive to economic conditions, with many loans
defaulting as soon as the economic conditions take a downturn. The condition
will be particularly adverse for Japanese banks, which have bought 75% of AAA
tranches and one-third of all CLOs, finance their operations by borrowing from
international markets. Losses can lead to difficulties in continuing operations,
which in turn may lead to a liquidity squeeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of a downturn, the CLOs pose a risk of creating adverse feedback
loops. Banks will be stuck with unsold loans clogging up inventories due to a
decrease in demand. Falling prices and tightening credit availability will cause
credit markets to seize up. Tighter credit will feed into the real economy
triggering losses, selling and price declines. Fears about the financial
positions of banks and investors will create havoc as depositors refuse to fund
banks and investors demand their money back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, it is clear that governments need to set in motion regulations and a
robust framework on how to go about dealing with CLOs. This is extremely
necessary as everyone today is accepting the fact that CLOs are a potentially
dangerous item capable of causing devastating chaos in the international
markets. Still, banks and institutional investors are pouring money into this
product with the hopes of higher returns from the higher risks they undertake.
It is clear that CLOs have the capability to topple the global financial markets
if it spirals out of control. Therefore, with the world talking of another
financial crisis, the question that needs to be answered is will it be the
phoenix of CDOs that proves to be the catalyst? The danger that currently
beholds us is that if we keep allowing investment junkies to get their
risk-fuelled fix, it will be the rest of us left to pick up the tab if the
international financial system enters rehab.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhishek Sancheti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">It’s funny to see the people who run financial markets so eagerly rushing into committing the same mistake. Rushing for what? The same old, usual story. The enticement of higher profits by undertaking higher risks provides the same high to these investors as drugs do to teens. The global financial markets, which had a near-death experience with CDOs just a decade ago, face a new product ready to facilitate its total obliteration. The product in question this time is CLOs, or Collateralized Loan Obligations. Believed to be a safer version of the infamous CDOs, or Collateralized Debt Obligations, which was one of the main culprits of the 2008 Financial Crisis, CLOs are already raising eyebrows all around the world. With the Governor of The Bank of England Mark Carney and the former Fed Chairman Janet Yellen warning about the potential risks, governments and the public are becoming wary. However, it looks like these warnings are having no effect on banks and institutional investors, for whom it was intended, as they continue buying CLOs. A CLO is very similar to a CDO which, as mentioned earlier, was the main reason for the downfall of the financial markets in 2008. A CLO is basically a huge collection of loans given out by a bank for sale to banks and institutional investors in small tranches or groups. The benefit that an investor gains from buying a CLO is that he gets to earn the entire interest from the loans in his group or “tranche”. With the amount of CLOs currently outstanding in the world crossing  $700 billion, and with $100 billion being added each year, the amount of CLOs has already reached the levels of CDOs before the Financial Crisis of 2008. The structuring of a CLO is the same as a CDO. The groups of CLOs are rated by rating agencies on the basis of the overall creditworthiness and mortgaged assets. The CLO groups are majorly rated into AA, BBB+, BBB- and so on. Within each individual group, each specific tranche is also rated. Hence, in an AA class group, there are tranches rated AA, BBB+, BBB- and so forth. The same goes for the BBB+ class group and all the other groups which follow. The highest tranche of the highest group is paid first, followed by all the tranches in the highest group, which is followed by all the groups and their respective tranches. Hence, the lowest class tranche of the lowest group is the riskiest, and promises the highest return, whereas, the highest class tranche of the highest group is the safest and promises least return. This allows investors to invest in groups and tranches according to their risk appetite. The only way in which CLOs have differed from CDOs have been stricter banking regulations and the type of loans which are being put into the groups. Instead of having only housing loans, CLOs offer a wide variety of loans such as automobiles, housing, retail and so on. Moreover, stricter regulations demand that banks hold some proportion of each group of CLOs in order to ensure that to earn a riskless profit, the banks are not just giving loans to any individual they meet, which happened in the case of CDOs during the Financial Crisis of 2008. Proponents of CLOs point towards the double-digit returns, low default rates and resilience to rising interest rates. With banks such as Credit Suisse, Nomura, Barclays and JP Morgan Chase showing confidence in CLOs due to its high returns and substantially low risks, the demand for CLOs is rising in international markets. The industry is stressing the fact that CLOs are not as vulnerable to rising interest rates as CDOs were a decade ago. They also stress the fact that only 36 tranches among the 1500 plus CLOs rated by S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings have defaulted since 1994. However, there are downfalls. Investors assume that the portfolios are safer as they are better diversified. But, diversification of portfolios has led to them being made of fewer and larger loans, which increases concentration risk. These leveraged loans are highly sensitive to economic conditions, with many loans defaulting as soon as the economic conditions take a downturn. The condition will be particularly adverse for Japanese banks, which have bought 75% of AAA tranches and one-third of all CLOs, finance their operations by borrowing from international markets. Losses can lead to difficulties in continuing operations, which in turn may lead to a liquidity squeeze. In the case of a downturn, the CLOs pose a risk of creating adverse feedback loops. Banks will be stuck with unsold loans clogging up inventories due to a decrease in demand. Falling prices and tightening credit availability will cause credit markets to seize up. Tighter credit will feed into the real economy triggering losses, selling and price declines. Fears about the financial positions of banks and investors will create havoc as depositors refuse to fund banks and investors demand their money back. Hence, it is clear that governments need to set in motion regulations and a robust framework on how to go about dealing with CLOs. This is extremely necessary as everyone today is accepting the fact that CLOs are a potentially dangerous item capable of causing devastating chaos in the international markets. Still, banks and institutional investors are pouring money into this product with the hopes of higher returns from the higher risks they undertake. It is clear that CLOs have the capability to topple the global financial markets if it spirals out of control. Therefore, with the world talking of another financial crisis, the question that needs to be answered is will it be the phoenix of CDOs that proves to be the catalyst? The danger that currently beholds us is that if we keep allowing investment junkies to get their risk-fuelled fix, it will be the rest of us left to pick up the tab if the international financial system enters rehab.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up</title><link href="/CL-QF" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up" /><published>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/CL-QF</id><content type="html" xml:base="/CL-QF">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City were narrowly defeated against a defiant Tottenham side in an enthralling Champions League quarter-final match that will live long in the memory of the competition’s illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first leg finished 1-0 to Spurs after Heung-Min Son’s late strike gave the home side the advantage heading into the second leg at the Etihad stadium; some will argue that the South Korean’s sole goal should have been saved by Ederson as it was close to his body but the sheer power off Son’s left boot managed to dumbfound the Brazilian goalkeeper. Perhaps the biggest turning point of the tie was Lloris’ early penalty save from Aguero, as from then on City’s opportunities were limited by a formidable Spurs defence who were successfully able to deny the Citizens from scoring a vital away goal. The first leg of the tie was a highly entertaining clash between two sides at the peak of their powers, but nobody expected the second leg to be as engrossing as it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Citizens needed to win by more than one goal at their home stadium to ensure going through to the semi-finals and despite the first leg defeat, City were still favourites to proceed to the next round, largely based on their impressive domestic successes and superior squad. Therefore, when Raheem Sterling scored in the 4th minute of the second leg to equal the aggregate score, many thought it would be a routine win for City, but these postulations were withdrawn after Heung-Min Son scored twice in quick succession to give Spurs the advantage. Astonishingly, Bernardo Silva’s deflected shot made it 2-2 within 11 minutes, and City, via Raheem Sterling again, added another before the interval to make it 3-2 on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expectedly, City began the second half putting immense pressure on the away side and their efforts eventually came to fruition after Sergio Aguero’s powerful near-post finish put City 4-2 up on 59 minutes. Spurs replied through Fernando Llorente, who became the unexpected hero after the ball bounced off his body into the net from a corner kick. In the end, the mesmerising game finished 4-3 to the Premier League champions, but it wasn’t enough as Spurs went through on away goals. The final few minutes of the tie saw Raheem Sterling score only for it to be ruled out for offside after VAR was consulted and City celebrations had already taken place in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After losing their talisman, Harry Kane, through a recurrent ankle injury in the first leg, few people expected Tottenham to beat Pep Guardiola’s prestigious team but Heung-Min Son stepped up to the plate in Kane’s absence, as he has numerous times this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result brings into question whether Pochettino is the better overall manager than Pep. Their rivalry stems from their time in Spain, as Espanyol and Barcelona managers respectively. Although Pep’s achievements in the game are unrivalled and has the superior record over the Argentine, Pochettino has had the lesser squad and defeated Pep in a quarter final despite not having made a signing since January 2018 and missing key players such as Harry Kane and Harry Winks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Messi shines again as Barcelona are into the semi-finals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona were 4-0 aggregate winners against a hopeless Manchester United side as the Catalan giants made light work of the Red Devils. After a 1-0 first leg defeat in which the Mancunians failed to provide any serious threat, United were made to pay for costly mistakes in the second leg as Leo Messi capitalised twice to give Barcelona a 3-0 aggregate advantage within 20 minutes of the second leg, all but ending the tie and sending Barcelona through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result marks Manchester United’s largest ever aggregate defeat in a two-legged European tie, while Barcelona will go on to face Liverpool in the last four of the competition, who will surely provide a sterner test than their English counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, it has become clear that Manchester United’s initial upsurge in form after Ole Gunnar Solskjaer’s appointment in December was only a short term reaction to the mood being lifted around the club. Since the unlikely comeback at the Parc des Princes in the competition’s round of sixteen stage, United have lost 6 of their last 8 matches in all competitions. The two games they did win (2-1 victories vs Watford and West Ham respectively) were unmerited by way of being the lesser side on both occasions. It still remains to be seen whether Solskjaer has the tactical know-how to match the enormity of the task being asked of him, which begs the question: why were United so hasty to appoint him as permanent manager, and why did they offer a three year contract, rather than a one-year rolling contract?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astounding Ajax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in Turin, Juventus were humbled by defeat against Dutch champions Ajax in a game in which the Italian heavyweights were strong favourites. Ajax stunned football fans with their accomplished displays against Real Madrid in the last round, and they continued to silence doubters by producing another set of proficient performances against Juventus. Ajax played Juventus off the park in both legs of the tie and if there is a stat that exemplifies the Dutch team’s dominance it is that Ajax scored three goals over the two legs, while Juventus only managed a measly three shots on target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ajax’s 3-2 aggregate win does not begin to tell the story of just how commanding they were over the Italian champions. However, if there can be any criticism pointed towards Ajax, it is that they are often wasteful in front of goal despite creating numerous chances. This may be partly due to not playing a recognised striker, as their front three is a combination of attacking midfielders and wingers, who are typically more involved in the build-up of goals rather than the finishing of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juventus were wholly uninspiring and lacklustre for a team that was tipped as a potential winner of the competition and Max Allegri’s job has now been called into question as reputable Italian newspapers report that his time at the club could be up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liverpool ease past Porto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porto were thumped 6-1 on aggregate by Liverpool as the Scousers comfortably swept aside the Portuguese champions to go on to the semi-finals. In truth, the scoreline does not truly reflect the nature of the game, in which Liverpool were made to defend for large parts to hang onto their lead. However, the result does reassert Liverpool’s defensive solidity and attacking prowess; the team is exceptional at both ends of the pitch. Liverpool defeated Porto by the same margin last season in the 16 round of the competition on their way to reaching the final and they will hope to do the same this year, although their next opponents will be Barcelona in a mouth-watering tie that promises to captivate audiences across the world as two European heavyweights go head-to-head for a place in this year’s final in Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jurgen Klopp has not yet lost a two-legged European tie during his stint at Liverpool and his side are now faced with a tough task of keeping this record intact against a Barcelona side who have only lost three games in all competitions this season. Luis Suarez and Philippé Coutinho will return to meet their former employers for the first time since leaving Anfield, which will host the second leg of the tie on 7th May at 20:00 BST.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ali Abdi</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UFC 236 Review</title><link href="/UFC-236" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 236 Review" /><published>2019-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/UFC-236</id><content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-236">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last weekend we saw arguably two of the greatest title fights in the history of the UFC. A pair of five round wars to decide the Interim Middleweight and Lightweight champion respectively were the standout highlights of a card many anticipated to be one of the most exciting this year. The Co-Main Event saw rising star and elite striker Israel ‘The Last Stylebender’ Adesanya take on the equally formidable Kelvin Gastelum, with the winner moving on to face Undisputed Middleweight Champion Robert Whittaker later in the year. Gastelum had previously been booked to face Whittaker a few months prior at UFC 234 in Melbourne, however Whittaker was forced to withdraw from the bout due to a hernia that could have proved fatal had the fight taken place. As the fight was pulled from the card, much to the disappointment of fans who were eager to see Whittaker face this latest test after two wars with Yoel Romero, Israel Adesanya and Anderson Silva stepped up to fill the main event slot. Adesanya won the fight by unanimous decision and this was seen by many as a passing of the torch, due to Adesanya’s similar fighting style to that of Silva’s. This victory prompted the creation of the fight between Adesanya and Gastelum which did not disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the main event of UFC 236, current Featherweight Champion Max ‘Blessed’ Holloway challenged himself by moving up a weight class to face Dustin ‘The Diamond’ Poirier for the Interim Lightweight Title, with the winner moving on to face Undisputed Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov after his suspension for his involvement in the post-fight brawl at UFC 229 in September. Holloway came into fight the -210 favourite, however it was Poirier who stepped up to shock the crowd in Atlanta’s State Farm Arena, walking Holloway down for the duration of the fight and landing the lion’s share of the damage inflicting strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the card saw Khalil Rowntree JR. come back from his devastating KO loss to young star Johnny Walker to convincingly beat Eryk Anders at Light Heavyweight, landing 158 significant strikes over the three five-minute rounds, scoring several knockdowns to earn him a unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Welterweight, Alan Jouban took on Dwight Grant, losing a very close split-decision which enraged Jouban, who in his post-fight interview stated his desire to speak to the judges and ask about their background in Martial Arts so as to better understand their reasoning behind what he saw as a clear win for himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening the main card at Light Heavyweight, Nikita Krylov was able to submit Ovince Saint Preux via a Rear Naked Choke in the second round. Krylov lost their first bout at UFC 171 in 2014 to a submission, so was clearly fired up for their second meeting, despite Saint Preux stating his desire to beat Krylov in a similar or worse way than last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prelims&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UFC 236 Prelims were made special by two fights in particular. Germany’s Khalid Taha proved his potential at Bantamweight by steamrolling his way through Hawaii’s Boston Salmon in just 24 seconds, landing ten strikes to Salmon’s zero, before a perfect left hook folded the Honolulu native, finishing the fight with ground and pound strikes to earn a TKO victory and improve his record to 12-2. The other fight that took centre stage in the prelims ended in similar fashion, with Flyweight’s Wilson Reis and Alexandre Pantoja squaring off. Less than three minutes into the fight, Pantoja was able to land a beautifully timed right hand and finished with ruthless ground and pound to earn his TKO victory. The two other fights in the prelims saw Max Griffin end Zelim Imadaev’s unbeaten run at Welterweight by outworking him to a majority decision victory, and at Lightweight Matt Frevola was able to outpoint Jalin Turner to a unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-Main Event&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To many, Kelvin Gastelum would be the first real test for Israel Adesanya. The number 4 ranked fighter is a formidable opponent, with brutal wins over former Middleweight Champion Michael Bisping (KO), Jacare Souza (Decision) and Vitor Belfort (KO). Gastelum’s boxing skills would prove to be a cause of concern for Adesanya, who was visibly rocked by a strong right-hand in the opening round. However, Adesanya, whose power was questioned by many, proved his doubters wrong, dropping Gastelum in the second round with a looping right-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gastelum’s moment came in the fourth, catching Adesanya with an unexpected head kick which sent Israel stumbling back towards the fence. Had Gastelum continued striking at this point, it looked possible for him to finish the fight, with referee Mark Goddard asking for a response from Adesanya. Instead, Gastelum strangely decided to shoot for a double leg takedown, which was shrugged off by Adesanya, who showed phenomenal takedown defence to stand up and continue to punish Gastelum with accurate and powerful strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it was the accuracy of Adesanya which proved to be the difference, dropping Gastelum twice in the fifth and final round with clean punches, almost finishing the bout in the final seconds. After the final bell, the two warriors showed their appreciation of each other’s efforts, embracing as Jon Anik described the fight as ‘one of the best championship fights you will see’, a statement echoed by UFC owner Dana White in the post-fight press conference, with the fight earning the Fight of the Night bonuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The judges each scored the contest 48-46 in favour of New Zealander Adesanya, who now moves on to face Australian Robert Whittaker for a Middleweight Unification bout for the right to be called the Undisputed Middleweight Champion of The World. Here’s to hoping for another classic match-up and another thrilling Adesanya performance. As for Gastelum, he moves down the Middleweight rankings to number 5, with his next fight potentially taking shape in the form of number 2 ranked Yoel Romero, or rising prospect Paulo Costa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Main Event&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event treated fans at The State Farm Arena to another classic title fight for the Interim Lightweight Title. A lot was laid on the line for this bout; Max Holloway was moving up a division to challenge number 3 ranked Lightweight Dustin Poirier, putting at risk his unbelievable 13 fight win streak at Featherweight, which featured milestone victories against the likes of Jose Aldo and Brian Ortega. For Poirier, this was his chance to prove that he was worthy of a title shot against Khabib Nurmagomedov, after two thrilling victories over Eddie Alvarez and fan-favourite Justin Gaethje.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question going into the fight was whether or not Holloway’s power would be transferred due to the difference in weight. Known typically as a volume striker, it became quickly evident that Holloway’s power was not up to the level of Poirier’s, with The Diamond almost finishing the fight within the opening round, landing huge punches, forcing Holloway to cover up. However, being the champion that he is, Holloway refused to back down, pushing back against Poirier’s advances, challenging his opponent to fight harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third and fourth round saw the peak of the fight for Holloway, as he rocked Poirier with fast, accurate volume strikes, pushing Poirier back up against the fence, landing strikes to the body and head respectively. Poirier was visibly rattled by the exchanges but was able to land a vicious knee to the head of Holloway, opening up a nasty cut on the forehead that proceeded to leak blood into Holloway’s eyes. However, this only motivated the Hawaiian, calling for Poirier to stand and bang with him. Poirier rallied in the fifth round, with both men swinging for the fences in the last ten seconds of a truly unbelievable title fight. The fight was scored 49-46 by all three judges in favour of Poirier, who was visibly fired up at the end of the fight, knowing he had finally captured UFC gold. The bout also won Fight of the Night bonuses and ended a truly historic card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next event sees Alistair Overeem take on Aleksei Oleinik in the main event of Fight Night St Petersburg in what promises to be an exciting bout. The next big event we see will take place on May 12th at the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, where the Brazilian takeover features the likes of Jessica Andrade, Anderson Silva and Jose Aldo to name but a few, with ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas putting her Women’s Strawweight Title on the line. 2019 certainly promises to be one of the most thrilling and monumental years in the history of the UFC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>James Eakin</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="mma" /><summary type="html">Event details</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Industrial Corridors in India: A New Vehicle for Industrialisation</title><link href="/Industrial-Corridors-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Industrial Corridors in India: A New Vehicle for Industrialisation" /><published>2019-04-19T23:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-19T23:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Industrial-Corridors-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Industrial-Corridors-India">&lt;p&gt;According to a Briefing Paper prepared for the UK’s House of Commons, China’s
share as a percentage of world manufacturing is 20% and as a percentage of its
GDP, it is 27%. In contrast, for India, the corresponding figures stand dismally
at 4% and 16% respectively. The Report has taken manufacturing output in 2015 as
the basis, using 2005 exchange rates. The burgeoning services sector
contribution to India’s GDP during the last decade has gone past 60%, whereas
the contribution of manufacturing activity to GDP has remained virtually
stagnant. This clearly indicates that India has been quick to adopt
technological advances in the services sector, but has failed to encourage
manufacturing entrepreneurship. Over the years, a clear need has been felt to
boost manufacturing activity in India. Mass consumerization of Indian society
due to rising disposable income and increased rural electrification have led to
a rise in demand for electronic consumer goods. It is expected to reach ₹3.15
trillion in the year 2022. If quality domestic products are not available,
people will buy imported goods. All this has further added to the necessity of
manufacturing led industrialisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to boost domestic manufacturing, the Indian Government tried to emulate
the Chinese experience as China had immensely benefited from its SEZ (Special
Economic Zones) policy. On similar lines, India enacted the SEZ Act in 2005.
However, Indian SEZs lacked the all-important connectivity to ports and thus,
failed to augment manufacturing activity in the country. It is this realisation
that has resulted in the introduction of the concept of industrial corridors
that is modelled on similar corridors in Japan and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is an Industrial Corridor?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An industrial corridor or economic corridor is a pathway comprising
manufacturing clusters, ancillary units and smart cities connected with rail,
road, air or sea links. The Indian government has envisaged five integrated
industrial corridors across the country in partnership with the respective State
governments. The National Industrial Corridor Development &amp;amp; Implementation Trust
(NICDIT) has been established as the apex body to oversee development of all
industrial corridors across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Industrial_Corridors.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industrial Corridor as Wheels of Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial corridors recognise the interdependence of various sectors of the
economy and offer effective integration between industry and infrastructure
leading to overall socio-economic development. Industrial corridors lead to the
creation of state-of-art infrastructure such as high-speed transportation
(rail/road) networks, ports with advanced cargo handling equipment, modern
airports, special economic regions/ industrial areas, logistic parks, etc. that
are focused on fulfilling the requirements of the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late C.K. Prahalad, a renowned management expert, had said that over the
next three decades if India does not create new cities to accommodate a whopping
500 million people desirous of urban life, every existing city would become a
slum. The establishment of manufacturing zones along the industrial corridors
will prevent distress migration and provide people with job opportunities close
to their dwelling place. The new smart cities created will mark the beginning of
a new wave of urbanisation in India and reduce pressure on existing cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buzz word connecting the various programmes PM of Modi’s Government - Make
in India, Digital India, and Skill India - is employment generation. Smart
cities and industrial corridors are no exceptions. The educational institutions,
roads, railways, airports, hospitals that will come up in these corridors is
expected to generate employment and raise the overall standard of living. The
government is targeting 100 million new jobs through industrial corridors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘The wheels of progress’ are encountering a plethora of issues on their road to
success, however. Of all the issues, acquisition of land at a snail’s pace is
the single biggest concern owing to the Right to Fair Compensation and
Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013. To
take an example, the $100-billion Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) was
expected to be completed in three phases spread over nine years starting from
January 2008. However, owing to mostly land acquisition issues, the first phase
is likely to be completed by December 2019 and revised deadlines for the second
phase and third phase have already been shifted to 2027 and 2037. The
governments at both India’s Central and State levels need to work out a
comprehensive land acquisition policy and not approach this issue in a piecemeal
manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, as India lacks technological expertise, it is prudent to bring in
foreign direct investment through established foreign entities that have the
required skill. At the same time, it is also important to encourage Indian
investment in setting up ancillary units in the same sector. This will provide
for smooth backward integration by ensuring regular supply of raw materials and
forward integration by providing ready markets. For example, the Chennai to
Bengaluru defence production corridor in India’s southern States will pass
through towns such as Trichy, Coimbatore, Salem and Hosur and will connect
ordnance factories and defence public sector units to ancillary units (which are
small and medium scale industries in the said corridor). The supplies from these
units to factories and Public Sector Undertakings is an example of forward
integration and purchases by the latter is backward integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, in order to encourage FDI, the government needs to rationalise the tax
structure. India’s corporate tax rate is high in comparison to many ASEAN
countries and stands at 30%. It is 20% in Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam.
Moreover, India also has very high import tariffs that make manufacturing of
products with imported components economically unviable or expensive as compared
to countries like Taiwan. To achieve success, the government should rationalise
the tariff structure, realising that it is export promotion not import
prevention that actually benefits an economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy of industrial corridors is poised to develop a sound industrial
base, characterised by excellent infrastructure and uninhibited growth of
manufacturing. However, all this would remain only rhetoric if stumbling blocks
are not removed and issues plaguing industrial corridor projects are not
resolved. This requires a holistic approach and involvement of all the
government departments, stakeholders such as farmers from whom land is to be
acquired, manufacturers who would be setting units for production, transport
operators, etc. With the onset of election season in India, it would be naive to
assume anyone has the time to truly calibrate policy, but with a new Government
and new ambitions post elections, one can only hope that the Industrial
Corridors project will take on new heights.  &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manya Manushi</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">According to a Briefing Paper prepared for the UK’s House of Commons, China’s share as a percentage of world manufacturing is 20% and as a percentage of its GDP, it is 27%. In contrast, for India, the corresponding figures stand dismally at 4% and 16% respectively. The Report has taken manufacturing output in 2015 as the basis, using 2005 exchange rates. The burgeoning services sector contribution to India’s GDP during the last decade has gone past 60%, whereas the contribution of manufacturing activity to GDP has remained virtually stagnant. This clearly indicates that India has been quick to adopt technological advances in the services sector, but has failed to encourage manufacturing entrepreneurship. Over the years, a clear need has been felt to boost manufacturing activity in India. Mass consumerization of Indian society due to rising disposable income and increased rural electrification have led to a rise in demand for electronic consumer goods. It is expected to reach ₹3.15 trillion in the year 2022. If quality domestic products are not available, people will buy imported goods. All this has further added to the necessity of manufacturing led industrialisation. In order to boost domestic manufacturing, the Indian Government tried to emulate the Chinese experience as China had immensely benefited from its SEZ (Special Economic Zones) policy. On similar lines, India enacted the SEZ Act in 2005. However, Indian SEZs lacked the all-important connectivity to ports and thus, failed to augment manufacturing activity in the country. It is this realisation that has resulted in the introduction of the concept of industrial corridors that is modelled on similar corridors in Japan and China. What is an Industrial Corridor? An industrial corridor or economic corridor is a pathway comprising manufacturing clusters, ancillary units and smart cities connected with rail, road, air or sea links. The Indian government has envisaged five integrated industrial corridors across the country in partnership with the respective State governments. The National Industrial Corridor Development &amp;amp; Implementation Trust (NICDIT) has been established as the apex body to oversee development of all industrial corridors across the country. Source: http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC Industrial Corridor as Wheels of Progress Industrial corridors recognise the interdependence of various sectors of the economy and offer effective integration between industry and infrastructure leading to overall socio-economic development. Industrial corridors lead to the creation of state-of-art infrastructure such as high-speed transportation (rail/road) networks, ports with advanced cargo handling equipment, modern airports, special economic regions/ industrial areas, logistic parks, etc. that are focused on fulfilling the requirements of the industry. The late C.K. Prahalad, a renowned management expert, had said that over the next three decades if India does not create new cities to accommodate a whopping 500 million people desirous of urban life, every existing city would become a slum. The establishment of manufacturing zones along the industrial corridors will prevent distress migration and provide people with job opportunities close to their dwelling place. The new smart cities created will mark the beginning of a new wave of urbanisation in India and reduce pressure on existing cities. The buzz word connecting the various programmes PM of Modi’s Government - Make in India, Digital India, and Skill India - is employment generation. Smart cities and industrial corridors are no exceptions. The educational institutions, roads, railways, airports, hospitals that will come up in these corridors is expected to generate employment and raise the overall standard of living. The government is targeting 100 million new jobs through industrial corridors.   The Way Forward ‘The wheels of progress’ are encountering a plethora of issues on their road to success, however. Of all the issues, acquisition of land at a snail’s pace is the single biggest concern owing to the Right to Fair Compensation and Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013. To take an example, the $100-billion Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) was expected to be completed in three phases spread over nine years starting from January 2008. However, owing to mostly land acquisition issues, the first phase is likely to be completed by December 2019 and revised deadlines for the second phase and third phase have already been shifted to 2027 and 2037. The governments at both India’s Central and State levels need to work out a comprehensive land acquisition policy and not approach this issue in a piecemeal manner. Secondly, as India lacks technological expertise, it is prudent to bring in foreign direct investment through established foreign entities that have the required skill. At the same time, it is also important to encourage Indian investment in setting up ancillary units in the same sector. This will provide for smooth backward integration by ensuring regular supply of raw materials and forward integration by providing ready markets. For example, the Chennai to Bengaluru defence production corridor in India’s southern States will pass through towns such as Trichy, Coimbatore, Salem and Hosur and will connect ordnance factories and defence public sector units to ancillary units (which are small and medium scale industries in the said corridor). The supplies from these units to factories and Public Sector Undertakings is an example of forward integration and purchases by the latter is backward integration. Thirdly, in order to encourage FDI, the government needs to rationalise the tax structure. India’s corporate tax rate is high in comparison to many ASEAN countries and stands at 30%. It is 20% in Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam. Moreover, India also has very high import tariffs that make manufacturing of products with imported components economically unviable or expensive as compared to countries like Taiwan. To achieve success, the government should rationalise the tariff structure, realising that it is export promotion not import prevention that actually benefits an economy. The strategy of industrial corridors is poised to develop a sound industrial base, characterised by excellent infrastructure and uninhibited growth of manufacturing. However, all this would remain only rhetoric if stumbling blocks are not removed and issues plaguing industrial corridor projects are not resolved. This requires a holistic approach and involvement of all the government departments, stakeholders such as farmers from whom land is to be acquired, manufacturers who would be setting units for production, transport operators, etc. With the onset of election season in India, it would be naive to assume anyone has the time to truly calibrate policy, but with a new Government and new ambitions post elections, one can only hope that the Industrial Corridors project will take on new heights.  </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Haven’t We Left Yet?</title><link href="/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Haven’t We Left Yet?" /><published>2019-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet">&lt;p&gt;How did it end up like this? It was only a dream. An independent Britain; free to strike its own trade deals with the world; free of the tyranny of the European Union’s tyrannical Commission. This was the dream behind Brexit. Only it hasn’t worked out that way. Today, Great Britain is trapped in a quagmire, from which its ancient and prestigious Parliament can’t find an escape. The pitiful Prime Minister Theresa May finds herself leading a government but without much power, after the failure of her Withdrawal Agreement, and the three votes vainly trying to pass it. If Theresa can take any solace, it will be in the fact that following Commons’ MP Oliver Letwin’s backbench coup, a solution to the Brexit mess still can’t be found. All the while, the British people wonder how did a great nation find itself in such a mess that it has had to beg the European Union for the second time for an extension of the Article 50 exit process. The European Union have been magnanimous in response to Britain’s self-humiliation, granting it another six months to figure out what type of Brexit it actually wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is worth remembering that the crisis Britain now faces shouldn’t have even been possible under the old Constitution. Britain’s tradition of Parliamentary Sovereignty is an anathema to referendums. Margaret Thatcher once called them “the tools of dictators and tyrants”. It all began in 1975, when the then Prime Minister Harold Wilson gave the British people a referendum on being a part of the European Economic Community (as the EU then was). Wilson won his referendum in favour of membership of the European Community by over 30%, a majority large enough to end the issue for a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, by introducing the practice of referendums to British politics, he had forever changed the unwritten Constitution of the sceptered Isle, in ways nobody could possibly foresee. The second strike, the anti-European strike, against Britain’s ancient Constitution would be self-inflicted. Back in 1999, the European Commission decreed that henceforth, all elections to the European Parliament would use ‘proportional representation’, a practise Britain’s dominant political parties had resisted. This had radical repercussions which neither the British establishment nor the European elite could expect. By introducing proportional representation to British politics, the European Commission broke the stranglehold that the two great parties had held on British politics since 1945. In 2009, Nigel Farage led the United Kingdom Independence Party (UKIP) to second place in the European Parliament elections. Then in 2014, UKIP came first in the European Parliament elections. For the first time, a party other than the Conservative or Labour Party had won a national poll since 1945.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delicate balance of Britain’s Constitution had been disturbed, leading David Cameron to promise that if he won the 2015 general elections, then he would hold a referendum on the membership of the European Union. Cameron lost, Britain voted to leave European Union and become independent of … something, which isn’t so clear. Today, the Parliament is broken into four factions neither of which is interested in compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most extreme faction is the &lt;em&gt;Hard Brexiteers&lt;/em&gt; who can’t accept anything but a complete Brexit. Where Britain would be completely separated from the European Union’s regulatory framework, and then trade with the EU, under the terms of the World Trade Organisation. They consider this as restoring Britain’s rightful place as a free buccaneering nation, arguing any short term pain would be more than worthwhile. This would involve a rough and hard separation from the EU’s single market—an idea Most British companies find terrifying. This option is prefered by a core group of less than fifty Brexit-extremist Members of Parliament led by Boris Johnson and Jacob Rees-Mogg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theresa May’s preferred option is unsurprisingly her &lt;em&gt;Withdrawal Agreement&lt;/em&gt; which manages the difficult task of both upsetting the &lt;em&gt;remainers and leavers&lt;/em&gt;, coming short on both their desires. Nevertheless, it is still supported by a majority of the Conservative Party, which struggles with those rebelling against their Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third faction, within the House of Commons, support the &lt;em&gt;Soft Brexit&lt;/em&gt;, which would involve Britain remaining in the European Union’s Customs Union and regulatory framework. This group includes most of the Labour party and many Conservative party rebels. However, it’s ambition of a soft Brexit is undermined by the House of Commons fourth group: the &lt;em&gt;anti-Brexiteers&lt;/em&gt;. This final group lead by Nicola Sturgeon (of the Scottish National Party) desires the complete revocation of the referendum, and the end of Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, there lies the problem of the four groups who can’t compromise with one another. And if they don’t, then a Parliamentary majority for any response to Brexit won’t be found. In the last two weeks, Theresa May has seemed to motion towards a compromise with the Labour Party’s position of a Customs Union between Britain and the EU. But any compromise with Jeremy Corbyn’s Labour Party faces stiff opposition from the Conservative backbenchers and grassroots. May and Corbyn are both incentivised to not walk away from the compromise talks to show the electorate that they are trying to find a solution. But they also can’t actually agree to one without alienating both their party’s grassroots. Hard Brexiteers thought that these stablemates would result in Britain crashing out of the EU without a deal on March 29, the original Brexit deadline. However, the European political elite has showed themselves to be just as worried about a no-deal, as the British establishment. Hence, their decision to give Britain another six-month extension, without any requirements from the British, wasn’t surprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Parliament can’t finally agree to a solution to Brexit, the only solution will be to dissolve it and elect again. However, following May’s previous disastrous election performance, when the Conservatives lost their majority to the Conservative backbenchers in marginal seats, it will be unlikely for her to call another one. Therefore, until May can be replaced as the Tory leader, another election seems off the table. This would be difficult, given that May has promised to resign the Conservative Party leadership only after her Withdrawal Agreement is passed in the Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the British Parliament is split between four opposing factions with different responses to Brexit. No one can command a majority in the current Parliament, whether it’s a &lt;em&gt;Hard, Soft or No Brexit&lt;/em&gt;. Theresa May once promised that Britain would leave on the 29th of March, that date is now three weeks past, and no end to the Brexit is in sight. Britain now faces another a six months of uncertainty as the Parliament squabbles over what to do. The current Brexit chaos is reminiscent of an old joke: a traveler asked a man how to find the local tavern, the man replied “Well, I wouldn’t start from here”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reuben Pritchard</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">How did it end up like this? It was only a dream. An independent Britain; free to strike its own trade deals with the world; free of the tyranny of the European Union’s tyrannical Commission. This was the dream behind Brexit. Only it hasn’t worked out that way. Today, Great Britain is trapped in a quagmire, from which its ancient and prestigious Parliament can’t find an escape. The pitiful Prime Minister Theresa May finds herself leading a government but without much power, after the failure of her Withdrawal Agreement, and the three votes vainly trying to pass it. If Theresa can take any solace, it will be in the fact that following Commons’ MP Oliver Letwin’s backbench coup, a solution to the Brexit mess still can’t be found. All the while, the British people wonder how did a great nation find itself in such a mess that it has had to beg the European Union for the second time for an extension of the Article 50 exit process. The European Union have been magnanimous in response to Britain’s self-humiliation, granting it another six months to figure out what type of Brexit it actually wants.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It Happens Only In India!</title><link href="/Only-In-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It Happens Only In India!" /><published>2019-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Only-In-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Only-In-India">&lt;p&gt;First-time Indian voters like me, along with other eligible ones, are keenly looking forward to flaunting the blue mark on their index finger. Seven-phased, four weeks long, this is the ‘Festival of the country’ (&lt;em&gt;Desh ka tyohaar&lt;/em&gt;, in Hindi) to choose the seventeenth Indian Lok Sabha. It is aptly called so because it witnesses unparalleled participation and everything in relation to it. About 900 million eligible voters will vote at a million polling stations in 543 constituencies across India. There are likely to be fifteen candidates, on an average, in each constituency. About 450 political parties are in the fray. This event has more people participating in it as compared to the combined population of Europe and Australia. Almost 3.96 million robust and tamper-proof Electronic Voting Machines (EVMs) accompanied by VVPAT (voter-verified paper audit trail) have been deployed. Estimated expenditure on these elections stands at $7 billion, which is 3.2 times the cost involved in conducting the US Presidential elections of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections 2019 is likely to be a close one and is a keen contest between two alliances - the ruling National Democratic Alliance (NDA) and the present opposition, United Progressive Alliance (UPA). The respective important constituents of these alliances are - the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) and the Indian National Congress (INC). This election reminds me of the famous  Abba  song – &lt;em&gt;Take a chance on me&lt;/em&gt;. Narendra Modi, the incumbent Prime Minister, and Rahul Gandhi, the most important leader of the Congress, have widely travelled across the length and breadth of the country in the past two months to woo voters. Both have liberally referred to armed forces in their speeches to derive some kind of political advantage. The five-year vision document of both the parties – the election manifesto - talks about the pro-farmer approach. While the Congress has promised to approach the issue of rural distress through a separate budget for farmers, the BJP has vowed to provide pensions for small and marginal farmers after the age of 60 and to double the income of farmers by 2022. Both parties have announced their cash transfer and income support schemes for people living in extreme poverty. Employment, security, and infrastructure feature prominently in the manifestos of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many contentious issues have no reference in Congress’ vision document while BJP is emphatic about these. Firstly, it has promised to build the Ram temple in Ayodhya (an important Hindu God believed to have been born there), whose construction Muslims have been opposing because of the existence of the Babri mosque at the same location. Its hardline approach on the abrogation of Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution is also evident in the document. These two articles give special status and privileges to the state and to the people of Jammu and Kashmir. The proposal to have a National Registry of Citizens (NRC) to check foreign nationals or illegal immigrants in India’s North-East, particularly in the State of Assam is also included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is closure possible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections to the Indian legislature highlights some important electoral policy issues that require, if not closure, then a serious attempt to address them. The first being the issue of simultaneous election to the Indian Parliament and the State Legislatures, second, the funding of elections, and third, the role of the media, including social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first four elections in India from 1952 through 1967 were conducted simultaneously. This concept ended when the fourth Lok Sabha was dissolved before the end of its term. The Law Commission wanted to reinstate this system as they felt that there is no proper governance across the country and the nation is continuously in the election mode, which leads to ministerial work suffering. Simultaneous elections will ensure that the ruling parties at the State and the Centre level will get sufficient time to execute the policies that they had talked about in their respective manifestos. This also will help in reducing the cost of elections. Though BJP has proposed it again, it seems to be too difficult a plan to be implemented, especially in light of the severe resistance it faces from the opposition parties. The stiff resistance is because it will involve cutting down or increasing the tenure of some present State Legislatures and a Constitutional Amendment as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, despite the Election Commission’s commitment to the idea of State funding of elections and recommendations for the same by various committees, not much progress has been made in this direction. In 2017, probably one of its kind in the world, Electoral Bonds were envisaged as an interest-free instrument to raise funding in a transparent manner. A corporate or an individual can purchase these promissory notes from an authorised bank and the identity of the donor will be known only to the bank. The anonymity clause attracted criticism and it was contended that it would lead to shell companies making donations. The very purpose of transparent funding would be defeated. Taking cognisance of this, on a petition, the Indian Supreme Court has asked all political parties to furnish receipts of electoral bonds along with the identity and bank account details of the donors and the amounts received to the Election Commission by May 30. The Electoral Bonds, in their present form, are otherwise playing a limited role. Experts estimate that all the political parties put together have raised only around $300 million through these bonds, which, is of course, far less than what they seem to be spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the electoral history of India, the media, especially electronic, has never spelled out its political affiliation as clearly as in this election. Instead of taking an independent stand, the views expressed by television channels are a reflection of their owner’s political ideology. Social media is being used by different parties for propaganda as well as to spread misinformation. Prominent social media companies, including Facebook along with its app services - Instagram and WhatsApp, have adopted a voluntary code of ethics for the general elections with the Election Commission of India (ECI). According to Facebook sources, it is removing around one million abusive accounts every day using Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voting the Indian way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the syncretic nature of Indian society, the massive scale of elections and many related issues remaining unresolved, the process and its resilience is quite impressive. It is quite interesting to note that a Pew Research poll on democracy, conducted last year, showed that 79% of the Indians are satisfied with democracy as a whole. Americans, whose country takes pride in being the cradle of democracy, have a satisfaction rate of only 46%. India’s free and fair elections for the last seventy years or so is no mean achievement for a country whose democratic institutions were far from being developed at the time of its independence. And, of course, there is no doubt in the matter that every Indian regards his/her freedom dearly. Probably, two hundred years of oppression have been proof enough that the freedom and democratic institution is of utmost importance. A nation, with vast diversity and chronic inequality, this is the time of the year when rich and poor come together to make a choice for their collective future. This is the time to voice out their desires and problems. Every Indian certainly takes pride in it. It is for young Indians to ensure that politicians do not disturb the democratic fibre of the country. It is for them to carry forward the greatness behind the legacy that was slowly built over the years, and that they too take pride in flaunting the blue mark on their finger. The blue mark is more than just a sign of vote, it is a symbol of the reminder that now they are free to choose their leader, and that the people run the country and elect the government. Their dissent towards the leaders comes as a vote against their party. So, they better serve in people’s favour.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manya Manushi</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">First-time Indian voters like me, along with other eligible ones, are keenly looking forward to flaunting the blue mark on their index finger. Seven-phased, four weeks long, this is the ‘Festival of the country’ (Desh ka tyohaar, in Hindi) to choose the seventeenth Indian Lok Sabha. It is aptly called so because it witnesses unparalleled participation and everything in relation to it. About 900 million eligible voters will vote at a million polling stations in 543 constituencies across India. There are likely to be fifteen candidates, on an average, in each constituency. About 450 political parties are in the fray. This event has more people participating in it as compared to the combined population of Europe and Australia. Almost 3.96 million robust and tamper-proof Electronic Voting Machines (EVMs) accompanied by VVPAT (voter-verified paper audit trail) have been deployed. Estimated expenditure on these elections stands at $7 billion, which is 3.2 times the cost involved in conducting the US Presidential elections of 2016.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Circle of Fire: A Lament and Lesson for Europe</title><link href="/Circle-of-Fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Circle of Fire: A Lament and Lesson for Europe" /><published>2019-04-11T04:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-11T04:29:00+00:00</updated><id>/Circle-of-Fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Circle-of-Fire">&lt;p&gt;1818, in a dusty, dawn-cast attic of a stately home, a statue begins to turn
from the grey of shaped limestone to the radiant gold of marble. It is a copy of
a very old Roman copy, of a Greek sculpture: “The Dying Gaul”, as commissioned
by Attalus I of Pergamon while celebrating his victory over the Celts of Turkey
in the 3rd Century BCE. In the dusty room, at daybreak, an amber light shines on
the torque tightly clasping the statue’s neck, a circle somehow proud, yet
broken, beneath his downcast brow. The “Dying Gaul” is depicted as so dismal, so
dejected a thing that many observe an inherent sadness in him. Admiring the
skill of the artist, even Lord Byron himself writes about the pathos engendered
by the scene. However, he dubs him &lt;em&gt;The Dying Gladiator&lt;/em&gt;, and so even as an art
piece, this lost, false picture of a man is, like his race, truly forgotten.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many miles away, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan, a Sikh wears a “Chakram” as he
prepares for a wedding ceremony. These metal rings recalling the mythological
weapon of the Hindu god Krishna, the disc-bearer. Despite having lost their
practical functionality after the British arrived, “chakrams” retain their
symbolic importance. Even in a Punjabi wedding, Indo-European Vedic traditions
remain, as a bride to be wedded has her feet painted in Mehndi by a woman older
than herself and already happily married.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So telling, how these traits of myth may endure, even through the ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of mythology, of all “divine poetry”, is to act as superlative verse to
the layman’s consideration of the passing day, to act as sacred words which fill
colour into the profane of our world. In fact, we might see our culture itself
as a sort of divine consort, as a partner to our existence, and determine that
an individual divested of culture is lonely. Our cultural identity is,
therefore, our spouse and it is given to us by our heritage. Ultimately, the
only thing which separates one group of people from another is the place they
are situated in, and religious beliefs are formed dependent on the surroundings
of said people. You would only pray for the sorts of things your lands made
plentiful or precious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, what follows is this: all mythology encompasses the relationship of a
people with their geological environment. This makes all religion, all cultural
heritage an ontological understanding of one’s surroundings. We process the
existence we know. That is the truly pagan way of being in oneself, that is the
truly human way. Nature will teach you; it will teach you everything. Nature has
many faces, but one voice and we must remember that Mother Nature has no
obligation to be fair to you. Neither do natural forces. But you can try to
understand them. Even, dare I say, try to communicate with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All religion serves to reconcile the distance between the earthly and the
heavenly, and it seems one patch of Earth, lived upon by one people in
opposition to another, becomes a different Earth. And the force which marries us
to our geographically-defined culture, religion, etc., is the same which would
bind one person to another. Once, what was called Sati in one place was observed
in different forms in others. Accounts from Ibn Fadlan and the verses from the
&lt;em&gt;Sigurðarkviða hin skamma&lt;/em&gt; assert that Norse people would offer up a wealthy
Chieftain’s &lt;em&gt;thralls&lt;/em&gt; or slaves, to his funeral pyre after his passing, and
Julius Caesar says the same of the Celts in &lt;em&gt;De Bello Gallico&lt;/em&gt;. This Roman
account is the origin of the ‘Wicker Man’ stereotype, where beloved ‘dependants’
of the deceased are given up along with other offerings to be purified into
something others would call &lt;em&gt;Agni&lt;/em&gt;, the sacred fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be more virtuous to plaster all discourse pertaining to such things
with comments on the barbarous vestiges of a less appropriately enlightened
past, but it might be more useful still to understand why people would do such
things. And so go from “ignorance to truth, darkness to light, and death to
immortality,” as per that enigmatic mantra echoed in Hindu Yagna rituals, it
would seem. If truth could be light. If that light could be immortality, it
would take the shape of a fire fed by and specified by one’s very beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how our belief ties us to our people, to our lands. We live and die by
them. We do not simply have our culture follow us into the fire. We go because
of it. And whether that is ethically speaking without blemish or not, it is
certainly powerful. We do things which seem illogical, which other animals do
not do. A culture is a truth, it is an understanding of the world. In such a
way, it considers rules and identifies what is to be prized in this
understanding of the world, and what is to be deemed more unsightly. And this is
the nature of our identities, as humans, as ethnicities. This is how we are
married to our cultures, not in bondage, but in heritage, as per a hypernatural,
proto-legal contract. This is us. &lt;em&gt;Alive&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Europe is becoming even less alive itself, because it is becoming less
Christian, which in and of itself would not necessitate unfortunate
circumstances, if only it did not entail the rise of Atheism. As a consequence,
Europe becomes ‘more lonely’. It manages the extraordinary feat of being somehow
formed of so many countries which remain so impossibly isolated from each other.
Yet, indeed, it is natural that this continent should have no faith, and no
faith in itself, for such things were bored out of it by the Romans and
Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my customary finding that things usually succeed in doing what they were
designed to do, and Christianity was designed to make the European people
complacent and easy to control. No wonder that as it falls, as the Church
awakens to every nightmare about paedophilia accusations in this hypocritical
bed it has made for itself, Europeans are not only impossible to control, but
they are directionless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity is more impactful from a cultural perspective than a spiritual one;
it served as a device of enforcing the Roman rule and extending the duration of
their Empire, supplanting an enduring (arguably militant) presence in their
lands as an oppressive crushing of culture on a local scale, imposing a single
identity-defining dogma. It was applied to control, and now the people are
uncontrollable, and inconsolably unruly since the Roman rule has decayed. Yet,
it is the state of the dominated to retain their chains after their master has
met their demise. It is surprising Europe has taken so long to throw off the
very yoke of Christendom in the first place. Albeit, Christianity had been
unknowingly preserving truly European, pagan culture. And, as it falls, so does
its inherited identity. Atheism has come and it brings with it a cold, stark
divestment of the European spirit from the European body. This makes every man
and woman less than human, for all different world cultures, all at least have a
notion of the spirit, and a cornered animal lashes out because it is afraid,
outnumbered, perhaps. &lt;em&gt;Alone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a time of division. Even as we speak, conversations are cracking open
about the consequences of Brexit in regards to Ireland’s relationship with
Northern Ireland, and while a united Éire may seem like a step forward, it also
indicates the breaking down of a much older order. One thing upon which we all
can agree is that changes are afoot. For better or for worse, it seems this
great and old continent will never be the same again. The end of individual
difference, so surely the end of our differences altogether, no? Ultimate unity
through ultimate, violent equity. Of course, it is rather beneficial for Church
and State alike to have its people be without identity; they are so much easier
to pra(e)y upon! And so, behold the touted saviour: &lt;em&gt;Socialism&lt;/em&gt;. It is at the
heart of globalisation, but socialism was purely and only an advent of chaos, a
machine designed to destroy. Karl Marx did not want to help the working classes,
but he did want to make them kill people, often each other.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marx believed a great change was on the horizon, but the problem with his ideas
was that he believed the change could only and must be reached via great
conflict. He believed society was on the verge of collapse, he never incited
peaceful resolution or the empowerment of workers and always sought only to arm
them rather than communicate with them. When he visited the German Workers’
Education Society of London in 1845, he found self-educated, self-made men. They
were anti-liberal, anti-bohemian and practically-minded, and he saw them as
lowly for not sharing his apocalyptic ambitions for the future. They engaged in
practical discussion, though without academic training in philosophy (which is
why he disliked working men and thought them beneath himself). This was not what
he wanted. He wanted revolution and chaos, for as he stated: “Socialism cannot
be brought into existence without revolution”. When his father died in 1838, he
spent much of his inheritance of 6000 ₣ on arming Belgian workers with guns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, the violent revolutions of the country I grew up in, France, have a
long history indeed of upheaving everything and distracting from the country’s
problems until they go away, but they ultimately benefited slightly wealthier
men seizing power, only to be deposed by men slightly less wealthy than
themselves. Every time, it is the slightly less hard-working man who gains
leadership at the expense of the slightly harder working man. The same can be
seen in the French-backed American Revolution, a systematic upheaval which
allowed wealthy English landowners in the New World to detach themselves from
their colonial control of ‘The British’ under the new identity of ‘The
American’, and they profited and suffered immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, marrying oneself to a new culture, a new identity, will dictate one’s
destiny. And so come into focus the fires of modern-day Paris, lit by the Gilets
Jaunes. Fire once more presides the times of chaos, the times of change. So how,
I ask, can this, revolution, be the answer? I cannot agree that Marx was right
in the larger sense that it is necessary, but I must wonder as to his related
belief that it is inevitable. Visions of fire, revolution and chaos, and one
must think of the Wheel of Fire, a Greek mythological image originating in the
punishment of Ixion after his lusting for Zeus’s divine consort, Hera. It
signifies a torturous chain of events leading to dire consequences, in result of
personal actions or flaws which are ultimately the victim’s fault. It provides a
caveat to be considered, in matters of want and misplaced ambition. It is the
fall from grace, and it is engendered by the foreboding betrayal of a sacred
matrimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I attend a concert by the folk-rock band Faun, at the end, a skaldic
lutist/mandolin player speaks as a grandiose orator, transforming from the
humble, weaselly man he has been every other time we hear him speak into
something approaching the divine musician we have seen play, as when he
performs, as when he sings. His band’s spectacle reaches an emotive pinnacle as
he speaks, almost preaching now, but with such zeal the likes of which a
hurricane could not bring any modern Christian priest to muster, with the
passion not seen since they were not merely excused by the burning of our wise
women but corralled it. The kind of power not seen unless truth and conviction
bolster the rightful in their unextinguished focus; he says we must remember who
we are. Remember nature. Our own nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he speaks in his complete form, finally, but only once, is mentioned the
creature who is the namesake of the band, the faun, the Pan figure, who just
like Krishna plays the flute and sits surrounded by the animals, a Master of
Beasts. And then he says how it was known by another name to the Celts, as
Cernunnos. Thus begins the cycle. A vision of a devil. A vision of nature,
personified. A herald of flame to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I contemplate this apple of my eye which I see on the horizon. Knowledge
of paganism is the knowledge of how to live and connect with our environment of
Europe, and so I say that, for the West, to transcend Christendom via the
produce of the trees of knowledge is the only way that we will be able to live
in this garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The serpent penetrates the apple. Perhaps, it is to be seized, like the
Snake-Witch Stone shows, perhaps it is to be defeated like the biblical
Leviathan. But it is no primitive return to nature which will save us now, but a
mature and learned taking into oneself the ways of yore. We must make of
ourselves ergonomic beings. A form of cultural bio-mimicry will be observed in
ancient lore, and this will tell us how to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, there are philosophies and facts to be observed in the natural
world, echoed in mythology, which can inform us on how to live our lives, so we
can be healthier, but also on how we should think, so we can be &lt;em&gt;holier&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I think on this vision, I must wonder what ‘true spiritual sun’ will be
unveiled to us, ‘hidden by a disc of golden light’. What truth will be known,
what duty done? What sacred feet, anointed now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking to the future, for Europe, for the world? &lt;em&gt;Fire&lt;/em&gt;. But will it be a wheel
or a dawn? This will depend on the nature, the aspect and, I fear, upon the
reception of this, the &lt;em&gt;Truth&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tales of myth and history weave in and out of each other, they remind us
of our inherent shared heritage defined not as humans, but as people. For, in
commiseration with history, mythology serves not only to grant us stories from
the past where we may learn how to rise, but also stories of the soul, that we
may learn not to fall. And what these similarities do tell us is that Europe
should be united under common ground, regardless of any Union - so long as it
remains European. As such, it is time Europe decided to whom it would be married
and what is to be the philosophical companion to its destiny, what identity will
accompany it towards an uncertain future. Some would say we look outside, or
without. I merely say we look within.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Morgan Black</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">1818, in a dusty, dawn-cast attic of a stately home, a statue begins to turn from the grey of shaped limestone to the radiant gold of marble. It is a copy of a very old Roman copy, of a Greek sculpture: “The Dying Gaul”, as commissioned by Attalus I of Pergamon while celebrating his victory over the Celts of Turkey in the 3rd Century BCE. In the dusty room, at daybreak, an amber light shines on the torque tightly clasping the statue’s neck, a circle somehow proud, yet broken, beneath his downcast brow. The “Dying Gaul” is depicted as so dismal, so dejected a thing that many observe an inherent sadness in him. Admiring the skill of the artist, even Lord Byron himself writes about the pathos engendered by the scene. However, he dubs him The Dying Gladiator, and so even as an art piece, this lost, false picture of a man is, like his race, truly forgotten.   Many miles away, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan, a Sikh wears a “Chakram” as he prepares for a wedding ceremony. These metal rings recalling the mythological weapon of the Hindu god Krishna, the disc-bearer. Despite having lost their practical functionality after the British arrived, “chakrams” retain their symbolic importance. Even in a Punjabi wedding, Indo-European Vedic traditions remain, as a bride to be wedded has her feet painted in Mehndi by a woman older than herself and already happily married. So telling, how these traits of myth may endure, even through the ages. The role of mythology, of all “divine poetry”, is to act as superlative verse to the layman’s consideration of the passing day, to act as sacred words which fill colour into the profane of our world. In fact, we might see our culture itself as a sort of divine consort, as a partner to our existence, and determine that an individual divested of culture is lonely. Our cultural identity is, therefore, our spouse and it is given to us by our heritage. Ultimately, the only thing which separates one group of people from another is the place they are situated in, and religious beliefs are formed dependent on the surroundings of said people. You would only pray for the sorts of things your lands made plentiful or precious. Therefore, what follows is this: all mythology encompasses the relationship of a people with their geological environment. This makes all religion, all cultural heritage an ontological understanding of one’s surroundings. We process the existence we know. That is the truly pagan way of being in oneself, that is the truly human way. Nature will teach you; it will teach you everything. Nature has many faces, but one voice and we must remember that Mother Nature has no obligation to be fair to you. Neither do natural forces. But you can try to understand them. Even, dare I say, try to communicate with them. All religion serves to reconcile the distance between the earthly and the heavenly, and it seems one patch of Earth, lived upon by one people in opposition to another, becomes a different Earth. And the force which marries us to our geographically-defined culture, religion, etc., is the same which would bind one person to another. Once, what was called Sati in one place was observed in different forms in others. Accounts from Ibn Fadlan and the verses from the Sigurðarkviða hin skamma assert that Norse people would offer up a wealthy Chieftain’s thralls or slaves, to his funeral pyre after his passing, and Julius Caesar says the same of the Celts in De Bello Gallico. This Roman account is the origin of the ‘Wicker Man’ stereotype, where beloved ‘dependants’ of the deceased are given up along with other offerings to be purified into something others would call Agni, the sacred fire. It might be more virtuous to plaster all discourse pertaining to such things with comments on the barbarous vestiges of a less appropriately enlightened past, but it might be more useful still to understand why people would do such things. And so go from “ignorance to truth, darkness to light, and death to immortality,” as per that enigmatic mantra echoed in Hindu Yagna rituals, it would seem. If truth could be light. If that light could be immortality, it would take the shape of a fire fed by and specified by one’s very beliefs. This is how our belief ties us to our people, to our lands. We live and die by them. We do not simply have our culture follow us into the fire. We go because of it. And whether that is ethically speaking without blemish or not, it is certainly powerful. We do things which seem illogical, which other animals do not do. A culture is a truth, it is an understanding of the world. In such a way, it considers rules and identifies what is to be prized in this understanding of the world, and what is to be deemed more unsightly. And this is the nature of our identities, as humans, as ethnicities. This is how we are married to our cultures, not in bondage, but in heritage, as per a hypernatural, proto-legal contract. This is us. Alive. But Europe is becoming even less alive itself, because it is becoming less Christian, which in and of itself would not necessitate unfortunate circumstances, if only it did not entail the rise of Atheism. As a consequence, Europe becomes ‘more lonely’. It manages the extraordinary feat of being somehow formed of so many countries which remain so impossibly isolated from each other. Yet, indeed, it is natural that this continent should have no faith, and no faith in itself, for such things were bored out of it by the Romans and Christianity. It is my customary finding that things usually succeed in doing what they were designed to do, and Christianity was designed to make the European people complacent and easy to control. No wonder that as it falls, as the Church awakens to every nightmare about paedophilia accusations in this hypocritical bed it has made for itself, Europeans are not only impossible to control, but they are directionless. Christianity is more impactful from a cultural perspective than a spiritual one; it served as a device of enforcing the Roman rule and extending the duration of their Empire, supplanting an enduring (arguably militant) presence in their lands as an oppressive crushing of culture on a local scale, imposing a single identity-defining dogma. It was applied to control, and now the people are uncontrollable, and inconsolably unruly since the Roman rule has decayed. Yet, it is the state of the dominated to retain their chains after their master has met their demise. It is surprising Europe has taken so long to throw off the very yoke of Christendom in the first place. Albeit, Christianity had been unknowingly preserving truly European, pagan culture. And, as it falls, so does its inherited identity. Atheism has come and it brings with it a cold, stark divestment of the European spirit from the European body. This makes every man and woman less than human, for all different world cultures, all at least have a notion of the spirit, and a cornered animal lashes out because it is afraid, outnumbered, perhaps. Alone. This is a time of division. Even as we speak, conversations are cracking open about the consequences of Brexit in regards to Ireland’s relationship with Northern Ireland, and while a united Éire may seem like a step forward, it also indicates the breaking down of a much older order. One thing upon which we all can agree is that changes are afoot. For better or for worse, it seems this great and old continent will never be the same again. The end of individual difference, so surely the end of our differences altogether, no? Ultimate unity through ultimate, violent equity. Of course, it is rather beneficial for Church and State alike to have its people be without identity; they are so much easier to pra(e)y upon! And so, behold the touted saviour: Socialism. It is at the heart of globalisation, but socialism was purely and only an advent of chaos, a machine designed to destroy. Karl Marx did not want to help the working classes, but he did want to make them kill people, often each other.   Marx believed a great change was on the horizon, but the problem with his ideas was that he believed the change could only and must be reached via great conflict. He believed society was on the verge of collapse, he never incited peaceful resolution or the empowerment of workers and always sought only to arm them rather than communicate with them. When he visited the German Workers’ Education Society of London in 1845, he found self-educated, self-made men. They were anti-liberal, anti-bohemian and practically-minded, and he saw them as lowly for not sharing his apocalyptic ambitions for the future. They engaged in practical discussion, though without academic training in philosophy (which is why he disliked working men and thought them beneath himself). This was not what he wanted. He wanted revolution and chaos, for as he stated: “Socialism cannot be brought into existence without revolution”. When his father died in 1838, he spent much of his inheritance of 6000 ₣ on arming Belgian workers with guns. Certainly, the violent revolutions of the country I grew up in, France, have a long history indeed of upheaving everything and distracting from the country’s problems until they go away, but they ultimately benefited slightly wealthier men seizing power, only to be deposed by men slightly less wealthy than themselves. Every time, it is the slightly less hard-working man who gains leadership at the expense of the slightly harder working man. The same can be seen in the French-backed American Revolution, a systematic upheaval which allowed wealthy English landowners in the New World to detach themselves from their colonial control of ‘The British’ under the new identity of ‘The American’, and they profited and suffered immensely. Again, marrying oneself to a new culture, a new identity, will dictate one’s destiny. And so come into focus the fires of modern-day Paris, lit by the Gilets Jaunes. Fire once more presides the times of chaos, the times of change. So how, I ask, can this, revolution, be the answer? I cannot agree that Marx was right in the larger sense that it is necessary, but I must wonder as to his related belief that it is inevitable. Visions of fire, revolution and chaos, and one must think of the Wheel of Fire, a Greek mythological image originating in the punishment of Ixion after his lusting for Zeus’s divine consort, Hera. It signifies a torturous chain of events leading to dire consequences, in result of personal actions or flaws which are ultimately the victim’s fault. It provides a caveat to be considered, in matters of want and misplaced ambition. It is the fall from grace, and it is engendered by the foreboding betrayal of a sacred matrimony. As I attend a concert by the folk-rock band Faun, at the end, a skaldic lutist/mandolin player speaks as a grandiose orator, transforming from the humble, weaselly man he has been every other time we hear him speak into something approaching the divine musician we have seen play, as when he performs, as when he sings. His band’s spectacle reaches an emotive pinnacle as he speaks, almost preaching now, but with such zeal the likes of which a hurricane could not bring any modern Christian priest to muster, with the passion not seen since they were not merely excused by the burning of our wise women but corralled it. The kind of power not seen unless truth and conviction bolster the rightful in their unextinguished focus; he says we must remember who we are. Remember nature. Our own nature. As he speaks in his complete form, finally, but only once, is mentioned the creature who is the namesake of the band, the faun, the Pan figure, who just like Krishna plays the flute and sits surrounded by the animals, a Master of Beasts. And then he says how it was known by another name to the Celts, as Cernunnos. Thus begins the cycle. A vision of a devil. A vision of nature, personified. A herald of flame to come. And so I contemplate this apple of my eye which I see on the horizon. Knowledge of paganism is the knowledge of how to live and connect with our environment of Europe, and so I say that, for the West, to transcend Christendom via the produce of the trees of knowledge is the only way that we will be able to live in this garden. The serpent penetrates the apple. Perhaps, it is to be seized, like the Snake-Witch Stone shows, perhaps it is to be defeated like the biblical Leviathan. But it is no primitive return to nature which will save us now, but a mature and learned taking into oneself the ways of yore. We must make of ourselves ergonomic beings. A form of cultural bio-mimicry will be observed in ancient lore, and this will tell us how to be. Simply put, there are philosophies and facts to be observed in the natural world, echoed in mythology, which can inform us on how to live our lives, so we can be healthier, but also on how we should think, so we can be holier. As I think on this vision, I must wonder what ‘true spiritual sun’ will be unveiled to us, ‘hidden by a disc of golden light’. What truth will be known, what duty done? What sacred feet, anointed now? Looking to the future, for Europe, for the world? Fire. But will it be a wheel or a dawn? This will depend on the nature, the aspect and, I fear, upon the reception of this, the Truth. These tales of myth and history weave in and out of each other, they remind us of our inherent shared heritage defined not as humans, but as people. For, in commiseration with history, mythology serves not only to grant us stories from the past where we may learn how to rise, but also stories of the soul, that we may learn not to fall. And what these similarities do tell us is that Europe should be united under common ground, regardless of any Union - so long as it remains European. As such, it is time Europe decided to whom it would be married and what is to be the philosophical companion to its destiny, what identity will accompany it towards an uncertain future. Some would say we look outside, or without. I merely say we look within.</summary></entry></feed>