<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-30T22:13:48+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">An Uphill Battle: The Plight of Gaza</title><link href="/The-Plight-of-Gaza" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Uphill Battle: The Plight of Gaza" /><published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Plight-of-Gaza</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Plight-of-Gaza">&lt;p&gt;For most of the world, restricted movement, fear of stepping out of their homes, isolation, stock-piling foods, looking over your shoulders, and living in fear are relatively new concepts. However, for the people living in the 365 square kilometres of occupied Gaza strip, these are essential elements of their life since 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gaza strip, a small coast between Egypt and Israel has been under heavy blockade since 2007, when Hamas, a militant group supporting Palestinian occupation won the legislative elections in Gaza with a majority. Israel, perceiving a threat to its power, implemented a heavy military blockade in Gaza, restricting movement and cutting off the small coast from the outside world while claiming that they have not occupied the territory and have only increased border protection for security. However, the fact remains that Israel blocks land, sea and air routes to Gaza, and the people of Gaza have lived under these stifling circumstances for thirteen years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tussle between Hamas and the Israeli regime is evolving into a very real possibility of a full-blown war, one that the people of Gaza and Hamas may not be able to win. According to an &lt;em&gt;Aljazeera&lt;/em&gt; report on August 26, 2020, in a series of consecutive attacks, Israeli warplanes and bombs have been attacking Hamas’ military sites, industrial and agricultural lands in retaliation to incendiary balloons launched by Palestinians into South Israel as a means to pressure Israel to live under the blockade. This act of rebellion by the Palestinians against the blockade has invigorated the Israeli regime in their efforts to completely annex Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaza is not the first or the last territory to become a victim of forced occupation, yet it does not make the act of forced occupation any less repugnant. The idea of home is analogous to the concept of safety and belongingness, but this has not been the case for the 1,820,000 people living in Gaza for a very long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The worst thing is the sense of being a stranger in your own land and feeling that not a single part of it is yours”&lt;/em&gt;, said Raja Shehadeh, a Palestinian lawyer and writer in an interview with Amnesty International. The feeling of safety and belongingness in one’s home is the basest of human needs. Access to land, water, food and other essential resources such as healthcare, education and economic opportunities have been restricted for the Palestinians living in Gaza as a means to force them from their homeland. The people of Gaza have been deprived of their freedom to move freely in their own homes, compounded by restrictions on trade, and constant military threat and violence, the situation has worsened every year since 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another saddening consequence of Israel’s occupation of Gaza is the ultimate loss of cultural identity of the people. Our cultures and who we are as individuals are determined by our homes. Development of our identity is an intrinsic part of growth and for the many children born under this occupation, military presence, fear and looming threats of war mould their childhood. The consequence of which is children growing up with hatred and fear in their hearts while the adults fear displacement from the only place they have known as their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2019, the United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA) reported the use of lethal force by Israeli forces that resulted in 252 deaths and 25,522 injuries to Palestinians in Gaza. Unlawful detention and torture of detainees are commonplace activities on the Gaza border by Israeli forces. Another report by Amnesty International reported that in March 2018, when the Palestinians conducted the ‘Great March of Return Protests’ and by December 27, 2018, 215 Palestinians were killed, including 47 children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While unlawful killings and torture form a major chunk of human rights violations in Gaza, the rest is formed of withholding health services and restricting movement. The Israeli blockade has isolated Gaza from the rest of the world through illegal air, land and sea restrictions. The Israeli regime determines the goods that enter into Gaza and the trade the people are able to partake in. They also control the electricity and water supply in the region, and, consequently, the Israeli regime has been utilising this control to starve hospitals, shops and people in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Hamas has retaliated by means of violence, protests and even legislative assemblies, its impact has not made a significant bearing on the occupation. It cannot be disputed that similar crimes have also been committed by Hamas, and violent means have been heavily used to fight back Israel. However, It is not fair that the innocent civilians Palestinians in Gaza suffer while the rest of the world ignores its suffering or worse, utilises their plight to establish trade deals like US President Donald Trump did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Notre-Dame burnt, the entire world cried. Yet when the Palestinians cried for help, they were easily ignored. This denial of aid is fueled by the Islamophobic perspective that most of the world subscribes to. The suffering of the predominantly Muslim community in Gaza is easy to ignore for the rest of the world as compared to violations in a non-Islamic nation, and the opportunity to gain control over a Muslim dominated region is too tempting to ignore for the Islamophobic leadership of the world. It is unsurprising that Israel’s actions will go unremarked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has not been an easy journey for the citizens of Gaza, yet their indomitable spirit and determination to fight back and not give up is commendable. Their fight will get difficult in the coming months, with threats of war and weakening global support, and it remains to be seen how they fight back.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anon.anon</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">For most of the world, restricted movement, fear of stepping out of their homes, isolation, stock-piling foods, looking over your shoulders, and living in fear are relatively new concepts. However, for the people living in the 365 square kilometres of occupied Gaza strip, these are essential elements of their life since 2007.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Racism is Profitable</title><link href="/Racism-is-Profitable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Racism is Profitable" /><published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Racism-is-Profitable</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Racism-is-Profitable">&lt;p&gt;This is simply not the time to be talking about how Nelson Mandela fought ‘apartheid’ in South Africa or how Rosa Parks refused to give up her bus seat to a white man, because that world was decades ago, fraught with exploitation, incarceration, brutalities, exclusion, all on the basis of a simple difference – skin colour. One may wonder that due to the efforts of these icons, the world, sixty years down the line, will be different, wherein all races are treated equally. Fast forward to 2020, does the phrase &lt;em&gt;“I can’t breathe”&lt;/em&gt; ring any bells? If it does, congratulations, you’re not living under a rock. George Floyd, an ordinary American man, was pinned down on the road, with a knee pressing on his throat, by a police officer for allegedly using a $20 counterfeit bill, “allegedly” being the keyword here. George Floyd was killed and the accused officer got so much so as a suspension. Why? Racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst the pandemic, the historic Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement took place and &lt;em&gt;#JusticeForGeorgeFloyd&lt;/em&gt; was trending all across the globe. Not just the black community, but people from all races came out in support of the cause and identified themselves as allies of the movement. Not only individuals and communities but even corporations, small and big, spoke on the cause and corporate executives expressed their contempt towards police brutality, establishing their coherence with the black community. So does this mean white supremacy has ended and finally there is socio-political and economic liberation for the black community? I think not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When multinational corporations like Amazon, Walmart, and Wall Street banks like CitiBank and JPMorgan Chase put out posters in support of the movement, the face value of it painted an empathetic picture. However, the harsh reality is that it was just a mere public relations stunt for them. Far from being the solution to systemic racism in America, these multi-billion dollar corporations have been actively perpetuating it. It is fair to say that corporate hypocrisy exists when on the one hand these banks, like JPMorgan Chase, claim to be inclusive by employing a few black employees and by giving press interviews where they urge everyone to be more inclusive in their respective workplaces and neighbourhoods, while on the other hand, they discriminate against their black customers by making them incur heavier costs for mortgage borrowing, and not addressing this form of discrimination despite recognising and identifying it. Not only customers but the figures show how JPMorgan Chase discriminates against its own employees by excluding black people from holding positions in the top tier of management. Barely about 4% of the bank’s top executives are black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind this is that corporations profit off of racism. The historic oppression and suppression, for example - removing native people from their land through theft and genocide, enslaving African people for work and reproductive labour, and so on- are proofs of the fact that ‘racial capitalism’ has existed for ages and continues to exist in the status quo wherein wealthy elites are motivated to keep suppressing the economic vitality of people of colour. This initiates a vicious cycle of an ‘oppression economy’ wherein this economic suppression leads on to prevent these communities from having any form of social capital and hence, hinders their political power and their ability to bring about any form of a political change in the society. In the 21st century, racism is not just limited to the difference in skin colour, but extends to acting as a means to an end; the means being the black community and the end being the flourishing of these multinational corporations. Economist Darrick Hamilton explains that the pursuit of profit, not hatred of black people, is the real root of discrimination,  &lt;em&gt;“Racism is a tool, a mechanism. In many settings, it’s purposeful. Sure, bias can become implicit or unconscious through socialization. But that is a secondary effect from the initial tool that was used”&lt;/em&gt;  said Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an extreme economic inequality among whites and blacks in the United States. This again stems from the fact that ‘racial capitalism’ or ‘oppression economy’ inherently functions by uplifting one community meanwhile pushing down the other. In such scenarios, when a community is discriminated against, there comes a paradigm of ostracisation wherein one community is never allowed to have equal rights, which leads to them being either unemployed or underpaid. Even governments, in the past, haven’t been able to tackle the effects of racism on the economy, and this was proved right when former US President Ronald Reagan asked black citizens to trust the marketplace in case they have distrust towards the government. And it is no secret how that panned out, considering the marketplace was discriminatory in its very essence, due to the existence of racial resentment and white supremacy. Even when some progressives wanted to bring about economic equality and infrastructural development, it meant that all races have to side with the government, and since racism creates divisions and distrust among citizens, siding with one government was not an option. Therefore, the progressives deemed it best to leave the reign of bridging economic inequality with the rich multinational corporations. And hence, the vicious cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From economic inequality stems wealth inequality, which means inequality in the amount of money one could save from their incomes. This form of wealth could also be in terms of bonds or real estate properties. Since the black community has been historically oppressed, their chance at inheriting any prior wealth is negligible, but moreover, they face uncountable barriers to creating any form of wealth in the current scenario. These barriers are again due to the systemic discrimination faced by the community. This lack of wealth and savings has shown its effects during the COVID-19 pandemic for the black community since they are the ones that face the brunt of environmental injustice, implications of poverty, and systemic racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People from the black community are also highly criminalised and penalised, at least three times more than their white counterparts. This also means profit for the corporations since a higher number of criminals means a higher number of prisons, which are in fact constructed and funded for by these corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the ‘oppression economy’ is not the need of the hour, but the ‘liberation economy’ is. And our only way to be able to get a ‘liberation economy’ is by firstly, supporting and electing candidates that will actively tackle issues of racism and better the economic policies for people of colour. Secondly, the unnecessary criminalisation of people from the black community has to end and the government has to tackle the root cause of the occurrence of such activities which may, in fact, stem from the socio-political or economic needs of these people. And lastly, the universal guarantee to have access to basic economic rights, healthcare and education should be made. Race is an inherent part of people’s identities and to deserve basic human decency, one should not be made to feel that they need to part with their identities. All communities together choose their governments and to simply leave the reign of controlling and dictating our lives in the hands of profit-driven corporations is a breach of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">This is simply not the time to be talking about how Nelson Mandela fought ‘apartheid’ in South Africa or how Rosa Parks refused to give up her bus seat to a white man, because that world was decades ago, fraught with exploitation, incarceration, brutalities, exclusion, all on the basis of a simple difference – skin colour. One may wonder that due to the efforts of these icons, the world, sixty years down the line, will be different, wherein all races are treated equally. Fast forward to 2020, does the phrase “I can’t breathe” ring any bells? If it does, congratulations, you’re not living under a rock. George Floyd, an ordinary American man, was pinned down on the road, with a knee pressing on his throat, by a police officer for allegedly using a $20 counterfeit bill, “allegedly” being the keyword here. George Floyd was killed and the accused officer got so much so as a suspension. Why? Racism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Will They, Won’t They?: India’s Iran Policy</title><link href="/Indias-Iran-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will They, Won’t They?: India’s Iran Policy" /><published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Indias-Iran-Policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Indias-Iran-Policy">&lt;p&gt;The Iran question comes back to India’s doorstep every few years. This time it is in the form of the fear that New Delhi is losing its hold over Iran. To make matters worse, this hold seems to be taken over by India’s fiercest rival in recent times, the People’s Republic of China. China’s expansion, both in territory and in influence, has been a growing concern for India. Both states have been vying for primacy in the South Asian region for many decades. By recently excluding India from the Chabahar rail link project at the same time when it was signing a partnership with China, Iran has raised many questions for the future of the India-Iran relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Chabahar Chronicles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chabahar port and the Rail link to Zahedan hold great significance in India’s foreign policy. Firstly, it provides a much-needed solution for trade with Central Asia. It is not possible to secure a land route for trade through Pakistan. Chabahar port, in the Gulf of Oman, is a mere 1,400 km from Mumbai’s coast. The proposed Rail link would be a way to connect to Afghanistan and subsequently, the rest of Central Asia as well as Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, this port was strategically important from the point of view of trade as well as to counter the presence of China in this coastal region. China has helped in the development of the Gwadar Port on Pakistan’s coastline not too far from Chabahar. Thus, the wider context of Chabahar must be kept in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, India and Iran signed the New Delhi Declaration. In this agreement, both countries had decided to jointly develop the Chabahar Port Complex on the coast of Iran. This port development was exempted from sanctions levied by the USA on Iran after a special request by India. In the past few years, India’s investment in the port complex has paid off as it had been operating one whole terminal of the complex. Since December 2018, 82 ships and almost 1,200,000 tons of bulk cargo have been handled through this terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the success of this project, a contract was signed in 2016 to develop the 628 km long Chabahar-Zahedan railway link along the Iran-Afghanistan border. IRCON, a Government of India undertaking under the Ministry of Railways, was appointed by India to gauge the feasibility of the project. They were to work with the Iranian Construction and Development of Transportation Infrastructures Company (CDTIC). After the site inspection and review of the feasibility report, some outstanding financial and technical issues still remained and the project was stalled for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Iran started the project in July 2020 without the inclusion of India. Although Iran eventually clarified that India could join at a later stage, a ray of distrust shone through the project. Additionally, this confusion occurred just as Iran and China were signing an economic and strategic partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This $400 billion deal was approved by the Iranian cabinet in June 2020. The partnership will vastly expand Chinese presence in banking, telecommunication, ports, railways and dozens of other projects. In exchange, China will receive a regular and heavily discounted supply of Iranian oil over the next 25 years. The document also describes deepening military cooperation. The military partnership would include joint training and exercises, joint research and weapons development, and intelligence sharing. This would give China a foothold in a region that has been a strategic preoccupation of the United States for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The China-Iran Agreement is also set to include a major port development project on the Strait of Hormuz. The oil transit line at the Strait of Hormuz is strongly held by Iran and is an important maritime chokepoint for the world. If this chokepoint comes under the influence of China, it may set the stage for a global shift in power by threatening the oil supply of the entire world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Farzad B Gas Field&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another similar incident occurred in relation to the Farzad B Gas Field located in the Persian Gulf. The contract for exploration of this field was signed by an Indian Consortium comprising ONGC Videsh, Oil India and Indian Oil Corporation. This contract expired in 2009 after the commerciality of the field was based on gas discovery.  Since this discovery, the consortium consistently made efforts to secure a deal for the development of the field. By 2018, 75% of the deal was finalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 2019, the US withdrew from the Iranian Nuclear Deal. In earlier instances of sanctions, India had still stood strong on certain points of trade with Iran. However, after the 2019 sanctions, India almost zeroed out on oil imports from Iran. It also slowed down the funding of the various infrastructure projects. Even though India managed to secure the exemption of the Chabahar Rail link project, they were unable to execute their duties in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran was apprehensive of trusting India after they readily complied with the US sanctions. In January 2020, India was informed that Iran would unilaterally develop the field in the near future. Again, they said that India would be included in the project at a later stage. Indian companies had invested millions of dollars in the gas discovery stage, only to be ousted at the development stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Re-evaluation of Policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both these incidents point to a recurring problem. It seems that India’s conduct with other countries is highly dependent on the actions of two powers - the US and China. India needs to re-evaluate its priorities in terms of its foreign policy. The collaborative projects with Iran could have been of great benefit to India’s economy. The recalibration of relations with Iran is in the best interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the process of reconciliation seems to have begun. Within the span of 3 days in September 2020, two of India’s high ranking ministers visited Tehran. Indian Defence Minister Rajnath Singh’s visit was related to security in the Persian Gulf and potential military cooperation between the states while Indian External Minister S Jaishankar’s visit was related to securing an Indian interest in Chabahar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue at hand brings the memory of the world order during the Cold War, where developing states conducted their relations with each other while the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) and the USA loomed in the background. They were forced to pick a side and many potential alliances were thwarted in this way. In this situation, it might be wise to look back at our nation’s first Prime Minister, Jawaharlal Nehru, and his undying determination for India to have an independent foreign policy. He was a founding member of the Non-Aligned Movement (NAM) which, although still in existence, has fallen out of the mainstream after the collapse of the USSR. It may be time for a revival of NAM so that countries like India and Iran can engage in activities of mutual benefit without looking over their shoulders every step of the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The Iran question comes back to India’s doorstep every few years. This time it is in the form of the fear that New Delhi is losing its hold over Iran. To make matters worse, this hold seems to be taken over by India’s fiercest rival in recent times, the People’s Republic of China. China’s expansion, both in territory and in influence, has been a growing concern for India. Both states have been vying for primacy in the South Asian region for many decades. By recently excluding India from the Chabahar rail link project at the same time when it was signing a partnership with China, Iran has raised many questions for the future of the India-Iran relationship.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EdTech: The New Normal of Learning?</title><link href="/EdTech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EdTech: The New Normal of Learning?" /><published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/EdTech</id><content type="html" xml:base="/EdTech">&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has impacted every area of our lives and left us with no choice but to find new alternatives. Schooling and education were no exception. Parents, teachers and students felt nothing but helpless as everything came to a standstill. Schools and universities were shut and the situation was uncertain. While it was convenient for adults to adapt to the new normal and work from home, teachers and students had a hard time figuring out a way to keep the learning going. Edtech, the practice of using technology in education, has been around for quite some years but it was never considered a substitute to classroom teaching. Parents have always preferred live learning as the best possible method. However, times changed and we ended up in a situation that required us to learn virtually and adopt edtech. It has been six months and the edtech sector has flourished more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise was huge and pretty visible as the sector dominated the market numbers. The edtech sector in India is currently estimated to be valued at $735 million and a growth of 150% is expected in 2020. A number of edtech startups have completed their long-term goals within these six months of lockdown. The users have increased manifold and the businesses are soaring high. The consumer base of these upcoming disruptors in the education arena, not only consists of students but also working professionals. Lockdown increased the time people had on their hands which they utilised by enhancing and developing their skill sets. These innovative startups have included various courses which attract not only students but also adults who are currently working. Employers have also encouraged their employees to learn new skills via these courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edtech has evolved over the years and has come a long way. It started with video-based learning which has now evolved into an interactive platform that adapts to the different needs of every learner. Students used to interact with peers and teachers which made learning more wholesome. Until recently, interactive virtual learning wasn’t a thing. But today, every edtech platform has various features that enhance the learning to make it more interactive and complete. Parents have started to rely on them as it makes learning fun and makes the concepts easy to understand. Moreover, allowing the students to learn at their own pace has proved to be another reason for their huge success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millions of people have signed up in the past few months and this massive growth has led to increased hiring and new opportunities. The increased consumer base demanded an increased workforce to deal with the complaints and enhance the learning experience for its users. Unlike Facebook and other social media platforms, these learning platforms offer paid services to its customers. Even besides all this, the growth is consistent. The reason being, most parents are willing to spend on their child’s education in the hope of a better future for them. Thus, paid subscriptions to e-learning was seen as an investment and was a big hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the edtech boom sustain post this lockdown period? It has been six months and most of us have adapted to this new normal of wearing masks and following social distancing at all points of time. The easing of lockdown has begun and people are getting back to work. Eventually schools, colleges and universities will open up for students, and in no time classroom teaching will overtake these virtual platforms. We cannot really predict how it is going to turn out for these companies in the near future, but it is highly likely that the growth might increase even in the post-COVID-19 period. First, the New Education Policy (NEP) will be implemented and the use of technology in learning will finally catch up with the outdated curriculums of schools. With the government’s plans to introduce coding for students, it is likely that parents would trust online tutors more than they would trust school teachers. The simple reason being that these edtech startups have the resources to onboard experienced coders and teachers in this field and many of these platforms already offer fundamental courses on coding. Second, with the growing demand for skills like Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning in every field, it seems like technology in education is here to stay. The edtech market will not die out soon as we are expecting a merger between online and offline learning in the entire education system. There are certain problems that might impact its growth as a whole, issues of internet connectivity in suburban and rural areas might be a problem for many. All these problems demand unique solutions that the developers need to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edtech is like any other service which makes our lives easier. It aids us by providing a simpler way of learning and understanding things. We don’t know as of now whether it can possibly replace our classroom learning, however, it can definitely be integrated with the existing system to make our approach more holistic. The burden now lies on the developers to attract maximum users and provide unique features to ensure sustainability. While the choice remains on the students and the parents if they choose to trust this form of education in the coming decades.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">COVID-19 has impacted every area of our lives and left us with no choice but to find new alternatives. Schooling and education were no exception. Parents, teachers and students felt nothing but helpless as everything came to a standstill. Schools and universities were shut and the situation was uncertain. While it was convenient for adults to adapt to the new normal and work from home, teachers and students had a hard time figuring out a way to keep the learning going. Edtech, the practice of using technology in education, has been around for quite some years but it was never considered a substitute to classroom teaching. Parents have always preferred live learning as the best possible method. However, times changed and we ended up in a situation that required us to learn virtually and adopt edtech. It has been six months and the edtech sector has flourished more than ever.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Caustic Crass of Casteism</title><link href="/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Caustic Crass of Casteism" /><published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism">&lt;p&gt;Facebook in India is incessantly flooded with memes — pictures or videos of casteist slurs against the marginalised communities, as those who belong to ‘upper caste’ per se, lament against caste-based reservations in public institutes and government jobs. Their rationale, more prominently since the implementation of the Mandal Commission in 1990, has been that it ‘kills’ the merit factor, i.e. meritorious students who belong to the namesake ‘General’ category are deprived of opportunities that marginalised communities get due to reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the mind of every student in this country is filled with this narrative even before they burn the midnight oil to crack the draconian entrance exams. Such a hate-spewing narrative naturally brings a certain anathema towards the ‘reserved’ categories of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hatred is evident from the repetitive use of &lt;em&gt;cham**r&lt;/em&gt;, a word used as a casteist expletive which generalises all the marginalised communities under a derogative umbrella term, by many students studying in various educational institutions, sub-consciously fuming their exasperation against reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of this article, who has been through the rat-race of preparing for the draconian engineering entrance exams, also blindly believed in this narrative. In hindsight, he now sees how it actually culminated with him profiling classmates and batchmates in the coaching classes, based on whether they could reap the benefits of reservation or not. His time also coincided with the ascendancy of Hindu-supremacist BJP at the centre, which also made him look slyly at Dr Ambedkar and the entire anti-caste movement. Of course, he found little sense in those rallying against casteism — for he only saw from a prism which showed them ‘entitled’ to higher-education in prestigious institutes without ‘merit’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This anecdote supports the aforementioned argument of how upper-caste propaganda embarks students on a path of discrimination and hatred — the wrongdoings of which are extremely difficult, if not impossible, to undo. What is even more concerning is that this propaganda under the garb of ‘merit’ and ‘equality’ brings a certain wind of legitimacy, the whiff of which is often hard to resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, ‘merit’ is the key working word in this debate. However, it has been painstakingly dissected and presented in “Does ‘Merit’ have a Caste?” on &lt;em&gt;The Wire&lt;/em&gt; and it would be a great disservice to the author if it is reiterated only for the sake of argumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duopoly of casteism and classism are the biggest yet the most obscure threat to India’s Xanadu, the liveable manifestation of the promulgations of the Indian Constitution. Caste and class inequalities, on the contrary, are being pushed further into obscurity by a rising intolerance towards monotheistic religions, Islam in particular. Hindu vigilantes are often in what could be a self-perceived duel against their Muslim counterparts and vice versa. The macabre riots in Delhi are a testament to this intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any conflict between religious communities obviously takes precedence over atrocities committed in the name of caste. In fact, the growing divide between monotheistic Islam and polytheistic Hinduism has given the latter a very powerful rationale for a ‘war cry’ of sorts, exhorting Hindus to ‘unite’ to ‘protect’ their sacrosanct religion. In reality, such exhortations culminate only with upper-caste Hindus to make a more impregnable clout and thereby, pushing the marginalised communities further away into oblivion. The upper echelons of public life in India are still largely dominated by upper-caste Hindus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, the author also believes that caste-based politicking is another reason for this growing divide. Whilst the government has brought upon the reformist measures to alleviate centuries of oppression, it still isn’t a step towards abolishing caste altogether. Many upper-caste Hindus often accuse political parties of caste-based political skullduggery for the marginalised communities have always been of a ‘vote-bank’, a sizeable population whose vote is crucial to win elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the author himself was led to strongly believe in the upper-caste narrative which denounces the existence of caste-based oppression altogether and accuses the marginalised communities to raise the caste question only to ‘cling’ onto the reservations that they are entitled to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an opinion of caste comes from a selective reading of society. In order to subscribe to this narrative, one must have class privilege, where the society is so-called ‘westernised’ enough to not bother knowing one’s caste as long as everyone belongs to the same economic class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it would be unfair to assume that being on top of the class pyramid saves one from the caste question, such selective perception of caste also comes from denial and ignorance; to put it crudely, one cannot deny the existence of casteism if one has never been subjected to caste-based discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caste dynamics in India are so precariously balanced that leaders such as Mahatma Gandhi are also accused of ensuring that the caste hierarchy remains. Man Booker-prize winning author Arundhati Roy in her essay ‘The Doctor and the Saint’ has opined that Gandhi supported the caste hierarchy only to appease the high-caste Marwari businessmen who, financially or otherwise, supported his &lt;em&gt;satyagraha&lt;/em&gt; (policy of nonviolent resistance) movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If probably the greatest statesman of this country paid his obeisance to casteism, it would be foolish to assume that a Hindu-supremacist government like the BJP would uproot this anachronistic practice. On the contrary, many Dalit activists are wary of the party’s intentions, and accuse it of ethnic profiling and cleansing with their divisive Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA) and the draconian National Register of Citizens (NRC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legacy of Dr B R Ambedkar, who perhaps was the most profound Dalit thinker, is also thrown in the cesspool of profanities and slurs, hurled by the upper-caste, the propaganda of hate deeply entrenched in their minds. The Indian education system, among its many inherent flaws, also fails to elucidate students about Dr Ambedkar as much as it embellishes Gandhi, which again reeks of the politics behind how impressionable minds are moulded to perceive the history and ethos of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Xanadu which was envisaged by those who broke the shackles of an oppressive colonial rule is questioned and dissected now. Despite Dr Ambedkar’s tribulations for a more egalitarian and just society, the existence of marginalised communities is reduced to a transactional relationship where ‘reservation’ is given in exchange for their suffrage. Whether the doors of an independent India were open for Dalits and tribals is a question that remains unanswered even after 73 years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Kant</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Facebook in India is incessantly flooded with memes — pictures or videos of casteist slurs against the marginalised communities, as those who belong to ‘upper caste’ per se, lament against caste-based reservations in public institutes and government jobs. Their rationale, more prominently since the implementation of the Mandal Commission in 1990, has been that it ‘kills’ the merit factor, i.e. meritorious students who belong to the namesake ‘General’ category are deprived of opportunities that marginalised communities get due to reservation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Clout of A New World Order</title><link href="/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Clout of A New World Order" /><published>2020-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Social psychologists believe that feelings of frailty and uncertainty associate an individual with a tendency to believe in conspiracies”&lt;/em&gt;, said Karen M Douglas, Professor of Social Psychology at the University of Kent in the United Kingdom. Conceivably, it is true, to have something to lean on is an instinct to regain a sense of control, even if the conspiracy is unrelated to what caused the lack of control in an individual’s life. But what if this is just another conspiracy theory to dwarf all the other conspiracy theories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember watching &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, you would probably remember Mr Anderson (Keanu Reaves), an otherwise rational person making the leap from prudent paranoia to a not so illogical conspiracy, which led him to the dilemma of choosing between the red and the blue pill. There exists a gnawing feeling of not having control over your life - the dissatisfaction which hinders you from living your life to the fullest. And that is what happened with Adam Weishaupt, founder of The Illuminati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in 1748 in Ingolstadt, Bavaria, Weishaupt was a descendant of Jewish converts to Christianity. Orphaned at a young age, his uncle took care of his education. After completing his studies, Weishaupt became a Professor of canon law at the University of Ingolstadt, got married and started a family. He seemed to have a conventional career until 1784 when the Bavarian state learned about his distinct and provocative ideas. Since childhood, being an avid reader, Weishaupt was convinced that religious ideas were no longer an adequate belief system and hence, he decided to find another form of illumination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May 1, 1776 saw the first Illuminati meet in a forest near Ingolstadt to find the order and there, they established the rules that were to govern the order. The order was a set of scientific ideas and practices that could be applied to radically change the way European states were run. By the end of 1784, Weishaupt’s secret order grew considerably to 3,000 members and by the mid 1780’s, theIlluminati caught the Bavarian government’s attention, which put an end to the secret society. Weishaupt fled and gave up the secret shenanigans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does the Illuminati want?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracy theorists obsessively analyse public events for evidence of Illuminati infiltration in the modern-day world. There have been many events which are said to be proof of the fact that the Illuminati has infiltrated the ranks of prominent leaders, celebrities, clergymen, business tycoons and pharmaceutical companies around the globe, who are affiliated with it and are collectively working to secure their main objective. Back in 2013, when Beyonce performed at superbowl and flashed a pyramid (believed to be the Illuminati’s symbol) with her hands, the internet was lit up with conjectures that she was a member of the secret society. While this might be a baseless conspiracy theory on the grounds of impracticality, it is logical for many who believe they have seen things. Moreover, there exists a condition called Pareidolia, which causes humans to see objective patterns in random stimuli, often attaching humane characteristics to non-living objects, for instance, seeing the face of Jesus in a cream cracker or the date of Apocalypse in Trump’s social security number. Though rationality makes conditions like Pareidolia seem utter nonsense, one can argue that wild-imagination has always fuelled pragmatic creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracy theorists have been warning about a New World Order for decades, going all the way back to the isolationist critics of Franklin Delano Roosevelt. The New World Order or NWO is claimed to be a totalitarian world government led by a secretive power elite conspiring to rule the planet. Though it holds little significance whether any secret society wants to instigate a new world order or a group of power-hungry humans who want to control the world, it nonetheless merits some investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the New World Order?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New World Order is a supposedly autocratic world government (or a Cosmocratic government), which signifies the idea of having ONE central government for every country, institution and state in the world. A Cosmocratic style of government can come to power either through violent world domination or voluntary supranational union. Cosmocracy is a polity made up with recombinant structures that are themselves products of constantly changing, yet permanently unfolding processes. It is a moving target that produces unexpected and highly unstable targets. Though that is one way to look at it, there are numerous ways to perceive this form of world order. Having a single government for everybody will result in absolute harmony among different nations implying that most likely there will be no trade and nuclear wars, rather homogeneity will breed bonhomie between countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single government at the world stage may also ensure that after people become unbound from nature, they will create more anthropocentric forms of organizations, and one among them is democracy. Cosmocracy brings this cycle to a close and leads us back to the essential unity of all things - nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is something like the NWO feasible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The likeliness of a Cosmocratic government’s rise to power is undoubtedly negligible, given the severe political and socio-economic turmoil it may bring. Any leader who is at the top of the world’s power structure and wields enormous power has a good chance of indulging in malpractices and corruption. The world surely cannot afford to give such power to a small group of individuals, because at the end of the day, they are just humans and have a good chance of becoming corrupt because of the unlimited power the position entails. Also, in the status quo, we live in a world in which people are inherently very proud of their cultural practices, which naturally results in any of their actions (at a macro level) aimed towards making their ‘nation’ great. In such a scenario, if we elect people from a particular country or even if we ensure that the Cosmocratic government is such which consists of equal representation from all parts of the world, there is no way we can eradicate personal bias towards their nations. This is a factor which defeats the purpose of having one government at a global level because if the leaders do not work to cater to the interests of all people across the world, the implementation of this new order will be futile. Moreover, setting up such a government is not pragmatic at all. We have around 200 countries in the world, albeit we cannot have 200 leaders at the world centre, so there has to be some type of filtration system to see from where the leaders are to be elected, which will naturally give the leaders from the first world nations an upper-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, such a type of government may surely be beneficial in a post-apocalyptic scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course of history, the most powerful advocates of change have emerged out of destructive circumstances. Citing some examples from history - the nation-state to geopolitics emerged from the Peace of Westphalia, which marked the end of the Thirty Years’ War (1618-48) in Central Europe. The political concept of balance of power gained greater importance with the Congress of Vienna, which emerged in the aftermath of the French Revolution and Napoleonic Wars (1792-1815). Besides, The League of Nations, a noble, yet short-lived experiment in circumscribing power competition, emerged from the First World War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation of the world order into a new world order may result from extremely farsighted diplomacy, for which diplomats and policymakers around the world will have to do more than push for incremental improvements within an inadequate system. A possibility entails that if not from diplomacy, the NWO may arise from an apocalypse, though it is terrifying to consider what might have to occur for a new order to emerge in this way, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“Social psychologists believe that feelings of frailty and uncertainty associate an individual with a tendency to believe in conspiracies”, said Karen M Douglas, Professor of Social Psychology at the University of Kent in the United Kingdom. Conceivably, it is true, to have something to lean on is an instinct to regain a sense of control, even if the conspiracy is unrelated to what caused the lack of control in an individual’s life. But what if this is just another conspiracy theory to dwarf all the other conspiracy theories? If you remember watching The Matrix, you would probably remember Mr Anderson (Keanu Reaves), an otherwise rational person making the leap from prudent paranoia to a not so illogical conspiracy, which led him to the dilemma of choosing between the red and the blue pill. There exists a gnawing feeling of not having control over your life - the dissatisfaction which hinders you from living your life to the fullest. And that is what happened with Adam Weishaupt, founder of The Illuminati. Born in 1748 in Ingolstadt, Bavaria, Weishaupt was a descendant of Jewish converts to Christianity. Orphaned at a young age, his uncle took care of his education. After completing his studies, Weishaupt became a Professor of canon law at the University of Ingolstadt, got married and started a family. He seemed to have a conventional career until 1784 when the Bavarian state learned about his distinct and provocative ideas. Since childhood, being an avid reader, Weishaupt was convinced that religious ideas were no longer an adequate belief system and hence, he decided to find another form of illumination. May 1, 1776 saw the first Illuminati meet in a forest near Ingolstadt to find the order and there, they established the rules that were to govern the order. The order was a set of scientific ideas and practices that could be applied to radically change the way European states were run. By the end of 1784, Weishaupt’s secret order grew considerably to 3,000 members and by the mid 1780’s, theIlluminati caught the Bavarian government’s attention, which put an end to the secret society. Weishaupt fled and gave up the secret shenanigans. What does the Illuminati want?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Money Tree</title><link href="/Money-Tree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Money Tree" /><published>2020-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Money-Tree</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Money-Tree">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why countries can’t just print more money to pay off their debts, to feed the homeless, to fix unemployment or for any other issue for that matter? This may seem like a rather silly question but I think it’s one of those questions that people may always wonder about but never ask. The answer can be summed up in just one word - inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inflation is defined as a persistent and substantial increase in the general level of prices related to an increase in the volume of money resulting in a loss of value of the currency, but I’ll get to that later. First, we need to establish what exactly money is. Now, this may seem obvious to many but we still need to clarify that money has absolutely no intrinsic value. This means money in itself is only considered valuable because it can buy things. But if you were stranded on an island, money would be totally useless. Money only has value because we believe it has value. It is called the ‘Tinkerbell Effect’. The tinkerbell effect is used to describe something that only exists because we believe it exists, and this is the case with money. Hypothetically speaking, if we suddenly start believing that money has no value, it wouldn’t have any value. Of course, it wasn’t always this way. Money as a concept has been around for thousands of years, and was first used in the form of commodity money, i.e things that had actual value and uses like salt, wheat, horses and weapons as well as precious metals such as gold and silver, which technically don’t have any intrinsic value either but due to the rarity they were almost universally accepted as currency. Then we have representative money, which makes more sense since carrying around everything you own can be difficult. Basically, you deposit your gold into a bank and they keep it safe for you and in return, they give you a piece of paper acknowledging that you own that gold. These pieces of paper can therefore be used as money. Anyone can go and redeem the gold at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, today almost every country in the world uses fiat money. Fiat money requires faith and trust in the government by the people. The people will have to value their money enough to use it for transactions. If we use a young country as an example, the United States has gone through all three monetary systems within 200 years. In 1790, when the United States stopped using European money as the Coinage Act of 1792 brought the inception of the US Dollar. USD was originally in the form of commodity money, in the form of gold, silver and copper coins. The coins were actually made from real gold, silver and copper, and the value of the metal that was used to make the coins was exactly equal to their face value. The country then moved on to a mixture of commodities and representative money with the Gold Standard Act of 1900. The government issued dollar bills that could be exchanged for gold anytime. The gold standard is a type of representative money that many countries used at the time. This was an effective way to accurately calculate the exchange rates between countries. For example - if one gram of gold costs £1 in Britain and $1.50 in America, then you can easily deduce that £1= $1.5. Later, gold coins were discontinued and silver was removed from other coins, effectively ending commodity money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1971, Richard Nixon officially abandoned the gold standard, and the US moved on to fiat money. So, money today isn’t backed by gold or anything else of value. Now, back to the question at hand: basic economics tells us that an increase in supply results in a fall in price. So, the more the money in the economy, the lower the value of each dollar. This means other countries can purchase more dollars in exchange for their currencies. A second supply and demand analysis shows why this leads to a rise in prices. More money in the economy causes a shift in the demand curve for goods and services, but since this isn’t matched by an increase in economic output, prices must rise. If we use an analogy to demonstrate this, imagine there are 4 people on a desert island, they have 10 pieces of fruit each. All fruits are considered equal in value. Now, imagine they discover a whole forest of apple trees. The total nominal value of the apples have increased because there’s more of them, but the actual value of an apple has gone down due to an increase in supply. Therefore, it now costs 10 apples for 1 banana since the demand for apples is low compared to its supply but the same is high for bananas. Just to make it clear, in this analogy, people represent different countries, the fruits their respective currency and the apple trees are the printed money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just because of economic theory that we know printing too much money is a bad idea, there are several examples throughout history. The most recent one is that of Zimbabwe, which in 2008 suffered extremely high inflation due to printing excess money. This was a result of some awful decisions by President Mugabe. When the economy took a turn for the worse, Mugabe printed more money to pay for government expenditure. This caused inflation to skyrocket and in mid-November 2008, Zimbabwe’s inflation peaked at 6.5 sextillion percent! To put that in perspective actually, first I need to provide some context. The inflation rate in the United States is around 1.5%. Economists generally agree that inflation levels around 1-3% are optimum. First world countries’ inflation rates range from 0 to 5%. A country is said to have entered hyperinflation when its inflation level exceeds 50%. So, with this in mind, Zimbabwe’s inflation at its peak got so bad that prices doubled every 24 hours. The government tried to solve the problem by printing more and more money with higher and higher denominations. They also kept knocking zeroes off the end by revaluing the Zimbabwean dollar 3 times, going through 4 different currencies with 4 different ISO codes. Before the final re-denomination, they were printing 100 trillion ZWR bills. People were literally using wheelbarrows full of cash to buy a loaf of bread. The government even made inflation illegal at one point and people were actually arrested for raising prices. In 2009, the Zimbabwean dollar was abandoned and till this day they still have no national currency, their people use currencies such as the US Dollar, the Pound sterling, or the Euro. Before the hyperinflation, the first Zimbabwean dollar was worth about $1.25. If the 100 trillion-dollar bill was worth that exchange rate, that single bill would be worth more money than there is in the entire world! But as ridiculous as this was, this is only considered to be the second-worst inflation in history after Hungary in 1946. Although Zimbabwe’s inflation peaked mid-November as of 2008, their overall highest monthly inflation was 79.6 billion percent which means prices doubled every 24.7 hours. Whereas Hungary’s highest monthly inflation took place in July 1946 which was 41.9 quadrillion percent with prices doubling every 15 hours. To put that in perspective, a country with a healthy inflation rate of around 3%, prices double every 23 years. In 1941, the exchange rate was about 5 Pengo to $1. In 1946, when the currency was discontinued, things had gotten so out of hand, that if you took every single banknote in the entire country, they would have a total value of one-tenth of a US Penny. Hungary then switched to the Fornit, where 1 Forint equaled 400 octillion Pengos. That number has 29 zeros!!! So, that’s why the government can’t just print money to pay off their debts, it does not end well. I’ll leave you with this final thought and what I think is possibly the best way to sum up why governments can’t just print unlimited amounts of money is &lt;em&gt;“If money grew on trees, wouldn’t it be as valuable as leaves?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Have you ever wondered why countries can’t just print more money to pay off their debts, to feed the homeless, to fix unemployment or for any other issue for that matter? This may seem like a rather silly question but I think it’s one of those questions that people may always wonder about but never ask. The answer can be summed up in just one word - inflation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spirituality and Marketing: An Amalgam</title><link href="/Spirituality-and-Marketing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spirituality and Marketing: An Amalgam" /><published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Spirituality-and-Marketing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Spirituality-and-Marketing">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Amalgam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is a highly inappropriate topic for the workplace, and only has an institutional connotation that manifests into the practice of rituals, adhering to dogmas and attending services. Spirituality, on the other hand, deals with life’s deeper motivations and an emotional connection to God and is a highly appropriate subject for discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that the world is smitten by the spirituality bug and marketing academics are oblivious of this development. Spirituality is increasingly impacting the beliefs and behaviours of consumers around the world. A &lt;em&gt;USA Weekend&lt;/em&gt; poll conducted in July 1998 revealed that 47% of Americans viewed spirituality as the most important element of their happiness. They care deeply about ecology and saving the planet, about relationships, peace, social justice, along with authenticity, self-actualisation, spirituality, and self-expression. They tend to be both inner-directed and socially concerned; they want to be activists, volunteers, and contributors to good causes. It’s 2020 and there is a massive influx of spiritual information, currently crowding the pages of popular newspapers, television programmes, and the glossiest mainstream magazines. Meditation classes are offered at the United Nations, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi uses visualisations and relaxation techniques to inspire the world, while political matters of spiritual and religious importance are the frequent subjects of public questioning and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have increasingly begun to use marketing as a spiritual practice to delve into a deeper wisdom, product offerings, and how they can help clients solve their problems. No jargon, no gimmicks, no trickery, just a deeper ‘wisdom’ in their marketing. Companies have started to use collaborative methods to co-vision with what the customer wants and help them see beyond their limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The root of spiritual marketing is clarity - the unwavering perception of how to do self-promotion. If you are clear about what you want and what you offer, your prospective customers will instantly know whether or not you offer what they need. A deep appreciation for a clear pricing strategy because consumers know the rule, &lt;em&gt;“if you have to ask how much, you probably can’t afford it”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have realised that spirituality is the human response to God’s gracious call to a one-on-one relationship with Him. Therefore, companies encourage customers to trust the transfer of their (profitable) divine goals and perceptions. What follows is a spiritual bond between the two parties where neither can survive without the other, built on a dynamic system of data projections from both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Big Fat Business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has mainstream spirituality gained popularity, but it has also become a big business. New age spirituality is a multi-billion-dollar industry, and some of the most popular contemporary spiritual teachers and gurus are among the wealthiest people in the world. Right from &lt;em&gt;“You can deprive the body, but the soul needs chocolate”&lt;/em&gt; to ‘Yoga-inspired athletic wear’ line of products, established companies and secular corporate firms are increasingly using spiritual appeals to identify and bond with consumers. It is one of the fast-growing industries. India’s estimated spiritual and religious market is over $30 billion. Studies have found that women comprise two-thirds of the active spiritual market consumers, particularly high income, educated, and middle-aged females but the men and youth market is also growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali  and Art of Living’s line of body care products and brands have created a niche for themselves in the market. The ageing of consumers in the western and Indian societies, coupled with their level of affluence, now permits them and the business community the luxury of seeking more meaning in their lives. Organisations like these are widening their reach in the production and distribution of these consumer goods. Furthermore some of these have entered into backward integration to source raw material as well. Once sold only at their &lt;em&gt;ashrams&lt;/em&gt; or particular outlets, today they can be found online or in supermarkets or even in &lt;em&gt;kirana&lt;/em&gt; stores. While FMCG companies need to invest a lot of time, effort, and money in branding and advertising their products, these spiritual gurus already have a huge number of devotees as their loyal consumer base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s to no surprise that such companies come up with unique, targeted and sound vocabulary and phraseology: “oneness”, “loving ourselves”, “we deserve”, “meditation”, “letting go”, “touching the void” among many others. Such marketing campaigns give an exotic edge, help unfurl competitive advantages, pep-up the spiritual image of the company, and facilitate the psychological transfer of ethics. Having a deep connection with clients and the community is what makes these business marketing techniques work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Magical World with Less Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the paucity of research on the topic of spirituality, bountiful opportunities and several interesting issues could be researched. For example, does the incidence of spirituality match with global macro-economic trends and how would these trends impact consumer behaviour and marketing practices? What is the relationship between rising incomes and economic development with the propagation of spiritually inspired ideas? Is spirituality increasingly used as a means of identity preservation and as a reaction to deterritorialisation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain these dynamics in the marketplace would require both strong qualitative and quantitative research. Scales that measure spirituality may be engineered by incorporating spiritual variables comprising both beliefs and practices. The need is to comprehensively conceptualise the concept of spirituality and delimit its boundaries so that its conflation with the concept of religion is not misunderstood and fairly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authentic spirituality is non-conceptual, and this presents a serious dilemma for spirituality in marketing for most of what attracts people is conceptual. Therefore, most authentic companies strike a balance between marketing and propagating non-conceptual bias, so that there is enough conceptualisation to hook people, but not too much to badly interfere with the marketing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said more simply, companies are all doing something inside themselves that is creating their outer results. Their inner state of being is creating their business or lack of it. Their inner spirit is doing their marketing. To paraphrase the famous Swiss psychologist Carl Jung, &lt;em&gt;“Until you make the unconscious conscious, it will direct your life and you will call it fate”.&lt;/em&gt; If you don’t consciously select where you want to go, you go where your unconscious wants you to go. Companies are having a great time skewing our unconscious minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today, spirituality in marketing is still a slippery construct, and only a systematic segmentation program of inquiry will provide meaningful and actionable insights. It’s a mystery yet, but if the business invests in its spiritual aspect, it will reap many unanticipated rewards, both financially and by gaining joy and bliss in doing their own business.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mehul Goyal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Amalgam</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?</title><link href="/Scottish-Independence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?" /><published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Scottish-Independence</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Scottish-Independence">&lt;p&gt;One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel Farage has often suggested that it would be illogical for Scotland to vote to become an independent country under Sturgeon’s leadership because a Scottish National Party (SNP) government would simply choose to pool Scottish sovereignty with Brussels instead of Westminster by re-joining the EU. Regardless of whether Farage’s point holds water, it might be more pertinent to turn his insight on its head: it was illogical, downright delusional in fact, to say Westminster would be totally sovereign over British laws after Brexit, because Parliament still governs the country alongside the regional assemblies in Edinburgh, Cardiff and Belfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-governance with the regional assemblies has been shown to be discordant ample times since ‘Brexit Day’ in January. The differing rules on the coronavirus lockdowns in the four nations of the UK have been immensely confusing, frequently smacking of plain political one-upmanship rather than proper scientific enquiry. On Brexit, it looks as if Sturgeon might disregard the government’s Internal Markets Bill and pass her own trade legislation, calling Johnson’s bill “a full-frontal assault on devolution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a constitutional expert, so I can’t say with certainty whether Sturgeon is right about that. But if the bill does in fact not represent overreach from Westminster, then part of the reason that Sturgeon can assert something which isn’t true is the fact that many of the terms of the relationship between Westminster and the devolved assemblies are poorly defined, arbitrary and hopelessly vulnerable to the transient whims of public opinion. Whilst most members of the commentariat have been focusing on making our relationship with the Europeans as stable and fruitful as possible, major instabilities within the British constitution have been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three devolved Parliaments are not like American state governments, the rights and jurisdictions of which are clearly laid out in the Constitution. If a state believes the Federal Government has overstepped the mark, the Supreme Court refers to the Constitution to assess whether overreach has occurred. All states have the same powers, and state governments are just as inherent a part of the US governance as the Federal government in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliaments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland, by contrast, were all created at different times, and all have slightly different powers. The devolved Parliaments can have their powers altered by the British government as long as the sitting Prime Minister desires it, and has a parliamentary majority to help him. After the Scottish independence referendum, David Cameron promised the Scots “devo-max”, as a way of responding to the close nature of the result. As a gesture of goodwill, he simultaneously enhanced the powers of the Welsh Assembly, but not to the same degree as the Scottish Parliament. However, he offered no explanation for why the Assembly in Cardiff would remain less powerful, or why he had interpreted nationalist fervour in Scotland as a clear sign that the Welsh were on the brink of drifting somewhere into the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the three Parliaments and its mothership in London resembles a rickety old building, the roof of which boasts a series of asymmetric and poorly built extensions. If a constitutional revolution did happen in Britain after 1945, it was devolution, not joining the EU. Random and arbitrary devolution has inhibited Westminster from governing the entire country far more than the European Commission ever did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, dysfunctionality doesn’t make the Scottish Parliament unconstitutional; the British Constitution is malleable and unwritten, which makes it much easier to change than the US Constitution. Ted Heath’s Tory government pooled our sovereignty with the Europeans in 1972 with a simple act of Parliament, thereby changing the British Constitution overnight. But just because something is constitutional doesn’t mean it works well. It doesn’t make it a good idea. The Internal Market Bill won’t be the last time that there are impasses in the years ahead, because the mandates of the Parliaments’ clash and their powers are far too easy to change. I’ve focused on Scotland here, but the potential for disaster in Northern Ireland is just as obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does the Prime Minister enter into the picture in all of this? He’s certainly having a torrid time dealing with Scotland at present. One year into his premiership, it’s obvious that he has few guiding principles. In truth, you didn’t need a year to see this. Whether Johnson’s love for the expedient would extend to advocating independence for Scotland is unlikely. But, privately at least, he must have clocked that not having to listen to those loudmouths over Hadrian’s Wall would definitely make his life easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like the job he’s doing (I count myself among you, by the way), then you might conclude you don’t mind that a by-product of our constitutional disorder is Johnson’s failure to deliver on his manifesto. What is worrying though, is that far from enhancing democracy in our country, devolution is compounding an incipient feeling that Britain is now ungovernable. I don’t blame Sturgeon for this; there is nothing wrong with scrutinising the government and its legislation, but there is an ocean of difference between careful scrutiny and institutional collapse. The former, essential to any democracy, was traditionally the responsibility of the opposition parties, the House of Lords, and an independent judiciary. The country was governed reasonably well with just one government. Creating three regional Parliaments on a whim and handing them new powers arbitrarily has simply led to a pile-up of different mandates, rather than improving accountability. If many different governments squabble over the right to govern, none of them &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; govern. In handing back power to our domestic governments, Brexit seems poised to unleash a crisis of democratic legitimacy far greater in severity than even itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paradiplomacy: A Catalyst for the Government?</title><link href="/Paradiplomacy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paradiplomacy: A Catalyst for the Government?" /><published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Paradiplomacy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Paradiplomacy">&lt;p&gt;We live in a highly globalised world that is undergoing a continuous transformation. That dynamism is especially true in the case of a modern state. The necessity to keep up with the dynamism creates space for a nation-state to employ modern tools to achieve its national interests. Modern states use such tools, for instance, soft power and public diplomacy, in foreign policy. Even as the primary objectives of diplomacy, the security of the state needs to be decided and implemented by the central authority, while other objectives can be implemented by a decentralised authority. One such decentralised tool of foreign policy is &lt;em&gt;paradiplomacy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Paradiplomacy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy can be defined as “foreign policy capacity of sub-state entities, their participation, independent of their metropolitan state, in the international arena in pursuit of their own specific international interests”. Therefore, paradiplomacy involves states (sub-unit of a country; not to be confused with nation-states) and cities as principal actors. Paradiplomacy, in contrast to the conventional foreign policy, makes space for the subnational units to engage in international relations in order to promote their own interests. Paradiplomacy, therefore, acts as a complement to a country’s efforts in carrying out its foreign policy. While the act of paradiplomacy is carried out by many sub-state actors across the world, the phenomenon is much more evident in federal states (e.g. the US and Canada) because the state units have a greater degree of autonomy. One such instance occurred in the US after President Donald Trump decided to withdraw from the Paris Climate Accord. Immediately after the decision was announced, twelve state governors came together to form the United States Climate Alliance to implement the Paris Agreement. 400 mayors across the US have also independently endorsed the accord on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is it Significant?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of paradiplomacy is significant for many reasons. One reason is that any agreement signed by the Central/Federal government cannot be successfully implemented without the cooperation of the state governments. Making the state governments a part of such discussion can yield better results. A second argument for paradiplomacy comes from the perspective of states bordering other countries. It is imperative for the border states to have better connections with their neighbouring countries. Any dispute that arises between two nations can be fruitfully resolved by engaging the border states in the discussions because most of the time these states either have grievances with or interests in solving disputes with the neighbouring nations. Another reason is that by letting the states engage in issues that deal with ‘low policy’, which include environmental issues, investment promotion, cultural and educational exchange, and more, a sense of competition could be fostered among the said states, and eventually, this would lead to better governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy in India is chaotic and less orderly. This is because the Indian Constitution gives the Central government exclusive control over all the matters pertaining to foreign affairs. It is interesting to note that the state governments, legally, are not even allowed to participate in any international conferences. There is no mechanism that allows the states to directly engage with international players. However, since the mid-1990’s, the state governments began to play a crucial role in foreign affairs. Two events facilitated this to happen. The first is the series of economic reforms launched by the Narasimha Rao government, and the second is the beginning of an era of coalition politics in the Indian political landscape. With the regional parties playing a significant role in the formation of the Central government, they started asserting themselves more vociferously; travelling abroad, entering into agreements, and signing memoranda of understanding independently. However, all such agreements still require the approval of the Central government to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;N Chandrababu Naidu, the former Chief Minister of Andhra Pradesh, travelled extensively across the world to sell the idea of Hyderabad as a technological hub and to attract foreign investments into the state. He travelled as many as six times in the nine years (1995-2004) that he was in power in the state. He succeeded in his effort as Microsoft established their office in Hyderabad and the Indian School of Business established their first-ever branch in India in Hyderabad. In 2014, after the partition of the state, upon becoming the Chief Minister once again, he visited Singapore and signed agreements to develop the new state’s capital. Gujarat is another state that has played a key role in the international arena. Narendra Modi, the then Chief Minister of Gujarat, had launched ‘Vibrant Gujarat’ which was a biennial summit with an objective of attracting foreign direct investments into the state. The summit has been a huge success since its launch, with many international dignitaries visiting the summit. It has also become a place for other Indian states to pitch themselves to various international actors. Apart from this, Narendra Modi, taking a cue from the Indian “Look East” policy, had travelled extensively to China, Japan, and Singapore to attract investments. More recently, the Gujarat government has signed a sister-city agreement for cooperation between Ahmedabad and Guangzhou city, in the Guangdong province in China. Furthermore, Telangana, another South Indian state, has also been playing a pivotal role too. Its success can be gauged from the fact that some of the world’s largest tech companies like Facebook, Apple, Microsoft and Amazon have their campuses in Telangana. The state had also signed sister-state agreements with New Jersey and California to extend cooperation ranging from investment promotion to tackling climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these are some of the positive developments, there are also some negatives that resulted due to the extra ‘enthusiasm’ of the states that proved deadly to India. One example is how West Bengal had stalled the Teesta river water treaty between India and Bangladesh. When the two countries had reached an agreement, it could not be signed due to stern opposition from the West Bengal Chief Minister Mamata Banerjee. Another example emerges from Tamil Nadu. When the United States moved a resolution at the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) against Sri Lanka seeking accountability for the horrific excesses of the country’s forces against the minority Tamil population, the Indian government facing pressure from the Tamil Nadu government, had to support the resolution. This had pushed Sri Lanka to move closer to China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy provides a framework for sub-national actors to assert themselves better. It effectively acts as a bridge between globalisation and regionalisation. For the Indian states too, there is a vast potential that the Indian states can exploit using paradiplomacy. Indian states until now have only been concerned with the economic aspect of paradiplomacy. They can also enter into agreements in the fields of tourism promotion, cultural exchange and urban planning. They can also enter into student exchange programs on behalf of public universities in their respective states, which will act as a mechanism for the Indian students to get exposed to bigger platforms or opportunities. Indian states can leverage their potential and use paradiplomacy to catalyse economic growth. All that is needed is the political will to act.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">We live in a highly globalised world that is undergoing a continuous transformation. That dynamism is especially true in the case of a modern state. The necessity to keep up with the dynamism creates space for a nation-state to employ modern tools to achieve its national interests. Modern states use such tools, for instance, soft power and public diplomacy, in foreign policy. Even as the primary objectives of diplomacy, the security of the state needs to be decided and implemented by the central authority, while other objectives can be implemented by a decentralised authority. One such decentralised tool of foreign policy is paradiplomacy.</summary></entry></feed>