<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-07T04:00:55+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Behind the Veil of Economic Growth</title><link href="/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behind the Veil of Economic Growth" /><published>2019-02-07T03:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T03:57:00+00:00</updated><id>/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth">&lt;p&gt;India’s short period of fast economic growth has been considerably eulogized. We are now the fastest growing economy in the world—an achievement that we pat ourselves on the back for. Yet, this shred of data is difficult to embrace after being a witness to ground realities. The rapid growth has manifested itself in a plethora of opportunities for many while leaving many others in conditions that seem to be helpless. One can’t help but feel something’s amiss in the “Indian Growth Story” narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the 21st century, there will be 1.5 billion Indians and 1.1 billion Chinese. Simply as a consequence of the number of people, India will continue to be among the world’s biggest economic powers. This will hold true even if the economy stagnates sometime in the future, or even if India’s efforts to become a middle-income country fall behind. In fact, we could be the largest economy with slightly more than two-thirds of China’s current per capita GDP by that time. It is well established that economic prosperity doesn’t imply people lead satisfied lives. The aspect which has failed to come to the forefront is how rapid economic growth doesn’t necessarily translate to better living standards. Their relationship hinges on how the government employs public revenue generated from economic growth. Unless the expenditure facilitates advancement in human capabilities, it isn’t really ‘growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While India is climbing up the ladder of per capita income, it is slipping down when it comes to social indicators. Public revenue generated from economic growth has not been used to expand social and physical infrastructure in a well-planned manner. While the middle and upper-middle classes have fared extremely well in terms of improved standards of living during the last three decades, the same cannot be said for those employed in the informal sector, who make up to 81% of India’s 487 million person workforce. For them, the pace of growth has been excruciatingly slow. Growth in real wages for poorer sections of the population has been severely lacking when compared to other developing economies. The reason lies in the failure to generate adequate employment, in what is best described as “jobless growth”. Rapid economic growth was led by the services sector. Since growth was concentrated in skill-intensive sectors rather than labour-intensive sectors, the educated labour force has been able to earn much higher wages and salaries. The rest of the workforce is employed in activities where wages and productivity have remained very low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official poverty estimates tell us that the poverty rate in the country has nearly halved in the ten years between 2006 and 2016. This appears to be a huge leap at first. However, as the density effect explains, since there are so many people just a little below the poverty line in India, a tiny increase in per capita income is enough to lift large numbers above the poverty line. It also explains why the official poverty line is so low (₹32 per day for rural India and ₹47 per day for urban India, which is equivalent to less than a US dollar per day). One may argue that India cannot rely on income growth alone to transform living conditions. But, the concern remains that India is not doing well in many respects even in comparison with some of the poorest countries in the world. India’s Human Development Index (HDI) ranking is 130 out of 189 countries, with a score of 0.64. Moreover, when inequality-adjusted HDI is considered, this value further falls by another 26.8%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “big brother” of the South Asian subcontinent is falling behind every other South Asian country in terms of many social indicators, notwithstanding it does much better in the growth of per capita income. Despite being much poorer than India, Bangladesh does better in terms of life expectancy, Infant Mortality Rate (IMR), immunization rates, Total Fertility Rate (TFR) and access to improved sanitation. It also fares better in the data on mean years of schooling and female literacy. Perhaps more intriguing is the case of Nepal, a country enmeshed in unstable politics and governance. In 1990, Nepal was severely lagging behind in terms of every development indicator. Over the years it has caught up with India and even overtaken it in maternal mortality, infant immunization, and female literacy. The comparison with Pakistan is more favourable to India, but not particularly flattering either. In 1990, only Sri Lanka had better social indicators than India. Now India appears to be the second worst in the region, ahead of Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although India is the poorest among the BRICS countries, much more needs to be done to bridge these gaps than to catch up in terms of per capita income. When compared with other BRICS countries which have the commonality of large populations, India lags abysmally behind in every social indicator, especially undernourishment among children below 5, child immunization rates, and universal literacy. Experiences within the country itself have been starkly contrasting. The Multi-Dimensional Poverty Index (MPI) places the North Indian states of Bihar and Jharkhand in the same category as Mozambique and Sierra Leone. However, the growth model in states like Kerala, Himachal Pradesh and Tamil Nadu continue to serve as examples of how economic growth can be complemented with sustained successful social policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What clearly works for rapid social progress is the universal provision of essential public services: school education, primary health care, electricity connections, sanitation and drinking water. Their provision has to be facilitated by an efficient administration that takes into account the structure of social inequality in the area while ensuring the involvement of local communities. Among BRICS countries, India is the only one that hasn’t gone through a phase of expansion of public support (elementary education, health care, social security) or economic redistribution. It also has the lowest expenditure on education and health, which have yet again taken a back seat in the face of a populist budget. The nation has much to learn from the policies and achievements of two of its neighbouring countries. From Bangladesh, it must learn female literacy programmes, microcredit and community mobilization to bring about social change. And from Sri Lanka, it should adopt the health care and public schooling system. India can have a serious advantage over these countries in implementing these same programmes. As Amartya Sen phrased it, “A poor country may have less money to spend on healthcare but it also needs to spend less to provide the same labour-intensive services.” Healthcare and education are primarily labour-intensive activities. Since wages are low in populous and poor India, these community building services can be provided at low costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about the nature of economic growth require much greater attention than they receive. Recently, a leaked government report put India’s unemployment rate on a 45-year high. Prominent NSSO employees (the institution who had prepared the report) had resigned in protest because the government was not releasing the report. The government’s reply to the leaked report? “You can’t be growing at 7.2% and say no jobs are being created.” A discussion on India’s economy lacks sufficient inquiry on the provision of jobs to the 1 million people who reach working age &lt;i&gt;every month&lt;/i&gt;, or the transparency on data for economic indicators, or the massive improvement required in malnutrition indicators. Unless we end our obsession with GDP numbers, we cannot expect our governments to focus on social indicators. After all, what a democratic system achieves depends largely on the issues that are brought into political engagement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reema Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">India’s short period of fast economic growth has been considerably eulogized. We are now the fastest growing economy in the world—an achievement that we pat ourselves on the back for. Yet, this shred of data is difficult to embrace after being a witness to ground realities. The rapid growth has manifested itself in a plethora of opportunities for many while leaving many others in conditions that seem to be helpless. One can’t help but feel something’s amiss in the “Indian Growth Story” narrative.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should Family Come First?</title><link href="/Should-Family-Come-First" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should Family Come First?" /><published>2019-02-07T03:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T03:46:00+00:00</updated><id>/Should-Family-Come-First</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Should-Family-Come-First">&lt;p&gt;The institution of family lies at the foundation of every society on Earth. But in India, it is so much more than just a foundation, family is the sustenance and the bane, the crutch and the agony of all festivals and all funerals, all of society and all of culture. But even when it’s a pain, it’s a pain we do not know how to live without. What seems overbearing and out of line in most cultures is the norm in Indian families. Indian families, with their little comprehension of space and boundaries, constantly barge, intrude and critique. From the ‘aunties’ glaring at exposed cleavages to the uncles who are making matches on marital websites, Indian families have never believed in hesitation. No advice is ever unsolicited. But there is something to say of the large joint families with people constantly milling around the house, the warm grandmothers with their secret recipes and the numberless siblings and cousins. There is something to say of the tightly knit structure of Indian households with an abundance of canopies of comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ever-presence and the intrusions are symbols of a certain type of familiarity; a manifestation and reminder of a claim, of a sanction given long ago in the pages of history. Families lay a claim over us, over our mental and spiritual selves, over our sense of being. These claims perhaps go a long way in making us feel loved, because who else would intrude and scold and worry except those who want to keep us safe and invest in us. Even though it might feel like an encroachment upon autonomy, it certainly has a warmth to it, a charm not found in western homes, which let go. India’s collective inability to let go is rooted in our love, our ever-holding-on, unwilling-to-be-apart love; it is rooted in the way we have been brought up: our values of butting in, and pointing out, and determining for others, what’s best for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the present generation and its streak of rebellion against family and tradition, familial bonds continue to be magnificent and powerful, encroaching and unjust, bustling with its magic and unwavering in its unfairness. These bonds become crucial because of increasing isolationism and the interference of ego in relationships, which make “enforcement and encroachment” necessary. Even when the connection is an enforced one, at least there is some degree of retention of connectedness. The presence of any support system, even if it is far from ideal, is better than having nothing but a dreary 1BHK to come back to. The price of complete autonomy is a high one, one that we Indians are yet to pay. Yet, is their romanticism in our narrative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value that comes out of family and the revered Indian lens through which it is viewed should not blind us to the problems that manifest as a result of the “family structure” being placed on a pedestal. The narratives of queer individuals, of women and of children cannot be pushed to the sidelines. It is easy to look at the cheery side of families and ignore the harshness. This attempt at pretence is easy, almost second nature to us. Growing up, we Indians imbibe a lesson from the world around us; that the front we put up for the world to see is far, far more important than what really goes on. India lives in a world in which the publicity of injustice wounds one more than the injustice itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Indian may dismiss abuse and torture of women as isolated incidents, not as crimes committed by depraved people not fit to engage with civilised society. Abuse doesn’t pop out of a void or only lurk in alleys. It stems from the idea of patriarchal entitlement over the bodies and decisions of women. It is in a household that this &lt;em&gt;entitlement&lt;/em&gt; begins and heightens, and manifests in the worst forms. There is a misguided sense of ownership men feel they have over the women in their families, and society just accepts that, which is why violence against women by family members does not scandalise one’s idea of social propriety or elicit the same response that violence by an outsider would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The false idea that familial ties lend some form of ownership over another human’s body is fed and drilled into one ever since childhood. India is a nation that is still far from even frowning upon children being hit by the elders of the family. Beyond the physical and emotional ramifications, hitting children also instills in them the idea that they have only partial autonomy over their bodies. It teaches children the lesson that bodily autonomy, while otherwise a valid concept, loses all ground when inside the house. This leads to toxic ideas of ownership which in turn leads to a path of denying oneself victimhood in the face of abuse, because if it’s family how wrong can it really be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems lie with us as a society when we twist and bend our limits and thresholds for what is right and what is wrong in order to excuse and justify whatever family does. This stems from the family being glorified as sacred and notions of entitlement that equate familial love with ownership. One’s inability to open up about any kind of trauma, pain or even smaller complaints that have to do with family comes from the belief that family always comes first. “Family always comes first” sounds like a noble sentiment but it can be exploited to make individuals feel as though they have to dismiss the wrong done to them by their family members, family being first is extrapolated to make a person feel as if opening up about family problems in front of friends, teachers, or lovers is wrong, or a form of shameful betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this article is not to say that Indian society must abandon the family structure that glues together the fabric of its society, but to examine how we have been systematically taught to worship and &lt;i&gt;pedestalize&lt;/i&gt; this structure, the institution of family and the people who constitute it. All the problematic things with family life become even more problematic because when our assumption that families provide a safe space fails, there is no alternative safe space to fall back on. The friends, peers, and lovers that should act as a safe space do not, because it becomes very difficult for a victim to break that inner wall of shame and talk about family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sad part is that communities are meant to look after the well-being of its members, but we Indians have become obsessed with merely the “illusion of functionality”. We venerate the ‘structure’ so much that we want to protect it even at the cost of real humans and their very real lives. So long as the overhanging structures of marriage, parenthood, and households stay intact we don’t really care what happens to the cogs that make up the wheel. How is it still that we have not redefined our idea of brokenness, how is it that people get abused and children are driven to committing suicide but we still think it’s working?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love and abuse, on the surface, seem to be mutually exclusive. Two concepts, so contrary, so antithetical to each other that they can never be thought of as coexistent. How can one love their abuser? How obvious, right? But the relationship between the abuser and the abused is anything but obvious. The world and this great nation are littered with tales of how the two thrive together, grip and dig into each other. Maybe the nature of love is such that it is with great difficulty that one might stop loving their abuser, but third parties and well-wishers can go a long way in helping one. Talking about experiences surrounding family that are grim will lead to a much-needed counter-narrative that will finally paint abuse as abuse, whether physical or emotional, that will finally show family as human beings, capable of falling, capable of wrong, and not as oracles who can dictate morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the love that comes for parents and siblings is not as organic in nature as one would like to believe. A lot of it also comes from the narrative that is flashed around us, of how much we are &lt;i&gt;supposed&lt;/i&gt; to and are &lt;i&gt;obligated&lt;/i&gt; to love. The love that is regarded with so much veneration, the devotion towards parents that is thought of as moral accomplishment itself is manufactured by society, it does not arise as authentically as one would like to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading all of this one might ask, &lt;i&gt;so what&lt;/i&gt;? So what if the structure is a certain way that has both pros and cons? The answer lies in valuing family but not pedestalizing it. The answer lies in acknowledging how the family has cared for one whilst understanding that families are not incapable of wrongdoing and some families even inflict grave abuse and injustice. Asking a nation which is willed to throw-off all balance, to approach a middle path might seem counterproductive. A nation in which family is all or nothing, asking for a path that both loves and censures family is daunting in itself. But God knows we’ve needed it, we’ve needed the balance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stuti Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The institution of family lies at the foundation of every society on Earth. But in India, it is so much more than just a foundation, family is the sustenance and the bane, the crutch and the agony of all festivals and all funerals, all of society and all of culture. But even when it’s a pain, it’s a pain we do not know how to live without. What seems overbearing and out of line in most cultures is the norm in Indian families. Indian families, with their little comprehension of space and boundaries, constantly barge, intrude and critique. From the ‘aunties’ glaring at exposed cleavages to the uncles who are making matches on marital websites, Indian families have never believed in hesitation. No advice is ever unsolicited. But there is something to say of the large joint families with people constantly milling around the house, the warm grandmothers with their secret recipes and the numberless siblings and cousins. There is something to say of the tightly knit structure of Indian households with an abundance of canopies of comfort.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Anthropological Consideration of Ugandan Knuckles: Or, The Opiate for a Poisoned State</title><link href="/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Anthropological Consideration of Ugandan Knuckles: Or, The Opiate for a Poisoned State" /><published>2019-02-07T03:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T03:20:00+00:00</updated><id>/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles</id><content type="html" xml:base="/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles">&lt;p&gt;I know, dear reader, that you have thought of this before, as I have; there may, in fact, be far more to the Ugandan Knuckles meme than meets the eye. Could it be that in this chaotic, disorganised vision of a cultural dead space, this wellspring of enjoyment is reflective of our times far more than was initially thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles meme encompasses, in truth and upon further inspection, a highly complex social structure. It has a diaspora of ethnographically observed motifs spawned forth from its hierarchies, with inner conflicts and philosophical, spiritual quandaries levied against the outside world from the safe confines of VRChat. After all, the people propagating the meme remain, if anything, human. And so from them, we may examine human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, the acolytes of this subculture organise themselves into a diverse and very complicated hierarchy. It is quite hard to discern, but I believe Knuckles avatars sporting a blue skin as opposed to the common red are still part of the same clan, though there may be a position in the social system implied, which is possibly the &lt;em&gt;“Ugandan Warrior”&lt;/em&gt; class. These will protect the Queen (more on her later). Yellow skin is likely the mark of &lt;em&gt;“The Commander”&lt;/em&gt;, a high position seemingly not coveted but accepted with humility by new initiates. It is likely that they frequently cycle this position over a short term in office and they do this because their true calling is to form a party capable of locating a female monarch.
They operate under a Sacral Democratic Monarchy, for they elect a Queen and will follow this Queen under the belief that she will grant them sacred knowledge of &lt;em&gt;“The Way”&lt;/em&gt;. The requirements for this position are few and, at times, scant or plentifully observed depending on the weeaboo and anime fan presence in the Chat Room. She need only be female, Japanese idol-like (Hatsune Mikus are frequently accosted), or Moe – fluorescent-haired preferable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they find a Queen, they will fawn over her and begin to voice their contentment with an a-linguistic motif. This is ‘clucking’, a vocalized ‘clock’ sound, as an aspirated glottal &lt;em&gt;/’klɒk/&lt;/em&gt; made with the tongue behind the teeth (very culturally unique) and would be called in linguistic anthropology a non-verbal acoustic call, conveying emotion. If the Queen can be found to have led them astray, the roving pack of miniatures will engage in a ‘spitting’, to indicate their rejection of this false divine saviour. They demand respect for the Queen, crave her love but will also spit on her.
Unfortunately, Ugandan Knuckles politics is far too complex to outline here, but it is apparent that conflicts of interest are quite common. Splinter groups forming as different female players displaying a lolicon aesthetic are frequently happened upon and hailed, willingly or no, as the next holy monarch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the anthropology of religion, The Divine Right, or Holy Mandate to rule is a frequently observed feature of cultures on planet earth where church and state are one. We might point in this case to the cause of such a phenomenon seen here with this meme format being a growing atheistic worldview in our society. As we feel a detachment from the spirit, we see the humorous taking on the responsibility of the severe, in a nervous rebuttal of the empty, godless nation-state. For how can we have faith in leaders who possess no faith themselves? Of course, such practices in the West date back to pre-Christian, Pagan Europe, a paradoxically dark, yet ethno-nationally enlightened time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles Clan members’ spiritual path, &lt;em&gt;“The Way”&lt;/em&gt;, is a nomadistic, possibly nihilistic, and devotional philosophy of the self defined by space and sovereignty tied to one’s destiny. In anthropological terms, this is a Durkheimian consideration of how society maintains coherence and integrity in the modern era, when traditionalism is lost and replaced by less organically defined economic, social institutions. A brother is kin, a member of the clan provides a sense of belonging, the love found in belonging to one’s nation allows for the fortitude necessary to sustain it. To ask, &lt;em&gt;“Why are you running?”&lt;/em&gt;, is to wonder how a friend can flee his destiny. Why doubt oneself? This exemplifies a unique rudimentary cultural Kismet ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles clans seek only to find meaning and satisfaction in their existence by being close to their Queen and their spiky brethren. This anthropological sense of self is defined as and functions by the mechanisms of Cultural Memory. If they find one of their flock to have strayed from &lt;em&gt;“The Way”&lt;/em&gt;, or to be in any manner unholy, they will voice sympathy and announce: &lt;em&gt;“We must pray for this one, my brothers”&lt;/em&gt;. Such camaraderie reflects a beauteous, shared heritage in shouldering the burden of life with one’s ethnocultural peers, a sentiment sadly lacking in today’s society, and it ought to be observed! One might say it is the trauma of meandering about, in search of one’s home which acts as what we call in anthropology a &lt;em&gt;“rite of passage”&lt;/em&gt;, serving the purpose of bonding together a generation of young men that they may go out into the world as brothers-in-arms—though this usually applies to something like the Mukanda ritual ceremony of the Ndembu people in Zambia, wherein young boys are taken away from the village at a certain age to have the extremities of their manhood cut-off. During this &lt;em&gt;“rite of passage”&lt;/em&gt;, young men enter what anthropologists call the Liminal State. In this state, young men are neither man nor child, which allows for the personal transformation of the self, body, and spirit. But how does this happen? Simple. To take from the famous adage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Gamers are the most oppressed group”.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the most cursory glance at &lt;em&gt;“Gamer Fashion”&lt;/em&gt;, a subset in the nomenclature formerly known as Gamer/Geek Culture (from which the Ugandan Knuckles ensued) has much to inform us. Gamer T-Shirts, which we will here be using as ethnographic evidence of their material culture, read thusly: &lt;em&gt;“Hey, SNOWFLAKE, there are only two genders, so get over it!”&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;“If you are reading this I’ll have you know I was forced to put my controller down and enter society”&lt;/em&gt;; or &lt;em&gt;“I’m a gamer, not because I don’t have a life, but because I choose to have many!”&lt;/em&gt;. Such a study clearly identifies these G-Fuelled, never-pulled, but-very-virile-in-the-season-pass plucky young miscreants. For these young men belong to the techno-fanatical, pseudo-radical, and pseudo-puritanical generation called Y-Z millennials. A less prudent man might cut themselves on this level of edginess, but not these brave souls, though they do face terrible hardship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, more articles have been published by various millennial plaintiffs decrying this Ugandan Knuckles meme, which they deem to be racist, therefore further displaying just how oppressed these poor, unfortunate outcast souls find themselves. Time and time again, they are dissatisfied with what their society gives them, as the West disowns itself with the neo-feminist, cultural-Marxist criticism of the post-colonial Occident. And yet still as they seek refuge, they are blasted in a flame war to light our skies in Cyberspace for generations. Down the line, they will speak of these days when the completed their “rite of passage”, as they do of the great Meme Wars, and tales of &lt;em&gt;“The Way”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“Pepe”&lt;/em&gt; alike will be told around pixelated campfires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the same, it ought not be forgotten that the creators of the 2010 Ugandan film &lt;em&gt;Who Killed Captain Alex?&lt;/em&gt;, having originated the quotes whose accents and manners were taken-on by the scarlet Ugandan Faithful have themselves endorsed the meme, sharing many iterations and supporting the sub-culture as best they can from their twitter page, @Wakaliwood. And really, it must not be omitted from the debate that in modern anthropological circles, the principle of Cultural Relativism posits that we should treat all cultures equally! And yet. And yet must this come at the expense of some cultures in favour of others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To speak as the Geek is to know the Geek; In the words of the ancient 10th-century Anglo-Saxon poem &lt;em&gt;The Wanderer&lt;/em&gt;, as repurposed into King Théoden’s monologue by J. R. R. Tolkien for his LOTR book &lt;em&gt;The Two Towers&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Where is the horse and the rider? &lt;br /&gt;
Where is the horn that was blowing? &lt;br /&gt;
They have passed like rain on the mountains, &lt;br /&gt;
like wind in the meadow. &lt;br /&gt;
The days have gone down in the West, &lt;br /&gt;
behind the hills... Into Shadow.”&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gentlemen, I say, in recalling the outcry and sensitivity previously observed within the Gaming community by the refrain, &lt;em&gt;“where is the justice for Harambe?”&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;“where is the respect due for this honourable and noble meme which may soon face oblivion?” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in observing such criticisms, this comes from the same media-climate as the cultural motifs which allowed and indeed enabled the late, bait, sombre-fated Gillette advert to happen, whence we see this same accusatory thought-process levelled against not only all white, cisgendered men but all men in general! Is it any wonder the self-removed would seek solace in the virtual arms of a neon-lit loli?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current cultural climate is unassertive, unsure and self-destructing. When a culture is diseased, it may find when turning around to scrub behind itself in the shower one day that oddly-formed but quite enigmatically defined growths in the shapes of secondary Sonic the Hedgehog characters have developed upon the rump! Visions beholding plagues of frogs reoccur…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then again, and from a laboratory perspective, the difference between a contemporary consideration of a “model society”, perhaps sat on a table as a maquette of what we might be (as envisioned by those who would have us constantly be in self-un-realisation) and a VR vat containing a vile, porous, clucking swarm of social parasites is that, scientifically speaking, such bacteria will eventually develop its own culture.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Morgan Black</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">I know, dear reader, that you have thought of this before, as I have; there may, in fact, be far more to the Ugandan Knuckles meme than meets the eye. Could it be that in this chaotic, disorganised vision of a cultural dead space, this wellspring of enjoyment is reflective of our times far more than was initially thought?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2001: A Metaphysical Odyssey</title><link href="/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2001: A Metaphysical Odyssey" /><published>2019-02-07T02:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T02:33:00+00:00</updated><id>/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey">&lt;p&gt;Stanley Kubrick has produced phenomenal works throughout his career. His relentless, unflinching approach to the subjects he chose certainly showed in his films and we cannot be thankful enough for his contribution to the art of filmmaking. That said, any further discourse on how great a filmmaker he was seems pointless to me as it has already been addressed umpteen times by several, far more accomplished personas at greater lengths. What I would prefer to bring under the microscope today is his magnum opus &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; and what lay at its heart. The film, which has now been minced to mere GIFs and iconic ringtones, was presumably his life’s most important and ambitious work, although I have no grounds to claim so. He started to work on &lt;em&gt;2001&lt;/em&gt; in 1964 after his overture to Arthur C. Clarke, who co-wrote the script for the film and authored a book of the same name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2001&lt;/em&gt; opens with a black screen and eerie music, giving a sense of void with all its horror. From the very beginning, Kubrick made sure he doesn’t send the wrong signal about this odyssey being just any sci-fi. This void was then succeeded by a scene of the camera rising up to behold the sun from beyond the edges of the moon and the Earth to the tune of Richard Strauss’ &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;. Now, this is where things get real. The use of &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; was no mere coincidence, and it should not be with someone as seminal as Kubrick. The extraordinary work by Friedrich Nietzsche at the dusk of his life was indeed the prime theme of the entire project, which Kubrick concurred to later on. And as for the scene in question, it was clearly the beckoning of the new morning that Nietzsche suggested in the book when he said, &lt;i&gt;“The noon when man stands the middle of his way between beast and Superman… a way to a new morning.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film primarily addresses three important themes: The Superman, Evolution and the Dionysian and Apollonian.
Now, if you’re familiar with these concepts you can avoid this paragraph and move on to the next, and if not I will walk you through them briefly. The Superman is a term coined not by DC comics but by Friedrich Nietzsche in his &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;. In it, he points out that it is not right for us to assume that evolution has ended. He argued that we are currently in the middle of our evolution, that we are the bridge between the hominids and the far superior Superman. Nietzsche declares in his book: &lt;i&gt;“What is ape to man? A laughing stock or a painful embarrassment. And man shall be that to the Superman: a laughing stock and painful embarrassment.”&lt;/i&gt; Nietzsche says his future Supermen would have their own values, being independently-minded, and forging their own path. These Supermen will accept the fact that they might need to hurt people for the sake of great things, that selfishness isn’t a vice but a necessity. They won’t despise the success of others and will accept suffering as a means to good things. They will also bear the cross of loneliness as a price for their hard nature. They will be gentle towards the weak because of their consciousness of their own strength and will exult at their capabilities. The other Nietzschean concepts, the Dionysian and Apollonian, are paradigms of human nature. The Dionysian engages in revelry, wine, and dance, in chaos and irrationality, he is instinctive and emotional; the Apollonian, on the other hand, is cultured, intellectual, engaging with logic and rationality, and wise and controlled. Finally there is evolution: while it is clear that our ancestors were Dionysian and we have evolved to be Apollonian, according to Nietzsche, we would further evolve to find the sublime balance between these two ideologies to forge our own paths.
Kubrick held Nietzsche in high regard and took dear to his views almost devoutly. He too believed that we are not at the end of evolution and must march forward to acquire greater psychological abilities. And even though many have foreseen machinery to be the biggest possible threat to humanity, Kubrick believed there’s nothing that our species cannot conquer given our superior psychological faculty, be it the leopards that once ambushed and attacked the apes or be it an artificially intelligent computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film starts at the dawn of mankind, when the ape-men amid their daily struggles to survive  and maintain their territory,  witnessed the first of four monoliths that supposedly changed the course of their lives. It bestowed them with the idea of using bones as weapons— this is Kubrick subtly asserting that violence underpins basic human nature. The second monolith is unearthed in the Moon, suggesting that humans are ready for their advent toward the next stage of evolution, to acquire the next level of intelligence. And thus the journey begins; the quiet and long journey which Kubrick infallibly filmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, the audience felt the tediousness of the journey. This is also the part where we come across the iconic Hal 9000 which till date is a big reference in pop culture. This artificially intelligent computer was given to monitor and supervise the journey but it all changed when it started making a few mistakes stoking doubts in the minds of the two other passengers – Dave and Frank - about its reliability. What follows is an epochal scene where Dave and Frank discuss in private in a pod bay about their plans to disconnect Hal which Hal oversees through the glass door of the pod bay. Dave first shows the signs of a Superman when he lets go of Frank to enter the spaceship himself without a moment’s trepidation. He sacrificed his colleague for the greater cause. When Dave struggled his way into the spaceship, he without delay hurried to disconnect Hal despite the constant pleadings from Hal, who tried to convince Dave into not disconnecting him.  Later, whilst he was disconnecting Hal, there was a moment when Dave took dear to Hal’s pleas and responded in kindness, knowing Hal’s final moments were soon approaching. Dave was gentle towards the weak Hal, even if he was ‘killing’ him, being aware of his own superiority. Dave personified independency of mind, being willing to act on his own accord even though he remained alone in the entire spaceship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the neoclassical room we see Dave, ageing and perishing in front of our eyes, approaching his final moments at the bridge, taking the next and final step towards evolution when he extends his hand toward the fourth monolith like Adam did in the painting, &lt;em&gt;Creation of Adam&lt;/em&gt; by Michelangelo. Nietzsche, through his character Zarathustra, says in his magnum opus, &lt;i&gt;“I love him who willeth the creation of something beyond himself and then perisheth.”&lt;/i&gt; Dave gives in to something greater than himself, he is the Star child on his deathbed. &lt;em&gt;Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; is about going beyond good and evil, it is Kubrick’s take on how we must evolve and embrace the Superman within in a future that may not be so far away.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Stanley Kubrick has produced phenomenal works throughout his career. His relentless, unflinching approach to the subjects he chose certainly showed in his films and we cannot be thankful enough for his contribution to the art of filmmaking. That said, any further discourse on how great a filmmaker he was seems pointless to me as it has already been addressed umpteen times by several, far more accomplished personas at greater lengths. What I would prefer to bring under the microscope today is his magnum opus 2001: A Space Odyssey and what lay at its heart. The film, which has now been minced to mere GIFs and iconic ringtones, was presumably his life’s most important and ambitious work, although I have no grounds to claim so. He started to work on 2001 in 1964 after his overture to Arthur C. Clarke, who co-wrote the script for the film and authored a book of the same name.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Picture of Dorian Gray</title><link href="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Picture of Dorian Gray" /><published>2019-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray">&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest
compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as
I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of
St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a
composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could
distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s
&lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of
&lt;em&gt;Die Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Figaro&lt;/em&gt; with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker
dramas, &lt;em&gt;The Turn of the Screw&lt;/em&gt; or perhaps &lt;em&gt;Owen Wingrave&lt;/em&gt;. I was mistaken. It
took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking
some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera
into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many
more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s
effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act
show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its
completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the
public by the wonderful people at &lt;em&gt;LoveOpera&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, no small part of me is turned towards retrospection: three years ago,
almost to the day of writing, I was asked by Jay Wolfe of &lt;em&gt;The Wolfian&lt;/em&gt; to write
a small article on the subject of setting about composing something of this
magnitude. I did my best – I had, at that point, only just finished &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;’s
Prologue (the –and-a-half act) and had only vague ideas what the rest of the
opera had in store for me. Nevertheless, I now look back upon that article and
see that there is a compositional thread that stayed with me throughout the
process, even from the pre-Foxian beginnings. I knew then as I know now that
Wilde’s novella brought together the myriad elements of philosophy, dark humour,
and gothic horror. Musically, that meant each of these strands had to be
individually emphasised without any single one dominating the general effect of
the music. Of course, this was no easy task. But I did find a solution, if I can
really claim to have one. I studied closely how the likes of Henry Purcell,
Benjamin Britten, Claude Debussy, and Richard Wagner musically synthesised
various themes in their operas. I also made it a point to follow the man
himself: Oscar Wilde, taking note of how he balanced these themes to create such
a fine piece of art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that there is a fortunate divide between the Prologue of the work and the
two Acts. It is a divide that I touched on in my previous article: much of the
dialogue of the Prologue, taken from the first two chapters of Wilde’s work,
consists of Basil, the painter, philosophising with his friend Lord Henry, the
prime corruptive influence upon young Dorian before the boy actually arrives to
kick-start the drama. This leads to moments of the Prologue that feel somewhat
slower than the rest of the show, a turgid calm before a hopefully more driving
roller-coaster of a storm. And I believe this is as it should be, but I may well
be wrong – I shall have to see after I hear from the audiences in July and
September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as the previous article focussed so heavily upon the Prologue, on
account of the fact that neither of the other two acts actually yet existed, I
feel it may be much more suitable for us now to turn ourselves to a brief
musical guided tour, as it were, through at least some of the show. Therefore,
some introductions must be made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; has a main cast of six – it was quite a task to reduce down the large,
high-society focused drama into six characters, but what else is a chorus for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The characters are, in order of appearance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basil Hallward, (tenor) - the artist who holds Dorian as his muse,
unfortunately;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Henry “Harry” Wotton, (baritone) - a modern-day Mephistopheles with a
heart, somewhere deep down in there;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dorian himself, (mezzo-soprano) - I had this idea when watching Mozart’s
&lt;em&gt;Marriage of Figaro&lt;/em&gt; and realising Dorian and the teenage sex-pest Cherubino,
also a trouser-role, are not so very much alike if you gave the latter money and
immortality;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lady Victoria Wotton, (soprano) - aside from a few witty flashes in the novella,
Henry’s wife is reduced to acting off-screen, as it were. Jamie and I changed
that, as you will see;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sybil Vane, (soprano) – Poor Sybil. To fall in love with an as-yet not fully
corrupted Dorian, only to so quickly jilted after one bad night on the stage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Vane, (bass) – Sybil’s brother arrives in the 2nd Act, and will avenge his
sister… or, at least, he’ll try his utmost, raging best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind these six there comes a host of minor characters that make up our show’s
chorus: the society lords and ladies, the audience of a run-down theatre, the
whores and opium fiends that make up the rich tapestry that is Victorian London
in Oscar’s (and our) minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Act one begins, with Dorian, now in possession of Basil’s masterful
portrait of him, sitting alone in Lord Henry’s living-room, awaiting his friend.
It is here that I can illustrate the first influence of any of the composers
mentioned in my previous article: the act opens with a harp gesture (Fig. 1)
that is at once a textural back-cloth for the scene, and also acts as a
leitmotif, to borrow from Richard Wagner’s vocabulary. The theme, extended by
the strings and later the flute, can be said, therefore to be a genius loci – it
represents the building, musically, suggesting the luxurious, lavish
surroundings of the Wottons’ town-house. When, therefore, it reappears to
introduce use to Dorian’s own house, in both acts one and two, it possibly tells
us something about Dorian’s own following of Henry’s teachings – indeed, this
ability to manipulate melodies is an incredibly useful tool, compositionally, as
melodies are often indelibly linked with the emotion, location or character
alongside which they first appear. Thus, the twisting of a motif by introducing
it to a new context can suggest many things to an audience – watch out for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we hear Henry’s own leitmotif, languorous triplets in the horns, except
this time it isn’t Henry, but his wife, whom neither we nor Dorian are expecting
to see. She has some interesting things to say on the subject of Wagner, too: “I
like Wagner’s music more than anyone’s. It is so loud that one can talk the
whole time without other people hearing what you say!” (I must say, I hope no
one uses &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; to gossip under!) Nevertheless, as Victoria is here only for
some witty repartee and to avoid her husband at this point in the drama, when
Henry does finally show up she departs in short order – it’s not the healthiest
of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry’s real entrance is accompanied by a different sort of music, though. He’s
a little drunk, and announces himself with a lop-sided little fanfare, before
launching in a duettino of banter with Dorian, which again manipulates his own
triplet motif into some fast-paced patter, as Dorian tells us that he has fallen
in rapturously love with an actress, “a rather commonplace debut” as Henry puts
it, named Sybil Vane. This confession leads to the first overtly romantic music
of the evening, as Dorian narrates how he came across his new sweetheart in a
sequence that is, structurally, a reflection of the early-Verdian style of
cantabile-cabaletta, but turned entirely on its head: in Verdi, or indeed,
Donizetti or Bellini, a cantabile-cabaletta consists of (as the name suggests) a
slow, more relaxed section that is very ‘sing-able’ followed by a more
barnstorming or pyrotechnic section. However, here Dorian sings them the wrong
way ‘round: first a fast, rhythmically twisting section (Fig. 2) describing her
beauty, and then two slower sections discussing first her acting ability and
then how lost he is in the romance of it all (Fig. 3), before the scene peters
out, and we transition to the next night, at the theatre&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, the theatre scene. This was a lot of fun to devise – I recall Jamie
gesticulating wildly as he explained to me that this was to be no great work of
Shakespearean spectacle, but a farcical experience, with a wooden, nervous
Juliet and a stout, middle-aged Romeo with a bit too much gut and far too much
Brian Blessed. And in the midst of it all sits Dorian, trying desperately to
convince Henry and Basil that Sybil is, in truth, a wonderful actress and well
worth his love. Therefore, I put my comedy hat on, and have tried to construct a
woeful imitation of Gilbert and Sullivan as an overture to this
play-within-a-play. There is no emotional core to this moment, no attempt to tug
at the heart-strings as one would expect from an overture to a performance of
&lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt;. It’s just dross. As is the acting that follows it, but for
that I had to get more creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I set up a sense of scurrying tension within the on-stage audience by way
of a tiny fragment of melody that, when repeated over and over, becomes an
ostinato-texture which, much like the harp motif of Fig. 1, serves as a backdrop
for the entire scene. Over this, both our trio and the on-stage audience mutter
between each other until the curtain comes up and we see a sequence of three
scenes from the play, each successively worse: steadily, we progress from thin,
dull orchestration and bad singing, add in meandering, meaningless chromaticism
and unstable harmonies, and finally top it all off with some bombastic as the
crowd get steadily more unimpressed with the performance (Fig. 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I write quite good ‘bad’ music, sometimes…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, Basil and Henry resolve to leave before the end of the show and
leave Dorian behind to talk to poor Sybil. Poor Sybil who is, in point of fact,
much more vivacious in real life than she ever was on stage, and so very much in
love with Dorian, as illustrated by her motif, which is itself an extension of
Dorian and the portrait’s own melody (Fig. 5, showing Dorian’s melody on top,
and Sybil’s extension below it), before flourishing into a much more lush
romantic gesture, and finally a re-hashing of one of Dorian’s own earlier
cantabile sections. She is so consumed by what could kindly be called her
infatuation or, worse, obsession with Dorian that she does not create her own
music, merely adopts his. And yet, in his refusal, Dorian himself mimics Henry’s
own more impassioned music from the Prologue; neither of them is, in truth, free
from obsessive thoughts about another person, or the ideals that they represent.
Unfortunately for Sybil, Dorian’s ideals lead him to abandon her, storm out,
have a wild night on the town before returning to his house, alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Dorian5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 5&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cap the act off, Jamie and I had a bit of a predicament: the novella contains
a long time-skip before a certain climactic scene that we both wanted to include
as the finale of Act One. Whilst this reads incredibly well on paper – as the
years pass, Dorian becomes more and more corrupt until he goes beyond the pale –
this does not work near so well on a stage, where the audience is best served by
having a cohesive narrative, at least according to critics as far back as
Aristotle and the classical unities (of action, time and place). Thus, we
conflated several scenes from the book in order to make this finale to Act One
as impactful as can be. As Dorian recovers from his hangover, portrayed by slow,
chromatic triplet descents, his torpor is interrupted by the arrival of Basil,
who has bad news. This is the first change, as Wilde has Henry come to Dorian’s
house to deliver this particular news – that Sybil has committed suicide. Basil
is, therefore, able to finally act more overtly and lovingly towards his muse.
This also sets up a further conflation, as there are two scenes of Basil, in his
moralising fashion, trying to help Dorian. In the one, he asks to see the
portrait and is rebuffed, and on the other, many years later, Dorian crosses a
line. Basil is never seen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we conflated these three scenes into one, I introduced, musically, one last
thing: the poor soprano playing Sybil would otherwise have only two scenes, and,
feeling sorry for her, I wrote her voice into the scene. Dorian, so affected by
the news of her death, can almost hear her calling out to him, turning a duet
into a trio, and having the final action of the scene, and indeed of the first
half of the Opera, become the deaths of two of &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;’s principals (Game of
Thrones style). I don’t believe I know of another opera where both the tenor and
the soprano are killed before we make it half-way. That ought to make an impact
– and hopefully leave the audience as eager to see the conclusion of the drama
as you may well be to read the final instalment of this little-guided tour
through my opera!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Olly Bowes</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s The Picture of Dorian Gray into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of Die Fledermaus or Figaro with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker dramas, The Turn of the Screw or perhaps Owen Wingrave. I was mistaken. It took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the public by the wonderful people at LoveOpera.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues</title><link href="/Self-Censorship" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues" /><published>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Self-Censorship</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Self-Censorship">&lt;p&gt;Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One argument is that this only brings online video streaming platforms at par with movie theatres and cinema halls. In India, all movies and series must be mandatorily certified by the Central Board of Film Certification (CBFC) before they are allowed to be screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, or on TV. The CBFC often orders some scenes to be cut or blurred out, failing which viewership is restricted to an adult audience only, or worse still, the film is not allowed to be screened at all. Scenes which are even remotely “obscene”, substantially against social morality, or which have the potential to create social friction are frequently the target of such restrictions. The CBFC’s ambit, however, does not extend to films streamed online. This attempt at self-censorship, based on general guiding principles which largely reflect how films are censored by the CBFC in practice, will – in theory – bring films streamed online on these platforms at par with those screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, and on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of self-censorship is not new. Advertisers, newspapers, TV channels, and other content publishers and disseminators across the world engage in varying levels of restraint in the content they publish, i.e. self-censorship, in-house or through a common self-regulatory mechanism set by a professional body. For instance, advertisers in India abide by the standards set by the Advertising Standards Council of India, a self-regulatory professional body constituted by advertisers and their representatives themselves. This policy of self-censorship by video streaming platforms is hence not unprecedented in the Indian media industry. However, it does raise its own, unique set of concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the unofficial ‘code’ video streaming platforms have committed themselves to at the moment is too vague, general, and broad. It risks building into the process a large degree of discretion, which may manifest itself as arbitrariness. At worst, it may lead to several versions of the same movie or series airing on different platforms. That will surely have disastrous business implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there is a glaring lack of an appeals process. Video streaming platforms appear to have carte blanche so far as self-censorship is concerned. An appeals process needs to be built in for the same reason courts of appeal exist – as a remedy against fallible human judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, where are the filmmakers? Excluding filmmakers and film professionals from the process of censorship leads to peculiar, laughable results. For a case in example, consider the Amazon Prime Original series, &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;. Mrs. Maisel routinely uses expletives while performing as a comedian – that is part of her unique charm. She even exposed her breasts before a club audience while performing an act. These acts get her arrested twice for public indecency, but she continues with them, largely unchanged. That is her unique charm, and it is a central quirk of the character. Now imagine if these expletives were to be censored, and the scene where Mrs. Maisel exposed her breasts cut out. It would strike at the core of the personality of the central character of a show, and therefore ruin the entire show completely. The persons best qualified to appreciate such artistic and cinematic nuances are film professionals, not tech corporates sitting in the air-conditioned offices of a video streaming platform. Delegating the job of censorship to non-film professionals risks this nuance of filmmaking getting lost in the process of censorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-censorship by online video streaming platforms raises some critical concerns which need to be addressed. It is imperative that online video streaming platforms come up with a clearer, more specific and well-defined code to be guided by while censoring content. An appeals process – both in-house and, at the level of a self-constituted professional body – should be built into such a code. Film professionals must be involved in the entire process of framing a code. Content does not fall on a binary scale of obscene/not obscene. Cinematic nuances, amply illustrated by the example – for instance – of &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;, need to be kept in mind both while framing the code and during self-censorship.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sagnik Sarkar</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?</title><link href="/NBA-Midseason-Awards" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?" /><published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/NBA-Midseason-Awards</id><content type="html" xml:base="/NBA-Midseason-Awards">&lt;p&gt;We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable Player: James Harden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many players putting up great numbers for the season so far, but nobody is even close to James Harden. He is putting up 36.7 points, 8.1 assists, 6.7 rebounds, and 2.1 steals per game. He is literally tearing up teams on a nightly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He even went through a five game stretch where he averaged 52.2 points per game. Its beyond impressive how someone can do that against the world’s best basketball players. The Houston Rockets are a much worse team than last year, but they are still contenders because of what Harden is doing this season. If he keeps it up he might just earn back to back MVP awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rookie of the Year: Luka Doncic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into the NBA, Luka was considered the best international prospect ever. So far he has lived up to the hype. He is averaging 19.0 points per game, 6.7 rebounds per game, 5.1 assists per game, and 1.1 steals per game. He is already competing at a high level as a nineteen year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doncic is a wizard with the ball, making shots you can’t believe and constantly coming up with clutch plays for the Mavericks. It’s a great feeling for a team to know that they have their franchise player, and the Mavericks are probably ecstatic knowing that they have their guy. The sky’s the limit for this young star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defensive Player of the Year: Paul George&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far Paul George is having the best offensive season of his career. It’s pretty extraordinary that his defense has been so impressive as well. He leads the NBA in steals and is third in defensive win shares. This award has typically gone to front court players in recent years, which emphasizes how remarkable Paul George’s defensive game has been. Instead of guarding down low, he has the task of locking down the other team’s best perimeter player every night. The Thunder have the best defensive rating in the NBA and a big reason why is because ‘PG’ is leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixth Man of the Year: Domantas Sabonis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabonis has been a key factor to the Pacers success this season. He is nearly averaging a double-double off the bench with 15.0 points and 9.6 rebounds per game. Sabonis is also pulling his weight in defense with one of the better defensive teams in the NBA. The Pacers are at their best when Sabonis is on the court which says a lot since they are currently third in the eastern conference. Why he’s not starting is a matter of logistics but with Victor Oladipo out for the rest of the year look for Domantas to have an even bigger role for the team going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Improved Player: De’Aaron Fox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sacramento Kings have been one of the big surprises this season. They are currently two and a half games out of the playoffs and a big reason for their unpredictable success is the development of De’Aaron Fox. He made a leap from last season going from 11.6 points, 2.8 rebounds, and 4.4 assist per game to 17.6 points, 3.7 rebounds, and 7.2 assist per game. Fox has stepped up as a leader for a team that hasn’t been this close to the playoffs in over a decade. He will be a key factor for the Kings in their late season push for the postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coach of the Year: Mike Budenholzer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Milwaukee Bucks are in the top seed in the East and Budenholzer is a big reason why. The Bucks have made a couple of tweaks this season which have them one of the best teams in the NBA. Offensively the Bucks have made great strides this season as Milwaukee has the second best offensive ranking in the association. With LeBron no longer playing in the East the conference is wide open and the Bucks are the favorites to win it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the second half of the season underway only time will tell if these players and teams can continue to play at the level they have been since the beginning of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;http://basketball-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Basketball-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jacob Jones</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Friday Night Lights to National Champion, What’s Next for Trevor Lawrence?</title><link href="/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Friday Night Lights to National Champion, What’s Next for Trevor Lawrence?" /><published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion</id><content type="html" xml:base="/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion">&lt;p&gt;Just a little over a year ago, a quarterback in Cartersville, Georgia was the #2 overall ranked high school QB in the nation. A couple weeks later, that same quarterback broke the record for career touchdown passes in Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you might not have known his name a year ago, you most definitely know it now. Trevor Lawrence has proved, as a 19-year-old freshman, that the Clemson Tigers have a new sheriff in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although he did not come into the season as the starting QB, Lawrence took over the job only 3 weeks into the season. He immediately lit up the scoreboards and stats sheets with 5 passing touchdowns in his first two games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading the Clemson Tigers to an undefeated, CFP Championship winning season, Lawrence quickly proved that he is ready for college football. He is the first true freshman quarterback to win the CFP National Championship in over 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some analysts say that Lawrence is already showing NFL level talent despite only being in his freshman year. He had a 30 touchdown season with only 4 interceptions. Along with the big arm, his accuracy was dead-on all season with a completion rate of 65.2 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This young man still has 2 maybe 3 years left in his college career. Also, Clemson have multiple true freshman threats at receiver helping Lawrence out. Coach Dabo Swinney said all season that this team was special, and they proved it in the playoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only wonder what will happen to Trevor Lawrence once his college career is over. Does he have the skills to make it to the NFL? Or will he be another bust like many of the other college quarterback superstars in recent history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on what Trevor Lawrence has done so far, it’s difficult to see him becoming a bust. As previously mentioned, he held the number 2 spot among the nation’s high school quarterbacks in his senior year. Because of this many people knew he would be good but were not sure exactly how he would fare in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He proved that he was ready for a college defense, as he embarrassed the Syracuse defense in his first start with a 97.6 quarterback rating and a 194 passing yard game. And with at least two more years of growth, a coach and teammates with 100% confidence behind him (as well as a brand-new ring) Lawrence’s prime is yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sports-reference.com/cfb/&quot;&gt;https://www.sports-reference.com/cfb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Tanberg</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">Just a little over a year ago, a quarterback in Cartersville, Georgia was the #2 overall ranked high school QB in the nation. A couple weeks later, that same quarterback broke the record for career touchdown passes in Georgia.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bullpen on a Rollercoaster</title><link href="/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bullpen on a Rollercoaster" /><published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster">&lt;p&gt;The convention of projecting the economic rise of the East over the West comes with its own ups and downs. The Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership or RCEP is trying to set up a free (not completely, but not important here) trade area between economies with different levels of openness. Consisting of India, China, Japan, South Korea, Australia, New Zealand, and the 10 ASEAN countries, RCEP (if signed) is set to be a major trading bloc in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASEAN bloc, a major part of RCEP, has itself not been completely integrated despite two decades into its existence. The reasons are numerous and quite technical but I am going to pose a twisted version to the readers: why are they even together? Clearly, it is two things: trade and finance. After the 1990’s, they have understood that they all face the same problem, namely, market sentiments of western countries―the &lt;i&gt;wiseguys&lt;/i&gt; with the greenback. The idea of presenting a united front and avoiding a skewed economy which pulls down the entire region is at the heart of the ASEAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In RCEP, however, different countries are at different places on the development curve, and economists can only ponder what they will prioritize upon reckoning with trouble. This can be extended to a related concern: which country is going to be the engine to which the economies chain themselves in RCEP? The core problem lies in the fact that RCEP is mismatch between developing economies and developed economies. To put it in a light manner, countries like India are the bride behind the veil and economies like Singapore play the groom. The bride is expected to keep the veil on for as long as possible and the groom is expected to act against that. And it is this skewered relationship which creates the confusion. Drawing parallels, the bride’s act of “&lt;i&gt;keeping the veil&lt;/i&gt;” symbolises the act of ‘protectionism’, while the groom’s act of trying to remove it symbolises greater ‘openness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topic where China has the smirk is the power of its political economy. Even though US tariffs have blistered China and the wound is still fresh. As is suspected, China is going into RCEP to expand its influence on the world economy. With the volatility of the Indian rupee (INR), oil prices and other assorted delicacies for a cancerous Current Account Deficit (CAD), Indians are sleeping through the negotiations with one eye open, pondering over the numbers but more importantly, over the political issues which have nothing but negative rents for the current Indian government. India is also in the cross-hairs due to the services-led structure of its economy. As there is no backstopping authority regarding RCEP, running huge trade deficits is not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economics is simple here. It is an election year in India and the fiscal taps are going to open; and countries are sitting with their eyes fixed on this. A market as large as India, with an increased demand due to populist government spending, will be exactly what the ‘hawks’ in a free trade agreement would desire. In simple terms, excessive demand in India means more exports for other countries in RCEP. The cost? India’s CAD.
The moment India nudges on the services sector, labour arbitrage (body shopping) will open itself up. Pharmaceuticals too, are a big thorn in some countries’ beds thanks to India, which is referred to as the “&lt;i&gt;pharmacy of the developing world&lt;/i&gt;” due to the cheap generic medicines it can provide. While exporters might see India (with its young population) as a potential market to tap, India’s services and pharma industry themselves threaten to destroy local competition in many RCEP countries.  Add on to this the fact that India has not been a part of any major free trade agreement like this before, and you can see why India can be a problem for both the bloc and itself. India is both threatened (by an explosion of imports from RCEP) and a threat (thanks to its services and pharmaceuticals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, political stability and a quest for a quasi-hyper globalised trade acting along with inward-looking policy making, cannot go hand-in-hand. This is a serious fault line etching itself into existence. All countries want to cash the dividends but not face rents of such an action. There are various tools, from basic common sense to game theoretic models to prove that, with the potential problems/costs all countries face, the RCEP might lead to policies which are de facto tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may ask why am I being so pessimistic about RCEP? There are two reasons – firstly, I can see the chinks in the contract; and secondly, the winds in global trade have become strong. The world does need a major bloc (in terms of GDP) from the oriental side to put certain perspectives on the global macroeconomic spotlight, ranging from the composition of major international institutions to the skewness sewed into global policy actions. RCEP could be a forum for coordinated action and a backstop to the forceful push of adoption to the western macroeconomic framework. It can also provide an opportunity to end the age of capital imperialism. There are numerous reasons why RCEP should be an opportunity pursued but it doesn’t really look like it could be. To that end, I hope the friends see the milk and cookies after the fight on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Adarsh Agarwal</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The convention of projecting the economic rise of the East over the West comes with its own ups and downs. The Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership or RCEP is trying to set up a free (not completely, but not important here) trade area between economies with different levels of openness. Consisting of India, China, Japan, South Korea, Australia, New Zealand, and the 10 ASEAN countries, RCEP (if signed) is set to be a major trading bloc in the world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Order in Chaos</title><link href="/The-Order-in-Chaos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Order in Chaos" /><published>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Order-in-Chaos</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Order-in-Chaos">&lt;p&gt;What is the most common phenomenon that binds together a seemingly bitter reality that manifests itself in nearly everything present in the universe? The answer, believe it or not, is chaos. Deep down we all know what chaos is, we have all experienced it and that’s why we despise it. From crowded halls to cluttered rooms to the endless traffic on the roads, chaos has been a most fundamental feature deeply woven into the fabric of our lives. It is not just in our day-to-day experiences, where chaos reigns. This miraculous yet notorious concept has also made its way into the most certain discipline of science as the “theory of chaos”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While chaos as a feature of human existence has been a cause of concern since time immemorial, its presence in the sciences as a separate area of study is relatively new. From the outset, the prime objective of science has always been about addressing the questions of uncertainty, and uncovering the underlying pattern in what is seemingly disoriented in nature. It was this pursuit of “pattern recognition” that resulted in the blossoming of Newtonian physics along with the belief that mathematics is the ultimate truth capable of generating precise predictions of the future. The universe was assumed to be a mechanical entity operating in accordance with certain unalterable mathematical principles and norms, making order and harmony almost synonymous with reality and existence. This belief, however, was short-lived. The prescient beauty of Newtonian claims of universal order crumbled into nothingness as Einsteinian theories and New Age Physics shook the scientific world. This advent of the new and the bold provided fertile ground for the recognition of “the chaos” hidden in the complexities of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of chaos was first brought into scientific scrutiny by the French mathematician Henri Poincaré in the 1880’s, during his study of the interaction between the planets, where he noted that even the slightest error or change in the initial conditions can produce enormous consequences in the final phenomenon. Later this took the form of the “butterfly effect” advanced by Edward Lorenz a mathematician and meteorologist in the 1960’s, who in spite of his precise calculations, could not predict the weather accurately. His findings culminated in his famous speech “Does the flutter of a butterfly’s wings in Brazil set up a tornado in Texas?” This speech was a major breakthrough in the history of chaos, establishing uncertainty to be the only certainty in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The butterfly effect is inherently present everywhere, be it in the uncertainty of weather mechanisms or in the most remarkable episodes of human history. After all, it was a rejected application to the Vienna Academy of Fine Art that caused the Holocaust and the Second World War. While this may sound utterly ridiculous, it is true that the Academy of Fine Arts did reject the application letter of the very infamous dictator, Adolf Hitler, which, as his autobiography &lt;i&gt;Mein Kampf&lt;/i&gt; itself tells you, culminated in his anti-Semitic feelings, his enrolment in the German army and much later the Second World War! Imagine how the world would have been had the Academy accepted him. History is replete with examples of how things could have turned out differently if only one tiny event were altered in the slightest way: Had Mughal Emperor Jahangir not been drinking buddies with Sir Thomas Roe―an emissary from England―the East India Company might never really have gained a true foothold in India. The very fact that you are reading this article right now makes the world function in a particular way than it would have otherwise. Who knows! Maybe two minutes of procrastination today may make you question your career choices tomorrow and lead you somewhere you never expected to be in 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is where do we find order? Is it even possible to find order in a world, which is so consumed and immersed in chaos? In a world of chaos, how did we attain our present form endowed with thinking and reasoning abilities, when we are in actuality nothing but a combination of molecules? How do simple cells with no central control system divide and differentiate on their own to form a complex foetus in the womb? This is precisely what the English mathematician Alan Turing discussed in his work, &lt;i&gt;The Chemical Basis of Morphogenesis &lt;/i&gt;, where he underscored the miraculously ingrained patterns of self-organisation observed in living organisms. This spontaneous order stems from the “local interactions” within the disordered system, such as a majestic flock of birds soaring high in the sky, or the schools of fish underwater. While these biological systems may seem chaotic when viewed from the standpoint of an individual constituent within the system (i.e. a bird flying in a flock), they exhibit extraordinary order and exquisite patterns, when analysed as a whole from a third person’s perspective (a human observing the flock of birds). It is self-organisation that leads to grains of sands being unconsciously assembled such that they create magnificent sand dunes. Trees, rivers and blood vessels branching into stunning patterns of self-similarity, all beautifully demonstrate this paradox of order in disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that we, in our petty human lives, fail to understand that chaos is nothing but a masked form of order and the key lies not in evading it but embracing it. While chaos may cause momentary frustration, it enables man to see the greater truth, showing him how his pathetic attempts to control everything around him may verily be the cause of his misery. In the words of the Buddha, “&lt;i&gt;Chaos is inherent in all compounded things. Strive on with diligence&lt;/i&gt;”. The beauty of life lies in the perfect blend of both the systems and not merely escaping from one. Embrace the chaos, rise every morning in the expectation of being surprised and learning something new, let life teach you how to have peace in all this turmoil that you cannot control.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">What is the most common phenomenon that binds together a seemingly bitter reality that manifests itself in nearly everything present in the universe? The answer, believe it or not, is chaos. Deep down we all know what chaos is, we have all experienced it and that’s why we despise it. From crowded halls to cluttered rooms to the endless traffic on the roads, chaos has been a most fundamental feature deeply woven into the fabric of our lives. It is not just in our day-to-day experiences, where chaos reigns. This miraculous yet notorious concept has also made its way into the most certain discipline of science as the “theory of chaos”.</summary></entry></feed>