<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-11T20:28:31+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Rational Pirates</title><link href="/The-Rational-Pirates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rational Pirates" /><published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Rational-Pirates</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rational-Pirates">&lt;p&gt;So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I would like to share the riddle with you and try to explain the solution and how game theory can help us in various situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good day to be a pirate. Andrew and his 4 mates, Brandon, Christian, David and Edmund have struck gold, a chest with 100 coins. But now, they must divide up the treasure according to the pirate code. The code is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the captain, Andrew gets to propose first about how to distribute the coins. Then, each pirate including Andrew himself gets to vote either ‘yes’ or ‘no’. If the vote passes, or if there is a tie, the coins are divided according to the plan proposed by Andrew, but if the majority votes ‘no’, Andrew must walk the plank into the deep sea and Brandon becomes the captain. Then, Brandon gets to propose a new distribution and all remaining pirates would vote again. If his plan is rejected, he walks the plank too and Christian takes his place. This process repeats with the captain’s hat moving to David and then to Edmund until either a proposal is accepted or there is only one pirate left.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each pirate’s primary objective is to stay alive while getting as much gold as possible. But since they are pirates, none of them trust each other so they can’t really collaborate in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If anyone thinks they will end up with the same amount of gold in two different scenarios, they will vote to make the captain walk the plank just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, each pirate is excellent at logical thinking and knows that the other pirates are too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question here is, what distribution should Andrew propose to make sure he lives and gets as much gold as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we follow our intuition, it seems like Andrew should try to bribe other pirates with most of the gold to increase the chances of his plan being accepted or maybe to propose a distribution like 40-30-20-10-0 or any other combination for that matter and hope for the best, but it turns out Andrew can do much better than that. Let’s have a look at the solution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you know, the pirates know each other to be top-notch logicians. So, when each one votes, they won’t just be thinking about the current proposal but about all the possible outcomes down the line. Moreover, because the rank order is known in advance, each one of them can accurately predict how others would vote in any situation and adjust their own votes accordingly. Since Edmund is last, he has the most outcomes to consider so let us start by following his thought process. He would reason out by working backward from the last possible scenario with only him and David remaining. David would obviously propose to keep all the gold and Edmund’s one vote would not be enough to override it. So, Edmund wants to avoid this situation at all costs. Now, we move to the previous decision point with three pirates left and Christian making the proposal. Everyone knows that if he is outvoted, the decision shifts to David who would then get all the gold while Edmund gets nothing. So to secure Edmund’s vote, Christian only needs to offer slightly more than nothing, that is, one coin. Since this ensures his support, Christian doesn’t need to offer David anything at all. What if there were 4 pirates? As captain, Brandon would still only need one other vote for his plan to pass. He knows that David wouldn’t want the decision to pass to Christian so he would offer David one coin for his support with nothing for Christian or Edmund. Going forward with other possible scenarios, now we’re back at the initial vote with all 5 pirates standing. Having considered all the other scenarios, Andrew knows that if he goes overboard, the decision comes down to Brandon which would be bad news for Christian and Edmund, so he offers one coin each to them, thus, keeping 98 for himself. Brandon and David vote ‘no’, but Christian and Edmund grudgingly vote ‘yes’, knowing that the alternative would be worse for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pirate game involves some amusing concepts from game theory. One is the concept of ‘common knowledge’ where each person is aware of what the others know and uses this to predict their reasoning and final distribution. Had it been the case where the pirates didn’t know the intellectual capabilities of each other, the situation would flip altogether and there would have been no accurate solution to the riddle but fortunately that wasn’t the case. This is a classic example of ‘Nash-equilibrium’, where each player knows every other player’s strategy and chooses them accordingly. Even though it may lead to a worse outcome for everyone than cooperating would, no individual player can benefit by changing their strategy. So, it seems like Andrew gets to keep most of the gold coins (98 to be precise) and the other pirates might need to find better ways to use those impressive logic skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole intention behind this article was to explain to you how a simple concept of game theory can help you gain more in life. The example here was not an appropriate one for you to relate to in real life (unless you obviously decide to become a pirate) but there are several other instances in which it might help you. The decision involving whether to go for a movie or a concert with your friends also involves game theory where we know what the other person wants and we try to manipulate the final result so as to do what we want. Also, in financial markets, the decision to invest in a certain bond or a stock after having all the relevant information about the company involves game theory as well. By investing in the company, you become a player and what the company does with that investment determines your gain or loss. These are just some cases where you can utilise game theory, the scope of it is wide-ranging and unexplored, and left for you to discover. As the British writer Charles Lamb rightly said, “Man is a gaming animal. He must always be trying to get better in something or other.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Domestic Violence Pandemic</title><link href="/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Domestic Violence Pandemic" /><published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Domestic violence is among the most common forms of crime. Very often, it is not even seen as a serious issue in various countries. Diverse cultures around the world have normalised intimate partner violence and some even encourage it in certain scenarios. The lack of proper action against perpetrators has left millions of victims around the globe hopeless, and the number of cases keeps rising every year. In the absence of effective preventive measures and relief facilities, the matter can only be expected to get worse as the years pass by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind my decision to write this piece is the astonishing rise in the domestic violence cases ever since the pandemic lockdown began. The UK’s largest domestic abuse charity, Refuge recorded an over 700% increase in calls to its helpline in a single day after the lockdown was initiated. In addition, a separate helpline for the perpetrators of domestic violence looking for ways to change saw a 25% increase. Now, once you sit down and think about it, this is a crisis that could have been foreseen. Everyone has been asked to remain within the confines of their homes, as much as possible, meaning that the victims have nowhere to go. This is exactly the kind of a scenario that abusers thrive in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, such surges in the number of cases were noticed in previous instances of crises too. This includes the global financial crisis in 2008 and natural disasters like the Christchurch earthquake of 2011. A few countries, however, have seen a drop in the number of intimate partner violence complaints during the quarantine period. The Office of Domestic Violence for the Supreme Court of Argentina has seen a drop in such complaints from 50 a day to 5. A lawyer stated later that the drop was probably due to the fact that abusers can now actively control their victims, who have no way to escape. A reported 25% increase in the calls to the emergency hotline confirms his suspicions. A steep fall in calls to the domestic violence helplines in countries like France and Italy can also be attributed to the same reason; the victims are being controlled, have no way to escape and are finding it difficult to look for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authorities have found it difficult to pin-point and to reach out to these victims. They have been actively trying to encourage victims to call them and let their conditions be known. Victoria Derbyshire, a BBC newsreader was seen hosting a BBC News programme with the domestic violence helpline number written on the back of her hand. She made it clear later that her aim was to get the number out to those who need it during the times of self-isolation. However, with the abuser always at home and the victim having nowhere else to go, something as simple as making a call for help can be an impossible task. It is estimated that on a regular basis, only 34% of those who are subjected to violence in the hands of an intimate partner receive medical help for their injuries. The numbers can only be expected to be worse in the present scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recent incident in Canada solidified concerns about the situation. The country witnessed its worst mass shooting on April 18, 2020. A 12-hour rampage perpetrated by a gunman disguised as a police officer left 22 people dead. This started with an argument between the gunman and his girlfriend which eventually resulted in an assault. She, however, managed to escape and hid in the woods overnight in an attempt to save herself. This is believed to have been the trigger for the shooting. While in this case, the victim was able to escape death, not everyone is that lucky. According to the US-based National Coalition Against Domestic Violence (NCADV), the presence of a gun in a domestic violence situation increases the risk of a homicide by 500%. In addition, 19% of all reported cases of domestic violence involve a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all these issues, the heavily sensationalised Amber Heard-Johnny Depp situation has brought a small detail to light. Domestic violence is, more often than not, seen as an exclusively non-male issue. While it is true that the numbers are higher on that end, an ignorance of the issues faced by men makes the situation only worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, Amber Heard accused her ex-husband Johnny Depp of domestic violence. These claims were supported by pictures of Heard with bruises from the alleged assault and a video of angry Depp throwing a wine bottle and glass. People all across the globe extended support towards Heard, who, unlike many could gather the courage to file a case against her abuser. The public outrage against the actor resulted in him losing some of his most coveted movie roles including his leading role as Jack Sparrow in the very successful &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Caribbean&lt;/em&gt; franchise. Amber Heard, on the other hand, landed the role of Mera in &lt;em&gt;Aquaman&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since she made her abuse story public, she has been given the opportunity to speak for women’s and children’s rights on numerous occasions. However, the real nature of Heard’s interactions with Johnny Depp while she was still married to him was brought to light earlier this year. The leaked recordings of conversations between the two showed a completely different story from the one that the actress had spent the last few years painting. Amber Heard was the abuser. Since then, several other sources helping prove Depp’s innocence in the matter have come to light and the actor has filed a defamation suit against his ex-wife. With the overwhelming amount of evidence against Heard, it is clear that the actress might face some jail time. However, in spite of massive support for her being removed from the DC cast, no such action has been taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Depp, on the career front, she has not been affected at all. This has increased concerns about an unequal treatment of genders when it comes to domestic abuse. According to statistics provided by the NCADV, while 1 in 4 women experience intimate partner physical violence, contact sexual violence and/or partner stalking with impacts such as injury, fearfulness, PTSD, contraction of STDs and so on and so forth, 1 in 9 men experience the same. Very few instances in which males experience domestic violence in the hands of others are usually reported. Now, the reason behind this is twofold. Firstly, patriarchy teaches men to be ‘masculine’, a word that has attributes like not crying or asking for help and beliefs like non-males are physically weaker and are incapable of inflicting pain upon males, associated with it, resulting in most cases going unreported. The second reason is a bitter after-effect of the first: men’s cries for help are often rejected, their words are not believed and they are often ridiculed in such a scenario. They, therefore, fear opening up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many claim that feminism is at fault in the Heard-Depp case. However, the reality is slightly different. Feminism is an ideology which aims to tackle patriarchy and inequality. Therefore, at its core, it does involve standing up for male victims of domestic violence and against the unequal treatment meted out to them. In addition, it also involves standing up against those who use feminism to cover up their crimes and ensure a thriving gender based inequality in society. Besides, Johnny Depp’s victimisation is a failure of the patriarchal society which refuses to believe in the idea that a woman can beat up a man and treats the issue accordingly. We need to remember that domestic abuse is not always physical abuse. It can be sadistic control and/or economic, sexual, emotional and psychological abuse. Heard is simply a bad human being and a terrible example of a feminist. Her actions should not discredit feminism in general and the millions of others who have actually faced domestic violence and are unable to move out of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are millions of people who live in poverty-stricken areas with no access to help in times of need. Many are unable to find a way out of their deplorable domestic situation and see their abusers face punishment for their actions. Besides, the fear of their partners is sometimes so intense that the victims even end up justifying the violence by claiming it as their own fault. There are also people of celebrity status who have faced such a situation. Case in point: Rihanna, who was assaulted by her ex-boyfriend Chris Brown in 2009. Anyone, anywhere can face abuse at any point of time. It is necessary to fight for these people and to ensure that the domestic violence pandemic sees an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue concerning intimate partner violence is the societal perception surrounding it. The views on domestic violence are largely moulded by religious teachings. Before I go further into this, it is important that I mention here that most religions do not have an absolute consensus on any matter pertaining to their religious teachings across all denominations or sects. However, we can always talk about what the majority believes in. In Islam, many claim that Sharia law encourages domestic violence against women whose husbands suspect ‘nushuz’ (disobedience or disloyalty). Sharia Law forms the basis for the legal system in multiple Islamic nations in the world. Some abusers also cite Bible verses (often Ephesians 5:22) to justify violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in recent times, people have come out in large numbers to speak against this justification of violence on religious grounds. They claim that encouraging domestic violence is nothing more than a misinterpretation or an outdated understanding of the holy books. Contrary to the aforementioned religions, Hinduism primarily preaches non-violence on all fronts. Nevertheless, domestic violence is a common issue in modern Hindu families. The most recurrent reason is the inability of the wife’s family to pay the required dowry. The Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961 was aimed at abolishing the dowry system in India. In spite of these efforts, the giving and taking of dowry continues to be a commonplace practice in marriages in the country and is a major contributor to the violence observed against Indian women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue of domestic violence has been a concern of feminists for a while now and a variety of legislations in recent times have only made their job more difficult. In 2017, Russia came under fire for decriminalising intimate partner violence. The new law, signed by Putin and popularly referred to as the ‘slapping law’, reduced the punishment for counts of domestic violence. The reason behind such a decision was claimed to be a desire to reduce governmental interference in people’s private lives. Soon protests broke out across the country against this law. Some of the activists even noted that a crisis that is, more often than not, shoved under rugs has been thrust into limelight because of the actions of the legislature and an increasing number of people are understanding the gravity of the situation. However, as a consequence of the law, a surge in the number of cases of domestic battery was noticed. Besides Russia, there are many other countries which do not provide any legal protection to the victims of domestic abuse. In fact, several cultures fail to even view intimate partner violence as a crime and as an issue that needs to be discussed at length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, the internalised acceptance of domestic violence is at a dangerous high. In addition to this, the act of slapping a woman has been romanticised to such an extent in the country that people view it as symbolic of love and care. In 2019, a Bollywood movie, titled &lt;em&gt;Kabir Singh&lt;/em&gt; was heavily criticised for its glorification of toxic relationships and abusive partners. In spite of this, the film went on to earn a whopping ₹3.8 billion. This is a clear indication of the fact that the majority of the public did not find an issue with the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 28, 2020, another movie titled &lt;em&gt;Thappad&lt;/em&gt; was released in India. The story follows a woman who is seeking divorce from her husband. Her reason, however, is not the conventional disloyalty. It is violence. Her husband slaps her at a party in front of a crowd and is unapologetic about it later. This act drives the woman to her decision. In her journey, she is faced with comments like “thoda bardasht karna sikhna chahiye auraton ko” (“women should learn to tolerate”) and “itni si baat?” (“such a tiny reason?”) over and over again. This movie was widely appreciated by feminists across the country. The IMDb rating of &lt;em&gt;Thappad&lt;/em&gt;, however, shows a marked difference between how men have rated it compared to women. The low ratings from men is an indication of the fact that many of the men in society disagree with the concept; for them domestic violence is justifiable. On the other hand, a higher rating from most women is an encouraging indication that the realisation of domestic violence being an unjustifiable act has finally started sinking in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is abundantly clear that the crisis of domestic violence is not limited to the times of pandemics, financial crises or natural disasters. It is a never-ending issue. Many people across the globe continue to refuse to acknowledge it as a heinous crime in the first place. This severely hampers the capacity to tackle the situation. For now, we can only hope that the increasing awareness among the people can one day result in an escalation in the number of protests and understanding among people, with the outcome of a safer world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Domestic violence is among the most common forms of crime. Very often, it is not even seen as a serious issue in various countries. Diverse cultures around the world have normalised intimate partner violence and some even encourage it in certain scenarios. The lack of proper action against perpetrators has left millions of victims around the globe hopeless, and the number of cases keeps rising every year. In the absence of effective preventive measures and relief facilities, the matter can only be expected to get worse as the years pass by.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Economy Incarcerated</title><link href="/Economy-Incarcerated" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economy Incarcerated" /><published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Economy-Incarcerated</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Economy-Incarcerated">&lt;p&gt;Prison, jail, penitentiary are all the same things. They are meant for the mental reform of a person convicted of criminal activities. However, sometimes they can even enhance the business acumen of a person. They are supposed to have very limited trade and economic activity. In such a world, the only way one could earn is through working official chores assigned by the prison and the only place to spend is the official commissary, or a canteen, extant in the jail premises. However, more often than not, the prisoners trade informally themselves. Goods are smuggled in and a variety of services are offered by the prisoners with skills. Such an informal or underground economy is a common sight in prisons, especially in prisons with people serving quite longer sentences. This article is an attempt to explain why informal economies spring up and how they are operated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why an informal economy springs up. Often the demand of the prisoners is not satisfied by the officials or the prison canteen. An exhaustive list of things that are trivial to the ‘free people’ and are taken for granted are luxuries for the prisoners and hence, have put a huge value on the. Such small things, like a blanket or warm and delicious food, are difficult to get hold of. The only way they can get the items is through illicit means. Second, although there is a canteen present in prison, it is practically the only shop and exercises monopoly power. This results, often, in the sale of goods for a premium on their original price. Many prisons prohibit prisoners from carrying cash with a concern that they would bribe the guards to get their way. Instead, each prisoner is assigned a card; into which they can load money and use it to make purchases. These cards can be loaded either by funds sent in for them by someone and/or the earnings of the prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above the only legal ways to earn money is to do the work allotted by the prison officials. However, the wages offered in the prison are diminutive, even below the statutory minimum in many countries. For instance, the average wage in the federal prisons in the US is &lt;a href=&quot;https://psmag.com/social-justice/taking-freedom-modern-day-slavery&quot;&gt;31 cents per hour&lt;/a&gt;, way below the minimum requirement of $7.25 per hour. The Indian prisons compete with their US counterparts in this aspect. The average amount of wage paid is approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.news.yahoo.com/jailonomics--how-to-survive-inside-an-indian-prison-100808012.html&quot;&gt;₹48 per day&lt;/a&gt; (the actual wage varies from state to state, as prisons fall under the state list), which is one-fourth of the prescribed minimum wage in the country. This clearly points out the enormous gap between the wages and the prices in a prison. Even if the goods were to be sold at the Maximum Retail Price, it would not be possible for the prisoners to afford it. It is also the case that the quality of food is abysmal and sometimes becomes quite hard to eat. This is another reason for the existence of an economy where it is not supposed to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore one thing is clear: there is a demand for goods and services (smuggling in drugs can also be categorised as a service!) in prison. This demand creates opportunities for prisoners to make money. The cost of a good mainly depends on the risk it takes to smuggle in the good. The stronger the security, costlier the good is. Supply of a good can come from two sources: either the prisoners get in the good through their external contact or pay the prison guards to bring the good. In his famous book, &lt;em&gt;Extreme Economies&lt;/em&gt;, Richard Davies quotes an ex-convict who served time in the Louisiana State penitentiary saying “…these [guards] are young and uneducated, they can triple their wages by bringing these things in.” This is mostly true for guards serving in other prisons as well because often the salary paid to these guards is often very low. For this reason, often, the guards are also willing to smuggle in the goods for prisoners. Therefore, the trading prisoners strike a deal with the guards and pay them commissions. Now that we have seen how the supply and demand are satisfied, we need to look at what is the medium of exchange. As cash is prohibited, prisoners come up with innovative ideas to solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can find the most popular medium of exchange for the most part of history has been ‘cigarettes’. Apart from cigarettes shower gel capsules, rosary beads, cigarette paper, etc. have also been used in UK prisons. In the US, after cigarettes, the most popular exchange mediums were postage stamps. Notice all the above items perfectly satisfy all the properties of a currency: store of value, a medium of exchange, and a measure of value. In recent times, however, a popular ‘currency’ emerged in the US: ‘mackerel’ (a type of packaged fish). The validity of a currency depends on the convention that ‘everyone values the currency because they expect everyone else to value it.’ This is exactly what happened with mackerel. While such an exchange was perfectly possible among the prisoners, convincing a guard to take it is hard; as they would only accept cash as payment. Richard Davies explains how the prisoners of Louisiana prison overcame this conundrum (this is also what happens across most of the US prisons): prepaid cards. Using a debit or credit card, one could purchase these prepaid cards (which have an upper limit of $500) basically anywhere. All you need to do is tell the beneficiary the 14-digit number that is behind the card and they could redeem it. So, the buyer and the beneficiary need not even know each other and the transaction happens. Moreover, the fact that no proof or ID is required to buy these cards means that it leaves no digital trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prisoners also engage in these activities because it provides a sense of identity and purpose to the prisoners. They find their lost dignity, in the society, by working and proving useful to their fellow prisoners. Also, the scarcity of the basic goods and, sometimes, prohibited goods means that they can be traded for huge sums. Prisoners that come from families with a relatively lower standard of living support their families with the income earned by engaging in the informal trade inside the prison. There are also success stories where people, after leaving prison, started their own businesses using the skills acquired during their time in prison. It is also important to take note of the fact that people can put their skills into negative use, say, by engaging in smuggling of drugs. Therefore, the solution to this informal arrangement, if one were to find such an economy harmful, is to recognise the fact the prisoners are people with unsatisfied needs, tastes, and demands; increase the wages substantially, to treat them like normal humans and to let them retain their sense of dignity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Prison, jail, penitentiary are all the same things. They are meant for the mental reform of a person convicted of criminal activities. However, sometimes they can even enhance the business acumen of a person. They are supposed to have very limited trade and economic activity. In such a world, the only way one could earn is through working official chores assigned by the prison and the only place to spend is the official commissary, or a canteen, extant in the jail premises. However, more often than not, the prisoners trade informally themselves. Goods are smuggled in and a variety of services are offered by the prisoners with skills. Such an informal or underground economy is a common sight in prisons, especially in prisons with people serving quite longer sentences. This article is an attempt to explain why informal economies spring up and how they are operated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Dear Pandemic Diary</title><link href="/Dear-Pandemic-Diary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dear Pandemic Diary" /><published>2020-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Dear-Pandemic-Diary</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dear-Pandemic-Diary">&lt;p&gt;Last time I was here, I was asking if you would like that Corona (the beer, folks) with lime or without, today, I might take a dozen bottles with or without you. I apologise in advance; this may seem like an untoward journal entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the pandemic is upon us, and God, is it upon us - I wonder to myself, is this regression to teen years going to bring me down, or the virus? While I don’t have to wake up at 5 am, listen to VH1 till 6:30 and move to school by 6:40 anymore, I have to deal with chaos that nobody ever told me about. No school lessons taught me how to be home and keep sane; hiding under the table definitely doesn’t work. Crisis intervention only tells me so much that I might truly have to be infected in order to utilise my knowledge. I wish I could run back to my 3rd grade moral lessons and really be the person that they proposed we be - the sane, calm, adjusted one that obviously had nothing but respect and compassion for everyone. It would make life easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we speak of the pandemic, many don’t realise that while the certainty of having the virus is difficult to deal with (and that may as well be an understatement), the uncertainty it brings with itself is the silent killer that may lead us to a Noah’s Ark situation. The aforementioned teen regression that I speak of? Well, people my age and around my age have had to come back home from being away for college or their respective jobs plainly because, “better be sick with family than without.” And people who were home already, have lost their autonomy and are back to being home with the ‘others’ deciding what is to be done. My teenage hormones, albeit crazy, perhaps, were the only thing that led me to the slightly retained sanity I used to encompass, till, well, a few days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having reread that paragraph, I understand if I might sound ungrateful, believe me, I’m not. I assure you, I’m aware of my privilege of being safe and healthy, of having resources to maintain that, of being able to share my thoughts and being able to help myself and others while I’m at it. I suppose all I’m trying to suggest here is how while ‘inside and isolated’ may drive us crazy, figuratively speaking - doing both while you’re in a toxic household or with someone who may be riddled with their own issues - may, literally speaking, make you crazy. Personally, having had to deal with a symptomatic-to-hypochondriac mother has been driving me up the walls, the paranoia that surfaces is so strong, that any denial will be harshly rejected, and that’s my reality to live with now. Upon asking my near and dear ones, I’m now able to recount several cases of unhealthy relationships, malfunctioning behaviour and what one may call unsettling dependency. My sample is too small, and perhaps not as generalisable - I mean it is, after all, purposive and convenient (Okay, I’m going to stop now). But, what may be concluded is that there’s a danger lurking, and we’re not aware of it or, well, not wanting to be aware of it. May as well dump it in that subconscious, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curse on mental health that social isolation is, is not unknown; there are plenty of people with flared anxieties or triggered depression - and then, there are people who may not even be aware of what they’re going through and end up more hurt than ever. As a future mental health professional, I can sit here and count out hundreds of flaws in self-isolation and social distancing, but the science behind it is not unknown and it definitely is better of the two evils. I can’t give an informed solution, as someone once told me: mental health is like fingerprints, different for everybody (and definitely, incriminating!). I only ask everyone to be more receptive to the idea of keeping your thoughts open and look for more sources of help (and try to be one, too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to intimate yourself with my thoughts - I don’t suppose the fear of COVID-19 is as high as having to figure out how to placate my mother, submit two assignments and attend 3 classes and write 2 research papers, while simultaneously completing my to-dos of ‘productive work during quarantine.’ Every time I watch the news, I worry that maybe the numbers that rise up everyday are just becoming statistics to me and my brain, and my empathy and fear will be drained out by my need to do chores and completing tasks and just proving that I’m ‘productive’. Or perhaps, it’s the other way round, maybe that is good, denial till faced with the issue - a (good?) coping mechanism. I wouldn’t know; if you do please, page me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only think of today as possibly weighed by my worries and the silliness that pertains to “whoa, today was busy”. Maybe, you can do one better and ask your near and dear ones how their day was. And yourself, it’s important that you ask yourself about your day. My day was mopping, Humanism and the utter joy followed after finding recent, high Impact Factor research papers. Well, it’s yet to be over, but you know I’ll keep you posted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">Last time I was here, I was asking if you would like that Corona (the beer, folks) with lime or without, today, I might take a dozen bottles with or without you. I apologise in advance; this may seem like an untoward journal entry.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">O Ray of Truth and Humanity</title><link href="/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="O Ray of Truth and Humanity" /><published>2020-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Not to have seen the cinema of Ray means existing in the world without seeing the sun or the moon”&lt;/em&gt;- Akira Kurosawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up in a Bengali household I was introduced to the world of art, music and cinema at a very early age. My love for cinema started when I watched &lt;em&gt;Sonar Kella&lt;/em&gt;, a film by Satyajit Ray. At that point in time I didn’t even know what direction was or how a movie was made, but somehow I understood that it would be nice to be able to make something like this! Like music in Bengal is tantamount to Rabindra Sangeet (ie. Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore’s collection of songs), intellectual cinema in the state is defined by the artistic excellence of Satyajit Ray. For those of you who do not know who Ray is, I’ll try my best to put down words that might help you to understand him—albeit I am certain that those words will never be able to do justice to this ‘Kohinoor’ among film directors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray was born in the year 1921 and was present when landslide changes that still affect Indian lives were afoot in the country. Now, cinema before Ray was mostly based on Indian literature. As flourished and as distinct our literature was, Indian cinema was yet to find its distinct voice. We didn’t have a lot of stories to tell, or more precisely, nobody really knew how to talk about their time. Until, of course, Ray’s film &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; (The Song of the Road) came along and changed Indian cinema forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; was based on a book of the same name by Bibhutibhushan Bannerjee. Although highly underrated initially, Bannerjee was later considered to be one of the most iconic writers of modern Bengali literature and also one of the most prominent writers in the post-Tagore era. Of course, there were literary works which beautifully expressed the scenario of India but none of those were as brilliant and as true as Bannerjee’s &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt;. When Bannerjee thought of publishing the novel, he was rejected by most of the publishing houses on the pretext that his story was too long and too upsetting. That used to be the predicament of any artist seeking to depict truth via any medium (that is what it still is).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, after a long time of rejection, at last a small-time publishing house named ‘Ranjan Prakashalay’ (Ranjan Publishers) agreed to publish the book. Without the book there wouldn’t have been a young Satyajit Ray coming out of a movie theatre in London after watching &lt;em&gt;The Bicycle Thief&lt;/em&gt; and thinking “This is what I want to be able to tell, the truth”. Ray decided to turn Bannerjee’s book into a film around 1946-47. Why? To quote Ray, it was because of the certain qualities that “made it a great book: its humanism, its lyricism, and its ring of truth”. It took a tremendous effort to turn this novel into a film, especially when each member of the crew was new to this. A bigger difficulty was funding the film, no producer was willing to finance the film, it lacked stars, songs and it wasn’t entertaining either. It took the film almost 2 years to complete, as the team faced financial crisis more than once. At last, in 1955, the film was released. A completely unorthodox film in Bengali cinema, very few people had any interest in seeing a film based on a village of West Bengal, but those that did see the film were mesmerised by its sheer simplicity. They understood that this new director named Satyajit Ray was something else altogether. The film later became one of the most significant works of art all over the world, winning numerous accolades in film festivals across the world. &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; was followed by two more films named &lt;em&gt;Aparajito&lt;/em&gt; (The Unvanquished), and &lt;em&gt;Apur Sansar&lt;/em&gt; (The World of Apu). Together they are known as ‘The Apu Trilogy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One significant feature of Ray’s films was the city of Kolkata. Due to the partition of India, the Bangladesh Liberation War and bad infrastructure, Kolkata became overly-crowded in the 70’s—which was also a period of nihilistic delusion for the youth of the city. The Naxalite period had just ended, and there was madness and frustration all around. Many people were without jobs, food, or a place to live. ‘The Kolkata Trilogy’ by Ray tells these stories of Kolkata. The trilogy contains the following films: &lt;em&gt;Pratidwandi&lt;/em&gt; (The Adversary), &lt;em&gt;Seemabaddha&lt;/em&gt; (Company Limited) and &lt;em&gt;Jana Aranya&lt;/em&gt; (The Middleman). Ray depicted the stories of three different men from three different social classes in these films, showing how the once-loved city became a nightmare for them, and how it showed them a ‘ray’ of hope as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, instead of merely focussing his attention on the lives of the downtrodden or grasping the frenzy of the times plainly, the maverick filmmaker’s Neo-Realism led him to weave his stories into profound human and social documentaries. Watching Ray’s Kolkata Trilogy is still the best way of understanding Kolkata and its history. That apart, the city played a huge part in his movies like &lt;em&gt;Charulata&lt;/em&gt; (The Lonely Wife) and &lt;em&gt;Mahanagar&lt;/em&gt; (The Big City). Both movies exhibit the richness of Ray’s thoughts and his genial ability to transport his audience to an adventurous yet real plethora of emotions. The problems described in Ray’s films are unfortunately still present in Indian society. Be it class struggle, the oppression of women, middle class identity crisis, religion or anything, we are still very much suffering from them. In the end, &lt;em&gt;we might cherish this man’s existence in our society but we couldn’t learn anything from his films&lt;/em&gt;. This man had the courage to talk about the problems of his time in his own way and we all know how difficult it is to talk about the truth through any art. We are becoming more and more stereotypical day-by-day, we are becoming too sensitive to hear and tell the truth each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won’t be fair to talk about Ray and not mention his love for children, his constant enthusiasm towards creating a different world for children, a world each and every kid in Bengal has been a part of while growing up. If you ever check his work you will see the huge amount of work he has done for children. A lot of it comes from his father, Sukumar Ray, who was a critically-acclaimed poet and writer and probably the first person to write nonsensical comedy for children in Bengali—a thing which is missing from today’s ‘woke’ generation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many directors can tell really serious stories through their work but they cannot and have not made a film for the children. Now, why I’m saying this is because I truly believe that making children happy and showing them something which can inspire them through generations is the most beautiful thing that you can achieve as a filmmaker. Ray has done innumerable things for children; he made films, he wrote stories, he created the first children’s magazine in Bengali, and he created and gifted us our very own Bengali detective named ‘Feluda’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satyajit Ray single-handedly created such an impact that it inspires generation after generation. Even today, when we watch a film by Satyajit Ray, we are drawn in. Technology was not as developed as today, resources to make a film were not readily available, yet by sheer willpower, talent and his love for the art, Ray created one masterpiece after the other. It won’t be fair to name just a couple of famous filmmakers who have been inspired greatly by Ray, as glimpses of his impact can be seen in every artist. Yesterday, ie. May 2, 2020 was our very own Manikda’s (Ray’s nickname) 99th birthday. I do not know if this article, in any way, does justice to this great human being, but I will always be thankful to Ray for showing me and our generation the truth of life, how can we learn things from our imagination and how to never stop doing what you love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belated Happy Birthday Manikda. May you always show us the ray of hope!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Satyaki Paul&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Satyaki Paul is a film enthusiast trying to explore the unseen in cinema everyday.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>guest.guest</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">“Not to have seen the cinema of Ray means existing in the world without seeing the sun or the moon”- Akira Kurosawa.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quality or Quantity?</title><link href="/Quality-or-Quantity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quality or Quantity?" /><published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Quality-or-Quantity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Quality-or-Quantity">&lt;p&gt;Why are so many students convinced that they should get good grades just because they spent so many hours on a particular paper? It is not a belief about the quality of those papers rather it is a belief about the hours and hours spent on writing them. This fundamental misconception about the value of labour lies at the root of Marx’s critique of capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hundreds of years, many economists believed that goods should be valued on the basis of the number of hours the labour spent to produce those goods. It was considered that any two goods that took the same time to be produced had the same value. This was termed as the ‘Labour Value of Theory’. One of the best-known advocates of this theory was Karl Marx. However, this theory has fallen out of favour among economists since the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory did have some superficial plausibility as it does seem that a good which involves a higher number of labour hours should be valued higher. However, the theory got increasingly complicated as it tried to explain some obvious objections. If we go by this theory the value of land should be nil, as there is no amount of labour that goes into ‘producing’ the land. What about the great pieces of art which hold hefty price tags, despite the fact that they do not require intense labour? What about the exorbitant prices paid to Michelin starred chefs? The theory failed to give a logical reason for these exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Marx, the labour value of theory lied at the center of the problems related to capitalism. The argument that capitalism exploited labourers depended crucially on the theory that labour was the source of all value-added, and that capitalists stole the profits from these labourers who deserved it more. According to him, capitalism destroyed our ability to enjoy the work that we do and forced us to work under their tyranny. Without the theory, Marx would have failed to justify the problems associated with capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It became increasingly difficult for the proponents of the theory to come up with logical explanations for the various exceptions to this theory. An individual’s skill set was completely ignored, it failed to account for the difference in the amount of time it takes for different individuals to perform a certain task. Moreover, it is clearly possible to spend a large amount of time on a product that ends up having no value eventually (something like a sandcastle). Additionally, goods that require the same amount of time to be produced should have the same market value, however, this is not always the case. Different goods have varying values in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition to the labour value of theory was proposed by Carl Menger when he stated that the value of goods is ‘subjective’. While the labour theory argued that the price of inputs determines the value of the final good, the subjectivist theory claimed that the value of a good is derived from the human perception of its usefulness. Value is not something that is objective or can be standardised for every person. It is a function of the role that an object plays in the plans of a certain human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, according to the subjectivists, land has value not because of the labour that goes into tilling it but because of the utility that people expect to derive out of it (such as growing crops to eat). People pay a high amount for solid coloured canvases not because of the painter’s efforts, but because of the beauty that they saw in the painting. Michelin starred restaurants are so pricey not because of the hours and hours that the chef spends in preparation of the food, but because of the satisfaction people get from eating that food. Therefore, the theory drew a line between the economic value of a good and the scientific value of the good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjective theory of value gave a new meaning to the value of labour: the value of inputs like labour depended on the value of outputs that they helped to produce. Hence, labour gets rewarded on the basis of producing things that others value. When you consider that combining labour with capital enables that labour to produce goods that others value, Marx’s arguments seem invalid. Capitalism, hence, provides tools to the labourers to produce valuable goods and thereby increases their remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, capitalism is basically a communication process through which humans try to make the best possible use of the limited resources available with them to satisfy their most urgent wants. Many academics are simply unaware of the fact. It depends on an individual what he values more, ‘quality’ or ‘quantity’.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Why are so many students convinced that they should get good grades just because they spent so many hours on a particular paper? It is not a belief about the quality of those papers rather it is a belief about the hours and hours spent on writing them. This fundamental misconception about the value of labour lies at the root of Marx’s critique of capitalism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Landmark Political Speeches and Rhetorics that Incited Historical Change</title><link href="/Landmark-Political-Speeches" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Landmark Political Speeches and Rhetorics that Incited Historical Change" /><published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Landmark-Political-Speeches</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Landmark-Political-Speeches">&lt;p&gt;One of the most earnest driving forces in the political landscape of human history has been the influence of revolutionary and powerful speeches. Some of the most well-written public speeches which attempt to influence audiences are a masterful combination of strong political emotions, the art of language and writing, efficient public speaking, clarity of stance, tensile communicative gestures and a tethered grip of the listeners’ attention. Such speeches combine a gravitative sense of the right pauses, accurate emphasis on event-centric phrases, truthful and emotional connection with the audience, and a perfect translation of thoughts into words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the most impactful speeches are delivered post remarkable events in history. All groundbreaking spectacles of human history are followed by a prideful example of magnificent public speaking. The speeches elaborated upon here have held hearts in dark times, provided hope in despondency, inspired the characters of men, ignited some brave feats, given courage to the downtrodden, kept the dead’s honour and changed the course of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Third Philippic&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Demosthenes, Athens, Greece, 342 BC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most ancient speeches should receive their due in setting historical standards. Demosthenes was a statesman and orator of Athens, his city-state, which he cherished with his life. He was born with a speech impediment—a very unbelievable fact. He would go to any lengths against anyone who might attempt to infringe on the privileges of life and freedom people enjoyed in his state. Unfortunately, this passion was seldom shared by his fellow Athenians. When Philip II of Macedon made unstoppable, bolder incursions into the Greek peninsula, the Athenians fell into a coursing dilemma. Demosthenes kept engaging with his powerful oratorical skills to awaken his fellow citizens from the rousing danger Philip posed. Philip slowly advanced on Thrace, and Demosthenes was sick of how his kinfolk were taking liberty for granted. He called a speech to induce action, at the end of which the assembly cried out, “To arms! To arms!” This speech has always been a classic example of a passionate leader guiding his people by calling out the follies they were succumbing to and rescuing them from subjugation under evil counsels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ain’t I A Woman?&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Sojourner Truth, Ohio, USA, May 29, 1851&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sojourner Truth was an escaped slave, an evangelist, an activist of feminism, and a preacher of abolitionism, who dared to deliver this iconic speech at the Women’s Rights Convention in Akron. This speech was a passionate response and an accusatory call out of male ministers who had protested the Convention believing that women were weaker and intellectually inferior to men. The men protested with citations trying to prove their horrid stance. They said that Jesus had been a man and that the original woman, Eve, had sinned — as documented proof to feed their egotistical male chauvinism. Sojourner Truth herself was a devoted Christain, and she used her own interpretation of the Bible to put the men in their place and become an inspiration to women for centuries to come. &lt;em&gt;“If the first woman God ever made was strong enough to turn the world upside down all alone, these women together ought to be able to turn it back, and get it right side up again! And now they [are] asking to do it, the men better let them.”&lt;/em&gt; She ignited many human rights crusaders through her empowering wisdom and instilled ideals of gender equality amongst the youngest of girls not just in her time, but for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Gettysburg Address&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Abraham Lincoln, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, November 19, 1863&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;272 words of perfectionist rhetoric, The Gettysburg Address is like a founding pillar of American freedom. The Battle of Gettysburg left eight thousand men dead, the land reeking murky of death, violence and absolute horror. It was meant to be solemnised by Edward Everett’s speech and Abraham Lincoln was meant to only add a few remarks to it. He did in two minutes what Everett couldn’t, even in his own ways, in two hours. Lincoln created the speech to be something far larger than merely memorialising the fallen. He invented a discourse and questioned, most importantly, whether the government can maintain the proposition of equality. It was at Gettysburg where the Constitution was etched with its forever embedded ideals of equality and liberty as the Civil War saw the same ideals crumbling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We Shall Fight on the Beaches&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Winston Churchill, House of Commons, London, June 4, 1940&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill was one of the greatest orators to be born out of the 20th century. Like many great orators before him, he was born with a speech impediment. It is tough to grasp that fact considering the massive tensile strength of his voice, one that riled up Britain during some of its darkest hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Battle of France, Allied Forces lost connection with their troops deployed south of the German penetration. These troops were precariously trapped at the Dunkirk bridgehead. On May 26, 1940, a rampant evacuation of these troops under the name ‘Operation Dynamo’ began. The Royal Air Force made an unimaginably successful effort (even for aerial warfare) at keeping the Luftwaffe at bay while thousands of ships, from military destroyers to small fishing boats, were used to safely rescue and ferry French and British troops. Churchill spoke before the House of Commons on June 4, delivering a speech celebrating the ‘miraculous deliverance’ at Dunkirk. He stood and spoke as he gave one of the most momentous speeches in the House of Commons as he defended Britain and France and it created history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Have A Dream&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Martin Luther King Jr., Washington D.C., USA, August 28, 1963&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This legendary speech of Martin Luther King Jr is unarguably one of the greatest, if not the greatest, piece of oratory in world history. King creates a league of his own with his personality and charisma, skills in rhetoric and passionate precision. A century after African-Americans were promised full equality, black people were being run down in the streets, looked down upon, turned away from public places and denied treatment as human beings. Amidst this horrendous track record of being discriminated against, Dr King embodied a humanity-driven, compelling message of hope. He talked about a dream he had, where egalitarianism thrived and discrimination was forgotten. The emotional quotient of this speech truly touched the most human parts of anybody listening. It is a masterpiece with the expression of a once in a lifetime kind of deliverance, yet with the layered ideals of humanity which we should all ethically thrive for as any society. This speech is, in its entirety, just as exhilarating and moving today as it was in 1963.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the aforementioned speeches have some gripping takeaways that will impact generations to come, so they can trace their ancestral passions and encapsulate an understanding of what preceded them. There have been innumerable speeches from the remotest of places that have ingrained the purposes of humanity and politics within the most different communities. It will take a lifetime to reflect on it all. Take this as a proposition to do so. One might find a leader in the most local roads trying to build oneness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">One of the most earnest driving forces in the political landscape of human history has been the influence of revolutionary and powerful speeches. Some of the most well-written public speeches which attempt to influence audiences are a masterful combination of strong political emotions, the art of language and writing, efficient public speaking, clarity of stance, tensile communicative gestures and a tethered grip of the listeners’ attention. Such speeches combine a gravitative sense of the right pauses, accurate emphasis on event-centric phrases, truthful and emotional connection with the audience, and a perfect translation of thoughts into words.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deng Xiaoping and Free Market ‘Communism’</title><link href="/Free-Market-Communism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deng Xiaoping and Free Market 'Communism'" /><published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Free-Market-Communism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Free-Market-Communism">&lt;p&gt;After the death of Mao Zedong and the subsequent arrest of China’s ‘Gang of Four’, the person who had the most influence on China’s policies was none other than Deng Xiaoping. As Mao described him in 1957, he was “a little man with a great future ahead of him”. Little did Mao know that this future would largely consist of dismantling Mao’s own vision of China and instituting one that could hardly be called communist in the true sense of the term. Debates are wide regarding Deng and his legacy. He has been called a revisionist by some, a murderer by others while on the other hand, he has also been hailed as the reason for China becoming a superpower in the 21st century. What is certain about him is that he changed the course of China’s development in an extremely significant and sudden way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the current Premier Xi Jinping has himself proclaimed, there were three historical phases in 20th century China which allowed it to break the deep consciousness of feudal subservience and to end hunger: the May Fourth Movement of 1911, the Revolution of 1949 and the Reform Era that began in 1978. Deng lived through two of these phases and spearheaded the last. During the May 4th Movement, an anti-imperialist student-led protest, Deng participated in anti-Japanese boycotts held in Chongqing. Despite being only 14 at that time, Deng’s actions shaped the course of his life. Ezra Vogel in &lt;em&gt;Deng Xiaoping and the Transformation of China&lt;/em&gt; wrote, “From this moment on, Deng’s personal identity was inseparable from the national effort to rid China of the humiliation it had suffered… and to restore it to a position of greatness.” This desire to ‘save’ China led him to join the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) in 1924.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deng was devoted to the Party, but the Party did not give him as much respect. He was very often blamed for being a revisionist and not believing strongly enough in the party’s goals. He was first demoted in 1931 during the Chinese Civil War when he was accused of not being ‘aggressive enough’ in attacking enemy troops. After the 1949 Revolution, Deng’s faith in Mao was firm until the disaster of the Great Leap Forward (1958-61), when an estimated 16-45 million died. His doubts grew during the Cultural Revolution (1966-76) when Deng was purged from the Party for being a ‘capitalist roader’ and forced to work in the countryside as a tractor repairman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the initial turmoil of the Cultural Revolution subsided, Deng was called back to Beijing in 1974, only to be purged again in spring 1976 for allegedly organising protests that occurred following the death of Zhou Enlai, the Premier. Only after Mao’s death that September and the subsequent arrest of the radical ‘Gang of Four’ while jostling for power with Hua Guofeng (Mao’s successor) did Deng finally gain traction in the Party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hua led a group that became known by their critics as the ‘Whatever.’ Hua declared, “We will resolutely uphold whatever policy decisions Chairman Mao made, and unswervingly follow whatever instructions Chairman Mao gave.” This was mocked by Deng and his supporters, who found a useful quotation from Mao Zedong from a time when Mao had been stressing that policy should be based on reality rather than dogma: “Seek Truth from Facts.” Deng said that the ‘Two Whatevers’ took Mao’s statements out of context and ignored the fact that even Mao recognised that some of his ideas had been wrong. Mao’s own slogan foreshadowed the impending ideological shift, away from strict Maoism and towards a philosophy based more on the shifting realities of China’s people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deng quickly asserted his dominance in the race for post-Mao leadership. However, he did not achieve this through an outright attack on Mao because, as he rightly observed, “discrediting Comrade Mao Zedong . . . would mean discrediting our Party and state.” The whole history of the Chinese Communist state was inextricably connected with the name and activities of Mao. However, Deng eventually became the person who did most to dismantle his legacy. Unlike Mao, who was a romantic idealist, Deng was a pragmatic realist. Under Deng, ‘reform’ and ‘opening up’, not just blind idealistic faith, were the key to China’s modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first attack was on the collectives. Collectivisation was essentially reversed in the early 1980’s. Peasant households became the basic farming unit. The farmers had to agree to sell a certain quantity of grain to the state but could earn more above that quota. They were also now free to develop other occupations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also a new focus on monetary rewards, and also on the production of consumer goods, for material incentives would have little effect if there was virtually nothing to buy, as it often was during Mao’s time. In 1980, four Special Economic Zones (SEZs) were set up in China’s coastal areas. In what the West began to call the ‘Open Door Policy’, Japanese, American, European and multinational companies were encouraged to participate in the expansion of the rapidly globalising Chinese economy. The economy eventually rose from the ravages of the Cultural Revolution. At the same time, it began to shed its communist skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deng and his supporters often used the phrase, “It doesn’t matter if a cat is black or white; if it can catch mice, it’s a good cat.” However, there comes a point after which this distinction becomes important. The reforms boosted the economy on one hand but reversed some of the achievements of the Mao regime on the other. Gender equality achieved in the communes saw considerable damage, and with the market economy, it became less profitable to teach in the countryside, lowering the levels of primary education. The ‘iron rice bowl’ no longer existed which meant job security and subsidised food was no longer a promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deng’s vigour for change was exemplified by three lines, quoted everywhere: “If we don’t change, we are at a dead end! Whoever does not reform will have to step down! Let some people get rich first!” The proclamation proved slightly unclear. Who were these people who were going to get rich first? Deng might have meant those the Communist Party supposedly represented: the ‘worker-peasant alliance.’ He might even have been talking about intellectuals with their knowledge and technological skills. But those who got rich first turned out to be Party members and their families and close associates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite his belief in a market economy, Deng remained a committed Communist until his death. He agreed with some aspects of Marxist Leninism. “If anything was sacred for Deng,” Ezra Vogel wrote, “it was the Chinese Communist Party.” Following the Leninist idea of democratic centralism, Deng believed that only an authoritarian organisation such as the CCP could implement the policies necessary for China’s development. It was Deng’s faith in the centrality of the Party that propelled him to end the Democracy Wall in March 1979 and, later, to violently clamp down on the Tiananmen Square protests. Deng’s family reported that “despite all the criticism he received, he never once doubted that he had made the right decision.” He believed in a free economy, but as could be seen, not so much in a free people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, many Chinese agree that Deng’s harsh response saved China from experiencing a similar fate to the socialist states of Eastern Europe. Even today, they are willing to accept the corruption and authoritarianism of the Party given the stability and economic growth it provides. Such a perspective may not sit well with the West, but it did provide much-needed stability at a turbulent time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most sectors of China’s economy today, the state no longer dictates what to produce and how to produce it. Almost all prices are now set according to demand and supply, as in a capitalist economy, rather than by administrative decree. Most government monopolies have given way to fierce competition between state-owned and nonstate-owned firms. But there are still many thousands of state-owned enterprises (SOEs) with tens of millions of employees in China. But even SOEs must now respond to market forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of the People’s Republic of China’s (PRC) move from a planned towards a market economy have been phenomenal. China has been one of the fastest-growing economies in the world for more than twenty years. GDP grew at an average rate of 10.3% per year from 1992 to 2012. China weathered the global recession of 2008-2009 far better than any other major economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while allowing a considerable degree of capitalism, national and local bureaucrats continue to exercise a great deal of control over the production and distribution of goods, resources, and services. Market reforms have gained substantial momentum that would be nearly impossible to reverse. But the CCP still ultimately determines the direction of China’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is normal to be confused about the nature of China’s political and economic structure. What is harmful, however, is confusing the true meaning of communism with the functioning of a state that claims to practice it. The political repression and human rights abuses that have gripped China has come to be associated with the term communism more than any of its other actions. Moreover, although socialistic tendencies in its economy remain to a great extent, it is not enough to practice centralised democracy to qualify as a communist state. The road that China was led upon by Deng Xiaoping took it far away from the Maoist model. Like all market economies, development has come at the cost of widening inequalities. This can be defended in many ways, but it would be best not to defend it in the name of communism. The very term that is often used to describe Deng’s policies - ‘market socialism’- is an oxymoron. It seems almost like the term existed solely to soften the blow from the sharp break from Maoist policies while simultaneously to justify the state repression of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">After the death of Mao Zedong and the subsequent arrest of China’s ‘Gang of Four’, the person who had the most influence on China’s policies was none other than Deng Xiaoping. As Mao described him in 1957, he was “a little man with a great future ahead of him”. Little did Mao know that this future would largely consist of dismantling Mao’s own vision of China and instituting one that could hardly be called communist in the true sense of the term. Debates are wide regarding Deng and his legacy. He has been called a revisionist by some, a murderer by others while on the other hand, he has also been hailed as the reason for China becoming a superpower in the 21st century. What is certain about him is that he changed the course of China’s development in an extremely significant and sudden way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Capitalism, Confucius and China’s Great Leap Backward</title><link href="/Capitalism-Confucius" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalism, Confucius and China’s Great Leap Backward" /><published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Capitalism-Confucius</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Capitalism-Confucius">&lt;p&gt;On October 1, 1949, 200,000 people gathered in Tiananmen Square as Mao Zedong proclaimed victory in the People’s War of Liberation. The nationalistic Kuomintang government had been banished to Taiwan, the ‘Century of Humiliation’ was at its end, and the People’s Republic of China had announced its arrival onto the stage of world history. China, Mao argued, would no longer lie prostrate in front of Western powers, but had begun a journey toward emancipation and self-sufficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, nearly 71 years later, it appears at first glance as though the Chinese people have indeed ‘stood up’ (although it is disputed whether Mao actually used this phrase). Between 1978 and 2013, the Chinese economy grew by an average of 10% per annum. In 1949, the life expectancy of the average Chinese citizen was 35 years, compared with 76 years today. China’s share of world income rose from 2.2% in 1980 to 14.4% by 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet statistics often paint a misleading picture; the China of today is a far cry from the agrarian, peasant-led nation that Mao envisioned, as the predominance of foreign capital and ethnonationalist repression of minorities within China reveals a dark underside to the thin veneer of prosperity and harmony depicted at the 2008 Olympic Games, for instance. Xi Jinping can simultaneously venerate Lenin and advocate for supply-side economics, as the CCP’s ideology, ‘Socialism with Chinese Characteristics’ promulgates that the growth of private enterprise within China does not contradict or inhibit socialism. Indeed, Article 13 of China’s Constitution explicitly safeguards the right to private property. China’s SOEs (State Owned Enterprises) largely function according to capitalist imperatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Century of Humiliation’, which lasted from the mid-19th Century until the mid-20th Century, was marked by the systematic pauperisation and impoverishment of the Chinese people by foreign capital. In the Opium Wars, the British, who were running out of silver to exchange for Chinese porcelain, turned to smuggling opium into China despite the prohibitions laid down by Imperial Commissioner Lin Zexu in 1839. The ratification of the Treaty of Nanking in 1842 forced China to cede control over tariff autonomy and the court system while opening up treaty ports to foreign control. European finance capital continued to subjugate China throughout the 19th and early 20th Century, as HSBC was set up to assist Britain in leaching profits from accounts in China, Malaysia, and Singapore. This legacy has arguably since been inverted, as China now engages in the subordination of other nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maoist thought once held that the ‘Third World’ (nations with antagonistic relations towards the Imperialist First World and the developing Second World) was the primary engine of the revolution, standing to gain nothing from the current system. The role that China has since assumed, as a creditor for infrastructural projects in Global South nations, may seem a method of modernising them, but actually functions as a means of driving these countries further into debts that inordinate sums of money must be spent to forgive. In 2017, for instance, Sri Lanka spent 95% of government expenditure avoiding defaulting on debts induced by Chinese loans. The failure to repay loans is typically followed by the privatisation of national assets including education and healthcare, following the coercive ‘structural adjustment’ model imposed on Global South nations by the World Bank and IMF. Moreover, there are clear ethnonationalist overtones to these programmes, as more than 95% of China’s ventures in Africa involve a requirement of 70% of Chinese contracted personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenin, writing in Imperialism: &lt;em&gt;Highest Stage of Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;, argued that &lt;em&gt;“imperialism is capitalism at the stage of development at which the export of Capital has acquired pronounced importance….at which the division of all territories of the globe among the biggest Capitalist powers has been completed”.&lt;/em&gt; The expansion of China’s ‘Belt and Road Initiative’ and ‘Digital Silk Road’ indicate that the modern methods of harvesting data and imposing state-led surveillance have become the modus operandi of Chinese predation. China’s record of eroding the civil liberties of citizens in Tajikistan and Turkmenistan is well documented, as instruments ranging from traffic cameras to cameras inside schools have been used to subject potential political dissidents to incessant government monitoring. This display of political and technological might demonstrates just how far removed modern China is from the ideals of Maoism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nationalistic and chauvinist character of the Chinese State is not just observable from economic and foreign policy, but from the way in which Xi Jinping’s conception of the identity of China as a nation diverges from Mao’s. China has frequently eschewed solidarity with the DPRK, following UN sanctions against them. This includes voting in favour of sanctioning the DPRK, banning all coal imports from 2017, and prohibiting imports of petroleum products and textiles. China remains the DPRK’s only viable trading partner, yet the CCP chooses to ingratiate China further with Western powers at the expense of a potential ally. This indicates that China interprets its role in the world differently; the CCP now views China as a prosperous and independent power in its own right, rather than a nation constrained by the dictates of Marxist theory and a necessity to show solidarity with other ‘Communist’ countries. Mao, in late 1950, sent 200,000 ‘people’s volunteers’ into Korea to help Kim Il-Sung resist US intervention. Prior to the foundation of the PRC, North Korea had assisted Chinese communists in overthrowing the Kuomintang nationalists and had allowed the People’s Liberation Army to use the Korean peninsula as a land base during the Chinese Civil War. The mutual support that existed between China, North Korea, and the Soviet Union during this time has not been replicated since, as China continues to take the side of Western Imperialists, even selling drones to Saudi Arabia to continue their genocide in Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xi Jinping’s decision to neglect socialist solidarity and proletarian internationalism not only represents a break from Mao’s policies but a regression to a pre-PRC understanding of the nature of the Chinese State. The new embrace of Confucianism, which was previously condemned by Mao as anti-Marxist and anti-materialist, indicates that Xi is attempting to reinstate an understanding of the national and historical roots of the Chinese people. In 2014, Xi referred to Confucianism as &lt;em&gt;“the cultural soil that nourishes the Chinese people”&lt;/em&gt;. Obedience to authority and correct behaviour are widely considered central tenets of Confucianism, as are rituals of the &lt;em&gt;Zhou&lt;/em&gt; dynasty and the inherent legitimacy of the family as an institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuation of accepted values and norms contradicts dialectical materialism, which as a product of the Enlightenment, holds that human history is a linear progression, driven by class struggle and control over the forces of production. Culture, religion, and family are considered ‘superstructures’ which are superseded by the economic ‘base’ that determines the material conditions of a society. Dialectical and historical materialism are therefore antithetical to any philosophy, including Confucianism, that denies the power of ‘progress’ and the uprooting of any social force that stands in the way of revolutionising the productive forces. Marx, for instance, championed the destructive potential of capitalism to undermine the conservative vestiges of feudal society, and to “drown” them in the “icy water of egotistical calculation”, to sow the seeds of its own destruction, and to pave the way for Communism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China may have risen to world power status since the Century of Humiliation ended in 1949, but it is a country with a manifestly different outlook and a hugely different identity. The principles of Marxism, proletarian internationalism and agrarian reform have been sidelined as debt-trap diplomacy and revanchist ultranationalism characterise Xi Jinping’s despotic rule. Material conditions including national share of world income may have improved, but morally, socially and with regard to its foreign policy, China has arguably undergone a Great Leap Backward.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">On October 1, 1949, 200,000 people gathered in Tiananmen Square as Mao Zedong proclaimed victory in the People’s War of Liberation. The nationalistic Kuomintang government had been banished to Taiwan, the ‘Century of Humiliation’ was at its end, and the People’s Republic of China had announced its arrival onto the stage of world history. China, Mao argued, would no longer lie prostrate in front of Western powers, but had begun a journey toward emancipation and self-sufficiency.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Horrendous Memories of the Raj: Colonial Rule and the Indian Economy</title><link href="/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Horrendous Memories of the Raj: Colonial Rule and the Indian Economy" /><published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj">&lt;p&gt;Before British rule in India, India was a self-sufficient and robust economy. It was popularly known as the ‘golden eagle’ signifying the wealth it had accumulated. India had already established itself on the world map as the largest exporter in the world with a global trade share of more than 27%. By the late 17th century, almost the whole of India (as we know it in its present form), along with Pakistan and a part of Afghanistan, was united under the name of the Mughal empire and became the largest economy and manufacturing power in the world, producing about a quarter of the global GDP. India was the world leader in manufacturing, producing 25% of the world’s total output until the mid-18th century. It was the world’s biggest producer of textiles, agricultural products, and precious metals and stones, including diamonds. The fact that industrialisation was on the doorstep of the Indian economy cannot be denied. Although primarily it was an agrarian economy, many manufacturing activities started picking up pace in pre-colonial India, and the exchange of ideas and technology with the western world had been free-flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these developments in the Indian sub-continent lured and attracted the British to capture India and use it as a cash-cow to fulfill the needs of their home country. The British came to India with the motive of colonisation. Their plans involved using India as a feeder colony for their own flourishing economy back in Britain. This exploitation continued for about two centuries, ending at last in 1947 after endless dark days of persecution, plunder and exploitation. The British took steps that ensured the development and promotion of the interests of their home country. They were in no way concerned about the course of the Indian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India experienced deindustrialisation and cessation of various craft industries under British rule, which along with fast economic and population growth in the West, resulted in India’s share of the world economy declining from 24.4% in 1700 to 4.1% in 1950, with its share in global trade declining from 27% in 1750 to 2% in the 1900’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian weavers and textile industries were well-known all over the world. They made superior and very fine quality cloth, it was actually known to be the ‘lightest woven-air’. The British came right in, smashed their thumbs, broke their looms, asserted tariffs and duties, and shipped the raw material from India to Britain. They shipped back industrially mass-produced stitched garments back to India, flooding the world’s market with what became the products of the dark and satanic Victorian era. This meant that the weavers and handloom workers in India went from being acknowledged worldwide for their work to being beggars and hence, destroying the forever thriving cloth and textile industry of India, in which it held its utmost pride. The Indian textile industry still hasn’t been able to fully recover from the effects that colonisation had on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British always emphasised the positives that took place during their reign. One such thing in which they took pride was that they built the railways in India. To this, the argument stands that a lot of other countries didn’t need to be colonised in order to build its railways. Railways were built just to serve the British purpose. They were used to transport troops and raw material from the hinterland to the ports to be shipped to Britain. The needs of the Indian public were incidental and there was no consideration to match the demand and supply of the railway services for the general public movement. The fact is that the building of railways was just another gimmick or as one might say a trick implemented by the British to ensure an extravagant return to its own people. They supplied all the equipment, controlled the technology, and promised the British investors vast returns on their investments in railways which were eventually paid out of the Indian taxpayers’ money, as pointed out by Shashi Tharoor. All this resulted in causing the cost of building 1 km of railways to inflate and become almost double of what it took to build in Canada or Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward to the First World War, India and the rest of the British dominions had no control over Indian defence and foreign policy in 1914. So, when the United Kingdom declared war on Germany on August 4, India and the rest of the British colonies were automatically at war with the Central Powers. Though India was suffering from recession, poverty and hunger at that time, the country supplied not only manpower but also 170,000 animals, 3.7 million tonnes of supplies, jute for sandbags, and a large loan (the equivalent of about £2 billion today) to the British government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;World War II was even worse; more than 2.4 million Indian men served in that war and out of Britain’s total war debt of £3 billion (in 1945 money), £1.25 billion was owed to India and was never really paid back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy frequently faced the occurrence of famines too during British rule. Commercialisation of agriculture hampered the production of food grains by transferring land from the cultivation of food crops to non-food crops like industrial raw materials. Moreover, the destruction of Indian handicrafts increased the pressure of population on land. All these led to the frequent occurrences of famines in India causing untold misery and suffering for the Indian cultivators and general people. Anywhere around 15 to 29 million Indians died due to British-induced famines in India during colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after all the miseries and horrendous exploitation incited by the British on India, they never accepted nor did they apologise for the wrongdoings that happened during that period. Today, after 73 years, India stands strong at a global stage as the 5th largest economy in the world, way ahead of its colonial rulers. Although India still has a lot to achieve in the field of sanitation, healthcare, education and other pillars of the economy, it has done a tremendous job till now and has risen above all the exploitation and plunder they suffered for 200 years as a British colony.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Before British rule in India, India was a self-sufficient and robust economy. It was popularly known as the ‘golden eagle’ signifying the wealth it had accumulated. India had already established itself on the world map as the largest exporter in the world with a global trade share of more than 27%. By the late 17th century, almost the whole of India (as we know it in its present form), along with Pakistan and a part of Afghanistan, was united under the name of the Mughal empire and became the largest economy and manufacturing power in the world, producing about a quarter of the global GDP. India was the world leader in manufacturing, producing 25% of the world’s total output until the mid-18th century. It was the world’s biggest producer of textiles, agricultural products, and precious metals and stones, including diamonds. The fact that industrialisation was on the doorstep of the Indian economy cannot be denied. Although primarily it was an agrarian economy, many manufacturing activities started picking up pace in pre-colonial India, and the exchange of ideas and technology with the western world had been free-flowing.</summary></entry></feed>