<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-02T23:35:06+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Through a Gender Lens: The Impact of Sanitation on Economic Development</title><link href="/Through-a-Gender-Lens-The-Impact-of-Sanitation-on-Economic-Development" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Through a Gender Lens: The Impact of Sanitation on Economic Development" /><published>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Through-a-Gender-Lens-The-Impact-of-Sanitation-on-Economic-Development</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Through-a-Gender-Lens-The-Impact-of-Sanitation-on-Economic-Development">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A simple internet search on the growth of a country would pop up uncountable figures on how each country is performing economically. Digging deeper into it would display numbers showing how each country compares with its international counterpart or neighbouring countries. Governments boast of their economic growth figures on international platforms but do these figures translate into actual economic development? Seldom do these numbers take into account how growth affects each individual in an economy. In neglecting the intersectionality a country possesses, governments often fail to account for the needs of the more vulnerable,&amp;nbsp; and equitable access to resources takes a backseat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A classic example of this practice is the lack of discussion, and the subsequent lack of policy measures, on the provision of sanitation facilities across various developing countries. The neglect of sanitation tends to disproportionately affect women and girls globally since social constraints dictate women to carry out their sanitation activities at far off locations during odd hours.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In most cultures and across low income countries in Asia and Africa, women and girls are primarily responsible for the management of household water supply, sanitation and health. It is a time-consuming and taxing activity that involves travelling great distances and leaving work or school if water is made available during working hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Yet, when policy discussions on sanitation take place, female users’ involvement in the design and location of sanitation facilities is kept severely limited. It is alarming how despite playing prominent roles and responsibilities in household water and sanitation, women are often out of the purview of consideration when such facilities are in the pipeline. Such discrimination leads to an excess burden on women and girls, and their productive participation in the economy suffers as a result since most of their time is spent performing unpaid domestic work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover, women are often subjected to abuse and gender-based violence when they are forced to walk to shared sanitation facilities or open defecation sites. The fear of sexual assault and harassment among women and girls while conducting sanitation activities has been documented extensively in places like Ethiopia, India and several refugee or internally-displaced persons' camps. There are several issues with women's access to open defecation. To reduce their vulnerability to sexual assault, they are forced to visit open defecation sites before dawn or at night, and in groups. This is proof of the looming fear of sexual violence that can limit freedom of movement and affect equal opportunities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Defecation in public causes its own set of issues, such as polluted water and an increase in the prevalence of water-borne illnesses, ultimately affecting the entire society at large. Women in India that can access public sanitation facilities find them typically filthy. In addition, men congregate near these facilities to verbally and sexually assault women as they attempt to use the facilities. Consequently, women tend to walk in groups to such facilities and often face time constraints and scheduling issues. The resulting health issues from poor sanitation, the absence of access to facilities at a convenient time and place, and the risk of violence has been severely under-investigated in sanitation-related research globally.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The World Health Organisation (WHO) came up with a measure called ‘sanitation insecurity score’, which measures the relationship between access to functioning sanitation facilities and psychological distress prevalent among women and found the former is predictive of the latter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In rural India, women and girls have a high sanitation insecurity score, which naturally leads to poor mental health. Further research on the physical and mental consequences of poor sanitation facilities on women, and how that deepens the gender divide and distorts the economic well-being of women and girls is an urgent necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another area of concern is the effect of poor sanitation on women’s physical and mental health during the time of menstruation, pregnancy, child-rearing, and other illnesses. Their specific hygiene needs are severely unmet during such times, which makes girls and women more vulnerable to health-related risks. These unmet needs often result in the restriction of equal participation of women in society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Various studies have indicated a strong association between poor sanitation and adverse pregnancy outcomes, such as preterm birth and low birth rate. However, a lot more needs to be studied on the overall health implications of inadequate sanitation on women and girls. The lack of sanitation facilities in schools and workplaces also has a significant impact on female literacy and labour force participation rates.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While there is much evidence of the impact of lack of toilets in schools on girls’ participation in education, there is far less evidence gathered on the absence of proper sanitation on working women, especially in the informal sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A priority area of focus in today’s age should be the participation of women in sanitation and hygiene decision-making. The effective use of water and sanitation facilities will be dependent on both men and women participating in the location and technology of such facilities, as well as taking responsibility for their operation and maintenance. There is evidence that empowering women to make sanitation decisions can improve household and community performance outcomes since their influence on sanitation and hygiene behaviour in households is undeniable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There is a lot that is yet to be achieved in terms of gender equity in several developing countries and regions of the world. The imminent need to adopt equitable practices into policy at all levels will be crucial to achieving the desired sanitation goals of any country. Furthermore, inequitable practices have cost millions of girls and women a chance at education and work and have severely limited the economic productivity of several developing countries by restricting the participation of women. With better access to safe sanitation facilities, the world will certainly witness improvements in health, educational outcomes, and productivity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Essentially, sanitation accounts for a major chunk of the sustainable development goals (SDGs) of any country, which also includes education and work. The sanitation discussion draws our attention to the need to reject the notion that economic growth figures demonstrate a country's overall performance. The need to assess economic development while accounting for equitable distribution and access to resources is pressing. Gender-sensitive approaches to policy discussions on one’s basic human rights, like sanitation, can help us minimize the existing gender gap in society and approach development in its true sense.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="economics" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">A simple internet search on the growth of a country would pop up uncountable figures on how each country is performing economically. Digging deeper into it would display numbers showing how each country compares with its international counterpart or neighbouring countries. Governments boast of their economic growth figures on international platforms but do these figures translate into actual economic development? Seldom do these numbers take into account how growth affects each individual in an economy. In neglecting the intersectionality a country possesses, governments often fail to account for the needs of the more vulnerable,&amp;nbsp; and equitable access to resources takes a backseat.&amp;nbsp; A classic example of this practice is the lack of discussion, and the subsequent lack of policy measures, on the provision of sanitation facilities across various developing countries. The neglect of sanitation tends to disproportionately affect women and girls globally since social constraints dictate women to carry out their sanitation activities at far off locations during odd hours.&amp;nbsp; In most cultures and across low income countries in Asia and Africa, women and girls are primarily responsible for the management of household water supply, sanitation and health. It is a time-consuming and taxing activity that involves travelling great distances and leaving work or school if water is made available during working hours. Yet, when policy discussions on sanitation take place, female users’ involvement in the design and location of sanitation facilities is kept severely limited. It is alarming how despite playing prominent roles and responsibilities in household water and sanitation, women are often out of the purview of consideration when such facilities are in the pipeline. Such discrimination leads to an excess burden on women and girls, and their productive participation in the economy suffers as a result since most of their time is spent performing unpaid domestic work. Moreover, women are often subjected to abuse and gender-based violence when they are forced to walk to shared sanitation facilities or open defecation sites. The fear of sexual assault and harassment among women and girls while conducting sanitation activities has been documented extensively in places like Ethiopia, India and several refugee or internally-displaced persons' camps. There are several issues with women's access to open defecation. To reduce their vulnerability to sexual assault, they are forced to visit open defecation sites before dawn or at night, and in groups. This is proof of the looming fear of sexual violence that can limit freedom of movement and affect equal opportunities.&amp;nbsp; Defecation in public causes its own set of issues, such as polluted water and an increase in the prevalence of water-borne illnesses, ultimately affecting the entire society at large. Women in India that can access public sanitation facilities find them typically filthy. In addition, men congregate near these facilities to verbally and sexually assault women as they attempt to use the facilities. Consequently, women tend to walk in groups to such facilities and often face time constraints and scheduling issues. The resulting health issues from poor sanitation, the absence of access to facilities at a convenient time and place, and the risk of violence has been severely under-investigated in sanitation-related research globally.&amp;nbsp; The World Health Organisation (WHO) came up with a measure called ‘sanitation insecurity score’, which measures the relationship between access to functioning sanitation facilities and psychological distress prevalent among women and found the former is predictive of the latter.&amp;nbsp; In rural India, women and girls have a high sanitation insecurity score, which naturally leads to poor mental health. Further research on the physical and mental consequences of poor sanitation facilities on women, and how that deepens the gender divide and distorts the economic well-being of women and girls is an urgent necessity. Another area of concern is the effect of poor sanitation on women’s physical and mental health during the time of menstruation, pregnancy, child-rearing, and other illnesses. Their specific hygiene needs are severely unmet during such times, which makes girls and women more vulnerable to health-related risks. These unmet needs often result in the restriction of equal participation of women in society.&amp;nbsp; Various studies have indicated a strong association between poor sanitation and adverse pregnancy outcomes, such as preterm birth and low birth rate. However, a lot more needs to be studied on the overall health implications of inadequate sanitation on women and girls. The lack of sanitation facilities in schools and workplaces also has a significant impact on female literacy and labour force participation rates.&amp;nbsp; While there is much evidence of the impact of lack of toilets in schools on girls’ participation in education, there is far less evidence gathered on the absence of proper sanitation on working women, especially in the informal sector.&amp;nbsp; A priority area of focus in today’s age should be the participation of women in sanitation and hygiene decision-making. The effective use of water and sanitation facilities will be dependent on both men and women participating in the location and technology of such facilities, as well as taking responsibility for their operation and maintenance. There is evidence that empowering women to make sanitation decisions can improve household and community performance outcomes since their influence on sanitation and hygiene behaviour in households is undeniable.&amp;nbsp; There is a lot that is yet to be achieved in terms of gender equity in several developing countries and regions of the world. The imminent need to adopt equitable practices into policy at all levels will be crucial to achieving the desired sanitation goals of any country. Furthermore, inequitable practices have cost millions of girls and women a chance at education and work and have severely limited the economic productivity of several developing countries by restricting the participation of women. With better access to safe sanitation facilities, the world will certainly witness improvements in health, educational outcomes, and productivity.&amp;nbsp; Essentially, sanitation accounts for a major chunk of the sustainable development goals (SDGs) of any country, which also includes education and work. The sanitation discussion draws our attention to the need to reject the notion that economic growth figures demonstrate a country's overall performance. The need to assess economic development while accounting for equitable distribution and access to resources is pressing. Gender-sensitive approaches to policy discussions on one’s basic human rights, like sanitation, can help us minimize the existing gender gap in society and approach development in its true sense.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The American Recipe for a Food Crisis</title><link href="/The-American-Recipe-for-a-Food-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The American Recipe for a Food Crisis" /><published>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-American-Recipe-for-a-Food-Crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-American-Recipe-for-a-Food-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;You might have heard about corporations profiting from sexism, homophobia, physical insecurities, poverty, and even, you! But have you ever wondered how these organisations feed off hunger?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article attempts to capture the Hunger Industrial Complex (a mechanism by which huge, capitalist organisations systemically perpetuate hunger in order to reap profits, all while maintaining the facade of ‘anti-hunger proponents’) through the story of the US.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chronology is simple. People are hungry. They can’t afford food. (Primarily because while the federal minimum wage in the US has been stuck at $7.25, the cost of groceries has &lt;a href=&quot;https://politicsofpoverty.oxfamamerica.org/what-is-the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gone up by 25% &lt;/a&gt;in the past decade.) Anti-hunger groups bank on charities from huge corporations to feed the hungry. These corporations shell out millions for the ‘noble cause’, while ensuring they turn a deaf ear to their employees demanding a wage hike, which would eliminate the need for food banks in the first place. People are hungry, again, the next day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the complexities better, we need to visit the three main actors in the process: The Donors, The Anti-Hunger Groups and Food Banks, and The Government, and trace their complicity and contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's first visit the big corporations vis-a-vis the benefactors or &lt;em&gt;donors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;to food banks through the lens of Walmart. As the largest employer in the US with nearly 1.6 million workers, Walmart has faced criticism for years over low wages, wage theft, and keeping workers on part-time schedules to shirk off employee security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;You can’t pay your bills, rent and buy groceries on $12 an hour. I don’t think anywhere in the United States, you can do that. No way&lt;/em&gt;,” said Mendy Hughes, 46, who has worked as a cashier for Walmart in Arkansas, for 11 years. Anna Turner, who had worked at Walmart in California for more than eight years before being fired for complaining about COVID-19 mismanagement in the workplace, noted that she made less than $15 an hour and was never hired for full-time hours, even though the department was chronically understaffed. “&lt;em&gt;They would always cut our hours so we couldn’t get full-time and health benefits&lt;/em&gt;,” said Turner. (Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2021/oct/28/walmart-pay-hourly-low-wages-working-conditions&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, even the Food Stamp Program that the US government has in place to provide food-purchasing assistance to low- and no-income people connects back to Walmart making money! Americans spend about &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10001424052702303843104579168011245171266?mod=djemITP_h&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;18% of all food stamp dollars&lt;/a&gt; at Walmart, which gives Walmart all the more incentive to force its employees to rely on food stamps.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So basically, Walmart is encouraging its employees to get food stamps, or go to food banks, because they don’t pay them enough wages in the first place. And surprisingly, the atrocities are legal as the federal minimum wage in the US, as mentioned before, is $7.25!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, Walmart’s not the only culprit, there are so many more corporations playing this game. In 2012, Arby’s (one of the biggest fast-foo&lt;a href=&quot;https://civileats.com/2013/09/05/the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;d chains of America)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://civileats.com/2013/09/05/the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;raised $2.7 million&lt;/a&gt; for the hunger cause, most of which &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arbysfoundation.org/Fundraiser.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;went to Share Our Strength&lt;/a&gt;, an organisation aiming to end childhood hunger. Ironically, all this while, Arby’s employees were protesting the fact that they didn’t earn enough to feed their children.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now another question arises, why would these companies rather make huge donations than pay their employees a little more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two facets to the answer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the ‘Maths’ of it. It wouldn’t require much calculation to figure that paying a ‘little’ more to millions of employees, every month, compounds to a much greater price than shelling out a good chunk of bucks every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the ‘PR’ of it. Donations and charities facilitate corporations to ‘greenwash’ their damaged reputations and boost their CSR (Corporate Social Responsibility) contribution in ways pay hikes could never accomplish. Charities make these corporations look like ‘hunger fighters’ instead of ‘hunger causers’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could still, for a minute, understand corporate complicity. But what about the food banks? What about anti-hunger groups?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s visit these one by one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A&lt;em&gt; food bank &lt;/em&gt;is a non-profit, charitable organisation that distributes food to those without the resources to evade their hunger, through intermediaries like food pantries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past few decades, food banks have become an integral and accepted part of America’s hunger response. According to a comprehensive government survey completed in 2002, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Food_bank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;over 90% of food banks were established in the US after 1981&lt;/a&gt;. In the early 1980's, President Reagan’s administration cut back several welfare programmes, which, combined with unemployment and a budding recession, led to a rapid rise in hunger relief activities. The “emergency food system”, supposedly a temporary measure, slowly became a rather permanent industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some believe food banks to be an example of active, caring citizenship, others express concern that the rise of food banks may corrode political support and incentive for welfare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next on the list are &lt;em&gt;anti-hunger groups.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are organisations attempting to alleviate hunger through long-term solutions, anti-hunger programmes, etc. Anti-hunger groups usually tie up with food banks to further their cause.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many groups see their role as ensuring that no kid misses a meal, rather than reducing the growing economic inequality (the underlying cause of hunger in the US). Their approach is not hunger elimination, but hunger maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to a pertinent question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anti-hunger groups are feeding people. But why aren’t they fighting hunger?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would expect anti-hunger groups to be lobbying for the signage of the living wage bill, or rallying against the violation of employees' rights at the hands of corporations like Walmart and Amazon. But it’s not that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps their lack of attention is grounded in the fact that many anti-hunger organisations find their roots in these greedy corporations. Look at these numbers: &lt;a href=&quot;https://civileats.com/2013/09/05/the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;One in every four&lt;/a&gt; food bank board members works at a Fortune 1000 company.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Walmart staff sit on the boards of about &lt;a href=&quot;https://civileats.com/2013/09/05/the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;one of every eight &lt;/a&gt;food banks.&amp;nbsp; And they are actively stopping anti-hunger organisations from engaging in public policy activism that threatens their business interest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, anti-hunger groups and food banks are not the bad guys, they just seem to be trapped in an intricate system of exploitative capitalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last actor is the &lt;em&gt;Government.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each year, the USDA (United States Department of Agriculture) spends roughly half a billion dollars in buying produce from farmers, and donates them to food banks. However, if only they spent these resources in increasing social safety net programmes instead, the impact would be truly durable. But that’s an impossible feat to achieve given the lobbying power of the corporate giants in the halls of American Congress.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To synthesise, there’s nothing the food banks can do, and there’s nothing the government or corporations want to do. So what’s the bottom line?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bottom Line&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anti-hunger movement needs to focus on anti-hunger efforts, not on charity but on the root causes of food insecurity, improving public health, and reducing income inequality. It needs anti-hunger groups to serve a broader agenda than just temporarily fading out hunger for the day, through federal programmes and charitable organisations. It needs to exact a much higher price from corporations in the form of greater social responsibility. It needs to urge the government to bring systemic changes, especially in the form of increased wages and benefits, policy reforms, etc. But most importantly, we need to familiarise ourselves with these systemic disadvantages and blockages, identify them, and uproot them, because, at the end of the day, no one deserves to be hungry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eeshita Verma</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">You might have heard about corporations profiting from sexism, homophobia, physical insecurities, poverty, and even, you! But have you ever wondered how these organisations feed off hunger? This article attempts to capture the Hunger Industrial Complex (a mechanism by which huge, capitalist organisations systemically perpetuate hunger in order to reap profits, all while maintaining the facade of ‘anti-hunger proponents’) through the story of the US.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The chronology is simple. People are hungry. They can’t afford food. (Primarily because while the federal minimum wage in the US has been stuck at $7.25, the cost of groceries has gone up by 25% in the past decade.) Anti-hunger groups bank on charities from huge corporations to feed the hungry. These corporations shell out millions for the ‘noble cause’, while ensuring they turn a deaf ear to their employees demanding a wage hike, which would eliminate the need for food banks in the first place. People are hungry, again, the next day! To understand the complexities better, we need to visit the three main actors in the process: The Donors, The Anti-Hunger Groups and Food Banks, and The Government, and trace their complicity and contributions. Let's first visit the big corporations vis-a-vis the benefactors or donors to food banks through the lens of Walmart. As the largest employer in the US with nearly 1.6 million workers, Walmart has faced criticism for years over low wages, wage theft, and keeping workers on part-time schedules to shirk off employee security. “You can’t pay your bills, rent and buy groceries on $12 an hour. I don’t think anywhere in the United States, you can do that. No way,” said Mendy Hughes, 46, who has worked as a cashier for Walmart in Arkansas, for 11 years. Anna Turner, who had worked at Walmart in California for more than eight years before being fired for complaining about COVID-19 mismanagement in the workplace, noted that she made less than $15 an hour and was never hired for full-time hours, even though the department was chronically understaffed. “They would always cut our hours so we couldn’t get full-time and health benefits,” said Turner. (Source: The Guardian)&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Moreover, even the Food Stamp Program that the US government has in place to provide food-purchasing assistance to low- and no-income people connects back to Walmart making money! Americans spend about 18% of all food stamp dollars at Walmart, which gives Walmart all the more incentive to force its employees to rely on food stamps.&amp;nbsp; So basically, Walmart is encouraging its employees to get food stamps, or go to food banks, because they don’t pay them enough wages in the first place. And surprisingly, the atrocities are legal as the federal minimum wage in the US, as mentioned before, is $7.25! Unsurprisingly, Walmart’s not the only culprit, there are so many more corporations playing this game. In 2012, Arby’s (one of the biggest fast-food chains of America) raised $2.7 million for the hunger cause, most of which went to Share Our Strength, an organisation aiming to end childhood hunger. Ironically, all this while, Arby’s employees were protesting the fact that they didn’t earn enough to feed their children.&amp;nbsp; Now another question arises, why would these companies rather make huge donations than pay their employees a little more? There are two facets to the answer.&amp;nbsp; First, the ‘Maths’ of it. It wouldn’t require much calculation to figure that paying a ‘little’ more to millions of employees, every month, compounds to a much greater price than shelling out a good chunk of bucks every now and then. Second, the ‘PR’ of it. Donations and charities facilitate corporations to ‘greenwash’ their damaged reputations and boost their CSR (Corporate Social Responsibility) contribution in ways pay hikes could never accomplish. Charities make these corporations look like ‘hunger fighters’ instead of ‘hunger causers’. I could still, for a minute, understand corporate complicity. But what about the food banks? What about anti-hunger groups? Let’s visit these one by one.&amp;nbsp; A food bank is a non-profit, charitable organisation that distributes food to those without the resources to evade their hunger, through intermediaries like food pantries.&amp;nbsp; In the past few decades, food banks have become an integral and accepted part of America’s hunger response. According to a comprehensive government survey completed in 2002, over 90% of food banks were established in the US after 1981. In the early 1980's, President Reagan’s administration cut back several welfare programmes, which, combined with unemployment and a budding recession, led to a rapid rise in hunger relief activities. The “emergency food system”, supposedly a temporary measure, slowly became a rather permanent industry. While some believe food banks to be an example of active, caring citizenship, others express concern that the rise of food banks may corrode political support and incentive for welfare. Next on the list are anti-hunger groups. These are organisations attempting to alleviate hunger through long-term solutions, anti-hunger programmes, etc. Anti-hunger groups usually tie up with food banks to further their cause.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Many groups see their role as ensuring that no kid misses a meal, rather than reducing the growing economic inequality (the underlying cause of hunger in the US). Their approach is not hunger elimination, but hunger maintenance. This brings us to a pertinent question. Anti-hunger groups are feeding people. But why aren’t they fighting hunger? One would expect anti-hunger groups to be lobbying for the signage of the living wage bill, or rallying against the violation of employees' rights at the hands of corporations like Walmart and Amazon. But it’s not that simple. Perhaps their lack of attention is grounded in the fact that many anti-hunger organisations find their roots in these greedy corporations. Look at these numbers: One in every four food bank board members works at a Fortune 1000 company. Walmart staff sit on the boards of about one of every eight food banks.&amp;nbsp; And they are actively stopping anti-hunger organisations from engaging in public policy activism that threatens their business interest.&amp;nbsp; So, anti-hunger groups and food banks are not the bad guys, they just seem to be trapped in an intricate system of exploitative capitalism.&amp;nbsp; The last actor is the Government. Each year, the USDA (United States Department of Agriculture) spends roughly half a billion dollars in buying produce from farmers, and donates them to food banks. However, if only they spent these resources in increasing social safety net programmes instead, the impact would be truly durable. But that’s an impossible feat to achieve given the lobbying power of the corporate giants in the halls of American Congress.&amp;nbsp; To synthesise, there’s nothing the food banks can do, and there’s nothing the government or corporations want to do. So what’s the bottom line? Bottom Line The anti-hunger movement needs to focus on anti-hunger efforts, not on charity but on the root causes of food insecurity, improving public health, and reducing income inequality. It needs anti-hunger groups to serve a broader agenda than just temporarily fading out hunger for the day, through federal programmes and charitable organisations. It needs to exact a much higher price from corporations in the form of greater social responsibility. It needs to urge the government to bring systemic changes, especially in the form of increased wages and benefits, policy reforms, etc. But most importantly, we need to familiarise ourselves with these systemic disadvantages and blockages, identify them, and uproot them, because, at the end of the day, no one deserves to be hungry.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 and Poverty: An Inevitable Link That Is Little Understood</title><link href="/COVID-19-and-Poverty-An-Inevitable-Link-That-Is-Little-Understood" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and Poverty: An Inevitable Link That Is Little Understood" /><published>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/COVID-19-and-Poverty-An-Inevitable-Link-That-Is-Little-Understood</id><content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-and-Poverty-An-Inevitable-Link-That-Is-Little-Understood">&lt;p&gt;Mother Teresa once said, &lt;em&gt;“we often think that poverty is only being hungry, naked and homeless. The poverty of being unwanted and uncared for is the greatest poverty.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; COVID-19 has changed the world in many ways. The shift from classrooms to mobile screens is evident, and the move from crowded celebrations to secluded festivities is too apparent. From jet lag to Zoom fatigue, the world has moved on tirelessly, if not effortlessly. What remains persistent is COVID-19 exacerbating the core issues that the world was already struggling with, the most significant of which being global poverty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the epicentre of the virus shifted from China to Europe, and further ahead to the United States, slowly making its way into comparatively poorer countries like that of Asia and Africa; nations that were already struggling to satisfy its populations' needs were rushed into a sense of emergency as their healthcare systems struggled hard to make ends meet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Debucquet in his paper, &lt;em&gt;Impacts of COVID-19 on Global Poverty, Food Security and Diets, &lt;/em&gt;claims that to understand the surge of global poverty in the COVID era, one must focus on the factors that are initiating it. He believes that the pandemic's impact on labour supply, the constant need for social distancing, reduction in savings and investment, coupled with lower demand for certain goods and services has pushed a major section of the populations of Asian countries into a state of joblessness and reduced options of income-earning opportunities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what seems to be inevitable is that for most economies the global recession and financial crises that COVID-19 has caused are far more intense than the financial crisis seen in 2008-2009. David Debucquet states that “t&lt;em&gt;he increases in poverty are concentrated in South Asia and Sub-Saharan Africa with impacts harder in urban areas than in rural areas. The COVID-19-related lockdown measures explain most of the fall in output, while declines in savings soften the adverse impacts on food consumption. Almost 150 million people are projected to fall into extreme poverty and food insecurity.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Labour Organisation (ILO) has attempted to understand how poverty has aggravated in the COVID era. According to their report published in 2020, the organisation estimated that during the first three quarters of 2020, the number of working hours worldwide declined by 17% relative to that in the last quarter of 2019; a drop equivalent to a loss of almost 500 million full-time jobs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, such figures tell us precious little. Homi Kharas, a senior fellow in the Center for Sustainable Development, in his article claims that it is surprising, and a harsh reality of the study of income poverty caused by COVID-19 that the world is less likely to know the full answers to the questions about it. He says that most of the poverty-related data that we find today has been collected from household surveys since it is close to impossible to conduct full-blown proper surveys in current conditions. He predicted that “c&lt;em&gt;ompared to 2019, poverty in 2020 could rise by 120 million people. Compared to the baseline path for poverty, the 2020 figure is 144 million people higher. Some of this will be offset as economies start to recover in 2021, but the longer-term scenario suggests that half of the rise in poverty could be permanent. By 2030, the poverty numbers could still be higher than the baseline by 60 million people.” &lt;/em&gt;And if one goes by SDG indicators, Kharas was right.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year 2020 did see a rise in poverty by 124 million (approx), of which 60% stem from South Asian countries. Some consider COVID-19 a temporary form of shock to the financial setups of most countries. This is interesting to note since countries such as China faced a sharp V-shaped recession and recovery, which most observers find fascinating and relevant. But, we must not overlook the economic damage that such quick shifts can cause has long term and almost everlasting effects on populations that have been pushed into poverty. Kharas claims that in terms of understanding poverty linked with COVID-19 one has to decipher what living with poverty entails and how long it lasts?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kharas says, “&lt;em&gt;The experience of living with poverty for short periods is harsh, but some families have coping mechanisms—assets they can sell, assistance from governments, relatives, and neighbours. But over longer periods, poverty leaves permanent scars—malnutrition, disease susceptibility, missed schooling. For this reason, it is useful to look at the longer-term impact of COVID-19 on poverty, despite all the caveats associated with any decade-long economic forecasts.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of COVID-19 has essentially attacked income security and employment opportunities but what remains eminently visible is that the biggest threat that prevails is to food security. Reduction in incomes can not only cause a subsequent decline in demand for food items, but also encourage shifts in the mix of products consumed, notably resulting in less consumption of more nutrient-rich foods (like fruits, vegetables, and animal-sourced foods) and comparatively more calorie-rich foods (like essential grains and sugar). This drives up food insecurity. Context-specific estimates of the impacts of poverty and food insecurity are to some extent accessible; it will be years before wide-ranging and relevant survey-based information on these impacts will be presented to general public knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculating the repercussions of the poverty impact of COVID-19 is no inconsequential topic to discuss and debate, it requires substantial and effective fixes that need to come about sooner than we think. This is not only because the crisis is still unfolding and available information of its precise socio-economic consequences is incomplete, but also because the channels of power are numerous and interconnected globally. Scholars have boiled their analysis of poverty in the COVID era down to the idea that “w&lt;em&gt;hile several analyses of the poverty impacts have used simple tools provided by the World Bank’s website and assumed uniform shifts in the distribution of income per country to provide estimates of the impacts on poverty, (see, for example, the studies by the World Bank in Mahler et al., 2020 and World Bank, 2020b; and that of UN-WIDER by Sumner et al., 2020), we are concerned that this assumption fails to account for the complexity of the channels of effect and may substantially underestimate the impacts of the pandemic&lt;/em&gt;.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the need of the hour remains in using effective methodology concerning understanding the effects of poverty and the arising need to solve the issues with it; As Nelson Mandela had once said, &lt;em&gt;“Overcoming poverty is not a gesture of charity. It is an act of Justice.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>trending aniba.junaid</name></author><category term="policy" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">Mother Teresa once said, “we often think that poverty is only being hungry, naked and homeless. The poverty of being unwanted and uncared for is the greatest poverty.&quot; COVID-19 has changed the world in many ways. The shift from classrooms to mobile screens is evident, and the move from crowded celebrations to secluded festivities is too apparent. From jet lag to Zoom fatigue, the world has moved on tirelessly, if not effortlessly. What remains persistent is COVID-19 exacerbating the core issues that the world was already struggling with, the most significant of which being global poverty.&amp;nbsp; When the epicentre of the virus shifted from China to Europe, and further ahead to the United States, slowly making its way into comparatively poorer countries like that of Asia and Africa; nations that were already struggling to satisfy its populations' needs were rushed into a sense of emergency as their healthcare systems struggled hard to make ends meet.&amp;nbsp; David Debucquet in his paper, Impacts of COVID-19 on Global Poverty, Food Security and Diets, claims that to understand the surge of global poverty in the COVID era, one must focus on the factors that are initiating it. He believes that the pandemic's impact on labour supply, the constant need for social distancing, reduction in savings and investment, coupled with lower demand for certain goods and services has pushed a major section of the populations of Asian countries into a state of joblessness and reduced options of income-earning opportunities.&amp;nbsp; And what seems to be inevitable is that for most economies the global recession and financial crises that COVID-19 has caused are far more intense than the financial crisis seen in 2008-2009. David Debucquet states that “the increases in poverty are concentrated in South Asia and Sub-Saharan Africa with impacts harder in urban areas than in rural areas. The COVID-19-related lockdown measures explain most of the fall in output, while declines in savings soften the adverse impacts on food consumption. Almost 150 million people are projected to fall into extreme poverty and food insecurity.” The International Labour Organisation (ILO) has attempted to understand how poverty has aggravated in the COVID era. According to their report published in 2020, the organisation estimated that during the first three quarters of 2020, the number of working hours worldwide declined by 17% relative to that in the last quarter of 2019; a drop equivalent to a loss of almost 500 million full-time jobs.&amp;nbsp; However, such figures tell us precious little. Homi Kharas, a senior fellow in the Center for Sustainable Development, in his article claims that it is surprising, and a harsh reality of the study of income poverty caused by COVID-19 that the world is less likely to know the full answers to the questions about it. He says that most of the poverty-related data that we find today has been collected from household surveys since it is close to impossible to conduct full-blown proper surveys in current conditions. He predicted that “compared to 2019, poverty in 2020 could rise by 120 million people. Compared to the baseline path for poverty, the 2020 figure is 144 million people higher. Some of this will be offset as economies start to recover in 2021, but the longer-term scenario suggests that half of the rise in poverty could be permanent. By 2030, the poverty numbers could still be higher than the baseline by 60 million people.” And if one goes by SDG indicators, Kharas was right.&amp;nbsp; The year 2020 did see a rise in poverty by 124 million (approx), of which 60% stem from South Asian countries. Some consider COVID-19 a temporary form of shock to the financial setups of most countries. This is interesting to note since countries such as China faced a sharp V-shaped recession and recovery, which most observers find fascinating and relevant. But, we must not overlook the economic damage that such quick shifts can cause has long term and almost everlasting effects on populations that have been pushed into poverty. Kharas claims that in terms of understanding poverty linked with COVID-19 one has to decipher what living with poverty entails and how long it lasts?&amp;nbsp; Kharas says, “The experience of living with poverty for short periods is harsh, but some families have coping mechanisms—assets they can sell, assistance from governments, relatives, and neighbours. But over longer periods, poverty leaves permanent scars—malnutrition, disease susceptibility, missed schooling. For this reason, it is useful to look at the longer-term impact of COVID-19 on poverty, despite all the caveats associated with any decade-long economic forecasts.” The impact of COVID-19 has essentially attacked income security and employment opportunities but what remains eminently visible is that the biggest threat that prevails is to food security. Reduction in incomes can not only cause a subsequent decline in demand for food items, but also encourage shifts in the mix of products consumed, notably resulting in less consumption of more nutrient-rich foods (like fruits, vegetables, and animal-sourced foods) and comparatively more calorie-rich foods (like essential grains and sugar). This drives up food insecurity. Context-specific estimates of the impacts of poverty and food insecurity are to some extent accessible; it will be years before wide-ranging and relevant survey-based information on these impacts will be presented to general public knowledge. Calculating the repercussions of the poverty impact of COVID-19 is no inconsequential topic to discuss and debate, it requires substantial and effective fixes that need to come about sooner than we think. This is not only because the crisis is still unfolding and available information of its precise socio-economic consequences is incomplete, but also because the channels of power are numerous and interconnected globally. Scholars have boiled their analysis of poverty in the COVID era down to the idea that “while several analyses of the poverty impacts have used simple tools provided by the World Bank’s website and assumed uniform shifts in the distribution of income per country to provide estimates of the impacts on poverty, (see, for example, the studies by the World Bank in Mahler et al., 2020 and World Bank, 2020b; and that of UN-WIDER by Sumner et al., 2020), we are concerned that this assumption fails to account for the complexity of the channels of effect and may substantially underestimate the impacts of the pandemic.”&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, the need of the hour remains in using effective methodology concerning understanding the effects of poverty and the arising need to solve the issues with it; As Nelson Mandela had once said, “Overcoming poverty is not a gesture of charity. It is an act of Justice.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sanitation: A Stinking Legacy of Social Stigma and Suffocation</title><link href="/Sanitation-A-Stinking-Legacy-of-Social-Stigma-and-Suffocation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sanitation: A Stinking Legacy of Social Stigma and Suffocation" /><published>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Sanitation-A-Stinking-Legacy-of-Social-Stigma-and-Suffocation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Sanitation-A-Stinking-Legacy-of-Social-Stigma-and-Suffocation">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are in your car with your windows down while it crosses a garbage dump or an open sewage drain. What would you do immediately? You will shut the car windows, perhaps make an annoyed face and cover your nose. But have you ever wondered about those who have to bear this smell - that too a hundred times more magnificent - those who are involved in manually cleaning it, daily?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one question that needs to be seriously pondered upon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every one of us has heard of the term - SANITATION. While most of us care about the sanitation and hygiene of ourselves and our homes, there are many who are deprived of sanitation in our society. It is so sad that on one hand, India has made significant progress in human and technological development wherein we are planning bullet trains, but on the other hand, it stands amongst the top in the list of countries with poor sanitation. The top 10% of the country enjoy clean and hygienic surroundings while there exists a community that makes its living by carrying human excreta and has no proper access to sanitation. Around 300 million Indians still practise open defecation. On top of it, every other day, one gets to hear of the death of sanitation workers working in extremely unhygienic conditions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanitation and cleaning are often linked to social stigma. It is considered as the work of the poor, more specifically to those belonging to lower castes in India. The caste system has impacted society to an extent that even basic sanitation and hygiene is considered to be a privilege. Our society not only differentiates spaces as pure and impure but also its people. Scooping out the filth and bearing the stench of sewage is considered as the legacy of the poor and lower castes; this social status has been pre-determined for ages and has remained that way. The most esteemed 'google' has&amp;nbsp; defined this work of manual scavenging as an inhuman practice and I won't even question the web! The sad fact is that in our country, not every person belonging to a lower caste is a manual scavenger but almost every sanitation worker does belong to a lower caste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From drains and sewers to septic tanks and railway tracks, millions of people are engaged in cleaning, carrying and disposing of human excreta in return for pittances of this humiliating job. People still believe - &lt;em&gt;&quot;Hamari jaati ke logo ka yahi kaam hota hai&quot;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&quot;hamare bache bhi yahi karenge.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; (&quot;People of our caste have only this work to do&quot; and &quot;Our children will also do this&quot;). It is astonishing to see how this age-old legacy created by our society has made them believe it to be their fate and destiny.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does this problem still exist? And are there not enough strict rules to deal with it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;'No manual scavenging deaths, 941 died while cleaning sewers'&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above statement was recently released by the government. It clearly points out a major problem. Even though there have been laws made to protect the dignity and rights of sanitation workers, either there is some flawed enactment within them or they are badly implemented. Although it has been claimed that there have been no deaths due to manual scavenging, does that mean it is justified to have deaths while cleaning sewers, when in reality there's hardly any difference between the two.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schemes and policies are being implemented in our country giving people the access to toilets but they haven't yet provided an appropriate and hygienic method for disposal. The manual work of carrying out human excreta is not only caste dependent, but also gender influenced. The majority of women from lower communities get paid as low as ₹10 to ₹50 per month for carrying human excreta. This reflects upon the huge irony which exists within the country. There have been schemes and policies aiming to protect the dignity of women by providing them with private sanitation spaces, while on the other hand, in reality their oppression has been further perpetuated through the humiliation of women dealing with human excreta.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actions and promises of the concerned authorities only come up at the time of elections with several inherent flaws. The multilevel-structural domination has left the sanitation workers with no option but to continue working. Moreover, government surveys are only confined to statutory towns, highlighting the fact that the concern is seen as an urban problem. This survey also misses out over a million estimated uncounted deaths of sanitation workers in the last 50 years who belonged to the private sector thereby not getting included. The pandemic also witnessed a surge in deaths of sanitation workers who handled the dead bodies in semi-urban and rural areas, and on the banks of the river Ganga.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem has prevailed for a long time and still continues to exist across regions. Despite the laws being in place, implementation and execution has been slow and redundant leading to numerous deaths over the years. The problem doesn’t limit itself to the present day workers but also to their families and generations that will follow. Attributing the job to certain vulnerable sections denies the people of their basic rights as individuals. This also sets up a ripple effect on the speed of development of a nation. Most of the workers suffer from severe illnesses and live shorter lives, thereby producing and earning less, and are unable to afford education and stable futures for their children.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need of the hour is to remove this blot on the idioms of justice. The social and gender issues related to sanitation have to be eradicated at the grassroots level. Assuring sustainable freedom not only requires awareness but also accessibility. Accessibility to alternate livelihood options with a right to a dignified life needs to be ensured. The problem of poor sanitation and such related issues won't be eradicated with the construction of toilets unless new and innovative ways to empty the pits without human intervention are explored. Moreover, a lot more difference can be made once individuals start thinking about the questions raised at the beginning of this article. The answer to 'how' will come up once it is truly understood by everyone!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shruti Indoria</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">Imagine you are in your car with your windows down while it crosses a garbage dump or an open sewage drain. What would you do immediately? You will shut the car windows, perhaps make an annoyed face and cover your nose. But have you ever wondered about those who have to bear this smell - that too a hundred times more magnificent - those who are involved in manually cleaning it, daily? This is one question that needs to be seriously pondered upon! Every one of us has heard of the term - SANITATION. While most of us care about the sanitation and hygiene of ourselves and our homes, there are many who are deprived of sanitation in our society. It is so sad that on one hand, India has made significant progress in human and technological development wherein we are planning bullet trains, but on the other hand, it stands amongst the top in the list of countries with poor sanitation. The top 10% of the country enjoy clean and hygienic surroundings while there exists a community that makes its living by carrying human excreta and has no proper access to sanitation. Around 300 million Indians still practise open defecation. On top of it, every other day, one gets to hear of the death of sanitation workers working in extremely unhygienic conditions.&amp;nbsp; Sanitation and cleaning are often linked to social stigma. It is considered as the work of the poor, more specifically to those belonging to lower castes in India. The caste system has impacted society to an extent that even basic sanitation and hygiene is considered to be a privilege. Our society not only differentiates spaces as pure and impure but also its people. Scooping out the filth and bearing the stench of sewage is considered as the legacy of the poor and lower castes; this social status has been pre-determined for ages and has remained that way. The most esteemed 'google' has&amp;nbsp; defined this work of manual scavenging as an inhuman practice and I won't even question the web! The sad fact is that in our country, not every person belonging to a lower caste is a manual scavenger but almost every sanitation worker does belong to a lower caste. From drains and sewers to septic tanks and railway tracks, millions of people are engaged in cleaning, carrying and disposing of human excreta in return for pittances of this humiliating job. People still believe - &quot;Hamari jaati ke logo ka yahi kaam hota hai&quot; and &quot;hamare bache bhi yahi karenge.&quot; (&quot;People of our caste have only this work to do&quot; and &quot;Our children will also do this&quot;). It is astonishing to see how this age-old legacy created by our society has made them believe it to be their fate and destiny.&amp;nbsp; Why does this problem still exist? And are there not enough strict rules to deal with it? 'No manual scavenging deaths, 941 died while cleaning sewers' The above statement was recently released by the government. It clearly points out a major problem. Even though there have been laws made to protect the dignity and rights of sanitation workers, either there is some flawed enactment within them or they are badly implemented. Although it has been claimed that there have been no deaths due to manual scavenging, does that mean it is justified to have deaths while cleaning sewers, when in reality there's hardly any difference between the two.&amp;nbsp; Schemes and policies are being implemented in our country giving people the access to toilets but they haven't yet provided an appropriate and hygienic method for disposal. The manual work of carrying out human excreta is not only caste dependent, but also gender influenced. The majority of women from lower communities get paid as low as ₹10 to ₹50 per month for carrying human excreta. This reflects upon the huge irony which exists within the country. There have been schemes and policies aiming to protect the dignity of women by providing them with private sanitation spaces, while on the other hand, in reality their oppression has been further perpetuated through the humiliation of women dealing with human excreta.&amp;nbsp; The actions and promises of the concerned authorities only come up at the time of elections with several inherent flaws. The multilevel-structural domination has left the sanitation workers with no option but to continue working. Moreover, government surveys are only confined to statutory towns, highlighting the fact that the concern is seen as an urban problem. This survey also misses out over a million estimated uncounted deaths of sanitation workers in the last 50 years who belonged to the private sector thereby not getting included. The pandemic also witnessed a surge in deaths of sanitation workers who handled the dead bodies in semi-urban and rural areas, and on the banks of the river Ganga.&amp;nbsp; The problem has prevailed for a long time and still continues to exist across regions. Despite the laws being in place, implementation and execution has been slow and redundant leading to numerous deaths over the years. The problem doesn’t limit itself to the present day workers but also to their families and generations that will follow. Attributing the job to certain vulnerable sections denies the people of their basic rights as individuals. This also sets up a ripple effect on the speed of development of a nation. Most of the workers suffer from severe illnesses and live shorter lives, thereby producing and earning less, and are unable to afford education and stable futures for their children.&amp;nbsp; The need of the hour is to remove this blot on the idioms of justice. The social and gender issues related to sanitation have to be eradicated at the grassroots level. Assuring sustainable freedom not only requires awareness but also accessibility. Accessibility to alternate livelihood options with a right to a dignified life needs to be ensured. The problem of poor sanitation and such related issues won't be eradicated with the construction of toilets unless new and innovative ways to empty the pits without human intervention are explored. Moreover, a lot more difference can be made once individuals start thinking about the questions raised at the beginning of this article. The answer to 'how' will come up once it is truly understood by everyone!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Greenhouse Gases and Empty Bowls</title><link href="/Greenhouse-Gases-and-Empty-Bowls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greenhouse Gases and Empty Bowls" /><published>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Greenhouse-Gases-and-Empty-Bowls</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Greenhouse-Gases-and-Empty-Bowls">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In October 2021, the Global Hunger Index ranked India at 101, slipping it seven ranks from 94, in a span of a single year. Even though the situation is particularly grim for India, the world, at present, stands on no winning side.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One out of seven people sleep on an empty stomach every night. India is not the only country of concern, rather its position is not as concerning as the African countries in the Sahara. While the condition in Somalia is ‘extremely alarming’, in countries like Chad, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Yemen, Madagascar and a few others, the condition has been categorised as ‘alarming’. Few of the South Asian countries too are the hotspots of hunger.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The adoption of the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals (2) aims at eradicating hunger, achieving food security, improving nutrition and promoting sustainable agriculture. This was signed by 193 countries that aim to eradicate any and all forms of malnutrition by 2030, which now looks implausible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With 820 million people suffering from chronic hunger, 20.5 million babies being born with low birth weight as their mothers couldn’t get enough nutrition, hunger has resulted in stunted growth of 149 million children. We, definitely, have a long road to travel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst the numerous reasons behind the rising hunger, the escalating climate emergency is a major contributor to this humanitarian emergency. The rapid economic growth that has been taking place for the last 150 years has resulted in a consequent rise in greenhouse gas emissions. This has pushed the average global temperature to 1°C above pre-industrial levels. The current rate of emissions, according to experts, will result in the average global temperature rising to somewhere between 1.5°C to 2°C in the period between 2030-2050.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Countries are predicted to have extremely hot weather conditions, untimely and heavy precipitation on the one hand, and a greater probability of droughts, on the other. These predictions are of utmost concern. Human systems, which includes food systems, will be largely affected due to these extreme conditions. Hunger and climate crises are inextricable in nature.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The United Nations World Food Programme (UNWFP) has analysed that a 2 °C rise in the average global temperature when compared to pre-industrial levels will result in an additional 189 million people being pushed to starve. The communities that are most vulnerable to this change include fishing, livestock and subsistence agriculture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To sum it up, all the communities that contribute the least to the climate crisis shall bear the maximum repercussions with no pillar to hold during the blow. Lack of safety nets will leave these communities dependent on humanitarian aid for their survival like the migrants of war across the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Not only this, the UNWFP has predicted that 41 million people (across 43 countries) shall bear the brunt of extreme famine. The poorer and underdeveloped countries are going to be the worst hit, even though they (i.e. the top ten food-insecure nations) contribute to only 0.08% of the global carbon emissions. Water scarcity, untimely rain, crop failure and declining nutrition due to multi-breadbasket failures shall threaten millions who have very little or no contribution to climate change.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The weather anomalies will affect the prices of food, and thus, its access to the poorer sections. Such effects shall not remain limited to specific regions as there exists a high degree of cross-connectedness between global food systems. Thus, extreme events in some regions hold the potential to disrupt the global food system. The lower-income countries will be, once again, the worst affected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Lack of safeguards against food insecurity and a fragile, rather deficit, capacity to adapt to climate change remain some of the many concerns for these countries. But the buck doesn’t stop here!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The nutrient value of the food items and the nutrients absorbed also change with changes in climatic conditions. The food item cultivated is likely to contain a decreased amount of protein, zinc and iron. This is because higher concentrations of carbon dioxide in the environment result in the reduction of these nutrients; this has been backed by recent studies. An additional 175 million people could be deficient in zinc with 122 million more people experiencing protein deficiency by 2050, if this trend continues.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact is not limited to crops, livestock shall suffer equally. Livestock is the second worst-hit sector during droughts. Those dependent on aquatic life as a means of living and for food, are not better-placed either. The fish are extremely vulnerable to constant changes in temperature and climate extremes. No surprise that the affected regions will include South and Southeast Asia, Africa and the Middle East. The amalgamation of these deficiencies, increased prices and poor health infrastructure does not present a very happy picture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Resilience-building amongst the vulnerable sections is the need of the hour in order to attain food security. The absence of collective and large-scale action increases the distance between the world and the goals of Agenda 2030 (to eradicate any and all forms of malnutrition by 2030).&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Grassroot-level actions plans and locally adaptable dietary plans will work in the long run instead of generic and single plans for the entire world. Wondering, why? Red meat consumption amongst Americans is 6.5 times more than the recommendation. On the other hand, South Asians consume only half of what is required for a healthy body. In the absence of the same starting line, how will we achieve the same milestone together?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We must view the food systems using the prism of adaptation to climate change and mitigation. This includes making the most vulnerable sections resilient to both climate change and pandemics. The continuous efforts to a greener and more sustainable planet should not lose the spotlight in this process. Governments need to come together with stronger partnerships and cooperation. Sailing the boat will become easier if the private sector and civil society organisations are also roped in. Financing the adaptation needs to be discussed in detail. The current kitty is insufficient in building resilience to climate change. Multilateral development banks and other financial institutions will have to be put to good use in order to attain the goals of Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the meantime, protecting and improving the livelihoods of the vulnerable communities, adaptation practices in agriculture (for climate resilient crops like millet) can be put into place for nutritional security. Innovation for small-holder farmers coupled with information related to climate change, and inculcating preparedness can help the ‘developing’ countries like India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Reimagining food systems towards sustainability, mitigation and balancing growth should be the new route to eradicate hunger.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">In October 2021, the Global Hunger Index ranked India at 101, slipping it seven ranks from 94, in a span of a single year. Even though the situation is particularly grim for India, the world, at present, stands on no winning side.&amp;nbsp; One out of seven people sleep on an empty stomach every night. India is not the only country of concern, rather its position is not as concerning as the African countries in the Sahara. While the condition in Somalia is ‘extremely alarming’, in countries like Chad, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Yemen, Madagascar and a few others, the condition has been categorised as ‘alarming’. Few of the South Asian countries too are the hotspots of hunger.&amp;nbsp; The adoption of the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals (2) aims at eradicating hunger, achieving food security, improving nutrition and promoting sustainable agriculture. This was signed by 193 countries that aim to eradicate any and all forms of malnutrition by 2030, which now looks implausible.&amp;nbsp; With 820 million people suffering from chronic hunger, 20.5 million babies being born with low birth weight as their mothers couldn’t get enough nutrition, hunger has resulted in stunted growth of 149 million children. We, definitely, have a long road to travel! Amidst the numerous reasons behind the rising hunger, the escalating climate emergency is a major contributor to this humanitarian emergency. The rapid economic growth that has been taking place for the last 150 years has resulted in a consequent rise in greenhouse gas emissions. This has pushed the average global temperature to 1°C above pre-industrial levels. The current rate of emissions, according to experts, will result in the average global temperature rising to somewhere between 1.5°C to 2°C in the period between 2030-2050.&amp;nbsp; Countries are predicted to have extremely hot weather conditions, untimely and heavy precipitation on the one hand, and a greater probability of droughts, on the other. These predictions are of utmost concern. Human systems, which includes food systems, will be largely affected due to these extreme conditions. Hunger and climate crises are inextricable in nature.&amp;nbsp; The United Nations World Food Programme (UNWFP) has analysed that a 2 °C rise in the average global temperature when compared to pre-industrial levels will result in an additional 189 million people being pushed to starve. The communities that are most vulnerable to this change include fishing, livestock and subsistence agriculture.&amp;nbsp; To sum it up, all the communities that contribute the least to the climate crisis shall bear the maximum repercussions with no pillar to hold during the blow. Lack of safety nets will leave these communities dependent on humanitarian aid for their survival like the migrants of war across the world.&amp;nbsp; Not only this, the UNWFP has predicted that 41 million people (across 43 countries) shall bear the brunt of extreme famine. The poorer and underdeveloped countries are going to be the worst hit, even though they (i.e. the top ten food-insecure nations) contribute to only 0.08% of the global carbon emissions. Water scarcity, untimely rain, crop failure and declining nutrition due to multi-breadbasket failures shall threaten millions who have very little or no contribution to climate change.&amp;nbsp; The weather anomalies will affect the prices of food, and thus, its access to the poorer sections. Such effects shall not remain limited to specific regions as there exists a high degree of cross-connectedness between global food systems. Thus, extreme events in some regions hold the potential to disrupt the global food system. The lower-income countries will be, once again, the worst affected.&amp;nbsp; Lack of safeguards against food insecurity and a fragile, rather deficit, capacity to adapt to climate change remain some of the many concerns for these countries. But the buck doesn’t stop here!&amp;nbsp; The nutrient value of the food items and the nutrients absorbed also change with changes in climatic conditions. The food item cultivated is likely to contain a decreased amount of protein, zinc and iron. This is because higher concentrations of carbon dioxide in the environment result in the reduction of these nutrients; this has been backed by recent studies. An additional 175 million people could be deficient in zinc with 122 million more people experiencing protein deficiency by 2050, if this trend continues.&amp;nbsp; The impact is not limited to crops, livestock shall suffer equally. Livestock is the second worst-hit sector during droughts. Those dependent on aquatic life as a means of living and for food, are not better-placed either. The fish are extremely vulnerable to constant changes in temperature and climate extremes. No surprise that the affected regions will include South and Southeast Asia, Africa and the Middle East. The amalgamation of these deficiencies, increased prices and poor health infrastructure does not present a very happy picture.&amp;nbsp; Resilience-building amongst the vulnerable sections is the need of the hour in order to attain food security. The absence of collective and large-scale action increases the distance between the world and the goals of Agenda 2030 (to eradicate any and all forms of malnutrition by 2030).&amp;nbsp; Grassroot-level actions plans and locally adaptable dietary plans will work in the long run instead of generic and single plans for the entire world. Wondering, why? Red meat consumption amongst Americans is 6.5 times more than the recommendation. On the other hand, South Asians consume only half of what is required for a healthy body. In the absence of the same starting line, how will we achieve the same milestone together?&amp;nbsp; We must view the food systems using the prism of adaptation to climate change and mitigation. This includes making the most vulnerable sections resilient to both climate change and pandemics. The continuous efforts to a greener and more sustainable planet should not lose the spotlight in this process. Governments need to come together with stronger partnerships and cooperation. Sailing the boat will become easier if the private sector and civil society organisations are also roped in. Financing the adaptation needs to be discussed in detail. The current kitty is insufficient in building resilience to climate change. Multilateral development banks and other financial institutions will have to be put to good use in order to attain the goals of Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp; In the meantime, protecting and improving the livelihoods of the vulnerable communities, adaptation practices in agriculture (for climate resilient crops like millet) can be put into place for nutritional security. Innovation for small-holder farmers coupled with information related to climate change, and inculcating preparedness can help the ‘developing’ countries like India.&amp;nbsp; Reimagining food systems towards sustainability, mitigation and balancing growth should be the new route to eradicate hunger.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Water Supply &amp;amp; Sanitation: Private vs Public Sector</title><link href="/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Water Supply &amp; Sanitation: Private vs Public Sector" /><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector">&lt;p&gt;Today, about 2.6 billion people live without basic sanitation and nearly 1.1 billion live without access to safe drinking water. Around 13% of the world population still defecates in the open. The&amp;nbsp; diarrhoeal diseases that result from poor sanitation kill more than five million children every year and 9% of these deaths happen to be of children aged less than five years. Up to 50% of malnutrition is attributable to poor water, sanitation and hygiene, as are many neglected tropical diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Death and disease due to inadequate sanitation not only burdens a country's healthcare system, it also causes a huge emotional and financial cost to families. Children drop out of school and fail to reach their potential, especially young girls. Moreover, research shows how poor sanitation has a substantial impact on the economy as well. Countries with poor access to sanitation are losing significant proportions of their GDP – in India, this figure is over 5%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It thus stands to reason that we need better sanitation for a better economy, a better society and a better world. The question is: how do we achieve that? Moreover, which sector should cater to Water Supply and Sanitation (WSS)? Private or Public?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economists champion public sector involvement in cases of market failures and unequal distribution of economic outcomes. The prime justification for public provision of WSS is market failures such as natural monopoly, externalities, and public good characteristics. A sole profit-oriented producer of a good with declining long-term average cost will restrict output to monopoly level, thereby leading to a social welfare loss. Thus, government intervention is essential to restore efficiency. Moreover, the positive externalities gained from use of WSS further strengthens this argument. It is the responsibility of the government to not just focus on efficiency (the primary focus of profit-oriented enterprises) but also to make sure that distribution is provided to all, without any disparity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, experiences from the past have shown that public-owned utilities have not always been successful both in developed and developing nations. This has been especially so in the latter case owing to various non-market failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public WSS services have remained lacking on grounds of efficiency. Large proportions of the population have little or no access to public WSS services, while the remaining who receive it often face issues of poor quality, characterised by frequent breakdowns and unreliable supply.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, these water utilities barely have enough to cover operational costs, leaving no surplus available to finance the expansion of networks, eventually leading to a downward spiral in customer service. This results in the consumer's reluctance to pay higher tariffs ultimately leading to a deterioration of assets and squandering of financial resources. This descending cycle attracts political interference and furthers the velocity of the fall.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, divergence of personal gains of employees from the social goals and absence of reliable measures to hold such officials accountable further exacerbates the deplorable functioning of such organisations. These organisations become hotbeds of corruption and maladministration. Hence, there have been growing views in favour of privatisation for increased competition and better efficiency. Furthermore, WSS does fulfil the prerequisite of a private good by being rivalrous in nature, and the additional benefits associated with its consumption generates a stronger incentive for individuals to pay higher for obtaining better quality services.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private sector has long played a role in the water sector, particularly in the industrialised economies. Historically, water supplies in many cities of the US were provided by private players until the government reverted the ownership to itself. The WSS services are entirely provided by the private sector in countries such as the UK, France, Philippines, etc.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owing to the principal role of Water and Sanitation, such countries do have in place mechanisms where the government has oversight over the private sector. It accomplishes this through models which outsource management and supply of WSS while retaining public ownership, or by providing concessions against contracts, or through the presence of a regulatory agency. The only exception is France where there exists no sort of supervision by the administration. Private sector involvement in such a key area of the economy presents numerous risks for the former, such as commercial, financial, technical, legal and political risks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commercial risks involve the fear that the private investors may not be able to recoup their investment and make a profit, while technical risks pertain to insufficient knowledge about the state of installations resulting in operational failures. Legal risks occur as a result of contractual disputes, while financial risks relate to currency devaluations and convertibility of local to foreign currency, especially when foreign borrowings are used to finance services. Political risks stem from governments' changing policy in the course of implementation of the contract or due to their reluctance in charging higher tariffs.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example to illustrate the risks posed could be seen in the case of Argentina. Water privatisation in Argentina began in 1992, where certain concessions were awarded by the administration to private companies. Post 2001, all concessions were terminated under the leadership of a different government on the basis that the contracts were not fulfilled by the providing company. The private companies conceded to their failure in meeting the targets, but argued that a freeze in tariffs at the time of the devaluation of the Peso during the Argentine economic crisis violated the contract, and thus, made it impossible for them to achieve the set targets. In July 2010, the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID) ruled in favour of the private concessionaires and entitled them to compensation. Thus, there were losses faced by both the private companies and the government, with no winners in such a fight.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private sector participation (in such areas) has generally been touted as the solution to the pressing need of huge capital investments in the water sector. However, the ability of the private sector to actually invest in water infrastructure is doubtful. As per the Global Water Partnership, estimates of the total investment needs for new water infrastructure amounted to $180 billion per year for the period of 2000–2005. However, according to historical data, total private investment in WSS has averaged $3.3 billion per year, i.e. only about 1.8% of the annual investment needs of developing countries. In Asia, the annual average private investment of $1.9 billion in water (World Bank PPI database) accounts for 7.9% of the total financing needs of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another claimed basis for involvement of private players is increased competition so as to improve the overall efficiency. However, the investment level in the distribution networks is massive relative to the size of the market, which obscures the potential for direct product market competition in developing countries. The entry to this market is often done on contractual basis from governments but factors like political risks, long payback periods, huge sunk costs and high degree of non-transparency while awarding the contracts deter private sector participation. Additionally, there has not been any substantial data to evidently prove the productive efficiency of the private sector in sanitation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one of the most important arguments in favour of private sector participation is the expansion in the scope of services due to the huge resources it brings with it. However, this theoretical abundance is difficult to translate into actions in the developing economies for the following reasons: 1) On the demand side, the unwillingness of the consumers to pay cost-recovering tariffs (maybe due to unawareness of the benefits of WSS); and 2) on the supply side, neglect of the poor by profit-oriented firms which pursue only the wealthy section to recoup their large investments. Moreover, rural areas have scattered populations that often present technical, organisational, and financial sustainability issues, thus proving to be unviable for private companies. As per data, private investments have appeared to have benefited the relatively wealthier countries due to the lower risks associated with them in ways such as market friendly policy and institutional environments, high household incomes, effective regulatory mechanisms, etc.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate, in the period 1990–2005, of the total&amp;nbsp; investment of $46.2 billion in WSS, the upper middle, lower middle and the lowest income nations captured 56%, 43% and 1% respectively.&amp;nbsp; Thus, one can conclude that provision of water supply and sanitation is not a game of either-or, rather an affair where the nation needs to create an enabling environment that can harness innovation and good governance for achieving success.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">Today, about 2.6 billion people live without basic sanitation and nearly 1.1 billion live without access to safe drinking water. Around 13% of the world population still defecates in the open. The&amp;nbsp; diarrhoeal diseases that result from poor sanitation kill more than five million children every year and 9% of these deaths happen to be of children aged less than five years. Up to 50% of malnutrition is attributable to poor water, sanitation and hygiene, as are many neglected tropical diseases. Death and disease due to inadequate sanitation not only burdens a country's healthcare system, it also causes a huge emotional and financial cost to families. Children drop out of school and fail to reach their potential, especially young girls. Moreover, research shows how poor sanitation has a substantial impact on the economy as well. Countries with poor access to sanitation are losing significant proportions of their GDP – in India, this figure is over 5%. It thus stands to reason that we need better sanitation for a better economy, a better society and a better world. The question is: how do we achieve that? Moreover, which sector should cater to Water Supply and Sanitation (WSS)? Private or Public? Economists champion public sector involvement in cases of market failures and unequal distribution of economic outcomes. The prime justification for public provision of WSS is market failures such as natural monopoly, externalities, and public good characteristics. A sole profit-oriented producer of a good with declining long-term average cost will restrict output to monopoly level, thereby leading to a social welfare loss. Thus, government intervention is essential to restore efficiency. Moreover, the positive externalities gained from use of WSS further strengthens this argument. It is the responsibility of the government to not just focus on efficiency (the primary focus of profit-oriented enterprises) but also to make sure that distribution is provided to all, without any disparity.&amp;nbsp; However, experiences from the past have shown that public-owned utilities have not always been successful both in developed and developing nations. This has been especially so in the latter case owing to various non-market failures. Public WSS services have remained lacking on grounds of efficiency. Large proportions of the population have little or no access to public WSS services, while the remaining who receive it often face issues of poor quality, characterised by frequent breakdowns and unreliable supply.&amp;nbsp; Simultaneously, these water utilities barely have enough to cover operational costs, leaving no surplus available to finance the expansion of networks, eventually leading to a downward spiral in customer service. This results in the consumer's reluctance to pay higher tariffs ultimately leading to a deterioration of assets and squandering of financial resources. This descending cycle attracts political interference and furthers the velocity of the fall.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, divergence of personal gains of employees from the social goals and absence of reliable measures to hold such officials accountable further exacerbates the deplorable functioning of such organisations. These organisations become hotbeds of corruption and maladministration. Hence, there have been growing views in favour of privatisation for increased competition and better efficiency. Furthermore, WSS does fulfil the prerequisite of a private good by being rivalrous in nature, and the additional benefits associated with its consumption generates a stronger incentive for individuals to pay higher for obtaining better quality services.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The private sector has long played a role in the water sector, particularly in the industrialised economies. Historically, water supplies in many cities of the US were provided by private players until the government reverted the ownership to itself. The WSS services are entirely provided by the private sector in countries such as the UK, France, Philippines, etc.&amp;nbsp; Owing to the principal role of Water and Sanitation, such countries do have in place mechanisms where the government has oversight over the private sector. It accomplishes this through models which outsource management and supply of WSS while retaining public ownership, or by providing concessions against contracts, or through the presence of a regulatory agency. The only exception is France where there exists no sort of supervision by the administration. Private sector involvement in such a key area of the economy presents numerous risks for the former, such as commercial, financial, technical, legal and political risks.&amp;nbsp; Commercial risks involve the fear that the private investors may not be able to recoup their investment and make a profit, while technical risks pertain to insufficient knowledge about the state of installations resulting in operational failures. Legal risks occur as a result of contractual disputes, while financial risks relate to currency devaluations and convertibility of local to foreign currency, especially when foreign borrowings are used to finance services. Political risks stem from governments' changing policy in the course of implementation of the contract or due to their reluctance in charging higher tariffs.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; An example to illustrate the risks posed could be seen in the case of Argentina. Water privatisation in Argentina began in 1992, where certain concessions were awarded by the administration to private companies. Post 2001, all concessions were terminated under the leadership of a different government on the basis that the contracts were not fulfilled by the providing company. The private companies conceded to their failure in meeting the targets, but argued that a freeze in tariffs at the time of the devaluation of the Peso during the Argentine economic crisis violated the contract, and thus, made it impossible for them to achieve the set targets. In July 2010, the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID) ruled in favour of the private concessionaires and entitled them to compensation. Thus, there were losses faced by both the private companies and the government, with no winners in such a fight.&amp;nbsp; Private sector participation (in such areas) has generally been touted as the solution to the pressing need of huge capital investments in the water sector. However, the ability of the private sector to actually invest in water infrastructure is doubtful. As per the Global Water Partnership, estimates of the total investment needs for new water infrastructure amounted to $180 billion per year for the period of 2000–2005. However, according to historical data, total private investment in WSS has averaged $3.3 billion per year, i.e. only about 1.8% of the annual investment needs of developing countries. In Asia, the annual average private investment of $1.9 billion in water (World Bank PPI database) accounts for 7.9% of the total financing needs of the region. Another claimed basis for involvement of private players is increased competition so as to improve the overall efficiency. However, the investment level in the distribution networks is massive relative to the size of the market, which obscures the potential for direct product market competition in developing countries. The entry to this market is often done on contractual basis from governments but factors like political risks, long payback periods, huge sunk costs and high degree of non-transparency while awarding the contracts deter private sector participation. Additionally, there has not been any substantial data to evidently prove the productive efficiency of the private sector in sanitation.&amp;nbsp; Lastly, one of the most important arguments in favour of private sector participation is the expansion in the scope of services due to the huge resources it brings with it. However, this theoretical abundance is difficult to translate into actions in the developing economies for the following reasons: 1) On the demand side, the unwillingness of the consumers to pay cost-recovering tariffs (maybe due to unawareness of the benefits of WSS); and 2) on the supply side, neglect of the poor by profit-oriented firms which pursue only the wealthy section to recoup their large investments. Moreover, rural areas have scattered populations that often present technical, organisational, and financial sustainability issues, thus proving to be unviable for private companies. As per data, private investments have appeared to have benefited the relatively wealthier countries due to the lower risks associated with them in ways such as market friendly policy and institutional environments, high household incomes, effective regulatory mechanisms, etc.&amp;nbsp; To illustrate, in the period 1990–2005, of the total&amp;nbsp; investment of $46.2 billion in WSS, the upper middle, lower middle and the lowest income nations captured 56%, 43% and 1% respectively.&amp;nbsp; Thus, one can conclude that provision of water supply and sanitation is not a game of either-or, rather an affair where the nation needs to create an enabling environment that can harness innovation and good governance for achieving success.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Healthcare Mantra for This Decade: Actionable, Accessible, Affordable!</title><link href="/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Healthcare Mantra for This Decade: Actionable, Accessible, Affordable! " /><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable-</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable">&lt;p&gt;While I was lazing around on a Sunday evening after spending the day watching some pointless TV show on Netflix, which would never further my intellect at any particular matter, my father pointedly remarked to me, ‘Health is Wealth! Go exercise your muscles for once.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That statement truly struck my brain muscles. I decided to exercise those for a change since I was too much of a sloth to get out and workout. It dawned upon me that the statement was absolutely bogus. Wonder why? In my limited experience of 23 years on this planet, it has often become vividly clear to me that indeed the reverse is true, ‘Wealth is Health.’ To die a death of peace, without gasping for oxygen, while sitting on a wheelchair, waiting outside a hospital for a bed and a cylinder, you would have needed (on an average) a few hundred thousand rupees back in May 2021 in New Delhi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to know the median household income in India? Well, it’s a handsome round off of about fifty thousand rupees per annum. Which begs the ultimate question, why is basic healthcare so expensive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With socio-health inequalities being a raging issue of debate for most forums amidst the Covid era, the discussion has always started and ended with the incompetency of the government and the neglect of the public health infrastructure, respectively. Do I agree with that? Not in its entirety. But to delve deeper into how this mechanism works, it would be prudent for one to revisit the consequential economic steppingstones to such inequities around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health Inequity, not Inequality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to address that health inequality should not be diluted into the mix of health inequity. That’s simply because health inequality is generally a by-product of disorders which kick in with older age, and often are hereditary, or genetic problems. For example, my mother’s forlorn battle with &lt;em&gt;Rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/em&gt; is one such inequality that couldn’t be helped.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the health inequity that the modern world faces so rampantly today, is different from my mother’s story. Health inequity often stems from a valley surrounded by the challenging mountains of income, physical environment, social support inequalities. Those are few of the major inequalities which isolate the socio-economically disadvantaged population into facing the burnt of a forged inequity arising from the disbalanced opportunities across our demographies. You literally must climb up the socio-economic mountain to attain the accessibility of such refined services and thus, better your chances at living a healthier and longer life. For example, research shows that asthma hospitalisations are over 1.5 times more in the lower-income neighbourhoods compared to the higher-income ones. Now this combined with our improved understanding of climate change, the ill-effects of bad air quality, and the ever-so-frequent cyclones, and floods, it is no joke when we finally realise that the physical and economic confinements of an individual lead them to bearing significant disadvantages in a health battle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health is a Right, not a Commodity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as an Economics major (which I am not sure if I should pride myself in), I cannot help but look at the notions of demand, supply, and utility in all aspects of life. They start with me succumbing to the urges of buying more affordable clothing from regular labour law abusers to deliberating if it's the healthcare policies which are truly at fault or not.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the situation from a strict Demand-Supply angle, I concede to the concept that government intervention is useless and give into the argument “let the forces of market play out to acquire efficiency”. Ah yes, ‘efficiency,’ the ‘It’ word of Economics. It is supposed to solve all our problems, right? Well, again not entirely true, just like every other ‘rational’ answer in economics which is based on an unstable jenga of numerous assumptions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow me to explain the jargon of ‘efficiency’ to you. &lt;em&gt;Economic efficiency&lt;/em&gt; is defined as a state where all goods and factors of production are distributed or productively allocated amongst the consumers to eliminate any chances of waste. However, what the jargon often leaves behind is the inability of efficiency to incorporate all players in the market. For example, if someone has more money at his or her disposal, then that person is perfectly capable and encouraged to acquire the scarce resource at a higher price while defeating another without those means. You know the saddest truth of healthcare? It is a Scarce Resource.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the statement “let the market play out” along with the assumption that the intervention of government only leads to market failures (through monopolistic behaviour) is ridiculous and a sure shot at worsening the pickle that we already find ourselves in. Therefore, it is time to set the record straight, “Affordable healthcare is my Right, no matter if I am poor or rich, today or tomorrow.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Pharma: Saints or Satan?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter the number of conventions, agreements and vigilance of health authorities, the pharmaceutical companies can not stop making billions off the pain of the global citizens. Again, going back to the demand and supply argument. The demand and supply should meet at equilibrium to fix the market prices. But it is a little different for drugs, especially life-saving ones. People simply don't have the option to refuse the exorbitant prices of drugs such as Hepatitis C or HIV, which gives the companies a massive leverage to fix prices as per their whims and profit margin targets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, let’s talk about Turing Pharmaceuticals and the CEO Martin Shkreli who hiked the price of an essential drug, &lt;em&gt;Daraprim&lt;/em&gt;, by 5,000% (from $13.50 to $750). This begs the question: Can buying licences to public funded research and innovations, and then hiking prices to make the public pay for it, even legal? According to the laws, mostly it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview when asked about what he would have liked to do differently, Shkreli went on to answer that “Healthcare prices are inelastic, I could have raised it higher and made more profits for my shareholders.” This one statement sums up the motive with which big pharma operates; they are not responsible for their patients, they are answerable to their shareholders and investors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unrivalled power in the lobbying halls of the American Congress and parliaments around the world has made big pharma the ultimate power player when it comes to deciding if we even have a shot at surviving. Even though they operate within the realms of humanity, they possess the strings to make us all dance on their commands. Recurring malaria symptoms due to a sudden lack of affordability to &lt;em&gt;Daraprim&lt;/em&gt; is not fateful, it is planned.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public-Private Partnerships: A farce or a force?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategic intervention of public policy in the healthcare sector is the need of the hour. In recent years, governments, international organisations and even private players have conceded to the argument that equality of opportunity should be the moral foundation to build our policies. The World Bank, for instance, has started using a Human Opportunity Index as one of the relevant indicators to assess social, human and economic development aspects.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many government initiatives, for example the Midday Meal Scheme in India, is geared towards ensuring social and educational protection routed through the maintenance of nutritional standards for children hailing from lower income communities. As deeply deliberated by economists Amartya Sen and Jean Dreze, nutritional inadequacies can often lead to future health problems, thus, making the poor vulnerable in a competitive labour market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, socio-health protection can stimulate economic growth for developing nations and be a key factor to combat a macroeconomic crisis. But the main problem, when seen through the lenses of developing countries, is often the laid-back attitude of the public sector projects which when coupled with a bar of fiscal deficit, can be difficult obstacles in planning a long-term inclusive plan. To bring in the private players into this mold would mean that it would contribute to capital accumulation and investment, risk management and offer diverse potential advantages to indirect stakeholders through multiplier effects. Therefore, bringing in private funding with the main hold of government in steering things to the correct conclusion, pricing, can be the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having suggested the inclusion of private players into the mold of healthcare, I must address the problem of private players slowly taking the charge to invest and maximise profits through expensive medication (inelastic demand). Therefore, the onus must lie upon the government to take action, diversify research, be responsible and accountable to the public at large, and be strict with the pricing models.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Am I Satisfied or Worried?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I would say, I am ‘impressed’. Don’t get me wrong, the statistics of COVID-19 cases unfolding while I cough my heart out to write these soulful words, has me chilled to my bones. But the honest truth is that the pandemic is here to stay. Yes, we already have a delta plus omicron variant and booster jabs available but it is not that which has impressed me (I am not a supporter of dystopia, in fact I am already dreading the advent of “oxicron”). I am impressed by the fact that our newsrooms, classrooms, zoom meetings and daily chats are now (more than ever before) focused on ‘health.’ It is probably for the first time in history that we have realised how much our lives are worth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of my favourite dialogues from the movie &lt;em&gt;Troy&lt;/em&gt; (2004), the character Odysseus goes on to tell Achilles that “War is young men dying, and old men talking.” In my opinion, this battle against Covid has proven yet again that neglect in the healthcare systems will cost us lives at all fronts, no matter how boldly the wise, grey haired intellectuals deliberate on fixing the situation without adequate expenditures. The advent of COVID-19 with the surges in internet usage around the globe has made interaction possible between people living in different continents. The debate of healthcare affordability is now no longer limited to the fancy parliament halls and the elite think tanks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, the global citizens, have proudly taken a step forward to progress the discussions on affordable healthcare, equitable healthcare, climate change and so much more. The GDP figures are not impressive any more. In fact they are on a dedicated downhill safari. What will it take to impress us? An increase in human development and opportunity indices, for starters, would be good. The discussions on our physical and mental health would be even better.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier (pre-Covid) the politics in my country India would generally revolve around two parties trying to degrade one another with quirkier rhetoric. Now, I am not denying that those rhetorics weren’t fun. They are an absolute amaze, both for meme and conversation purposes. Who in the world would not enjoy a wholesome trash talk between the ‘defenders of faith’. It is terribly fun to watch. But it is not the essence of our existence as politics made us believe in. Our population will only truly prosper when everyone has equal opportunities and access. The world has finally started demanding what is truly theirs, and now we are debating these topics in our homes. Home, where the general scope of discussion was limited to taking trash out and gossiping about neighbours. That is steep progress according to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I am hopeful when I say that I am looking forward to this decade’s unfolding. This will no doubt be one of the most ‘efficient,’ remarkable and decisive decades of human history. This time the war will not be fought on the enemy lines, rather it will be fought within our homes as we sanitise our hands and take those jabs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has brought more than 19 months of caged life. So much so that going out without a mask feels alien to me at this point. But what it also helped us realise is that being healthy (and ‘negative’) is golden. Therefore, socio-health protection, extensive public health research funding and awareness is required if we are to be the ‘defenders of human existence’ and strike down these ultra effective viruses and other anomalies. By being ultra productive in building infrastructure for it and investing in pertinent research, maybe we will have a shot at it. But above all what is to be appreciated amid all of this chaos, is the resilience of humankind in not giving up. So, three cheers to humanity at large!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">While I was lazing around on a Sunday evening after spending the day watching some pointless TV show on Netflix, which would never further my intellect at any particular matter, my father pointedly remarked to me, ‘Health is Wealth! Go exercise your muscles for once.’ That statement truly struck my brain muscles. I decided to exercise those for a change since I was too much of a sloth to get out and workout. It dawned upon me that the statement was absolutely bogus. Wonder why? In my limited experience of 23 years on this planet, it has often become vividly clear to me that indeed the reverse is true, ‘Wealth is Health.’ To die a death of peace, without gasping for oxygen, while sitting on a wheelchair, waiting outside a hospital for a bed and a cylinder, you would have needed (on an average) a few hundred thousand rupees back in May 2021 in New Delhi.&amp;nbsp; Want to know the median household income in India? Well, it’s a handsome round off of about fifty thousand rupees per annum. Which begs the ultimate question, why is basic healthcare so expensive? With socio-health inequalities being a raging issue of debate for most forums amidst the Covid era, the discussion has always started and ended with the incompetency of the government and the neglect of the public health infrastructure, respectively. Do I agree with that? Not in its entirety. But to delve deeper into how this mechanism works, it would be prudent for one to revisit the consequential economic steppingstones to such inequities around the world. Health Inequity, not Inequality It is important to address that health inequality should not be diluted into the mix of health inequity. That’s simply because health inequality is generally a by-product of disorders which kick in with older age, and often are hereditary, or genetic problems. For example, my mother’s forlorn battle with Rheumatoid arthritis is one such inequality that couldn’t be helped.&amp;nbsp; However, the health inequity that the modern world faces so rampantly today, is different from my mother’s story. Health inequity often stems from a valley surrounded by the challenging mountains of income, physical environment, social support inequalities. Those are few of the major inequalities which isolate the socio-economically disadvantaged population into facing the burnt of a forged inequity arising from the disbalanced opportunities across our demographies. You literally must climb up the socio-economic mountain to attain the accessibility of such refined services and thus, better your chances at living a healthier and longer life. For example, research shows that asthma hospitalisations are over 1.5 times more in the lower-income neighbourhoods compared to the higher-income ones. Now this combined with our improved understanding of climate change, the ill-effects of bad air quality, and the ever-so-frequent cyclones, and floods, it is no joke when we finally realise that the physical and economic confinements of an individual lead them to bearing significant disadvantages in a health battle. Health is a Right, not a Commodity Now, as an Economics major (which I am not sure if I should pride myself in), I cannot help but look at the notions of demand, supply, and utility in all aspects of life. They start with me succumbing to the urges of buying more affordable clothing from regular labour law abusers to deliberating if it's the healthcare policies which are truly at fault or not.&amp;nbsp; Looking at the situation from a strict Demand-Supply angle, I concede to the concept that government intervention is useless and give into the argument “let the forces of market play out to acquire efficiency”. Ah yes, ‘efficiency,’ the ‘It’ word of Economics. It is supposed to solve all our problems, right? Well, again not entirely true, just like every other ‘rational’ answer in economics which is based on an unstable jenga of numerous assumptions.&amp;nbsp; Allow me to explain the jargon of ‘efficiency’ to you. Economic efficiency is defined as a state where all goods and factors of production are distributed or productively allocated amongst the consumers to eliminate any chances of waste. However, what the jargon often leaves behind is the inability of efficiency to incorporate all players in the market. For example, if someone has more money at his or her disposal, then that person is perfectly capable and encouraged to acquire the scarce resource at a higher price while defeating another without those means. You know the saddest truth of healthcare? It is a Scarce Resource.&amp;nbsp; Therefore, the statement “let the market play out” along with the assumption that the intervention of government only leads to market failures (through monopolistic behaviour) is ridiculous and a sure shot at worsening the pickle that we already find ourselves in. Therefore, it is time to set the record straight, “Affordable healthcare is my Right, no matter if I am poor or rich, today or tomorrow.”&amp;nbsp; Big Pharma: Saints or Satan? No matter the number of conventions, agreements and vigilance of health authorities, the pharmaceutical companies can not stop making billions off the pain of the global citizens. Again, going back to the demand and supply argument. The demand and supply should meet at equilibrium to fix the market prices. But it is a little different for drugs, especially life-saving ones. People simply don't have the option to refuse the exorbitant prices of drugs such as Hepatitis C or HIV, which gives the companies a massive leverage to fix prices as per their whims and profit margin targets.&amp;nbsp; For instance, let’s talk about Turing Pharmaceuticals and the CEO Martin Shkreli who hiked the price of an essential drug, Daraprim, by 5,000% (from $13.50 to $750). This begs the question: Can buying licences to public funded research and innovations, and then hiking prices to make the public pay for it, even legal? According to the laws, mostly it is. In an interview when asked about what he would have liked to do differently, Shkreli went on to answer that “Healthcare prices are inelastic, I could have raised it higher and made more profits for my shareholders.” This one statement sums up the motive with which big pharma operates; they are not responsible for their patients, they are answerable to their shareholders and investors.&amp;nbsp; The unrivalled power in the lobbying halls of the American Congress and parliaments around the world has made big pharma the ultimate power player when it comes to deciding if we even have a shot at surviving. Even though they operate within the realms of humanity, they possess the strings to make us all dance on their commands. Recurring malaria symptoms due to a sudden lack of affordability to Daraprim is not fateful, it is planned.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Public-Private Partnerships: A farce or a force? Strategic intervention of public policy in the healthcare sector is the need of the hour. In recent years, governments, international organisations and even private players have conceded to the argument that equality of opportunity should be the moral foundation to build our policies. The World Bank, for instance, has started using a Human Opportunity Index as one of the relevant indicators to assess social, human and economic development aspects.&amp;nbsp; Many government initiatives, for example the Midday Meal Scheme in India, is geared towards ensuring social and educational protection routed through the maintenance of nutritional standards for children hailing from lower income communities. As deeply deliberated by economists Amartya Sen and Jean Dreze, nutritional inadequacies can often lead to future health problems, thus, making the poor vulnerable in a competitive labour market. Therefore, socio-health protection can stimulate economic growth for developing nations and be a key factor to combat a macroeconomic crisis. But the main problem, when seen through the lenses of developing countries, is often the laid-back attitude of the public sector projects which when coupled with a bar of fiscal deficit, can be difficult obstacles in planning a long-term inclusive plan. To bring in the private players into this mold would mean that it would contribute to capital accumulation and investment, risk management and offer diverse potential advantages to indirect stakeholders through multiplier effects. Therefore, bringing in private funding with the main hold of government in steering things to the correct conclusion, pricing, can be the way forward. Having suggested the inclusion of private players into the mold of healthcare, I must address the problem of private players slowly taking the charge to invest and maximise profits through expensive medication (inelastic demand). Therefore, the onus must lie upon the government to take action, diversify research, be responsible and accountable to the public at large, and be strict with the pricing models.&amp;nbsp; Am I Satisfied or Worried? Well, I would say, I am ‘impressed’. Don’t get me wrong, the statistics of COVID-19 cases unfolding while I cough my heart out to write these soulful words, has me chilled to my bones. But the honest truth is that the pandemic is here to stay. Yes, we already have a delta plus omicron variant and booster jabs available but it is not that which has impressed me (I am not a supporter of dystopia, in fact I am already dreading the advent of “oxicron”). I am impressed by the fact that our newsrooms, classrooms, zoom meetings and daily chats are now (more than ever before) focused on ‘health.’ It is probably for the first time in history that we have realised how much our lives are worth.&amp;nbsp; In one of my favourite dialogues from the movie Troy (2004), the character Odysseus goes on to tell Achilles that “War is young men dying, and old men talking.” In my opinion, this battle against Covid has proven yet again that neglect in the healthcare systems will cost us lives at all fronts, no matter how boldly the wise, grey haired intellectuals deliberate on fixing the situation without adequate expenditures. The advent of COVID-19 with the surges in internet usage around the globe has made interaction possible between people living in different continents. The debate of healthcare affordability is now no longer limited to the fancy parliament halls and the elite think tanks.&amp;nbsp; We, the global citizens, have proudly taken a step forward to progress the discussions on affordable healthcare, equitable healthcare, climate change and so much more. The GDP figures are not impressive any more. In fact they are on a dedicated downhill safari. What will it take to impress us? An increase in human development and opportunity indices, for starters, would be good. The discussions on our physical and mental health would be even better.&amp;nbsp; Earlier (pre-Covid) the politics in my country India would generally revolve around two parties trying to degrade one another with quirkier rhetoric. Now, I am not denying that those rhetorics weren’t fun. They are an absolute amaze, both for meme and conversation purposes. Who in the world would not enjoy a wholesome trash talk between the ‘defenders of faith’. It is terribly fun to watch. But it is not the essence of our existence as politics made us believe in. Our population will only truly prosper when everyone has equal opportunities and access. The world has finally started demanding what is truly theirs, and now we are debating these topics in our homes. Home, where the general scope of discussion was limited to taking trash out and gossiping about neighbours. That is steep progress according to me. Therefore, I am hopeful when I say that I am looking forward to this decade’s unfolding. This will no doubt be one of the most ‘efficient,’ remarkable and decisive decades of human history. This time the war will not be fought on the enemy lines, rather it will be fought within our homes as we sanitise our hands and take those jabs.&amp;nbsp; COVID-19 has brought more than 19 months of caged life. So much so that going out without a mask feels alien to me at this point. But what it also helped us realise is that being healthy (and ‘negative’) is golden. Therefore, socio-health protection, extensive public health research funding and awareness is required if we are to be the ‘defenders of human existence’ and strike down these ultra effective viruses and other anomalies. By being ultra productive in building infrastructure for it and investing in pertinent research, maybe we will have a shot at it. But above all what is to be appreciated amid all of this chaos, is the resilience of humankind in not giving up. So, three cheers to humanity at large!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 21st Century Pandemics: What Does the Future Hold?</title><link href="/The-21st-Century-Pandemics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 21st Century Pandemics: What Does the Future Hold?" /><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-21st-Century-Pandemics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-21st-Century-Pandemics">&lt;p&gt;Pandemics have made appearances throughout history and many a time, are credited with exceptional events and periods like the Renaissance (which took place after the Black Death) and the Roaring 20’s (which followed the Spanish Flu pandemic of the early 20th century). But what is often overlooked in history lessons but we, as a community, have learnt over the past two years is how scary and devastating these pandemics are. No amount of hope for a more golden period in the future can give anyone the strength to endure such a difficult time. Not without breaking down once in a while at the very least. It is important to acknowledge the urgency of the medical threats that the human world is currently facing or is expected to face shortly and take action accordingly. Some problems can be prevented while some can be made tractable. This article discusses three such threats and what the future holds for us.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The COVID-19 Pandemic&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite honestly, there is not much I could add to the knowledge that almost each one of us already possess about the ongoing pandemic due to the fear surrounding the same. At the time of writing this article, the Omicron variant, which is 25% more infectious than the Delta variant, is causing panic and claiming lives across several countries. Therefore, yes, it is present and will most likely continue to be a cause for concern for a while.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How long this pandemic is going to continue is up for debate. It is dependent on multiple factors: how fast can the booster doses of the vaccines, that are effective against the Omicron variant, be rolled out; whether oral therapeutics can be scaled and made available to the public to restrict an infection to a mild one; and whether the society is capable of taking notes from the mistakes committed over the last two years and make urgent changes. For now, it is safe to say that we might have to hang on to the masks and take necessary COVID-19 safety precautions for a while.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Permafrost Pandemic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possible permafrost pandemic is something that the scientific community and everyone else outside has been studying and debating for the last couple of years. Siberia and other parts of the Arctic have been facing record-breaking heat waves recently. Land surface temperatures as high as 45°C have been recorded, and studies have confirmed that the Arctic is heating up almost twice as fast as the rest of the planet. And this is all thanks to the much questioned and quoted phenomenon of 'global warming'. Global warming is very simply the warming up of the planet. This is primarily caused by the Greenhouse Effect.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An increase in the number of greenhouse gases (GHGs) like carbon dioxide, sulphur dioxide, oxides of nitrogen and methane in our atmosphere results in the formation of a sort of a blanket that traps the sun’s heat, resulting in climate change. GHGs are released by the burning of fossil fuels, among various other sources. Deforestation too has a huge contribution in this matter. Trees are capable of absorbing CO2 and giving out oxygen. In the absence of trees, this process does not occur, resulting in the accumulation of CO2.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get into the details of the possible permafrost pandemic, it is important to understand what the term 'permafrost' really means. It refers to any kind of earth material like soil or gravel which has been at or under 0°C for two or more consecutive years. This definition, contrary to popular belief, does not include the glacial or sea ice. The thawing of the permafrost is what has been bothering scientists for a while. Apart from being the main cause of the ever-rising sea levels and the runaway climate change due to the release of the greenhouse gases trapped within, it might have several disease-causing microbes frozen at the moment which may be released eventually. The thawing of the permafrost is a phenomenon that has been around for no longer than the last two decades. It is only in its fetal stages and the process is likely to be expedited by the way the world is run today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The active layer of the permafrost is in the form of water over the summer. It has been growing for a while now and is capable of forming a habitat for the newly thawed microbes. Essential biological processes can be activated here. The talik layer of the permafrost is rarely frozen. The microbes can even move to this layer and this would ensure that they are not frozen again. While the scientific community is in agreement that bacteria can survive for quite a long time, how long they can survive is still a matter of inquiry. Researchers have been attempting to revive ancient viruses from permafrost samples to determine the possibility of a pandemic caused by newly thawed microbes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, DNA viruses are the most feared in this matter. Being more chemically stable than RNA viruses, they are more likely to survive the process of freezing and thawing. The two known possible viruses that could emerge from the permafrost are pox and anthrax. However, several other microbes are yet unknown and could be even more deadly than those known to mankind presently. Exactly how dangerous this possible permafrost pandemic could be is one of the many questions that the scientific community is unable to answer or agree on.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is exacerbated by the refusal of a portion of the human population to acknowledge the existence and effects of global warming. Barely anything at all is being done to tackle climate change. However, it is very clear that preparing the health systems for a permafrost pandemic eventuality and working to reverse climate change are the main, and perhaps, the only ways to survive it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Silent Pandemic&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR), meaning resistance to antimicrobial drugs possessed by certain microbes, is a popular term in the scientific and medical communities. This is more so because of the ever-increasing fear of a pandemic due to diseases caused by microbes resistant to all existing drugs, also known as 'superbugs'. Superbugs kill about 700,000 (estimated) people each year and the statistics are predicted to cross ten million by the year 2050.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antibiotics have been around since the discovery of penicillin by Sir Alexander Fleming in 1928. They have revolutionised our lives by adding 23 years to the average life span and by becoming an integral part of modern medical practices. When a person suffers from a bacterial disease, they are offered antibiotics and this kills some of the bacteria. The remaining microbes, which are resistant to the drug, survive and proliferate. This leads to the existence of panic-inducing superbugs that are resistant to all known drugs. It makes it difficult and, in some cases, impossible to cure previously tractable diseases. Densely populated regions of the world with poor sanitary conditions and water quality are feared to be more susceptible to the possibility of becoming epicentres of outbreaks of superbugs. The change in microbes that make them resistant to drugs is unstoppable. When antibiotics are overused (much like it is today), microbes are exponentially more likely to become resistant. If the situation is not handled exigently, minor infections may turn fatal. This is known as the silent pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the story does not end there. The COVID-19 pandemic has had a hand in making the situation much worse. Studies have demonstrated that over 70% of COVID-19 patients have been administered antibiotic treatment despite only 10% of the cases having bacterial infections. This was especially because in the embryonic stages of the pandemic it was difficult to distinguish between a bacterial infection and COVID-19 infection. Later, the fear of bacterial co-infections caused the overuse of antibiotic drugs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must spread awareness about AMR and the overuse of antibiotics. Otherwise, they will soon be rendered ineffective and alternative treatment may be required to tackle diseases. This might have even more severe side effects or may not be effective at all. Prudent use of antibiotics can decelerate the AMR, ensuring their availability to treat microbial infections effectively in the future.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this article is not to create fear but to point out that neglecting concerns like those that preceded the outbreak of COVID-19 could result in other, perhaps even more catastrophic, pandemics. It is important to learn from our past mistakes when it comes to handling diseases. It is also important to know that it is practicable to reduce the possible effects or even prevent certain disastrous eventualities. All it takes is to have an open mind, make changes in our lifestyles and carry out proper scientific research to address the problems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">Pandemics have made appearances throughout history and many a time, are credited with exceptional events and periods like the Renaissance (which took place after the Black Death) and the Roaring 20’s (which followed the Spanish Flu pandemic of the early 20th century). But what is often overlooked in history lessons but we, as a community, have learnt over the past two years is how scary and devastating these pandemics are. No amount of hope for a more golden period in the future can give anyone the strength to endure such a difficult time. Not without breaking down once in a while at the very least. It is important to acknowledge the urgency of the medical threats that the human world is currently facing or is expected to face shortly and take action accordingly. Some problems can be prevented while some can be made tractable. This article discusses three such threats and what the future holds for us.&amp;nbsp; The COVID-19 Pandemic&amp;nbsp; Quite honestly, there is not much I could add to the knowledge that almost each one of us already possess about the ongoing pandemic due to the fear surrounding the same. At the time of writing this article, the Omicron variant, which is 25% more infectious than the Delta variant, is causing panic and claiming lives across several countries. Therefore, yes, it is present and will most likely continue to be a cause for concern for a while.&amp;nbsp; How long this pandemic is going to continue is up for debate. It is dependent on multiple factors: how fast can the booster doses of the vaccines, that are effective against the Omicron variant, be rolled out; whether oral therapeutics can be scaled and made available to the public to restrict an infection to a mild one; and whether the society is capable of taking notes from the mistakes committed over the last two years and make urgent changes. For now, it is safe to say that we might have to hang on to the masks and take necessary COVID-19 safety precautions for a while.&amp;nbsp; The Permafrost Pandemic The possible permafrost pandemic is something that the scientific community and everyone else outside has been studying and debating for the last couple of years. Siberia and other parts of the Arctic have been facing record-breaking heat waves recently. Land surface temperatures as high as 45°C have been recorded, and studies have confirmed that the Arctic is heating up almost twice as fast as the rest of the planet. And this is all thanks to the much questioned and quoted phenomenon of 'global warming'. Global warming is very simply the warming up of the planet. This is primarily caused by the Greenhouse Effect.&amp;nbsp; An increase in the number of greenhouse gases (GHGs) like carbon dioxide, sulphur dioxide, oxides of nitrogen and methane in our atmosphere results in the formation of a sort of a blanket that traps the sun’s heat, resulting in climate change. GHGs are released by the burning of fossil fuels, among various other sources. Deforestation too has a huge contribution in this matter. Trees are capable of absorbing CO2 and giving out oxygen. In the absence of trees, this process does not occur, resulting in the accumulation of CO2.&amp;nbsp; Before we get into the details of the possible permafrost pandemic, it is important to understand what the term 'permafrost' really means. It refers to any kind of earth material like soil or gravel which has been at or under 0°C for two or more consecutive years. This definition, contrary to popular belief, does not include the glacial or sea ice. The thawing of the permafrost is what has been bothering scientists for a while. Apart from being the main cause of the ever-rising sea levels and the runaway climate change due to the release of the greenhouse gases trapped within, it might have several disease-causing microbes frozen at the moment which may be released eventually. The thawing of the permafrost is a phenomenon that has been around for no longer than the last two decades. It is only in its fetal stages and the process is likely to be expedited by the way the world is run today.&amp;nbsp; The active layer of the permafrost is in the form of water over the summer. It has been growing for a while now and is capable of forming a habitat for the newly thawed microbes. Essential biological processes can be activated here. The talik layer of the permafrost is rarely frozen. The microbes can even move to this layer and this would ensure that they are not frozen again. While the scientific community is in agreement that bacteria can survive for quite a long time, how long they can survive is still a matter of inquiry. Researchers have been attempting to revive ancient viruses from permafrost samples to determine the possibility of a pandemic caused by newly thawed microbes.&amp;nbsp; Generally, DNA viruses are the most feared in this matter. Being more chemically stable than RNA viruses, they are more likely to survive the process of freezing and thawing. The two known possible viruses that could emerge from the permafrost are pox and anthrax. However, several other microbes are yet unknown and could be even more deadly than those known to mankind presently. Exactly how dangerous this possible permafrost pandemic could be is one of the many questions that the scientific community is unable to answer or agree on.&amp;nbsp; The problem is exacerbated by the refusal of a portion of the human population to acknowledge the existence and effects of global warming. Barely anything at all is being done to tackle climate change. However, it is very clear that preparing the health systems for a permafrost pandemic eventuality and working to reverse climate change are the main, and perhaps, the only ways to survive it.&amp;nbsp; The Silent Pandemic&amp;nbsp; Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR), meaning resistance to antimicrobial drugs possessed by certain microbes, is a popular term in the scientific and medical communities. This is more so because of the ever-increasing fear of a pandemic due to diseases caused by microbes resistant to all existing drugs, also known as 'superbugs'. Superbugs kill about 700,000 (estimated) people each year and the statistics are predicted to cross ten million by the year 2050.&amp;nbsp; Antibiotics have been around since the discovery of penicillin by Sir Alexander Fleming in 1928. They have revolutionised our lives by adding 23 years to the average life span and by becoming an integral part of modern medical practices. When a person suffers from a bacterial disease, they are offered antibiotics and this kills some of the bacteria. The remaining microbes, which are resistant to the drug, survive and proliferate. This leads to the existence of panic-inducing superbugs that are resistant to all known drugs. It makes it difficult and, in some cases, impossible to cure previously tractable diseases. Densely populated regions of the world with poor sanitary conditions and water quality are feared to be more susceptible to the possibility of becoming epicentres of outbreaks of superbugs. The change in microbes that make them resistant to drugs is unstoppable. When antibiotics are overused (much like it is today), microbes are exponentially more likely to become resistant. If the situation is not handled exigently, minor infections may turn fatal. This is known as the silent pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, the story does not end there. The COVID-19 pandemic has had a hand in making the situation much worse. Studies have demonstrated that over 70% of COVID-19 patients have been administered antibiotic treatment despite only 10% of the cases having bacterial infections. This was especially because in the embryonic stages of the pandemic it was difficult to distinguish between a bacterial infection and COVID-19 infection. Later, the fear of bacterial co-infections caused the overuse of antibiotic drugs.&amp;nbsp; We must spread awareness about AMR and the overuse of antibiotics. Otherwise, they will soon be rendered ineffective and alternative treatment may be required to tackle diseases. This might have even more severe side effects or may not be effective at all. Prudent use of antibiotics can decelerate the AMR, ensuring their availability to treat microbial infections effectively in the future.&amp;nbsp; The aim of this article is not to create fear but to point out that neglecting concerns like those that preceded the outbreak of COVID-19 could result in other, perhaps even more catastrophic, pandemics. It is important to learn from our past mistakes when it comes to handling diseases. It is also important to know that it is practicable to reduce the possible effects or even prevent certain disastrous eventualities. All it takes is to have an open mind, make changes in our lifestyles and carry out proper scientific research to address the problems.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One of the Poorest Nations in the World</title><link href="/One-of-the-Poorest-Nations-in-the-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One of the Poorest Nations in the World" /><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/One-of-the-Poorest-Nations-in-the-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="/One-of-the-Poorest-Nations-in-the-World">&lt;p&gt;Good health and access to a safe and balanced diet are undeniable characteristics of an existence that meets the basic standard of living. Our health determines our ability to participate in society and contribute to the economy. Good health, according to the renowned economist Amartya Sen, is the minimum that an individual should have to be considered not-poor in terms of capability deprivation. Going by this definition, India is one of the poorest nations in the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A malnourished mother is more likely to give birth to a malnourished child,” says the &lt;em&gt;Down To Earth&lt;/em&gt; magazine’s article on 'Why India Remains Malnourished'&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;in 2018. According to the last National Family Health Survey conducted in India for 2015-16, 54.3% of women in rural India aged 15 to 49 were anaemic, and only 8.8% of the children of the 6-23 months age range in rural India receive an adequate diet. It is not surprising that almost a fifth of children under the age of five in rural areas are wasted whereas almost half of the children are stunted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2015-16, India noted the fastest economic growth in five years at 8.2% GDP growth and was considered one of the fastest-growing economies in the world. Yet, according to the Global Nutrition Report published in 2018, India is home to one-third of the world’s stunted children.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the International Food Policy Research Institute, “nutrient-rich non-staple foods are up to ten times more expensive than staple foods in most poor countries”. Widespread poverty in India makes it difficult for people to purchase nutrient-rich food to meet their dietary requirements. Compounded by the lack of education and awareness, the ability to consume a balanced diet ranks pretty low in the lives of rural poor in India. Consequently, we see poor health indicators in the form of high malnutrition and infant mortality rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scenario has been exacerbated by the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic. A sudden lockdown, closed ration shops, and a disrupted food chain has made access to basic nutritional requirements, for the already deprived in India, even more difficult and with the schools closed, children are deprived of the balanced meal plans under the midday meal programmes run by the Indian provincial governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, malnutrition makes children and women in rural India extremely vulnerable to disease. To meet the nutritional requirements of the nation and to reduce the vulnerability of women and children to COVID-19, the Government has started prioritizing national food security programmes such as the public distribution systems, &lt;em&gt;POSHAN Abhiyan &lt;/em&gt;(Nutrition Scheme), and the national health mission. These schemes play a significant role in reducing mortality and deaths in rural areas. One such scheme is the Integrated Child Development Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Integrated Child Development Scheme (ICDS) is considered the world’s largest scheme for childhood care and development, which is appropriate when we recall that India consists of one-third of the world’s stunted children. Launched in 1975, the ICDS aims to “provide pre-school non-formal education on one hand and break the vicious cycle of malnutrition, morbidity, reduced learning capacity and mortality on the other”. As of 2019, the estimates suggest that there are over 85 million children from the ages of zero to six and lactating and pregnant women who are beneficiaries of the scheme.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under this scheme, the government offers services of supplementary nutrition, immunization, health check-ups, and referral services to the beneficiaries. These services are provided by the front-line workers under the scheme called the Anganwadi workers and Anganwadi helpers. Additionally, pre-school education to children of age three to six years and nutrition and health education to women of age 15-45 years is also provided through Anganwadi workers and Anganwadi helpers. Anganwadi centres are established according to population parameters. These centres are built to meet the infrastructural needs and requirements of the Anganwadi workers and are the epicentre of operations. These services offered under the ICDS are divided into six smaller schemes: Anganwadi Service Scheme, Pradhan Mantri Matru Vandana Yojana (the Prime Minister's Maternity Benefits Programme), National Creche Scheme (daycare facilities), POSHAN Abhiyaan (nutrition scheme), Scheme for Adolescent Girls (nutrition and gender support for young girls) and Child Protection Scheme.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the impact of the ICDS on rural undernutrition levels has been less than what one would expect from a scheme of ICDS’ level. ICDS has been mired in a series of troubles because of inefficient funding and infrastructural growth, including technological advancement.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the funding allocated to the ICDS in the last five years, we see a consistent rise in the budget allocation to the Indian Ministry for Women and Child Development, but we still see various complaints of inadequate funding and infrastructural inadequacies in Anganwadi centres for the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anganwadi workers are the backbone of the scheme and without their contribution, the scheme would not be able to achieve its objectives. According to the 2015-16 records available on the official ICDS website, there is one Anganwadi centre (AWC) for a population of 400-800, two AWCs for 800-1600, three AWCs for 1600-2400, which amounts to one worker per 20 individuals. However, this allocation is not always followed. The salaries of the workers vary across the country, starting from as little as Rs. 2,500/month to Rs.12,000/month. This remuneration has to suffice for living costs, essentials, meals as well as accommodate travelling. The Anganwadi workers are demanding a minimum monthly wage of Rs.18,000 along with better benefits in the form of maternity leaves, paid sick leaves, and internet access. The workers have often complained of poor quality food provided to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are in charge of the polio programmes as well as other health services in the villages. However, they are ill-equipped and untrained in dealing with these illnesses. The Anganwadi workers have been protesting for better pay and work environment since 2018. Since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic, the Anganwadi workers have taken charge of limiting the spread of the disease as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To lay the foundation for proper psychological, physical, and social development of the child, pre-schools have been established in villages near the Anganwadi centres. However, provisions for teachers and essentials like books, stationery, seating arrangements remain absent. Learning and education are constantly disrupted due to the aforementioned reasons and have been exacerbated by COVID-19, hence defeating the purpose. The ICDS has also focused on reducing dropout rates for young girls. But there are no provisions or incentives for young girls to stay in school. Lack of information and awareness only worsens the situation, and Anganwadi workers are too overworked to take over this aspect as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These workers are responsible for all the services provided under the scheme and have minimal contact with their supervisors to file complaints. The centres are poorly furnished and maintained. They are also required to file and report for each service provided under the latest attempt to digitize, leading to one-sided accountability. The Anganwadi work is vital and imperative in rural India regardless of its deficiencies. However, due to its innumerable failings, it makes for a poor employment opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These issues can be easily solved by paying better wages to the workers, providing them with proper orientation and training, and establishing a system of checks and balances to ensure that funds are appropriately utilized. The Anganwadi workers are the implementers of a vision of India where at least children have health and are, thus, not poor. But the way they are treated and the support that is given to the schemes that they implement is shambolic. The funding and infrastructural deficiencies of the ICDS programme are an obstacle to the government’s aim of tackling malnutrition in India. Following the devastation of the COVID-19 pandemic, the government must prioritize solving these issues, lest it be held responsible for the doom of the future citizens of a country of 1.3 billion due to a lack of healthcare. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>.</name></author><category term="policy" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">Good health and access to a safe and balanced diet are undeniable characteristics of an existence that meets the basic standard of living. Our health determines our ability to participate in society and contribute to the economy. Good health, according to the renowned economist Amartya Sen, is the minimum that an individual should have to be considered not-poor in terms of capability deprivation. Going by this definition, India is one of the poorest nations in the world.&amp;nbsp; “A malnourished mother is more likely to give birth to a malnourished child,” says the Down To Earth magazine’s article on 'Why India Remains Malnourished' in 2018. According to the last National Family Health Survey conducted in India for 2015-16, 54.3% of women in rural India aged 15 to 49 were anaemic, and only 8.8% of the children of the 6-23 months age range in rural India receive an adequate diet. It is not surprising that almost a fifth of children under the age of five in rural areas are wasted whereas almost half of the children are stunted.&amp;nbsp; For 2015-16, India noted the fastest economic growth in five years at 8.2% GDP growth and was considered one of the fastest-growing economies in the world. Yet, according to the Global Nutrition Report published in 2018, India is home to one-third of the world’s stunted children.&amp;nbsp; As per the International Food Policy Research Institute, “nutrient-rich non-staple foods are up to ten times more expensive than staple foods in most poor countries”. Widespread poverty in India makes it difficult for people to purchase nutrient-rich food to meet their dietary requirements. Compounded by the lack of education and awareness, the ability to consume a balanced diet ranks pretty low in the lives of rural poor in India. Consequently, we see poor health indicators in the form of high malnutrition and infant mortality rates. This scenario has been exacerbated by the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic. A sudden lockdown, closed ration shops, and a disrupted food chain has made access to basic nutritional requirements, for the already deprived in India, even more difficult and with the schools closed, children are deprived of the balanced meal plans under the midday meal programmes run by the Indian provincial governments.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, malnutrition makes children and women in rural India extremely vulnerable to disease. To meet the nutritional requirements of the nation and to reduce the vulnerability of women and children to COVID-19, the Government has started prioritizing national food security programmes such as the public distribution systems, POSHAN Abhiyan (Nutrition Scheme), and the national health mission. These schemes play a significant role in reducing mortality and deaths in rural areas. One such scheme is the Integrated Child Development Scheme. The Integrated Child Development Scheme (ICDS) is considered the world’s largest scheme for childhood care and development, which is appropriate when we recall that India consists of one-third of the world’s stunted children. Launched in 1975, the ICDS aims to “provide pre-school non-formal education on one hand and break the vicious cycle of malnutrition, morbidity, reduced learning capacity and mortality on the other”. As of 2019, the estimates suggest that there are over 85 million children from the ages of zero to six and lactating and pregnant women who are beneficiaries of the scheme.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Under this scheme, the government offers services of supplementary nutrition, immunization, health check-ups, and referral services to the beneficiaries. These services are provided by the front-line workers under the scheme called the Anganwadi workers and Anganwadi helpers. Additionally, pre-school education to children of age three to six years and nutrition and health education to women of age 15-45 years is also provided through Anganwadi workers and Anganwadi helpers. Anganwadi centres are established according to population parameters. These centres are built to meet the infrastructural needs and requirements of the Anganwadi workers and are the epicentre of operations. These services offered under the ICDS are divided into six smaller schemes: Anganwadi Service Scheme, Pradhan Mantri Matru Vandana Yojana (the Prime Minister's Maternity Benefits Programme), National Creche Scheme (daycare facilities), POSHAN Abhiyaan (nutrition scheme), Scheme for Adolescent Girls (nutrition and gender support for young girls) and Child Protection Scheme.&amp;nbsp; However, the impact of the ICDS on rural undernutrition levels has been less than what one would expect from a scheme of ICDS’ level. ICDS has been mired in a series of troubles because of inefficient funding and infrastructural growth, including technological advancement.&amp;nbsp; Looking at the funding allocated to the ICDS in the last five years, we see a consistent rise in the budget allocation to the Indian Ministry for Women and Child Development, but we still see various complaints of inadequate funding and infrastructural inadequacies in Anganwadi centres for the scheme. The Anganwadi workers are the backbone of the scheme and without their contribution, the scheme would not be able to achieve its objectives. According to the 2015-16 records available on the official ICDS website, there is one Anganwadi centre (AWC) for a population of 400-800, two AWCs for 800-1600, three AWCs for 1600-2400, which amounts to one worker per 20 individuals. However, this allocation is not always followed. The salaries of the workers vary across the country, starting from as little as Rs. 2,500/month to Rs.12,000/month. This remuneration has to suffice for living costs, essentials, meals as well as accommodate travelling. The Anganwadi workers are demanding a minimum monthly wage of Rs.18,000 along with better benefits in the form of maternity leaves, paid sick leaves, and internet access. The workers have often complained of poor quality food provided to them. They are in charge of the polio programmes as well as other health services in the villages. However, they are ill-equipped and untrained in dealing with these illnesses. The Anganwadi workers have been protesting for better pay and work environment since 2018. Since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic, the Anganwadi workers have taken charge of limiting the spread of the disease as well.&amp;nbsp; To lay the foundation for proper psychological, physical, and social development of the child, pre-schools have been established in villages near the Anganwadi centres. However, provisions for teachers and essentials like books, stationery, seating arrangements remain absent. Learning and education are constantly disrupted due to the aforementioned reasons and have been exacerbated by COVID-19, hence defeating the purpose. The ICDS has also focused on reducing dropout rates for young girls. But there are no provisions or incentives for young girls to stay in school. Lack of information and awareness only worsens the situation, and Anganwadi workers are too overworked to take over this aspect as well.&amp;nbsp; These workers are responsible for all the services provided under the scheme and have minimal contact with their supervisors to file complaints. The centres are poorly furnished and maintained. They are also required to file and report for each service provided under the latest attempt to digitize, leading to one-sided accountability. The Anganwadi work is vital and imperative in rural India regardless of its deficiencies. However, due to its innumerable failings, it makes for a poor employment opportunity.&amp;nbsp; These issues can be easily solved by paying better wages to the workers, providing them with proper orientation and training, and establishing a system of checks and balances to ensure that funds are appropriately utilized. The Anganwadi workers are the implementers of a vision of India where at least children have health and are, thus, not poor. But the way they are treated and the support that is given to the schemes that they implement is shambolic. The funding and infrastructural deficiencies of the ICDS programme are an obstacle to the government’s aim of tackling malnutrition in India. Following the devastation of the COVID-19 pandemic, the government must prioritize solving these issues, lest it be held responsible for the doom of the future citizens of a country of 1.3 billion due to a lack of healthcare.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting Our Sh*t Together: Wetlands and the Future of Sanitation</title><link href="/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Our Sh*t Together: Wetlands and the Future of Sanitation" /><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Human civilisation is rightly considered to be a departure from the natural order. No other species on this planet manipulates its external environment to the extent that we do for our needs. Yet, it stands to reason that we thrive most when we work &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the environment instead of &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; it. Nowhere is this more true than in the realm of sewage disposal. It may seem odd to suggest that our economic and environmental salvation lies in eco-friendly potty disposal. But as it happens, getting our sh*t together is more than a mere metaphor when it comes to avoiding both ecological collapse and facilitating basic sanitation for all.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The biggest living proof of how nature is our friend in matters of sewage treatment is found in the East Calcutta Wetlands. The East Calcutta Wetlands are a vast network of marshland that cover an area of 125 sq km lying to the East of the city of Calcutta, India. These wetlands were named and discovered by a man named Dhrubajyoti Ghosh, a humble sanitation engineer, who then went on to win an award from the UN due to his assiduous efforts to conserve the wetlands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The wetlands are, by all means, a marvel, as explained by Ray Chaudhuri Et al, in an article in the &lt;em&gt;OnLine Journal of Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt;. The waterways and channels of the wetlands receive heaps of sewage and other solid waste (about one-third of the sewage produced by a city of over ten million) which are then deposited in setting ponds. In the shallow settling ponds, the waste is broken down by the sun's UV rays and the algae and plankton that are abound in the marshland. Water hyacinth processes some of the heavy metals in the purification process. The byproduct of this naturally-processed sewage is the nutrient-rich water and soil, which is used for extensive fish farming and vegetable farming. Precisely, the wetlands provide around 150 tons of vegetables daily and around 10,500 tons of fish every year. This is a great boon for Calcutta, its Bengali population is famously pescitarian and around much of the vegetable produce from the wetlands is supplied to the city. These activities also provide direct employment to more than 50 thousand people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is important to note that the wetlands are the result of years of assiduous human efforts, they aren't just nature's gift presented on a platter. Originally, the region consisted of large salt water lakes between the Bidyadhari river in the East and the Hooghly river in the West. The Bidyadhari river does not exist any longer due to the fact that the region became a dumping ground for the waste coming from the Second City of the Empire during the days of the British Raj and also post Indian Independence. Great strides were taken by a certain Bholanath Sen, who leased tracts of land in the marshes in 1879 and began growing vegetables using a unique landform which had alternate rows of garbage and water bodies. Thereafter, in the 1930's a gentleman named Bibhuti Bhushan Ghosh, innovated a perennial system of wastewater fisheries and in 1985 a comprehensive map of the marshes was published. Legal protections were put in place in 1992, when the High Court at Calcutta issued an order prohibiting the reclamation of the wetlands, which was followed by a law passed in 2006 that set up a conservation authority.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, unlike the many stories of humanity being an enemy of the planet, the wetlands represent a concerted human attempt at preserving ecological balance. Not only that, the East Calcutta Wetlands are a beacon for humanity, guiding us to a future that might not involve climate collapse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Man-made wetlands have now been recognised as a cheap and extremely effective means for dealing with effluents and waste generated by urbanisation. The first most striking feature of this organic sewage treatment mechanism is how little it costs. A book titled ‘&lt;em&gt;Treatment Wetlands’ &lt;/em&gt;published as far back as 1996 estimated that to treat 3,786 cubic meters of sewage per day, a conventional sewage treatment plant would cost $4.12 million for construction and then require $156,000 as yearly maintenance costs. However, for treating the same amount, a constructed wetland would require only $3.6 million as construction costs and a mere $45,000 as yearly maintenance costs. Recently, a sewage treatment plant in Arizona was replaced by a constructed wetland which cost a minuscule $3.5 million, compared to the estimated $625 million that would have been spent on upgrading the said plant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Of course, all of this comes with a catch, we need a lot more land to construct a wetland than a conventional sewage treatment plant. For treating 3,786 cubic metres a day in a wetland, as mentioned above, one would need 90 acres of land, whereas a treatment plant would occupy a mere five acres of land. This problem would be multiplied by the fact that much expenditure would have to be incurred by authorities to acquire such lands and compensate the owners. But there is an opportunity presented by this challenge.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The use of constructed wetlands for aquaculture and vegetable farming can bring about serious economic rewards to any region. Non-arable land of low value can be transformed into fertile areas that bring prosperity to local communities as in the case of the East Calcutta Wetlands, thus increasing the asset profile and revenue-generation capacity of the authorities acquiring such land. In turn, this can help such authorities raise finances far more easily for funding projects that are proper investments rather than mere sewage treatment facilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;That apart, there is the conservation of biodiversity that follows as a direct consequence of constructing wetlands. It is estimated that the East Calcutta Wetlands harbour around 104 plant species, 40 bird species, 20 important types of mammals, many rare endangered reptiles, and more than 52 varieties of fish, of which 34 species are endangered. It is well-known that habitat destruction due to human activity poses perhaps the greatest threat to Earth's flora and fauna. A constructed wetland bucks this trend. It's usage and making involves human activity that brings about habitat conservation and enrichment, thereby contributing significantly to environmental conservation in general. By making constructed wetlands an essential feature of urbanisation, we can turn our cities into supporters of the environment instead of being a drain on the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Indeed, constructed wetlands can be sensitive to climatic conditions, unlike traditional sewage treatment plants. Floods, droughts, changes in soil salinity, cyclones, etc., can really affect the viability of a man-made wetland. However, even that drawback is a blessing in disguise. The wetland can act as the first line of defence against such weather events, absorbing the worst of the impact, leaving cities unharmed in many ways and circumstances.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, wetlands can be a great source of commercial utility. They can be beautified to create marvelous recreational spaces. In fact, the Environmental Protection Agency gives excruciating details on the kind of plant species that can be added to beautify man-made swamps in a document that lays out a plan for constructing wetlands. The flora and fauna can generate tourism-related revenue. The lakes can be used for boating and other light water sports. In other words, our shit can literally be used to make life more fun.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Keeping all of that in mind, it seems almost bizarre that such an easy and brilliant solution for one of humanity's fundamental problems is not utilised more often. Sewage swamps and wetlands are meant for many more cities and towns than my home city of Calcutta. If constructed scientifically and strategically, they can truly assist in sustainable development whilst also alleviating poverty and saving communities that may have been damaged due to the denigration of soil quality and loss of livelihoods. It is hoped that this article will stir the public imagination and induce readers to bat for an ingenious solution to a perennial problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harsh Tiwari</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><category term="humanity" /><summary type="html">Human civilisation is rightly considered to be a departure from the natural order. No other species on this planet manipulates its external environment to the extent that we do for our needs. Yet, it stands to reason that we thrive most when we work with the environment instead of against it. Nowhere is this more true than in the realm of sewage disposal. It may seem odd to suggest that our economic and environmental salvation lies in eco-friendly potty disposal. But as it happens, getting our sh*t together is more than a mere metaphor when it comes to avoiding both ecological collapse and facilitating basic sanitation for all.&amp;nbsp; The biggest living proof of how nature is our friend in matters of sewage treatment is found in the East Calcutta Wetlands. The East Calcutta Wetlands are a vast network of marshland that cover an area of 125 sq km lying to the East of the city of Calcutta, India. These wetlands were named and discovered by a man named Dhrubajyoti Ghosh, a humble sanitation engineer, who then went on to win an award from the UN due to his assiduous efforts to conserve the wetlands.&amp;nbsp; The wetlands are, by all means, a marvel, as explained by Ray Chaudhuri Et al, in an article in the OnLine Journal of Biological Sciences. The waterways and channels of the wetlands receive heaps of sewage and other solid waste (about one-third of the sewage produced by a city of over ten million) which are then deposited in setting ponds. In the shallow settling ponds, the waste is broken down by the sun's UV rays and the algae and plankton that are abound in the marshland. Water hyacinth processes some of the heavy metals in the purification process. The byproduct of this naturally-processed sewage is the nutrient-rich water and soil, which is used for extensive fish farming and vegetable farming. Precisely, the wetlands provide around 150 tons of vegetables daily and around 10,500 tons of fish every year. This is a great boon for Calcutta, its Bengali population is famously pescitarian and around much of the vegetable produce from the wetlands is supplied to the city. These activities also provide direct employment to more than 50 thousand people.&amp;nbsp; It is important to note that the wetlands are the result of years of assiduous human efforts, they aren't just nature's gift presented on a platter. Originally, the region consisted of large salt water lakes between the Bidyadhari river in the East and the Hooghly river in the West. The Bidyadhari river does not exist any longer due to the fact that the region became a dumping ground for the waste coming from the Second City of the Empire during the days of the British Raj and also post Indian Independence. Great strides were taken by a certain Bholanath Sen, who leased tracts of land in the marshes in 1879 and began growing vegetables using a unique landform which had alternate rows of garbage and water bodies. Thereafter, in the 1930's a gentleman named Bibhuti Bhushan Ghosh, innovated a perennial system of wastewater fisheries and in 1985 a comprehensive map of the marshes was published. Legal protections were put in place in 1992, when the High Court at Calcutta issued an order prohibiting the reclamation of the wetlands, which was followed by a law passed in 2006 that set up a conservation authority.&amp;nbsp; Thus, unlike the many stories of humanity being an enemy of the planet, the wetlands represent a concerted human attempt at preserving ecological balance. Not only that, the East Calcutta Wetlands are a beacon for humanity, guiding us to a future that might not involve climate collapse.&amp;nbsp; Man-made wetlands have now been recognised as a cheap and extremely effective means for dealing with effluents and waste generated by urbanisation. The first most striking feature of this organic sewage treatment mechanism is how little it costs. A book titled ‘Treatment Wetlands’ published as far back as 1996 estimated that to treat 3,786 cubic meters of sewage per day, a conventional sewage treatment plant would cost $4.12 million for construction and then require $156,000 as yearly maintenance costs. However, for treating the same amount, a constructed wetland would require only $3.6 million as construction costs and a mere $45,000 as yearly maintenance costs. Recently, a sewage treatment plant in Arizona was replaced by a constructed wetland which cost a minuscule $3.5 million, compared to the estimated $625 million that would have been spent on upgrading the said plant.&amp;nbsp; Of course, all of this comes with a catch, we need a lot more land to construct a wetland than a conventional sewage treatment plant. For treating 3,786 cubic metres a day in a wetland, as mentioned above, one would need 90 acres of land, whereas a treatment plant would occupy a mere five acres of land. This problem would be multiplied by the fact that much expenditure would have to be incurred by authorities to acquire such lands and compensate the owners. But there is an opportunity presented by this challenge.&amp;nbsp; The use of constructed wetlands for aquaculture and vegetable farming can bring about serious economic rewards to any region. Non-arable land of low value can be transformed into fertile areas that bring prosperity to local communities as in the case of the East Calcutta Wetlands, thus increasing the asset profile and revenue-generation capacity of the authorities acquiring such land. In turn, this can help such authorities raise finances far more easily for funding projects that are proper investments rather than mere sewage treatment facilities.&amp;nbsp; That apart, there is the conservation of biodiversity that follows as a direct consequence of constructing wetlands. It is estimated that the East Calcutta Wetlands harbour around 104 plant species, 40 bird species, 20 important types of mammals, many rare endangered reptiles, and more than 52 varieties of fish, of which 34 species are endangered. It is well-known that habitat destruction due to human activity poses perhaps the greatest threat to Earth's flora and fauna. A constructed wetland bucks this trend. It's usage and making involves human activity that brings about habitat conservation and enrichment, thereby contributing significantly to environmental conservation in general. By making constructed wetlands an essential feature of urbanisation, we can turn our cities into supporters of the environment instead of being a drain on the same.&amp;nbsp; Indeed, constructed wetlands can be sensitive to climatic conditions, unlike traditional sewage treatment plants. Floods, droughts, changes in soil salinity, cyclones, etc., can really affect the viability of a man-made wetland. However, even that drawback is a blessing in disguise. The wetland can act as the first line of defence against such weather events, absorbing the worst of the impact, leaving cities unharmed in many ways and circumstances.&amp;nbsp; Finally, wetlands can be a great source of commercial utility. They can be beautified to create marvelous recreational spaces. In fact, the Environmental Protection Agency gives excruciating details on the kind of plant species that can be added to beautify man-made swamps in a document that lays out a plan for constructing wetlands. The flora and fauna can generate tourism-related revenue. The lakes can be used for boating and other light water sports. In other words, our shit can literally be used to make life more fun.&amp;nbsp; Keeping all of that in mind, it seems almost bizarre that such an easy and brilliant solution for one of humanity's fundamental problems is not utilised more often. Sewage swamps and wetlands are meant for many more cities and towns than my home city of Calcutta. If constructed scientifically and strategically, they can truly assist in sustainable development whilst also alleviating poverty and saving communities that may have been damaged due to the denigration of soil quality and loss of livelihoods. It is hoped that this article will stir the public imagination and induce readers to bat for an ingenious solution to a perennial problem.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry></feed>