<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-15T12:00:14+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Guess the Average!</title><link href="/Guess-the-Average" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guess the Average!" /><published>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Guess-the-Average</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Guess-the-Average">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll try to explain it to you and we’ll reason our way to the answer. This game is played under the condition known to the game theorists as ‘common knowledge’. Not only does every player have the same information, but each player also knows that every other player knows this. Now, the highest possible average that can occur is 100 which is possible only if every person guessed 100. In that case, two-thirds of the average would be 66.66. Since everyone can figure this out, it wouldn’t make sense to guess anything higher than 67. If every player comes to the same conclusion, no one will guess higher than 67.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now 67 is the new highest possible average so no reasonable guess should be higher than two-thirds of that which is 44. This logic can be extended further and further. With each step, the highest possible logical answer keeps getting smaller. So it would seem sensible to guess the lowest number possible and indeed if everyone chose zero, the game would reach what is known as ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Rational-Pirates&quot;&gt;Nash Equilibrium&lt;/a&gt;’ (which I extensively explained in my previous article on game theory). This is a state where every player has chosen the best possible strategy for themselves given everyone else playing, and no individual player can benefit by choosing differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that’s not what happens in the real world. People, as it turns out, either aren’t perfectly rational or they don’t expect each other to be perfectly rational. Or, perhaps, it might be some combination of the two. When this game is played in real-world settings, the average tends to be somewhere between 20 and 35. Danish newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Politiken&lt;/em&gt;, ran the game with over 19000 readers participating, resulting in an average of roughly 22, making the correct answer 14. Economic game theorists have a way of modelling this interplay between rationality and practicality called ‘K-level Reasoning’, where ‘K’ stands for the number of times a cycle of reasoning is repeated. A person playing at ‘K-level zero’ would approach our game naively and guess a number randomly without thinking about other players. At ‘K-level-1’, a player would assume everyone else is playing at level zero, resulting in an average of 50 (everyone choosing integers at random between 0 to 100 gives an average of 50) and thus guess 33. At ‘K-level-2’, they’d assume that everyone else is playing at level-1 leading them to guess 22. It will take twelve K-levels to reach zero. The pieces of evidence and various studies suggest that most people stop at 1 or 2 K-levels and that’s useful to know because K-level thinking comes into play at high stake situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, stock traders evaluate stocks not only based on earning reports, but also on the value that others place on those numbers. Another example is during penalty kicks in soccer, both the shooter and the goalie decide whether to go right or left based on what they think the other person is thinking. Goalies often memorise the pattern of their opponents well in advance but penalty shooters know that and can play accordingly. In each case, participants must weigh their own understanding of the best course of action against how well they think other participants understand the situation but 1 or 2 K-levels is by no means a hard and fast rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I think you would wonder what would happen if people played this game after understanding the difference between the most logical approach and the most common? The answer is that it is up to the person’s understanding and intuition.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Error 404: Democracy Unachievable in your Region</title><link href="/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Error 404: Democracy Unachievable in your Region" /><published>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region">&lt;p&gt;For Hong Kong, the year 2019 has been a monumental one. In April last year, the citizens of Hong Kong took to the streets to protest against the controversial extradition bill. This bill could have potentially undermined the judicial independence of Hong Kong and silenced the dissidents by exposing the Hongkongers to unfair trials by Beijing. In September, after 5 months of protests, the bill was withdrawn. However, this has led to a bigger uprising: one against Beijing as Hong Kong now demands full democracy and an inquiry into the police’s actions. With this, the protests continue. However, as the entire world got caught up by COVID-19, the protestors withdrew from the streets to escape the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An opportunist Beijing swooped in during this period with the National People’s Congress (NPC) approving to impose a highly contentious national security law in Hong Kong on May 28, 2020. The legislation seeks to ban secession, subversion of state power, terrorism, foreign intervention, and allow mainland China’s state security agencies to operate in Hong Kong. This essentially means that the harshest criticism of China and the ruling party will be criminalised. Detailed legislation, however, still needs to be drafted and enacted, which could be done within the next few months. Critics fear it threatens the political and civil freedoms enjoyed by the semi-autonomous territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong’s government has signalled support for the legislature and said it would cooperate with China to enforce the laws in Hong Kong. Carrie Lam, Hong Kong’s Chief Executive, has also made a public statement reiterating China’s stance saying that the law will only target a handful of people involved in terrorism or subversion. On the other hand, the Hongkongers have retaliated with a series of protests despite fears of coronavirus. On a forum popular with protestors, LIHKG (often referred to as the Hong Kong version of Reddit), users have called for a ‘hundred-day war’, calling it the last opportunity to protest before the law comes into force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Pompeo, US Secretary of State, condemned the legislation by calling it a ‘disastrous proposal’. He also stated that Hong Kong is no longer autonomous from China and threatened to revoke the special status it enjoys in trade with the USA. In a joint statement, Australia, Canada, the UK and the US have expressed their ‘deep concern’ regarding the law. They have also called on Beijing to work with the Hong Kong government and people to find a “mutually acceptable accommodation”. Taiwan, Japan and Germany are also standing in solidarity with Hong Kong and have called for China to not undermine Hong Kong’s freedoms. As these countries line up in support of Hong Kong, Beijing is getting more suspicious that these foreign efforts aim to exploit its domestic weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong was handed over to China in 1997 by the United Kingdom after 150 years of colonisation. As a part of China, it operates under the ‘one country, two systems’ principle ensuring Hong Kong enjoys independence in its legislature, judiciary and economy. Set to expire in 2047, the arrangement allows Hong Kong to enjoy autonomy and freedom of speech and assembly. These freedoms, however, don’t exist in mainland China. To aid this, a document called the Basic Law – Hong Kong’s mini-constitution - was drafted which ensured Hong Kong its freedom and set out a structure for governance of the territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article 23 of the Basic Law already calls for Hong Kong to enact national security laws to prohibit “treason, secession, sedition [and] subversion” against the Chinese government. While the article already exists as a part of the Basic Law, it has never been enacted. In 2003, a similar attempt was made by Hong Kong’s first Chief Executive, Tung Chee-hwa but was abandoned post mass protests. The next three successors never attempted to repeat this out of fear of protests, despite repeated warnings from China stating that they were obliged to do so. This time, however, China plans to enact the law without Hong Kong’s approval by pursuing an ‘unconstitutional’ method. The laws will be enacted through a provision that bypasses Hong Kong’s legislature and therefore, public debate and consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draconian legislation comes when China is already under the scrutiny of the international community after the coronavirus outbreak. It is said to be China’s way of tightening its grip on Hong Kong after a year of pro-democracy protests. Seeing how the legislation eerily echoes the mainland’s current legal framework, it is safe to believe that the drafted legislation will not be compatible with international human rights obligations binding on Hong Kong. Provisions regarding anti-terrorism and sedition under existing laws are already inconsistent with global standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong has acted as a haven for dissent with its freedom of speech and assembly. The legislation, however, seeks to attack these freedoms and silence the loudest voice against China. Many are afraid that China will set up its institutions in Hong Kong under the garb of ‘national security’ that could introduce China’s law enforcement to the city. This could further affect the judicial system of Hong Kong. According to Professor Johannes Chan, a scholar at the University of Hong Kong, the security law poses a major problem. “Almost all trials involving national security are conducted behind closed doors. It [is] never clear what exactly the allegations and the evidence are, and the term national security is so vague that it could cover almost anything,” said the Professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislation, additionally, bans all “activities of foreign forces” interfering in Hong Kong’s affairs. People also worry that this could affect Hong Kong’s attractiveness as a business and economic powerhouse. This is a troubling aspect for an economy already struggling with tourism in the past year because of protests and COVID-19. This, however, isn’t the first step taken by China to counter the rising pro-democracy narrative in Hong Kong. In February 2020, China announced Xia Baolong, the man known for the clampdown on Christian churches in the Zhejiang province during 2014-15, as the head of the Hong Kong &amp;amp; Macau Office. China also revamped the reporting structure that crystalised the clear chain of command from Hong Kong to Beijing. Additionally, Luo Huining, known for executing Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption campaign, was appointed to head the Chinese Liaison Office in Hong Kong. “They’ve got two guys who are not familiar with Hong Kong issues, and who have governed provinces in China in a heavy-handed way and think they can do the same in Hong Kong,” said Kwok, who has a law degree from King’s College, University of London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, on June 4, 2020, Hong Kong’s legislature passed a contentious bill that makes insulting the Chinese national anthem, illegal. Anyone who shall intentionally insult the anthem will face up to 3 years in prison plus fines worth at least $6,000. The bill was introduced by Beijing last year in response to the Hong Kong soccer fans booing at the anthem at the 2015 FIFA matches. Post the bill being passed, students at the Hong Kong University held a silent protest at the Pillar of Shame, a sculpture commemorating the victims of the Tiananmen crackdown. With a foggy future ahead, Hongkongers tread on a narrow road to democracy with no destination in sight. More clashes between the two parties are to be expected in the future, but it’s going to take a long time before either party backs down. Hong Kong’s pro-democracy fire will not burn out anytime soon. In a world where the global community blames China for the coronavirus outbreak and the USA further imposes tariffs on Chinese goods, China will do all it can to retain its power and reputation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">For Hong Kong, the year 2019 has been a monumental one. In April last year, the citizens of Hong Kong took to the streets to protest against the controversial extradition bill. This bill could have potentially undermined the judicial independence of Hong Kong and silenced the dissidents by exposing the Hongkongers to unfair trials by Beijing. In September, after 5 months of protests, the bill was withdrawn. However, this has led to a bigger uprising: one against Beijing as Hong Kong now demands full democracy and an inquiry into the police’s actions. With this, the protests continue. However, as the entire world got caught up by COVID-19, the protestors withdrew from the streets to escape the virus.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘Vultures’ 2020</title><link href="/Vultures-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Vultures’ 2020" /><published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Vultures-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Vultures-2020">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;I’m really, really sorry. The pain of life overrides the joy to the point that joy does not exist. …depressed … without (a) phone … money for rent … money for child support … money for debts … money!!! … I am haunted by the vivid memories of killings &amp;amp; corpses &amp;amp; anger &amp;amp; pain … of starving or wounded children, of trigger-happy madmen, often police, of killer executioners …&lt;/em&gt;” - Kevin Carter (an excerpt from his suicide note)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 28, 2020, during an Indian Supreme Court hearing on the humanitarian crisis faced by the intra-state migrant workers due to the nationwide lockdown, Tushar Mehta, the Solicitor General (SG) of India, referred to the story of Kevin Carter, a South African photojournalist who won the Pulitzer Prize for depicting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1993_Sudan_famine&quot;&gt;1993 famine in Sudan&lt;/a&gt; through a photograph titled “The Vulture and The Little Girl.” Troubled by all that he had seen, Carter committed suicide at the age of 33.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/nostri-imago/5000121934&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//sudan_famine1993.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narrating this from an archival perspective, Tushar Mehta aimed this towards the way the media is reporting the ongoing migrant crisis; by displaying their visuals, using mounting death tolls as headlines. According to Mehta, the ones documenting this are nothing but ‘vultures’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this very documentation led the Supreme Court to issue a notice to all governments, ordering the Indian Central government and the State governments to immediately provide free-of-cost transport, food, and shelter to migrant workers on May 26, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faye D’Souza, a journalist, retweeted the Supreme Court’s entire conversation and raised a very relevant question – “Would he (SG) prefer if these stories were never told?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a journalism student, I have had and have read plenty of comments and opinions towards the media. I have tried to differentiate criticism from mockery and take the constructive part out of the two. However, statements like the one made by the SG make me feel that even the courts in my country aren’t democratic but just political in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine, &lt;em&gt;Caravan&lt;/em&gt;, in an article on May 28, 2020, reflects upon the plight of the journalists reporting during the pandemic. A snippet from the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Every journalist who has been reporting on the pandemic has been traumatised by what they saw or reported. No one has done it for a moral license to feel better about themselves—this work, in fact, has the opposite effect on journalists. Over time, it changes you forever. The activist, filmmaker, and writer Susan Sontag summed up this journalistic dilemma best: “The person who intervenes cannot record; the person who is recording cannot intervene.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SG, however, told &lt;em&gt;The Times of India&lt;/em&gt; that his statement was being misread as he was referring to some of the pseudo-NGO (Non-Governmental Organisation) workers who have just been criticising the government and the Court for doing nothing when they themselves also haven’t contributed enough to make the situation better for the migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, I personally feel that the justification given here is not exactly matching with the description the SG gave about the journalists in the court. The fact that the SG thought that the documentation could have been done in a better way is nothing but a step back towards blurring the lines of reality presentation by the fourth pillar of democracy. Is this not against the ethics of journalism? Has journalism been reduced to comfort news and neglecting the underprivileged? Is journalism NOT about grabbing the attention of the authorities in charge that have turned too blind to see the plight of the very people that made them sit in power today? Is journalism NOT about raising the voices of the voiceless? Yet the journalists who have been doing all this as responsible media personnel, at the expense of their own health during the pandemic, have been termed as ‘vultures’ in the Court? The SG has forgotten that the ones he claims to be vultures also got the country THREE Pulitizer Prizes 2020 for feature photography depicting the plight of Kashmir after the revocation of Article 370 by the Indian government in August 2019. In places like Kashmir, journalists themselves become stories and their work instead of being appreciated is reduced to zero or charged under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA) by its very own government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journalists like Barkha Dutt have been on road since the past 70-80 days covering the pandemic crisis and helping the migrants get adequate attention so that they reach their homes safely. They are out on the field and are away from their quarantined safe places, documenting stories of the ones who want to go to their own homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So probably for the next time, I can only hope there is a decent amount of respect for the ones who are actually contributing to help the fellow members of the society instead of passing a generalised bland statement for all the media because, in that way, you not only disrespect the journalists working on the documentation but also the sufferers who want to be voiced.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Himanshi Saini</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“I’m really, really sorry. The pain of life overrides the joy to the point that joy does not exist. …depressed … without (a) phone … money for rent … money for child support … money for debts … money!!! … I am haunted by the vivid memories of killings &amp;amp; corpses &amp;amp; anger &amp;amp; pain … of starving or wounded children, of trigger-happy madmen, often police, of killer executioners …” - Kevin Carter (an excerpt from his suicide note)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?</title><link href="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?" /><published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me">&lt;p&gt;Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The birth of a child is considered a moment of unbound joy and is believed to provide families with a wholesome experience. What follows next is a series of sleepless nights, great anxiety, and several &lt;em&gt;potty&lt;/em&gt; training sessions. Raising a child in today’s world is no piece of cake, be it in terms of personal devotion, child-care responsibilities or financial needs. Families, rich and poor alike, face their own set of challenges with respect to the same. Putting this into perspective, these issues arising from varied aspects add up to one big question: what is in it for the parents? Let alone going through the process more than once, is it all truly worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raising this question, we believe children born in different set-ups, in terms of beliefs and economic backing, add varied sorts of value to the particular household. A family belonging to the lower-income group generally believes that having a larger number of children means more hands to work in the field or otherwise, completely negating the cost of actually raising these children. For those poor, rural families, children are not only seen as an economic asset but also as an insurance policy for old age, especially in societies with zero state pension and health care. However, we observe that as the income of a family increases, the smaller the family is, i.e. they prefer to have fewer children. With rising incomes, families don’t need their children to be an economic asset; the family can afford for their children to be an economic liability. Furthermore, people with a superior economic standing believe in providing better education and lifestyle to their children. Hence, while, children in impoverished communities contribute to their family income, children in the developed world subtract from family finances through the cost of their education and upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can also be measured by weighing the marginal cost against the marginal utility of procreating. The marginal cost and utility, incurred and reaped respectively, largely depend upon the budget constraint of each household. Hence, so does the optimum number of children. This brings us to the conclusion that there is a negative correlation between family income and family size which further leads to a trade-off between the quantity and the quality of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the idea that having a higher number of children reduces the cost of raising each additional child; in short, highlighting diminishing marginal cost. The reason behind this is that most of the necessary child raising equipment- like high chairs, cribs, and clothes - can be passed onto the next child, and no additional money is required to be spent on the same. Moreover, with many family and parent-child health insurance plans, the monthly premium remains the same, irrespective of the number of children. This points to a lower cost per person. Additionally, there are several universities in the States that provide various benefits to families with more than one child. Therefore, it could so happen that due to these benefits the cost per unit of putting ten children through college could be less than that of putting one. Who says houses cannot be run on economies of scale?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of the economies of scale, there are substantial costs that remain fixed: a large number of children leads to the dilution of parental resources- financial as well as time. These fixed costs include expenses on food, healthcare, and basic clothes for lower-income groups. Similarly, the fixed costs of higher-income groups are much larger as they involve education, and extra-curricular activities amongst others. Moreover, these children also give their parents a fair share of headaches. Being anxious about everything pertaining to their children forms a crucial part of a parent’s identity. This leads us to another opportunity cost which is the personal freedom of these caregivers. This causes the parents to juggle between giving time to their children and finding time for themselves and their work. Therefore, as the number of children increases, there is a marked drop in the time spent with each child. Many of them might grow up feeling neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like identified in the foregoing paragraphs, the utility and benefits that the parents reap from their children can be seen in the form of economic and old-age support. However, it is also important to realise that as the number of children that a couple has increases, there is a decline in the marginal utility. This is because, with each additional child, there is a decreasing extra satisfaction that the couple will gain. This can be seen in the way that if a couple has 5 children then they will receive more satisfaction with their firstborn than they did from their last born (5th child in this case). Hence, as the number of children a couple has increases, the law of diminishing returns starts to hold true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, what is truly in it for the parents purely depends upon the type of income groups that they belong to. Thus, regardless of whether couples want children for personal attachment or joy, it all eventually boils down to the economic cost and utility of having one!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>kabir.kochar sanya.puri</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Crime of Menstruation</title><link href="/The-Crime-of-Menstruation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crime of Menstruation" /><published>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Crime-of-Menstruation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crime-of-Menstruation">&lt;p&gt;The amount one knows about the phenomenon known as menstruation depends on a number of things; sex, age, ethnicity and other characteristics. This is in spite of the fact that having periods is perhaps just as common as any other human bodily process, and is experienced on a monthly basis by roughly half of the world’s population. While there is a general awareness that periods are a necessity for fertility in women, not many people across the world are appreciative of what is involved in the process. Menstruating women are widely seen as ‘dirty’ and steps are taken to avoid them at all costs by people of certain communities. However, this stigma associated with menstruation is not just an issue of the ‘backward’ or ‘illiterate’ communities; it affects the most modern of societies too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several religious superstitions associated with periods and pink products like tampons and pads. In cultures like Hinduism, women who are on their periods are often exempted from the rites and rituals that characterise the religion. They are not permitted inside the kitchen, to adorn themselves with flowers or to even touch anyone or anything, as far as possible. In fact, there are several temples that do not permit the entry of menstruating women or women of menstruating age. One such instance that drew wide condemnation is the Sabarimala Temple located in the state of Kerala in India. For centuries, this temple has restricted the entry of women of menstruating age (roughly between 10 and 50 years). This is claimed to be out of respect for the celibate nature of the patron deity. In a historic verdict on September 28, 2018, the Supreme Court of India lifted the ban on the entry of women, stating that discrimination against them, even on the grounds of religion, is unconstitutional. While feminists hailed this as a great victory, many others, including women, were not very appreciative of the step, and the Court has decided to review its decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such restrictions are not unique to Hinduism. In Islam, women are not permitted to partake in the fasting that characterises the month of Ramadan and are essentially seen as ‘impure’. Men are instructed to stay away from women on their periods and to refrain from having sexual intercourse during this time. Similarly, Judaism refers to such women as &lt;em&gt;‘niddah’&lt;/em&gt; and the Torah bans intercourse between a man and a menstruating woman. Besides, early Western Christian cultures considered a menstruating woman dangerous and placed restrictions on her to ensure safety for all. Even today, some church fathers continue to support the exclusion of women from the ministry on the basis of ‘uncleanliness’. The idea of women being impure or unclean during their periods is a very common notion among most of the world’s most popular religions and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are however, some religions that do not view menstruation in a bad light. This category includes the Sikhs and Buddhists. Now, there are some denominations of these religions that share the idea of menstruating women being unclean, but in general, their beliefs are less overbearing compared to the others. A similar and rather astonishing example is Shaktism, a major denomination of Hinduism. The followers of this sect celebrate the annual menstrual cycle, called Ambubachi, of Goddess Kamakhya at the Kamakhya Temple of Assam, India. This takes place every year in the month of June. It is celebrated in the form of the Ambubachi Mela, a four-day festival, wherein the doors of the temple remain closed for three days and open on the fourth to welcome thousands of pilgrims from around the world. This view of the natural process of menstruation is in stark contrast with the more popularly held Hindu views. It is important to note here that the most popular religions and their denominations across the world belong to the former category and do not view periods positively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion up until now provides a view that only the most religious people tend to see menstruation adversely. This is, however, not very accurate. A casual stigma associated with having periods pervades among all of us. Common experiences of women bear testimony to that. In India, packets of sanitary napkins are wrapped in newspaper and then handed over to the customer in a black polyethene packet. At this point, I am pretty sure the entire demographic is aware of what is inside and we might as well opt for a new measure to hide the fact that women menstruate. Girls often feel embarrassed while shopping for period products when the experience should be the same as buying band-aids. Many refrain from using tampons due to the fear of breaking their hymen before marriage, something that is often culturally looked down upon. Girls also usually feel ashamed after discovering a stain on their clothes, which again, under normal circumstances, should not have been viewed any differently than a blood soaked bandage. The point is this, we are consciously trying to hide the fact that having periods is a normal occurrence, affecting about half the human population every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misconceptions surrounding menstruation have always given it a bad name and resulted in women being oppressed. In Nepal, a very common practice is to move women on their periods to often very unhygienic menstrual huts. This practice, referred to as ‘Chhaupadi’, is actually illegal in Nepal, and yet it continues to exist as a commonplace practice. Several women die every year due to suffocation, snake bites, excessively cold weather and assault during their exile in these huts. The exact number of deaths due to this practice, however, is unknown as most of these cases go unreported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discrimination is not just limited to these instances. On a wider scale, menstruating women face the phenomenon of the ‘pink tax’. It is a common knowledge that a gender based wage gap exists even today in most fields of work. An additional value added tax to feminine products in such a scenario effectively reduces the purchasing power of women in general. Moreover, our economic structure fails to recognise period products as a necessity and chooses to see them as items of luxury. Thus, even they are not exempted from the pink tax. As I have mentioned in one of my previous articles, this comes across as if menstruation is a crime and women are being fined for the crime of menstruation. There have, however, been some positive changes in this avenue over the last few months. Due to the continuous efforts of Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and other Democrats, a few states in the US have taken the decision to repeal the Tampon Tax. The biggest win in this avenue was achieved by Scotland when the country became the first in the world to make all period products available to all women free of cost on February 27, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most other countries continue to charge heavily for menstrual hygiene products. The introduction of GST (Goods and Services Tax) in India on July 1, 2017 resulted in a 12% taxation on sanitary napkins. This sparked protests across the country and consequently, the tax on pads had to be repealed a year later. However, period products continue to be beyond the affordability of a large number of women in India. In rural areas of developing countries like India and other places where women’s accessibility to pads and tampons is very limited, menstruating women resort to the use of leaves for cleaning purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Period poverty is a major issue in the modern world. Many organisations across the world have taken it upon themselves to strive to ensure these basic requirements for all women. Sanjay Wijesekera, former UNICEF Chief of Water, Sanitation and Hygiene was once quoted as saying, “Meeting the hygiene needs of all adolescent girls is a fundamental issue of human rights, dignity and public health.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another rather surprising aspect of period products and menstruation is the lack of understanding of the subject among males. Now, since they do not have to face the monthly pain, they don’t really have to know how tampons are used. But a basic understanding of why it happens and the physical and mental complications associated with it is a necessity to at least make an attempt to tackle the misunderstandings and stigma around menstruation. Shockingly, even women tend to harbour a lot of misconceptions about the process like the belief that women living in close proximity sync up their menstrual cycles or that one cannot get pregnant while on their period. However, most educational set-ups across the world fail to clear these misconceptions due to the stigma associated with speaking about periods. It is almost an unspoken rule to not mention a naturally uncontrollable bodily phenomenon like menstruation. Even popular television shows like &lt;em&gt;Survivor&lt;/em&gt; and others, which have a basic premise of surviving in nature, fail to talk about how women deal with menstruation during their stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of the fact that women have been experiencing this phenomenon forever, the advancement in period products is rather disappointing. Tampons and pads, which are among the most popular period products to be used, are actually very bad for the environment. Besides, wearing one of these for a prolonged period of time may lead to the overgrowth of &lt;em&gt;staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; bacteria in the vagina and result in a condition called toxic shock syndrome. The symptoms include dizziness, diarrhoea and even fever. Very few environmentally-friendly options that are completely safe to use exist and these are well beyond the affordability of most women across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another of the major side effects of the menstrual stigma are the taunts. Back in 2015, when Donald Trump was caught in a tirade of questions from Fox News host Megyn Kelly, he claimed that she had “blood coming out of her wherever”, probably in an attempt to shut her up. He, however, denied it, later saying that he was actually referring to Kelly’s apparently bleeding nose. Comments like this have always been around and various aspects of menstruation have been used to provide variety to the taunts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premenstrual syndrome (PMS) is often used as a weapon to devalidate a woman’s concerns and feelings. In fact, my apprehensions involving PMS are not limited to just that. The phenomenon of premenstrual syndrome is characterised by a wide variety of symptoms including fatigue, cramps, diarrhoea, insomnia and depression. While each of these symptoms individually garners sympathy from most and can be a primary cause for being excused from work, the amalgamation of all, which is arguably worse, fails to do the same. This is primarily because of the association with the forbidden word: menstruation. The causes of these symptoms are not very well understood among the medical community but are primarily attributed to hormonal changes during the menstrual cycle. The lack of sympathy and understanding often results in adverse conditions for menstruating women, especially in the workplace. About 50 years ago, when Western women were entering the workforce in large numbers for the first time, conservative activists like Phyllis Schlafly claimed that women were hormonally ill-suited for positions of responsibility. This ideology continues to hinder women’s capacity to get an upgrade to a position of authority even today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that we are not talking enough about menstruation and unknowingly, continue to keep the stigma associated with it alive. As much as all of us want to believe that women are not oppressed anymore, it is still a dream that we might need a while to realise. Active measures to educate the masses on the body function, making period products and clean water available to all and actively fighting against cultural practices of discriminatory nature is the need of the hour. And this begins with people talking about periods, rather than pretending as if they are Voldemort and must not be named.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The amount one knows about the phenomenon known as menstruation depends on a number of things; sex, age, ethnicity and other characteristics. This is in spite of the fact that having periods is perhaps just as common as any other human bodily process, and is experienced on a monthly basis by roughly half of the world’s population. While there is a general awareness that periods are a necessity for fertility in women, not many people across the world are appreciative of what is involved in the process. Menstruating women are widely seen as ‘dirty’ and steps are taken to avoid them at all costs by people of certain communities. However, this stigma associated with menstruation is not just an issue of the ‘backward’ or ‘illiterate’ communities; it affects the most modern of societies too.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rioting Doesn’t Matter, Nothing Does</title><link href="/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rioting Doesn't Matter, Nothing Does" /><published>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter">&lt;p&gt;To anyone with any concern for humanity, what has happened in America should be deeply saddening and infuriating. The brutal killing of George Floyd by a police officer in Minneapolis has opened the floodgates of fury in America’s general populace. The National Guard has had to be deployed in many places. Courthouses, shops, town halls, homes and so many places have been burned to the ground by rioters. While thousands have been arrested, some rioters, police officers and protestors have been killed. President Trump has declared Antifa a terrorist organisation and has threatened to use the military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the situation is dire. Those on America’s Right have broadly issued boilerplate condemnations of the incident of police brutality, of course, but with no acknowledgement of the systemic oppression of Black people in America. And in classic American conservative fashion, they have condemned the retributive violence with evident dog whistles like those calling for “law and order” to be restored. The liberals, well, have been liberals, making boilerplate condemnations of systemic oppression without any real commitment towards an actual solution. As usual, they have been busy ‘turning people’s heads’ to bring attention to the problem by changing their profile pictures. In complete contrast, the leftists have been rejoicing; to them this is the beginning of a revolution that is going to end the hegemony of the ruling class in America and fulfill Marx’s prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the zeal of the American leftist in these riots is more masturbatory than it is idealistic, representing a mere Lacanian fantasy to find a new master instead of a true desire to usher in a just society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, one can see where the need for violence arises from. It would be foolish and immoral to argue that ‘violence is never the answer’. Violence becomes necessary to achieve tangible goals when the conscience of the powers that be simply remains unmoved by the scale of their own exploitation. Violence becomes unavoidable when the hand of the ‘system’ only seeks to whip and coerce people into submission. And in America, it should be incontrovertible to say that these conditions stand fulfilled, for police brutality against George Floyd is only the tip of the iceberg; crime, death, poverty, unfair treatment and so much more clearly evidences that American Black people are second-class citizens in a country that is partially built on enslaving them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, violence needs to be clearly channelised. It needs to be used to truly storm the Bastille or storm the Tsar’s Winter Palace. What it is definitely not supposed to be used for is burning a 7-11 or destroying the livelihoods of a lot of small businesses or pelting stones at everyday citizens. One can make theoretical arguments of how all businesses and everyday citizens who have been mute throughout, are complicit and need to face the fury as well. But one has to honestly ask oneself if that argument really holds water: The factum of being born in a society means one is subjected to its all-pervading influence that indoctrinates all into marginalising certain peoples, does that mean everyone in the world should be subjected to violence? Of course not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the social lives of conscious beings like humans, violence is as much physical as it is psychological. When we burn down a building or kill someone as part of a movement, we inevitably seek to psychologically challenge what that building or person represents. This is why there is a world of difference between burning a police station and vandalising a convenience store. The former is a clear challenge to the system of authority that killed George Floyd. The latter is saying that a person is not allowed to carry on his business because of their theoretical complicity, that the people who depended on that business for their wages do not deserve them. It should take no intellectual exegesis to point out that the latter kind of violence is directed at those who are merely the blind serfs of the overlord that is systemic oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that we find that the so-called revolution going on in America today is more ‘ideological’ in the postmodernist sense than anything. The violence in American streets hasn’t affected the American oligarchs at all. What it has done is far more miniscule yet far more sinister: the riots have ensured that the anger of the marginalised is directed at those who are only theoretically guilty to ensure that those who actually are guilty can continue to maintain their power. The ‘owners’ of the oasis in the desert of post-ideology have ensured that the thirsty fight against those who are allowed to fetch a pail of water instead of those who consume the whole pond. This is eminently proved by the outpouring of support that so many warlocks of the system, the TV show hosts, actors and musicians have shown for the riots. In fact, some of them have even offered to bail the rioters out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The riots in America are a clear example of how far late capitalism has gone to ensure it cannot be challenged. Even in this outpouring of violence, we are able to locate not a true challenge to the Machine. We can only see rage, rage that only affirms the master’s discourse. Perhaps that is all we can now have against capitalism, the trappings of ideology are far too great, the sinews of the invisible exploitative hand are too strong. Maybe, just maybe, we are doomed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anon.anon</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">To anyone with any concern for humanity, what has happened in America should be deeply saddening and infuriating. The brutal killing of George Floyd by a police officer in Minneapolis has opened the floodgates of fury in America’s general populace. The National Guard has had to be deployed in many places. Courthouses, shops, town halls, homes and so many places have been burned to the ground by rioters. While thousands have been arrested, some rioters, police officers and protestors have been killed. President Trump has declared Antifa a terrorist organisation and has threatened to use the military.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Private Data: A Public Good?</title><link href="/Private-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Private Data: A Public Good?" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Private-Data</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Private-Data">&lt;p&gt;While global economies have sent their growth-obsessed capitalistic policy approach on a hiatus for the year, with even the disgraced dragon dropping its annual economic growth targets for the first time since the 1990’s, the competitive aspect of the battle against COVID-19 has not left the grounds of policy-making. Taiwan has surfaced as a recent beneficiary of the comparative analysis initiated by global media houses. The nation is being rightfully lauded for managing to contain the current number of active cases under 500, despite its close proximity and intimate relations with China, the epicentre of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides proper screening, increasing testing capacity and mass insurance, the nation implemented a dynamic containment plan that required the government to partner with the local telecom operators in order to ensure that suspects were properly quarantined by tracking their GPS locations. The surveillance is said to be so precise that one asymptomatic carrier claimed via Twitter that the local police arrived at his doors within half an hour when he accidentally switched off his phone in the early morning hours, back in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During ordinary times, even a mild parliamentary discussion on tracking private data by the government would have been globally marketed as a sign of the nation becoming a digital dictatorship. However, the current crisis has demonstrated that perhaps drawing inferences from private data and using them as a public good has benefits that exceed the costs involved, while simultaneously upholding the privacy of individuals. (A public good is a non­-excludable, non-rivalrous good, i.e., individuals may consume without paying for it and one individual’s consumption does not hinder that of the other individuals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to correctly recognise the benefits of private data as a public good, one must acknowledge that the lack of information is a fundamental economic problem, in the non-textbook economic setup. Lack of resources then becomes a secondary issue in policy making, since a data inference needs to be drawn first to decide the direction of redistribution before subjecting it to any resource constraints. Often policymakers resolve the information problem by statistical sampling which is in itself expensive. Data can become quickly outdated which may lead to non-representative samples and other specification errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when digitalisation comes into the picture, it brings in better solutions to the information problem. It assists not only in policymaking but also in enforcing free-market equilibrium in certain markets by increasing the degree of market efficiency and allowing smoother real-time price discovery mechanisms, thus minimising distortions. An example would be E-NAM (Electronic National Agricultural Market), the online trading platform for agricultural goods, launched by the Indian government, which now has a membership of nearly 4.5 million farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other indirect and more relevant advantages of digitalisation include the large scale database of the digital footprints of a population. Presently, smartphones have become a very accessible device in even developing and emerging nations. The data generated by these devices is mainly with the concerned individual’s telecom operator, as well as other private parties that collect data from the users who install their mobile applications, e.g. Google, Facebook, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the private app developers have facilitated the birth of controversial practices like that of surveillance capitalism, by utilising the competitive edge provided in advertising avenues, the data generated can still be deemed an instrumental tool in studying various macro-level indicators about the population. For instance, by studying the pathway of the telecom antennae one’s device was connected to, one can easily track the real-time mobility of a population and generate migration patterns. Upon analysing the frequency and multitude of online transactions made in a certain period, one can even concretise their hypothesis about the direction of the economy in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If governments, like that of Taiwan, consistently manage to extract benefits out of aggregates of anonymised private data, they can manage to do so without violating individual rights as well as without robbing private benefactors off of the competitive edge generated by the data. The Economic Survey 2019, published by the Indian government, rightfully stated that data is of the people, for the people, and by the people. It acknowledged the lack of clarity and sophistication in the law specifying the ownership of data and elaborated upon the need to take advantage of the multitude of data that is generated. Due to data explosion, the marginal costs of data storage have fallen drastically, with one-gigabyte storage requiring a mere ₹3.48 now, as compared to ₹61,000 back in 1981.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even dissemination costs are negligible owing to real-time transfers over the internet. The marginal benefits, which include evidence-based policymaking, targeted implementation of the same and augmentation of accountability, easily outweigh the costs involved. Of course, in order for these benefits to be realised, there needs to be uniformity in the data circulated. Many schemes have already been launched as an initiative to merge data, such as the ‘Samagra Vedika’ initiative by the Telangana State government in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concerns about privacy are certainly valid since once the government gets its hands on the data; it may do with it as it pleases, which is why better laws need to be in place. Private data is very intimate individually, but collectively, it generates great value for the society, and hence, it is important to provide the data in an anonymised and aggregated form to the government. In the light of COVID-19, greater weight is added to the argument of involving public officials in the picture, not simply because we must track the cases and localise the spread, but also because it will help in conducting future studies to deduce patterns and give early warning signs. The debate is ongoing, but it is high time we make use of the data that is at our disposal to its full potential, in a manner that aligns with the population’s core values about the issue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">While global economies have sent their growth-obsessed capitalistic policy approach on a hiatus for the year, with even the disgraced dragon dropping its annual economic growth targets for the first time since the 1990’s, the competitive aspect of the battle against COVID-19 has not left the grounds of policy-making. Taiwan has surfaced as a recent beneficiary of the comparative analysis initiated by global media houses. The nation is being rightfully lauded for managing to contain the current number of active cases under 500, despite its close proximity and intimate relations with China, the epicentre of the crisis.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume</title><link href="/Lockdown-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Lockdown-Diaries</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Lockdown-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t know how to start; the last time I wrote to myself was in the eighth grade, when I wished desperately for the English exam to end, lest my hand fall off and I live without one with an awkward story to tell for as long as the world sustains. It’s not as weird as I thought it would be, honestly. I do talk to myself all the time, at 3 AM, wavering between what I should’ve said to some people two years back and all the possible ways that the world might end in (Armageddon is not left unconsidered, by the way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure this time is hard for every living person on the surface of this planet, and I’m not in this alone. Sometimes, my problems seem like a tiny little whine when I open the news and read about the horrible things happening around; people trying to survive, to get food and just breathe every day, hoping the sun doesn’t set, because if it does, there is another day of suffering waiting for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas as soon as I wake up, I wait eagerly for the dusk, creating a mental picture of the day ahead in my head, trying to bring a sense of organisation and calm to this commotion that life has become. It is almost like an annoying traffic jam, cars glued to the ground, an utterly piercing horn in the background that isn’t ready to subside and your foot on the pedal trying to move your car one bit at a time, as much as you can, to get out of this rut so that you can finally glide onto the highway, roll down your windows and let the cool autumn breeze embrace you until it touches your feet and you feel like all is okay in the world again. I feel as if these days I’m just waiting for this jam to clear, so that I can take in that air again as I rush my car through the freeway, and go anywhere I want, no restrictions, just the journey and the destination ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I just romanticise a pandemic? I’m afraid so. Reading a little too much of Mitch Albom, watching a string of Jane Austen classic movies and smelling books and teas doesn’t make you a &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; millennial, I’m sure. Just your average old-school -person, who loves cardigans and sighs when they look at &lt;em&gt;tiktoks&lt;/em&gt;, referring to it as ‘these kids’ when you’re a 20-year-old yourself (or more like an 80-year-old woman stuck in a 20-year-old’s body).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even though I enjoy my old-person traits most days, it’s certainly hard to keep up with it when you live in the year 2020, jailed amidst the four walls of your room. The internet and social media isn’t a respite because you cannot for the life of you comprehend the conundrum that is #quarantineandchill or the Dalgona coffee trend? (I mean it’s just coffee upside down). I know that I have all the time in the world to read all those books and literary wonders that I keep crying about when I didn’t have enough time or listen to Sam Cooke all day and Paul McCartney the next. And it was all about those books, songs and heartwarming movies but only for a good four weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the fifth week started to unfold, I missed the smell of freshly roasted coffee that came wafting from the cafes that I walked past, pulling me towards themselves as the moon does to the tides - just simple laws of gravity. And that’s just not it. I miss my entire commute to university every day - waking up early yet late, at 7 am (yes that was sadly late) and crying about it, while I rush to get ready and catch a ride to the metro-station as my hair is soaking wet and I drench the marble floors of my house as I sprint around, trying to find my glasses and earphones. I would gulp my cold coffee whole, while my mother gave me a sniggering look for skipping breakfast and yet would sneak in a sandwich wrapped in aluminium foil in my bag when I wasn’t looking. I miss the morning breeze that air-dried my hair in the auto-rickshaw, while I fiddled with my earphones and rummaged through my playlist for a morning boost of Mumford and Sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would give up all of the social media, yes, Instagram and Snapchat and whatever new application the kids are using these days for a train ride to college, filled with strangers, all so hurried, so hasty, to reach somewhere, pushing and fumbling through the metro - I would find an uncanny sense of calm in it. This uncertainty and muddled life has made me realize how much I also miss studying or skipping the first-morning class to hang out in the cafeteria instead with a cup of steaming coffee and half-forgotten anecdotes from old nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me or does anyone else also miss the yellow and red flowers strewn about on the streets in March? It is not easy for a memory hoarder to get through these tough times without lapsing into nostalgia every other minute. Not easy for a person who loves stray discourses on politics, life, love, career and books over a cup of tea to text people and still have that fiery enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not undermining my privilege, for I know these aren’t the issues that matter in the least right now. But I think writing them down makes me feel a tad better - like I’m ranting to someone as I would in the &lt;em&gt;old days&lt;/em&gt;, if I may.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like a true old-soul, these past three months have made me realize how much I enjoy my own company rather than texting away or relying on social media to get through the day. And I don’t think less of anyone who does that; whatever one finds their peace in. But it’s hard to blend in sometimes for monochromes in this vibrant world, when all you want is to cook yourself nice, steaming-hot banana bread and curl into your bed with a sad PDF. (I miss the smell of books).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think all I want is a redo sometimes. I know I couldn’t change anything; I couldn’t stop the pandemic because that is beyond my corporeal control. However, if I do get a redo, as I imagine- &lt;em&gt;I see myself standing at the jostling platform of Rajiv Chowk Metro Station in Delhi- people brushing past and into each other. I might be looking at them indifferently, as my earphones pulse to the tunes of The Beach Boys. It looks like a tiresome day and I don’t pay heed to the stranger next to me, who smells like Fijian Water Lotus mist. If only I knew it was the last time I’d smell an unfamiliar perfume, I would’ve stepped a little lighter, would’ve breathed a little longer. I would’ve lingered for a slow second before stepping out the metro doors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waiting,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poorvi.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?</title><link href="/European-Central-Bank" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?" /><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/European-Central-Bank</id><content type="html" xml:base="/European-Central-Bank">&lt;p&gt;Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms Lagarde, however, is of the view that monetary policy is not the first line of defence and feels that fiscal response must be given much more importance. The persistent heterogeneity in the Euro area has also been a long-standing concern for the single monetary policy. It severely complicates the conduct of this policy. The current crisis exposed these vulnerabilities, once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since 2008, the EU has been in a non-stop crisis mode. Even the interest rate it charges to the commercial banks is almost nil leaving very little margin for further rate cuts to stimulate the economy out of this rut. The ECB has acknowledged how they are facing an unprecedented crisis with historic consequences which might just push the European economy to worse than what it was in 2008. If the crisis is not controlled by the stimuli, it risks pushing the already wobbly European economy to the state of recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 16, the ECB went ahead and announced the measures it will be taking on the monetary policy front while it gives time to the respective governments to formulate fiscal policy measures. The ECB took certain measures to prevent the crisis from becoming a full-blown financial crisis with two broad objectives: first, to restore the orderly functioning of presently volatile European financial markets, and second, to ensure that the accommodative monetary policy measures support firms and households in incurring the social and economic costs of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECB response consists of three major mutually reinforcing grounds. The first one relating to broad-based asset purchases to address illiquidity and volatility in core segments of the European economy. The temporary Pandemic Emergency Purchase Programme (PEPP) constitutes the core of this component. The economies in the entire Eurozone have been struggling with tightening fiscal and economic conditions, the PEPP expects to release the pressure on these economies. It foresees purchases at a volume of €750 billion of eligible private and public securities throughout this year, and longer if needed.  The ECB also aims to mitigate the impact of the crisis on the funding conditions of businesses and banks. For the same, it has decided to divert a considerable fraction of the additional €120 billion purchase envelope under the Asset Purchase Programmes (APP), as well as of the PEPP, for eligible private sector bonds. However, one cannot turn a blind eye to the fact that the bank has already been conducting purchases of government bonds, and now, it does not have much to re-purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, measures to ensure that the banks remain effective carriers of the monetary policy of the ECB have been introduced. The enhanced Targeted Longer-Term Refinancing Operations (TLTROs), as well as a comprehensive set of collateral easing measures, form part of this component.  The interest rate on all targeted TLTROs was reduced by 25 basis points to -0.5% from June 2020 to June 2021. Measures to ensure the solvency of banks by holding up the role of lender of the last resort to the banks which will help the ECB drive the way for economic growth. This becomes all the more necessary considering that the European economy is majorly a bank-based economy than a financial market one, so just supporting the financial markets would not help alleviate the effects of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures for small and medium-sized firms are equally necessary, which include bank lending and loan guarantee schemes to protect the already overdrawn credit lines by cash strapped firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Italy, for example, bank lending conditions for firms remained remarkably resilient in recent years despite significant swings in market-based funding conditions of the banks and firms. Again, the measures can provide a valuable bridge to the future and help keep aggregate external funding costs of firms stable until the economy recovers and uncertainty diminishes further. This also includes accepting a wider range of assets as collaterals from small and medium-sized firms along with consistently working on the liquidity conditions of the banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ECB fails to improve liquidity indirectly through these measures, it always has the option to exercise its right to issue ‘helicopter money’. This alternative would put the money straight into the ‘hands’ of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these measures, the ECB hopes to improve liquidity and market behaviour in the sovereign yield bonds market, which in turn form the basis of pricing of assets in the economy. The ECB uses the GDP-weighted Euro area government bond yield curve as a measure for the effectiveness of the economy, but currently, this curve has been badly disrupted. So the ECB will focus on stabilising this curve and reversing the steepness of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while the Eurozone faces an increasingly threatening risk of a slowdown in the economy, which can take years to recover from and get back to the normal levels, the ECB and various governments are taking steps to tackle this challenge. The cluster of countries has recovered from far worse situations in the past, like the global economic crisis of 2008, and emerged stronger than ever. It remains to be seen what other steps the European Union takes as a much worse crisis than COVID-19 awaits the global economy and how the relief package unravels for the Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kashish Jindal</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can Self-Reliance be the New Norm: A Take on India’s ‘Atma-nirbharata’</title><link href="/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Self-Reliance be the New Norm: A Take on India’s ‘Atma-nirbharata’" /><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm">&lt;p&gt;“To stand on one’s own feet” is how 10th-grade economics teachers sum up the concept of self-reliance. The thinking behind India’s advocacy for this concept is premised upon the scars of colonialism. However, with the liberalisation of the Indian economy by the Narasimha Rao-led government, the concept had practically faded away from Indian public policy discourse. 29 years later, with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calling upon Indians to ‘be vocal for local’ and emphasising self-reliance, it seems to be taking the centre-stage once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-reliance can be defined as “dependence on one’s own natural resources to produce goods and services to satisfy the demand”. One of the many problems with this is that every economy faces a dearth of resources, which are inputs required to produce goods (and services). One rather famous quip in economics goes like this: ‘resources are limited, while [human] wants are unlimited’. Every nation cannot produce everything on a scale sufficient to meet its domestic demand. Even if we suppose, for argument’s sake, that we could achieve the impossible, it is important to realise that self-reliance is a dynamic concept. If you look at it, achieving self-reliance is to successfully meet the aggregate demand of all the people in an economy; that is, conforming production along the lines of consumers’ tastes and preferences. There is no guarantee that these tastes will remain constant (unless, of course, if states ‘determine’ tastes!). So, if one were to adhere to the definition of self-reliance, one ought to change production constantly, keeping pace with the change in tastes and demands of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, the scarcity of resources prompts states to resort to protectionist measures so as to encourage local producers. There is no ruling-out of a misallocation of resources in such circumstances, due to lack of economies of scale (a resultant of protectionist policies). This leads to a drastic loss in the productivity of a country and results in a deadweight loss for society. To put this in perspective, let us look at the total factor productivity of India. Total Factor Production may be defined as the increase in the growth of output that can be attributed to factors other than capital and labour. This can be the result of many reasons including a change in the quality of inputs, new techniques of production, better management of resources, and so on. One study finds that the average total factor productivity growth was negative for the 1970’s, when protectionism was at its heyday. In fact, there were frequent instances of negative growth in total factor production (where total factor production fell below zero) before 1991. Only after reforms, did the metric pick up pace, remaining positive throughout. From 2001-2008, total factor production grew at an average of 3.36%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second impact of protectionist measures is that the cost of production is (relatively) high and results in higher prices for the consumers. Why should a government, in the name of self-sufficiency, let its consumers pay a higher price for a good that would be available for a cheaper price when imported? This certainly is not how a rational entity would (or should) behave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of self-reliance also begs the question of who is to determine the scale and intensity of production to achieve this self-reliance and how is this to be determined. If history is any guide, this is often determined by the state. And this means curtailing of choices on the part of the consumer and a massive involvement of the government in the supply side or the production side. It implies that the allocation of resources is controlled by the government and every producer (or entrepreneur) relies heavily on the government to take any decision. This control is exercised by the way of issuing licenses. The infamously dubbed practice of ‘license raj’ is exactly this. This can also discourage potential entrepreneurs from coming forward to start a business. Accepting this excessive government control would mean that bureaucrats, with no experience in business management whatsoever, would run the businesses rather than people competent to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, this is not the type of self-reliance a country should be aiming for. A country should be aiming at self-reliance in terms of human capital. In today’s global world, ideas and innovation are what sets a country apart. As renowned economist and Nobel laureate Paul Romer said, “&lt;em&gt;Growth springs from better recipes, not just from better cooking&lt;/em&gt;”. His view was that ideas of non-rival character, generated by profit-maximising entrepreneurs will lead to economic growth. This emphasises the role of human capital in the course of economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for many reasons, there has been a constant outflow of human capital from our country to advanced nations like the US and the UK. It is crucial for India to recognise that every emigrant is productivity lost and innovation foregone. So, when I say self-reliance on human capital, I mean the creation of institutions of the highest excellence to truly harness human capital. However, the disappointing budget allocation for education by the Indian government (4.6% of the GDP in 2019-2020) shows that it has no plans to improve in this specific sector. India ought to increase education spending and allocate (and disburse) more funds toward PhD research, which are now sparse and available mainly for technology courses. Only self-reliance in terms of human capital is sustaining and yields increasing returns and hence should be a priority for the government. This is important to arrest the outflow of human capital out of the country whether for studies or permanent migration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">“To stand on one’s own feet” is how 10th-grade economics teachers sum up the concept of self-reliance. The thinking behind India’s advocacy for this concept is premised upon the scars of colonialism. However, with the liberalisation of the Indian economy by the Narasimha Rao-led government, the concept had practically faded away from Indian public policy discourse. 29 years later, with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calling upon Indians to ‘be vocal for local’ and emphasising self-reliance, it seems to be taking the centre-stage once again.</summary></entry></feed>