<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-31T20:00:31+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Rise of the New Age Nazis</title><link href="/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the New Age Nazis" /><published>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis">&lt;p&gt;On December 14th, 2020, the Labour leader Keir Starmer appeared on radio show LBC with host Nick Ferrari when a caller, introducing herself as ‘Gemma from Cambridge,’ took the opportunity to propagate the Neo — Nazi ‘Great Replacement’ conspiracy theory on a national media platform. She stated: “in the wake of organisations such as BLM and other racial advocacy groups pushing what’s best for their people, I just want to ask, should white people also start playing identity politics now, before they become a minority themselves by 2066?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bizarre event was made even more bewildering when a Twitter user &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/redflareinfo/status/1338453892661714945&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt; that ‘Gemma from Cambridge’ was in fact Jody Swingler, a yoga teacher and musician living in Ibiza, a far cry from the archetypal image of the hapless neo-nazi social outcast in their parents’ basement, pulling the wings off flies and ranting on obscure online messageboards about how The Jews had prevented them from securing a girlfriend. Swingler had also &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/redflareinfo/status/1338453897258668033&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt; two YouTube shows with Mark Collett and Laura Melia, leaders of the white nationalist political party Patriotic Alternative, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hopenothate.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/HnH_Patriotic-Alternative-report_2020-08-v3.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;opposes&lt;/a&gt; the “replacement and displacement” of white Britons by people who “have no right to these lands.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem striking that people who advocate new age, spiritual beliefs, previously associated with ‘flower power’ and the countercultural movement of the 1960s, could wind up on the same side as the far right. But in fact, the link between new age spirituality and extremist politics is not new. The Nazis drew support from the occultist Thule Society, and prominent Nazi figures such as Heinrich Himmler and Rudolf Hess endorsed homeopathy and alternative medicine, with Himmler supporting using plant extracts to cure cancer. In 1934, Hess set up an alternative medicine centre in Dresden. Their embrace of holism and spirituality, broadly, was underpinned by a rejection of the precepts of the Enlightenment, which posited that the world could be understood through logical processes, subordinating religious and monarchical obscurantism to the supremacy of the faculty of reason. Many Nazi figures saw a romanticised, agrarian age as a solution to the modern menaces of industrialisation and materialism. For example, Ernst Lehmann, a Nazi professor of botany, stated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We recognize that separating humanity from nature, from the whole of life, leads to humankind’s own destruction and to the death of nations. Only through a reintegration of humanity into the whole of nature can our people be made stronger… This striving toward connectedness with the totality of life, with nature itself, a nature into which we are born, this is the deepest meaning and the true essence of National Socialist thought.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A desire to undo the crude, materialist logic that undergirded liberal democracy, and to restructure the relationship between the citizen and the State, therefore, spawned the Nazis’ fascination with holism and the reintegration of man with nature. “Blood and soil” meant an organic connection with one’s homeland that could not be expressed through the civic or legal frameworks engendered by the minority protection clauses of the League of Nations, but only through the maintenance of racial purity. Mark Mazower wrote in his book ‘Dark Continent’ that:“The League (of Nations) , after all, was an organisation of States. But what was the State? According to Hitler’s biological view of politics, it was no less than a ‘living organism,’” adding: “Hitler’s own vision of geopolitics unlike that of many geopoliticians — rested upon race: the State itself was merely an expression of the racial ‘Volk.’” Railing against the ‘juridification of politics,’ many Nazi legal theorists saw the nation as a biological organism, corruptible by outside influences and requiring protection from alleged Jewish subversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Marquette University history professor Peter Staudenmeier &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/154971/rise-ecofascism-history-white-nationalism-environmental-preservation-immigration&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;describes&lt;/a&gt; as the “link between a yearning for purity in the environmental sphere and a desire for racialized purity in the social sphere” also undergirds the ecofascist tendencies common to many modern neo-nazis such as Anders Brevik and the El Paso shooter, who characterised non white populations as invaders seeking to despoil the environment through having more children and consuming more resources. This was also reflected in the writings of ecologist Garrett Hardin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/individual/garrett-hardin&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;listed&lt;/a&gt; by the SPLC as a white nationalist, who wrote about the supposed threats that overpopulation posed to the Earth’s future. The myth of overpopulation has, however, been roundly debunked; a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2020/sep/21/worlds-richest-1-cause-double-co2-emissions-of-poorest-50-says-oxfam#:~:text=1%20month%20old-,World's%20richest%201%25%20cause%20double%20CO2,of%20poorest%2050%25%2C%20says%20Oxfam&amp;amp;text=The%20wealthiest%201%25%20of%20the,2015%2C%20according%20to%20new%20research.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; from Oxfam showed that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, the contention that COVID-19 is a hoax has been a point of convergence between new age hippies and the far-right. Back in October, thousands of anti-vaxxers marched through Trafalgar Square in London at the COVID-sceptic ‘Unite for Freedom’ event, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nicktolhurst/status/1299729414767497219?lang=en&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;during which&lt;/a&gt; a BUF (British Union of Fascists) flag was spotted. The event was hosted by notorious conspiracy theorist David Icke, whose theories have been endorsed by both neo-nazis groups such as Combat 18, and the new age spiritual movement. It was also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-election-2020/jake-angeli-qanon-shaman-stormed-capitol-b1784091.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt; that Jake Angeli, a Trump supporter nicknamed the ‘QAnon shaman’ who stormed the Capitol, had stated that COVID-19 was a hoax. According to his mother, he had also refused to eat non-organic food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two groups are united in their rejection of the perceived infringement on their liberties; in the case of the far-right, the supposed stifling of their ability to criticise the unaccountable technocracy that is allegedly imposing open borders and multiculturalism, and in the case of the new age conspiracists, the personal, bodily autonomy connoted by “natural” methods of healing, which are at odds with modern, scientific forms of inoculation such as vaccines. The excoriation of Bill Gates as a central figure in a supposed global plot to undermine civil liberties by using vaccines as a method of social control, including implanting microchips into unfortunate victims, has also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymotion.com/video/x64vj4&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;propagated&lt;/a&gt; by conspiracy theorist Alex Jones, who has suggested that vaccines are part of a government- induced eugenics programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A theory known as the ‘Great Reset’ has also taken root in many far right circles, pushed by websites such as Breitbart, which asserts that COVID-19 represents an attempt by a cabal of wealthy politicians, financiers and bureaucrats to establish a global government, eroding national sovereignty and dictating fiscal and monetary policy. During a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ugRnjpXEwTo&amp;amp;t=114s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;conversation&lt;/a&gt; with former Alex Jones acolyte Paul Joseph Watson, Breitbart columnist James Delingpole described the Great Reset as “another variation on the theme of the New World Order,” stating: “it’s a technocratic elite — an unelected technocratic elite — deciding how you and I should live our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scepticism towards authority and heightened awareness of the erosion of civil liberties by governments using crises as a pretext to usher in technocratic dominance is not without merit. In an era characterised by the technocratic monopolisation of communications by companies whose business models are predicated on mining consumer data, in which a global pandemic has drastically increased the purview of the State’s influence over the lives of ordinary citizens, and in which finance, industry and production have all been centralised in the hands of a few multinational corporations, it is not unreasonable to be wary of authoritarian overreach.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the vague criticisms of systems of power enunciated by new age hippies, and the wild, conspiratorial denunciations of the ‘New World Order’ or the ‘Great Reset,’ common to extreme right wing political figures lack an empirical, material analysis. While it is certainly true that in Britain, at least, the pandemic has seen a worrying development in outsourcing the ‘Test and Trace’ system to companies such as G4S and Serco, which have been involved in nefarious operations from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-51573510&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;setting up&lt;/a&gt; immigration detention centres to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justice.gov.uk/about/hmps/contracted-out&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;developing&lt;/a&gt; some of Britain’s first for-profit prisons, the potential for government overreach is no grounds for denying the existence, or the severity, of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As outlined above, both aforementioned groups reject a materialist, empirically rigorous analysis of the global economy and the role of the State in abrogating civil liberties, idealising a preindustrial, agrarian past and asserting that the world’s problems are caused by a shadowy cabal (the root of most antisemitic conspiracy theories). This pandemic has shown that these groups, though widely considered to have diametrically opposed political interests, are more similar than they appear, and have been willing to set aside their ideological differences for the pursuit of wider goals. Unless their scepticism of the technocratic impulses of governments seeking to curtail civil liberties, much of which is justified, can be countered with a thorough and precise refutation of conspiratorial political narratives, the implications of this unholy alliance could be significant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">On December 14th, 2020, the Labour leader Keir Starmer appeared on radio show LBC with host Nick Ferrari when a caller, introducing herself as ‘Gemma from Cambridge,’ took the opportunity to propagate the Neo — Nazi ‘Great Replacement’ conspiracy theory on a national media platform. She stated: “in the wake of organisations such as BLM and other racial advocacy groups pushing what’s best for their people, I just want to ask, should white people also start playing identity politics now, before they become a minority themselves by 2066?” This bizarre event was made even more bewildering when a Twitter user revealed that ‘Gemma from Cambridge’ was in fact Jody Swingler, a yoga teacher and musician living in Ibiza, a far cry from the archetypal image of the hapless neo-nazi social outcast in their parents’ basement, pulling the wings off flies and ranting on obscure online messageboards about how The Jews had prevented them from securing a girlfriend. Swingler had also recorded two YouTube shows with Mark Collett and Laura Melia, leaders of the white nationalist political party Patriotic Alternative, which opposes the “replacement and displacement” of white Britons by people who “have no right to these lands.” It may seem striking that people who advocate new age, spiritual beliefs, previously associated with ‘flower power’ and the countercultural movement of the 1960s, could wind up on the same side as the far right. But in fact, the link between new age spirituality and extremist politics is not new. The Nazis drew support from the occultist Thule Society, and prominent Nazi figures such as Heinrich Himmler and Rudolf Hess endorsed homeopathy and alternative medicine, with Himmler supporting using plant extracts to cure cancer. In 1934, Hess set up an alternative medicine centre in Dresden. Their embrace of holism and spirituality, broadly, was underpinned by a rejection of the precepts of the Enlightenment, which posited that the world could be understood through logical processes, subordinating religious and monarchical obscurantism to the supremacy of the faculty of reason. Many Nazi figures saw a romanticised, agrarian age as a solution to the modern menaces of industrialisation and materialism. For example, Ernst Lehmann, a Nazi professor of botany, stated: “We recognize that separating humanity from nature, from the whole of life, leads to humankind’s own destruction and to the death of nations. Only through a reintegration of humanity into the whole of nature can our people be made stronger… This striving toward connectedness with the totality of life, with nature itself, a nature into which we are born, this is the deepest meaning and the true essence of National Socialist thought.” A desire to undo the crude, materialist logic that undergirded liberal democracy, and to restructure the relationship between the citizen and the State, therefore, spawned the Nazis’ fascination with holism and the reintegration of man with nature. “Blood and soil” meant an organic connection with one’s homeland that could not be expressed through the civic or legal frameworks engendered by the minority protection clauses of the League of Nations, but only through the maintenance of racial purity. Mark Mazower wrote in his book ‘Dark Continent’ that:“The League (of Nations) , after all, was an organisation of States. But what was the State? According to Hitler’s biological view of politics, it was no less than a ‘living organism,’” adding: “Hitler’s own vision of geopolitics unlike that of many geopoliticians — rested upon race: the State itself was merely an expression of the racial ‘Volk.’” Railing against the ‘juridification of politics,’ many Nazi legal theorists saw the nation as a biological organism, corruptible by outside influences and requiring protection from alleged Jewish subversion. What Marquette University history professor Peter Staudenmeier describes as the “link between a yearning for purity in the environmental sphere and a desire for racialized purity in the social sphere” also undergirds the ecofascist tendencies common to many modern neo-nazis such as Anders Brevik and the El Paso shooter, who characterised non white populations as invaders seeking to despoil the environment through having more children and consuming more resources. This was also reflected in the writings of ecologist Garrett Hardin, listed by the SPLC as a white nationalist, who wrote about the supposed threats that overpopulation posed to the Earth’s future. The myth of overpopulation has, however, been roundly debunked; a study from Oxfam showed that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%. More recently, the contention that COVID-19 is a hoax has been a point of convergence between new age hippies and the far-right. Back in October, thousands of anti-vaxxers marched through Trafalgar Square in London at the COVID-sceptic ‘Unite for Freedom’ event, during which a BUF (British Union of Fascists) flag was spotted. The event was hosted by notorious conspiracy theorist David Icke, whose theories have been endorsed by both neo-nazis groups such as Combat 18, and the new age spiritual movement. It was also revealed that Jake Angeli, a Trump supporter nicknamed the ‘QAnon shaman’ who stormed the Capitol, had stated that COVID-19 was a hoax. According to his mother, he had also refused to eat non-organic food. The two groups are united in their rejection of the perceived infringement on their liberties; in the case of the far-right, the supposed stifling of their ability to criticise the unaccountable technocracy that is allegedly imposing open borders and multiculturalism, and in the case of the new age conspiracists, the personal, bodily autonomy connoted by “natural” methods of healing, which are at odds with modern, scientific forms of inoculation such as vaccines. The excoriation of Bill Gates as a central figure in a supposed global plot to undermine civil liberties by using vaccines as a method of social control, including implanting microchips into unfortunate victims, has also been propagated by conspiracy theorist Alex Jones, who has suggested that vaccines are part of a government- induced eugenics programme. A theory known as the ‘Great Reset’ has also taken root in many far right circles, pushed by websites such as Breitbart, which asserts that COVID-19 represents an attempt by a cabal of wealthy politicians, financiers and bureaucrats to establish a global government, eroding national sovereignty and dictating fiscal and monetary policy. During a conversation with former Alex Jones acolyte Paul Joseph Watson, Breitbart columnist James Delingpole described the Great Reset as “another variation on the theme of the New World Order,” stating: “it’s a technocratic elite — an unelected technocratic elite — deciding how you and I should live our lives.” Scepticism towards authority and heightened awareness of the erosion of civil liberties by governments using crises as a pretext to usher in technocratic dominance is not without merit. In an era characterised by the technocratic monopolisation of communications by companies whose business models are predicated on mining consumer data, in which a global pandemic has drastically increased the purview of the State’s influence over the lives of ordinary citizens, and in which finance, industry and production have all been centralised in the hands of a few multinational corporations, it is not unreasonable to be wary of authoritarian overreach.&amp;nbsp; However, the vague criticisms of systems of power enunciated by new age hippies, and the wild, conspiratorial denunciations of the ‘New World Order’ or the ‘Great Reset,’ common to extreme right wing political figures lack an empirical, material analysis. While it is certainly true that in Britain, at least, the pandemic has seen a worrying development in outsourcing the ‘Test and Trace’ system to companies such as G4S and Serco, which have been involved in nefarious operations from setting up immigration detention centres to developing some of Britain’s first for-profit prisons, the potential for government overreach is no grounds for denying the existence, or the severity, of COVID-19. As outlined above, both aforementioned groups reject a materialist, empirically rigorous analysis of the global economy and the role of the State in abrogating civil liberties, idealising a preindustrial, agrarian past and asserting that the world’s problems are caused by a shadowy cabal (the root of most antisemitic conspiracy theories). This pandemic has shown that these groups, though widely considered to have diametrically opposed political interests, are more similar than they appear, and have been willing to set aside their ideological differences for the pursuit of wider goals. Unless their scepticism of the technocratic impulses of governments seeking to curtail civil liberties, much of which is justified, can be countered with a thorough and precise refutation of conspiratorial political narratives, the implications of this unholy alliance could be significant.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Relax, AI is Not as Smart as You Think</title><link href="/Relax-AI-is-Not-as-Smart-as-You-Think" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Relax, AI is Not as Smart as You Think" /><published>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Relax-AI-is-Not-as-Smart-as-You-Think</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Relax-AI-is-Not-as-Smart-as-You-Think">&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a term broadly used to describe some innovation that is trying to solve yet another problem. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/artificial-intelligence-public-awareness-survey&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; by the UK government in 2019 on over 2,400 individuals reported that a good majority know what AI is, but only 12% know a lot about AI. This is no surprise, and the media doesn’t do well to clarify this uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An early definition of AI was proposed by Alan Turing 70 years ago. He described a method to determine if a machine exhibits intelligent behaviour, known as the 'Imitation Game' - a game where an interrogator judges if the responses to their questions are from a human or machine. Unsurprisingly, this is a great definition. However, as technology advances, problems that were once thought of as only solvable by humans have become ‘easily’ solvable by AI, and are no longer classified as AI problems. This paradox is known as the 'AI Effect'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before breaking down some AI that you might have heard of, I want to be clear about something that is very often misunderstood. AI can be grouped into two categories: Logic Programming&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(rule-based intelligence) and Machine Learning&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(data-driven intelligence). In the former category, the intelligence of the AI is developed by researchers. They would very carefully study the domain of the problem and describe a set of rules and instructions which would best output a solution to the problem. In the latter category, intelligence is learned by AI. The researcher would typically use an existing learning technique on a model with tweakable settings, and apply it to historical data from the domain of the problem. Then the settings of the model which would output the best possible solution to the problem are found based on the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI in both these categories has garnered a great deal of positive media attention, and rightfully so, but they have attributed to the great misunderstanding of AI that is widespread in society. Two examples of board game matches from the past 25 years apparently exhibit great strides in AI, but are mostly a testament to computing power rather than intelligent behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Logic Programming AI made history in 1997 when IBM’s supercomputer Deep Blue beat the then reigning world champion in a match of chess under standard tournament conditions. Deep Blue follows a set of logical rules to search for the best sequence of moves needed to win, with its prowess coming from its computational speed. At the time, it could evaluate about 200 million chess moves per second (7-12 turns ahead) and its strategy to win could be completely analysed and interpreted by the researchers, i.e. the reason why it made a particular move was fully understood. Although Deep Blue has no practical applications other than playing chess, it proved that AI could outperform human intelligence at a game often associated with requiring high intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a similar problem, a Machine Learning AI made history in 2016 when Google’s AlphaGo beat the 18-time world champion in a match of Go. Go is a far more complicated game than chess and it is arguably the most complex game ever devised. The number of possible moves from each position of a chess game is about 20 whereas a Go game is about 200. A Logic Programming AI would need to evaluate about 60 trillion moves to think just 6 turns ahead, so finding the best sequence of moves needed to win the game would be unfeasible. Google’s researchers used Deep Reinforcement Learning to tackle the problem. This learning technique was developed in the 1980's and stemmed from research into animal psychology. In this case, the AI was initially presented with 100,000 games of Go and, given rewards when it won, it learned how to play the game. It then played against itself millions of times to iteratively get better, until it was better than a world champion Go player. Unfortunately, this intelligent behaviour comes at a cost; it took 3 days to train AlphaGo and it consumed what would usually be $&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yuzeh.com/data/agz-cost.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2 million&lt;/a&gt; of Google's computational power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to Deep Blue, the researchers developing AlphaGo didn’t need to have any prior knowledge of the rules of the game. The AI managed to learn the rules of the game and how to win all by itself. This was a feat of general intelligence, but there are some shortcomings to this kind of AI. What exactly has AlphaGo learned and was it worth the cost?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AlphaGo belongs to a subset of Machine Learning known as Deep Learning (note that the naming of Deep Blue is a coincidence and it is not classified as Deep Learning) which is notorious for requiring a substantial amount of computational power to learn. Deep Learning AIs spend days churning data to learn how to solve a problem. A study on the energy consumption of hardware built for Deep Learning revealed that the learning process can &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.02243&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;emit as much carbon&lt;/a&gt; as the lifetime of five midsize sedans. In addition to that, the intelligent behaviour learned is uninterpretable by even the developers themselves, i.e. we will never know why AlphaGo makes a particular move. Maybe this isn’t such a big problem in a game of Go as the results of the AI are phenomenal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of AI has amazingly made its way into governments and judicial systems, but has also been the centre of criticism from the media and public alike. In 2016, the Wisconsin Supreme Court ruled for judges to use it as an aid to assess the risk of recidivism. Little is understood about COMPAS since it uses trade secrets. This prompted two independent researchers to compare it to the most basic Machine Learning AI (a linear regression), and they found that there was no significant difference; COMPAS does nothing extraordinarily ‘intelligent’. To add insult to injury, an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/article/how-we-analyzed-the-compas-recidivism-algorithm&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; into its risk assessments revealed that there is an inherent bias that favours white people to be classified as low-risk and black people to be classified as high-risk. This is a big concern in Machine Learning which is driven by historical data. If the data itself is inherently biased then the AI learning from it would be biased as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cherry on top for how AI is misunderstood was seen in Australia; the RoboDebt scheme. In 2016, the Australian government decided to enlist the help of AI to crack down on the abuse of their welfare system and clawback A$1.5 billion in three years. They implemented an automated debt recovery system (a seemingly Logic Programming AI) that was meant to accurately calculate how much a person owed or was owed by the government. Ironically, it has since incurred the Australian government A$1.2 billion in refunds and payouts.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many things wrong with the implementation of the RoboDebt scheme, but let’s look at it from a purely technical standpoint. To this day, there hasn’t been any scrutiny against the AI used. Put simply it did exactly what it was meant to do and nothing more. The human checks and balances that were in place prior to the AI, however, were completely removed and they weren’t replaced. Fundamental errors in the system weren’t caught. In fact, the biggest technical scrutiny was from the way the Australian government averaged income. This was in place much before RoboDebt and its introduction only perpetuated the already existing problem at a rapid rate. Perhaps an AI is only as ‘intelligent’ as the people it is solving a problem for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the AI stories that make it to the headlines greatly tip the scales of its perception and propagate misunderstanding in society. A single AI story shouldn’t shape it as a whole as there are many different types of AI, and we have only scratched the surface in this article. Most AI research doesn’t make it to the headlines. However, there are many great applications and use cases of AI which will shape our future, and only when it does will we hear about it. Until then all we can do is learn a little more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kheeran Naidu</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a term broadly used to describe some innovation that is trying to solve yet another problem. A survey by the UK government in 2019 on over 2,400 individuals reported that a good majority know what AI is, but only 12% know a lot about AI. This is no surprise, and the media doesn’t do well to clarify this uncertainty. An early definition of AI was proposed by Alan Turing 70 years ago. He described a method to determine if a machine exhibits intelligent behaviour, known as the 'Imitation Game' - a game where an interrogator judges if the responses to their questions are from a human or machine. Unsurprisingly, this is a great definition. However, as technology advances, problems that were once thought of as only solvable by humans have become ‘easily’ solvable by AI, and are no longer classified as AI problems. This paradox is known as the 'AI Effect'. Before breaking down some AI that you might have heard of, I want to be clear about something that is very often misunderstood. AI can be grouped into two categories: Logic Programming (rule-based intelligence) and Machine Learning (data-driven intelligence). In the former category, the intelligence of the AI is developed by researchers. They would very carefully study the domain of the problem and describe a set of rules and instructions which would best output a solution to the problem. In the latter category, intelligence is learned by AI. The researcher would typically use an existing learning technique on a model with tweakable settings, and apply it to historical data from the domain of the problem. Then the settings of the model which would output the best possible solution to the problem are found based on the data. AI in both these categories has garnered a great deal of positive media attention, and rightfully so, but they have attributed to the great misunderstanding of AI that is widespread in society. Two examples of board game matches from the past 25 years apparently exhibit great strides in AI, but are mostly a testament to computing power rather than intelligent behaviour. A Logic Programming AI made history in 1997 when IBM’s supercomputer Deep Blue beat the then reigning world champion in a match of chess under standard tournament conditions. Deep Blue follows a set of logical rules to search for the best sequence of moves needed to win, with its prowess coming from its computational speed. At the time, it could evaluate about 200 million chess moves per second (7-12 turns ahead) and its strategy to win could be completely analysed and interpreted by the researchers, i.e. the reason why it made a particular move was fully understood. Although Deep Blue has no practical applications other than playing chess, it proved that AI could outperform human intelligence at a game often associated with requiring high intelligence. On a similar problem, a Machine Learning AI made history in 2016 when Google’s AlphaGo beat the 18-time world champion in a match of Go. Go is a far more complicated game than chess and it is arguably the most complex game ever devised. The number of possible moves from each position of a chess game is about 20 whereas a Go game is about 200. A Logic Programming AI would need to evaluate about 60 trillion moves to think just 6 turns ahead, so finding the best sequence of moves needed to win the game would be unfeasible. Google’s researchers used Deep Reinforcement Learning to tackle the problem. This learning technique was developed in the 1980's and stemmed from research into animal psychology. In this case, the AI was initially presented with 100,000 games of Go and, given rewards when it won, it learned how to play the game. It then played against itself millions of times to iteratively get better, until it was better than a world champion Go player. Unfortunately, this intelligent behaviour comes at a cost; it took 3 days to train AlphaGo and it consumed what would usually be $2 million of Google's computational power. In contrast to Deep Blue, the researchers developing AlphaGo didn’t need to have any prior knowledge of the rules of the game. The AI managed to learn the rules of the game and how to win all by itself. This was a feat of general intelligence, but there are some shortcomings to this kind of AI. What exactly has AlphaGo learned and was it worth the cost?&amp;nbsp; AlphaGo belongs to a subset of Machine Learning known as Deep Learning (note that the naming of Deep Blue is a coincidence and it is not classified as Deep Learning) which is notorious for requiring a substantial amount of computational power to learn. Deep Learning AIs spend days churning data to learn how to solve a problem. A study on the energy consumption of hardware built for Deep Learning revealed that the learning process can emit as much carbon as the lifetime of five midsize sedans. In addition to that, the intelligent behaviour learned is uninterpretable by even the developers themselves, i.e. we will never know why AlphaGo makes a particular move. Maybe this isn’t such a big problem in a game of Go as the results of the AI are phenomenal. The use of AI has amazingly made its way into governments and judicial systems, but has also been the centre of criticism from the media and public alike. In 2016, the Wisconsin Supreme Court ruled for judges to use it as an aid to assess the risk of recidivism. Little is understood about COMPAS since it uses trade secrets. This prompted two independent researchers to compare it to the most basic Machine Learning AI (a linear regression), and they found that there was no significant difference; COMPAS does nothing extraordinarily ‘intelligent’. To add insult to injury, an investigation into its risk assessments revealed that there is an inherent bias that favours white people to be classified as low-risk and black people to be classified as high-risk. This is a big concern in Machine Learning which is driven by historical data. If the data itself is inherently biased then the AI learning from it would be biased as well. The cherry on top for how AI is misunderstood was seen in Australia; the RoboDebt scheme. In 2016, the Australian government decided to enlist the help of AI to crack down on the abuse of their welfare system and clawback A$1.5 billion in three years. They implemented an automated debt recovery system (a seemingly Logic Programming AI) that was meant to accurately calculate how much a person owed or was owed by the government. Ironically, it has since incurred the Australian government A$1.2 billion in refunds and payouts.&amp;nbsp; There were many things wrong with the implementation of the RoboDebt scheme, but let’s look at it from a purely technical standpoint. To this day, there hasn’t been any scrutiny against the AI used. Put simply it did exactly what it was meant to do and nothing more. The human checks and balances that were in place prior to the AI, however, were completely removed and they weren’t replaced. Fundamental errors in the system weren’t caught. In fact, the biggest technical scrutiny was from the way the Australian government averaged income. This was in place much before RoboDebt and its introduction only perpetuated the already existing problem at a rapid rate. Perhaps an AI is only as ‘intelligent’ as the people it is solving a problem for. Most of the AI stories that make it to the headlines greatly tip the scales of its perception and propagate misunderstanding in society. A single AI story shouldn’t shape it as a whole as there are many different types of AI, and we have only scratched the surface in this article. Most AI research doesn’t make it to the headlines. However, there are many great applications and use cases of AI which will shape our future, and only when it does will we hear about it. Until then all we can do is learn a little more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Many but One, One but Many</title><link href="/Many-but-One-One-but-Many" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Many but One, One but Many" /><published>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Many-but-One-One-but-Many</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Many-but-One-One-but-Many">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The “Universality” that became a necessary paradox, the “Singularity” that wound up becoming a senseless contradiction.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are only as strong as we are united, as weak as we are divided.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;~ J.K. Rowling, &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no longer any denying that our country, India, is in the throes of historic national upheaval, its ramifications are so vast and frightening that even now, shocked into numbness and disbelief, the Indian protestors have not yet fully grasped what is happening to them. The grim data is clear enough and is still building. Since the winter of 2019, our cities, big and small, have been wracked by social disorder. As people, we are accustomed to violence, lawlessness, vigilantism. We see rampaging, looting mobs prompting officials to use lathi charge and tear gas shells against them, and think of it as just unstable politics. The nation’s identity has been overturned, to say the least.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our history, we can find certain events of civil unrest in India put a serious strain on the democratic foundation of society. Be it the Nirbhaya Movement of 2012 or the Anti-Corruption Movement by Anna Hazare in 2011, they caught the sight of thousands expressing that they’ve had enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the long silence of large-scale people’s movements since 2014, India is now flaring up with various collective mobilizations. From the protest against the &lt;strong&gt;Citizenship Amendment Act&lt;/strong&gt; (CAA) in Shaheen Bagh last winter to the protests against the three farm laws this winter, we all have shared a glimpse of ever-mounting suffering that’s staring back at us. Though both of these mobilizations are against unjust legislation, they have been received differently. While the former was attacked for being anti-national, the latter enjoyed the imaginary nationalism that it succeeded in evoking, making it a welcome move for the health of our democracy. Does this difference tell us anything about public morality and ethics when it comes to collective mobilisations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was probably the first time in the history of independent India that so many Muslims came out on the streets demanding to be heard. Anti-CAA protests were disparate in that most of its harbingers were women. Women, who have historically been sidelined in the public sphere, became a ubiquitous face of the protest. Their presence did manage to trigger an intense public debate. On one hand, it got them questioning if in times of political and social tumult, is it ethical to draw children into polarised protests and revolutionary movements? Does it leave them traumatised, or does it teach them how to express dissent in a democracy? On the other hand, their prominence indicated that these protests were no longer just a fight for what’s rightfully theirs, it was about saving democracy and the Constitution too. The participation of women and the elderly in the farmers’ protests too suggests that it’s the “beginning of a new era” where, in words of Sheryl Sandberg, “women need to take charge because social gains are never handed out, they must be seized.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the stark similarities that these protests and their protestors have to their names, the differential treatment of the two movements cannot be overlooked. On the part of the government, both of them were treated with congruous contempt originally. When the BJP saw no sign of triumph in the Shaheen Bagh elections, the agitation was stereotyped as ‘anti-national’. Similarly, the farmers were and still are too often labelled ‘Khalistanis’ who aim to divide India and turn the Indian state of Punjab into a unilaterally run state for Sikhs. The ruling party has in the past asserted that these laws are being resisted only by rich farmers from Punjab and Haryana. The chaos and mindless violence that was unleashed on the national capital on Republic Day was abhorrent – it not only crumbled the reputation of an agitation that had remained largely peaceful for nearly two months but also has made it crucial for the officials to bring the real culprits to book in order to nip in the bud a dangerous communal slant before it slips out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Universality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the anti-CAA protests are a drop of rain, the farmers’ movement is a storm. If the former is a thought, the latter is the mind, not thousands of different individual minds, just one, united – the unfathomable wonder that tiny individualism cannot even conceive. Individuality or Unity? I say there’s room for both. But the universality of today’s farm bill protests forms a necessary paradox, while the singularity of the anti-CAA uproar of 2020 ended up becoming a senseless contradiction. The clear advantage that one has over the other is the &lt;strong&gt;“idea of nationalism”&lt;/strong&gt; that one engenders and the other doesn’t. One has &lt;strong&gt;“contagious multiplicity”&lt;/strong&gt; for it belongs to various regions as well as religions, even if it’s being led by the Sikhs of Punjab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Singularity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s fair to argue how else should the Muslim community reciprocate to the laws that specifically call them out. The farmers’ protests carry moral and ethical weight, a different kind of acceptability that arises out of empathy for the vulnerable, provided he/she is not limited by the religious imprint as happened in the protests led by the Muslims. The singularity associated with one movement failed to provide patriots with a popular portrayal of belonging and trust. &lt;strong&gt;Amartya Sen&lt;/strong&gt; in his book, &lt;em&gt;The Idea of Justice&lt;/em&gt;, argues that “any identity that is imagined in the singular will always remain a source of violence, it is in the multiplicity that dialogic conditions are created.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singularity is always prone to be misread as a form of prejudice, discrimination, or hatred arising from attaching relations of inferiority and superiority to differences between subdivisions within a group. This religious sectarianism differs from the larger appeal that farmers bring to the table; there are Muslims too in the farmers’ movement, but they are farmers first, a religious minority next. Amartya Sen in his other book, &lt;em&gt;Identity and Violence: The Illusion of Destiny&lt;/em&gt;, introduces the idea of &lt;strong&gt;“illusion of a singular identity”&lt;/strong&gt;. The theory suggests that violence is created by the illusion of a singular identity, to the exclusion of others, and draws on the past and the present to create problems that are being faced by a strife-torn world.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Sen’s view, far too much violence in the world today is fomented by the illusion that people are destined to a &lt;strong&gt;“sectarian singularity”&lt;/strong&gt;. Stereotyping protests with a singular identity leads to resignation and a sense of inevitability about violence. Singularity partitions people and civilizations into binary oppositions and ignores the plural ways in which people identify themselves with others. We, as humans, enjoy plural identities. And this may not be the best excuse to treat anti-CAA protests as if they were anti-national, but this does explain the place of “morals of universality and inclusion” when it comes to a clash of civilizations. There is no mathematical explanation of why we define ourselves in terms of inclusivity or what Sen refers to as &lt;strong&gt;“diverse diversities”&lt;/strong&gt;. We don’t just use politics and violence to advance our interests, we use them for defining our identities too. &lt;em&gt;We know who we are only when we know who we are not and often only when we know whom we are against.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the two things can happen. If anti-CAA protests are to be reignited after the pandemic, they may have to move beyond their singularity to avoid the isolation that has been imposed on this movement because the farmers’ protests are good enough evidence of the fact that Sikhs as Khalistanis can be put down with force but not Sikhs as farmers. Or, we can transcend our illusion of identity by what Sen calls &lt;strong&gt;“reasoned choice”.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of living as if some irrational fate destines people to a confrontation with others who are different, we need to make a rational choice about what relative importance to attach to any single trait. We all laugh at weddings, cry at funerals, worry about our children. More important than any of our external differences, even though they are powerful, is our shared humanity. We are divided, but we are not locked up in tight little boxes from which we emerge only to attack each other, we are not a &lt;strong&gt;“miniaturization of humanity”.&lt;/strong&gt; We are better than that. We are here, and here is nowhere in particular.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Imagine there’s no country, it isn’t hard to do, nothing to kill or die for, and no religion too, imagine all the people living life in peace, you may say I’m a dreamer, but I’m not the only one.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;-John Lennon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggested Readings:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.&lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2019-08-moral-obligation-protest.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://phys.org/news/2019-08-moral-obligation-protest.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/newsletters/women-rule/2020/06/12/how-women-make-protests-more-successful-489512&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.politico.com/newsletters/women-rule/2020/06/12/how-women-make-protests-more-successful-489512&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/singular-identity-leads-to-violence-amartya-106033001157_1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/singular-identity-leads-to-violence-amartya-106033001157_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anjali Harjani</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The “Universality” that became a necessary paradox, the “Singularity” that wound up becoming a senseless contradiction.” “We are only as strong as we are united, as weak as we are divided.” &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;~ J.K. Rowling, Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire There is no longer any denying that our country, India, is in the throes of historic national upheaval, its ramifications are so vast and frightening that even now, shocked into numbness and disbelief, the Indian protestors have not yet fully grasped what is happening to them. The grim data is clear enough and is still building. Since the winter of 2019, our cities, big and small, have been wracked by social disorder. As people, we are accustomed to violence, lawlessness, vigilantism. We see rampaging, looting mobs prompting officials to use lathi charge and tear gas shells against them, and think of it as just unstable politics. The nation’s identity has been overturned, to say the least.&amp;nbsp; In our history, we can find certain events of civil unrest in India put a serious strain on the democratic foundation of society. Be it the Nirbhaya Movement of 2012 or the Anti-Corruption Movement by Anna Hazare in 2011, they caught the sight of thousands expressing that they’ve had enough. After the long silence of large-scale people’s movements since 2014, India is now flaring up with various collective mobilizations. From the protest against the Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA) in Shaheen Bagh last winter to the protests against the three farm laws this winter, we all have shared a glimpse of ever-mounting suffering that’s staring back at us. Though both of these mobilizations are against unjust legislation, they have been received differently. While the former was attacked for being anti-national, the latter enjoyed the imaginary nationalism that it succeeded in evoking, making it a welcome move for the health of our democracy. Does this difference tell us anything about public morality and ethics when it comes to collective mobilisations? It was probably the first time in the history of independent India that so many Muslims came out on the streets demanding to be heard. Anti-CAA protests were disparate in that most of its harbingers were women. Women, who have historically been sidelined in the public sphere, became a ubiquitous face of the protest. Their presence did manage to trigger an intense public debate. On one hand, it got them questioning if in times of political and social tumult, is it ethical to draw children into polarised protests and revolutionary movements? Does it leave them traumatised, or does it teach them how to express dissent in a democracy? On the other hand, their prominence indicated that these protests were no longer just a fight for what’s rightfully theirs, it was about saving democracy and the Constitution too. The participation of women and the elderly in the farmers’ protests too suggests that it’s the “beginning of a new era” where, in words of Sheryl Sandberg, “women need to take charge because social gains are never handed out, they must be seized.” Despite the stark similarities that these protests and their protestors have to their names, the differential treatment of the two movements cannot be overlooked. On the part of the government, both of them were treated with congruous contempt originally. When the BJP saw no sign of triumph in the Shaheen Bagh elections, the agitation was stereotyped as ‘anti-national’. Similarly, the farmers were and still are too often labelled ‘Khalistanis’ who aim to divide India and turn the Indian state of Punjab into a unilaterally run state for Sikhs. The ruling party has in the past asserted that these laws are being resisted only by rich farmers from Punjab and Haryana. The chaos and mindless violence that was unleashed on the national capital on Republic Day was abhorrent – it not only crumbled the reputation of an agitation that had remained largely peaceful for nearly two months but also has made it crucial for the officials to bring the real culprits to book in order to nip in the bud a dangerous communal slant before it slips out of control. The Universality If the anti-CAA protests are a drop of rain, the farmers’ movement is a storm. If the former is a thought, the latter is the mind, not thousands of different individual minds, just one, united – the unfathomable wonder that tiny individualism cannot even conceive. Individuality or Unity? I say there’s room for both. But the universality of today’s farm bill protests forms a necessary paradox, while the singularity of the anti-CAA uproar of 2020 ended up becoming a senseless contradiction. The clear advantage that one has over the other is the “idea of nationalism” that one engenders and the other doesn’t. One has “contagious multiplicity” for it belongs to various regions as well as religions, even if it’s being led by the Sikhs of Punjab. The Singularity It’s fair to argue how else should the Muslim community reciprocate to the laws that specifically call them out. The farmers’ protests carry moral and ethical weight, a different kind of acceptability that arises out of empathy for the vulnerable, provided he/she is not limited by the religious imprint as happened in the protests led by the Muslims. The singularity associated with one movement failed to provide patriots with a popular portrayal of belonging and trust. Amartya Sen in his book, The Idea of Justice, argues that “any identity that is imagined in the singular will always remain a source of violence, it is in the multiplicity that dialogic conditions are created.” Singularity is always prone to be misread as a form of prejudice, discrimination, or hatred arising from attaching relations of inferiority and superiority to differences between subdivisions within a group. This religious sectarianism differs from the larger appeal that farmers bring to the table; there are Muslims too in the farmers’ movement, but they are farmers first, a religious minority next. Amartya Sen in his other book, Identity and Violence: The Illusion of Destiny, introduces the idea of “illusion of a singular identity”. The theory suggests that violence is created by the illusion of a singular identity, to the exclusion of others, and draws on the past and the present to create problems that are being faced by a strife-torn world.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In Sen’s view, far too much violence in the world today is fomented by the illusion that people are destined to a “sectarian singularity”. Stereotyping protests with a singular identity leads to resignation and a sense of inevitability about violence. Singularity partitions people and civilizations into binary oppositions and ignores the plural ways in which people identify themselves with others. We, as humans, enjoy plural identities. And this may not be the best excuse to treat anti-CAA protests as if they were anti-national, but this does explain the place of “morals of universality and inclusion” when it comes to a clash of civilizations. There is no mathematical explanation of why we define ourselves in terms of inclusivity or what Sen refers to as “diverse diversities”. We don’t just use politics and violence to advance our interests, we use them for defining our identities too. We know who we are only when we know who we are not and often only when we know whom we are against.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; One of the two things can happen. If anti-CAA protests are to be reignited after the pandemic, they may have to move beyond their singularity to avoid the isolation that has been imposed on this movement because the farmers’ protests are good enough evidence of the fact that Sikhs as Khalistanis can be put down with force but not Sikhs as farmers. Or, we can transcend our illusion of identity by what Sen calls “reasoned choice”. Instead of living as if some irrational fate destines people to a confrontation with others who are different, we need to make a rational choice about what relative importance to attach to any single trait. We all laugh at weddings, cry at funerals, worry about our children. More important than any of our external differences, even though they are powerful, is our shared humanity. We are divided, but we are not locked up in tight little boxes from which we emerge only to attack each other, we are not a “miniaturization of humanity”. We are better than that. We are here, and here is nowhere in particular.&amp;nbsp; “Imagine there’s no country, it isn’t hard to do, nothing to kill or die for, and no religion too, imagine all the people living life in peace, you may say I’m a dreamer, but I’m not the only one.” -John Lennon Suggested Readings: 1.https://phys.org/news/2019-08-moral-obligation-protest.html 2.https://www.politico.com/newsletters/women-rule/2020/06/12/how-women-make-protests-more-successful-489512 3.https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/singular-identity-leads-to-violence-amartya-106033001157_1.html</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Taxing Verdict for the Indian Tax Man</title><link href="/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Taxing Verdict for the Indian Tax Man" /><published>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague, in its arbitral ruling, has once again dealt a blow to the Government of India by ruling in favour of the gas and oil exploration company, Cairn Energy Plc over tax disputes. The verdict comes post the September 25, 2020 victory of Vodafone International Holdings BV against the Indian government over the same dispute relating to the retrospective tax amendment in 2012.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006-07, Cairn UK, as part of an internal rearrangement process, transferred shares of Cairn India Holdings to Cairn India. Later, in 2011, the Edinburgh-headquartered organisation sold its Cairn India stake to the mining conglomerate Vedanta. In January 2014, the Indian income tax authorities, in view of the retroactive amended income tax law, alleged that the gas exploration firm made capital gains of ₹245.03 billion in the rearrangement process and hence was liable to pay a tax of ₹102.47 billion to the authorities. The company’s interpretation of Indian laws on capital gains differed, and consequently, it refused to pay the amount. In response, the authorities stopped the sale of the 10% stake to Vedanta and froze dividend pay-out to UK based parent company.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, Cairn initiated an international arbitration proceeding against the Indian authorities under article 9 of the Agreement between the Government of the Republic of India and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for Promotion and Protection of Investments (India-UK BIT). Countries enter into treaties, especially tax treaties, to prevent double taxation of corporations’ incomes earned by foreign investments, so as to promote a healthy business relationship and trade between two countries in this growing globalised world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose behind the said BIT provision was also the same, i.e. ensuring protection of the investors of the contracting state against any disruption/harassment of business in the territory of the host state. (See, Fair and Equitable Treatment – UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreement II).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final assessment order was slapped on the oil corporation in 2016, which included interest amounting to ₹188 billion, in addition to the principal tax amount.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three-member international arbitration tribunal, including a nominee of the Indian government, unanimously ruled in favour of the exploration organisation, and ordered the Indian administration to compensate the former for the total harm suffered including interest and the costs of arbitration. In its judgment, the arbitration panel said, “&lt;em&gt;Tax demand against the claimants (Cairn Energy Plc and Cairn UK Holdings Limited) in respect of AY (assessment year) 2007-08 is inconsistent with the treaty and the claimants are relieved from any obligation to pay it and [the tribunal] orders the respondent (Indian government) to neutralise the continuing effect of the demand by permanently withdrawing the demand.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sovereign country has the power to impose tax from a retrospective date. Nonetheless, such an action when a past transaction, which was not liable to taxation as on that date, is taxed under the aegis of a retrospective amendment, it is naturally seen to be unjust and discriminatory. Officials usually defend the amendments by stating that such moves are brought into effect to correct earlier flaws that defeated the purpose of the legislation in the first place.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to observe India’s follow-up on the issue. The government has until this month to challenge the award in a higher court in Singapore. By February end, Cairn’s CEO &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C1RXQR_enIN928IN928&amp;amp;sxsrf=ALeKk03IPhQp-AiVjX-3f-BE1qS7-EiNXw:1614752810068&amp;amp;q=Simon+Thomson&amp;amp;stick=H4sIAAAAAAAAAOPgE-LUz9U3sDCxtCxX4gIx85LzcgqNtBSzk63084vSE_MyqxJLMvPzUDhWyan5i1h5gzNz8_MUQjLyc4vz83awMgIATPkbn08AAAA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjgi5P9vpPvAhWTXSsKHSlvCAoQmxMoATApegQIIRAD&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Simon Thomson&lt;/a&gt; in his conversation with the Ministry of&amp;nbsp; Finance conveyed the corporation’s desire for a speedy resolution that is in the interest of all stakeholders involved. The government has hinted that the only possible solution for both parties to avoid further litigation is for the former to agree to the government’s&amp;nbsp;'&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/direct-tax-vivad-se-vishwas-bill-how-govt-aims-to-reduce-direct-tax-litigation-6254981/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vivad se Vishwas&lt;/a&gt;' (From Litigation to Trust) &amp;nbsp;tax amnesty. This scheme, announced in the Indian Budget 2020, provides speedy resolution for tax disputes in the forms of certain compensation between individuals and the tax department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oil discovery company aims to enforce the award under international arbitration rules, and can use this judgment to approach courts in countries like the UK, USA to seize any overseas property owned by India, to recover the money if the award is not honoured. If it does happen, India would not be the first country to face seizure of its international assets from an energy company. In 2019, US Oil firm ConocoPhillips, under international arbitration law, seized Venezuela’s overseas assets to execute an arbitration award of more than $8 billion. Cairn is reportedly identifying India’s overseas assets, including bank accounts and even Air India planes or Indian ships, that could be seized in the absence of a settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also worthwhile to note that if the Indian government accepts the award, then this move would be welcomed by the business corporations. India's reputation has taken a severe beating as a result of these cases. The BJP government has, in the past, denounced the introduction of a retrospective tax amendment by the previous Congress government as &quot;tax terrorism&quot;. Prime Minister Narendra Modi had promised to bring an end to &quot;tax terror&quot; after coming to power in 2014. However, the opposite happened when the government carried on with the case.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a government struggling to find revenue and seeking to boost its economy post-COVID-19, it is essential for the government to reduce compliance troubles and stumbling blocks such as retrospective taxation, lest it finds itself seriously damaging its potential post economic liberalisation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague, in its arbitral ruling, has once again dealt a blow to the Government of India by ruling in favour of the gas and oil exploration company, Cairn Energy Plc over tax disputes. The verdict comes post the September 25, 2020 victory of Vodafone International Holdings BV against the Indian government over the same dispute relating to the retrospective tax amendment in 2012.&amp;nbsp; In 2006-07, Cairn UK, as part of an internal rearrangement process, transferred shares of Cairn India Holdings to Cairn India. Later, in 2011, the Edinburgh-headquartered organisation sold its Cairn India stake to the mining conglomerate Vedanta. In January 2014, the Indian income tax authorities, in view of the retroactive amended income tax law, alleged that the gas exploration firm made capital gains of ₹245.03 billion in the rearrangement process and hence was liable to pay a tax of ₹102.47 billion to the authorities. The company’s interpretation of Indian laws on capital gains differed, and consequently, it refused to pay the amount. In response, the authorities stopped the sale of the 10% stake to Vedanta and froze dividend pay-out to UK based parent company.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In 2015, Cairn initiated an international arbitration proceeding against the Indian authorities under article 9 of the Agreement between the Government of the Republic of India and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for Promotion and Protection of Investments (India-UK BIT). Countries enter into treaties, especially tax treaties, to prevent double taxation of corporations’ incomes earned by foreign investments, so as to promote a healthy business relationship and trade between two countries in this growing globalised world. The purpose behind the said BIT provision was also the same, i.e. ensuring protection of the investors of the contracting state against any disruption/harassment of business in the territory of the host state. (See, Fair and Equitable Treatment – UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreement II). A final assessment order was slapped on the oil corporation in 2016, which included interest amounting to ₹188 billion, in addition to the principal tax amount.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The three-member international arbitration tribunal, including a nominee of the Indian government, unanimously ruled in favour of the exploration organisation, and ordered the Indian administration to compensate the former for the total harm suffered including interest and the costs of arbitration. In its judgment, the arbitration panel said, “Tax demand against the claimants (Cairn Energy Plc and Cairn UK Holdings Limited) in respect of AY (assessment year) 2007-08 is inconsistent with the treaty and the claimants are relieved from any obligation to pay it and [the tribunal] orders the respondent (Indian government) to neutralise the continuing effect of the demand by permanently withdrawing the demand.” A sovereign country has the power to impose tax from a retrospective date. Nonetheless, such an action when a past transaction, which was not liable to taxation as on that date, is taxed under the aegis of a retrospective amendment, it is naturally seen to be unjust and discriminatory. Officials usually defend the amendments by stating that such moves are brought into effect to correct earlier flaws that defeated the purpose of the legislation in the first place.&amp;nbsp; It would be interesting to observe India’s follow-up on the issue. The government has until this month to challenge the award in a higher court in Singapore. By February end, Cairn’s CEO Simon Thomson in his conversation with the Ministry of&amp;nbsp; Finance conveyed the corporation’s desire for a speedy resolution that is in the interest of all stakeholders involved. The government has hinted that the only possible solution for both parties to avoid further litigation is for the former to agree to the government’s&amp;nbsp;'Vivad se Vishwas' (From Litigation to Trust) &amp;nbsp;tax amnesty. This scheme, announced in the Indian Budget 2020, provides speedy resolution for tax disputes in the forms of certain compensation between individuals and the tax department. The oil discovery company aims to enforce the award under international arbitration rules, and can use this judgment to approach courts in countries like the UK, USA to seize any overseas property owned by India, to recover the money if the award is not honoured. If it does happen, India would not be the first country to face seizure of its international assets from an energy company. In 2019, US Oil firm ConocoPhillips, under international arbitration law, seized Venezuela’s overseas assets to execute an arbitration award of more than $8 billion. Cairn is reportedly identifying India’s overseas assets, including bank accounts and even Air India planes or Indian ships, that could be seized in the absence of a settlement. It is also worthwhile to note that if the Indian government accepts the award, then this move would be welcomed by the business corporations. India's reputation has taken a severe beating as a result of these cases. The BJP government has, in the past, denounced the introduction of a retrospective tax amendment by the previous Congress government as &quot;tax terrorism&quot;. Prime Minister Narendra Modi had promised to bring an end to &quot;tax terror&quot; after coming to power in 2014. However, the opposite happened when the government carried on with the case.&amp;nbsp; For a government struggling to find revenue and seeking to boost its economy post-COVID-19, it is essential for the government to reduce compliance troubles and stumbling blocks such as retrospective taxation, lest it finds itself seriously damaging its potential post economic liberalisation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part II</title><link href="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part II" /><published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This article is the final part of the two-part series discussing the perils in the path of India becoming a superpower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Judicial Reforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Law enforcement and the judicial system are the pillars on which the effectiveness of justice delivery depends. We have looked at the problems bugging India’s law enforcement in the first part of the article. Here we discuss the judiciary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The primary problem with the Indian judiciary is the pendency of cases. At the time of this writing, a total of 37,206,322 are&lt;a href=&quot;https://njdg.ecourts.gov.in/njdgnew/?p=main/pend_dashboard&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://njdg.ecourts.gov.in/njdgnew/?p=main/pend_dashboard&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/a&gt; before the District and subordinate courts in India. Another 5,660,908 cases, of which 87.54% are cases more than a year old, are pending before the High Courts in India. The result is one of an overburdened and sub-optimal judiciary. Some estimates put the time taken to resolve all the pending cases before the Indian Courts close to 300 years! So, what is the way forward?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One suggestion is to establish appellate courts to expedite the pending cases. Courts of appeals at the district level, state level and national level can help reduce the burden on the courts. The Supreme Court of India also acts as an appellate Court, apart from acting as the Constitutional Court (which the Court can do under Article 133 and 134 of the Indian Constitution in civil and criminal matters respectively). This puts additional burden on the Supreme Court, and it is in fact plagued by a huge workload. To reduce this burden, the appellate work of the Supreme Court may be separated by setting up a Supreme Appellate Court, and its benches could be set up across the country. Apart from this, cognitive technologies could be incorporated into the dispute resolution mechanism (in civil cases). For instance, the biggest litigants today are the various governments in India. Government officials, who decide not to appeal an adverse order, often run the risk of having to justify why they did not pursue the matter more vigorously. Incorporating cognitive technologies can help these officials analyse the chances of a successful appeal better. They can also help the judges in the decision-making process, which could lead to faster decisions and thus, could dispose of a case quickly. But most important of all, the lower rung of courts should be strengthened by filling the vacancies, establishing new posts and developing the infrastructure; for, most of the cases are filed at the lower level and most of the disputes are settled there itself.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another problem with the courts today is the lack of accountability. The introduction of the collegium system in 1998 means that the judges across all the Indian courts are appointed by the higher courts but not the political executive. This is clearly against the principle of checks and balances. The Government of India tried to establish a National Judicial Appoints Committee in 2014. Despite the Parliament of India clearing it, the Supreme Court struck it down saying it violated ‘the basic structure’ doctrine. Collegium, therefore, can only be abolished if all the members of Parliament come together and stand up to the highest court of the land and force its hand. They should do it because it is in the best interest of the country. The Supreme Court should also exercise restraint when it wades into the duties of the executive and legislature and uphold the doctrine of separation of powers. This judicial activism, which has sometimes worked well to deliver justice, has also harmed the Indian economy (from the cancelation of 2G spectrum auctions, the cancellation of coal licences to the recent staying of the farm laws enacted by the Indian Parliament).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;After all is said and done, the judiciary, for all its failures, provides places for discussion and debate. IT acts as a forum for a certain amount of churn. Reforming the judiciary, therefore, is in the best interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social indicators should be improved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We Indians are constantly obsessed with ranks. “India is the world’s fastest growing economy,” “India is the world’s third largest economy” we exclaim. But economic growth is not everything, we forget. A look at the social indicators of the country paints a much darker picture. India lags behind its neighbours in human development and social development indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By comparing India with its neighbours, we can analyse the situation. The infant mortality rate, the number of infant deaths per 1,000 births, is 32 in India while it was 27 in Bangladesh in 2017. As of 2015, India’s life expectancy is 68.35, lagging behind Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Between 2003 and 2015 Bangladesh was successful in bringing down the open-defecation rate from 43% to 1%, while India is still struggling with it. Back in 2010 only, infant immunization for DPT and measles in Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Nepal was about 80%, while India stood somewhere around 65%. In terms of sanitation facilities too, India’s neighbours outperform, though the situation is improving in India. The first&amp;nbsp; phase of the National Family Health Survey (NFHS) released in December 2020 indicates that India could be seeing an increase in child undernutrition. Child undernutrition, measured using three indicators namely stunting, wasting and underweight, has grown in many of the states in the latest NFHS. A rise in the all-India figures would mean that India is reversing the gains it had achieved since 1998-1999. Of all, the problem of stunting is serious in that it affects the cognitive abilities of the children and it could take up to three generations to undo the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is not that the Indian government is not capable of delivering things. It had successfully carried out the polio vaccination programme and eradicated polio. More recently, it succeeded in getting the people to wear masks to combat the COVID-19 pandemic and proved false the many estimates which predicted 200-300 million deaths due to the pandemic. To improve the social indicators, the government can start by educating people through spreading information via cell phones when someone calls the other. Most importantly, NGOs in India are doing a commendable job in tackling various social problems in India. Government can very well incorporate them and work alongside them to change things where India’s performance lacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There are many other areas which need complete overhaul or effective management. For instance, from modernization of military equipment to facing the challenge of low diplomatic corps, India’s external security faces many challenges. India faces major national security challenges from a more authoritative China and an unstable Pakistan. Another area is that of data collection. Data collection faces huge problems and the depth of the problem is drastic. Often, due to lack of coordination among the various government departments, same data is collected by different departments and, sometimes, the departments arrive at different conclusions! To make cross-state comparisons, one often has to move mountains to gather and then interpret data. It is important to have standardised data collection mechanisms and data interpretations platforms so as to formulate policies that are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, the problems are huge. And they should be fixed if India has any hopes of playing an important role globally. India faces a (funny?) paradox. On the one hand, various governments in India are among the largest employment providers in the country and on the other practically every department is understaffed. This tells us that we need more personnel, but in the right places. India should also invest in creating a knowledge base for all relevant and necessary functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India is a pre-industrial economy living through an information age. Often, the state has to play a strong role in an industrial economy, but has to take a back seat in the information economy. How the Indian state sets about resolving this paradox also determines India’s future. If we look at history, the most resistance to change comes from villages; and they tend to become violent to resist change. This also presents India with unique challenges. However, the biggest of the problems is in realising all that we have discussed are not any of these. It is that these policies present huge political risks. In a country where the political representation is so heavily skewed towards rural India, whose population is about 30%-40%, the political priorities are also skewed towards rural India and their problems. India needs a leader who focuses on not winning the next election, but on doing the right thing, to get what we have discussed done. That leader may not come to power, but he/she/the will forever changed the fate of the country for the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">This article is the final part of the two-part series discussing the perils in the path of India becoming a superpower. Judicial Reforms Law enforcement and the judicial system are the pillars on which the effectiveness of justice delivery depends. We have looked at the problems bugging India’s law enforcement in the first part of the article. Here we discuss the judiciary. The primary problem with the Indian judiciary is the pendency of cases. At the time of this writing, a total of 37,206,322 are pending before the District and subordinate courts in India. Another 5,660,908 cases, of which 87.54% are cases more than a year old, are pending before the High Courts in India. The result is one of an overburdened and sub-optimal judiciary. Some estimates put the time taken to resolve all the pending cases before the Indian Courts close to 300 years! So, what is the way forward?&amp;nbsp; One suggestion is to establish appellate courts to expedite the pending cases. Courts of appeals at the district level, state level and national level can help reduce the burden on the courts. The Supreme Court of India also acts as an appellate Court, apart from acting as the Constitutional Court (which the Court can do under Article 133 and 134 of the Indian Constitution in civil and criminal matters respectively). This puts additional burden on the Supreme Court, and it is in fact plagued by a huge workload. To reduce this burden, the appellate work of the Supreme Court may be separated by setting up a Supreme Appellate Court, and its benches could be set up across the country. Apart from this, cognitive technologies could be incorporated into the dispute resolution mechanism (in civil cases). For instance, the biggest litigants today are the various governments in India. Government officials, who decide not to appeal an adverse order, often run the risk of having to justify why they did not pursue the matter more vigorously. Incorporating cognitive technologies can help these officials analyse the chances of a successful appeal better. They can also help the judges in the decision-making process, which could lead to faster decisions and thus, could dispose of a case quickly. But most important of all, the lower rung of courts should be strengthened by filling the vacancies, establishing new posts and developing the infrastructure; for, most of the cases are filed at the lower level and most of the disputes are settled there itself.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another problem with the courts today is the lack of accountability. The introduction of the collegium system in 1998 means that the judges across all the Indian courts are appointed by the higher courts but not the political executive. This is clearly against the principle of checks and balances. The Government of India tried to establish a National Judicial Appoints Committee in 2014. Despite the Parliament of India clearing it, the Supreme Court struck it down saying it violated ‘the basic structure’ doctrine. Collegium, therefore, can only be abolished if all the members of Parliament come together and stand up to the highest court of the land and force its hand. They should do it because it is in the best interest of the country. The Supreme Court should also exercise restraint when it wades into the duties of the executive and legislature and uphold the doctrine of separation of powers. This judicial activism, which has sometimes worked well to deliver justice, has also harmed the Indian economy (from the cancelation of 2G spectrum auctions, the cancellation of coal licences to the recent staying of the farm laws enacted by the Indian Parliament). After all is said and done, the judiciary, for all its failures, provides places for discussion and debate. IT acts as a forum for a certain amount of churn. Reforming the judiciary, therefore, is in the best interest of India. Social indicators should be improved We Indians are constantly obsessed with ranks. “India is the world’s fastest growing economy,” “India is the world’s third largest economy” we exclaim. But economic growth is not everything, we forget. A look at the social indicators of the country paints a much darker picture. India lags behind its neighbours in human development and social development indicators. By comparing India with its neighbours, we can analyse the situation. The infant mortality rate, the number of infant deaths per 1,000 births, is 32 in India while it was 27 in Bangladesh in 2017. As of 2015, India’s life expectancy is 68.35, lagging behind Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Between 2003 and 2015 Bangladesh was successful in bringing down the open-defecation rate from 43% to 1%, while India is still struggling with it. Back in 2010 only, infant immunization for DPT and measles in Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Nepal was about 80%, while India stood somewhere around 65%. In terms of sanitation facilities too, India’s neighbours outperform, though the situation is improving in India. The first&amp;nbsp; phase of the National Family Health Survey (NFHS) released in December 2020 indicates that India could be seeing an increase in child undernutrition. Child undernutrition, measured using three indicators namely stunting, wasting and underweight, has grown in many of the states in the latest NFHS. A rise in the all-India figures would mean that India is reversing the gains it had achieved since 1998-1999. Of all, the problem of stunting is serious in that it affects the cognitive abilities of the children and it could take up to three generations to undo the problem. It is not that the Indian government is not capable of delivering things. It had successfully carried out the polio vaccination programme and eradicated polio. More recently, it succeeded in getting the people to wear masks to combat the COVID-19 pandemic and proved false the many estimates which predicted 200-300 million deaths due to the pandemic. To improve the social indicators, the government can start by educating people through spreading information via cell phones when someone calls the other. Most importantly, NGOs in India are doing a commendable job in tackling various social problems in India. Government can very well incorporate them and work alongside them to change things where India’s performance lacks. There are many other areas which need complete overhaul or effective management. For instance, from modernization of military equipment to facing the challenge of low diplomatic corps, India’s external security faces many challenges. India faces major national security challenges from a more authoritative China and an unstable Pakistan. Another area is that of data collection. Data collection faces huge problems and the depth of the problem is drastic. Often, due to lack of coordination among the various government departments, same data is collected by different departments and, sometimes, the departments arrive at different conclusions! To make cross-state comparisons, one often has to move mountains to gather and then interpret data. It is important to have standardised data collection mechanisms and data interpretations platforms so as to formulate policies that are relevant. Finally, the problems are huge. And they should be fixed if India has any hopes of playing an important role globally. India faces a (funny?) paradox. On the one hand, various governments in India are among the largest employment providers in the country and on the other practically every department is understaffed. This tells us that we need more personnel, but in the right places. India should also invest in creating a knowledge base for all relevant and necessary functions. India is a pre-industrial economy living through an information age. Often, the state has to play a strong role in an industrial economy, but has to take a back seat in the information economy. How the Indian state sets about resolving this paradox also determines India’s future. If we look at history, the most resistance to change comes from villages; and they tend to become violent to resist change. This also presents India with unique challenges. However, the biggest of the problems is in realising all that we have discussed are not any of these. It is that these policies present huge political risks. In a country where the political representation is so heavily skewed towards rural India, whose population is about 30%-40%, the political priorities are also skewed towards rural India and their problems. India needs a leader who focuses on not winning the next election, but on doing the right thing, to get what we have discussed done. That leader may not come to power, but he/she/the will forever changed the fate of the country for the better.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Decade of Arab Spring: A Retrospective Outlook Into Democratic Imperatives and Western Imperialism</title><link href="/The-Decade-of-Arab-Spring" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Decade of Arab Spring: A Retrospective Outlook Into Democratic Imperatives and Western Imperialism" /><published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Decade-of-Arab-Spring</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Decade-of-Arab-Spring">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘Arab Spring’ was given to the series of anti-government protests, rebellions, and people’s uprisings that took place in the early 2010's in the regions of the Middle East and North Africa. It has been a long decade since the Arab Spring as it has entailed a rather mixed legacy. Be it the civil wars in Libya, Yemen and Syria or the democratic shift in Tunisia. With civil wars turning into behemoth proxy wars, constant military intervention by global geopolitical interests, and the ongoing regional agitations, the Arab Spring has led to a lot of complicated dissonances. Internal displacements and a widespread influx of refugees has also led to a global refugee crisis. Let us trace these legacies in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Tunisian Revolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also popularly known as the Jasmine Revolution, the Tunisian Revolution was a 28-day long civil resistance ousting the then-President Zine El Abidine Ben Ali in 2011. An intensive series of street demonstrations led to a thorough democratisation of the country through free and democratic elections. There were a lot of factors which contributed to this mass agitation, namely unemployment rates, corruption, food inflation, poor living conditions and little to no political freedoms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests were sudden due to the most extreme lengths of protesting one can imagine - self-immolation. On December 17, 2010, Mohamed Bouazizi set fire to himself to death willingly as an act of extreme agitation. He was a 26-year-old vendor who was treated badly by some local officers, and he made the decision to self-immolate. This, of course, catalysed an entire movement throughout the country. The government of Tunisia tried its best to end the unrest by using violence on the street demonstrations and issuing economic concessions. The protests couldn’t be halted, and eventually, this led to an overwhelming of the security forces and compelled Ben Ali to step down and flee away to Saudi Arabia on January 14, 2011. In October of 2011, Tunisians participated in a free and democratic election to choose the members of a council which drafted a new constitution. The new democratically elected president and prime minister took oath in December, 2011. A new constitution came into effect in January, 2014. It is the first country to have gotten a peaceful transfer of power from one democratic government to another in 2019 due to the Arab Spring protests, making it the most successful story of the Arab Spring yet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Egyptian Revolution of 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also known popularly as the 25 January Revolution, for that was a day on which various youth groups decided to revolt against the Egyptian government of Muhammad Hosni El Sayed Mubarak. This was done on the ‘police holiday’ because of the increasing instances of police brutality in Egypt. It invoked demonstrations, marches, occupancies, civil resistance, acts of civil disobedience and strikes throughout the country. There were millions of protestors from different socio-economic, cultural and religious backgrounds united to demand an overthrow of President Mubarak. By January 28, Tahrir Square (also known as the Liberation Square) became the crucible of relentless demands for Egypt. Within two weeks of all the demonstrations, it set the bed for Mubarak's end. The then US President Barack Obama withdrew his support from the Egyptian leader and showed solidarity with the revolutionaries who were forgoing their lives to end Mubarak's 30-year-long rule.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Military forces sparked violent clashes against the protestors and resulted in the death of 846 people and injured around 6,000 people! The protestors in retaliation burned down 90 police stations across the country! On February 11, the day Mubarak resigned, an Egyptian activist Nancy Okail exclaimed that the days to come would be a pedestal for a seamless transition to democracy. During the uprising, Cairo was described as a &quot;war zone&quot;. After the revolution resulting in Mubarak stepping down, Egypt saw a period of rule by the Supreme Council of the Armed Forces, and then it saw the Muslim Brotherhood take power through a series of popular elections. Eventually, Egyptians elected Islamist Mohamed Morsi to the presidency in June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Non-Domino Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An overly difficult yet successful revolution in two predominantly ruled-upon states led to protest movements in Yemen, Libya, Bahrain and Syria in the first three months of 2011. However, as we now know it, their protests turned bloody and insurmountably gory as dictatorial regimes overpowered opposition groups. This only strengthened its dictators as authoritarianism has a tighter grip on its people than ever, and its people have been traumatised by their struggles for too long now. Bashar al-Assad and his brutal retaliation have turned Syria into a human slaughterhouse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after a decade of civil unrest overthrowing Muammar Gaddafi in Libya, it is a state whose struggle with authority precipitated the outbreak of a civil war in 2014. In Yemen, when Ali Abdullah Saleh was protested out of the state, he returned after four months unexpectedly and stirred the country with increased confusion about the political future of Yemen. Even after Hadi took over control in Yemen after being the sole candidate in the February 2012 elections, he was unable to maintain a stable state. As increasing state opposition and armed rebellion took over, Yemen devolved into a civil war. Today it is the victim of the largest humanitarian crisis in history, and still suffers as a nation overruled by foreign powers like Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bahrain, at the end of March 2011, demanded political and economic reforms by human rights activists. Aftermath of which saw protest leaders being imprisoned for being allies to anti-government activities, hundreds of suspected Shi’i workers being fired from their jobs and their mosques being demolished. In various other countries like Algeria, Jordan, Morocco and Oman, rulers offered a myriad of concessions to pro-democratic movements in order to not emulate the results of all the other bloodied movements in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Arab Spring ignited an interconnected yet unique democratic movement throughout these countries to end authoritarian corruption and reinstate a democratic civil life. A decade after a spark, these demonstrations and people’s voices are still being perpetuated even after challenges like the coronavirus pandemic. In February of 2019, Algerian protests toppled the government of President Abdelaziz Bouteflika. In April 2019, Sudan’s military halted the 30-year-long rule of President Omar al-Bashir. Countries like Iraq and Lebanon, so deeply divided, put up massive demonstrations demanding the government’s accountability towards major national crises in 2019-2020.&amp;nbsp; Observers have also come to refer to this phase of protests as the second Arab Spring. While tyranny has little to no end, the Arab Spring made these small dictatorial states believe in the power of unison and its effects in turning around their countries’ fates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The term ‘Arab Spring’ was given to the series of anti-government protests, rebellions, and people’s uprisings that took place in the early 2010's in the regions of the Middle East and North Africa. It has been a long decade since the Arab Spring as it has entailed a rather mixed legacy. Be it the civil wars in Libya, Yemen and Syria or the democratic shift in Tunisia. With civil wars turning into behemoth proxy wars, constant military intervention by global geopolitical interests, and the ongoing regional agitations, the Arab Spring has led to a lot of complicated dissonances. Internal displacements and a widespread influx of refugees has also led to a global refugee crisis. Let us trace these legacies in detail. The Tunisian Revolution Also popularly known as the Jasmine Revolution, the Tunisian Revolution was a 28-day long civil resistance ousting the then-President Zine El Abidine Ben Ali in 2011. An intensive series of street demonstrations led to a thorough democratisation of the country through free and democratic elections. There were a lot of factors which contributed to this mass agitation, namely unemployment rates, corruption, food inflation, poor living conditions and little to no political freedoms.&amp;nbsp; The protests were sudden due to the most extreme lengths of protesting one can imagine - self-immolation. On December 17, 2010, Mohamed Bouazizi set fire to himself to death willingly as an act of extreme agitation. He was a 26-year-old vendor who was treated badly by some local officers, and he made the decision to self-immolate. This, of course, catalysed an entire movement throughout the country. The government of Tunisia tried its best to end the unrest by using violence on the street demonstrations and issuing economic concessions. The protests couldn’t be halted, and eventually, this led to an overwhelming of the security forces and compelled Ben Ali to step down and flee away to Saudi Arabia on January 14, 2011. In October of 2011, Tunisians participated in a free and democratic election to choose the members of a council which drafted a new constitution. The new democratically elected president and prime minister took oath in December, 2011. A new constitution came into effect in January, 2014. It is the first country to have gotten a peaceful transfer of power from one democratic government to another in 2019 due to the Arab Spring protests, making it the most successful story of the Arab Spring yet.&amp;nbsp; The Egyptian Revolution of 2011 Also known popularly as the 25 January Revolution, for that was a day on which various youth groups decided to revolt against the Egyptian government of Muhammad Hosni El Sayed Mubarak. This was done on the ‘police holiday’ because of the increasing instances of police brutality in Egypt. It invoked demonstrations, marches, occupancies, civil resistance, acts of civil disobedience and strikes throughout the country. There were millions of protestors from different socio-economic, cultural and religious backgrounds united to demand an overthrow of President Mubarak. By January 28, Tahrir Square (also known as the Liberation Square) became the crucible of relentless demands for Egypt. Within two weeks of all the demonstrations, it set the bed for Mubarak's end. The then US President Barack Obama withdrew his support from the Egyptian leader and showed solidarity with the revolutionaries who were forgoing their lives to end Mubarak's 30-year-long rule.&amp;nbsp; Military forces sparked violent clashes against the protestors and resulted in the death of 846 people and injured around 6,000 people! The protestors in retaliation burned down 90 police stations across the country! On February 11, the day Mubarak resigned, an Egyptian activist Nancy Okail exclaimed that the days to come would be a pedestal for a seamless transition to democracy. During the uprising, Cairo was described as a &quot;war zone&quot;. After the revolution resulting in Mubarak stepping down, Egypt saw a period of rule by the Supreme Council of the Armed Forces, and then it saw the Muslim Brotherhood take power through a series of popular elections. Eventually, Egyptians elected Islamist Mohamed Morsi to the presidency in June 2012. The Non-Domino Effect An overly difficult yet successful revolution in two predominantly ruled-upon states led to protest movements in Yemen, Libya, Bahrain and Syria in the first three months of 2011. However, as we now know it, their protests turned bloody and insurmountably gory as dictatorial regimes overpowered opposition groups. This only strengthened its dictators as authoritarianism has a tighter grip on its people than ever, and its people have been traumatised by their struggles for too long now. Bashar al-Assad and his brutal retaliation have turned Syria into a human slaughterhouse.&amp;nbsp; Even after a decade of civil unrest overthrowing Muammar Gaddafi in Libya, it is a state whose struggle with authority precipitated the outbreak of a civil war in 2014. In Yemen, when Ali Abdullah Saleh was protested out of the state, he returned after four months unexpectedly and stirred the country with increased confusion about the political future of Yemen. Even after Hadi took over control in Yemen after being the sole candidate in the February 2012 elections, he was unable to maintain a stable state. As increasing state opposition and armed rebellion took over, Yemen devolved into a civil war. Today it is the victim of the largest humanitarian crisis in history, and still suffers as a nation overruled by foreign powers like Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp; Bahrain, at the end of March 2011, demanded political and economic reforms by human rights activists. Aftermath of which saw protest leaders being imprisoned for being allies to anti-government activities, hundreds of suspected Shi’i workers being fired from their jobs and their mosques being demolished. In various other countries like Algeria, Jordan, Morocco and Oman, rulers offered a myriad of concessions to pro-democratic movements in order to not emulate the results of all the other bloodied movements in the Middle East. The Arab Spring ignited an interconnected yet unique democratic movement throughout these countries to end authoritarian corruption and reinstate a democratic civil life. A decade after a spark, these demonstrations and people’s voices are still being perpetuated even after challenges like the coronavirus pandemic. In February of 2019, Algerian protests toppled the government of President Abdelaziz Bouteflika. In April 2019, Sudan’s military halted the 30-year-long rule of President Omar al-Bashir. Countries like Iraq and Lebanon, so deeply divided, put up massive demonstrations demanding the government’s accountability towards major national crises in 2019-2020.&amp;nbsp; Observers have also come to refer to this phase of protests as the second Arab Spring. While tyranny has little to no end, the Arab Spring made these small dictatorial states believe in the power of unison and its effects in turning around their countries’ fates.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The ‘D word’ is missing, Sir</title><link href="/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘D word’ is missing, Sir" /><published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The world is watching&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These four words, employed in the joint statement issued by the embassies of the European Union, the United Kingdom and Canada along with 11 other nations to condemn the 2021 military coup in Myanmar, truly reflect the political reality of the nation. The February coup shouldn't come as a surprise to anyone remotely acquainted with contemporary Burmese politics. Free elections had been allowed by the military &lt;em&gt;junta &lt;/em&gt;in 1990 with the presumption that it enjoyed popular support. However, much to the dismay of the generals, Aung San Suu Kyi’s National League for Democracy (NLD) won by a large margin. The narrative henceforth followed a trajectory jarringly similar to the one we see today. The military, steadfast in its refusal to part with power, placed Suu Kyi under house arrest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military, known as Tatmadaw, enjoyed power for 22 years till 2011. As part of the ‘7-Step Roadmap’, the third constitution of Myanmar was drafted in 2008 and the nation took its first steps towards achieving democracy. The 2015 elections general elections resulted in a victory for the National League for Democracy. Yet the achievement could not be appreciated in all its due regards, as the military continued to exert significant influence. It enjoyed the right to appoint one-fourth of the members of the parliament.&amp;nbsp; History repeated itself when the results of the 2020 November elections witnessed the NLD's victory, with the party winning 396 out of 476 parliamentary seats. It had surpassed its previous margins achieved in the 2015 elections. On the other hand, the Union Solidarity and Development Party representing the military junta could win only 33 seats. This electoral result has been attributed as the spark which ignited the coup d’etat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Chronology of the Coup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At about 3 AM on February 1, 2021, Suu Kyi and Han Thi Myint,&amp;nbsp; who is the party spokesperson of the NLD were placed under detention, and communication channels were severely disrupted. The army's TV station declared that power had been handed over to commander-in-chief Min Aung Hlaing and that an emergency was being imposed for the next year. Such kill switch tactics, usually reserved for the Rakhine State, were replicated all over the nation. The roads to the Burmese capital Naypyidaw were blocked by soldiers. 400 elected members of parliament representing the NLD were placed under house arrest. Social media users called for holding a parliament within the same government guest house where they were forced to reside. This was a convincing argument as the number of MPs present in the guest house was meeting the quorum.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two sides have locked horns even though the military clearly has an upper hand when it comes to hard power. Defying military dictates, 70 NLD MPs took the oath of office on February 4. The military also announced on February 4, 2021 that 24 ministers and deputies had been removed from office and 11 replacements had been appointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coup also received a religious tint with the soldiers detaining several Buddhist monks who had led the 2007 Saffron Revolution. The Assistance Association for Political Prisoners has identified 133 officials, 14 civil society activists who had been detained by the military since the coup's inception. Min Aung Hlaing, head of the Tatmadaw, has established the State Administration Council to establish direct control of state affairs and has also imposed a curfew from 8 PM to 4 AM in all major cities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 13, a shocking violation of the freedom of the press was noticed as the military administered Ministry of Information (MoI) exerted pressure upon the press to delete the phrases “junta” and “regime” to describe the coup. The recent military order involves facing 20 years of prison if an individual is found encroaching on the work of the security forces. This order also bestows the power to make arrests, carry out searches and even detain individuals for a period of more than 24 hours without trial or right to proper judicial recourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Deeper&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military had carried out their first coup d'etat against a civilian government in 1962. But the present action may be studied in the context of the time in which it has occurred. This week was to witness the first session of the parliament in which the new democratically elected government would have been officially anointed to power. It is noteworthy that more than 70% of the voters had challenged the pandemic scenario to vote and elect Suu Kyi. This is particularly noteworthy considering the flak that she had been receiving for the genocide against the Rohingyas. Public resentment against the military government is thus inevitable. The primary opposition levelled by the military is that the election was marked by fraud, blaming the UEC (Union Election commission) for voter list irregularities.&amp;nbsp; Sounds familiar? Trumpian? Gotcha.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, there's no evidence to support the claim.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business and financial interests of Min Aung Hlaing's family too have been a cause of contention. He oversees the twin military conglomerates: Myanmar Economic Corporation (MEC) and Myanma Economic Holdings Limited (MEHL) with his daughter, son and daughter-in-law holding substantial business interests in each. Moreover, a few days prior to the coup, the International Monetary Fund had released $350 million in cash to the Central Bank of Myanmar as a COVID-19 relief package. It didn't contain any clause for refund. The misuse of this fund seems to be a likelihood in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way ahead&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manufactured emergency holds little ground legally. The president can declare an emergency only after due consultation with the National Defence and Security Council. The military has proven itself to be enjoying a stature above that of the constitution. The military states that it would rule only for a year and then hold a fresh election. It doesn't require too much political clairvoyance to predict that such an election would be completely orchestrated by the military. The public perception regarding the military has indeed undergone a setback. Burmese Twitter account holders used #RespectOurVotes, #HearTheVoiceofMyanmar among others. Myo Ko Ko, a Burmese student activist articulates the anxiety as he says “We strongly believe in democracy and human rights. We know that it's risky.” The coup has elicited mixed reactions from the nation's diverse ethnic groups. While the Restoration Council of Shan State has strongly condemned the coup, the Kachin Independence Organisation with a large population has remained silent about it. The coup has attracted international reactions, including Jacinda Ardern severing New Zealand's diplomatic ties with Myanmar. The UN Security Council held an emergency meeting upholding the resolution of restoring democracy in Myanmar. The statement however couldn't garner the support of all the members, with permanent members China and Russia refusing to back it. The regional implications in South Asia are, however, muted, with nations including India resorting to soft tactics and not being vocal about the situation. The ASEAN nations continue to stick to their non-interference tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the uncertainty persists amidst the three-finger salute in Myanmar. The gesture of defiance against the spectre that has returned back to haunt the nation, yet again. Democracy, the elusive D-word rests in agitation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“The world is watching.” These four words, employed in the joint statement issued by the embassies of the European Union, the United Kingdom and Canada along with 11 other nations to condemn the 2021 military coup in Myanmar, truly reflect the political reality of the nation. The February coup shouldn't come as a surprise to anyone remotely acquainted with contemporary Burmese politics. Free elections had been allowed by the military junta in 1990 with the presumption that it enjoyed popular support. However, much to the dismay of the generals, Aung San Suu Kyi’s National League for Democracy (NLD) won by a large margin. The narrative henceforth followed a trajectory jarringly similar to the one we see today. The military, steadfast in its refusal to part with power, placed Suu Kyi under house arrest.&amp;nbsp; The military, known as Tatmadaw, enjoyed power for 22 years till 2011. As part of the ‘7-Step Roadmap’, the third constitution of Myanmar was drafted in 2008 and the nation took its first steps towards achieving democracy. The 2015 elections general elections resulted in a victory for the National League for Democracy. Yet the achievement could not be appreciated in all its due regards, as the military continued to exert significant influence. It enjoyed the right to appoint one-fourth of the members of the parliament.&amp;nbsp; History repeated itself when the results of the 2020 November elections witnessed the NLD's victory, with the party winning 396 out of 476 parliamentary seats. It had surpassed its previous margins achieved in the 2015 elections. On the other hand, the Union Solidarity and Development Party representing the military junta could win only 33 seats. This electoral result has been attributed as the spark which ignited the coup d’etat.&amp;nbsp; A Chronology of the Coup At about 3 AM on February 1, 2021, Suu Kyi and Han Thi Myint,&amp;nbsp; who is the party spokesperson of the NLD were placed under detention, and communication channels were severely disrupted. The army's TV station declared that power had been handed over to commander-in-chief Min Aung Hlaing and that an emergency was being imposed for the next year. Such kill switch tactics, usually reserved for the Rakhine State, were replicated all over the nation. The roads to the Burmese capital Naypyidaw were blocked by soldiers. 400 elected members of parliament representing the NLD were placed under house arrest. Social media users called for holding a parliament within the same government guest house where they were forced to reside. This was a convincing argument as the number of MPs present in the guest house was meeting the quorum.&amp;nbsp; The two sides have locked horns even though the military clearly has an upper hand when it comes to hard power. Defying military dictates, 70 NLD MPs took the oath of office on February 4. The military also announced on February 4, 2021 that 24 ministers and deputies had been removed from office and 11 replacements had been appointed. The coup also received a religious tint with the soldiers detaining several Buddhist monks who had led the 2007 Saffron Revolution. The Assistance Association for Political Prisoners has identified 133 officials, 14 civil society activists who had been detained by the military since the coup's inception. Min Aung Hlaing, head of the Tatmadaw, has established the State Administration Council to establish direct control of state affairs and has also imposed a curfew from 8 PM to 4 AM in all major cities.&amp;nbsp; On February 13, a shocking violation of the freedom of the press was noticed as the military administered Ministry of Information (MoI) exerted pressure upon the press to delete the phrases “junta” and “regime” to describe the coup. The recent military order involves facing 20 years of prison if an individual is found encroaching on the work of the security forces. This order also bestows the power to make arrests, carry out searches and even detain individuals for a period of more than 24 hours without trial or right to proper judicial recourse. Looking Deeper&amp;nbsp; The military had carried out their first coup d'etat against a civilian government in 1962. But the present action may be studied in the context of the time in which it has occurred. This week was to witness the first session of the parliament in which the new democratically elected government would have been officially anointed to power. It is noteworthy that more than 70% of the voters had challenged the pandemic scenario to vote and elect Suu Kyi. This is particularly noteworthy considering the flak that she had been receiving for the genocide against the Rohingyas. Public resentment against the military government is thus inevitable. The primary opposition levelled by the military is that the election was marked by fraud, blaming the UEC (Union Election commission) for voter list irregularities.&amp;nbsp; Sounds familiar? Trumpian? Gotcha.&amp;nbsp; And yes, there's no evidence to support the claim.&amp;nbsp; The business and financial interests of Min Aung Hlaing's family too have been a cause of contention. He oversees the twin military conglomerates: Myanmar Economic Corporation (MEC) and Myanma Economic Holdings Limited (MEHL) with his daughter, son and daughter-in-law holding substantial business interests in each. Moreover, a few days prior to the coup, the International Monetary Fund had released $350 million in cash to the Central Bank of Myanmar as a COVID-19 relief package. It didn't contain any clause for refund. The misuse of this fund seems to be a likelihood in the near future. The way ahead&amp;nbsp; The manufactured emergency holds little ground legally. The president can declare an emergency only after due consultation with the National Defence and Security Council. The military has proven itself to be enjoying a stature above that of the constitution. The military states that it would rule only for a year and then hold a fresh election. It doesn't require too much political clairvoyance to predict that such an election would be completely orchestrated by the military. The public perception regarding the military has indeed undergone a setback. Burmese Twitter account holders used #RespectOurVotes, #HearTheVoiceofMyanmar among others. Myo Ko Ko, a Burmese student activist articulates the anxiety as he says “We strongly believe in democracy and human rights. We know that it's risky.” The coup has elicited mixed reactions from the nation's diverse ethnic groups. While the Restoration Council of Shan State has strongly condemned the coup, the Kachin Independence Organisation with a large population has remained silent about it. The coup has attracted international reactions, including Jacinda Ardern severing New Zealand's diplomatic ties with Myanmar. The UN Security Council held an emergency meeting upholding the resolution of restoring democracy in Myanmar. The statement however couldn't garner the support of all the members, with permanent members China and Russia refusing to back it. The regional implications in South Asia are, however, muted, with nations including India resorting to soft tactics and not being vocal about the situation. The ASEAN nations continue to stick to their non-interference tactics. Meanwhile, the uncertainty persists amidst the three-finger salute in Myanmar. The gesture of defiance against the spectre that has returned back to haunt the nation, yet again. Democracy, the elusive D-word rests in agitation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A High ROE can be Misleading!</title><link href="/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A High ROE can be Misleading!" /><published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Investment is most intelligent when it’s most businesslike&lt;/em&gt;”- Benjamin Graham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Benjamin Graham and Warren Buffet have emphasised on the need for the investor to only invest in companies whose business they duly understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do we do that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in an obsession with numbers. Plain odd numbers that mean something to a blank eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like the Greeks had an obsession with Golden Ratio, investors are the same with Financial ratios. Ratios are shortcuts and who doesn’t like them? Especially when “more time means more money”, seems real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such important ratio that makes the kitty of the most important financial ratios to consider for an Investor is the “Return on Equity (ROE)” Ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And both these gentlemen mentioned above love this ratio. They do warn you on single-factor investing and urge you to consider other key factors but that’s in line with every valuation metric that comes with a “&lt;em&gt;yes, but…&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why do they love it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it’s businesslike. It showcases the business owner’s ability to employ equity into money-making ventures. It measures profitability. It gives a raw sense of what the company is doing with its equity and how efficient it is in engineering its cash to generate more cash. More earnings mean higher valuations and higher valuation would mean capital appreciation for stakeholders. It’s simple math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as all math do,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It starts with a simple formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Return on Equity (ROE) = Net Income/Shareholder’s equity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toggle to the company’s P&amp;amp;L statement and pick up the bottom-line item, ‘Net Income’ and divide it by the total shareholder’s equity present on the balance sheet and that’s how easily you can calculate the ROE of your desired company. The rule of thumb is, the higher the ROE, the more the company is efficient in its operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too excited to already switch tabs? Wait!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the trouble begins.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplicity by which ROE can be calculated should already make you apprehensive about its god-like relevance. Good things don’t come easy, right? Well, let’s dig deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s multiply and divide the above equation, once by the ‘Total Sales’ and again by ‘Total Assets’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ROE= (Net Income/Total Sales) * (Total Sales/Total Assets) * (Total Assets/Shareholders Equity)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total Sales cancel Total Sales and Total Assets cancel Total Assets but for now, let’s analyse each portion individually. Reframing the above equation, we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ROE= Net Profit Margin * Total Asset Turnover Ratio * Financial Leverage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we have is something known as the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;DuPont Formula&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which breaks down ROE into 3 key drivers, all of which independently relate to the ROE and can help back-test the components of the formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Net Profit Margin is indicative of how well the company is in managing and financing its operations per unit of sales. A higher Net Profit Margin would eventually mean more earnings for the company and higher ROE. Asset turnover ratio means how efficiently the company is using its assets to drive sales. A higher Total Asset Turnover Ratio would mean that the company is deploying its assets correctly to target higher sales per unit of the asset owned. Hence, a higher ROE. Lastly, Financial Leverage is the extent to which the company uses debt in relation to equity to finance its assets. In brief, higher leverage would mean greater financial risk but substituted by higher Return on Equity (ROE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ideal firm should have a high Net Profit Margin, high Asset Turnover Ratio but use less leverage to reach there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, however, that a company cannot grow earnings faster than its current ROE without raising additional cash. Now raising cash comes at a cost and cuts through the firm’s profits. If the company decides to raise money by way of debt, the interest gets paid as an expense and if it decides to raise equity, Earnings-per-share (EPS) goes down, which in turn affects investor sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ROE is the limiter to a firm’s growth. It’s a gauge against the excessive heating up of the company. That is why ROE forms an integral part of the investor analysis but here comes the catch. When something holds such importance within stakeholders' minds and the management knows it, will not all companies tend to magnify ROE to seem better on the stock exchange?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, but soon you’ll know higher ROE numbers are no shortcut for diligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manipulating the ROE numbers isn’t an ordeal. There are numerous ways by which this can be done and that make higher ROE’s a subject for debate. This is where the trouble gets bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Share Buybacks:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the ROE equation? A simple math student would tell how to increase its value. Either increase the Net Earnings (Numerator) or decrease Total Shareholders Equity (Denominator). An ideal and natural practice for companies would be to focus on increasing the numerator by increasing the Asset Turnover Ratio that drives sales with no additional asset cost or by increasing the Net profit Margin by efficiently managing operations. Both these practices done in tandem would result in a significantly higher ROE. But not all companies resort to this technique. Some adopt a latter technique and decrease shareholder’s equity by rolling out share buyback schemes. When they do say they use the retained earnings to buy stock and thus decrease the shareholder equity which in turn magnifies the firm’s ability to turn equity investments into profits (ROE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;High Leverage:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to decrease shareholder equity is to tweak the company’s capital structure by playing around with the Debt/Equity ratio. Companies issue debt to raise capital and then use that to generate profits. Indeed, the finance cost will increase for a given capital requirement but that would only be a fraction of total debt and not enough to offset the decrease in shareholder’s equity. Higher Net Profits would boost ROE higher, but that has hidden risks related to insolvency and inability to survive during economic downturns. Because debt is an obligation to pay back with interest, it is neutral to the company’s bad run. Companies that issue large debt run the risks of overleveraging in the form of high-interest payments and greater chances of default. These companies may rely heavily on debt and hence have an Inflated and misleading ROE figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Off-balance sheet items and write-downs:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of Off-balance sheet items has been in talks ever since &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sir David Tweedie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; was the chairman of the IASB. He joked that he wanted to fly in an aircraft that actually existed on an airline’s balance sheet. That is to say that it’s not on operating lease or any such way that the companies adopt to evade showing huge assets in their balance sheets. By doing this, they forgo depreciation expense and incur impairment charges when they right down assets, which in turn decreases Shareholders' equity on the balance sheet. This keeps equity investors in an obscure environment by hiding the true amount of capital invested in the business. This is further treated maliciously by the management to offset natural ROE figures and make them appear more inflated and following a growth trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem with the ROE calculations is the ‘E’ part in it. The “Net Earnings” line item is such an entry that can easily be tricked and especially when the management bonus is linked to hitting ROE targets, they can have a strong interest in artificially boosting it. Further, it does not take into account risks associated with income generation and is subject to a wide variety of accounting conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the number is so susceptible to management intervention and unchallenging to intrude and alter, higher ROE can be misleading. If not anything this is what companies did in the wake of the 2008 Financial Crisis and during the ongoing Covid-19 Pandemic. Since the market was undervalued on both occasions, companies came in with various offers to interest investors and appear good on paper. This rigorous attempt was also done to avoid a dent in the ROE history of the company. An ROE that’s greater than the return available from a lower risk investment motivates the Investor to see interesting but false prospects building within the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While companies do all this to fuel their investor's confidence, misinformed investors are caught in a tyranny of financial malpractices, unwinding which is a luxury for a common Investor. Investors can’t know whether that ROE number is reliable or pumped to perfection. One company might have a significantly higher ROE than a competitor simply because it’s more aggressively exploiting uninformed investors rather than being superior in terms of profitability. ROE lacks the necessary meticulous conscientiousness to buttress intelligent investment decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though every single ratio has a caveat. ROE is the dumbest of all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you with one thought, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If such a flawed financial metric catches the attention of mass-market participants, then there should be a profitable arbitrage strategy that exploits that anomaly?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mehul Goyal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“Investment is most intelligent when it’s most businesslike”- Benjamin Graham. Both Benjamin Graham and Warren Buffet have emphasised on the need for the investor to only invest in companies whose business they duly understand. But how do we do that? The answer lies in an obsession with numbers. Plain odd numbers that mean something to a blank eye. Just like the Greeks had an obsession with Golden Ratio, investors are the same with Financial ratios. Ratios are shortcuts and who doesn’t like them? Especially when “more time means more money”, seems real. One such important ratio that makes the kitty of the most important financial ratios to consider for an Investor is the “Return on Equity (ROE)” Ratio. And both these gentlemen mentioned above love this ratio. They do warn you on single-factor investing and urge you to consider other key factors but that’s in line with every valuation metric that comes with a “yes, but…”.&amp;nbsp; But why do they love it? Because it’s businesslike. It showcases the business owner’s ability to employ equity into money-making ventures. It measures profitability. It gives a raw sense of what the company is doing with its equity and how efficient it is in engineering its cash to generate more cash. More earnings mean higher valuations and higher valuation would mean capital appreciation for stakeholders. It’s simple math. But, as all math do, It starts with a simple formula. Return on Equity (ROE) = Net Income/Shareholder’s equity. Toggle to the company’s P&amp;amp;L statement and pick up the bottom-line item, ‘Net Income’ and divide it by the total shareholder’s equity present on the balance sheet and that’s how easily you can calculate the ROE of your desired company. The rule of thumb is, the higher the ROE, the more the company is efficient in its operations. Too excited to already switch tabs? Wait! This is where the trouble begins.&amp;nbsp; The simplicity by which ROE can be calculated should already make you apprehensive about its god-like relevance. Good things don’t come easy, right? Well, let’s dig deeper. Let’s multiply and divide the above equation, once by the ‘Total Sales’ and again by ‘Total Assets’. ROE= (Net Income/Total Sales) * (Total Sales/Total Assets) * (Total Assets/Shareholders Equity) Total Sales cancel Total Sales and Total Assets cancel Total Assets but for now, let’s analyse each portion individually. Reframing the above equation, we have: ROE= Net Profit Margin * Total Asset Turnover Ratio * Financial Leverage What we have is something known as the DuPont Formula which breaks down ROE into 3 key drivers, all of which independently relate to the ROE and can help back-test the components of the formula. The Net Profit Margin is indicative of how well the company is in managing and financing its operations per unit of sales. A higher Net Profit Margin would eventually mean more earnings for the company and higher ROE. Asset turnover ratio means how efficiently the company is using its assets to drive sales. A higher Total Asset Turnover Ratio would mean that the company is deploying its assets correctly to target higher sales per unit of the asset owned. Hence, a higher ROE. Lastly, Financial Leverage is the extent to which the company uses debt in relation to equity to finance its assets. In brief, higher leverage would mean greater financial risk but substituted by higher Return on Equity (ROE). An ideal firm should have a high Net Profit Margin, high Asset Turnover Ratio but use less leverage to reach there. It turns out, however, that a company cannot grow earnings faster than its current ROE without raising additional cash. Now raising cash comes at a cost and cuts through the firm’s profits. If the company decides to raise money by way of debt, the interest gets paid as an expense and if it decides to raise equity, Earnings-per-share (EPS) goes down, which in turn affects investor sentiment. So, ROE is the limiter to a firm’s growth. It’s a gauge against the excessive heating up of the company. That is why ROE forms an integral part of the investor analysis but here comes the catch. When something holds such importance within stakeholders' minds and the management knows it, will not all companies tend to magnify ROE to seem better on the stock exchange?&amp;nbsp; Yes, but soon you’ll know higher ROE numbers are no shortcut for diligence. Manipulating the ROE numbers isn’t an ordeal. There are numerous ways by which this can be done and that make higher ROE’s a subject for debate. This is where the trouble gets bigger. Share Buybacks: Remember the ROE equation? A simple math student would tell how to increase its value. Either increase the Net Earnings (Numerator) or decrease Total Shareholders Equity (Denominator). An ideal and natural practice for companies would be to focus on increasing the numerator by increasing the Asset Turnover Ratio that drives sales with no additional asset cost or by increasing the Net profit Margin by efficiently managing operations. Both these practices done in tandem would result in a significantly higher ROE. But not all companies resort to this technique. Some adopt a latter technique and decrease shareholder’s equity by rolling out share buyback schemes. When they do say they use the retained earnings to buy stock and thus decrease the shareholder equity which in turn magnifies the firm’s ability to turn equity investments into profits (ROE). High Leverage: Another way to decrease shareholder equity is to tweak the company’s capital structure by playing around with the Debt/Equity ratio. Companies issue debt to raise capital and then use that to generate profits. Indeed, the finance cost will increase for a given capital requirement but that would only be a fraction of total debt and not enough to offset the decrease in shareholder’s equity. Higher Net Profits would boost ROE higher, but that has hidden risks related to insolvency and inability to survive during economic downturns. Because debt is an obligation to pay back with interest, it is neutral to the company’s bad run. Companies that issue large debt run the risks of overleveraging in the form of high-interest payments and greater chances of default. These companies may rely heavily on debt and hence have an Inflated and misleading ROE figure. Off-balance sheet items and write-downs: The concept of Off-balance sheet items has been in talks ever since Sir David Tweedie was the chairman of the IASB. He joked that he wanted to fly in an aircraft that actually existed on an airline’s balance sheet. That is to say that it’s not on operating lease or any such way that the companies adopt to evade showing huge assets in their balance sheets. By doing this, they forgo depreciation expense and incur impairment charges when they right down assets, which in turn decreases Shareholders' equity on the balance sheet. This keeps equity investors in an obscure environment by hiding the true amount of capital invested in the business. This is further treated maliciously by the management to offset natural ROE figures and make them appear more inflated and following a growth trend. Another problem with the ROE calculations is the ‘E’ part in it. The “Net Earnings” line item is such an entry that can easily be tricked and especially when the management bonus is linked to hitting ROE targets, they can have a strong interest in artificially boosting it. Further, it does not take into account risks associated with income generation and is subject to a wide variety of accounting conventions. Conclusion: Since the number is so susceptible to management intervention and unchallenging to intrude and alter, higher ROE can be misleading. If not anything this is what companies did in the wake of the 2008 Financial Crisis and during the ongoing Covid-19 Pandemic. Since the market was undervalued on both occasions, companies came in with various offers to interest investors and appear good on paper. This rigorous attempt was also done to avoid a dent in the ROE history of the company. An ROE that’s greater than the return available from a lower risk investment motivates the Investor to see interesting but false prospects building within the company. While companies do all this to fuel their investor's confidence, misinformed investors are caught in a tyranny of financial malpractices, unwinding which is a luxury for a common Investor. Investors can’t know whether that ROE number is reliable or pumped to perfection. One company might have a significantly higher ROE than a competitor simply because it’s more aggressively exploiting uninformed investors rather than being superior in terms of profitability. ROE lacks the necessary meticulous conscientiousness to buttress intelligent investment decisions. Though every single ratio has a caveat. ROE is the dumbest of all. I’ll leave you with one thought, though. If such a flawed financial metric catches the attention of mass-market participants, then there should be a profitable arbitrage strategy that exploits that anomaly?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Unfunny Joke of Italian Democracy</title><link href="/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Unfunny Joke of Italian Democracy" /><published>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy">&lt;p&gt;It looks as if Mario Draghi will become Italy’s Prime Minister next week. The former European Central Banker is, you might say, the ultimate technocrat. Never elected to public office, he replaces a dysfunctional government and inherits an Italian economy so bad that words can barely describe it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draghi’s skills as an economist cannot be questioned. However, what ought to be questioned is why a man of the pro-European centre, a brand of politics decisively rejected at the ballot box in Italy three years ago, is now set to take the reins of power. Polls suggest that if an election were held tomorrow, the pro-European centre would be repudiated again. This poses a worrying question: does democracy in Italy mean anything at all, or is it all for the show?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even liberal Italians should be concerned with Draghi’s appointment. It suggests that no matter how often the country rejects the pro-EU parties, the faction inevitably ends up governing the country. Faux-democracy has made politics in Italy vicious and angry, and the country now seems fertile ground for the sort of low-level violence which has gripped American politics in recent years. If the country is to pull back from the brink, its governments need to respond more effectively to its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italy’s political system seems capable of only delivering ideologically vacuous, weak governments. Since the electoral system is that of proportional representation, governments are made up of coalitions of multiple parties. After the last election in 2018, the populist Five Star Movement emerged as the largest party. The ruling Blairite Democratic Party was decisively beaten, losing two-thirds of its seats, and the right-wing Lega, previously a fringe separatist movement based in the country’s North, became the second-largest party in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The election had signalled a rejection of the pro-EU centre-left in both the North and South of Italy and, albeit imperfectly, the new coalition government of the eurosceptic Five Star and Lega parties reflected that. But then, in 2019, Lega’s Matteo Salvini walked away from the coalition, leaving Five Star in the lurch. And which party stepped back into government? The Democratic Party, the pro-EU party that was so clearly shown the door in 2018. Suddenly, the new direction charted at the last election was put to an end, without any say-so from ordinary Italians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A merry-go-round style of government makes it very difficult to change major government policy. In Britain, the Democratic Party would have been consigned to opposition for five years until the next election. But in Italy, no matter what happens at elections, defeated parties are never too far away from power. Draghi’s appointment is merely the latest demonstration of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economically, the Italians are also caught in an unpleasant bind. The Euro constraints the Italian government’s ability to take the reins of the economy. Since the European debt crisis, the EU has threatened Italy with disciplinary actions for failing to conform to budget cuts, leaving the government with little room for manoeuvre on fiscal issues. Populists who win elections in Italy by pledging to spend their way out of stagnation quickly learn that they aren’t the ones who get to decide when to loosen the purse strings. When they propose to side-step this problem by leaving the EU, the adults in the room draw the curtains to point out the cliff edge which such an action would lead Italy towards; it is only the protections of the Customs Union which stops Italy’s economy from being exposed to the fury of global competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italian democracy, then, suffers from two problems. On the one hand, it languishes under a political system which fails to deliver strong governments with coherent policy proposals. On the other, even if such a government were to emerge, the country’s relationship with the EU would likely prevent major policy changes from occurring. This erodes trust in democracy because people are continually led to believe that the government can solve problems which it cannot. It also leads to poorer governance; real wages have hardly grown in Italy since 1995, youth unemployment hovered resolutely at 30% even before the pandemic, and the country has struggled to find a sustainable solution to the migrant crisis, which has overwhelmed the South of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn’t hard to see how populists thrive in such an environment. In weak, mushy governments, men like Draghi have been running Italy for the best part of 30 years, and whilst Draghi might be to the taste of liberal Italians and the European Commission, a cursory look at the polls will tell you that he isn’t the man that most Italians want as Prime Minister. Instead, they are placing their trust in Lega, and Brothers of Italy, a new party of the populist right. Even if these parties agree to support Draghi as Prime Minister in the short term (Lega and Five Star probably will, whereas Brothers of Italy may choose to stay in opposition), there is no way a government of national unity will hold for long, because its constituent parties do not believe in the same things. Such a situation helps nobody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democracy is a deeply imperfect system, and, as noted, the spendthrift, quick-fix solutions of Italian populists would be unlikely to reverse Italy’s gradual decline. However, if Italy is to be governed democratically, democracy must be more than a façade. Populist solutions, if popular, must be implemented properly. If they fail, so be it, but they must be allowed to fail. Otherwise, the feeling that Italy’s institutions are impervious to change will continue to grow, and Italians will never stop rooting around for new flavour-of-the-month populists like those who lead the polls currently. If people are to see what is wrong with populism, the populists must have their day. Then, and only then, might Italians start to vote for the likes of Mr Draghi to pick up the pieces. Nevertheless, I wish Mr Draghi the very best of luck in his new position. He’s going to need all the good fortune he can get.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">It looks as if Mario Draghi will become Italy’s Prime Minister next week. The former European Central Banker is, you might say, the ultimate technocrat. Never elected to public office, he replaces a dysfunctional government and inherits an Italian economy so bad that words can barely describe it. Draghi’s skills as an economist cannot be questioned. However, what ought to be questioned is why a man of the pro-European centre, a brand of politics decisively rejected at the ballot box in Italy three years ago, is now set to take the reins of power. Polls suggest that if an election were held tomorrow, the pro-European centre would be repudiated again. This poses a worrying question: does democracy in Italy mean anything at all, or is it all for the show? Even liberal Italians should be concerned with Draghi’s appointment. It suggests that no matter how often the country rejects the pro-EU parties, the faction inevitably ends up governing the country. Faux-democracy has made politics in Italy vicious and angry, and the country now seems fertile ground for the sort of low-level violence which has gripped American politics in recent years. If the country is to pull back from the brink, its governments need to respond more effectively to its citizens. Italy’s political system seems capable of only delivering ideologically vacuous, weak governments. Since the electoral system is that of proportional representation, governments are made up of coalitions of multiple parties. After the last election in 2018, the populist Five Star Movement emerged as the largest party. The ruling Blairite Democratic Party was decisively beaten, losing two-thirds of its seats, and the right-wing Lega, previously a fringe separatist movement based in the country’s North, became the second-largest party in Italy. The election had signalled a rejection of the pro-EU centre-left in both the North and South of Italy and, albeit imperfectly, the new coalition government of the eurosceptic Five Star and Lega parties reflected that. But then, in 2019, Lega’s Matteo Salvini walked away from the coalition, leaving Five Star in the lurch. And which party stepped back into government? The Democratic Party, the pro-EU party that was so clearly shown the door in 2018. Suddenly, the new direction charted at the last election was put to an end, without any say-so from ordinary Italians. A merry-go-round style of government makes it very difficult to change major government policy. In Britain, the Democratic Party would have been consigned to opposition for five years until the next election. But in Italy, no matter what happens at elections, defeated parties are never too far away from power. Draghi’s appointment is merely the latest demonstration of this. Economically, the Italians are also caught in an unpleasant bind. The Euro constraints the Italian government’s ability to take the reins of the economy. Since the European debt crisis, the EU has threatened Italy with disciplinary actions for failing to conform to budget cuts, leaving the government with little room for manoeuvre on fiscal issues. Populists who win elections in Italy by pledging to spend their way out of stagnation quickly learn that they aren’t the ones who get to decide when to loosen the purse strings. When they propose to side-step this problem by leaving the EU, the adults in the room draw the curtains to point out the cliff edge which such an action would lead Italy towards; it is only the protections of the Customs Union which stops Italy’s economy from being exposed to the fury of global competition. Italian democracy, then, suffers from two problems. On the one hand, it languishes under a political system which fails to deliver strong governments with coherent policy proposals. On the other, even if such a government were to emerge, the country’s relationship with the EU would likely prevent major policy changes from occurring. This erodes trust in democracy because people are continually led to believe that the government can solve problems which it cannot. It also leads to poorer governance; real wages have hardly grown in Italy since 1995, youth unemployment hovered resolutely at 30% even before the pandemic, and the country has struggled to find a sustainable solution to the migrant crisis, which has overwhelmed the South of the country. It isn’t hard to see how populists thrive in such an environment. In weak, mushy governments, men like Draghi have been running Italy for the best part of 30 years, and whilst Draghi might be to the taste of liberal Italians and the European Commission, a cursory look at the polls will tell you that he isn’t the man that most Italians want as Prime Minister. Instead, they are placing their trust in Lega, and Brothers of Italy, a new party of the populist right. Even if these parties agree to support Draghi as Prime Minister in the short term (Lega and Five Star probably will, whereas Brothers of Italy may choose to stay in opposition), there is no way a government of national unity will hold for long, because its constituent parties do not believe in the same things. Such a situation helps nobody. Democracy is a deeply imperfect system, and, as noted, the spendthrift, quick-fix solutions of Italian populists would be unlikely to reverse Italy’s gradual decline. However, if Italy is to be governed democratically, democracy must be more than a façade. Populist solutions, if popular, must be implemented properly. If they fail, so be it, but they must be allowed to fail. Otherwise, the feeling that Italy’s institutions are impervious to change will continue to grow, and Italians will never stop rooting around for new flavour-of-the-month populists like those who lead the polls currently. If people are to see what is wrong with populism, the populists must have their day. Then, and only then, might Italians start to vote for the likes of Mr Draghi to pick up the pieces. Nevertheless, I wish Mr Draghi the very best of luck in his new position. He’s going to need all the good fortune he can get.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Will the Bills Bear Fruit?!</title><link href="/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will the Bills Bear Fruit?!" /><published>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit">&lt;p&gt;The past year was certainly filled with uncertainty at every point! The pandemic affected lives and livelihoods in the most unexpected manner and the entire world was in a state of despair. Most of us are very hopeful that 2021 will be different. As we start this year full of hope and joy, there are many who welcomed it in the most unforeseen manner. The ongoing farmers' protest in and around Delhi, India is in full swing. The farmers are determined and have been protesting for over 60 days now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian government passed three farm bills in September 2020. The bills claim to revolutionise the agriculture sector and related services. They also aim to double the income of farmers with the help of new rules and regulations. Even after these promises, the farmers are reluctant and want the government to withdraw the bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The bills are as follows:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Price Assurance and Farm Services Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the existing system, farmers were supposed to sell their produce in registered Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) markets (&lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;). As the first bill comes into effect, it will allow the farmers to sell their produce outside of these APMC markets. This gives free entry to private corporations in the market and to directly deal with the farmers. Even though this sounds good, as farmers will now have autonomy regarding where to sell their produce, it won’t be as beneficial as it claims to be. Reports show that 85% of the farmers fall in the category of marginal or small farmers who own less than 2 hectares of land. These farmers will now have to face competition in the open market as government regulations will be reduced. Since most of them are marginal farmers, big corporates will certainly try to exploit them during transactions. Thus, these farmers will be worse off in the revolutionised era. The corporations will find it easy to buy produce at minimum prices, thereby increasing their profits. Without government intervention, it will be easy for corporations to use unfair practices during trade. The effects of the bills on farmers are manifold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second bill allows farmers to enter into contract farming with agribusiness firms, wholesale vendors or large retailers at pre-agreed prices. Even though this move helps the big farmers as they won’t be regulated by a third party, the marginal farmers won’t be gaining much out of the scheme. No regulation from the government's end also gives an edge to the firms in negotiations. Farmers are seeing this bill as an opportunity for agribusiness firms and retailers to expand themselves and dominate the market. They would definitely earn more profits without the imposition of rules. Thus, the bill is more beneficial for the corporations rather than the farmers, especially the small farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third bill removes many commodities like pulses, cereals, onions, etc. from the essential commodities list. This allows firms and retailers to hoard these commodities for longer periods. This essentially gives them the power to manipulate pricing and dominate the farmers during trade and transactions. This also means that the minimum support price (MSP) won’t be given for these commodities. This leaves the farmers with little or no incentive to continue the production of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above explanation gives us an idea that the three bills don’t directly benefit the farmers much. They are simply easing the regulation that existed in the agricultural sector. It gives a free entry to private players who in turn will exploit the marginal and poor farmers for their personal gains. As soon as the government steps out, the negotiating power of the farmers also reduces. They will be more vulnerable and the removal of MSP from certain commodities makes it even worse for them. As mentioned before, 85% of the farmers are small and thus are barely making any profits. These bills do not incentivise them in any way. The demands of the farmers still remain the same and unheard. Improved infrastructure and farming supplements at subsidised prices would benefit them way more than the privatisation which these bills indirectly aim at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protest has prolonged since September and the Indian government&amp;nbsp; has ignored it all along. The maximum population of our country is involved in agriculture and thus makes it a vital part of our economy. These disruptions directly affect the flow of business cycles as well. The bills have been painting a very rosy picture which doesn’t really fit the frame. The only people who will make money after the implementation will be the rich retailers and firm owners. The exploitation will increase without government intervention and thus farmers will have to struggle more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently witnessing the largest protest ever held and that conveys the urgency of the issue. It directly hits the poor who will most likely lose out on their meagre incomes once these laws come into play. The consequences are cyclic and the propensity of loss increases on this side. Welfare has always been a priority for our state. We have managed to follow a mixed economic model, which has proved&amp;nbsp; beneficial for all sectors. Privatisation might be the next step towards the reform but not at the cost of farmers losing out on their livelihoods. The need of the hour is to make them more self-reliant and provide them with farming supplements at cheaper rates. Reforms are only helpful when everyone is capable of making the best out of the available opportunities!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The past year was certainly filled with uncertainty at every point! The pandemic affected lives and livelihoods in the most unexpected manner and the entire world was in a state of despair. Most of us are very hopeful that 2021 will be different. As we start this year full of hope and joy, there are many who welcomed it in the most unforeseen manner. The ongoing farmers' protest in and around Delhi, India is in full swing. The farmers are determined and have been protesting for over 60 days now. The Indian government passed three farm bills in September 2020. The bills claim to revolutionise the agriculture sector and related services. They also aim to double the income of farmers with the help of new rules and regulations. Even after these promises, the farmers are reluctant and want the government to withdraw the bills. The bills are as follows: -&amp;nbsp; The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill, 2020 -&amp;nbsp; The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Price Assurance and Farm Services Bill, 2020 -&amp;nbsp; The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Bill, 2020 In the existing system, farmers were supposed to sell their produce in registered Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) markets (mandis). As the first bill comes into effect, it will allow the farmers to sell their produce outside of these APMC markets. This gives free entry to private corporations in the market and to directly deal with the farmers. Even though this sounds good, as farmers will now have autonomy regarding where to sell their produce, it won’t be as beneficial as it claims to be. Reports show that 85% of the farmers fall in the category of marginal or small farmers who own less than 2 hectares of land. These farmers will now have to face competition in the open market as government regulations will be reduced. Since most of them are marginal farmers, big corporates will certainly try to exploit them during transactions. Thus, these farmers will be worse off in the revolutionised era. The corporations will find it easy to buy produce at minimum prices, thereby increasing their profits. Without government intervention, it will be easy for corporations to use unfair practices during trade. The effects of the bills on farmers are manifold. The second bill allows farmers to enter into contract farming with agribusiness firms, wholesale vendors or large retailers at pre-agreed prices. Even though this move helps the big farmers as they won’t be regulated by a third party, the marginal farmers won’t be gaining much out of the scheme. No regulation from the government's end also gives an edge to the firms in negotiations. Farmers are seeing this bill as an opportunity for agribusiness firms and retailers to expand themselves and dominate the market. They would definitely earn more profits without the imposition of rules. Thus, the bill is more beneficial for the corporations rather than the farmers, especially the small farmers. The third bill removes many commodities like pulses, cereals, onions, etc. from the essential commodities list. This allows firms and retailers to hoard these commodities for longer periods. This essentially gives them the power to manipulate pricing and dominate the farmers during trade and transactions. This also means that the minimum support price (MSP) won’t be given for these commodities. This leaves the farmers with little or no incentive to continue the production of the same. The above explanation gives us an idea that the three bills don’t directly benefit the farmers much. They are simply easing the regulation that existed in the agricultural sector. It gives a free entry to private players who in turn will exploit the marginal and poor farmers for their personal gains. As soon as the government steps out, the negotiating power of the farmers also reduces. They will be more vulnerable and the removal of MSP from certain commodities makes it even worse for them. As mentioned before, 85% of the farmers are small and thus are barely making any profits. These bills do not incentivise them in any way. The demands of the farmers still remain the same and unheard. Improved infrastructure and farming supplements at subsidised prices would benefit them way more than the privatisation which these bills indirectly aim at. The protest has prolonged since September and the Indian government&amp;nbsp; has ignored it all along. The maximum population of our country is involved in agriculture and thus makes it a vital part of our economy. These disruptions directly affect the flow of business cycles as well. The bills have been painting a very rosy picture which doesn’t really fit the frame. The only people who will make money after the implementation will be the rich retailers and firm owners. The exploitation will increase without government intervention and thus farmers will have to struggle more than ever. We are currently witnessing the largest protest ever held and that conveys the urgency of the issue. It directly hits the poor who will most likely lose out on their meagre incomes once these laws come into play. The consequences are cyclic and the propensity of loss increases on this side. Welfare has always been a priority for our state. We have managed to follow a mixed economic model, which has proved&amp;nbsp; beneficial for all sectors. Privatisation might be the next step towards the reform but not at the cost of farmers losing out on their livelihoods. The need of the hour is to make them more self-reliant and provide them with farming supplements at cheaper rates. Reforms are only helpful when everyone is capable of making the best out of the available opportunities!</summary></entry></feed>