<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-15T21:36:23+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">East Asia - Growth in a Bubble</title><link href="/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="East Asia - Growth in a Bubble" /><published>2019-01-15T00:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T00:35:00+00:00</updated><id>/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble</id><content type="html" xml:base="/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble">&lt;p&gt;The Second World War had just ended. Even though the Axis powers had lost, one could argue that all of humanity was the loser. Millions of people had been killed, wounded or displaced. Assets worth billions of dollars were lost and socio-economic infrastructure in various countries was in tatters. The war, directly or indirectly, also contributed to the freedom of various colonies in Asia. But the question remained was that how these former colonies would prosper economically after being completely decimated by a war between their colonial masters? It would require a miracle, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a miracle it was. Between 1965-90, the East Asian Economies and the High Performing Asian Economies (HPAEs) grew at an average of more than 5% per annum. Their growth rate was three times faster than Latin America and South Asia, and five times faster than Sub-Saharan Africa. During the same period, their real income per capita more than doubled. It was clear that this group of economies, which included Indonesia, Malaysia, Thailand, South Korea, Japan, Hong Kong and Singapore had clearly outperformed the rest of the world in terms of economic growth and development. Some analysts and economists have argued that these seven economies shared some common economic characteristics which set them apart from the rest. Even though these seven countries were highly diverse in population, culture, economic policy, natural resources and types of governance, there were some characteristics common to all of them which led to the growth story of these highly diverse economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textbook Economics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For starters, public policy played a major contributing role in the rapid development of these economies. These countries were simply able to get the basics right. The governments of these economies were able to provide a stable macroeconomic environment, a sound legal framework, limited fiscal deficit, and moderate and predictable inflation. They also invested extensively in education, infrastructure and technological know-how. They welcomed investment both in terms of domestic savings and Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) by providing a favourable environment which included high and steady interest rates and lax tax policy. These initiatives by the government boosted growth and development in the economy along with human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workforce forms the base of any economy. And government-financed education led to an increase in the literacy rate of these economies. The pains taken by the government in the field of education bore fruit: all these countries had a strong, educated and dedicated workforce. These economies also followed a unique and creative approach while dealing with labour problems and unions. Instead of giving in to the demand of labour unions to increase wages, the government focused on job creation. The increase in the number of jobs led to an increase in the demand for labour which automatically increased the productivity as well as the wage of labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rapidly develop their economies, the governments focused on infrastructure development, leading to a booming real estate market. And this (keeping in mind the high wages) ensured housing for the population which once again kept the people happy. The governments ensured that the investment coming from domestic as well as foreign investors was fully utilized. They also specifically invested in particular sectors so as to gain a comparative advantage in that sector (example, South Korea in the electronics sector). This extra effort paid its dividends as there was a rapid increase in the number of MSMEs and full-scale industries, which led to an increase in total output and increased exports. East Asia was a beautiful car ride where everyone was happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Illiquidity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as it is said, all good things must end. As already mentioned, these governments had kept high-interest rates and kept on encouraging FDI. Soon, it was seen that the amount of short-term foreign debt obligations which these economies had to pay in the international market far exceeded their foreign exchange reserves. This type of a situation in which the amount of short-term foreign debt obligations exceeded the total reserves of foreign exchange is called international illiquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International illiquidity became one of the main factors contributing to the fall of these economies in the Asian Financial Crisis of 1997. These countries had excessively liberalized their financial structure to attract more foreign investment. Foreign loans kept piling up as late as May 1997 before someone took notice of it. But alas, it was too late to notice. The ratio of short-term debt to foreign reserves rose to about 7 in Indonesia and Korea, and 4.5 in the Philippines. In other East Asian Economies of Malaysia, Bangkok, Singapore, and Japan, this ratio was well above 1. The government policies of these East Asian Economies to increase investment by moving towards a freer, more market-oriented financial system came to bite them back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happened, most of these economies kept a fixed exchange rate to maintain real interest rates and to woo investors. They maintained the exchange rate by buying up foreign exchange in case of excess supply and selling foreign exchange in case of excess demand. However, as the short-term debt was well over the amount of foreign exchange these economies had, the economy would not be able to meet all the short-term debt obligations if they came at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, on the other half of the globe, the US Federal reserve started increasing the interest rates on US Treasury Bonds to woo investment and revive America from the 1990-91 recession. As this increase in interest rates was not matched by these East Asian Economies, the investors started pulling out investments from these economies and started investing in risk-free US Bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let the Speculation Begin…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 14 and 15, 1997, the Thai Bhat was hit by speculative crisis and investors started pulling out their investments. As feared, the economy ran out of forex reserves to maintain the exchange rate and it was forced to devalue the Bhat. Consequently, the Thai Bhat lost more than 60% of its value in a single day of trading. The news spread like wildfire in the international community and the sentiment of the investors turned against the East Asian Economies. As markets are run on sentiments, investors viewed these economies to be highly volatile and started pulling out their investments. In a span of few days, the Indonesian Rupiah, the Malaysian Ringgit, the Philippine Peso, and the Korean Won were also devalued. These currencies were losing as much as 85% of their face value in a single day of trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This devaluation of currency led to an increase in the nominal value of loans which these economies had borrowed from the international market. As the economy had taken these loans in hard currency and loaned the general public in local currency, this burden could not be passed on to the general public. Therefore, the economy and private banks had to take this hit and sell off their assets in order to repay these loans. An increase in the supply of assets in the markets led to fall in the price of these assets in the markets. And the banks were not able to raise enough funds to pay back these loans to the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Thing Leads to Another…Again&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, a large number of banks and financial institutions collapsed in these economies. Thousands of jobs were lost, there was a fall in nominal GNP per capita, a fall in income per capita, a fall in purchasing power parity, and a fall in economic growth rate. Moreover, the economy had little to no funds to undertake developmental projects and provide subsidies and concessions. The real estate market, MSME sector, education sector, human resource sector, and others, which depended on government aid and support, crashed terribly. As a result, economic growth and prosperity of these countries almost came to a standstill. It is believed that more than 10,000 people committed suicide in Hong Kong, Japan, and South Korea as a result of this crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What started as a blessing for these East Asian Economies and helped them undertake rapid growth in a span of 30 years took all it gave in a matter of few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were the East Asian Economies able to bounce back in the international community and reach the pinnacle of growth and prosperity? Or, was this setback the final nail in the coffin and led them to a period of economic darkness? The second part of this story in the next article.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhishek Sancheti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The Second World War had just ended. Even though the Axis powers had lost, one could argue that all of humanity was the loser. Millions of people had been killed, wounded or displaced. Assets worth billions of dollars were lost and socio-economic infrastructure in various countries was in tatters. The war, directly or indirectly, also contributed to the freedom of various colonies in Asia. But the question remained was that how these former colonies would prosper economically after being completely decimated by a war between their colonial masters? It would require a miracle, no less.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Conservative Party’s Internal Squabbles created Brexit and Divided a Nation</title><link href="/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Conservative Party's Internal Squabbles created Brexit and Divided a Nation" /><published>2019-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is a bit of a mess. It threatens to have dire effects on the British and European economies, permanently undermine the continent’s security institutions, and leave behind a culture war which could divide Britain for decades to come. The old are pitted against the young, the elites against the working class and the ‘Brexiteers’ against the ‘Remainiacs’. A marginal Brexit victory of only 4% two years ago has fatally undermined any attempt to form a consensus about which Brexit (hard or soft) should be attempted, resulting in Prime Minister May’s kerfuffle negotiations. This has left Britain with a choice of: (1) no-deal Brexit (which Remainers dread); (2) remaining in the EU (which outrages Brexiteers); or (3) May’s deal (which is happily despised by all). This wasn’t what David Cameron expected. Brexit began as a bit of internal housekeeping within Cameron’s Conservative Party and as an attempt to finally settle the decades-old rift which had kept the Tories out of government for 13 years. But this intellectual dispute within the Conservative Party led to a most serious outcome that may now change Britain beyond recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of Brexit goes deep. It is underpinned by the memory of the Blitz spirit and Churchill, the triumph of Trafalgar against the wee Napoleon and the very first Brexit, when King Henry VIII separated with the Church of Rome. But for brevity’s sake, we begin in 1990, when Britain’s first female Prime Minister, Baroness Thatcher, said “No, No, No” to the radical European integration agenda of Commission President Jacques Delors. She feared an erosion of British sovereignty. The speech was a reversal of her earlier support for the creation of the European Single Market (Customs Union) in 1987, and it injected euroscepticism into the Conservative Party. Strange as it sounds now, in the 1980’s, the Conservatives had been Britain’s pro-European party, while the Labour Party had proposed leaving the European superstate at the 1983 election. Thatcher’s new found euroscepticism was one of the key factors leading to her forced resignation, alongside the poll tax scandal and poor popularity polls. Her successor as leader of the country and the Conservative Party was John Major, who would now have to navigate the passing of the Maastricht Treaty through Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maastricht Treaty formally transformed the European Economic Community into the European Union, replacing a club for economic cooperation with a political union that had an ominous commitment to “ever closer union”. Major was committed to a shared European future but knew many on the Conservative Parties’ backbenches saw it as affront to national sovereignty, meanwhile many Thatcher loyalists were angry at the new regime. Major negotiated a series of opt-outs for the UK, including the right to not adopt the Euro or the European Workers’ Directive. This was enough for most of the party, and the Maastricht Treaty was ratified by Parliament in 1992. However, as the magnitude of the competences Britain had acceded to the EU became clear, a large faction grew in the Conservative backbenches of eurosceptics angry with Major’s ‘betrayal’ of Britain. Major branded this group “the bastards” and they would be a constant thorn in Major’s side until his crushing defeat to Tony Blair in 1997. It must be noted that through all this (and upto 2014) very few members of the public really noticed that the European Union existed at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, two of Brexit’s greatest characters enter the story: Boris and Nigel. Nigel Farage had been a market trader and Tory party member who quit both following the betrayal of the Maastricht Treaty, choosing to devote his life to the recently formed United Kingdom Independence Party (UKIP). Meanwhile, Boris Johnson was a young Telegraph journalist based in Brussels who began building his fame with a series of spectacularly witty articles lampooning the ridiculousness of EU regulations. Nevermind the articles were full of distortions and half-truths, Boris had began his path to stardom. In 2016, Boris and Nigel would find themselves the public faces of the Brexit campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005, David Cameron was elected Conservative Party leader, promising to get the party to “shut up about Europe”, and to end the constant infighting that had undermined the party during the Major era. Thereafter, riding a wave of political disillusionment, UKIP (lead by Farage) won the the 2014 British elections to the European Parliament. Cameron considered UKIP to be a party of Conservative voters in rebellion, and he thought that by promising a referendum he could win voters back from UKIP in the 2015 election. It was all so simple, then the Brexit campaign began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment the Leave campaign became real was when Boris Johnson and Michael Gove announced their support, Cameron had expected both to begrudgingly support Remain. The support of two of the Conservative Party’s “big beasts” gave the Leave campaign the legitimacy needed to make Brexit believable to the public. For the first time in 30 years, leaving the European Union was a decision supported by major politicians, not fringe figures such as Farage or Enoch Powell. The campaign focused on the simple message of “take back control”, which hit a chord with the left behind of British society. The Brexit battle bus was decorated with the immortal line “we send 350 million to the EU a week, let’s give it to our NHS instead”. A brilliant lie. Britain’s contribution to the EU is offset by millions of EU development funds and subsidies, the real figure would have been around 80 million. But all the British people heard was that millions were sent to Brussels. Exactly what the Leave campaign wanted them to hear. In the end, Britain voted by a narrow margin of 52% to 48% to leave the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the chaos began. Hoping to encourage support for Remain during the referendum, Cameron had prevented contingency planning for a Leave victory by the Civil Service. And the day after the referendum, the British political class was in crisis. For 30 years, support for the European Union had been a consensus across the ruling elite in London. None had expected a Brexit and none were ready to accept it. Following Cameron’s resignation on the day of the vote, the Conservative Party turned to Theresa May (a Remain supporter) to be the next Prime Minister. She was seen as the only adult in the room, a safe pair of hands who could solve the crisis of a nation voting for a policy which none of its social, political or business elite supported. That was was 2016, two years later after a litany of mistakes: the failed general election, a ‘dementia’ tax and the European backstop, it has become clear she was not up to the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Britain is paralysed. Experts rightly warn that a no-deal Brexit could cause food shortages, power outages and grounded planes. But if Britain chooses to stay in the EU now, after all that’s happened, something greater could be lost. I’ve spoken to family members who say that if Brexit is cancelled they will never vote again. The working class and their long running suspicion that democracy was ‘bollocks’, that no matter what happened, the elite would always have the power, would be horrifically confirmed. Britain was arguably the world’s first true democracy, its Parliament is the mother of the world’s legislative bodies. Brexit began as an internal squabble within the Conservative Party. But now, if it’s abandoned, the legitimacy of British democracy itself might be permanently undone. There are no easy solutions to this crisis. At the very least this article may have given you a idea of how we got here, what happened and who to blame.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>reuben.pritchard</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Brexit is a bit of a mess. It threatens to have dire effects on the British and European economies, permanently undermine the continent’s security institutions, and leave behind a culture war which could divide Britain for decades to come. The old are pitted against the young, the elites against the working class and the ‘Brexiteers’ against the ‘Remainiacs’. A marginal Brexit victory of only 4% two years ago has fatally undermined any attempt to form a consensus about which Brexit (hard or soft) should be attempted, resulting in Prime Minister May’s kerfuffle negotiations. This has left Britain with a choice of: (1) no-deal Brexit (which Remainers dread); (2) remaining in the EU (which outrages Brexiteers); or (3) May’s deal (which is happily despised by all). This wasn’t what David Cameron expected. Brexit began as a bit of internal housekeeping within Cameron’s Conservative Party and as an attempt to finally settle the decades-old rift which had kept the Tories out of government for 13 years. But this intellectual dispute within the Conservative Party led to a most serious outcome that may now change Britain beyond recognition.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winter Solstice Ceremony at Stanton Drew Stone Circle</title><link href="/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winter Solstice Ceremony at Stanton Drew Stone Circle" /><published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony">&lt;p&gt;How I wish, dear reader, that I might tell you of how blemishless this ceremony was, how perfectly it did unfold, but sadly, it rather unravelled to dismal disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so it was, on Friday, December 21, 2018 at 5 o’clock in the morning, that myself, a cohort, a witch and two accidentally encountered friends (plucked completely by chance as we crossed paths with them on the way to an uber pick-up point) did become companions in the most bizarre but heartwarming of undertakings; there was to be a Druidic ceremony, at sunrise, at a Neolithic stone circle near the village of Stanton Drew on the outskirts of Bristol, UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are greeted by a film crew and a small contingency of middle-aged women cloaked in long robes and walking with staffs at their sides. The filmographic team will be shooting a documentary for National Geographic, with the footage of the ceremony to be narrated by Morgan Freeman (who sadly would not be attending our English rural romp in person).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battered by wind and rain, we moved all of us through the emptiness of this winter night’s morning and into a dark field. Trundling across the expanse, it seemed our numbers did increase as if by magical apparitions of many who came from all directions, all to converge in a central mass, to become a large group, to surround and step into the circle which was the Stanton Drew Stones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The megaliths loomed out of the darkness as scars of grey, with rippling light, rain running across their listless and ancient surfaces as we shuffled, bustled and edged our way into position. Lights were erected by the film crew but were torn from their hinges by the furious wind, leaving whole swarms of people consumed in pitch black. Thankfully, as if by command, after half an hour, the elements lessened and eased upon us. Shivering in our boots, we were told by the Head Druid assembled with perhaps six or seven of his entourage that the ceremony would soon commence. A single bodhrán (a kind of drum) began playing a steady beat which seemed somehow suddenly louder than the heaviest of the weather—leaving us only with a harsh breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We formed, as instructed, a great circle of possibly seventy people all holding hands. The Head Druid came through the only passage of free movement in and out the circle, a parting at the Western stones reminiscent of the passages often seen in Neolithic round barrows. Followed by the others, this leader of neo-pagan priests began a song with simple words by which all could soon join-in, a pleasant if contrived jaunt of a hymn with text and melody likely an oft-heard ditty in such Neo-Pagan communities, mentioning personification of animals and land with a shared spiritual connection, but probably dating back no further than the New Age movement in the 1970’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This man proclaimed the start of this public ritual and the start of a new phase in time, telling us of how this is, at the solstice, a time for new beginnings and rebirth. Our druids then distributed, in perhaps one of the only truly ‘sacred’ moments of the proceeding, branches of mistletoe which had not yet touched the ground. Such a ritual for their procurement, performed by a druid who must climb an oak tree to cut the mistletoe with a golden sickle and allow it to be caught by others in a white cloak, is the only religious practice for which we have definite knowledge, coming to us from the Roman writings of Pliny the Elder. Coupled with the sacrifice of two white bulls, a brew made from this undertaking on the 6th day of the moon was heralded to bestow fertility and cure all ailments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connection to mistletoe was later perhaps a little misconstrued at our ceremony—one of the druids giving speeches on behalf of the directions, light, darkness, etc, mentions Baldr, the beautiful god, son of Odin and Frigg, who was slain by Loki with an arrow of mistletoe, for though his mother had endeavoured to ask all things in the land to never harm her beloved child, she had neglected this harmless plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparative mythology, one might see a link to the Llew of Welsh legends, who is nigh-unkillable until his beloved Blodeuwedd, the maiden made of flowers, betrays his weakness to an enemy. But this would be the only motif we might connect in this narrative to the ‘Celtic’ identity promulgated by these neo-druids. And until we see evidence of this legend being related to the winter solstice, reader, this punter of the ancient, the eldritch and the occult will not be convinced. In considering the fertility aspect of the divine associated with Celtic festivals, one druid opted to describe the passionate and sexual embrace of his male partner, complete with graphic descriptions of everything they would with their tongues and bodies. He also went about anointing this circular congregation with water, many times, even through the speeches of other druids, saying that water was life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, along with various (unsuccessful) attempts to set alight a soaked pile of bushes in the centre of the circle, multiple wishes that there be ‘peace throughout all the world’, and the gathering being generally unable to fully hear the druids speaking at a pathetically moderate volume on this magnificently windy morning (a far cry indeed from the thunderous tones of Christopher Lee’s operatic chanting atop the tower of Isengard) made the entire affair seem really rather tame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a drab conclusion, having closed once more the gates of the North, the East and company (but mistaking one for the other), the circle, now blessed by dim, grey daylight, concluded the happenings with probably the best part of that morning, this being a great skipping and hopping, a roving of the congregation that so that we became a revolving set of linked lines in a disorganised but joyful dance set to traditional music. We thence went our separate, hitch-hiking ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask me – and in fact, ask anyone you like – paganism ought to be something wild. Raw and uncompromising, within reason of course, and putting us in-mind at least in spirit of the fierce pre-Christian people who did once inhabit this noble and ancient land. And yet, bearing in consideration the words of these, in truth, well-meaning hippies, I begin to wonder, as a man must if he is to mean anything to himself and his close ones, what is it I must give up, in the new year? What is it that I must sacrifice? As my ancestors did before. And what is it I hope for in return?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I leave you with this; the solstice is a time of loss. With thoughts drawn as to what we must gain and what we cannot live without. In place of new year’s resolutions, let us have new year’s dissolutions, in considering the sacrifices we may make, and perhaps must make, in our personal lives. Here is hoping that one day, we will in the South of Britain be able to put on a show in a ritualistic, religious context the likes of which our friends in the North, the Scots, have achieved every year on April, 30 since 1988 at the Beltane Fire Festival, in Edinburgh. Scantily-clad, red-body-painted dancers, revellers and all. I will look for you in the slithy toves and among the bracken and the rough. I will be there in that wind-scathed paysage, upon yonder scraggy and leering hill. Will I see you?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Morgan Black</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">How I wish, dear reader, that I might tell you of how blemishless this ceremony was, how perfectly it did unfold, but sadly, it rather unravelled to dismal disappointment.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why ‘Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word</title><link href="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why 'Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word" /><published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindutva as a political ideology manifests the ‘Hinduness’ of the Indian people. On a primitive level, Hindutva means the ‘Inherent Hinduness’  of all Indian people. Savarkar, who coined the term Hindutva, was an atheist himself and defined Hindutva in a strictly geographical and cultural sense. The word ‘Hindu’ comes from ‘Indus’ (the river around which we started off as a civilization) and the common bond which all Indians inherently share is hence called ‘Hindutva’. Simply put, any person born within the boundaries of the subcontinent is a Hindu and his inherent ‘Bharatiyata’ is called Hindutva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definition of Hindutva is, historically, the only true answer for Indians to the question “Who are we?” All other answers divided Indians into different religions, castes, regions and even races. In fact, the Hindu Code Bill defined a Hindu as someone who is “NOT a Christian, Jew, Parsi or Muslim”! Clearly, we need this ‘Bharatiya’ definition of Hindutva to have a true, positive consciousness of our identity as an extremely diverse nation. Socially, the concept of Hindutva, or there being a certain kind of Hinduness which we inherit from the fact of us being born in this holy land looks beyond divisions of caste and religion to unify the Indian masses. It brilliantly distinguishes Indians from the rest of the world. An American does not start possessing Hindutva if he converts to Hinduism (Sorry David Frawley). But an Indian Muslim has an inherent Hindutva and is very distinct from an Arabic or South-east Asian Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not fashioning an artificial answer here on the question of Indian identity based only in geography. Instead, we are verily identifying the common culture and syncretic tradition that exists only within that geography. The Hindutva we speak of is not simply due to the happenstance of people living in a piece of land, it’s due to the overarching unity among diversity they have developed, the story they have told themselves. This Hindutva is manifested in the numerous public holidays of Eid, Christmas and Diwali we Indians enjoy together― whether we are Hindu, Christian, or Muslim. It is found in the consistent requests for Biryani by Hindus to their Muslim friends. From the Rig Veda’s declaration (RV 1.164.46) that “Indra, Mitra, Varuna, Agni…The wise speak of what is One in many ways” to Kabir’s elegant verses on religious unity, Hindutva is about the rich cultural inheritance of all Indians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first key aspect of Hindutva is the fact that we have overcome so many foibles and problems, skirmishes and conflicts to emerge as one nation. Yes, there was once a time we officially designated people as ‘untouchable’ but still, our Constitution was written by a ‘Dalit’ man. Yes, Mahmud Ghazni plundered the Somnath Temple 17 times, but Ghalib’s verses would be non-existent without Muslims. It is through the schisms between us that we have developed this complex and unique identity. We have been through multiple disagreements on grounds of caste, faith, state and language. And in overcoming them we have discovered our underlying unity. Therefore, the first theme of Hindutva involves a sense of Indian pride, a feeling of common triumph of having risen above so many conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second aspect of Hindutva is religion, or rather the peculiar part it plays in making us so distinct. Religion is very strongly present in India’s public life, from the raucous dispute surrounding the Babri Masjid to the controversy on beef and mob lynchings. However, even if religion is a cause of conflict in India, it is undeniably the bedrock of its cultural identity too. Without Hinduism and its multiple gods, esoteric texts and ancient hymns, India is unimaginable. Without the Buddha its culture is barren; and without an Indian version of Islam, there would be no Sufism, no qawwalis. Faith is a wonderful thing in India that makes us separate from the barren West. In the West, as Nietzsche states (in The Gay Science), “God is dead, he remains dead, and [they] have killed him”. In India, the ‘Samudra Manthan’ of religions yields the nectar of meaning, whether it be in the form of Khwajaji’s sermons, Adi Shankara’s works, or Lalan Fakir’s songs, all we need to do is share it equally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third historical aspect of Hindutva explains how our unity exists through our diversity, and not despite it. We Indians may have had our problems, but just like a big Indian joint family, we are one. Hindutva ideologues like Golwalkar (in his Bunch of Thoughts) and Deendayal Upadhyaya (in his Integral Humanism) have time and again emphasised how Hindutva is broader than Hinduism because Indians following ‘Avaidik’ Dharmas like Sikhism, Jainism, Buddhism and even religions like Islam and Christianity have Hindutva in them. The reason for that is cultural intermingling. Arjuna’s marriage to Naga princess Ulupi and Manipuri princess Chitrangada in The Mahabharata is a classical and literary example of how we Indians cherish a mixing of traditions in our rich mythology. Even the Indian Supreme Court noted in 1995 that Hindutva is a way of life (and a ‘state of mind’). This way of life has been accepting of all people (both the oppressed and the oppressors), and even ‘foreign-origin’ rulers like the towering Mughal Emperor Akbar have patronised this way of life that epitomises a unity that stems from diversity. While the Parsis immigrated to both China and India, it was the latter where they finally found refuge in. The Jews have thanked us enough for being the only country without an instance of anti-Semitism. In fact, the Jewish quarters of Kochi stand right next to the Palace of the King of Kochi. The Hindu philosophical idea of every creature being a part of the Supreme Brahman (irrespective of his faith) has made us an all-welcoming people. And the word Hindutva embodies that openness of mind ever so poignantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line of this article is to tell the reader to embrace Hindutva. Why? Because Hindutva is India’s gift to the world. It was Hindutva which ‘Indianized’ parts of Iran, Afghanistan, Tibet, South-East Asia and even Japan. Thailand’s erstwhile capital is named Ayutthaya, after Lord Ram’s capital Ayodhya. What makes India stand out is not its history, its philosophy or its many religions, but an optimum combination  of all three. Once upon a time, European merchants wanted to trade with us, hence the mad pursuits by Columbus and Vasco Da Gama to ‘discover’ the magical land called India. But what do we find today? Growing westernization and inferiority complex amongst Indians! The same India which was a shining example of an ideal country to the world is now restyling itself based on western ‘isms’ like Capitalism and Socialism. This cannot happen. Hindutva is India’s ‘Soft Power’. All Indians have to be proud of Hindutva, for we can’t expect the world to respect us if we don’t respect ‘who we are’. Unless India becomes ‘Indianized’ again, ‘Superpower 2020’ (realistically speaking, ‘Superpower 2050’), will remain a distant dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The Oxy Moron</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chile – A Bright Spot or a Lost Case?</title><link href="/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chile – A Bright Spot or a Lost Case?" /><published>2019-01-03T21:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T21:41:00+00:00</updated><id>/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case">&lt;p&gt;Just like every individual, every country has its own journey. The journey is, without a doubt, the most important aspect because there is no destination or end goal for a country. It has to keep going. Here, we talk about Chile, a country that has seen its fair share of ups and downs, with a journey to remember. Here, we try to point out specifically, those few moments in its history which have actually shaped the course for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin America, a continent overpowered by political fomentation and social unrest, has led to the creation of states which are run by only a few individuals. Most states are witnessing a huge problem of power and wealth disparity, but the bigger problem is that numerous methods have failed to curb such problems. Chile also seems to be in the same zone as its neighbours. However, there are certain things that it has done differently over the last three decades. This has made the country distinct and a potential role model for the other Latin American countries (in both good and bad ways).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start at the beginning. It all started with the advent of the very charismatic military leader, Pinochet. Pinochet came into power after carrying out a coup on September 11, 1973, and he presided over Chile until 1990. However, what is interesting about this military dictator is that he turned the tide by building a nation on the foundation of strong economic reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began with the massive movement of privatisation. And he implemented privatisation successfully even before Thatcher or Reagan. From education to prison to highways, everything was given to private companies. And business was fuelled with aggressive free trade and huge foreign investments. Unlike countries such as Venezuela or Colombia, Chile was a safe bet for western Europeans and Americans, who back then were looking for potential avenues for investment abroad. The way Pinochet implemented his vision is something that till date is a matter of awe for experts all over the globe. Being an emerging nation back then, it had evidently harnessed the benefits of free trade, making the policies attractive for others to follow. Yet, even though this early dive into market-oriented reforms was pretty useful in giving people vast opportunities, Pinochet was still not loved by his nation. It was probably because he was, after all, a military dictator. His political ambition of gaining absolute power as the dictator of Chile made him less likeable to his countrymen. The social restrictions on the people were immense. Pinochet had successfully cancelled all elections and declared himself the supreme leader. Strict monitoring and regulatory laws in place curbed the powers of the media and also of his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people, however, began to achieve their goal of greater democracy when they managed to orchestrate a plebiscite in order to ratify their leaders. Soon, this wave of change and rebellion got them full democracy, which was much needed in order to restore the liberty of the people. However, the next two consecutive leaders followed, more or less, in the footsteps of Pinochet. This led to a crisis and inequality increased manifold, which led to numerous movements by commoners who demanded welfare. In 2006, this led to the first win for the Socialist Party since the end of the Pinochet era. Michelle Bachelet took office, the first woman to do so in Chile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She had won the elections promising reform and redistribution, a deadly combination that can potentially bring a country to its heels. She started with the reforms in the education sector which was highly privatised and had been a massive cause for unrest among the majority. Equal opportunities for all was promised and thus, specific changes were made to favour the underprivileged. However, all these changes had borne one problem, the increase in the size of government. This led to a reform in the taxation policies. The transition mostly affected the domestic enterprises which were at a major disadvantage now. Chile’s corporate tax was placed above the average of the OECD states. And as predicted by experts, this paved way for a slowdown in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebastian Pinera replaced Bachelet in the elections of 2010. His focus, unfortunately,  was not on reforming the taxation policies. We can see that post-2010, most emerging states, especially in Asia, had increased subsidies and loans manifold. This led to a brilliant scope for the businesses to grow which boosted the nation. It had also given leeway for newcomers to enter the market and start their own enterprises. Innovation was rewarded and the masses thrived. However, Chile was at a disadvantage. A major focus on decreasing disparity had not really helped them in the long run. It surely made the rich poorer, but did it make the poor richer? The answer is no. Even with all those policies in place, the commoners were still not satisfied and slowdown of the economy helped no one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Election time had come and Bachelet came into power again. She faced battles of her own. By this time the rich class was weary of the welfare policies which had led to vast losses in a profitable global period. Hence, this obviously started a conflict between the administration and the business class. It took a toll on the polity, economy, and society. Political interferences were prevalent which made it exceedingly hard for the administration to even execute innovative ideas. By the end of her term, Bachelor’s approval ratings had taken a deep dive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chile is run on its traditional sectors, from mining to infrastructure. Innovation and start-ups are generally not favoured by the laws. Most importantly, there are very few patrons of ideas in most formal sectors. Thus, Chile lags behind at the core and its policies make it a stagnant nation. Probably, the major fault on the administration’s part was focusing on equality and not growth. One cannot happen without the other and thus, even attention should have been given to both. Chile’s main drawback is not the fact they couldn’t redistribute the wealth, rather the reality is that the administration is incapable of providing opportunities to people to rise up the ladder. The inhibitions limit the potential of the state. Now, personally, I do believe that yes, it is an honest plight for a government when it doesn’t know what actually works for its people. However, we can deduce one answer from the above instance that quick fixes and aggressive welfare policies are unlikely to benefit any country in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, one must concede that Chile indeed has been a bright spot in the Latin American region, despite all the problems it currently faces. How much hope is left (or lost) with this South American nation, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Just like every individual, every country has its own journey. The journey is, without a doubt, the most important aspect because there is no destination or end goal for a country. It has to keep going. Here, we talk about Chile, a country that has seen its fair share of ups and downs, with a journey to remember. Here, we try to point out specifically, those few moments in its history which have actually shaped the course for the future.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jan Lokpal: The half-waged war for anti-corruption</title><link href="/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jan Lokpal: The half-waged war for anti-corruption" /><published>2019-01-03T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption">&lt;p&gt;India’s “war on corruption”, which erupted in 2011 with the hunger strikes of the activist Anna Hazare in New Delhi, seems to have lost itself underneath a mountain of bureaucratic jargon and political propaganda. Over seven years ago, Anna Hazare, with his unflinching voice and grit, demanded the formulation and approval of the Jan Lokpal Bill, a citizen’s ombudsman bill, that requires the appointment of a Jan Lokpal, an independent body that would investigate corruption cases, complete the investigation within a year and ensure that the trial in the case gets over in the next one year. The Jan Lokpal Bill was passed after the protests started by Hazare spread across the country in 2013. However, the vision of an India rid of corrupt officials and leaders is still quite distant simply because the Lokpal bill was never implemented. Over the years, along with political activists and India’s Central and State governments, the judiciary has also become involved in the process of the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. Yet, national policy has come to a standstill on the issue, and no remarkable progress has been made in over five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lokpal issue has been raging in the country since 1968, when the bill was first introduced in the Indian Parliament. The need for this reform is certainly apparent. In a fast-developing economy like India, which is emerging as a powerful player of the future, accountability and transparency can no longer be compromised. And so, Anna Hazare began his revolution of a “Swachh” or “Clean” economy and polity for the country. His protests in Delhi became a historic symbol of the country’s battle against corruption. In fact, the formulation of the Aam Aadmi Party (AAP), which constitutes the current government of Delhi, is viewed as a product of these protests. It was Mr Hazare’s protests that led to the Jan Lokpal, a committee of eight headed by a chairperson as the country’s ultimate anti-corruption watchdog. The Jan Lokpal bill provides for special protection of the whistleblower and covers all categories of public servants, including the Prime Minister, with only the armed forces being exempted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the ineffective executive mechanisms that run the nation, have once again, proved themselves. Due to vested interests of significant parties and leaders, the Jan Lokpal is not even solving corruption theoretically. The first issue to spark up was related to the procedure of appointment of the Lokpal itself. According to the provisions of the Bill, The Lokpal is appointed by a five-member committee including the Prime Minister, the Parliamentary Speaker, the Chief Justice of India, the Leader of Opposition and a member appointed by the Prime Minister. The problem is India doesn’t have a Leader of Opposition as of now. By definition, the Leader of Opposition is from a party that has 10 percent seats in the Lok Sabha or Lower House and no party satisfies this criterion. Thus, an amendment was introduced that called for the leader of the largest opposition party to be on the panel for selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in 2017, the Indian Supreme Court ruled that the absence of the Leader of the Opposition should not become a hindrance to the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. But this has evidently been ineffective. And the Court was dragged into the matter again in 2018 when the government had made no notable progress. The petition was filed by an NGO called Common Cause, which was represented by senior lawyer Prashant Bhushan. The petition questioned why the Lokpal has not been appointed as yet, despite an order by the apex court in April last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we now move onto January 2019, the Supreme Court has sought a response from the Centre on a plea that the leader of the single largest opposition party be treated as the Leader of the Opposition and be included in high-level committees involved in the appointment of heads of statutory bodies like CBI, CVC, CIC and Lokpal. NGO Common Cause has even suggested that the SC should appoint the Lokpal. But it only seems that with so many layers of executive, legislative and judicial interventions, India has become tangled in an all-too-familiar web of stagnation. The activist Anna Hazare, after a long period of silence, has decided to step up again and restart his hunger strike. He is expected to fast again from January 30, 2019. This can mark a crucial turning point for the Lokpal law, and the half-waged war on corruption. His aura may once again be successful in bringing people together. But can the man, who awed the public once, five years ago, repeat his own feat? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till then, Indians, like always, have to simply cope with a sad reality brought about by perennial administrative bottlenecks. The Jan Lokpal, that once became the torchbearer of India’s struggle for freedom from black money and corruption, has now become a distant issue. The media seems to have “moved on”. But what remains is the fact that the Jan Lokpal is the need of the hour. Public awareness and intervention alone can help save the cause for Lokpal and develop the economically “Swachh Bharat”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">India’s “war on corruption”, which erupted in 2011 with the hunger strikes of the activist Anna Hazare in New Delhi, seems to have lost itself underneath a mountain of bureaucratic jargon and political propaganda. Over seven years ago, Anna Hazare, with his unflinching voice and grit, demanded the formulation and approval of the Jan Lokpal Bill, a citizen’s ombudsman bill, that requires the appointment of a Jan Lokpal, an independent body that would investigate corruption cases, complete the investigation within a year and ensure that the trial in the case gets over in the next one year. The Jan Lokpal Bill was passed after the protests started by Hazare spread across the country in 2013. However, the vision of an India rid of corrupt officials and leaders is still quite distant simply because the Lokpal bill was never implemented. Over the years, along with political activists and India’s Central and State governments, the judiciary has also become involved in the process of the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. Yet, national policy has come to a standstill on the issue, and no remarkable progress has been made in over five years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Universal Healthcare and The India Story</title><link href="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Universal Healthcare and The India Story" /><published>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</updated><id>/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story">&lt;p&gt;A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations has envisaged Universal Health Coverage (UHC) as a possible solution to address this humongous problem. According to the WHO, Universal health coverage (UHC) means, “all people and communities can use the promotive, preventive, curative, rehabilitative and palliative health services they need, of sufficient quality to be effective, while also ensuring that the use of these services does not expose the user to financial hardship”. The underlying idea behind UHC is health for all at an affordable cost. The concept of Universal Health Coverage (UHC) emerged with the World Health Report of 2010 and considering its importance, the United Nation (UN) in 2015 included it as one of the Sustainable Development Goals. It has earmarked December 12 of every year as International Universal Health Coverage (UHC) Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the UHC movement has gained unprecedented momentum globally during the last five-six years, Japan, Singapore, and Thailand in Asia have been doing commendable work in this arena for many of the past decades. More than seventy countries across the world, with the notable exception of USA, have framed policies around the UHC. The common thread running across all such programmes is governmental involvement and action. India, the largest democracy of the world, too, has taken a vital step towards Universal Health Coverage (UHC). The Indian government rolled out a scheme- Ayushman Bharat: the National Health Protection Mission on September 25, 2018. This scheme has been framed after taking into consideration the dismal status of the health-care system in India, and also as a response to the order given by the Supreme Court of India to the Central Government to “do something” when the exorbitant prices of medical care were brought to its attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayushman Bharat is aimed at providing guaranteed access to free treatment to about 40% of India’s population. The population will be selected based on socio-economic factors. About 150,000 wellness clinics will be set up. They will provide comprehensive health care facilities such as free essential drugs, maternal and child health services, treatment for non-communicable diseases and much more. Setting up clinics is a tried and tested component of UHC that many countries like China and Sri Lanka have adopted to improve access to health services to the poor. And, theoretically, it should work in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1977, South Korea gave a strong push to compulsory health insurance and Japan designed national health insurance coverage as early as in 1961. To replicate their success, a second element  of Ayushman Bharat is providing insurance cover to a fixed percentage of the population of the country against expensive in-patient hospital care. They are assured a sum of over 7000 USD (half a million INR) per year per family. Both these elements are integrated to form the base of the policy. The scheme aims to cover 100 million poor and vulnerable families, making it the world’s largest public health-care scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation of any UHC scheme requires huge financial resources. The financing issue is a matter of greater concern in countries like India with low public health care financing. The Indian Government’s public health spending is less than 1.5% of its GDP while the global average is six percent and even the World Health Organisation (WHO) recommends at least 5%. To bridge this huge gap in financing, some countries have devised innovative public finance schemes. The government spending on health care in the Philippines increased from 1.8% to 4.8% within a span of six years after the implementation of the Sin Tax Reform Law of 2012. Sin taxes collected on tobacco and alcohol were used to finance this increased spending. President Jokowi of Indonesia is financing expenditure on providing health care facilities to the poor through savings from cutting fuel subsidies besides increasing taxes on tobacco. In order to raise finance for the country’s public health system, the NITI Aayog, India’s government think-tank, in its Vision Document has proposed raising taxes on tobacco, alcohol and unhealthy foods such as sweetened beverages. The Indian Government has also committed to raising its public health spending to 2.5 percent of GDP by 2025. But that is hardly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor that is important for the success of UHC is cooperation among nations. To take an example, India and Japan have signed an agreement in October to hone the surgery skills of Indian doctors in the treatment of trauma. Countries can enter into arrangements similar to the International Health Partnership (IHP) entered into by the European Union countries to promote Health Systems Strengthening (HSS) and effective development of cooperation in the field of health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a serious look at and resolution of all the related policy issues, UHC could also pass off as mere rhetoric. India has made some progress with Ayushman Bharat, but there are still issues with the policy and major challenges ahead. India’s PM Modi faces elections this year and his underperformance vis-a-vis UHC in India will cost him both policy-wise and politics-wise.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manya Manushi</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding the Absurdity of Life</title><link href="/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Absurdity of Life" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life">&lt;p&gt;What is the meaning of life? This has been perhaps one of the most vexing questions of all time which has transformed several ordinary men into brooding intellectuals. While the world has seen the emergence of diverse theories propounded by the greatest of philosophers, none seem to have completely quenched the ultimate thirst for an objective analysis of life and its meaning. It was in the pursuit of this meaning that philosophers like Sartre, Kierkegaard and Albert Camus sowed the seeds from which eventually sprang a full grown tree of a new philosophical discourse on absurdism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albert Camus, in particular, has spoken at length about absurdity in his manuscript called the “Myth of Sisyphus”. Here, he has endeavoured to explicate the futility of investigating for the absolute meaning of life—which doesn’t really exist. “The absurd” for Camus stems from the discord between “the human need and the unreasonable silence of the universe”. This ultimately culminates into a sense of hopelessness and despair in the human heart. Camus addresses what he considers the most crucial problem of philosophy: suicide, and whether the absurdity of life is a good reason for committing suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men, by their very nature, are seekers of meanings, and in this pursuit, turn to religion and dogmatism to explain a world which in reality is characterised by sheer indifference and ‘irrationality’. An illusionary world embellished with meanings serves as a major source of comfort to humans as it offers false hope and reassurance, but once this world is stripped of all its meanings, man is thrown in an abyss of chaos and upheaval. Men continue to live in their robotic way, pursuing goals and ambitions mindlessly as if they are in a never-ending race. Then comes a day when they suddenly wake up from this deep slumber of ignorance after receiving a huge blow from the absurdity of life. An alien feeling of disharmony dawns upon them, and life, with all its essence and beauty, loses significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to imagine yourself as an invisible person and look at the world around you. It’s nothing but a mechanical interplay of relations with people chasing temporary materialistic pleasures and associating their very being with these short-lived passions. Such an existence is like an exile or punishment, just like the one awarded to the Greek mythological character named Sisyphus who was condemned by the Gods to perform the futile labour of rolling a massive boulder up the hill only to watch it fall down again and again till eternity. It begs Camus’ ever-so-important question: should we live life at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human understanding is only limited to their own standards. Efforts to reduce the enormity of the universe into a set of uniform principles is futile. In an attempt to content himself, man attaches humanistic feelings of love and suffering to the apathetic universe. While a man’s craving for certainty persists, the universe remains still. And, it is from this relationship between the truth-seeking man and an unfeeling universe that the feeling of absurdity emanates. Science, the most authentic form of inquiry is itself based on hypothesis and conjectures. The claims believed to be true centuries ago are being altered and disproved now. In the face of such dynamism, certainty becomes a far-fetched dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is not the individual or the world that is absurd, but the incongruous relation between the two. The absurd originates from comparisons and confrontation. In the case of man and the world, the absurd lies in the clash between the human desire to look for meanings in a meaningless universe. Although a little baffling to comprehend, once man develops faith in the absurd, it plays an active role in guiding his life’s choices. Apart from accepting the absurd, the other option open to men is to either physically end their lives once and for all, or commit a philosophical suicide, where they assume artificial meanings and purpose of life by resorting to theology or religion. While suicide may seem a reasonable option, it simply negates the problem and does not answer it. Camus staunchly denies suicide and refers to it as ‘a repudiation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is to embrace this absurdity and live with it. This produces three consequences - &lt;strong&gt;Revolt, Freedom, and Passion&lt;/strong&gt;. The revolt is identified by the relentless longing for an objective meaning, which is impossible to achieve. Freedom, on the other hand, is characterised by the realisation that an absurd man is free to act and doesn’t have to submit to the restrictions imposed by life. And finally, consequence or passion arises as a result of living life to the fullest by accepting the absurd and caring only about the present rather than the future or past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now go back to our ‘absurd hero’, Sisyphus. His perpetual toil of pushing the boulder up and watching it roll down enables us to acknowledge the melancholic truth of absurdity. And the only way to remove this anguish is by imagining Sisyphus as a happy person, who despite all the struggle, is enjoying the whole process. Likewise, we must also contemplate the absurd and accept the inevitable drudgery of existence, which can only happen when we conquer our fate without expecting anything in return. So, what are you thinking? Go, enjoy your life, so what if you’ve failed a test, missed a deadline or many deadlines. Such occurrences are insignificant in the grand scheme of things. Appreciate and observe the grandeur of the world around you. Feel the sunlight, the delicate touch of petals, the cold droplets of rain and the beauty of nature, and maybe even derive a meaning out of it (bearing in the mind that it’s absurd of course!). Live your life passionately, and above all, cherish every moment. Stay happy because, at the end of the day, that’s what matters the most!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">What is the meaning of life? This has been perhaps one of the most vexing questions of all time which has transformed several ordinary men into brooding intellectuals. While the world has seen the emergence of diverse theories propounded by the greatest of philosophers, none seem to have completely quenched the ultimate thirst for an objective analysis of life and its meaning. It was in the pursuit of this meaning that philosophers like Sartre, Kierkegaard and Albert Camus sowed the seeds from which eventually sprang a full grown tree of a new philosophical discourse on absurdism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Space and Loneliness</title><link href="/On-Space-and-Loneliness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Space and Loneliness" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/On-Space-and-Loneliness</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On-Space-and-Loneliness">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxi Driver’s principle character Travis Bickle outlines these very principles as espoused by the great American author (who I happen to be a big fan of) Thomas Wolfe. Loneliness is a derivative of several complex emotions which arise within the spheres of our consciousness. This article however will not stress on our individual perspective of loneliness but rather a collective sense of loneliness, i.e. the feeling that we could be the only civilization to breed conscious life in a whole goddamn universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1961, Frank Drake, in his very famous equation, discussed the possibility of the existence of the extraterrestrial beings and our chances of actually finding them and making contact with them. This was not to quantify the number of civilizations in the universe but rather a way to stimulate scientific dialogue on the search for extraterrestrial beings. It is just an estimation technique which is popularly known in the scientific community as the Fermi Problem. It provides a back-of-the-envelope solution to the entire problem at hand. The Drake equation features 7 unknown parameters which can be treated as variables in order to find an answer. This includes variables like the number of civilisations in our galaxy with which communication might be possible (i.e. which are on our current past light cone); the average rate of star formation in our galaxy; the fraction of those stars that have planets; the average number of planets that can potentially support life per star that has planets; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inspirations behind these variables was actually an article in the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; journal that was provocatively titled: “Searching for Interstellar Communications”. One of the first known attempts to connect with the extraterrestrial beings was made by the 1977 American Scientific program that employed the use of 2 robotic satellite probes, namely, Voyager 1 and Voyager 2, respectively. It was actually intended to study the outer solar system, i.e. the outer planets of Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune. It was launched under conditions of a favourable alignment of the four planets. The initial plan was to study the four planets, but currently, the Voyagers explore the outer boundary of the heliosphere in interstellar space and the mission has been extended way above it’s time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacecrafts contain very advanced technological instruments in order to collect and transmit proper, accurate data back home. The Voyagers have stabilized guidance systems, controlled by computers, to point their high gain antennas to Earth for efficient transfer of important results and data. The message transmission is also helped by the use of an electronic photography system which has been an instrumental part of the satellites. One thing of immense interest in the spacecraft, however, is the Voyager Golden Record. These records are phonograph records which contain sounds and images , “selected to portray the diversity and culture on Earth” to any intelligent extraterrestrial life that may come across it. Carl Sagan, the renowned astrophysicist who was allocated the duty to decide which records to include on the disk noted that “the spacecrafts will be encountered and the record played only if there are advanced space-faring civilisations in interstellar space”. But the launching of this “bottle” into the cosmic ocean says something very hopeful about life on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl Sagan chose and assembled 115 images and varieties of natural sounds. There are collections of songs and spoken greetings and printed messages from the likes of US President Jimmy Carter and UN Secretary General Kurt Waldheim. It includes an inspirational message which is “per aspera ad astra” or “ through hardships to the stars”, which is what this entire struggle of choices is supposed to signify. There are several photographs from the notable photographer Ansel Adams along with the recorded brain waves of Ann Druyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one song which resonates with this entire struggle is the simple choice of a gospel blues song written and performed by American musician Blind Willie Johnson that was recorded in 1927. The song was named: “Dark was the Night. Cold was the Ground”. It is basically an instrumental song with the self-taught slide style used by Willie and accompanied by his moaning and humming. Johnson was not blind when he was born, but it is speculated that he was blinded by his stepmother when was only 7 years old. Apparently, during an argument, she splashed Willie with a caustic solution of lye water which ended up permanently blinding him. However, that was not the end of his suffering. He used to perform on the streets and had a tin cup tied to his neck to collect money. During his career, he was praised for his style which became quite popular but he was never financially well off. Post the Great Depression, his audience was completely wiped off, and he never recorded again. And in strange series of circumstances in 1945, his home got destroyed in a fire and he continued to live within the ruins of his house, where he was exposed to humidity and dampness, following which he contracted Malaria. His health steadily worsened due to several other factors and hospitals were not willing to admit him owing to his visual impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He passed away on September 18, 1945. His life has been a true testimony of his song, which has immortalized humankind’s search to cure loneliness. His song truly represents the primal feeling which we all have, whether individually or collectively, for a greater purpose and a direction to every event. Floating in the endless space, it represents a sign of hope and a possibility on how loneliness could be a feature which could give us a new path to our existence. But maybe being alone is not bad after all. Maybe we could all be God’s lonely men. I guess we simply need a few aliens to tell us what the truth is.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Helping Hand to Helping Hands</title><link href="/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Helping Hand to Helping Hands" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands</id><content type="html" xml:base="/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands">&lt;p&gt;In February 2018, an Emirati mother and daughter were sentenced to one and a half years of jail for torturing their migrant maid to death. The husband, who was the sponsor of the maid, was penalised for three thousand dinars. Numerous cases like this have surfaced in the media reports in the last few years. Though these reports are just skin-deep when it comes to the extent to which millions of domestic workers all around the world are exploited on a daily basis. The incident brings forth a lot of queries regarding the laws for labour protection present in the host country. In retrospect, it also makes us question the value of a life. Does the status of the person really determine the value of his or her life and mental or physical trauma that he or she endures? Also, does the position of an individual’s work signify how that person should be treated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to ILO reports, the demand for domestic help in Asia has increased by roughly an estimate of 50% over the last 15 years (1995-2012). It might be based on the fact that the disparity is quite extensive in Asia compared to the other continents. The richer states often face a shortage in the supply of workers willing to work in a private household. Therefore, they redeem themselves by importing the services from poorer states. The main importers in Asia are the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC), Singapore, Hong Kong, and Malaysia, whereas the dominant exporters in the market are the Philippines, India, Indonesia, and Sri Lanka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is a huge sector with a lot of potential, there are only a few laws in place which actually regulate the market. This problem is heightened by the fact that labour legislation in most Asian countries doesn’t recognise these workers as a part of the labour body. Also, workers’ trade unions are usually not prevalent in most Asian countries. Thus, low-skilled workers lose out on bargaining power when it comes to their security, wages, working hours and other facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plight of the migrant workers is worse because they solely rely on employment contracts which paves the way for their residence in a foreign country. They are fully dependent on their employers, who act as their sponsors to the host country. They are also responsible for their work visa. On the other hand, the service agencies, the intermediaries between the two parties, also pressurise the employees to work under all circumstances. Most of these workers have no knowledge of the local tongue or the laws of the country. Therefore, this builds a power structure which gives immense control to the employers. Due to this, there is more opportunity for abuse of power and exploitation of labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equal pay for equal content of work is not a reality, even for skilled females in formal sectors. Eighty percent of the domestic workers, globally, are women. Thus, this sector is plagued by low wages. It is fuelled by the popular notion that household work should be done by any woman. Thus, the significance of the workers’ innate skills is minimal. In an investigation conducted by the Singaporean government, it was found that the average income of a housemaid is one-tenth of the average income of a Singaporean. Adding to this is the problem of severe working conditions: no fixed working hours (assumptions of employers that the housemaid should be available around-the-clock), no rest day a week (normally, its consecutive 24 hours of leave for other labour work), no proper paid annual leaves, no overtime compensation, and isolation for the foreign workers in a new country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rectify this situation, the ILO is now asking for the major host countries to define maximum time limits for work in a week. Also, proper laws for overtime work, rest days should be fixed between the worker and employer at the time when the contract is made along with the pre-decided annual holidays. Another problem in this setup is that most contracts do not mention any paid maternity leave. This is the biggest problem for the highly feminised sector and a problem that laws generally don’t focus on. Moreover, in certain countries, discrimination on the basis of ethnicity, religion, and age is extensive in nature. For example, in the GCC countries, a Filipina housemaid is highly valued and is paid higher compared to the workers from other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, the governments of the labour exporting countries have tried to fix a few problems by entering into bilateral memoranda with the host countries. The Philippines is a good example and it has worked extensively to protect the rights of its nationals in foreign countries. They have recently passed the Kasambahay Bill in the parliament in an act of protecting the privacy and freedom of their citizens working abroad. But this is not a fully effective substitute for proper laws which are not present in the employing nations.
For the migrant housemaids, the problem is aggravated by the mere fact that they are completely dependent on the employers for accommodation and basic necessities. It is not uncommon to find the workers complaining about the lack of food and very bad living conditions. Overworking their bodies without a break or proper meals forces a lot of them to run away from their employers. But these cases are still humane compared to other kinds of harassment that are faced by the housemaids on a daily basis. Their complaints fall on deaf ears or no ears at all. There have been a massive number of cases in which the housemaid has been subjected to verbal, physical and sexual abuse from the members of the family that they have to live with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report by ILO states that around 60% of the domestic workers are victims of abuse. It is truly a helpless situation for them. The restriction on freedom to movement (in some countries, they don’t have their passports or their employers lock them in) and imbalances in the power structure make them absolutely vulnerable to all sorts of violence and injustice. According to a report, more than 40% of workers in Singapore have faced some sort of abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is pretty tame compared to the conditions of the workers in the Gulf countries. The GCC countries have a pre-dominant Kafala system which basically confiscates the passports of the labourers as soon as they land in the airport. It seems as if the workers lose all their rights when they step onto the foreign land. Contract labourers at times get no help from the agency and are left at the mercy of the employers. The law, in every way, happens to work against the innocents, who have no option of fleeing from aggressive employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an act to appease the ILO, certain countries of the GCC, like Bahrain and Lebanon, have come forward to repeal the Kafala system to make the confiscation of passports illegal. However, media reports from these countries say that such is not the ground reality. The change is not very evident. All in all, it seems as if the employers don’t really see the housemaids as humans. Until that happens, legal and social change will not occur. It will simply take a lot more time before employers are made to face justice, a justice where they cannot get away with a crime just by paying off penalties or blood money.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In February 2018, an Emirati mother and daughter were sentenced to one and a half years of jail for torturing their migrant maid to death. The husband, who was the sponsor of the maid, was penalised for three thousand dinars. Numerous cases like this have surfaced in the media reports in the last few years. Though these reports are just skin-deep when it comes to the extent to which millions of domestic workers all around the world are exploited on a daily basis. The incident brings forth a lot of queries regarding the laws for labour protection present in the host country. In retrospect, it also makes us question the value of a life. Does the status of the person really determine the value of his or her life and mental or physical trauma that he or she endures? Also, does the position of an individual’s work signify how that person should be treated?</summary></entry></feed>