<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-09T10:49:32+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Chomsky-esque Analysis of Farmer Protests</title><link href="/A-Chomsky-esque-Analysis-of-Farmer-Protests" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Chomsky-esque Analysis of Farmer Protests" /><published>2021-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Chomsky-esque-Analysis-of-Farmer-Protests</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Chomsky-esque-Analysis-of-Farmer-Protests">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Arguably the most important intellectual alive&lt;/em&gt;” according to &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, Noam Chomsky is a veteran linguist and public intellectual who has immensely contributed to the field of media studies. My exploration of Chomsky’s writings happened during my graduation course in journalism. What intrigued me most about his works was the application of his studies to a plethora of current affairs. Talking specifically about his ‘Propaganda Model’ which he first presented with Edward. S Herman in their book &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manufacturing_Consent&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1988), the theory examines media control in the social, cultural and political sectors of society. In their book, Chomsky and Herman explain the effect of wealth and power on mass media interests and choices. They say, “[The model]&lt;em&gt; traces the routes by which money and power are able to filter out the news fit to print, marginalise dissent, and allow the government and dominant private interests to get their messages across to the public.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parallels of four of the five filters presented in the Propaganda Model seem to be striking in the current times as India records one of the biggest protests in world history, led by Indian farmers protesting against the three farm laws passed by the BJP Government (the Central Government). The first filter is about ‘media ownership’ which proposes that since media organisations (mostly) run with a profit motive, they tend to serve the consumers with biased news items. Selective promotion of interests and opinions fit well in the explanation of this filter. A clear depiction of this is how clearly the protesting farmers have defined the biased media by simply turning their backs at them and not agreeing to be reported by the channels that contribute to lapdog media, also popularly known as the ‘&lt;em&gt;Godi&lt;/em&gt; Media’ in India. The protestors seem to be aware of the business interests of media outlets as well as the hidden agendas of political figures who are principal investors in such outlets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advertising revenue is the second filter according to which stories that have a ‘buying mood’ in the economy find more space in the publications. What matters here is that these stories majorly rely upon the interests of the advertisers who see news more like a money-generating process than an information-driven service in journalism. This begins the marginalisation of news items as we evidently see in the current times. Top stories are altered so that there are more eyeballs on the news rather than understanding them from an objective point of view. While I agree that this very objectivity is over-celebrated in the world today, India sees a lack of representation of opinions because of conflict of interests and motives of the investors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;News18&lt;/em&gt; channel broadcasted a piece of news titled “&lt;em&gt;Dilli Chalo War Cry: Who is misleading the farmers?&lt;/em&gt;” on November 26, 2020 that not only legitimised the injustice caused to the farmers but also assumed that they were being ‘misled’, further justifying or rather supporting the government’s decision and laws. This title brings me to the third filter that Chomsky termed as ‘sourcing’. It is important to note that the news that is broadcasted via television or print is provided through a source that can be either an agency or an individual. When the source itself decides a particular side, it only passes on information that it considers to be on the right side of the issue. This comprises the ethical and objective concerns of journalism. Asian News International (ANI), an Indian news agency has lately been criticised for such biased sourcing. While history records the largest protest in the world, reflecting the coexistence of hope and anger in the farmer’s agitation in India, ANI reported how a ‘delegation’ of farmers met the Union Agriculture Minister Narendra Singh Tomar and extended their support to the new farm laws. ANI is one of the biggest news agencies of India and its claims are widely consumed and believed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the mainstream media organisations have submitted themselves to propaganda by avoiding negative responses from the ruling party based on their published content. Here, ‘flak’, as the fourth filter, is used by such media to ensure that nothing against the will of the ‘right’ side is broadcasted as it might put the news outlet into trouble and bring down their relations and reputation amongst their viewers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we are moving towards the exponential development of the digital era, it becomes even more important to subject media to close scrutiny. News is travelling in no time and the repercussions of propaganda-based journalism can polarise the communities of the country instead of saving the sinking boat of democracy. Noam Chomsky’s Propaganda Model not only tells us about the limitations of objectivity in mass media but at the same time aligns with the manufactured consent as prevalent in the Indian context today during the Farmers’ Protest 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Himanshi Saini</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“Arguably the most important intellectual alive” according to The New York Times, Noam Chomsky is a veteran linguist and public intellectual who has immensely contributed to the field of media studies. My exploration of Chomsky’s writings happened during my graduation course in journalism. What intrigued me most about his works was the application of his studies to a plethora of current affairs. Talking specifically about his ‘Propaganda Model’ which he first presented with Edward. S Herman in their book Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media (1988), the theory examines media control in the social, cultural and political sectors of society. In their book, Chomsky and Herman explain the effect of wealth and power on mass media interests and choices. They say, “[The model] traces the routes by which money and power are able to filter out the news fit to print, marginalise dissent, and allow the government and dominant private interests to get their messages across to the public.” The parallels of four of the five filters presented in the Propaganda Model seem to be striking in the current times as India records one of the biggest protests in world history, led by Indian farmers protesting against the three farm laws passed by the BJP Government (the Central Government). The first filter is about ‘media ownership’ which proposes that since media organisations (mostly) run with a profit motive, they tend to serve the consumers with biased news items. Selective promotion of interests and opinions fit well in the explanation of this filter. A clear depiction of this is how clearly the protesting farmers have defined the biased media by simply turning their backs at them and not agreeing to be reported by the channels that contribute to lapdog media, also popularly known as the ‘Godi Media’ in India. The protestors seem to be aware of the business interests of media outlets as well as the hidden agendas of political figures who are principal investors in such outlets. Advertising revenue is the second filter according to which stories that have a ‘buying mood’ in the economy find more space in the publications. What matters here is that these stories majorly rely upon the interests of the advertisers who see news more like a money-generating process than an information-driven service in journalism. This begins the marginalisation of news items as we evidently see in the current times. Top stories are altered so that there are more eyeballs on the news rather than understanding them from an objective point of view. While I agree that this very objectivity is over-celebrated in the world today, India sees a lack of representation of opinions because of conflict of interests and motives of the investors.&amp;nbsp; News18 channel broadcasted a piece of news titled “Dilli Chalo War Cry: Who is misleading the farmers?” on November 26, 2020 that not only legitimised the injustice caused to the farmers but also assumed that they were being ‘misled’, further justifying or rather supporting the government’s decision and laws. This title brings me to the third filter that Chomsky termed as ‘sourcing’. It is important to note that the news that is broadcasted via television or print is provided through a source that can be either an agency or an individual. When the source itself decides a particular side, it only passes on information that it considers to be on the right side of the issue. This comprises the ethical and objective concerns of journalism. Asian News International (ANI), an Indian news agency has lately been criticised for such biased sourcing. While history records the largest protest in the world, reflecting the coexistence of hope and anger in the farmer’s agitation in India, ANI reported how a ‘delegation’ of farmers met the Union Agriculture Minister Narendra Singh Tomar and extended their support to the new farm laws. ANI is one of the biggest news agencies of India and its claims are widely consumed and believed. Most of the mainstream media organisations have submitted themselves to propaganda by avoiding negative responses from the ruling party based on their published content. Here, ‘flak’, as the fourth filter, is used by such media to ensure that nothing against the will of the ‘right’ side is broadcasted as it might put the news outlet into trouble and bring down their relations and reputation amongst their viewers. As we are moving towards the exponential development of the digital era, it becomes even more important to subject media to close scrutiny. News is travelling in no time and the repercussions of propaganda-based journalism can polarise the communities of the country instead of saving the sinking boat of democracy. Noam Chomsky’s Propaganda Model not only tells us about the limitations of objectivity in mass media but at the same time aligns with the manufactured consent as prevalent in the Indian context today during the Farmers’ Protest 2020.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Doxxing: Everything You Should Know About Not Falling Victim</title><link href="/Doxxing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doxxing: Everything You Should Know About Not Falling Victim" /><published>2021-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Doxxing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Doxxing">&lt;p&gt;Doxxing has been around for a long time. You might have been a victim of doxxing – on a smaller or larger scale – and you didn't even know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this piece, we discuss what doxxing is and what you can do to prevent it from happening in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Doxxing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also known as doxxing, it refers to a specific form of cyber-attack where an internet user's details are revealed and made publicly available.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doxing often occurs as a personal attack launched on a specific internet user to make them uncomfortable in their own homes. It is also a way to let the internet user know that they are not safe from their attacker's reach, no matter where they might go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to prevent doxxing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth about doxxing is that nothing you didn't put out there will be found. Thus, it can be prevented in its entirety if you know what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the ways to keep off the radar of this damaging attack include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watching Social Media Activity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is an information mine that you are not considering as much as you should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From constant updates, picture uploads, random tweets, and more, you might be letting on bits and pieces of personal information which could be pieced together to uncover your identity online. Here, details such as your email address, home address, personal cell number, and more can be revealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do well to limit the kind of information that you share online. If possible, make your social media accounts private such that only friends and family can follow your updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Masking your IP Address&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The internet works on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wpbeginner.com/glossary/ip-address/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a system of IP addresses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which are uniquely assigned to each computer. Just like a physical address, the IP address is used to approximate or pinpoint the location where your computer is accessing the internet from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, anyone with access to your IP address information can extract where you are reaching the web from. Hence, they have your location also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good measure against this is to use the Tor browser or get &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.expressvpn.com&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a VPN app to protect your identity online&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Both services are excellent for assigning a new IP address to you whenever you access the web. Thus, anyone tracking you will always be sent on a wild goose chase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preventing Packet Sniffing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, make sure your internet network is as secure as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, the hacker can break the Wi-Fi protocols and access the computers on that network. From there, there is no limit to the amount of personal information that they can get on you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An excellent place to start here is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/comcast/risks-of-using-public-wifi.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;avoid public and free Wi-Fi networks altogether&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When on a personal router network also, ensure the best practices at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a sponsored article from TechWarn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>tech.warn</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="sponsored" /><summary type="html">Doxxing has been around for a long time. You might have been a victim of doxxing – on a smaller or larger scale – and you didn't even know it. In this piece, we discuss what doxxing is and what you can do to prevent it from happening in the first place. What is Doxxing? Also known as doxxing, it refers to a specific form of cyber-attack where an internet user's details are revealed and made publicly available.&amp;nbsp; Doxing often occurs as a personal attack launched on a specific internet user to make them uncomfortable in their own homes. It is also a way to let the internet user know that they are not safe from their attacker's reach, no matter where they might go. How to prevent doxxing The truth about doxxing is that nothing you didn't put out there will be found. Thus, it can be prevented in its entirety if you know what you are doing. Some of the ways to keep off the radar of this damaging attack include: Watching Social Media Activity Social media is an information mine that you are not considering as much as you should be. From constant updates, picture uploads, random tweets, and more, you might be letting on bits and pieces of personal information which could be pieced together to uncover your identity online. Here, details such as your email address, home address, personal cell number, and more can be revealed. Do well to limit the kind of information that you share online. If possible, make your social media accounts private such that only friends and family can follow your updates. Masking your IP Address The internet works on a system of IP addresses which are uniquely assigned to each computer. Just like a physical address, the IP address is used to approximate or pinpoint the location where your computer is accessing the internet from. In other words, anyone with access to your IP address information can extract where you are reaching the web from. Hence, they have your location also. A good measure against this is to use the Tor browser or get a VPN app to protect your identity online. Both services are excellent for assigning a new IP address to you whenever you access the web. Thus, anyone tracking you will always be sent on a wild goose chase. Preventing Packet Sniffing In other words, make sure your internet network is as secure as it can be. Otherwise, the hacker can break the Wi-Fi protocols and access the computers on that network. From there, there is no limit to the amount of personal information that they can get on you. An excellent place to start here is to avoid public and free Wi-Fi networks altogether. When on a personal router network also, ensure the best practices at all times. This is a sponsored article from TechWarn.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtual Classrooms and Open Book Examinations</title><link href="/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual Classrooms and Open Book Examinations" /><published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations">&lt;p&gt;Virtual classrooms is a phrase that has become an important part of the new normal, and along with it comes the infamous open-book examinations. Who would have thought that in 2020, the mainstream physical examinations would be replaced by open book examinations. But then again, who in their wildest dreams would have thought that the whole world will be stuck inside their homes, or away from it, for almost a year. The pandemic has clearly uprooted the lives of many, and the students, all across the globe, are no different.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students have been forced to stay within the four walls of their houses, and attend digital schooling. In a country like India or the UK, it was March or April when the lockdown started as a result of the pandemic, and honestly, at that time no one thought it would go on for this long. In fact, no one was prepared for this pandemic and surely wasn’t ready to adapt to it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear from the start that the educational institutions were going to make decisions that might not be suited for the heterogeneous society that we are. Too many debates, discussions and uncertainty led to all sorts of discussions on what to do for the students who had their exams approaching. Thus, emerged the idea of open-book examinations for final year college students. This was initially taken up by Delhi University. The exams got postponed so many times that by the time we took the test we had lost the count. But when these examinations did take place, they happened at a definite, not-so-unclear cost.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, as a person, who could afford to have a separate room and a laptop to take the exams in peace, I was still drowned in intense amounts of anxiety. For, as a student since the past 17 years, all I had to focus on was my paper. Anything from a wrong question, to doubts, to submission of sheets was to be taken care of by the invigilators. The usage of any sort of technology wasn't even a part of the discussion. So these 17 years taught me to dedicate my whole three hours to write the exam. But with this pandemic and open-book examinations, it meant that for once I was required to do all the tasks by myself, using technology, an approach that many of us were clueless about, the added stress being whether the sheets were being uploaded and were the scanned images even clear. All this made me wonder about those who did not have all these layers of privilege I had, and the added stress levels they had to deal with. Obviously, by no means can I even come close to understanding how dreadful all this would have been for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in times like these where the only source of interaction and schooling is through technology, people are forced to be left out, just because they cannot afford such a luxury. Thus, in such situations, something like education that we consider a necessity, in fact, becomes a luxury for many people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the past few months, all the classes are being taken online. Within the span of these months, the mode of examinations has expanded to become MCQ-based or assignment-based. Despite all of this, looking at the state of students, it all doesn't look so different from the idea of a zero academic year, which many people find absurd. The students are constantly stuck onto the screens to study and then to do their homework and assignments, no wonder they are so tired from it all. From teachers figuring out how to make it all understandable to a class with no video and microphone on, to the students attending the class but sleeping through most of it. There is little to no education taking place.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this seems like it was bound to happen because our teaching methods have been developed for face-to-face interactions and not for video-call sessions. Moreover, Indian education systems aren't even reformed enough to focus on teaching the concepts, rather than focusing on exams, which clearly doesn't sit well with the condition we are in currently. Hence, it really makes no sense to have open-book examinations or any form of virtual examinations for that matter, when our whole education system is based on seeing how well you remember what you have learnt, and not really how well you grasp the concept.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has already increased our anxiety levels, and an education like this just adds to it all. This is only the state of the ones who are privileged enough to actually have access to such resources and means of education. There are so many students out there who due to different reasons cannot take up online classes. And hence have no other option but to skip this year, in the hopes that they'll get to join next year. No one can imagine the stress of these children and the huge loss to their mental health as a result of not being able to take up classes this year. We did see one such incident come forth from Lady Shri Ram College, Delhi University, where a brilliant student was so burdened by the stress of her family's financial incapability that it made her take her own life. It was only then that the college decided to take action towards reducing fees and providing help to those in need. But is it really the lack of financial capability of the family, or the lack of concern of the people sitting on the other end, who refuse to look into how the pandemic could be affecting the students and their families?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking around we do see differences when it comes to how the private institutions and government institutions have dealt with digital schooling. And definitely, there is a clear difference between nations across the globe. However, despite these differences, with some institutions clearly having a better grasp of virtual classroom systems, none of the institutions were prepared to shift their entire curriculum fully online for a whole year, or maybe even more. And even though, for once I am willing to believe that all the educational institutions took the most suitable option in the current scenario, there are still aspects which they just chose to ignore. While they adapted to the new normal, they forgot to look into the students who too had to adapt to it. From lack of concern towards the cash crunch that people are facing, to the effects of the pandemic on the mental and physical well-being of students — all of this is far from being discussed. There are still students left who haven't taken examinations due to various reasons, and they are constantly under stress, with the uncertainty of when they'll actually take them only growing. Every day my Instagram stories are filled with students crying over the extensive amount of pressure from the deadlines of assignments and the upcoming exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this makes us wonder what is the point of such an education that only focuses on finishing the curriculum and not even on making sure that each and every student is actually able to attend these classes. Even if it seems that digital schooling is the only possible option right now, is it really worth it if it is at the expense of the sanity of the students, especially with so many students being left out of it altogether?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Priyanshi Mehra</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Virtual classrooms is a phrase that has become an important part of the new normal, and along with it comes the infamous open-book examinations. Who would have thought that in 2020, the mainstream physical examinations would be replaced by open book examinations. But then again, who in their wildest dreams would have thought that the whole world will be stuck inside their homes, or away from it, for almost a year. The pandemic has clearly uprooted the lives of many, and the students, all across the globe, are no different.&amp;nbsp; Students have been forced to stay within the four walls of their houses, and attend digital schooling. In a country like India or the UK, it was March or April when the lockdown started as a result of the pandemic, and honestly, at that time no one thought it would go on for this long. In fact, no one was prepared for this pandemic and surely wasn’t ready to adapt to it.&amp;nbsp; It was clear from the start that the educational institutions were going to make decisions that might not be suited for the heterogeneous society that we are. Too many debates, discussions and uncertainty led to all sorts of discussions on what to do for the students who had their exams approaching. Thus, emerged the idea of open-book examinations for final year college students. This was initially taken up by Delhi University. The exams got postponed so many times that by the time we took the test we had lost the count. But when these examinations did take place, they happened at a definite, not-so-unclear cost.&amp;nbsp; You see, as a person, who could afford to have a separate room and a laptop to take the exams in peace, I was still drowned in intense amounts of anxiety. For, as a student since the past 17 years, all I had to focus on was my paper. Anything from a wrong question, to doubts, to submission of sheets was to be taken care of by the invigilators. The usage of any sort of technology wasn't even a part of the discussion. So these 17 years taught me to dedicate my whole three hours to write the exam. But with this pandemic and open-book examinations, it meant that for once I was required to do all the tasks by myself, using technology, an approach that many of us were clueless about, the added stress being whether the sheets were being uploaded and were the scanned images even clear. All this made me wonder about those who did not have all these layers of privilege I had, and the added stress levels they had to deal with. Obviously, by no means can I even come close to understanding how dreadful all this would have been for them. It is in times like these where the only source of interaction and schooling is through technology, people are forced to be left out, just because they cannot afford such a luxury. Thus, in such situations, something like education that we consider a necessity, in fact, becomes a luxury for many people.&amp;nbsp; Since the past few months, all the classes are being taken online. Within the span of these months, the mode of examinations has expanded to become MCQ-based or assignment-based. Despite all of this, looking at the state of students, it all doesn't look so different from the idea of a zero academic year, which many people find absurd. The students are constantly stuck onto the screens to study and then to do their homework and assignments, no wonder they are so tired from it all. From teachers figuring out how to make it all understandable to a class with no video and microphone on, to the students attending the class but sleeping through most of it. There is little to no education taking place.&amp;nbsp; All of this seems like it was bound to happen because our teaching methods have been developed for face-to-face interactions and not for video-call sessions. Moreover, Indian education systems aren't even reformed enough to focus on teaching the concepts, rather than focusing on exams, which clearly doesn't sit well with the condition we are in currently. Hence, it really makes no sense to have open-book examinations or any form of virtual examinations for that matter, when our whole education system is based on seeing how well you remember what you have learnt, and not really how well you grasp the concept.&amp;nbsp; The pandemic has already increased our anxiety levels, and an education like this just adds to it all. This is only the state of the ones who are privileged enough to actually have access to such resources and means of education. There are so many students out there who due to different reasons cannot take up online classes. And hence have no other option but to skip this year, in the hopes that they'll get to join next year. No one can imagine the stress of these children and the huge loss to their mental health as a result of not being able to take up classes this year. We did see one such incident come forth from Lady Shri Ram College, Delhi University, where a brilliant student was so burdened by the stress of her family's financial incapability that it made her take her own life. It was only then that the college decided to take action towards reducing fees and providing help to those in need. But is it really the lack of financial capability of the family, or the lack of concern of the people sitting on the other end, who refuse to look into how the pandemic could be affecting the students and their families?&amp;nbsp; Looking around we do see differences when it comes to how the private institutions and government institutions have dealt with digital schooling. And definitely, there is a clear difference between nations across the globe. However, despite these differences, with some institutions clearly having a better grasp of virtual classroom systems, none of the institutions were prepared to shift their entire curriculum fully online for a whole year, or maybe even more. And even though, for once I am willing to believe that all the educational institutions took the most suitable option in the current scenario, there are still aspects which they just chose to ignore. While they adapted to the new normal, they forgot to look into the students who too had to adapt to it. From lack of concern towards the cash crunch that people are facing, to the effects of the pandemic on the mental and physical well-being of students — all of this is far from being discussed. There are still students left who haven't taken examinations due to various reasons, and they are constantly under stress, with the uncertainty of when they'll actually take them only growing. Every day my Instagram stories are filled with students crying over the extensive amount of pressure from the deadlines of assignments and the upcoming exams. All of this makes us wonder what is the point of such an education that only focuses on finishing the curriculum and not even on making sure that each and every student is actually able to attend these classes. Even if it seems that digital schooling is the only possible option right now, is it really worth it if it is at the expense of the sanity of the students, especially with so many students being left out of it altogether?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking Down the New Farming Laws of 2020</title><link href="/Breaking-Down-the-New-Farming-Laws-of-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking Down the New Farming Laws of 2020" /><published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Breaking-Down-the-New-Farming-Laws-of-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Breaking-Down-the-New-Farming-Laws-of-2020">&lt;p&gt;There are innumerable farmers who have laid siege to the Indian capital of New Delhi by protesting at the Singhu border, blocking all entry points to the city. Consequently, there is heavy police deployment alongside New Delhi’s borders. A nationwide strike was declared on December 8, 2020, in response to the new farming laws which are inimical to the interests of the farmers. The farmers, who are mostly from the North Indian states of Punjab, Haryana and Uttar Pradesh, seem like they will not accept anything less than the withdrawal of the three new farm laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Two Laws of Benefit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Act is a law about taking away the Indian government's power to impose stock holding limits on food, except under the clause of “extraordinary conditions”, which imply situations of war, famine and other natural calamities that are grave. This also entails an annual retail price rise exceeding 100% in horticultural produce like onions and potato, and 50% for non-perishable produce like cereals, pulses, and edible oils.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that the stock limits mentioned in this law only apply towards traders, the amendment proposed especially exempts processors, exporters and another chain of value participants, as long as the quantities they keep don’t exceed their demands and requirements. It does not concern farmers at all. This law would only benefit farmers as it would remove the stocking restrictions from trade. This would grant them unlimited buying and demand for their products without having to worry about external restrictions on trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement on Price Assurance and Farm Services Act provides a regulatory framework for contract cultivation. This directly concerns the agreements that farmers enter into with agri-business firms which include processors, large retailers or exporters. These agreements revolve around supplying produce of predetermined quality at the minimum guaranteed prices. The Act basically enables contract farming. In crops that have particular processing grades, these exclusive agreements between companies and farmers are already operational. For example, potatoes used by corporate food companies like PepsiCo for their brands Lays and Uncle Chipps. In such agreements, the processors or exporters undertake assured buyback at previously agreed prices and provide farmers seeds, material and extensive support to ensure that only a desired standard of produce is grown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important thing to understand is that contract cultivation is voluntary in nature, including only crops that are not amenable for trading in regular agriculture produce markets. There is seldom any domestic market for gherkins, as is for the low sugar content potato that PepsiCo requires. Neither can farmers sell sugarcane and milk in domestic agricultural produce markets. And the produce that these sugar mills and dairy makers source from them are also a type of contract farming. This Act only formalises contract cultivation within the national framework and clearly prohibits any sponsoring firm from acquiring farmers’ lands, be it through the means of purchase, lease or mortgage, making it a strong and welcoming law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Main Law of Contention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Farmers’ Produce Trading and Commerce Act, 2020 (FPTC Act) is the real bone of contention aggravating the protests at the borders of New Delhi. It permits the sale and purchase of farm produce outside the premises of Agricultural Produce Market Committees (APMC) &lt;em&gt;mandis.&lt;/em&gt; Under the State APMC Act or any other State law, these trades shall not gain any market fees, cess, or levy. The main issue is the very right of the Central government of India to enact legislation on agricultural marketing. Entry 33 of the Concurrent List of the Indian Constitution covers trade and commerce in “food, including edible oilseeds and oils, fodder, cotton, and jute”, implying that the Centre can pass any law that removes a hindrance in both inter-state and intra-state trade within farm produce, while automatically suspending the State APMC Acts. Therefore, making the 2020 Act the “APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; bypass Act.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There must be a distinction between agricultural marketing and agricultural trade. Agriculture marketing includes everything from field preparation and cultivation to the primary sale of that produce in the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. The agricultural trade can only begin after the produce has been agriculturally marketed by the farmers themselves. Therefore the regulation of the first sale of agricultural produce is a responsibility of the Indian states and not the Centre. Farmers just don’t want any restrictions on the movement, stocking, and export of their produce. Their concerns for protesting are not to gravitate towards trade but towards agricultural marketing. They want to dismantle the monopoly of APMCs as the farmers of Punjab and Haryana are not convinced about the “freedom of choice to sell to anyone and anywhere” due to the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their reasons are valid because the government procurement of paddy, wheat, pulses, cotton, groundnut, and mustard at the Minimum Support Prices happens only in APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. If trading moves out of these APMCs, the regulated markets will lose their revenues. They will not formally shut, but if the government stops buying, they will have no option but to sell their produce to big corporates even if they don’t want to. Their main problem is essentially the FPTC Act and its provisions which they know will weaken the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. They are also now demanding for Minimum Support Price as a legal right, which is harmful to their selling market. Because if corporations refuse to pay at MSP and decide to import produce, the farmers will be left with no place to sell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is undoubtedly clear from some of the farmers’ concerns that they are confused about some aspects of all the new Acts that they are opposing. But it is important to examine the merits and feasibility of their new demands as the protests elongate, especially in the FPTC Act. We will have to wait to see how the government decides to further negotiate and handle the situation at hand as they confront the biggest challenge in their six and a half year tenure. Will the decision spin away on excessive sentimentality and result in distorted policymaking? Or will the agrarian sector finally see more inclusive changes? We will have to wait until there are answers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">There are innumerable farmers who have laid siege to the Indian capital of New Delhi by protesting at the Singhu border, blocking all entry points to the city. Consequently, there is heavy police deployment alongside New Delhi’s borders. A nationwide strike was declared on December 8, 2020, in response to the new farming laws which are inimical to the interests of the farmers. The farmers, who are mostly from the North Indian states of Punjab, Haryana and Uttar Pradesh, seem like they will not accept anything less than the withdrawal of the three new farm laws. The Two Laws of Benefit The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Act is a law about taking away the Indian government's power to impose stock holding limits on food, except under the clause of “extraordinary conditions”, which imply situations of war, famine and other natural calamities that are grave. This also entails an annual retail price rise exceeding 100% in horticultural produce like onions and potato, and 50% for non-perishable produce like cereals, pulses, and edible oils. Given that the stock limits mentioned in this law only apply towards traders, the amendment proposed especially exempts processors, exporters and another chain of value participants, as long as the quantities they keep don’t exceed their demands and requirements. It does not concern farmers at all. This law would only benefit farmers as it would remove the stocking restrictions from trade. This would grant them unlimited buying and demand for their products without having to worry about external restrictions on trade. The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement on Price Assurance and Farm Services Act provides a regulatory framework for contract cultivation. This directly concerns the agreements that farmers enter into with agri-business firms which include processors, large retailers or exporters. These agreements revolve around supplying produce of predetermined quality at the minimum guaranteed prices. The Act basically enables contract farming. In crops that have particular processing grades, these exclusive agreements between companies and farmers are already operational. For example, potatoes used by corporate food companies like PepsiCo for their brands Lays and Uncle Chipps. In such agreements, the processors or exporters undertake assured buyback at previously agreed prices and provide farmers seeds, material and extensive support to ensure that only a desired standard of produce is grown. The important thing to understand is that contract cultivation is voluntary in nature, including only crops that are not amenable for trading in regular agriculture produce markets. There is seldom any domestic market for gherkins, as is for the low sugar content potato that PepsiCo requires. Neither can farmers sell sugarcane and milk in domestic agricultural produce markets. And the produce that these sugar mills and dairy makers source from them are also a type of contract farming. This Act only formalises contract cultivation within the national framework and clearly prohibits any sponsoring firm from acquiring farmers’ lands, be it through the means of purchase, lease or mortgage, making it a strong and welcoming law. The Main Law of Contention The Farmers’ Produce Trading and Commerce Act, 2020 (FPTC Act) is the real bone of contention aggravating the protests at the borders of New Delhi. It permits the sale and purchase of farm produce outside the premises of Agricultural Produce Market Committees (APMC) mandis. Under the State APMC Act or any other State law, these trades shall not gain any market fees, cess, or levy. The main issue is the very right of the Central government of India to enact legislation on agricultural marketing. Entry 33 of the Concurrent List of the Indian Constitution covers trade and commerce in “food, including edible oilseeds and oils, fodder, cotton, and jute”, implying that the Centre can pass any law that removes a hindrance in both inter-state and intra-state trade within farm produce, while automatically suspending the State APMC Acts. Therefore, making the 2020 Act the “APMC mandi bypass Act.” There must be a distinction between agricultural marketing and agricultural trade. Agriculture marketing includes everything from field preparation and cultivation to the primary sale of that produce in the APMC mandis. The agricultural trade can only begin after the produce has been agriculturally marketed by the farmers themselves. Therefore the regulation of the first sale of agricultural produce is a responsibility of the Indian states and not the Centre. Farmers just don’t want any restrictions on the movement, stocking, and export of their produce. Their concerns for protesting are not to gravitate towards trade but towards agricultural marketing. They want to dismantle the monopoly of APMCs as the farmers of Punjab and Haryana are not convinced about the “freedom of choice to sell to anyone and anywhere” due to the law. Their reasons are valid because the government procurement of paddy, wheat, pulses, cotton, groundnut, and mustard at the Minimum Support Prices happens only in APMC mandis. If trading moves out of these APMCs, the regulated markets will lose their revenues. They will not formally shut, but if the government stops buying, they will have no option but to sell their produce to big corporates even if they don’t want to. Their main problem is essentially the FPTC Act and its provisions which they know will weaken the APMC mandis. They are also now demanding for Minimum Support Price as a legal right, which is harmful to their selling market. Because if corporations refuse to pay at MSP and decide to import produce, the farmers will be left with no place to sell. It is undoubtedly clear from some of the farmers’ concerns that they are confused about some aspects of all the new Acts that they are opposing. But it is important to examine the merits and feasibility of their new demands as the protests elongate, especially in the FPTC Act. We will have to wait to see how the government decides to further negotiate and handle the situation at hand as they confront the biggest challenge in their six and a half year tenure. Will the decision spin away on excessive sentimentality and result in distorted policymaking? Or will the agrarian sector finally see more inclusive changes? We will have to wait until there are answers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fear of a Green Planet</title><link href="/Fear-of-a-Green-Planet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fear of a Green Planet" /><published>2020-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Fear-of-a-Green-Planet</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Fear-of-a-Green-Planet">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘ecofascism’ is a notable addition to the lexicon of climate change sceptics and the anti-environmentalists. It is an attempt to discredit those who observe that limitless compound growth on a planet with finite resources can only end in ecological catastrophe, and to portray environmentalists as misanthropic, unfeeling Malthusians with totalitarian inclinations. While this was once a left wing epithet, intended to criticise those who wrongly saw overpopulation as the main driver of the climate crisis, it has been hijacked by right wingers who use this term to smear all environmentalists. Indeed, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desmog.co.uk/global-warming-policy-foundation&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Global Warming Policy Foundation (GWPF)&lt;/a&gt;, Britain’s most prominent rabble of climate change deniers, used this term to attack environmentalists in the aftermath of the El Paso shooting, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thegwpfcom/status/1164575475328520197&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;tweeting&lt;/a&gt;: “The greens' loathing of population growth, technological progress and free markets has disturbing roots in totalitarian movements of the past. 'Ecofascism' cannot be ignored.” Even former UKIP and Brexit Party leader and seemingly ubiquitous grifter Nigel Farage, who has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desmog.co.uk/nigel-farage&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; wind energy as a “collective economic insanity”, has &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Nigel_Farage/status/1232464628250075137&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;used the term&lt;/a&gt; to describe a vote by LSE students to ban beef from their campus.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This represents a snide attempt for climate change deniers to discredit leftists and environmentalists on their own terms; accusing those who often champion the cause of the poorest and most disadvantaged of being motivated by underlying misanthropy is an effective tactic, no doubt. But in fact, genuine environmentalists have always disavowed fascists and Malthusians who dress themselves up in green. Murray Bookchin recognised that, “&lt;em&gt;There are barely disguised racists, survivalists, macho Daniel Boones and outright social reactionaries who use the word ecology to express their views, just as there are deeply concerned naturalists, communitarians, social radicals, and feminists who use the word ecology to express theirs&lt;/em&gt;.” The ‘overpopulation’ myth remains a marginal viewpoint among environmentalists. The idea that rising populations in the Global South are responsible for exacerbating climate change has been debunked extensively, as a study from Oxfam&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2020/sep/21/worlds-richest-1-cause-double-co2-emissions-of-poorest-50-says-oxfam#:~:text=1%20month%20old-,World's%20richest%201%25%20cause%20double%20CO2,of%20poorest%2050%25%2C%20says%20Oxfam&amp;amp;text=The%20wealthiest%201%25%20of%20the,2015%2C%20according%20to%20new%20research.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;showed&lt;/a&gt; that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%, and that between 1990 and 2015, CO2 emissions rose by 60%, but the increase in emissions from the top 1% was three times larger than the increase from the bottom half. ‘Overpopulation’ is a falsehood that pseudo-environmentalists turn to when they are unable or unwilling to adequately critique an economic system which relies on the constant expansion and reinvestment of capital by firms who must stay competitive or go under - requiring endless growth at 3% per year to ensure its very survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attacks on environmentalists as misanthropes have not just been deployed by outright climate change deniers. Within environmental discourse, a broad schism exists between those who believe that economic growth is perfectly compatible with solving climate change, as long as renewable energy is developed significantly, and those who believe that a more drastic course of action, a programme of ‘degrowth’ is necessary. Those who advocate for degrowth consistently face the aforementioned accusations, as Branko Milanovic, for instance, wrote an article entitled, ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://glineq.blogspot.com/2017/11/the-illusion-of-degrowth-in-poor-and.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The illusion of ‘degrowth’ in a poor and unequal world&lt;/a&gt;’. However, overwhelming evidence suggests that degrowth is not only necessary to alleviate the catastrophic consequences of climate change, but can also be accompanied by an increase in living standards for the poorest and most vulnerable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1972, the Club of Rome published their ‘Limits to Growth’ report, which tracked hypothetical models of industrialisation, pollution and resource use up to the year 2100, predicting ecological “overshoot and collapse”, before 2070, on current trends. Despite being consigned to the “dustbin of history” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desmog.co.uk/bjorn-lomborg&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bjorn Lomborg&lt;/a&gt;, new research has shown that we are on course to meet that trajectory, unless we do something about it. This is not to say that clean energy is entirely useless or that its development is completely superfluous in dealing with the climate crisis, but it is important to maintain some perspective. Current trends &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paecon.net/PAEReview/issue87/Hickel87.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;indicate&lt;/a&gt; that we are producing 8 billion Kwh, more clean energy than in 2000, which is positive, but the 3% per annum growth imperative means that the demand for energy is 48 billion Kwh. Scaling up the amount of clean energy to meet these demands &lt;a href=&quot;https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/09/06/the-path-to-clean-energy-will-be-very-dirty-climate-change-renewables/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;would likely require extraction&lt;/a&gt; of metals such as lithium, cobalt and silver, which are required to build renewable technologies such as solar panels, electric car batteries and wind turbines, to increase by as much as 105% in the case of silver and 920% in the case of indium, in addition to cobalt extraction increasing by a projected factor of four. The ‘Scramble for Africa’ at the end of the 19th century spawned ruthless imperialist exploitation of labour and materials such as tin, copper and rubber from the Congo, Zambia and countries further afield such as Malaysia, facilitating the development of combustion engines, railroads and motors. Similarly, the 21st century may give rise to a new wave of imperial domination, as a rush to exploit the aforementioned resources facilitates the development of renewable technologies in rich, western countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this, of course, presupposes that the 3% per annum growth imperative is maintained, and that the rollout of clean energy is compelled to meet these demands. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paecon.net/PAEReview/issue87/Hickel87.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according to Jason Hickel&lt;/a&gt;, under the 3% growth imperative, decarbonisation must occur at 10.5% per year to achieve 1.5 degrees celsius of global warming, which is unheard of for any technology. &lt;a href=&quot;http://jwsr.pitt.edu/ojs/jwsr/article/view/977/1488&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;According to Minqi Li&lt;/a&gt;, a Professor of Economics at the University of Utah, emissions intensity of GDP only declined by 0.87% between 1990 and 2018, despite 2.81% growth. It is unsurprising that growth offsets the decline in emissions intensity that renewable energy achieves, as the ‘Jevons Paradox’ dictates that for any advancement in the efficiency of a new technology, the benefits can be rendered obsolete by rising demand and rising production. For example, it might be affordable to cut pollutants by car in half as a result of developing electric cars. If the number of cars doubles, however, the emissions will have to be cut in half again to maintain the same air quality, and if the number of cars doubles three times, emissions will have to be cut by 87.5% to maintain the same air quality. The ‘degrowth’ alternative, involving a 40% reduction in global energy consumption, makes it much more feasible to decarbonise.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dismissal of degrowth as a form of eco-austerity, coupled with the erroneous association between GDP and human prosperity, has sidelined degrowth as a viable alternative to climate change within mainstream environmentalism. It is incorrectly assumed that degrowth, which is a planned contraction of excess energy use in line with ecological boundaries, involves sacrificing the wellbeing of the poorest people on the planet to stave off ecological breakdown. But these claims are incorrect; GDP is merely a measure of the total exchangeable value of all commodities in a country at any given time, and is unrelated to, and often diametrically opposed to genuine, tangible measures of wellbeing. For example, an &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2010/06/15/oil-spill-may-end-up-lifting-gdp-slightly/#:~:text=The%20continuing%20oil%20spill%20in,at%20J.P.%20Morgan%20Chase%20said.&amp;amp;text=Commercial%20fishing%20in%20the%20Gulf,about%200.005%25%20of%20U.S.%20GDP.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico increased GDP&lt;/a&gt; despite incurring substantial environmental damage, and even a car crash could increase GDP if more production and manufacturing was required to repair the cars, irrespective of the damage done to the victims. Indeed, GDP in the United States had tripled in the four decades prior to the COVID-19 pandemic while wages stagnated, homelessness skyrocketed and food insecurity mounted. Only the richest in society accrued any concrete advantages from this. Karl Marx summarised this tendency in &lt;em&gt;Capital Volume 1&lt;/em&gt;, stating that, “Accumulation of wealth at one pole is, therefore, at the same time accumulation of misery, agony of toil slavery, ignorance, brutality, mental degradation, at the opposite pole, i.e, on the side of the class that produces its own product in the form of capital.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Degrowth is primarily concerned with opposing these capitalistic metrics of wellbeing, and ensuring that waste and energy throughput are minimised through democratic planning. It has been estimated that wealthier nations could meet their citizens’ material needs with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasonhickel.org/blog/2017/11/19/why-branko-milanovic-is-wrong-about-de-growth&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;up to 80% less resource use&lt;/a&gt;, and a third of global food production is wasted due to capitalist overproduction, which ensures that goods that cannot be sold at a profit are simply discarded, as workers cannot afford to buy the goods that the capitalist system produces. Planned obsolescence, which ensures that products are built to break down so more can be sold, must also be eliminated if environmental externalities are to be avoided. Degrowth is not about depriving those who are already poor of basic necessities, or about enacting a Malthusian population cull, as the climate change sceptics argue. Rather, it is about ending wasteful production and decommodifying private goods, re-localising production and minimising carbon-intensive global trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the paradox of degrowth; despite being castigated by conservatives as a Malthusian ideology, at odds with the onward march of technological innovation, growth and endless progress, it is an ostensible conservative idea, valuing the dignity of small producers and communities over the destabilising, corrosive influence of giant multinational corporations. George Monbiot recognised this, &lt;a href=&quot;https://davidaslindsay.blogspot.com/2018/07/the-contradictions-run-through.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;As a young man, I was amazed to see the burghers of middle England look the other way as their beautiful market towns were turned into car parks and the glorious countryside that surrounded them into chemical deserts&lt;/em&gt;”, continuing: “&lt;em&gt;As a road-building programme driven by the demands of construction companies ripped through ancient monuments and nature reserves, they did nothing, leaving hippies and anarchists to defend our national heritage&lt;/em&gt;.” It is the constant expansion and accumulation of capital that commodifies and denudes nature, subjecting it to a balance sheet, and is the most un-conservative idea imaginable. Far from being a misanthropic ideology, at the heart of degrowth is the restoration of autonomy and dignity to the small producer, as opposed to the footloose corporation, and to the family farm, as opposed to the agro-industrial behemoths whose techniques of production erode the soil and &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.croneri.co.uk/feature-articles/biodiversity-loss-and-threat-food-production#WKID-201907161229020146-97944295&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;perpetuate biodiversity loss&lt;/a&gt;. As T S Elliot summarised, “&lt;em&gt;The endless cycle of idea and action, endless invention, endless experiment, brings knowledge of motion, but not of stillness.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The term ‘ecofascism’ is a notable addition to the lexicon of climate change sceptics and the anti-environmentalists. It is an attempt to discredit those who observe that limitless compound growth on a planet with finite resources can only end in ecological catastrophe, and to portray environmentalists as misanthropic, unfeeling Malthusians with totalitarian inclinations. While this was once a left wing epithet, intended to criticise those who wrongly saw overpopulation as the main driver of the climate crisis, it has been hijacked by right wingers who use this term to smear all environmentalists. Indeed, the Global Warming Policy Foundation (GWPF), Britain’s most prominent rabble of climate change deniers, used this term to attack environmentalists in the aftermath of the El Paso shooting, &amp;nbsp;tweeting: “The greens' loathing of population growth, technological progress and free markets has disturbing roots in totalitarian movements of the past. 'Ecofascism' cannot be ignored.” Even former UKIP and Brexit Party leader and seemingly ubiquitous grifter Nigel Farage, who has described wind energy as a “collective economic insanity”, has used the term to describe a vote by LSE students to ban beef from their campus.&amp;nbsp; This represents a snide attempt for climate change deniers to discredit leftists and environmentalists on their own terms; accusing those who often champion the cause of the poorest and most disadvantaged of being motivated by underlying misanthropy is an effective tactic, no doubt. But in fact, genuine environmentalists have always disavowed fascists and Malthusians who dress themselves up in green. Murray Bookchin recognised that, “There are barely disguised racists, survivalists, macho Daniel Boones and outright social reactionaries who use the word ecology to express their views, just as there are deeply concerned naturalists, communitarians, social radicals, and feminists who use the word ecology to express theirs.” The ‘overpopulation’ myth remains a marginal viewpoint among environmentalists. The idea that rising populations in the Global South are responsible for exacerbating climate change has been debunked extensively, as a study from Oxfam showed that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%, and that between 1990 and 2015, CO2 emissions rose by 60%, but the increase in emissions from the top 1% was three times larger than the increase from the bottom half. ‘Overpopulation’ is a falsehood that pseudo-environmentalists turn to when they are unable or unwilling to adequately critique an economic system which relies on the constant expansion and reinvestment of capital by firms who must stay competitive or go under - requiring endless growth at 3% per year to ensure its very survival. The attacks on environmentalists as misanthropes have not just been deployed by outright climate change deniers. Within environmental discourse, a broad schism exists between those who believe that economic growth is perfectly compatible with solving climate change, as long as renewable energy is developed significantly, and those who believe that a more drastic course of action, a programme of ‘degrowth’ is necessary. Those who advocate for degrowth consistently face the aforementioned accusations, as Branko Milanovic, for instance, wrote an article entitled, ‘The illusion of ‘degrowth’ in a poor and unequal world’. However, overwhelming evidence suggests that degrowth is not only necessary to alleviate the catastrophic consequences of climate change, but can also be accompanied by an increase in living standards for the poorest and most vulnerable.&amp;nbsp; In 1972, the Club of Rome published their ‘Limits to Growth’ report, which tracked hypothetical models of industrialisation, pollution and resource use up to the year 2100, predicting ecological “overshoot and collapse”, before 2070, on current trends. Despite being consigned to the “dustbin of history” by Bjorn Lomborg, new research has shown that we are on course to meet that trajectory, unless we do something about it. This is not to say that clean energy is entirely useless or that its development is completely superfluous in dealing with the climate crisis, but it is important to maintain some perspective. Current trends indicate that we are producing 8 billion Kwh, more clean energy than in 2000, which is positive, but the 3% per annum growth imperative means that the demand for energy is 48 billion Kwh. Scaling up the amount of clean energy to meet these demands would likely require extraction of metals such as lithium, cobalt and silver, which are required to build renewable technologies such as solar panels, electric car batteries and wind turbines, to increase by as much as 105% in the case of silver and 920% in the case of indium, in addition to cobalt extraction increasing by a projected factor of four. The ‘Scramble for Africa’ at the end of the 19th century spawned ruthless imperialist exploitation of labour and materials such as tin, copper and rubber from the Congo, Zambia and countries further afield such as Malaysia, facilitating the development of combustion engines, railroads and motors. Similarly, the 21st century may give rise to a new wave of imperial domination, as a rush to exploit the aforementioned resources facilitates the development of renewable technologies in rich, western countries.&amp;nbsp; All of this, of course, presupposes that the 3% per annum growth imperative is maintained, and that the rollout of clean energy is compelled to meet these demands. For example, according to Jason Hickel, under the 3% growth imperative, decarbonisation must occur at 10.5% per year to achieve 1.5 degrees celsius of global warming, which is unheard of for any technology. According to Minqi Li, a Professor of Economics at the University of Utah, emissions intensity of GDP only declined by 0.87% between 1990 and 2018, despite 2.81% growth. It is unsurprising that growth offsets the decline in emissions intensity that renewable energy achieves, as the ‘Jevons Paradox’ dictates that for any advancement in the efficiency of a new technology, the benefits can be rendered obsolete by rising demand and rising production. For example, it might be affordable to cut pollutants by car in half as a result of developing electric cars. If the number of cars doubles, however, the emissions will have to be cut in half again to maintain the same air quality, and if the number of cars doubles three times, emissions will have to be cut by 87.5% to maintain the same air quality. The ‘degrowth’ alternative, involving a 40% reduction in global energy consumption, makes it much more feasible to decarbonise.&amp;nbsp; The dismissal of degrowth as a form of eco-austerity, coupled with the erroneous association between GDP and human prosperity, has sidelined degrowth as a viable alternative to climate change within mainstream environmentalism. It is incorrectly assumed that degrowth, which is a planned contraction of excess energy use in line with ecological boundaries, involves sacrificing the wellbeing of the poorest people on the planet to stave off ecological breakdown. But these claims are incorrect; GDP is merely a measure of the total exchangeable value of all commodities in a country at any given time, and is unrelated to, and often diametrically opposed to genuine, tangible measures of wellbeing. For example, an oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico increased GDP despite incurring substantial environmental damage, and even a car crash could increase GDP if more production and manufacturing was required to repair the cars, irrespective of the damage done to the victims. Indeed, GDP in the United States had tripled in the four decades prior to the COVID-19 pandemic while wages stagnated, homelessness skyrocketed and food insecurity mounted. Only the richest in society accrued any concrete advantages from this. Karl Marx summarised this tendency in Capital Volume 1, stating that, “Accumulation of wealth at one pole is, therefore, at the same time accumulation of misery, agony of toil slavery, ignorance, brutality, mental degradation, at the opposite pole, i.e, on the side of the class that produces its own product in the form of capital.” Degrowth is primarily concerned with opposing these capitalistic metrics of wellbeing, and ensuring that waste and energy throughput are minimised through democratic planning. It has been estimated that wealthier nations could meet their citizens’ material needs with up to 80% less resource use, and a third of global food production is wasted due to capitalist overproduction, which ensures that goods that cannot be sold at a profit are simply discarded, as workers cannot afford to buy the goods that the capitalist system produces. Planned obsolescence, which ensures that products are built to break down so more can be sold, must also be eliminated if environmental externalities are to be avoided. Degrowth is not about depriving those who are already poor of basic necessities, or about enacting a Malthusian population cull, as the climate change sceptics argue. Rather, it is about ending wasteful production and decommodifying private goods, re-localising production and minimising carbon-intensive global trade. This brings us to the paradox of degrowth; despite being castigated by conservatives as a Malthusian ideology, at odds with the onward march of technological innovation, growth and endless progress, it is an ostensible conservative idea, valuing the dignity of small producers and communities over the destabilising, corrosive influence of giant multinational corporations. George Monbiot recognised this, writing: “As a young man, I was amazed to see the burghers of middle England look the other way as their beautiful market towns were turned into car parks and the glorious countryside that surrounded them into chemical deserts”, continuing: “As a road-building programme driven by the demands of construction companies ripped through ancient monuments and nature reserves, they did nothing, leaving hippies and anarchists to defend our national heritage.” It is the constant expansion and accumulation of capital that commodifies and denudes nature, subjecting it to a balance sheet, and is the most un-conservative idea imaginable. Far from being a misanthropic ideology, at the heart of degrowth is the restoration of autonomy and dignity to the small producer, as opposed to the footloose corporation, and to the family farm, as opposed to the agro-industrial behemoths whose techniques of production erode the soil and perpetuate biodiversity loss. As T S Elliot summarised, “The endless cycle of idea and action, endless invention, endless experiment, brings knowledge of motion, but not of stillness.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bye, Bye Pinochet: Chile’s Journey Towards a New Constitution</title><link href="/Bye-Bye-Pinochet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bye, Bye Pinochet: Chile’s Journey Towards a New Constitution" /><published>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bye-Bye-Pinochet</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bye-Bye-Pinochet">&lt;p&gt;In 1990, Chile saw the end of President Pinochet’s dictatorship. Yet, they carried his legacy forward for the next three decades. Finally, on October 25, 2020, Chileans voted to get rid of his most prominent legacy: the Constitution formulated during his rule. This change was essential and long overdue and it was a consequence of a year-long protest, the second state of emergency since Pinochet’s rule and mass protests and destruction of public property. Chile had amended its Constitution more than 40 times, yet the fundamental principles of the book remained the same. In essence, the old Constitution had two major issues: &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt;, it favoured the private sector at the cost of public welfare and &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt;, it gave too much power to the President over the proceedings of the Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests were sparked by a rise of 30 pesos in the price of the peak-hour metro fare. While it may seem like a trivial issue for the world, for the people of Chile it was a move that tipped the scales against the government. The pre-referendum system of governance in Chile favoured the market and private sector. The private sector controlled major public services and the government played second fiddle.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile has a two-level healthcare structure, wherein the public chooses between a private healthcare system (called Isapres) and a publicly funded one. The public healthcare system is mired with troubles: they have long queues, and poor staff and medical resources, whereas the private healthcare facilities offer the finest services in a fraction of the time that the public healthcare system takes. Unsurprisingly, the private system is also exorbitantly priced and largely unaffordable for a majority of people in Chile. The government offered no intervention or made zero effort to improve the circumstances. The education system followed a similar track of poorly funded state schools and expensive private universities. The schools are poorly staffed and so resource-starved that parents often have no choice but to take out loans and send their child to a private school if they want proper education for their offspring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poor state of healthcare and education; two of the most important components of a decent standard of living fueled the fire of the revolution in Chile, another catalyst, that perhaps led the protests was the pension scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One of the trademarks of Pinochet’s model was a pension system of individual savings account in private funds known as AFPS, with no contributions by employers or governments” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2020/03/12/can-chile-reinvent-itself&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Santiago, 2020&lt;/a&gt;) The pension system was based on the idea that private savings should have a “70% of final salary” of payout, however, the actual payout was less than the minimum wage in the country. The military did not have a private fund based pension system, which meant that the government was spending more on military pensions than for the rest of the country. This was a force point of contention between the government and the protestors, partly because the AFPS was a pro-market scheme which gave more power to private insurers and consequently aligned perfectly with the right-wing regime’s agendas. However, for the rest of the country, this scheme was a deadly noose. Almost 60% of the country’s population lie in the middle-lower income bracket. This group had to take massive loans to access basic healthcare and education services, and the pension scheme was a beacon of light for these people to be able to pay back those loans to the private companies. However, due to the low payout, the pension scheme created a debt trap.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile has the widest income inequality gap in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), an elite group of countries that Chile became a part of in 2010. It was the first country in Latin America to have joined OECD owing to its rapidly growing economy. However, this economic progress slowed down significantly in 2014. Yet, economic growth was one of the major arguments of pro-Pinochet-era constitution groups.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these arguments may have some merit, it does not negate the fact that there are huge gaps in the distributions of economic gains within the country. The policies and laws favour the elite and rich community. There existed a trade-off between economic growth and basic human needs when there was no need for such a binary. The public has very little trust in the democratic institutions of the country. The revolution was against inequality, it was a revolt against the elite and it has finally come to fruition in the form of a new Constitution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the new Constitution is to make Chile socially-democratic. A committee formed under it will have women forming half its total strength and will focus on improving economic and social equality. The laws would likely amend the structure of important facilities: education, healthcare, housing and pension. It will also aim to reduce the influence of the private sector in the public services sphere and install greater checks and balances on the powers accorded to the President, who until now had powers to prioritise bills debated in the Parliament and be one of the few people in the Congress with the power to introduce fiscal policy bills. The people have high hopes of this change in Chilean political structure, and so far it seems as legitimate a chance as it can be. The people will decide the committee that will make the new Constitution, and there are little chances of the elite in the parliament bull-dozing the proceedings because any new convention would require a minimum of 67% approval in the committee. The focus, now, would shift towards creating an ecosystem where equality and economic growth will sustain together. The new Constitution of Chile is expected to make a decent and healthy standard of life in Chile affordable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In times of heavy anti-democracy movements and governance across the globe, this revolution in Chile is a silver lining in the otherwise dark cloud of global governance and one congratulates the people of Chile on this hard-earned victory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In 1990, Chile saw the end of President Pinochet’s dictatorship. Yet, they carried his legacy forward for the next three decades. Finally, on October 25, 2020, Chileans voted to get rid of his most prominent legacy: the Constitution formulated during his rule. This change was essential and long overdue and it was a consequence of a year-long protest, the second state of emergency since Pinochet’s rule and mass protests and destruction of public property. Chile had amended its Constitution more than 40 times, yet the fundamental principles of the book remained the same. In essence, the old Constitution had two major issues: one, it favoured the private sector at the cost of public welfare and two, it gave too much power to the President over the proceedings of the Parliament. The protests were sparked by a rise of 30 pesos in the price of the peak-hour metro fare. While it may seem like a trivial issue for the world, for the people of Chile it was a move that tipped the scales against the government. The pre-referendum system of governance in Chile favoured the market and private sector. The private sector controlled major public services and the government played second fiddle.&amp;nbsp; Chile has a two-level healthcare structure, wherein the public chooses between a private healthcare system (called Isapres) and a publicly funded one. The public healthcare system is mired with troubles: they have long queues, and poor staff and medical resources, whereas the private healthcare facilities offer the finest services in a fraction of the time that the public healthcare system takes. Unsurprisingly, the private system is also exorbitantly priced and largely unaffordable for a majority of people in Chile. The government offered no intervention or made zero effort to improve the circumstances. The education system followed a similar track of poorly funded state schools and expensive private universities. The schools are poorly staffed and so resource-starved that parents often have no choice but to take out loans and send their child to a private school if they want proper education for their offspring.&amp;nbsp; The poor state of healthcare and education; two of the most important components of a decent standard of living fueled the fire of the revolution in Chile, another catalyst, that perhaps led the protests was the pension scheme. “One of the trademarks of Pinochet’s model was a pension system of individual savings account in private funds known as AFPS, with no contributions by employers or governments” (Santiago, 2020) The pension system was based on the idea that private savings should have a “70% of final salary” of payout, however, the actual payout was less than the minimum wage in the country. The military did not have a private fund based pension system, which meant that the government was spending more on military pensions than for the rest of the country. This was a force point of contention between the government and the protestors, partly because the AFPS was a pro-market scheme which gave more power to private insurers and consequently aligned perfectly with the right-wing regime’s agendas. However, for the rest of the country, this scheme was a deadly noose. Almost 60% of the country’s population lie in the middle-lower income bracket. This group had to take massive loans to access basic healthcare and education services, and the pension scheme was a beacon of light for these people to be able to pay back those loans to the private companies. However, due to the low payout, the pension scheme created a debt trap.&amp;nbsp; Chile has the widest income inequality gap in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), an elite group of countries that Chile became a part of in 2010. It was the first country in Latin America to have joined OECD owing to its rapidly growing economy. However, this economic progress slowed down significantly in 2014. Yet, economic growth was one of the major arguments of pro-Pinochet-era constitution groups.&amp;nbsp; While these arguments may have some merit, it does not negate the fact that there are huge gaps in the distributions of economic gains within the country. The policies and laws favour the elite and rich community. There existed a trade-off between economic growth and basic human needs when there was no need for such a binary. The public has very little trust in the democratic institutions of the country. The revolution was against inequality, it was a revolt against the elite and it has finally come to fruition in the form of a new Constitution.&amp;nbsp; The aim of the new Constitution is to make Chile socially-democratic. A committee formed under it will have women forming half its total strength and will focus on improving economic and social equality. The laws would likely amend the structure of important facilities: education, healthcare, housing and pension. It will also aim to reduce the influence of the private sector in the public services sphere and install greater checks and balances on the powers accorded to the President, who until now had powers to prioritise bills debated in the Parliament and be one of the few people in the Congress with the power to introduce fiscal policy bills. The people have high hopes of this change in Chilean political structure, and so far it seems as legitimate a chance as it can be. The people will decide the committee that will make the new Constitution, and there are little chances of the elite in the parliament bull-dozing the proceedings because any new convention would require a minimum of 67% approval in the committee. The focus, now, would shift towards creating an ecosystem where equality and economic growth will sustain together. The new Constitution of Chile is expected to make a decent and healthy standard of life in Chile affordable.&amp;nbsp; In times of heavy anti-democracy movements and governance across the globe, this revolution in Chile is a silver lining in the otherwise dark cloud of global governance and one congratulates the people of Chile on this hard-earned victory.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Conundrum of Crackers: A Deeper Look into Religious Reform</title><link href="/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Conundrum of Crackers: A Deeper Look into Religious Reform" /><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers">&lt;p&gt;The deafening sound of crackers bursting left, right and centre on Diwali&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;often gag the factions who are vociferously at loggerheads with each other. One faction who believes in burning crackers under the garb of ‘Hindu traditions’ and upholding the ‘Hindu way of life’. The other dons a more ‘reformist’ stance of making Hindu practices and traditions amend to the times we live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the Indian government has started to take cognisance of how a night of burning crackers recklessly exacerbates the already alarming rate of air pollution. It did earn the ire of the traditionalists; who, infuriated, got onto primetime slots on news channels and denouncing the move, calling it Hinduphobic and a threat to Hindu practices. Populist Indian anchors such as Arnab Goswami engaged in expected whataboutery by asking Muslim clerics if &lt;em&gt;aazan&lt;/em&gt; doesn't amount to noise pollution every day—with cultural icons like Sonu Nigam further normalising it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration banning firecrackers indeed brings up a rather pertinent question — whether religious reforms should be done by the legislature, or those who practice the faith itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right-wing organisations in India currently promote a more radical form of Hinduism, which often clobbers Hindus with memories of the tumultuous history of Islamic conquest in India — rifling the narrative with the sight of blemished or razed temples, on which many mosques built in that period purportedly stand today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is from this radical branch of Hinduism where the recalcitrancy of refusing to give up firecrackers stems from. Twitter is mostly bombarded with whataboutery whenever and wherever this debate rises; where Muslims sacrificing goats every year doesn't account for slaughter and Christmas trees don't account for &quot;deforestation&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more liberal argument from the same branch has a clarion call to ban crackers indefinitely and not do so only on Diwali as the rationale behind a more &quot;progressive&quot; decision is religionism, not environmentalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing the damage by burning crackers to the aforementioned practices in Islam or Christianity sets regressive precedence — for it doesn't leave room for reform at all. For time immemorial, Hinduism has evolved to fit societal paradigms. Although the precarious issues of caste and Brahminical hegemony show that Hinduism is a far cry away from major reform, Hindus should strive to constantly reform the tenets of the religion, irrespective of how other religions around the world function.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extremists deserve credit for coming up with this ruse where Hindus bear the brunt of being righteous. To its bare-bones, it is analogous to a near-anarchistic milieu — where people refuse to conform to a righteous path because others around them are diabolical.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, accusing the administration of using religionism as an impetus to ban crackers is reflective of yet another trope of the extremist narrative — to live with an inherent 'insecurity' that Hinduism is under a constant threat from monotheism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an insecure demeanour for an ancient religion is a deterrent to an egalitarian and equivocal India, which is set-in-stone in the Constitution. This insecurity is what the right-wing extremists stand for — making people believe in a false, internal enemy who is alleged to be constantly at loggerheads with Hindus and make conniving plots to attack Hinduism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The far-right ruling party’s fervent and Islamophobic attack on ‘love jihad’ — a term promoted by far-right organisations to discredit inter-faith relationships and marriages, is another way that they convolute harmony by victimising Hindu women who ‘fall’ for traps set by ‘well-groomed, handsome’ Muslim men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the country is rifled with intolerance to an extent where there is institutionalised normalisation of coercive endogamy, Hindus should introspect the tenets of the faith that exists in the mainstream narrative. Legislative measures won’t suffice reforms in Hinduism as long as it is in tandem with the resolute of Hindus to seek reform. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Kant</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The deafening sound of crackers bursting left, right and centre on Diwali often gag the factions who are vociferously at loggerheads with each other. One faction who believes in burning crackers under the garb of ‘Hindu traditions’ and upholding the ‘Hindu way of life’. The other dons a more ‘reformist’ stance of making Hindu practices and traditions amend to the times we live in. Lately, the Indian government has started to take cognisance of how a night of burning crackers recklessly exacerbates the already alarming rate of air pollution. It did earn the ire of the traditionalists; who, infuriated, got onto primetime slots on news channels and denouncing the move, calling it Hinduphobic and a threat to Hindu practices. Populist Indian anchors such as Arnab Goswami engaged in expected whataboutery by asking Muslim clerics if aazan doesn't amount to noise pollution every day—with cultural icons like Sonu Nigam further normalising it. The administration banning firecrackers indeed brings up a rather pertinent question — whether religious reforms should be done by the legislature, or those who practice the faith itself.&amp;nbsp; Right-wing organisations in India currently promote a more radical form of Hinduism, which often clobbers Hindus with memories of the tumultuous history of Islamic conquest in India — rifling the narrative with the sight of blemished or razed temples, on which many mosques built in that period purportedly stand today.&amp;nbsp; It is from this radical branch of Hinduism where the recalcitrancy of refusing to give up firecrackers stems from. Twitter is mostly bombarded with whataboutery whenever and wherever this debate rises; where Muslims sacrificing goats every year doesn't account for slaughter and Christmas trees don't account for &quot;deforestation&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A more liberal argument from the same branch has a clarion call to ban crackers indefinitely and not do so only on Diwali as the rationale behind a more &quot;progressive&quot; decision is religionism, not environmentalism.&amp;nbsp; Comparing the damage by burning crackers to the aforementioned practices in Islam or Christianity sets regressive precedence — for it doesn't leave room for reform at all. For time immemorial, Hinduism has evolved to fit societal paradigms. Although the precarious issues of caste and Brahminical hegemony show that Hinduism is a far cry away from major reform, Hindus should strive to constantly reform the tenets of the religion, irrespective of how other religions around the world function.&amp;nbsp; The extremists deserve credit for coming up with this ruse where Hindus bear the brunt of being righteous. To its bare-bones, it is analogous to a near-anarchistic milieu — where people refuse to conform to a righteous path because others around them are diabolical.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, accusing the administration of using religionism as an impetus to ban crackers is reflective of yet another trope of the extremist narrative — to live with an inherent 'insecurity' that Hinduism is under a constant threat from monotheism.&amp;nbsp; Such an insecure demeanour for an ancient religion is a deterrent to an egalitarian and equivocal India, which is set-in-stone in the Constitution. This insecurity is what the right-wing extremists stand for — making people believe in a false, internal enemy who is alleged to be constantly at loggerheads with Hindus and make conniving plots to attack Hinduism. The far-right ruling party’s fervent and Islamophobic attack on ‘love jihad’ — a term promoted by far-right organisations to discredit inter-faith relationships and marriages, is another way that they convolute harmony by victimising Hindu women who ‘fall’ for traps set by ‘well-groomed, handsome’ Muslim men. When the country is rifled with intolerance to an extent where there is institutionalised normalisation of coercive endogamy, Hindus should introspect the tenets of the faith that exists in the mainstream narrative. Legislative measures won’t suffice reforms in Hinduism as long as it is in tandem with the resolute of Hindus to seek reform.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Retail Binge for the Mental Twinge</title><link href="/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Retail Binge for the Mental Twinge" /><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;They say, “When the going gets tough, the tough go shopping.” This is more commonly known as &lt;em&gt;Retail Therapy&lt;/em&gt;. It is a phenomenon where people shop to improve one’s disposition and raise spirits. People in distress often resort to this as a source of solace. A study published in the journal &lt;em&gt;Psychology and Marketing&lt;/em&gt; states that retail therapy has a lasting positive effect on mood. While its findings pointed out that these are impulsive purchases, the survey suggested that feelings of guilt or regret were not associated among the respondents.&amp;nbsp;The name in itself is ironic. Shopping is a concept deeply rooted in materialism. As its positive impact is temporary, it does not qualify as a ‘therapy’ in the medical sense. However, it is a fairly popular phrase used around the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In a 2001 survey conducted by the European Union, it was found that 33% of the shoppers surveyed had a “high level of addiction to rash buying”. The study also revealed that ‘binge purchasing’ was most common among the Scottish youth. Another study of 1,000 American adults, conducted in 2013, detected that more than half of the respondents indulged in retail therapy. It also threw light on the gender aspect of the practice, stating that it is more common among women than men. It was found that 64.9% of women and 38.9% of men binge purchased while women mostly bought clothing, men indulged in ‘comfort food’. This was further reinforced by the Youngstown State University with similar male-female percentages, showing that relief from stress was the most common reason behind the practice. A more adverse extension of retail therapy is Oniomania or Compulsive Buying Disorder, which is an obsession with shopping, resulting in serious financial and mental consequences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Whys behind the Comfort Buys&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While stress, anxiety and sadness are a part of daily life, they can be tackled through other means such as reaching out to others, practicing yoga, mindfulness and meditation, journaling, exercising and consulting experts in more severe cases. Despite there being these solutions, which on an average are cheaper than shopping, why do people indulge in purchasing things to boost their mood? To understand the causes behind retail therapy, the behavioral aspect of individuals needs to be analysed in a twofold manner. Even though, at first glance, these reasons seem simple — associated with daily life, a deeper analysis suggests that the root cause can be traced back to psychological theory.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Firstly, we examine the relatively straightforward causes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;When everything goes wrong and nothing falls into place as you imagined it to, how do you feel? Out of control, right? Thus, one of the reasons people indulge in retail therapy is that shopping is a coping mechanism that helps people feel more in control. From deciding where to shop, to choosing what to purchase, it allows people to exercise autonomy and make decisions. In my personal opinion, shopping can also make one feel a sense of achievement. Utilising good offers and deals, applying coupons to get discounts and sometimes even getting goods for free certainly makes one feel happier as they ‘save’ along with fulfilling a guilty pleasure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Secondly, retail therapy can be a useful mechanism for smooth transitions of life as it enables people to envisage their lives post such changes. For instance, people often shop excessively before they are going to live alone for the first time, shifting to a new house, getting married or having a baby. Shopping may ease anxiety by making people feel more in control by helping them to prepare themselves for such huge transitions through the process of ‘visualisation’, which is a process that boosts performance, confidence and reduces anxiety.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another way in which retail therapy boosts mood is through a pleasant gush of creativity. Specifically, clothing of various kinds of colors and textures, accessories like jewelry, footwear, bags, sunglasses, etc, home decor items may induce a positive breeze of art and aesthetics. For example, the arrival of a new outfit may stir your creative juices in thinking about what shoes, jewelry and bag to pair it up with. This may certainly bring about a calmness in a way similar to art therapy, a well-known method of healing and reducing stress.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Some people treat shopping, both online and offline as a source of refreshment from the humdrum of daily life. Being a mindless activity, it enables people to relax and take some time off from their sources of stress. This form may vary from window shopping to scrolling on an online website or going to a shopping-mall for a break.&amp;nbsp;Yet another reason behind binge-purchasing may be the need to ‘feel connected’. For instance, one may shop for a sweater with a snowman or bells, candies and wreaths for decoration during Christmas, to feel more socially connected to the festival. Or someone may shop for a beret before visiting Paris to feel a part of the culture of the fashion capital. Thus, retail therapy may help individuals to feel closer to society and culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An extensive scrutiny of the idea suggests that the root cause lies in Sigmund Freud’s Pleasure Principle of psychology. The principle claims that individuals instinctively seek immediate pleasure to avoid experiencing feelings of stress, pain and sadness. In the context of impulsive purchasing, the principle fits well, as it is only a short term coping mechanism rooted in instant relief from stress. As compared to the Freudian Reality Principle, the Pleasure Principle is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inability of individuals to defer immediate gratification of certain desires and wants that rationality and reality may disallow.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sadness Cycle&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even though retail therapy eases the anxiety and pain in people’s lives, such a positive impact may be short-lived. While retail therapy can be supported by psychological reasoning, Economics does not go hand-in-hand with the concept due to its assumption of rationality among all individuals. From the point of view of rationality, the problems of running out of budget and debts arise due to limited financial resources. Impulsive overspending may lead people to become even more anxious and distressed due to the inability of paying bills and lacking a sound financial base, in the long run. A rough patch after having run out of budget may seem more dramatic and difficult to handle, due to a lack of finance to purchase something to feel better. In desperate times like these, individuals addicted to the method, may resort to desperate measures like taking loans from others or stealing. This might be complemented with feelings of guilt due to unrealistically high expenditure patterns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, retail therapy, to an obsessive degree can lead to reverse effects by introducing a cycle of stress and anxiety for an individual rather than helping one fight the tough times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ‘Viral’ Remedy&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With the Coronavirus pandemic hitting the world, people across the globe felt paralysed due to being restricted homes all the time. While this altered the work culture among people, the norms of schooling among students and put a halt to dining out, it had an impact on the shoppers. Research suggests that elements appealing to an individual’s senses, like aroma, music, a creative arrangement of products in a store, temperature contribute to the experience of shoppers. Unfortunately, with the lockdown implemented across the world, this ‘sensory’ experience was no longer available. As a result of this, one would expect sales to fall. However, the online retail industry led to a different turn of events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to &lt;em&gt;Forbes&lt;/em&gt;, as of March 2020, several online retail categories experienced a 74% year over year increase in sales, as compared to March 2018. Some of the top categories that saw a surge in the sale are home goods like furniture and home decor items and athletic and loungewear. While it may be argued that these categories resonate more with individuals in the current scenario due to the need to stay home, it must be noted that none of these items are essentials. Thus, it can be suggested that individuals binge purchased during the pandemic to escape the fears and stress of the situation and its uncertainty, thereby serving as a recent instance of retail therapy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact of retail therapy on an individual’s life depends upon the degree of engagement. On one hand, retail therapy in the form of window shopping, purchasing with adherence to one’s budget or buying pre-planned things can help to reduce stress and sadness both in the short term and long run. On the other hand, if the simple habit intensifies to become an addiction, it results in adverse problems which in turn brings more distress, thereby defeating the purpose of the ‘therapy’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">They say, “When the going gets tough, the tough go shopping.” This is more commonly known as Retail Therapy. It is a phenomenon where people shop to improve one’s disposition and raise spirits. People in distress often resort to this as a source of solace. A study published in the journal Psychology and Marketing states that retail therapy has a lasting positive effect on mood. While its findings pointed out that these are impulsive purchases, the survey suggested that feelings of guilt or regret were not associated among the respondents.&amp;nbsp;The name in itself is ironic. Shopping is a concept deeply rooted in materialism. As its positive impact is temporary, it does not qualify as a ‘therapy’ in the medical sense. However, it is a fairly popular phrase used around the world.&amp;nbsp; In a 2001 survey conducted by the European Union, it was found that 33% of the shoppers surveyed had a “high level of addiction to rash buying”. The study also revealed that ‘binge purchasing’ was most common among the Scottish youth. Another study of 1,000 American adults, conducted in 2013, detected that more than half of the respondents indulged in retail therapy. It also threw light on the gender aspect of the practice, stating that it is more common among women than men. It was found that 64.9% of women and 38.9% of men binge purchased while women mostly bought clothing, men indulged in ‘comfort food’. This was further reinforced by the Youngstown State University with similar male-female percentages, showing that relief from stress was the most common reason behind the practice. A more adverse extension of retail therapy is Oniomania or Compulsive Buying Disorder, which is an obsession with shopping, resulting in serious financial and mental consequences.&amp;nbsp; The Whys behind the Comfort Buys&amp;nbsp; While stress, anxiety and sadness are a part of daily life, they can be tackled through other means such as reaching out to others, practicing yoga, mindfulness and meditation, journaling, exercising and consulting experts in more severe cases. Despite there being these solutions, which on an average are cheaper than shopping, why do people indulge in purchasing things to boost their mood? To understand the causes behind retail therapy, the behavioral aspect of individuals needs to be analysed in a twofold manner. Even though, at first glance, these reasons seem simple — associated with daily life, a deeper analysis suggests that the root cause can be traced back to psychological theory.&amp;nbsp; Firstly, we examine the relatively straightforward causes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;When everything goes wrong and nothing falls into place as you imagined it to, how do you feel? Out of control, right? Thus, one of the reasons people indulge in retail therapy is that shopping is a coping mechanism that helps people feel more in control. From deciding where to shop, to choosing what to purchase, it allows people to exercise autonomy and make decisions. In my personal opinion, shopping can also make one feel a sense of achievement. Utilising good offers and deals, applying coupons to get discounts and sometimes even getting goods for free certainly makes one feel happier as they ‘save’ along with fulfilling a guilty pleasure.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, retail therapy can be a useful mechanism for smooth transitions of life as it enables people to envisage their lives post such changes. For instance, people often shop excessively before they are going to live alone for the first time, shifting to a new house, getting married or having a baby. Shopping may ease anxiety by making people feel more in control by helping them to prepare themselves for such huge transitions through the process of ‘visualisation’, which is a process that boosts performance, confidence and reduces anxiety.&amp;nbsp; Another way in which retail therapy boosts mood is through a pleasant gush of creativity. Specifically, clothing of various kinds of colors and textures, accessories like jewelry, footwear, bags, sunglasses, etc, home decor items may induce a positive breeze of art and aesthetics. For example, the arrival of a new outfit may stir your creative juices in thinking about what shoes, jewelry and bag to pair it up with. This may certainly bring about a calmness in a way similar to art therapy, a well-known method of healing and reducing stress.&amp;nbsp; Some people treat shopping, both online and offline as a source of refreshment from the humdrum of daily life. Being a mindless activity, it enables people to relax and take some time off from their sources of stress. This form may vary from window shopping to scrolling on an online website or going to a shopping-mall for a break.&amp;nbsp;Yet another reason behind binge-purchasing may be the need to ‘feel connected’. For instance, one may shop for a sweater with a snowman or bells, candies and wreaths for decoration during Christmas, to feel more socially connected to the festival. Or someone may shop for a beret before visiting Paris to feel a part of the culture of the fashion capital. Thus, retail therapy may help individuals to feel closer to society and culture.&amp;nbsp; An extensive scrutiny of the idea suggests that the root cause lies in Sigmund Freud’s Pleasure Principle of psychology. The principle claims that individuals instinctively seek immediate pleasure to avoid experiencing feelings of stress, pain and sadness. In the context of impulsive purchasing, the principle fits well, as it is only a short term coping mechanism rooted in instant relief from stress. As compared to the Freudian Reality Principle, the Pleasure Principle is the inability of individuals to defer immediate gratification of certain desires and wants that rationality and reality may disallow.&amp;nbsp; The Sadness Cycle&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Even though retail therapy eases the anxiety and pain in people’s lives, such a positive impact may be short-lived. While retail therapy can be supported by psychological reasoning, Economics does not go hand-in-hand with the concept due to its assumption of rationality among all individuals. From the point of view of rationality, the problems of running out of budget and debts arise due to limited financial resources. Impulsive overspending may lead people to become even more anxious and distressed due to the inability of paying bills and lacking a sound financial base, in the long run. A rough patch after having run out of budget may seem more dramatic and difficult to handle, due to a lack of finance to purchase something to feel better. In desperate times like these, individuals addicted to the method, may resort to desperate measures like taking loans from others or stealing. This might be complemented with feelings of guilt due to unrealistically high expenditure patterns.&amp;nbsp; Thus, retail therapy, to an obsessive degree can lead to reverse effects by introducing a cycle of stress and anxiety for an individual rather than helping one fight the tough times.&amp;nbsp; The ‘Viral’ Remedy&amp;nbsp; With the Coronavirus pandemic hitting the world, people across the globe felt paralysed due to being restricted homes all the time. While this altered the work culture among people, the norms of schooling among students and put a halt to dining out, it had an impact on the shoppers. Research suggests that elements appealing to an individual’s senses, like aroma, music, a creative arrangement of products in a store, temperature contribute to the experience of shoppers. Unfortunately, with the lockdown implemented across the world, this ‘sensory’ experience was no longer available. As a result of this, one would expect sales to fall. However, the online retail industry led to a different turn of events. According to Forbes, as of March 2020, several online retail categories experienced a 74% year over year increase in sales, as compared to March 2018. Some of the top categories that saw a surge in the sale are home goods like furniture and home decor items and athletic and loungewear. While it may be argued that these categories resonate more with individuals in the current scenario due to the need to stay home, it must be noted that none of these items are essentials. Thus, it can be suggested that individuals binge purchased during the pandemic to escape the fears and stress of the situation and its uncertainty, thereby serving as a recent instance of retail therapy.&amp;nbsp; The impact of retail therapy on an individual’s life depends upon the degree of engagement. On one hand, retail therapy in the form of window shopping, purchasing with adherence to one’s budget or buying pre-planned things can help to reduce stress and sadness both in the short term and long run. On the other hand, if the simple habit intensifies to become an addiction, it results in adverse problems which in turn brings more distress, thereby defeating the purpose of the ‘therapy’.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">11.11 - The Singles’ Date</title><link href="/11-11-The-Singles-Date" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="11.11 - The Singles’ Date" /><published>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/11-11-The-Singles-Date</id><content type="html" xml:base="/11-11-The-Singles-Date">&lt;p&gt;China is one of the world’s biggest powerhouses in innovation and technology. While the country has its own set of laws, it has a holiday that not many people around the globe know about- the &lt;em&gt;Singles’ Day&lt;/em&gt;! It might sound peculiar, but it is a huge part of modern Chinese culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Singles’ Day&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Double 11&lt;/em&gt;, originally called&lt;em&gt; Bachelors’ Day&lt;/em&gt;, is celebrated on November 11. It is a Chinese commercial holiday to celebrate being romantically unattached and paradoxically, turns out to be the largest physical retail and online shopping day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative behind the Singles’ Day is pretty nice. It originated at Nanjing University in 1993. A group of lonely, yet positive students decided that instead of lamenting their lack of a significant other, they would celebrate being single. The reasoning? 11.11 looks like four, single sticks, strung together trying to make the most out of their time. The anti-Valentine’s Day celebration of singledom caught on and spread across universities throughout China, generally characterised by fun and harmless events. With the widespread use of social media, the day has become increasingly popular within contemporary Chinese culture and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alibaba’s Blockbuster Growth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alibaba’s co-founder Jack Ma instituted the first Singles’ Day sale in 2009, laying the foundation for the highest-grossing shopping day of the year in the world. In 2012, the e-commerce company officially trademarked ‘Double 11’. Next in 2017, Alibaba’s mobile wallet app Alipay broke the record for the greatest number of transactions per second, whoa!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not be Singles’ Day without Alibaba having some great deals available. This year, the company’s annual sales frenzy broke records again by raking in roughly $75 billion. The total includes an earlier three-day period that was added to boost post-pandemic sales. The company claimed that, compared to the same timeframe as last year, this year’s haul represents an increase of 26%. Chinese consumers, who already buy about 30% of the nation’s retail purchase online, have become more reliant on e-commerce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, Alibaba also held a ‘Go Global 11.11 Pitch Fest’ aimed at small and medium-sized US brands, offering them a chance to be spotlighted during the event. Besides that, the company has been trying to involve more foreign brands globally. In 2019, Americans commanded the second-highest sales among importers, behind Japan but ahead of South Korea, Australia, and Germany.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, Alibaba makes stupendous efforts to hype up Double 11 with its extravagant, rather over-the-top countdown gala. It featured appearances from celebrities such as Nicole Kidman, Kobe Bryant, Scarlett Johansson, Mariah Carey, Pharrell Williams, Miranda Kerr, Jessie J, Lionel Messi, and Taylor Swift in the preceding years. Pop star Katy Perry, who has performed at the event before, made an appearance at the company’s gala this season, albeit via a live stream, as travel restrictions on outside visitors remain in place in China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though many other online platforms and stores take part in Singles’ Day, it is still closely tied to Alibaba.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crazy Sale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For brands and retailers scrambling to recover from months of shuttered shops and consumers hunkered down indoors, the profitable Chinese shopper is a much-needed bright spot. It is estimated that the participation of luxury brands has doubled on Singles’ Day, as millions of Chinese who have been unable to travel overseas on shopping trips go online for what experts are dubbing ‘revenge spending’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the buzz of Singles’ Day led the retailers worldwide to opt for special promotions to boost sales. &lt;em&gt;Uniqlo&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Foot Locker&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Best Buy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Steam&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Target&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Expedia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Topman&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Brooklinen&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Levi’s&lt;/em&gt;, and numerous other companies offered massive deals and discounts, orbiting the holiday. Three million workers, aided by 4,000 planes and ships got ready for the world’s biggest online sale in the current year- with ‘revenge spending’ tipping to be one of this year’s biggest trends.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey by market research firm &lt;em&gt;Oliver Wyman&lt;/em&gt; found out that 86% of Chinese consumers were willing to spend the same as or more than what they did during last year’s Singles’ Day. The remaining 14% of survey respondents said that they had spent less on Singles’ Day, because of the unprecedented times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On The Outside&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singles’ Day has become the most lucrative shopping holiday in several places outside China as well. The holiday has particularly grown in Southeast Asia, with customers in Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam, who are the recipient of the huge discounts offered by Alibaba’s subsidiary Lazada. In the United Kingdom, Singles’ Day is marked on March 11. It was initiated by a group of internationally recognised dating experts to help singles embrace themselves. Furthermore, Swedish Electronic retailer &lt;em&gt;Elgiganten&lt;/em&gt; promoted a Singles’ Day campaign in Norway before implementing it in the other Nordic countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MediaMarkt&lt;/em&gt;, a German Company, also promotes this day in its stores. Conversely, Belgian &lt;em&gt;MediaMarkt&lt;/em&gt; also participates but the reactions have been negative. It is because November 11 is the anniversary of the Armistice of 1918 that ended the First World War.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, awareness of Singles’ Day in New Zealand is still relatively low. According to a survey by &lt;em&gt;PriceSpy&lt;/em&gt;, around 73% of Kiwis have never heard of this day, with just 12% of Kiwis reporting to have brought something during the world’s biggest shopping bonanza.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singles’ Day will continue to grow in importance for retailers outside of China, particularly in the United Kingdom, which last year grew their discounting assortment to mirror the United States. In the light of the pandemic and feel of 2020, upbeat marketing angles that touch on celebrating and treating yourself are drawing attention globally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Antidote to Valentine’s Day&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally on Singles’ Day, people buy things, take themselves out for dinner, watch movies, sheepishly ruin dates, hang out with their other single friends and delve into the gratifying embrace of self-love. This phenomenon of retail therapy has resulted in oodles of sales, easily surpassing Black Friday and Cyber Monday combined.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, it is fun getting gifts on your birthday, Christmas and on other occasions- but how can people know what you actually want? On this day, you get to shop for yourself. I’m not just talking about buying yourself flowers or a decent meal. It is the day to show yourself some real love and appreciation. Go on, indulge. Splurge on those jeans you have been eying, or fancy wine club membership- you have earned it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retailers all over the world are instigating exclusive, singles-oriented deals in Alibaba’s footsteps. Grab the benefit of special promotions- ticket for 1 to Fiji? Yes, please.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samakshi Garg</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">China is one of the world’s biggest powerhouses in innovation and technology. While the country has its own set of laws, it has a holiday that not many people around the globe know about- the Singles’ Day! It might sound peculiar, but it is a huge part of modern Chinese culture.&amp;nbsp; The Singles’ Day or Double 11, originally called Bachelors’ Day, is celebrated on November 11. It is a Chinese commercial holiday to celebrate being romantically unattached and paradoxically, turns out to be the largest physical retail and online shopping day of the year. Genesis The narrative behind the Singles’ Day is pretty nice. It originated at Nanjing University in 1993. A group of lonely, yet positive students decided that instead of lamenting their lack of a significant other, they would celebrate being single. The reasoning? 11.11 looks like four, single sticks, strung together trying to make the most out of their time. The anti-Valentine’s Day celebration of singledom caught on and spread across universities throughout China, generally characterised by fun and harmless events. With the widespread use of social media, the day has become increasingly popular within contemporary Chinese culture and society.&amp;nbsp; Alibaba’s Blockbuster Growth Alibaba’s co-founder Jack Ma instituted the first Singles’ Day sale in 2009, laying the foundation for the highest-grossing shopping day of the year in the world. In 2012, the e-commerce company officially trademarked ‘Double 11’. Next in 2017, Alibaba’s mobile wallet app Alipay broke the record for the greatest number of transactions per second, whoa!&amp;nbsp; It would not be Singles’ Day without Alibaba having some great deals available. This year, the company’s annual sales frenzy broke records again by raking in roughly $75 billion. The total includes an earlier three-day period that was added to boost post-pandemic sales. The company claimed that, compared to the same timeframe as last year, this year’s haul represents an increase of 26%. Chinese consumers, who already buy about 30% of the nation’s retail purchase online, have become more reliant on e-commerce.&amp;nbsp; This year, Alibaba also held a ‘Go Global 11.11 Pitch Fest’ aimed at small and medium-sized US brands, offering them a chance to be spotlighted during the event. Besides that, the company has been trying to involve more foreign brands globally. In 2019, Americans commanded the second-highest sales among importers, behind Japan but ahead of South Korea, Australia, and Germany.&amp;nbsp; Undoubtedly, Alibaba makes stupendous efforts to hype up Double 11 with its extravagant, rather over-the-top countdown gala. It featured appearances from celebrities such as Nicole Kidman, Kobe Bryant, Scarlett Johansson, Mariah Carey, Pharrell Williams, Miranda Kerr, Jessie J, Lionel Messi, and Taylor Swift in the preceding years. Pop star Katy Perry, who has performed at the event before, made an appearance at the company’s gala this season, albeit via a live stream, as travel restrictions on outside visitors remain in place in China.&amp;nbsp; Even though many other online platforms and stores take part in Singles’ Day, it is still closely tied to Alibaba.&amp;nbsp; Crazy Sale For brands and retailers scrambling to recover from months of shuttered shops and consumers hunkered down indoors, the profitable Chinese shopper is a much-needed bright spot. It is estimated that the participation of luxury brands has doubled on Singles’ Day, as millions of Chinese who have been unable to travel overseas on shopping trips go online for what experts are dubbing ‘revenge spending’.&amp;nbsp; Unsurprisingly, the buzz of Singles’ Day led the retailers worldwide to opt for special promotions to boost sales. Uniqlo, Foot Locker, Best Buy, Steam, Target, Alibaba, Expedia, Topman, Brooklinen, Levi’s, and numerous other companies offered massive deals and discounts, orbiting the holiday. Three million workers, aided by 4,000 planes and ships got ready for the world’s biggest online sale in the current year- with ‘revenge spending’ tipping to be one of this year’s biggest trends.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A survey by market research firm Oliver Wyman found out that 86% of Chinese consumers were willing to spend the same as or more than what they did during last year’s Singles’ Day. The remaining 14% of survey respondents said that they had spent less on Singles’ Day, because of the unprecedented times.&amp;nbsp; On The Outside Singles’ Day has become the most lucrative shopping holiday in several places outside China as well. The holiday has particularly grown in Southeast Asia, with customers in Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam, who are the recipient of the huge discounts offered by Alibaba’s subsidiary Lazada. In the United Kingdom, Singles’ Day is marked on March 11. It was initiated by a group of internationally recognised dating experts to help singles embrace themselves. Furthermore, Swedish Electronic retailer Elgiganten promoted a Singles’ Day campaign in Norway before implementing it in the other Nordic countries.&amp;nbsp; MediaMarkt, a German Company, also promotes this day in its stores. Conversely, Belgian MediaMarkt also participates but the reactions have been negative. It is because November 11 is the anniversary of the Armistice of 1918 that ended the First World War.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, awareness of Singles’ Day in New Zealand is still relatively low. According to a survey by PriceSpy, around 73% of Kiwis have never heard of this day, with just 12% of Kiwis reporting to have brought something during the world’s biggest shopping bonanza.&amp;nbsp; Singles’ Day will continue to grow in importance for retailers outside of China, particularly in the United Kingdom, which last year grew their discounting assortment to mirror the United States. In the light of the pandemic and feel of 2020, upbeat marketing angles that touch on celebrating and treating yourself are drawing attention globally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; An Antidote to Valentine’s Day&amp;nbsp; Traditionally on Singles’ Day, people buy things, take themselves out for dinner, watch movies, sheepishly ruin dates, hang out with their other single friends and delve into the gratifying embrace of self-love. This phenomenon of retail therapy has resulted in oodles of sales, easily surpassing Black Friday and Cyber Monday combined.&amp;nbsp; Certainly, it is fun getting gifts on your birthday, Christmas and on other occasions- but how can people know what you actually want? On this day, you get to shop for yourself. I’m not just talking about buying yourself flowers or a decent meal. It is the day to show yourself some real love and appreciation. Go on, indulge. Splurge on those jeans you have been eying, or fancy wine club membership- you have earned it.&amp;nbsp; Retailers all over the world are instigating exclusive, singles-oriented deals in Alibaba’s footsteps. Grab the benefit of special promotions- ticket for 1 to Fiji? Yes, please.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge</title><link href="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge" /><published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge">&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan. The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF. India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp; This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma. However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.</summary></entry></feed>