<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-24T20:00:28+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy.</title><link href="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy." /><published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths">&lt;p&gt;From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least  400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the criminal context, this leads to some bold and difficult questions that have left even the Behavioral Science Unit of the FBI scratching their heads. How could we, by asking the right set of questions, successfully identify what kind of person is likely to commit a crime? How can we understand his possible motive behind his crime? And, most importantly, can we preempt the criminal’s future course of action? In examining these questions, the term this Behavioral Science Unit coined for the perpetrators of repeated crimes, i.e. ‘serial killer’ is now cult famous. These were the people who would go on a certain form of a spree, committing possibly similar or even dissimilar acts in order to prevent any trace leading up to them. The Unit was exploring how to connect these actions and how to develop a fool-proof method of doing so. Moreover, the Unit wanted to distinguish someone who just kills people and someone who does that because he believes the devil commands him to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were too many questions which could have been asked and none of them could have had any proper answers. But John E Douglas, a member of the Behavioral Science Unit, notes that there was a lot of fruit borne out of their investigations and rightly so. Douglas and his colleagues spent years interviewing criminals across penitentiaries all over the country in a span of more than a decade. Their subjects included Ted Bundy, the killer of several innocent girls, John Wayne Gacy, the infamous “Killer Clown”, who is also thought of to be the inspiration for IT’s antagonist—a killer clown called Pennywise. The Unit interviewed the “Son of Sam”, David Berkowitz, who claimed that he shot people in cold blood because his cat – a manifestation of Satan himself – asked him to do so. They also interviewed Ed Kemper, a ‘giant’ in all literal senses with an extraordinary IQ of 145, who was convicted of killing his own mother, grandparents and 3 others whilst engaging in necrophilia with their bodies. The insight the Behavioral Science Unit gained from these studies influenced criminal profiling and psychopathic documentation over the years, giving rise to new fields within psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinctive features, John Douglas noted, that were possessed by most of these subjects was an incessant amount of ego. Douglas compared Ted Kaczynski, the Unabomber who was an extraordinarily intelligent criminal, and Dennis Rader, a comparatively less-educated one, and said that both their downfalls were due to their narcissism. Douglas contended that a heightened sense of ego, a lack of remorse and all such associated feelings, innate aggression, a traumatic childhood, and a poor, sexually malignant upbringing were all factors that could contribute to a person’s choices of insanity and crimes. He wrote his critically-acclaimed book, The Mindhunter, on his studies which till date serves as a manual for some at the Quantico, which is the training ground for FBI agents in the US. This book explores all of his findings and delves deeper into the psyche of how a psychopath could possibly be thinking in accordance with Freudian psycho-sexual stimulation or violence-induced arousal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting fact, however, is that Douglas points out that it is wrong to believe that all psychopaths are just remorseless, guiltless, killing machines. He says that there is more complexity to them than that. Psychopaths have a lopsided view of emotions and morality, it’s not that they don’t ‘feel’, just that they feel very differently from the way most people do. Their ability to take cold, completely unemotional decisions is one that is cherished by most CEOs in today’s world. The only difference between psychopathic killers and corporate executives is the presence of external factors like a tough childhood, poverty, trauma etc., which makes the former a threat to society. As it is posed by another psychopath, albeit fictional in this case, Hannibal Lecter from the series of books by Thomas Harris, the human mind has an unfathomable level of variability and complexity. Who knows for sure what makes the Bundys and the Kempers the people they are? All we know is that they’re not born so, they are made to be so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least 400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People’s Pain</title><link href="/Cry-Me-A-River" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People's Pain" /><published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Cry-Me-A-River</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Cry-Me-A-River">&lt;p&gt;While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have to look much further, one search on Google and I was met with my favourite word ever: Schadenfreude. Oxford Dictionary defines Schadenfreude as pleasure derived by someone from another person’s misfortune. The word is borrowed from German and is a compound of Schaden, “damage, harm”, and Freude, ‘joy’. “Harm-Joy”, that’s the only equivalent in English one can find for this word. In fact, in 1926, a journalist in The Spectator asserted that “there is no English word for Schadenfreude because there is no such feeling here.” We shall see about that, UK, we shall. One can mistake Sadism for it, but sadism has an implication of infliction, while Schadenfreude is about merely observing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English might be falling behind on finding a word for this feeling, others? Not so much. The Japanese have a saying: “The misfortunes of others taste like honey.” The French speak of ‘joiemaligne’, a diabolical delight in other people’s suffering. The Danish talk of ‘skadefryd’, and the Dutch of ‘leedvermaak’. In Hebrew, enjoying other people’s catastrophes is ‘simcha la‑ed’, in Mandarin, ‘xìng‑zāi‑lè‑huò’, in Serbo-Croat it is ‘zlùradōst’, and in Russian ‘zloradstvo’. More than 2,000 years ago, Romans spoke of ‘malevolentia’. Earlier still, the Greeks described ‘epichairekakia’ (literally epi, over, chairo, rejoice, kakia, disgrace). “To see others suffer does one good,” wrote the philosopher Friedrich Nietzsche, “To make others suffer even more so. This is a hard saying, but a mighty, human, all-too-human principle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about the emotion, how does it even manifest itself? Exactly like joy does: gleam in our eyes, a wide smile, or perhaps a small one, one may even consider it a smirk. In a laboratory in Würzburg in Germany in 2015, thirty-two football fans agreed to have electromyography pads attached to their faces, which would measure their smiles and frowns while watching TV clips of successful and unsuccessful football penalties by the German team, and by their arch-rivals, the Dutch. The psychologists found that when the Dutch missed a goal, the German fans’ smiles appeared more quickly and were broader than when the German team scored a goal themselves. The smiles of Schadenfreude and joy are indistinguishable except in one crucial respect: we smile more at the failures of our enemies than at our own success. We have used humiliation and the failures of other people to make ourselves happy for a long time. We often use said emotion to work in our favour, people use self-deprecating stories in novice situations to evoke ease amongst the rest and present themselves as non-threatening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word was first mentioned in German in the 1740’s, and in English writing in 1853. Richard Chenevix Trench mentioned it in his book on philology On the Study of Words. For Trench, however, the mere existence of the word Schadenfreude was unholy and fearful, a “mournful record of the strange wickednesses which the genius of man, so fertile in evil, has invented.” Ever since, several have spoken it and have eagerly adopted the word, associating it with a range of pleasures, from hilarity to self-righteous vindication, and from triumph to relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five common themes to be found in the idea of Schadenfreude. The first being that Schadenfreude is usually thought of as an opportunistic pleasure, felt when we stumble across another’s misfortune which we have not caused ourselves. The Hollywood villain gloating when Bond is caught by his dastardly plot is not experiencing Schadenfreude, but sadistic pleasure. By contrast, the sidekick who sniggers as a Hollywood villain is accidentally foiled by his own dastardly plot when he trips and presses the self-destruct button is enjoying Schadenfreude. The second is as a furtive emotion, outbursts of merriment at another’s catastrophes are generally a sign of great villain-ness. Shylock can barely contain himself on learning that his rival Antonio has lost a cargo ship at sea: “I thank God, I thank God. Is’t true, is’t true?” We might be worried not just about looking malicious, but that our Schadenfreude exposes our other flaws too—our pettiness, our envy, our feelings of inadequacy. However, the third feature is that we often feel entitled to it when the other person’s suffering can be construed as a comeuppance—a deserved punishment for being smug or hypocritical or for breaking the law. While it is unlikely that we’d enjoy our moral superiority to their face, gloating is generally permissible at a safe distance. Fourth, we may see it as a form of respite—the failures of others appease our own envy and inadequacy and give us a much-needed feeling of superiority. And just as satire is only funny when it punches up, we are most comfortable sniggering at the failures of those more wealthy, attractive and talented than us. Fifth, often thought of as glee at minor discomforts and gaffes rather than at dire tragedies and deaths, we are willing to see celebrities, or people from the remote past, endure horrors that would dismay us if they were happening now or to our friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, Schadenfreude has been talked about more often than ever. Now I don’t know what it says about our generation, i.e. if we’re more aware than ever or if Schadenfreude is a ‘problem’. A great multitude of researches exist to explain to us how it works, what ages experience it more, is it okay to experience it in the first place, and if not, how not to feel it? As somewhat of a researcher, I can conclude that the latter questions are yet to receive a clear answer. While everybody experiences it every now and then, the literature shows that people with the traits of Machiavellianism, narcissism, or psychopathy, together known as the “dark triad”, feel Schadenfreude more often. Some researchers propose that feeling Schadenfreude requires us to dehumanise the person whose failure we are laughing at. They further suggest dehumanisation might be the fundamental aspect of this emotion, though further research is needed before that can be proven. They sure sound dark, especially because Schadenfreude is such a universal emotion (this had me sweating, I can’t lie). But they justify it by suggesting that dehumanisation occurs more often than most would like to think. The researchers explain that people with low self-esteem are more likely to feel Schadenfreude when they see other people fail. This is because the success of others can be a threat to their sense of self and seeing the mighty fall can be a comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s age, Schadenfreude is all around us, it’s in the way we do politics, how we treat celebrities, and in online fail videos. We felt it when NASA lost a $125 million Mars orbiter because half the team was using imperial measurements, and the other half, metric. We felt it when Trump walked the ramp to his private flight with toilet paper stuck to his right shoe. We feel it when the self-righteous satisfaction of hypocrites is thoroughly exposed, when a celebrity is caught cheating on his/her significant other. You hear it when Bob Dylan sings ‘Like a Rolling Stone’, or when Jessie J flaunts her success in ‘Who’s Laughing Now’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Arthur Schopenhauer called Schadenfreude “an infallible sign of a thoroughly bad heart and profound moral worthlessness,” the very worst trait in human nature. There are often comparisons to how the emotion is on the flip side of empathy. Debates muster up enough evidence for the same but not enough for the debate to be over. Twenty-first-century humanists who regard empathy as a “natural” response under threat in a frenetic, atomistic modern world find Schadenfreude awkward too. It has variously been called the “absence of empathy,” the “opposite of empathy” and “empathy’s shadow,” casting the two as fundamentally incompatible. Some suggest that only a few of us enjoy other people’s pain for its own sake, but more often because we have judged it deserved or useful in some way, evidence not strictly of malice but of our desire to preserve a moral balance. Schadenfreude has been told to be beneficial by some, a quick win which alleviates inferiority or envy; a way of bonding over the failure of a boss or smug senior colleague. And above all, it is a testament to our capacity for emotional flexibility, as opposed to moral rigidity, and our ability to hold apparently contradictory thoughts and feelings in the mind simultaneously. If asked, I’d say Schadenfreude and sympathy are not either/or responses as is sometimes suggested, but can be felt all at once, but, that is for all of us to seek for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schadenfreude has become a part of how we are engaging with everyone online – it creates camaraderie and political momentum. The big question for moral philosophers, now, is whether by enjoying Schadenfreude you are endangering empathy, trust, and a good society. Both ancient and early modern descriptions of comic enjoyment acknowledge proximity to cruelty, but they usually stop short of admitting kinship. The same goes for Schadenfreude, it may well be rested in the bed of cruelty but what connections may we retain? We may well be living in an Age of Schadenfreude, and fear that this emotion is leading us astray. But as with all emotions, condemning it only gets you so far. What we really need is to think afresh about the work this much-maligned emotion does for us, and what it tells us about our relationships with ourselves and each other. The brain will always choose pleasure over fear, always. Understanding why you feel what you feel creates an advantage and opportunity to respond with more thought than impulsivity. As a very smart lady once said, “Don’t reach for the halo too soon. You have plenty of time to enjoy yourself, even a little maliciously sometimes, before you settle down to being a saint.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World</title><link href="/Christendom-Today" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World" /><published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Christendom-Today</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Christendom-Today">&lt;p&gt;There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity certainly is a house divided. The Protestant Reformation played a major role in this (and the proliferation of Protestant denominations continues to prove this) but it also made the Catholic Church wake up from centuries of semi-stagnation, resulting in a major resurgence of traditionalism, as we see in the great world missions of the Counter-Reformation. Indeed, the Jesuits – zealous evangelists and promoters of the Roman faith – probably wouldn’t have existed hadn’t it been for the polarising catalyst that was Martin Luther.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those divisions haven’t yet come to an end, rather Christianity is even more diverse than it was in the 17th century. Thankfully, the different bodies calling themselves Christian are reaching out to each other in a spirit of sincerity and dialogue and are repenting the terrible sectarian bloodshed that so often categorised post-Enlightenment Europe. But the various Christian ‘sects’ are still very different and continue to operate and influence the world in their own unique way. Let us begin with the largest group of all – the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The Spirit of Vatican II”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-20th century, the Catholic Church held a worldwide pastoral council called the Second Council of the Vatican, or – to put it simply – “Vatican II” (hereafter referred to as V2). Unlike previous councils, V2 never chose to define dogma or clarify church teaching – rather it wanted to bring about ecclesiastical reforms to be able to better respond to the new world of the 20th century. But many Catholics agree that V2 was an absolute disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V2 resulted in the sharp splintering of the Church. The liberals and the ‘modernists’ complain that it didn’t go far enough in eroding “medieval superstition”, while the conservatives argue that the ambiguous language in its documents creates a great danger for doctrinal error to be spread. In addition to these two groups, there are more than half-a-million traditionalist Catholics who reject it altogether, calling it a non-infallible “robber’s council” – the best example of this is the Priestly Society of St Pius X, with supporters around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, V2 has resulted in a change of attitude among many believers. Today, Catholics are much more focused on preaching about “social justice” than before. This is best seen in the lives of Mother Teresa and Oscar Romero, both saints of the Catholic Church, as well as in the current Pontiff, Pope Francis. The rise of the so-called “Liberation theology” has created a great impact in Latin America (particularly Brazil), with some calling it the “Marxist version of Catholicism”. The “left-wing Church” in this part of the world has played an instrumental role in protesting against totalitarian right-wing bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberation theologians contend that the root cause of poverty and social injustice is sin (the implication being that social justice cannot return unless people begin to lead saintly lives) and that the poor, the oppressed and the marginalized are the “privileged channels of God’s grace”. The result is that a direct link has been made between theology and social activism. To be a good Christian, one must fight against and oppose oppressive structures of power, say the Liberation theologians. While Liberation theology is certainly not a branch of Communism in any formal sense of the word, the similarity with Marxist rhetoric has, at times, concerned many conservatives, not least among them being Pope Emeritus Benedict XVI. This is very ironic because the Catholic Church of the 20th century was one of the most powerful anti-Communist forces in the world, with many (including New York Times bestselling author and scholar Paul Kengor) crediting Pope St John Paul II as having played an instrumental role in the fall of the Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luther’s Revenge: The Worldwide Resurgence of Evangelicalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelical Christianity is by far the most powerful and dynamic religious force in the world today. Evangelicalism is converting people by the hundreds of thousands. The best example of this is the late Baptist missionary Billy Grace, who preached to more than 3 billion people during his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelicalism is characterised by both simplicity and zeal. There is no Pope or central authority structure to dictate dogma – the Bible is the only rule. There is no long and boring liturgy as we see in Catholic and Orthodox Churches – rather, church services tend to have contemporary music that is very appealing to the youth. They are not led by old and haggard clerics barely able to even speak a word – on the contrary, their leaders tend to be charismatic, scholarly and lively. The sacramental emphasis is replaced by a much freer and fluid form of spirituality, and it is not uncommon to hear the phrase “Christianity is a relationship, not a religion”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the Christian apologists defending the veracity of Christian truth in the academia are also Evangelicals. William Lane Craig, Ravi Zacharias, NT Wright, Richard Bauckham, Michael F Bird, Craig Keener, Craig Blomberg, James DG Dunn, Alvin Plantinga – the list is very impressive indeed. Not only are these devoted (Evangelical) Christians eager to convert souls, they also represent the top brass of scholarship in their respective fields. For instance, William Lane Craig and Alvin Plantinga are one of the most cited scholars in the philosophy of religion, while Wright and Bauckham have both had an association with universities like Oxford and Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, Evangelical Christianity is very American, and very, very Republican. So, while Catholics seem to veer leftward, Evangelicals are solidly in support of capitalism and the notion of a culturally advanced Western Civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holy Mother Russia: The Re-Baptism of Rus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the fall of the USSR, the resurgence of Eastern Orthodoxy was all but inevitable. Today, the Moscow Patriarchate can be called the unofficial state religion of the Russian Federation. Now operating with Vladimir Putin’s open consent and cooperation, they are rebuilding Churches long destroyed and reconstructing schools that had been annihilated by anti-religious sentiment. In fact, some Orthodox followers and clergy are actively advocating the restoration of a Christian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodox Christians are very, well, ‘orthodox’. When the Pope visited Serbia, he was greeted by sloganeers protesting “the Papist heresy”. Even the Patriarch – while having met the Pope at the airport – refused to offer Mass with him. Similarly, Russia is cracking down on “fringe groups” – not least among them being the non-Trinitarian Jehovah’s Witnesses, who have had to face fierce persecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What animates these people? It a vision of the legendary Byzantium, an empire so wonderful that it may be fittingly called the kingdom of God on earth. When the ambassadors of Prince Vladimir of Kiev first saw the Latin Mass, they were not too impressed, but when they witnessed the Byzantine Divine Liturgy, they wrote back exclaiming that this was the most heavenly thing they had ever seen. In the Orthodox narrative, the Church of Rome fell into heresy when it started claiming for itself ecclesiastical supremacy. It was then excommunicated and replaced by the Church of Constantinople, the New Rome. And when Constantinople fell under the sword of Islam, God raised up Moscow – the “Third Rome”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that if there will ever be a Christian state in the 21st century, it will exist mainly in Orthodox-dominated lands (and perhaps in Catholic Poland). For the rest of the Christian world, political Christendom is dead and gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atheists and critics of religion sometimes contend that Christianity is on the decline. But is this true? While it is without a doubt correct to say that Europe and the Western World is secularising at an exponential rate, this does not hold true with regard to the rest of the world. There is an explosion of Christian growth in the global south, particularly in Africa which has proven to be a fertile mission field for the Christian message. As far as academia is concerned, the resurgence of orthodox Christian scholarship in recent years is also a sign of life. However unpopular the faith may be among young white people, it certainly has a long and bright future ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Jungian Shadow</title><link href="/The-Jungian-Shadow" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Jungian Shadow" /><published>2019-02-18T12:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-18T12:46:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Jungian-Shadow</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Jungian-Shadow">&lt;p&gt;What if you’ve got it all wrong: the whole idea of who you are, your identity and how you want to be seen. What if there’s more to your personality: another dimension maybe, or even a caliginous shadow, harbouring in it the nasty demonic tendencies of your very being? While this idea may seem bizarre, the truth of it is hard to deny. There lies in all of us a mysterious unconscious realm seated within the deepest recesses of our personality. This is the Shadow archetype, the Id, or the dark side. Devoid of the conscious light, it is in this tenebrous side where thrives the primitive, malicious, even creative aspects of our being that have long been repressed by the Freudian Ego. Engulfed in obscurity, the Shadow largely remains hidden from the understanding of the Self, making us live in pretence and deception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Propounded by the very renowned Swiss psychoanalyst Carl Jung, the concept of the Shadow operates on the Pleasure Principle. Subdued ideas, primitive instincts, desires, drives, abjections, fears, all are encompassed by this concept, which further mirrors the latent, unknown and dark aspects of the psyche that the conscious Ego fails to resonate with. The Shadow is of two types: the personal and the collective. While the personal Shadow pertains to the individual psyche, the collective Shadow emanates from a united unconsciousness of society-members, a projection of which has resulted in the greatest of evils, in the form of prejudice advanced by society against other communities to conceal their own weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lying under unfathomable depths, the Shadow develops alongside the Ego and Persona. As a child gets culturally conditioned to differentiate between good and bad, certain possessed behaviours and qualities are evaluated by them as deplorable and, ultimately, despised and rejected. In the whole process of growing up, humans also tend to masquerade their identity and don on a façade to gain greater acceptance in society. This is known as a Persona. But the Persona only hides the Shadow, it doesn’t eliminate its gestating potency to unleash the worst in human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is essential for one to accept the Shadow rather than seeking validation in the Persona. For a harmonious universe, the intermingling of both the aspects of good – bad, order - chaos, the yin and yang, becomes necessary. Likewise, for a balanced personality, one needs to unearth the dark aspects of one’s soul from the dreary suppressions of the Ego and integrate them with their conscious side. This is extremely important, for the very reason that each time your Ego represses a part of you, your Shadow gets denser, sprouting in it the destructive potential to completely overshadow your conscious light and cast on you a dark cloud of gloom for the rest of your life. A convenient trick is to think like the antagonist or villain in books or movies, learning to work with the people one hates or feels irritated around, and identifying the lies that they can unravel to challenge ‘the good’―both in society and in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of exploring one’s Shadow is not to bring forth some inner Machiavelli. It is about ensuring one truly understands oneself and accepts that there is a very horrible, unspeakable side to one’s own psyche. Without such knowledge and such humility, one is bound to remain a Nietzschean Last Man, afraid of life and it’s problems, driven not by a sense of true purpose but primal instincts. However, by overcoming the Shadow and directing its destructive forces on the right path, one can achieve true inner peace and the ability to fully realise oneself as The Super Man―thereby taming the demon within to achieve inner peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">What if you’ve got it all wrong: the whole idea of who you are, your identity and how you want to be seen. What if there’s more to your personality: another dimension maybe, or even a caliginous shadow, harbouring in it the nasty demonic tendencies of your very being? While this idea may seem bizarre, the truth of it is hard to deny. There lies in all of us a mysterious unconscious realm seated within the deepest recesses of our personality. This is the Shadow archetype, the Id, or the dark side. Devoid of the conscious light, it is in this tenebrous side where thrives the primitive, malicious, even creative aspects of our being that have long been repressed by the Freudian Ego. Engulfed in obscurity, the Shadow largely remains hidden from the understanding of the Self, making us live in pretence and deception.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Higher Ups: Appointments and Disappointments</title><link href="/The-Higher-Ups" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Higher Ups: Appointments and Disappointments" /><published>2019-02-15T01:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-15T01:50:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Higher-Ups</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Higher-Ups">&lt;p&gt;In this article, we take a look at the people in the past decade and more who had exponential burdens placed on their shoulders and examine how they fared. The men and women who moved markets and sentiments; whose names were heard on the internet and in households across the globe, setting examples to follow and learn from, for the generation ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mario-draghi-ecb&quot;&gt;Mario Draghi (ECB)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/55/Mario_Draghi_-_World_Economic_Forum_Annual_Meeting_2012.jpg/1024px-Mario_Draghi_-_World_Economic_Forum_Annual_Meeting_2012.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Mario-Draghi.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; Italy &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; La Sapienza University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mario Draghi has been in and out of &lt;i&gt;Most Influential&lt;/i&gt; around the world for more than a decade, topping out at number 2 on &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/worlds-greatest-leaders/mario-draghi-2/&quot;&gt;Fortune greatest&lt;/a&gt; world leaders. Before taking Jean-Claude Trichet’s place at the top of the European Central Bank, he had served as the Governor of the Bank of Italy and was elected as Chairman of the Financial Stability Forum of 2006. But his biggest achievements came in the form of righting the ship that was the European economy, which was on the brink of collapse with a host of countries running on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=10&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjh6Nj26aPgAhULS48KHV9fDZkQFjAJegQIChAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.telegraph.co.uk%2Fnews%2F0%2Feuropean-debt-crisis-not-just-greece-drowning-debt%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0sq0KE3R4uEWXWRaxmklU1&quot;&gt;failing&lt;/a&gt; economies, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwivr_fr6aPgAhUGSY8KHc-uAcsQFjABegQICBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.thebalance.com%2Fwhat-is-the-greece-debt-crisis-3305525&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1nusWDPX7zHeB3hayomLwC&quot;&gt;huge debts&lt;/a&gt; and crippling deficits. He said he would  do “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pq1V0aPEO3c&quot;&gt;…whatever it takes…&lt;/a&gt;” to preserve the Euro and so he did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only time will tell how this proven leader will stand up to the task of a Britain-less EU economy, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: President of the European Central Bank&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jean-claude-trichet-ecb&quot;&gt;Jean-Claude Trichet (ECB)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/117994717@N06/15890096265&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Jean-Claude-Trichet.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; France &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; University of Paris, Sciences Po&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming off the worst &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/1401696/French-candidate-to-head-Euro-bank-faces-fraud-trial.html&quot;&gt;banking scandal&lt;/a&gt; in French History, Jean-Claude Trichet was able to successfully manoeuvre himself out of the French Treasury and into the leading post at the ECB. It was under his Presidency that Europe plunged into the Great Recession of the 21st Century, and many still believe that he should get most of the blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was 2009 when an IMF report showing telling signs of a Greek default came out, but Mr Trichet was not ready to budge, standing firmly in resistance stating, “no European country could ever be allowed to go bankrupt”. Instead of fixing the problems &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/business/global/europes-two-years-of-denials-trapped-greece.html?_r=1&quot;&gt;he chose to resist any contemplation of a default&lt;/a&gt; until October 2011, when a consensus to devalue Greek bonds was reached. He resigned as President before the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Board of Directors, Airbus Group&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;janet-yellen-federal-reserve&quot;&gt;Janet Yellen (Federal Reserve)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/fordschool/33842410502&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Janet-Yellen.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; United States of America &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Brown University, Yale University&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the huge success stories of the last decade, Janet Yellen has done more than defy expectations and targets set for the economy. Starting her term as Vice-Chair in 2010, and later serving as 14th Chair of the Federal Reserve, she replaced the outgoing Ben Bernanke whose $3 trillion stimulus package she &lt;a href=&quot;http://money.cnn.com/2013/11/14/news/economy/janet-yellen-confirmation-hearing/&quot;&gt;defended throughout&lt;/a&gt; the Senate hearings. She has successfully overseen a gradual return to full employment as well as an increase in real income growth. She has even managed to scale back the stimulus packages to the economy while simultaneously leaving inflation rates stagnant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/higherups-graph.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although considered to be a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20131113032024/http://www.sfgate.com/business/investopedia/article/Janet-Yellen-Background-And-Philosophy-4902126.php&quot;&gt;dove&lt;/a&gt;”, she has gradually raised interest rates in the past few years from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/robertlenzner/2017/12/16/janet-yellen-leaves-us-with-goldilocks-economy/#4067146794b6&quot;&gt;1.5% to 2.25%&lt;/a&gt;. Donald Trump may not approve of her but the people definitely do, as she has left a great inheritance for Trump’s nominee Jay Powell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Distinguished Fellow in Residence at Brookings Institution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;john-stumpf-wells-fargo&quot;&gt;John Stumpf (Wells Fargo)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/hieronymus/3635257139&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/John-Stumpf.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; United States of America &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; St Cloud State University, University of Minnesota&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Stumpf was the commander and captain of a $1.9 trillion empire. Today he has lost it all; well, nearly all of it. Rising steadily through the ranks from 1998 he finally assumed the position of Chairman and CEO of Wells Fargo Bank, the fourth-largest bank in the US by total assets, and it was all going well as Wells Fargo emerged as arguably the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwigwbiEqqTgAhWOT30KHdKfDK8QFjABegQIBxAF&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.fool.com%2Finvesting%2Fgeneral%2F2015%2F11%2F04%2Fwells-fargo-is-the-biggest-bank-in-america-accordi.aspx&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3kFZ7WWDtQhkoh2bN7nYuX&quot;&gt;biggest player&lt;/a&gt; in the American economy. In December 2008, when the world was in the middle of an economic collapse, he led the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20121213150723/https://www.wellsfargo.com/about/corporate/executive_officers/stumpf&quot;&gt;purchase of Wachovia bank&lt;/a&gt;, one of the biggest mergers in the history of banking. However, in September of 2016, the bank was charged with opening &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/oct/12/wells-fargo-ceo-john-stumpf-retires-fake-accounts&quot;&gt;2 million accounts without customers’ permission&lt;/a&gt;, just so that they could meet the sales quotas of the company. Slapped with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/oct/14/john-stumpf-retirement-wells-fargo-ceo-jail-time&quot;&gt;$185 million fine&lt;/a&gt; by US regulators for their fraudulent activities, John Stumpf had to eventually resign in the wake of the disaster. His story is still a matter of public hatred, as he got away with a hefty &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usatoday.com/story/money/markets/2016/10/12/wells-fargo-ceo-retires-under-fire/91964778/&quot;&gt;$134 million paycheck&lt;/a&gt;, although a Wells Fargo spokeswoman had this to say, “Mr.John Stump will not receive any severance payment”. At least when it comes to banking, no severance payment doesn’t mean severance from a payday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Just bought a $3.77M mansion in the Arizona valley&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;christine-lagarde-imf&quot;&gt;Christine Lagarde (IMF)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1e/Women_in_Economic_Decision-making_Christine_Lagarde_%288414041294%29.jpg/1024px-Women_in_Economic_Decision-making_Christine_Lagarde_%288414041294%29.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Christine-Lagarde.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; France &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Paris West University, Institute of Political Studies- Aix&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2011 the IMF made history by electing Christine Lagarde as its first ever woman head. It was also slap-bang in the middle of the European sovereign debt crisis and Europe needed her, to call her strict or strong would be an understatement. She has repeatedly shown her unforgiving nature, especially when it comes to doing what needs to be done, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/financialcrisis/9293602/Irate-Greeks-vilify-IMF-chief-on-Facebook-after-she-brands-them-tax-dodgers.html&quot;&gt;Greece knows it far too well&lt;/a&gt;. If you were to ask her about the way she handles such issues, she &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vogue.com/article/christine-lagarde-changing-of-the-guard&quot;&gt;says that she relates&lt;/a&gt; to “Adam Smith— that is liberal”. Initially hesitant towards writing off Greek debts, she had repeatedly asked for austerity measures to be carried out. But when the people of Greece decided &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/may/25/payback-time-lagarde-greeks&quot;&gt;to just not pay&lt;/a&gt; their taxes, she was forced to take the initiative of creating a rescue package for the debt-ridden country. When she knew that the help arranged was still &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424127887324299104578527202781667088&quot;&gt;not enough&lt;/a&gt; to save the country, she decided to finally write off the debts and was even ready to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2015/jul/17/imf-steps-up-greek-bailout-criticism-debt-relief-package&quot;&gt;call for debt relief on a global scale&lt;/a&gt; on behalf of the IMF. This IMF MD is as close as an “Iron lady” as you can find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Managing Director and Chair of the IMF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;raghuram-rajan-rbi&quot;&gt;Raghuram Rajan (RBI)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d5/Raghuram_Rajan%2C_IMF_69MS040421048l.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Raghuram-Rajan.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; India &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; IIT Delhi, IIM Ahmedabad, MIT Sloan School of Management&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He started out as an assistant professor of finance in 1991 at the Chicago Booth School of Business, but his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiZrrP0t6TgAhXIEHIKHUUpBkgQFjABegQICRAC&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Ffaculty.chicagobooth.edu%2Fluigi.zingales%2Fpapers%2Fresearch%2Fcapintro.pdf&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0fVqHg4mb3p14Lobhs89dX&quot;&gt;Saving Capitalism from the Capitalists&lt;/a&gt; caught the eye of the IMF’s first deputy managing director Anne Krueger, who appointed him as the Chief Economist. This made him the first Indian and the youngest ever at his post. He helped the IMF make huge strides in financial sector analysis and led increasing research into their effects on a macro level. In 2012, he was appointed chief economic adviser of India and even prepared the Economic Survey of India for the year. It was less than a year later that he was appointed Governor of the Reserve Bank of India. It was under his tenure that India experienced a fall of 6 percentage points in its retail inflation rate and a historically low rate of wholesale inflation. With global support on his side, India’s foreign exchange reserves &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiqxbnlt6TgAhWKF3IKHXy1ALEQFjAAegQICRAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fqz.com%2Findia%2F774034%2Fa-comparison-of-indias-economy-when-raghuram-rajan-took-charge-at-rbi-and-now-as-urjit-patel-steps-in%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1c_zvCu7ALa8t76Xctf9lk&quot;&gt;ballooned to $380 million in a matter of only two years&lt;/a&gt; and with the election of the new government, prospects of the Indian economy were as bright as ever, despite the many tussles with the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, his will to return to academia got the better of him and the government wanted to head in a different direction (Note: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwja6vfHt6TgAhVab30KHY1IDuYQFjABegQIBxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Findianexpress.com%2Farticle%2Fbusiness%2Feconomy%2Fdemonetisation-rbi-gst-raghuram-rajan-economic-growth-5440435%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1qs88yKq6IarMKs5iGYswa&quot;&gt;Demonetization&lt;/a&gt;) while he preferred taxation to tackle the issues of black money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Katherine Dusak Miller Distinguished Service Professor of Finance at University of Chicago&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;zhou-xiaochuan-pboc&quot;&gt;Zhou Xiaochuan (PBOC)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/f/fb/Secretary_Geithner_and_People%27s_Bank_of_China_Governor_Zhou_Xiaochuan%2C_following_a_working_lunch_on_May_23%2C_2010_in_Beijing.jpg/1220px-Secretary_Geithner_and_People%27s_Bank_of_China_Governor_Zhou_Xiaochuan%2C_following_a_working_lunch_on_May_23%2C_2010_in_Beijing.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Zhou-Xiaochuan.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; China&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Beijing Institute of Chemical Technology, Tsinghua University&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After serving as president of China Construction Bank and Chairman of the China Securities Regulatory Commission, he was appointed as governor of the People’s Bank of China by Premier Zhu Rongji, a tenure which lasted a whopping 15 years. Unlike its contemporaries from across the globe, the People’s Bank of China is not independent. Almost everything has to go through the State Council whose members prefer to have low interest rates and lots of credit. Yet it is through these confines that Zhou Xiaochuan has managed to manoeuvre policies &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/2013/03/16/china-parliament-zhou-idUSL3N0C7CV920130316&quot;&gt;in and outside of his jurisdiction&lt;/a&gt; that truly set up the Chinese economy as an international investment opportunity. He is responsible for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/0631ab2e-2387-11e8-8138-569c3d7ab0a7&quot;&gt;internationalising the renminbi, encouraging the growth of online banking&lt;/a&gt; throughout the nation and clearing up more than $800 million in bad loans. The man is considered among the most academically capable among the Chinese leadership, has an increasingly friendly openness toward the media and is the only Chinese higher-up who has been published in a Western Journal. Add to that his attitude toward markets,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;If the market can solve the problem, let the market do it. I am just a referee. I am neither a sportsman nor a coach.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you probably have one of the biggest reasons why China has roared into the foray as a global economic powerhouse over the past decade. After opening up the Chinese economy through a legacy of financial reform, he stepped down in 2018, just as the fear of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble&quot;&gt;Chinese slowdown&lt;/a&gt; was materialising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Member of China Investment Corp.’s (CIC) International Advisory Council&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shohan Mukherjee</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">In this article, we take a look at the people in the past decade and more who had exponential burdens placed on their shoulders and examine how they fared. The men and women who moved markets and sentiments; whose names were heard on the internet and in households across the globe, setting examples to follow and learn from, for the generation ahead.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">South Africa’s New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion</title><link href="/South-Africa-Land-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="South Africa's New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion" /><published>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/South%20Africa-Land-Policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/South-Africa-Land-Policy">&lt;p&gt;Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue has its genesis in the Natives Land Act, 1913, that reserved about 93% of the land for the white minority. The Native Trust and Land Act, 1936, subsequently reduced it to 87%. Further, these Acts legally sanctioned historical dispossession of the African people’s land. The year 1994 saw the end of apartheid in South Africa. It brought along with it hope of land redistribution to the Rainbow Nation’s communities. Section 25 of the Constitution provided for land expropriation with just and equitable compensation. The government relied on a “willing-seller, willing-buyer” land redistribution policy to correct the historical wrong. Under this approach, the government bought land against compensation and redistributed it to the dispossessed people. The policy did not yield desired results due to the unwillingness of property owners to sell and their demand of exorbitantly high prices in many cases. Even today, 72% of agricultural land is in the hands of white South Africans, i.e. 8% of the population, whereas only 4% of land is owned by black South Africans (over 80% of the population). President Jacob Zuma’s government tried to address this issue in 2016 by introducing a bill in the parliament to end the “willing-buyer, willing-seller” policy and providing for payment for land acquired by expropriation in the public interest at adjudicator value. In view of growing discontent coupled with a high rate of unemployment, Zuma’s successor, Cyril Ramaphosa pushed the idea of redistribution of (only unused) land without compensation in 2017. The year 2018 saw the adoption of a report by the South African Parliament, recommending the amendment of section 25 of the Constitution to expropriate land without compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea of addressing the present skewed land ownership issue has initiated a debate and has made land a hot-button issue. The breakaway group of the ruling African National Congress, the Economic Freedom Fighters (EFF), is in principle against Ramaphosa’s policy. But only because it favours a more radical nationalisation of banks and land as the only means to undo historical injustice. However, opponents of expropriation without compensation argue that South Africa may go Zimbabwe’s way, where a fast track land reform process led to large-scale violence. Many white farmers fled the country at the turn of the century to neighbouring countries like Zambia, Mozambique, the Congo and Nigeria. This exodus converted Zimbabwe from a food exporting country to one facing frequent food shortages. According to an estimate by a Zimbabwean economist and legislator, Eddie Cross, the total cost that the economy has borne due to the adoption of this policy is around $20 billion. Banks have also expressed their reservation on the proposed amendment. They have about $114 billion of mortgages outstanding against land. Their concerns are not being addressed. Further, the possibility of civil war engulfing the most industrialised country in Africa cannot be ruled out. Many far-right groups have claimed that white farmers are being killed and forced expropriations are already happening. In August 2018, Donald Trump’s tweet in their support added fuel to the fire. If violence spreads, it is likely to affect tourism, which contributes about 10% to the GDP. It would dampen the investor sentiment as well. The country, at present, is an attractive emerging market despite economic woes for investors because of two reasons. Firstly, it has an expanding middle class and secondly, its location at the tip of the African continent makes it a perfect gateway to the huge African market consisting of about one billion people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many defects in Ramaphosa’s policy design. It is unclear on what basis land will be redistributed, and how the beneficiaries will be identified. If land has changed hands against adequate compensation, will it have any impact on new owner’s rights? The parameters to identify ‘unused land’ have not been clearly defined. The policy seems to be the government’s ploy to counter the growing popularity of the EFF in the country, particularly against the background of upcoming elections in May 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One really wonders why politicians around the world try to achieve inclusion of one group by excluding another. Such inclusion-exclusion is certainly not a zero-sum game because players over the years change. After all, why must the present generation pay for the ‘wrongs’ done by their forefathers? The Indian policy of caste-based quotas for achieving social justice through inclusion is continuing even after seventy years of independence. More and more groups are demanding quotas, causing social unrest at times. In South Africa, even after 25 years in power, the ANC has failed to conclude a fair land reform process successfully. But will South Africa’s new (and potentially dangerous) experiment with inclusion lead to the desired result (whatever that is)? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manya Manushi</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Social Responsibility, if Any, Do or Should Corporations Have in Society Today?</title><link href="/Corporate-Social-Responsibility" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Social Responsibility, if Any, Do or Should Corporations Have in Society Today?" /><published>2019-02-14T21:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-14T21:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/Corporate-Social-Responsibility</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Corporate-Social-Responsibility">&lt;p&gt;Consistent with McWilliams and Siegel’s approach in &lt;i&gt;The Academy of Management Review&lt;/i&gt;, we define Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) as the spectrum of undertakings in which the firm goes beyond compliance and engages in “actions that appear to further some social good, beyond the interests of the firm”. It is said to be the company’s way of giving back to the community it is making so much out of, i.e. a sort of return gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gifts, of course, make consumers happy and this is the basic logic behind the social responsibility of corporations today: to make sure elated customers return to provide more business. This process of giving back to society adds to the goodwill of the company and ensures consumer loyalty. In professional language, this art of deceiving customers by producing a philanthropic image of a corporation is termed “corporate strategy”. It is a framework, as argued by Fombrun &amp;amp; Shanley in the &lt;i&gt;Academy of Management Journal&lt;/i&gt; that demonstrates how the reputation of a firm captures returns to socially responsible behaviour. Consumers tend to give more business to a firm that perhaps donates a part of its income to some village in Saharan Africa, than to one that does nothing of the sort or does something similar but of a lesser magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the same reason, Fortune 500 companies and multinational corporations are in a race over who can be more charitable, simply because CSR happens to have somewhat substituted direct advertising. Even though it is not legally required in most economies, companies seem to have diverted a significant proportion of their funds exclusively for CSR, rather than investing them in sales or advertising, as they traditionally did. They have realised that they can leverage social responsibility as a vehicle to bring customers to their doorstep, rather than making the effort of going to theirs. Therefore, we see a dramatic change in the policies of corporations today relative to just a few decades ago. They are using the same marketing budget in a much more efficient way and sustaining customer relationships by showing them a movie. The funny part is customers are actually enjoying the movie, but they fail to see the reality behind the seemingly altruistic endeavours of these corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Disney’s classic retelling of the fable &lt;i&gt;Pinocchio&lt;/i&gt;, after the Blue Fairy grants him life, Geppetto’s wooden boy is granted a conscience. Now, since corporations do not have a conscience, they need a reliable external source to show them right from wrong. But what is that external source? Is it a set of laws like the several others these corporations never follow? Is it the government that in fact partners with them at times to privatise services like the provision of clean drinking water? Or is it people like you and me who are busy watching the movie these corporations are showing us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporations have always had just one responsibility – the responsibility to serve themselves. They do not care about the consequences their activities have on society. After being declared “legal persons”, 288 of the 307 appellants who sought jurisdiction of the Supreme Court of the United States of America under the 14th Amendment, were corporations and not African-Americans, for whom the amendment had actually been made. This just goes on to prove how self-centred and blatantly selfish corporations are. But wait a minute, why shouldn’t they be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it be harm to human health by companies such as Monsanto or harm to the environment by a variety of industries, corporations can cross any limits and employees need not even regret their wrongdoings because well – limited liability – they’re safe! How can they be held accountable for decisions that a corporation took? After all, a corporation doesn’t have the ability to base decisions on morals or feelings, then how can we expect it to be socially responsible? But then, what is the social responsibility of businesses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Milton Friedman once stated in the &lt;i&gt;The New York Times Magazine&lt;/i&gt;: “The social responsibility of business is to increase its profits.” Friedman wanted to clearly bring out a distinction between the legal and ethical aspects involved in the debate on social responsibility, by affirming that businesses are simply groups of people and that only people have responsibilities, not inanimate entities! To quote J. Hood of the &lt;i&gt;Foundation for Economic Education&lt;/i&gt;“If a corporation makes a donation to charity without the shareholders’ authorization, wrote Friedman, the managers are deciding how to spend other people’s money. It would be better to return the money to shareholders as dividends or capital gains and let them decide which charities to support.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative and opposite theory to Friedman’s was developed by Freeman, who argued in his book &lt;i&gt;Strategic Management: A Stakeholder Approach&lt;/i&gt; that corporate social responsibility is a vital part of strategic management. His argument was based on the thought that firms are associated with numerous parties whose interests should be considered, since the firm can’t continue to survive without the support of these stakeholders – employees, customers, suppliers and the community. This view was expanded by Donaldson &amp;amp; Davis by the introduction of Stewardship Theory in the&lt;i&gt;Australian Journal of Management&lt;/i&gt;. According to this theory, there is a moral imperative for managers to “do the right thing,” without regard to how such decisions affect the firm’s financial performance. This rationale becomes difficult to adhere to internationally, because there may be no consensus on what “the right thing” is. However, this was a more ethically-centred approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s a simpler question to be asked in all this scholarly debate. Before managing social responsibility outside their organisation, shouldn’t corporations focus on fulfilling their internal social responsibility? Paying a few cents to workers who produce products that sell for hundreds of dollars! Is it not hypocritical of companies to talk big about social responsibility while they exploit their own employees? It is clear to me that corporations survive on externalities and that they are purely utilitarian. They want to make others pay the cost for their impact on society, while they luxuriate in soaring profits. But then again, isn’t this why corporations exist in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe corporations do have a social responsibility, however, that responsibility predominantly lies confined to their own internal affairs: first, the demands of employees, financers and executives ought to be delivered. Commercial activity in itself comes with social benefits such as greater employment, improved standards of living, globalisation and a better quality of life. These benefits aren’t derived from any extra effort by corporations – it’s not obligatory for them to put in extra effort anyway – but they are derived simply by virtue of the existence of corporations. Since a corporation can’t think and feel like a human with flesh and blood, it need not care about any other social responsibility, unless it comes with an advantage. If community giving helps boost sales and multiply profits, implement CSR. This means we’ll still be watching a movie, however, there will certainly be a simultaneous social impact, to whatever small extent possible. So, corporations may consider their dedicated business undertakings a social responsibility, or, their newfound marketing technique – either one suits me…as long as it does some good, especially to those people on whom the corporation truly depends for its profits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivang Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Consistent with McWilliams and Siegel’s approach in The Academy of Management Review, we define Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) as the spectrum of undertakings in which the firm goes beyond compliance and engages in “actions that appear to further some social good, beyond the interests of the firm”. It is said to be the company’s way of giving back to the community it is making so much out of, i.e. a sort of return gift.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Questioning Humanity: The Stanford Prison Experiment</title><link href="/Questioning-Humanity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questioning Humanity: The Stanford Prison Experiment" /><published>2019-02-14T21:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-14T21:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Questioning-Humanity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Questioning-Humanity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Whoever fights monsters should see to it that in the process he does not become a monster. And if you gaze long enough into an abyss, the abyss will gaze back into you.”&lt;/em&gt; - Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Humanity’ as a word essentially includes, but is not limited to, all the better things in the world: Peace, Happiness, Co-operational Existence for the betterment of the community, Altruism and so on. But what if this definition was farcical at the very least, or worse, misleading and based on chosen references rather the entire spectra of Truth? What if humans are the monsters they are themselves scared of? History does cite its own examples and notions on this issue. Tyrants, dictators and people in positions of power have always exploited those not in power since the beginning of time. But what if this was the true nature of Man? To seek answers to this question and more, Dr Philip Zimbardo along with his associates conducted the now infamous Stanford Prison Experiment in August 1971 in the basements of Stanford University’s Psychology Department. The aim of the experiment, as decided by Dr Zimbardo, was to conduct a social psychology experiment. Zimbardo’s primary motive for conducting the experiment was to focus on the power of roles, rules, symbols, group identity and situational validation of behaviour that generally would repulse ordinary individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Zimbardo, in his own words at the Toronto Symposium in 1996, “had been conducting research for some years on deindividuation, vandalism and dehumanization that illustrated the ease with which ordinary people could be led to engage in antisocial acts by putting them in situations where they felt anonymous, or they could perceive of others in ways that made them less than human, as enemies or objects”. In the Stanford Prison Experiment, he created a struggle of sorts between two groups and decided to evaluate the power dynamics behind it. He created a prison-like setup, where a certain set of individuals would be representing the ‘guards’ (the dominant strata) who would be controlling the ‘prisoners’ (the lower strata). The unsuspecting, and must we also add, willing volunteers in the experiment were divided into the groups only as a matter of chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Zimbardo set up the experiments to establish the breakdown of one’s own personality to take someone else’s. The guards were asked to react harshly in order to establish their power over the prisoners. Dave Eshelman, the most infamous guard during the experiment recalled that all actions were committed in order to fulfil the purpose behind the experiment, even though the experiment showed that some guards had very sadistic tendencies. The prisoners were taken from their own homes, and the Palo Alto Police cooperated with Zimbardo for a more genuine atmosphere. The prisoners were stripped and searched, their names were taken away from them and they were assigned numbers. The first day of the experiment went as it was expected to, without any issues. There were 9+3 guards and they were arranged to take charge in shifts. The conditions of the small container-like prison cells were largely in contrast with the living conditions of the guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the second day, however, things started turning more macabre. The prisoners locked their doors and refused to come out. The guards used fire extinguishers to subdue the revolt without any permission from Zimbardo, who acted as the “superintendent of the prison”. The guards decided that there would be privilege rooms, which had way better food and beds, where the prisoners who did not support the rebellion would be kept. The interesting thing was even the people who had not supported the rebellion did not choose to be in these rooms. The guards continued to establish their dominance by removing the mattresses and forcing the prisoners to sleep on the ground, not even allowing them to clean their chamber pots. After 36 hours, a certain prisoner #8612 claimed to have lost his mind and was forced to be released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the atrocities of the guards continued. They stripped the prisoners and asked them to repeat the numbers assigned to them in order to enforce their new identity on them. While Zimbardo was concerned that the released prisoner would come back and was busy relocating the experiment, the guards continued their naked displays of power. A certain prisoner #416 locked himself in his room and refused to eat his sausages. He was forced into solitary confinement. There were several times when the prisoners asked for parole, only to be refused under the condition of no payment for their services. Zimbardo claimed that the prisoners stayed back even if no money was involved because they had internalised the roles of the oppressed prisoners in themselves. It was only after Zimbardo’s fiancé, Maslach, arrived on the sixth day of the experiment and questioned the morality of the situation that finally the experiment concluded. Zimbardo noted that out of the 50 people who participated in the experimented, nobody questioned its morality apart from Maslach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several thought experiments and social and anthropogenic situations reenacted along the lines of the Stanford Prison Experiment. A notable one is the Milgram Experiment, where a person in one room was given the option of using an electronic switch which would send a current to another person in another room. The result of these experiments gives us a simple forlorn conclusion: Humans are, in most circumstances, sadistic creatures, and those with power will most likely prey on those without it. Even though the Stanford Experiment is challenged for having fraudulent methodology, the question remains that if humans are provided with an unrestricted and unbounded amount of power, will they behave like the guards did or will their ways be dependent on other factors such as the surrounding environment, i.e. the factors which were left unaccounted for in Zimbardo’s version? Or is there more to it than what meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several questions which arise on the origins of morality and cognitive behaviour if we analyse the results of the Stanford Prison Experiment. Maybe we will find more about it when we recreate the circumstances. Or maybe we could all just accept the tyrant within us, the mass murderer within us and also embrace the empathy within ourselves and let them battle it out for the soul of mankind. In &lt;i&gt;Dark Knight&lt;/i&gt; , the movie, The Joker presents a similar experiment where he provides people with the option of destroying one of two boats, where one is filled with civilians and the other is filled with criminals and the remote for the detonation of the bomb in one boat is placed in the other boat. Even though the film chooses not to explore the darker aspects of the human mind and depicts humanity as still residing within us, it is after all the matter of a film. The question is: what if this happens with all of us right now? What would you choose? The ball is in your court.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“Whoever fights monsters should see to it that in the process he does not become a monster. And if you gaze long enough into an abyss, the abyss will gaze back into you.” - Friedrich Nietzsche</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Venezuela: A Country Being Played?</title><link href="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venezuela: A Country Being Played?" /><published>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/atreyi.bhaumik/&quot;&gt;In my previous articles&lt;/a&gt;, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign support to the country, especially in monetary terms, is relatively minuscule. China has poured almost $60 billion into the country as foreign investment, and through trade. But now, even China is reluctant, and new money given to the nation doesn’t add up to significant amounts. The only country showing faith amongst all others is Russia. However, foreign support or not, the disaster that has been wrecked throughout Venezuela by the present regime of Nicolas Maduro is too great to really be helped at all. There is not even an ounce of doubt regarding the fact that, under Nicolas Maduro, power has been abused. And from healthcare to education, the country is struggling to keep afloat. People in huge numbers are suffering from diseases like malaria, measles and tuberculosis, with no medical help or any other proper facilities. Underinvestment and corruption have left the healthcare system in shambles. Starvation, poverty, corruption, and violence in the nation has led to the commoners fleeing to get away from an oppressive rule. In fact, statistics show that approximately three million people have fled the country since 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is one of the most astounding cases of economic mismanagement and too much concentration of power in the hands of the state. Venezuela’s people see no hope for the future, while their country sees prices double every month. The GDP has halved and the country’s pension scheme helps no one. Oil production has gone down to a meagre one million barrels a day, cutting off a huge proportion of revenue from the oil export business. In addition, the country is so deep in debt that people have lost the ability to hold their heads high. The middle class is highly irked and aggressively vocal about their feelings towards the dictator. And this has led to protests in most of the regions, especially due to the fact that they believe the elections were rigged. According to a survey report, about 80% of the population (32 million) does not recognise Mr Maduro as their supreme leader. But Maduro seems to be untouchable with the army at his disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, the world is finally responding to the crisis along with Venezuela’s political opposition. Juan Guaido, the leader of the National Assembly has proclaimed to be the true leader of the nation. To show support and appreciation for Guaido, around one million men and women took to the streets. Their march was a demand for a proper democracy and greater rights for the innocent people who are paying the price for an unruly regime. Guaido too is playing on the same emotions of the people. He has stated that he wants to “rebuild” the country and bring back proper democracy. The path to removing Maduro, however, is a dangerous one. Many might even call it fruitless. The dictatorship has in the past responded to such opposition leaders with violence. However, Venezuelans believe that Guaido’s case is different from the rest because of the timing. The army, which has fiercely protected Maduro till now, is said to have lost interest, given they are not paid enough. Due to hyperinflation, the 36 thousand bolivars that they earn per month is almost next to nothing. The army demands and supports the side with money. If Maduro cannot keep them satisfied, then the situation might reverse in favour of Guaido and the people. Towards the end of January, Guaido released a statement saying that he has indeed talked to the army in order to make it switch sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various western countries have stood up in support of Guaido as the interim President till the elections are announced.  The United States has taken the matter to the United Nations and has called for military intervention. So now, instead of it being a Venezuelan matter, it is becoming an issue of global politics. Everyone is pitching in according to whom they favour more. The US and its allies have come down on Maduro. The US government has withheld payments for oil and has stated that they would pay only when the legitimate leader, Guaido, comes into power. Economic sanctions imposed on the country have made Venezuela even poorer, and the lack of money has facilitated a sharper drop in the production of crude oil. The oil industry of Venezuela could collapse any day now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the main game, under such circumstances remains between the US, Russia, and China. It seems like this is a desperate move by the US to regain control in Latin America, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/China-in-Latin-America&quot;&gt;where Chinese presence has grown by leaps and bounds over half a decade&lt;/a&gt;. As for Russia, a military intervention in Venezuela would show (to put it bluntly) the finger to the US just like in Crimea. But the real question is, does military intervention (by the US or Russia) really help the masses in Venezuela? How can one be sure that it wouldn’t turn into another Libya or Syria, where the US military had intervened to “give power back to the people” but ended up causing chaos and violence. Will US military action unite Venezuela by removing Maduro from power or destroy yet another country with oil reserves? The truth of the situation right now is that if the US really comes down to military action, then no other country will stop it. Be it China or Russia. They will all watch the spectacle because going against the US in its own backyard is foolish and in every way a loss for them, economically or politically. The aggression will make them pay dearly, and they are not really interested in what happens to Venezuela. Also, the showdown will only make matters messier and no one wants another Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should get to know what happens next in a matter of time, given the amount of urgency that’s been shown on both the fronts. For the Venezuelans, it is a choice between the lesser and bigger evil, and one cannot know which is which. But the truth is that people are suffering and the world community, as usual, is playing the power game that it so dearly loves. What hasn’t changed is that human lives and their conditions are all being overlooked. In this day and age, power is dear to all. Thus, all try to hold on strongly to their power. All rationale aside, this situation begs the question of where power truly lies. Is the US way of military supremacy a better method than the Chinese methodical hegemony or not? Recognizing Juan Guaido as the interim President has already started a massive uprising, and we are yet to see if this intervention in Venezuela starts a civil war or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In my previous articles, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Vedantic Influence on Indian Foreign Policy</title><link href="/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Vedantic Influence on Indian Foreign Policy" /><published>2019-02-07T04:37:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-07T04:37:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy">&lt;p&gt;The great Indian mystic and seer Swami Vivekananda once remarked, “All differences in this world are of degree and not of kind, because oneness is the secret of everything.” This idea finds reflection in the way India engages with the world via its foreign policy. Foreign policy is undoubtedly an important part of any government or administration’s agenda. This is especially so in the case of the current Indian government led by Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who is (in) famous for his numerous foreign and diplomatic trips. To Modi, “Foreign policy is about finding the common meeting points.” And it is in this context that PM Modi refers to the Sanskrit phrase &lt;i&gt;“Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam”&lt;/i&gt; which roughly translates to mean “the world is one family” as being India’s philosophy. This is not just a descriptive phrase, rather it is the mantra of India’s diplomatic lexicon. &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is a Vedantic thought and is an integral part of Hindu philosophy. It stresses compassion, collaboration, partnership and coexistence with zero vested interests. In fact, a “Universal Brotherhood Day” is observed on September 11 every year to commemorate Swami Vivekananda’s speech in Chicago on religious harmony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, The Indian PM Modi opened his historic UN address with a tribute to this principle of world fraternity, which has guided his nation from time immemorial. Modi’s speech emphasised the need to combat climate change, external security threats and the need to utilise the untapped potential of space exploration. He highlighted the need for unity in combating various social menaces and called for the participation of ‘G-All’. He called for reforms to the UN Security Council and asked countries to move beyond the policy of zero-sum games. PM Modi even evoked this policy at the World Economic Forum (Davos). He delivered the keynote address at the plenary session and stated that this policy was crucial to bridge the existing fissure in humanity itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C. Raja Mohan, a prominent Indian foreign policy analyst, considers this timeless current of civilisational ethic to be India’s strategy of cultural diplomacy and soft power politics. It acts as a symbol of cultural nationalism to counter China’s expansionist nationalism. PM Modi’s diplomatic outreach via his visits to cultural sites in Japan, China etc. and the Asia-Pacific Growth Corridor highlight India’s ancient civilisational connectedness with these countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a departure from the previous government, a crucial dimension of the Modi administration’s foreign policy is a vibrant and dynamic rapport with the diaspora. Any cultural ambassador talking about India’s foreign policy, both consciously and unconsciously, would speak in the language of multilateralism. The Modi administration endorses this contact with the diaspora both quantitatively and qualitatively by making it a part of its development agenda (Grievance redressal, rule simplification, public meetings etc). It has taken steps to strengthen this contact through the consistent use of social media. In fact, it would appear that the Prime Minister’s much criticised ceaseless foreign visits have indeed been fruitful. The PM had fruitful interactions with leaders of the US and Japan on the lines of the G20 Summit in Buenos Aires. China, Russia, and Australia have also come within its loop. This becomes important for the proper operationalisation of India’s “Act East” Policy. The narrative of  &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; became so popular that the then US Secretary of State, John Kerry stated that America shared this goal and was willing to work in full cooperation with the new government to realise it. The PM has successfully constructed India’s narrative on global challenges, even if real peace with neighbours and actual success in the West is yet to be a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, since foreign policy is a continuum, there cannot usually be a tectonic change when governments change. India’s former PM Rajiv Gandhi evoked &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; to challenge the concept of First, Second and Third World Countries, putting forward his idea of one world and “Earth citizens”. Modi’s ideological predecessor, Mr Vajpayee referred to it at the Asia Pacific forum to put forward the traditional Indian understanding of human rights as being universal. In his Harvard Alumni Association address, Prime Minister Manmohan Singh contrasted &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; with Huntington’s “Clash of Civilizations” to assert his preference for the former philosophy of global unity. It’s almost as if the continuous narrative has been that the idea of &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is the idea of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Kissinger (well, obviously) once stated: “A country that demands moral perfection in its foreign policy can achieve neither perfection nor security.” India’s world-embracing philosophical narrative stands against communal polarisation and regional jingoism. But this is far from being a reality at all. Regional jingoism has become the very definition of India’s relationship with Pakistan or China. Not unlike Trump v Kim Jong-un, the most recent espousal of ‘universal brotherhood’ between Messrs. Imran Khan and Narendra Modi was reduced to mean tweets. The relationship with China has only superficial bonhomie; post the stand-off in the Himalayas in 2017, both India and China have been low-key at loggerheads over trade and border disputes. Finally, the humanitarian Rohingya crisis is being ignored by India—which is deporting Rohingya refugees and doing nothing to rebuke Myanmar’s organised genocide. The philosophy of &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; preaches tolerance in a highly insular world where race and ethnicity are used to incite hate crimes against humanity. But the chief proponent of that philosophy falters in promoting that in its own country and in its neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though an ideal, a world that lives as one family is worth creating. It works for India as well, making it a force of good in the world. It reflects the changing horizons of India’s foreign policy marked by the opening of several arenas of untapped opportunity. It may be worthwhile to consider projecting &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; in a more sustained manner at various global forums so that it may find resonance all over the world. Yet actions speak louder than words. India needs to deal with challenges pragmatically and innovatively, it has to fix its relationships with its neighbours and actually stand up for human rights in South Asia. For the last thing that should happen to &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is it being reduced to an empty slogan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The great Indian mystic and seer Swami Vivekananda once remarked, “All differences in this world are of degree and not of kind, because oneness is the secret of everything.” This idea finds reflection in the way India engages with the world via its foreign policy. Foreign policy is undoubtedly an important part of any government or administration’s agenda. This is especially so in the case of the current Indian government led by Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who is (in) famous for his numerous foreign and diplomatic trips. To Modi, “Foreign policy is about finding the common meeting points.” And it is in this context that PM Modi refers to the Sanskrit phrase “Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam” which roughly translates to mean “the world is one family” as being India’s philosophy. This is not just a descriptive phrase, rather it is the mantra of India’s diplomatic lexicon. Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam is a Vedantic thought and is an integral part of Hindu philosophy. It stresses compassion, collaboration, partnership and coexistence with zero vested interests. In fact, a “Universal Brotherhood Day” is observed on September 11 every year to commemorate Swami Vivekananda’s speech in Chicago on religious harmony.</summary></entry></feed>