<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-16T20:04:57+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Story of Easter</title><link href="/The-Story-of-Easter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Easter" /><published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Story-of%20Easter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Story-of-Easter">&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, everyone has a worldview, a lens through which he/she views the world, however implicit this worldview might be. And every worldview is, ultimately, a story. I don’t mean this in a condescending manner – stories can be true! My mother used to tell me stories about my childhood, and I have no doubt concerning the sincerity of her testimony. In fact, it is stories that drive our world. Everyone has their own story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this on the twelfth of April, 2020. It is a Sunday, it is Easter. And what better to write on this occasion than to simply tell the story of Easter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world is a strange, dark and forsaken world. Even in the midst of apparent joy, there is deep and real suffering. Even the ancient Indian prince Siddhartha could not help but realise that the world was filled with pain and anguish. And this realisation was so shocking and heart-wrenching for him that, as the legend goes, he forsook all royalty in search for the enlightenment that he believed would reveal to him the secret of joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things haven’t changed much. In fact, today’s world is filled with Siddharthas, desperate to discover the secret of happiness. Every advertisement you have ever seen, every product you have been keen to buy, every place you have wanted to visit, every prize you have been ambitious to win – in other words, everything you have ever done, you have done it in the hope that what you are about to do will finally bring you the joy and peace that your heart desires – or at the very least, will increase the joy that you already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, here you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I too was a lot like Siddhartha. In fact, my mother wanted to name me Siddhartha, but ultimately decided against it for fear that I would ultimately become a monk. But against all hope, as it turned out, I did have a very ‘monastic’ spirit, even early on. From very early on in my life, I have been searching for answers – answers to the big questions of life. Why am I here? What is my purpose? Why does this world exist? Where am I going?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: what does it all mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thirst to discover these answers eventually became like a madness, like an obsession that had wormed itself deep into my psyche. I’m certain I was the only person in seventh grade who did not know how to play cricket, but who had, in fact, read the entire Bhagavad Gita cover to cover. I was the only kid in high school who was not a Muslim but who wanted to carry the Qur’an with him to read during the tiffin break. I was, in other words, probably exactly the kind of person my mother had initially dreaded I would become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most people, I sought for something that would give purpose to my life: religion, politics, worldly success as a writer or an actor were high on the list. And yet, the questions remained. At one point in my life, I even contemplated raw, naked materialist atheism. I started reading atheist literature and was initially greatly impressed by the force of the rhetoric. Richard Dawkins, in particular, was a crucial influence. There he stood, marshalling all the powers of reason and science in an intellectual assault upon all forms of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, for a while, it seemed the candle had been blown out. There was no god. There was no purpose. There was no meaning to anything. There was no good, there was no evil – there was simply matter, endlessly morphing. As Christopher Hitchens wrote, “To the dumb question, ‘Why me?’ the cosmos barely bothers to return the reply: why not?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atheist ‘enlightenment’ informed me that, at best, I was an accident. I didn’t have to be here, but I was. And I would one day flicker out of existence. I came into being for no reason, and eventually, I would perish for no reason. And all my precious joys, passions, loves, desires, ambitions, fears and sorrows would perish with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the worldview which the atheists presented to me, death was more real than life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was then that I encountered a person who completely changed my life. His name was Dr William Lane Craig. An academic philosopher of religion and a deeply Christian soul, he was a man who had debated leading atheists at universities around the world. He had faced off against big names like Lawrence Krauss, Dan Barker, Sam Harris, Peter Atkins and a whole host of other atheist heavyweights. And with him, for the first time, I saw someone who was able to give a clear and intellectually compelling case in favour of theism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, as I studied more, I came to realise that most militant atheism was more motivated by anger against religion than any careful consideration of the question of whether or not God exists. Many of the arguments atheists had been putting forward, I realised, were extremely poor and shabby, often based upon misunderstandings and caricatures of Christian arguments and theology. And some of the leading atheists like Lawrence Krauss seemed unwilling to even consider the possibility of there being a God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than overthrowing dogmas, at times it seemed that the atheists were championing new dogmas – dogmas based less upon careful intellectual thought and more upon prejudice and hatred for a particular social order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I identify not as an atheist, but as a convinced believer in Jesus Christ. I believe in Jesus – and, even more unthinkably, in the Catholic Church - because I believe Christianity – and Catholicism – are true. And I believe the story of Christianity, which is really the story of Easter, can truly change people’s lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible opens with a very grand and simple line: In the beginning, God created the heavens and earth. In the Biblical worldview, God is the reason why this universe exists. God created us, and we exist because of Him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Bible also tells us that human beings sinned. Though we were originally created holy and good, we turned against God and rebelled against Him. All the evil that exists in the world is merely the outworking of man’s original sin. And the bad news is that none of us is innocent, because we have all participated in this unholy work of sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the good news that Christianity brings is the proclamation that God did not abandon us. On the contrary, He descended from heaven and became one of us. He shared in our misery, our suffering, our loneliness, our pain and our anguish. But He did not share in our sins. He was crucified by men who hated His claims, but as He was dying on the Cross, He offered His life as a sacrifice – to atone for the sins of man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the powers of evil gathered together and climaxed on the Cross of Jesus 2,000 years ago… because there was no sin more grotesque than the murder of God’s only Son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the Christian worldview, death did not have the last word. On the contrary, Jesus Christ rose from the dead, physically, bodily, on the third day, triumphing over the powers of sin and death. Though men murdered Him, death could not hold Him, because He had committed no sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who hold to materialist dogma will scoff at this idea. For countless souls, miracles and resurrections are the stuff of legend. They cannot happen and do not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you doubt the Resurrection, then I highly recommend you to take the time to study it, historically. The Oxford atheist philosopher (and later convert to theism, though not to Christianity) Antony Flew admitted in his debate with the historian Gary Habermas that the Resurrection of Jesus had better evidence than claimed miracles in any other religion. The Gospels, after all, are not myths written centuries after the time of Jesus, but rather are biographical accounts that can, more or less, all be traced back to the first century. Though written by various authors, they all testify that Jesus rose bodily from the dead. It is the same with the letters of Paul of Tarsus, an anti-Christian Jew who was later converted after seeing a vision of the resurrected Jesus. His letter to the Galatians contains a moving testimony of his conversion, and his story is corroborated by the Book of Acts, written by a man named Luke. These documents I speak of are not fabrications, but rather the writings of real people, who lived at specific times in history, and whose biographical and at times autobiographical claims largely corroborate each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my mind, the Resurrection of Jesus is the single most extraordinary event of human history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I invite you – whoever you may be – to consider the claims of Christianity for yourself. You have nothing at all to lose. If Christianity is true, then you have everything to gain from discovering its truthfulness. But if it’s false, then a careful study will only reveal its falsity, because the truth cannot ultimately be hidden. Either way, you will increase your knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What convinced me was the intellectual arguments in favour of God’s existence, the extraordinary testimony of the resurrection of Jesus, the fulfilled prophecies of the Old Testament, the beauty and power of the very words of the Saviour, and, of course, my personal experience of grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you might have questions, and you might want to learn more. If this is so, I rejoice in this, and I encourage you wholeheartedly to follow the truth wherever it leads. A good place to start is the YouTube channel Capturing Christianity, which regularly hosts discussions between Christian and atheist intellectuals and scholars. Bishop Robert Barron’s book &lt;em&gt;Catholicism: A Journey to the Heart of the Faith&lt;/em&gt; is also a great place to start. I also highly recommend the work of Edward Feser, an atheist philosopher whose studies in the philosophy of religion and mind eventually led him to convert to Christianity – I especially commend his book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs of the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;, which, in my mind, is the best intellectual and reasoned defence of classical theism that has been made in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, I urge you to take the time out and read the New Testament, which is a collection of these ancient historical writings that testify to the life and works of Jesus of Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that there are people who will read this article of mine and laugh. Why then do I write? Why then do I spend so much time telling people about a man who lived 2,000 years ago, a man I have never met in person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I believe this man is no mere man, but rather the incarnate Son of God. I write because this Man has changed my life, and He can change yours as well, if only you allow Him. And if you do, you will come to possess a joy that the world cannot give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telling people about the amazing person that is Jesus is worth any sacrifice and any cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the faith that has inspired millions, that has shaken empires, that has changed the course of human history. This is the faith of the martyrs, the confessors and the saints of the Cross. And this is the audacity with which I can stare death in the eye and proclaim that Christ is risen and that He lives forever more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Omidvar</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part II)</title><link href="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part II)" /><published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II">&lt;p&gt;The similarities between 18th century France and modern America apply not only to the background to the French Revolution but to the early stages of the Revolution in which a moderate, professional bourgeoisie sought to consolidate their power and stem the tide of economic and political radicalism emanating from the peasantry and sans-culottes. This article chronicles the various aspects of this divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Representative Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Blanning, writing in &lt;em&gt;The Pursuit of Glory&lt;/em&gt;, argued that the French Revolution “wrapped into one explosive package the three great abstractions of modern politics: the People, the State, and the Nation”, and that “the French people announced their arrival as the main actors in the nation’s political life.” That sovereignty resided in the nation and that Louis XVI was answerable not to God but to the constitutional law of the State (for the first part of the Revolution anyway), were principles that would lead to the self-assertion of the French people, as mass participation in assemblies and demonstrations and universal conscription under the Jacobins meant that they could no longer be ignored. But for the first part of the Revolution, representation was monopolised by the most middle-class, reformist elements of the French society. America today suffers from a similar problem, as the DNC continuously props up Joe Biden’s campaign, and acts as an obstacle to any substantive change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Estates-General sat on May 5, 1789, Louis XVI having had little choice over its convocation following the difficulties in levying taxes and rents on an increasingly recalcitrant peasantry, coupled with the fears of the bourgeoisie that the loans they had made to the State might not be paid back. The Third Estate was represented by 610 men, about 1/6th of whom were capitalists and bankers, and many of whom were lawyers, indicating that despite representing 95% of the French people, the Third Estate exclusively advanced the interests of the educated middle classes. As such, the Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen, which Lafayette consulted Thomas Jefferson in drawing up, was a crystallisation of Enlightenment principles that affirmed the universal power of reason, the ability of man to surmount all obstacles and control his own government and society, and the principle of equality before the law with noble privileges abolished. Article IV of the Declaration stated that liberty constituted anything that did not harm others by infringing on the rights to liberty, property and security and that only the rule of law could delineate these boundaries. Private property remained a ‘natural right’, and the unchecked ability to accumulate capital and influence the political process did not infringe any of the aforementioned negatively-defined ‘rights’, and so was sanctified by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Eric Hobsbawm, “A constitutional monarchy based on a propertied oligarchy expressing itself through a representative assembly was more congenial to most bourgeois liberals than the democratic republic which might have seemed a more logical expression of their theoretical aspirations.” The demands articulated by the peasantry for the restoration of communal lands and material prosperity could be ignored, and by August 10, 1789, the bourgeoisie had taken up arms against the peasantry in Dauphine and Burgundy. Characterising peasant agitations as the work of ‘brigands’, the troops were called out to crush all men without professions and domiciles. This brutality saw 160 prisoners killed at Cluny, and 80 hanged in Lyon. Following the storming of the Bastille and the August 4 reforms that established equality in taxation and admission to public office, in addition to the redemption of manorial lands, it was clear that the peasantry and sans-culottes were the vessels of social change, repelled by bourgeois anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glaring flaws in a supposedly ‘representative’ system have also shown themselves in the recent Democratic primaries, where Bernie Sanders’ campaign has cratered. In Iowa last month, the app meant to coordinate the results of the Caucus mysteriously crashed, and it later transpired that the app was built by a for-profit company named Shadow Inc. that Pete Buttigieg’s campaign had paid millions of dollars. The US Constitution, like France’s Declaration of the Rights of Man, protects the rights of private business to hike prices, depress wages and lock other competitors out of the market, and the rights of political institutions such as the DNC to sabotage the electoral process in favour of candidates who are more conducive to a capitalist economic setting. Nothing legally prevents the DNC from limiting the number of debates and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-politics/bernie-sanders-democratic-primary-dnc-convention-superdelegates-nomination-2020-election-a9363626.html&quot;&gt;blocking Bernie Sanders from winning the nomination.&lt;/a&gt; The freedoms of speech and voluntary exchange are theoretical abstractions that give way to the realities of market competition and the profit motive, as while individuals enjoy the superficial freedoms to participate in democracy, the real power lies in the hands of multinational corporations or nepotistic political behemoths like the DNC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Shades of Moderation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moderate voices within the National Assembly, who would later go on to form the Legislative Assembly in 1791, recognised that their interests were broadly in line with a limited monarchy, rather than a democratic republic. In what became the National Constituent Assembly, a class of propertied ‘active citizens’ formed a constitutional monarchy that banned trade unions and guild corporations, instituted the enclosure of communal lands and sold off ecclesiastical domains. These reforms were designed to create an internal market for goods, rather than to satiate the demands of the peasantry, as the ensuing price fluctuations led to agitations in rural areas. The distinction between the property-owning moderates of the Legislative Assembly who favoured opening up internal markets and creating a class of landless agrarian wage-labourers, and the peasantry and sans-culottes who favoured the communal ownership of land and higher income and inheritance tax was becoming more evident. The storming of the Tuileries and the establishment of the National Convention in 1792 was the apotheosis of this struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incompatibility of moderate defenders of the status quo with the vast numbers demanding transformative change is also characteristic of the schisms between Bernie Sanders and his supporters with the centrist Democrats. Much like the Girondins and moderates in the National Constituent Assembly, Joe Biden and his supporters pretend to rail against the corruption and despotism of the Trump administration while obscuring how much they have in common with the Republicans. In addition to his already disastrous record of voting in favour of NAFTA, supporting the war in Iraq and playing a key role in the war on drugs that has devastated many families (particularly Black and Hispanic), Biden continues to oppose Medicare for All, even suggesting that he would &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politifact.com/factchecks/2020/mar/10/facebook-posts/when-biden-was-asked-if-he-would-veto-medicare-all/&quot;&gt;veto it if it passed both houses and came to his desk.&lt;/a&gt; Furthermore, the centrist Democrats and Bernie Sanders’ supporters are separated not only by policy disagreements but a profound and seemingly irreconcilable divergence in worldview. The centrist Democrats are consequentialist; it is unsurprising that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2020/03/suburbanites-are-backing-biden/607726/&quot;&gt;base of primarily middle-class professionals&lt;/a&gt; are concerned with results and efficacy above all else, and maintain that the ends (beating Trump) justify the means (nominating Biden). Much like the bureaucratic moderates in the Legislative Assembly, the centrist Democrats view capitalism as a natural accompaniment to their utilitarian, consequentialist worldview. If one believes that man is a rational, utility maximising agent entering into voluntary exchanges with others, then the consequences of mutual trade and transaction are all that matters, and anything not amenable to the rationalist calculus of profitability can be discarded. Bernie Sanders’ supporters are more ideological (and, indeed, deontological), advocating for transformative measures such as Medicare for all and the abolition of ICE as ends in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be mentioned, however, that the situation in France that enabled the storming of the Bastille in 1789 and the Tuileries in 1792 is not entirely analogous to the modern American situation, as the peasantry and sans-culottes in France represented a broadly unified coalition, committed to establishing communally-owned land and preventing monopolisation and speculation. They had both suffered the effects of inflation and famine during the 1770’s and 1780’s, and both saw their enemy as the nobility and bourgeois professionals. The American working class, by contrast, remains divided along racial lines, as well as on geographic and occupational lines. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aese.psu.edu/directory/smm67/Election16.pdf?wpisrc=nl_daily202&amp;amp;wpmm=1&quot;&gt;A study from Penn State University&lt;/a&gt; showed that Donald Trump performed best in swing states that were worst affected by deindustrialisation and the opioid epidemic, and had experienced employment losses over recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political divisions between professional, liberal capitalists who sought to make an existing system more amenable to their interests and the disaffected masses who sought radical change are common to both late Ancien Regime France and 21st century America. The disillusionment with the machinery of governance that led the sans-culottes to believe that the Estates General did not represent them also motivates many Bernie Sanders supporters who view the DNC as an obstacle to power. If the French Revolution was the time for the French people to assert themselves as a prominent force, then the coming economic depression may foreground the schism between unrepresentative political institutions and the people they have disenfranchised.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The similarities between 18th century France and modern America apply not only to the background to the French Revolution but to the early stages of the Revolution in which a moderate, professional bourgeoisie sought to consolidate their power and stem the tide of economic and political radicalism emanating from the peasantry and sans-culottes. This article chronicles the various aspects of this divide.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban</title><link href="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban" /><published>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalyst for the aforementioned sad tale, the US-Taliban peace accord, signed February 29, 2020 holds the US time-bound to remove its troops within the decided 14-month time period, but not the Taliban to keep its promises. The removal of UN sanctions under the peace deal further weakens any leverage that the US might hold in Afghanistan. With the removal of the US-Troops, and a burgeoning Taliban influence, the people of Afghanistan have a bleak future to look forward to, and India, perhaps not as worse off, is definitely in the line of fire.s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No individual who has ever witnessed an India-Pakistan cricket match can be ignorant of the 70-year old festering wound between the two countries. The unceasing tussle for power between the two countries and Pakistan’s inclination towards providing refuge to terrorist organisations as a way to one-up India is not a secret. And, consequently, Pakistan’s close friendship with and ideological alikeness to the Taliban is the primary impetus to the threat to India’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan has been responsible for harbouring prominent terrorist organisations such as JeM and LeT on its territory and providing them protection after attacks on India. While Taliban promises not to allow Al-Qaeda in Afghanistan, the aforementioned organisations have been left out of the deal, allowing these terrorist organisations the opportunity to garner support and refuge in Afghanistan as well. Pakistan was a staunch supporter of having the Taliban as an active participant in the 2001 Bonn Agreement which was intended to establish an Afghani government after the Taliban’s removal. Furthermore, Pakistan’s support of a Taliban-led government in Afghanistan only makes Pakistan dearer to them. Juxtaposed with India’s past dealings (or lack thereof) with Taliban, India is likely to find itself in an ‘enemy of my friend’ situation. India has historically vehemently refused to acknowledge the Taliban as anything other than a terrorist organisation and has always supported the Afghanistan government. On a quest to counter Pakistani influence in Afghanistan, India has spent considerable time, money and effort to build a trusting relationship with the Afghan government through its multiple development and infrastructure projects, posing them as a direct adversary to the Taliban. And now that the Afghan government is itself in a precarious position, India’s assurance of relative peace on the India-Afghanistan border is dwindling and its efforts conclude to be naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another facet of this predicament is the apparent and sudden benevolence shown by the US to Pakistan. Pakistan has been a key player in bringing the Taliban to the table long enough for a peace accord to be established. And considering that President Trump’s re-election campaign is contingent on him bringing the American troops back, he currently considers Pakistan to be in his good books. Hence, Pakistan finds itself in a far more favourable position to cause considerable damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the US is by association to the Taliban making deals with the Haqqani network as well. The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008. Hence, America is giving legitimacy and validation to a terrorist group which has posed a threat to India in the past. This legitimisation and validation by a country that India considers to be an ally is only an affirmation of the USA’s indifference to any more peace violations by the Taliban in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to this, the instability currently in India over the abrogation of Article 370 in Kashmir and the mass unrest and chaos due to the CAA/NRC protests, India finds itself in a pernicious position. The Al-Qaeda and the Haqqani network have made attempts and calls to fight India on the issue of Kashmir and on behalf of Pakistan. With the newly-minted support in Afghanistan and far more freedom once US-troops leave, India will have its hands full dealing with them. Much like Afghanistan, India’s dependence upon the US troops to fight a war not their own proves to be its Achilles heel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one was to consider the possibility of India stepping up to protect its borders, it doesn’t seem improbable, however, it is the approach that remains to be seen. India could increase border security, employ more force and troops, it can hope for the peace accord to hold and pray that the Taliban does not establish a government and Pakistan does not use this to its advantage to attempt an ambush. Or perhaps, less likely and more smartly, India can continue to build and facilitate growth and development projects in Afghanistan, making India a friend to anyone in authority, very much like it did with the previous Ghani-led government. One cannot tell for sure what the currently-ruling BJP government will do, and keeping in mind their almost negligible previous response to the peace accord, we can only hope for some undertaking. The consequences of the deal may not be apparent right now especially when currently, the COVID-19 pandemic takes precedence, as it should, yet it will not always be so and India must be ready with a water-proof plan for when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?</title><link href="/British-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?" /><published>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/British-Economy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/British-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recently introduced skills-focused points-based immigration policy by PM Boris Johnson is going to have a huge impact on the economy. More than one-third of doctors, pharmacists, and dentists in the UK are foreign-born, as are more than 20% of nurses. Seven in 10 workers in the meat-processing industry are from the EU. However, next year onwards, the UK’s Byzantine immigration system for non-EU migrants will also apply to those from the EU. While immigration criteria for skilled labour will be loosened, it will be almost impossible for non-skilled labour to obtain a work visa. One of the hardest-hit sectors will be ‘care for’ the elderly. There is already a shortage of workers in this sector. Moreover, ‘care for’ work is the occupation with the most projected employment growth in the coming years. The UK under the guise of treating EU and non-EU migrants equally on the basis of skills is actually turning away industrious and enterprising individuals who help power its economy and provide for the basic needs of its greying population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the recent examples of what the British government is doing wrong. There are certain structural problems as well that need to be addressed. Capital spending as a share of GDP has fallen to around 17% from 20% in 2007. Capital investment is required in order to ensure long-term economic growth by increasing future production capacity. Moreover, the expenditure on R&amp;amp;D remains persistently below 2% of the GDP. In addition to this, the output per person has remained well below than what would have been termed as satisfactory. The unemployment figures have been relatively good recently, however, these have come at the cost of stagnating real wages and lower labour productivity per hour. Moreover, there has been a constant increase in the number of &lt;em&gt;zero-hour&lt;/em&gt; contracts. In such contracts, the workers have no guarantee of how many hours of work they will be getting. This could be one of the major reasons for under-employment in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2019, the manufacturing activity took a turn for the worse with the sharpest deterioration in output in more than seven years. The IHS Markit/CIPS manufacturing Purchasing Managers’ Index sank to 47.5 in December from 48.9 in November, although it was marginally higher than an initial flash estimate of 47.4. The figure marks the eighth consecutive month with a reading below 50, which indicates a majority of businesses reporting deteriorating activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has a large current account deficit as well. It was around 4.6% of the GDP in 2019. This has been majorly due to negative investor sentiments because of all the political instability. Also, the UK economy has been hit badly by the economic slowdown in the major trading partners, namely, China and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another worrying aspect is the monopoly power in public utility services like electricity and gas. A lack of competition keeps prices high and affects the real incomes of millions of consumers. Moreover, economic, social and demographic pressures continue to mount on public services such as the NHS. Some economists argue that the NHS needs a major injection of extra funding over the next 5-10 years; others believe that there are enough savings still to be achieved by addressing inefficiencies in public health care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With economic forecasts suggesting that the UK’s GDP growth won’t exceed 1.5%, the government will have to watch its discretionary spending even if a recession is avoided, because of spending on national services like the NHS. Moreover, there is also an additional threat to the economy posed by coronavirus. Much remains to be seen how the policymakers will tackle this burden and if the economy will be able to overcome this. The current situation doesn’t leave room for high hopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to plunging stock markets worldwide, the Bank of England cut its key rate by half a percentage point to 0.25%.  The Bank of England introduced a new program for cheap credit and reduced a special capital buffer to give banks more room to lend as well. Rishi Sunak, the Chancellor of the Exchequer,  also scrapped business rates for small firms to help them deal with the disruption caused by the outbreak of coronavirus. Business rates are taxes to help pay for UK local services, charged on most commercial properties. Britain’s retail sector has complained for the longest time that the current business rates system was unfair and needed reform. While the retail sector accounts for 5% of the UK economy, it is burdened with 10% of all business taxes, and 25% of business rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chancellor Sunak also scrapped a planned cut in corporation tax, and he is expected to raise around £6 billion from scrapping a planned drop, money he indicated could be spent on hospitals and doctors across the country. He also announced that the government would establish a coronavirus job retention scheme for all employers, large or small, that will cover 80% of wages, up to £2,500 a month. This scheme was introduced for an initial period of three months but can also be extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a month after stepping into the new job, Rishi Sunak has a lot to prove. There are a lot of expectations for the new Chancellor. Additionally, when the UK is facing an increasing threat from the coronavirus, his job becomes all the more important. It remains to be seen whether Rishi Sunak will break free of any puppet strings or be swept aside by a Treasury insider. Brexit coupled with the coronavirus outbreak has left the country on borrowed time to revamp the economy. What happens in the next few weeks could possibly define the future of the country in the coming years. What we need to wait and watch is whether the government and its policies fall into place in order to break free the shackles of a never-ending system of going back and forth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sexism and the City</title><link href="/Sexism-and-the-City" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sexism and the City" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Sexism-and-the-City</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Sexism-and-the-City">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism can affect anyone, however, there have been few men on the receiving end. It affects men and boys when they don’t conform to gender roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this article, we will restrict the ambit of our discussion to only the University level in India. Sexist attitudes are not just limited to boys rating girls on a scale of 0-10 based on their physical appearances. It has transcended into limiting the opportunities for women, imposing draconian rules and observing traditions that are misogynistic and chauvinist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often consider academia as the citadel of everything fair and progressive. However, we don’t live in a utopian world. Just like other institutions that have these notions of male superiority deep-rooted in their practices and norms, so does education. Many people benefit from these power dynamics in the status quo, and thus, have no incentive to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a stark imbalance in the male to female ratio in many courses such as law, management, and STEM disciplines. Considered the holy grail of education and achievement, Indian Institutes of Technology (IITs), suffer from the worst gender imbalance with only 9.3% of females. This gap further increases with progression in these careers, with an utter lack of women in leadership positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see this trend across central universities in India. Out of 46 central universities, only 5 have women placed as the heads of the institutions. Even in India’s most liberal universities, like Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU), no women has ever been the head of the institute. The selection committees are dominated by men, who give little weightage to women candidates as many view women as someone who has stolen a job a man was entitled to do. This perception has risen from the cultural view that men are the bread-earners of the family while women are the homemakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In colleges with extreme gender disproportion, the environment becomes testosterone-driven, leading to women students being subjected to sexual innuendos and sexist remarks. Language and communication make people recognise or demean their contribution to society. Our language shapes our thoughts, and the way we think influences our actions. Gender-discriminatory language reinforces sexist attitudes and behaviours. Thus, female students become conditioned to accept subtle sexism and lewd remarks as the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism in Indian universities isn’t just limited to leadership positions but encompasses norms that affect the day-to-day lives of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many colleges across India, dress codes are imposed on women. For example, The Government Medical College, Kerala issued a dress code for its female students instructing them not to wear jeans, leggings, short tops or noisy ornaments. Many girls’ hostels also follow curfews, thus increasing the red tape for them to step out. Many institutions like Jamia Milia University, IITs and the University of Delhi have come under the light in the past for such rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such draconian measures show how expecting equality remains a far-off dream for girls. These rules concretise the notion that the price for the safety of women is curbing their freedom rather than bringing a systemic change in the attitude of men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symbiosis Center for Media and Communication (SCMC) Pune is widely recognised for its option of ‘film and television’ specialisation as a part of its three-year undergraduate program. In her article for &lt;em&gt;The Print&lt;/em&gt;, Vaishnavi Suresh, an SCMC alumnus highlights the rampant sexism in the coveted institution. Being a media college, the students spend a large amount of time in classes watching films. Vaishnavi, however, notes how the students barely had any female filmmakers as role models. In an incident where some people from her class suggested they study a female filmmaker, the professor shot down their requests and instead taught them about another male filmmaker. She also noted how by the time they came to their 3rd year, only 2 women out of her batch were still invested in the camera by practising photography or videography. She cites the reason for this to be the “reality of the industry drilled into them constantly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A college that prides itself on being liberal lacks showing its students that women could be role models too. Having female role models is important for breaking the stereotype of men being better than women to propagate for a more inclusive world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, while the #MeToo movement was still in its nascent stage, the students of Women Centred Practices at Tata Institute of Social Sciences (TISS), Mumbai organised a ‘Gender Sensitisation Week’ in their campus. Amidst the gender sensitisation week, a signed comment was noticed on a banner that was put up for people to anonymously share accounts of sexist instances on campus. It read, “Sexism is an accusation, sluts level against dissenting voices for recognising that a slut is a slut.” Instances like these make one realise that the notion of some campuses being ‘more sensitive and liberal than the rest of the world’, is nothing but a facade. People still trivialise sexual harassment, use the word ‘slut’ as a derogatory term and push aside voices of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a few pre-university colleges in Bengaluru set higher cut-off marks for girls for admission into the courses. On inquiring about the reason behind this move, the Vice-Chancellor of Christ PU College, Fr Abraham VM, commented - “Girls are smart, and this is not a new trend. If there is no higher cut-off, the college will have only girls. The higher cut-off is to bring in gender balance.” Subsequently, the cut-off for science stream in Christ college was fixed at 93.92% for girls and 91.04% for boys. This move begs the question that in a society where historically almost every classroom has been dominated by men, why do we fear if women step into those shoes. It seems like a move to &lt;em&gt;punish&lt;/em&gt; women for breaking the glass ceiling despite being on the worse off end of the access to opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most famous sexist tradition would be the regressive Virgin Tree ‘Pooja’ on Valentine’s Day at Hindu College (University of Delhi). The Pooja is a customary tradition wherein the boys’ hostel decorates a ‘virgin tree’ on campus with condoms and posters of an actress naming her the Damdami Mai. This actress, seen as a sex symbol, is ‘worshipped’ on Valentine’s Day and according to legend, the people partaking in this practice lose their virginity in the coming six months or at least get into a relationship. In a university space, where we regard sexuality-related conversations as a taboo, they often term such a celebration as ‘liberatory.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V-Day pooja, which has been taking place since 1953, is ridden in a Brahmanical and casteist notion of prayer and reward. Highly offensive and misogynistic, the pooja follows a hollow notion of ‘sex-positivity’ while overlooking homosexual relationships. The celebration reinforces the existing patriarchal structures which have ingrained insecurity in the minds of young women by reducing their value to just the pleasure of and determined by an external male gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;College is the first encounter of the young adults with reality by giving them a peek into the larger world out there. It introduces us to the workings of the ‘real world’ and underpins many of our perspectives and expectations in a social context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexist practices create a climate of fear and insecurity by producing feelings of worthlessness, self-censorship, and changes in behaviour. This further leads to the deterioration of people’s mental health and makes them acceptable to violence, as they now think they &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When students are exposed to these ideas in college, it either normalises these ideas for many by ingraining notions of male superiority. Or it makes people recognise and fight the problem. The wave of social consciousness and woke culture have made the youth today more liberal than their predecessors, leading to more inclusive spaces for women and homosexuals in institutions. They, however, remain a minority faction and their wokeness hasn’t led to a ripple effect big enough to shake down sexism on a bigger level. The boy’s hostel at Hindu College plans to host the Virgin Tree Pooja in 2021, many girls’ hostels continue to follow the archaic dress codes and curfews, and conversations among men will continue to be casually sexist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All over the world, people have celebrated 46 International Women’s Days and 6 Zero Discrimination Days and will celebrate many more, but until we abolish all discriminatory and sexist practices, we won’t be celebrating these days in their true essence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pink: The Hated Colour of Love</title><link href="/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pink: The Hated Colour of Love" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love">&lt;p&gt;The first image that props up in your mind when you think of the word ‘pink’ is probably a dainty young lady wearing a pretty pink dress. Indeed, for many people, especially girls, this colour represents weakness or ‘girly-ness’ because of what it has been associated with in recent years. The negative connotations associated with being ‘girly’ are very similar to the way in which we perceive most of the other so-called feminine words or traits. We have always associated the female gender with characteristics that are intrinsically inferior to those associated with the male gender. While females are seen as weak, submissive, caring and sensitive, males are seen as brash, well built, hard-working people with strong control over their emotions. “You fight like a girl”, “stop crying like a girl” and so on and so forth are very common in our conversations even today and they reflect the inherent mindset of the people in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pink represents a lot of rather adverse aspects of society in the eyes of many. One of the most important among them is the pink aisle in toy stores. This lane is meant only for young girls and is thus decorated accordingly, using the colour pink. Similarly, the lane meant for boys is decorated primarily using blue. A closer look at the items on display and for sale reveals a lot about us and our society. The blue lane has miniature construction kits, motor cars and so on: all toys that boys are ‘supposed’ to play with. Likewise, the pink lane houses a collection of kitchen sets, dolls and miniature makeup kits. What is happening here is subtle but significant. Not only are we, as a society, pushing a conventional binary structure of the gender system on our children, but we are also dictating what each gender is meant to be like. In other words, we are laying down the basis of gender roles from a very early age. Laura Bates, the founder of ‘Everyday Sexism’ believes ‘pinkification’ spreads the message that “women cook, men work”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While girls are expected to be obsessed with makeup, enjoying cooking and babysitting dolls, boys are directed towards tech using gender-specific toys. Research by the Institute of Engineering and Technology in 2016 suggests that STEM-based toys are three times more likely to target boys than girls. Jess Day of ‘Let Toys be Toys’ actively advocates for toys to be not categorised by gender for the same reason. In 2016, she was quoted saying: “We previously asked women engineers and scientists about the toys they played with as children and the most interesting find was not that they all played with construction or science toys, but they didn’t recall being aware of a distinction between girls’ and boys’ toys at all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem has been well addressed by Debbie Sterling in her TEDxPSU speech. She started her presentation by asking the audience to close their eyes and to imagine an engineer. She then asked them to tell her by a show of hands how many imagined a woman in that role. The number was underwhelming. In her roughly 17 minute long talk that followed, she quoted different researches to drive home the point that the problem of the astonishingly low number of women in STEM careers is not a biological issue but a cultural one. She attributed the loss in interest in science and technology among girls to the pink aisle. Sterling explained how she came to this conclusion by sharing stories of her own struggle as an engineering student. Being a very creative girl, she did not expect to find a course titled Engineering Drawing to be difficult and yet she did find it so. This course involved drawing in perspective and the guys in class excelled at it. She, however, had to put in a lot more effort to pass the course. Sterling explained that this is a rather common phenomenon and can be attributed to the fact that most girls have under-developed spatial skills. The majority of those who do well in spatial skills tests grew up with construction toys, irrespective of gender. The market did not, however, have construction toys targeted at girls. It was just not seen and is still popularly not seen as a ‘girly’ thing to do. Sterling went on to build an extremely popular construction toy for girls named GoldieBlox which featured the world’s first girl engineer character in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such pink related thing that women are not very happy about is the Pink Tax. This tax is not always a literal tax. It is a form of gender-based price discrimination observed today. Feminine versions of everyday items like razors and deodorants usually cost more than those meant for males. In fact, feminine hygiene products are astonishingly expensive in most countries. This includes menstruation hygiene products like sanitary pads and tampons. Research in the USA in 2019 by the New York City Department of Consumer Affairs revealed that women pay 13% more for personal health care products, 8% more for adult clothing, 7% more for toys and accessories and 4% more for children’s clothing than men. There are a lot of issues with this pink tax, especially since it seems as if the structure is penalising one for being born female. Menstruation is an essential human bodily process just like any other and to pay such high amounts for menstruation hygiene products is borderline oppressive. The main economic impact of this phenomenon is that women have less purchasing power, especially considering the fact that a gender-based pay gap already exists. Although recent activism in this matter has seen some positive outcomes in terms of repealing the pink tax in certain places like in Ohio, the price discrimination continues to exist in most other places in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is apparent that there are abundant instances where pink has been associated with something that not many are happy about. One thing that is bluntly clear is that this colour has been largely used to describe things, both positive and negative, that are related to the female gender. This notion of pink being only for girls is pushed on us over and over again. The pink ribbon is used to symbolise and raise awareness for breast cancer. The teenage section of Victoria’s Secret is named ‘Pink’. A 2016 Indian film about a molestation case filed by a woman was titled &lt;em&gt;Pink&lt;/em&gt;. This recurring appearance of pink in connection with the female gender has successfully established this shade as a predominantly feminine colour. Women are almost expected to like and wear pink and its variations and yet, there are conditions that come with it. People often criticise dark-skinned women seen wearing pink and other related shades. This really does not make any sense and might just be an expression of an additional stereotype that dark-skinned women are loud and confrontational, characteristics that the society does not believe goes well with the feminine gender. Conversely, women who do love pink and sparkles, as the stereotype suggests, are seen as weak, submissive, obsessed with appearance and unprofessional. Many have tried to destroy this image over the years. In 2019, a female scientist named Rita J King opted for an eye-catching sparkly ensemble to give a talk at NASA. This evoked both positive and negative responses from across the world. King later explained her decision later by stating “I came across this gown and remembered the little girls who sent me a letter and asked me to wear something sparkly… so they could believe that scientists could also be sparkly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of all this, movies popularly continue to portray women who love wearing pink as rather dumb, mean or maternal and any exception to this rule becomes a big deal - the idea is treated as the most important aspect of the plot and the movie is deemed as unusual and female-centric. All this is in spite of the fact that the nerd of the class, irrespective of gender, in any random school, can be a pink lover. It is almost an unspoken crime to portray them in the regular teen flicks that way and the female lead as a blue lover. The Pink Ranger is always the ‘girliest’ female in the group. The high school princesses who have spent their entire lives waiting to be crowned the Prom Queen and are always mean to other girls are more often than not seen wearing pink. Somehow in the movie world, blue and black lovers are never popular or ‘girly’. Have a look at the posters of &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; and other similar teen flicks for proof of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notable exceptions include movies like &lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde&lt;/em&gt;, where a pink loving, makeup obsessed, popular and beautiful fashion student named Elle goes on to become a successful lawyer. However, this transition happens only after she is dumped by her boyfriend, Warner Huntington III. Warner prefers to be with an all-blue or black wearing ‘serious’ woman who is studying law as it would improve his image in the real world. Elle cracks the LSATs and joins her ex-boyfriend’s college, Harvard Law School to win him over. Over the course of time, she realises how much of a terrible person her ex-boyfriend was and the sexism that exists in the world of law. One thing that is praiseworthy about this movie is that although Elle goes on to become a successful lawyer, she does not give up on her fashion-obsessed side-love for pink. In fact, Elle wins her first case using her knowledge of how a specific beauty procedure and its maintenance work and a fashion stereotype involving the gay community. Now, this might seem like she is being portrayed as someone whose knowledge is strictly restricted to the domain of fashion and that her winning the case was a fluke but she is previously shown as a hardworking and knowledgeable law student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have established the popular notions about the colour, let us talk about the several problems associated with this narrow view of pink. The laundry list begins with the fact that pink was a masculine colour for a very long time. It was established as a feminine colour only around the 1940’s. In 20th century Europe, the most common practice was to assign colour based on the complexion of the child and thus, any of the genders could be associated with pink or blue. Paintings from the 19th century show young boys wearing pink. In the 18th century, pink was actually seen primarily as a masculine colour as it is related to the ‘war-like’ red colour. A 1918 article published in &lt;em&gt;The Infants’ Department&lt;/em&gt; titled ‘Pink or Blue’ stated that the generally-accepted rule was that pink was for boys and blue for girls. It said, “The reason is that pink, being a decided and stronger colour is more suitable for the boy, while blue, which is more delicate and dainty, is prettier for the girl.” It is actually very difficult to pin-point when in history this role reversal of the colours took place. Baby boomers were probably the first to be dressed in the modern sex-specific coloured clothing that we are familiar with today. This took a hard hit during the women’s liberation movements of the 1960’s-70’s when the female participants of the movement started developing a view that dressing up stereotypically ‘girly’ would limit their opportunities and consequently, parents started preferring gender-neutral colours. However, the practices involving gender-specific colours are pretty prevalent even today and the numerous fancy gender reveal videos on social media bears testimony to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another very popular pink symbol from the past is the pink triangle. Back in the Germany of the 1930’s and 1940’s, the Nazis not only prosecuted the Jews but also several other groups of people. Homosexuals were one of them and this symbol was used for identification just as the David’s Star was used for the Jews. Bisexuals and transgenders were also included in this category. Back then, it was a symbol of utter shame. Later, in the 1970’s, it was revived as a symbol of protest against homophobia. Its popularity increased manifold in the 1980’s as the pink triangle established its place as a positive icon: a symbol of self and community identity. It commonly represented both the gay and the lesbian communities. The rainbow pride flag that we have come to popularly associate with the LGBTQIA+ community was originally designed by Gilbert Baker for the 1978 San Francisco Gay Freedom Day and had eight stripes. This version was soon replaced by the seven stripe version that we use and see today. The original flag had an additional pink stripe that was symbolic of sexuality. In fact, pink is very popularly associated with all kinds of love. No wonder Taylor Swift’s Lover era pieces are an explosion of pink. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, pink is fast-tracking its way to become a symbol of the feminist movement. Various activists and artists have made generous use of this colour to complement their views and activism. Let us take an example: American singer, P!nk aka Alecia Moore. She declared herself as a feminist long before any other popular artist, long before it was ‘in’. In 2006, she criticised Republican President, George Bush in her song titled, &lt;em&gt;Dear Mr President&lt;/em&gt;. The song’s lyrics like “What kind of father (parent) would take his own daughter’s rights away? What kind of father (parent) might hate his own daughter (child) if she were gay?” is an expression of her beliefs, her support for women’s rights activism and her support for the LGBTQIA+ community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, she has shared several stories of struggle and change on different platforms. The most memorable of these is perhaps her 2017 MTV Video Music Awards speech after she won the Michael Jackson Vanguard Award. She shared a story of her daughter who had once conveyed to her, “I’m the ugliest girl I know” and that she thought that she looked like a boy with long hair. That day, Pink sat down with her and talked to her about great artists who look very different especially androgynous artists, like Freddie Mercury, David Bowie, Prince, Michael Jackson, Kurt Cobain, Janis Joplin and so on. She also told her about the negative comments that she herself receives about her rather boyish look and the fact that that does not stop her from making great music and selling out arenas. Her message is clear: how one looks or dresses has nothing to do with one’s capacity to excel at something. Similarly, wearing pink does not make anyone any less of a capable person or any less of a feminist as the title of Scarlett Curtis’s book, &lt;em&gt;Feminists Don’t Wear Pink and Other Lies’&lt;/em&gt; suggests. By extension, being fashionable and ‘girly’ does not intellectually handicap anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, we are pretty far away from this realisation. In 2016, a young graphic designer named Katherine Young re-created the cover of &lt;em&gt;Girls’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum- articles on fashion and other career choices? Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and fashion-forward outfit less accomplished or symbolic of an empowered woman than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that most of the pink related problems that exist today exist because of our distorted perceptions of the colour and the undertones that cling onto the word. Associating the colour with conservative notions of gender is an utter disrespect of a shade that for years has symbolised love of all kinds and has represented all genders. While the issue will continue to persist until men start wearing pink casually in movies and in real life and women proudly wear feminine clothing in pastel shades without getting undermined, a lot of progress has been made over the last decade. Only time can tell us if we are capable of reaching a pedestal where we no longer associate a specific colour with a particular gender or certain traits&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The first image that props up in your mind when you think of the word ‘pink’ is probably a dainty young lady wearing a pretty pink dress. Indeed, for many people, especially girls, this colour represents weakness or ‘girly-ness’ because of what it has been associated with in recent years. The negative connotations associated with being ‘girly’ are very similar to the way in which we perceive most of the other so-called feminine words or traits. We have always associated the female gender with characteristics that are intrinsically inferior to those associated with the male gender. While females are seen as weak, submissive, caring and sensitive, males are seen as brash, well built, hard-working people with strong control over their emotions. “You fight like a girl”, “stop crying like a girl” and so on and so forth are very common in our conversations even today and they reflect the inherent mindset of the people in general.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can India Keep Up with The Coronavirus?</title><link href="/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can India Keep Up with The Coronavirus?" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus">&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus, a tiny virus, has been causing chaos across the world since January. Countries are going into lockdowns, international travel has been banned, businesses are shutting down and healthcare systems are coming under unprecedented pressure. The virus has led to a global standstill and thus, to a global slowdown of economic growth, if not a global recession. Policymakers are now considering or already taking quick large steps to both ease the health care challenges and stem the economic pain. The Economist Intelligence Unit (of &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt; magazine) estimates a negative growth rate of 2.2% of the GDP in countries of the G20 group for 2020. Amidst this crisis, one probably would have come across the talks about the trade-off between the lives of the people and the economy. No doubt, lives are of utmost importance, but not paying attention to the economy will critically affect the lives of the people once the crisis is over. The crisis will have an adverse impact on India which is already on the path of a slower growth rate. In this context, what has India done? And what can it do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Prime Minister has announced a nation-wide lockdown from March 23, 2020, for a period of 3 weeks, till April 15. Following this came the decisions to ban international travel and shut the state borders, with an exception to vehicles transporting essentials. All of the non-essential businesses (manufacturing, construction, IT, etc) have come to a grinding halt and this has led to a supply and demand shock to the economy of India. It is crucial to note that 92% of the Indian workforce is engaged in the informal sector and one could find hordes of people migrating across the country in search of a job. These people are largely construction workers or people working in farms and survive on their daily wages only. Two days after the lockdown was announced, the Central Government announced a package of ₹1.7 trillion to help the poorest sections of the society. The wages under the National Rural Employment Scheme (NRES) were increased to ₹202 (i.e. about $2.69) from ₹182 (i.e. about $2.42). The Central Government, among other things, has also announced an allowance of 5 kg rice (or wheat per person) and 1 kg of pulses per family each month for 3 months. Some Indian states have announced cash transfers to all subsidy cardholders, in addition to the Centre’s cash transfers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these two measures have some problems. First, the objective of a total lockdown is to practice social distancing and thereby, no one is allowed out. Now, transferring cash through NRES wouldn’t work because people cannot come out to work; and even if they did, they will form a gathering and hence, defeat the purpose of a lockdown. Second, the average daily minimum wage in India in 2014 was ₹272 (i.e. about $3.62 in todays money). For simplification purposes, let us assume it to be ₹200. Now, if a person works for, say, 5 days a week that person would earn ₹1,000. This would total to ₹4,000 a month. What this means is that they earn more than what is being offered now, and the ₹1,500-₹ 2,000 (Central plus State Governments) per month given to these migrant workers is simply not enough of an incentive for them to stay indoors, thus once again, defeating the purpose of the lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing worth considering here is the prices of essential commodities. Given the shortage of supply, prices of some essentials are likely to increase. This will slash the real value of the money being distributed to the beneficiaries and would not be able to support them. Therefore, the government should increase the amount (Amit Seru, a prominent economist from Stanford has said this should be 5-6% of the GDP) disbursed to the targeted groups, not restricting the scope of the beneficiaries. That a large proportion of people are in the informal sector makes the transfers difficult, but India has the mechanism to carry out these transfers. It is also imperative to note that without much emphasis on the accurate number of beneficiaries, India must rather focus on transferring the amount because time is of the essence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, due to the crisis there are demand and supply side shocks to all the economies. A majority of the economists polled by the IGM Booth panel, however, opined that the economic effects of demand side shocks are larger than those from the supply side. As the businesses shut, the income of the people fell and so did the demand for goods and services in the economy. This is a critical cycle where income and demand depend on each other and when one falls it drives down the other and this is accompanied by a sharp rise in unemployment (in the informal sector mainly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic crisis entailing the global pandemic is the textbook example of the good old Keynesian economics. And the conventional cure to this problem is fiscal expansion. Fiscal expansion, by way of government spending, will yield results with immediate effect. One cannot be concerned about the rise of fiscal deficit, given the seriousness of the current situation and it should be allowed to rise both at the Centre and the state level. The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Act (FRBM) can be amended or an ordinance can be issued to that effect. A greater degree of autonomy should be given to the states by means of allocation of funds or disbursal of the welfare schemes, as it is much faster to implement all these at the state level. For this, the contributions to the newly started PM-CARES should be distributed on war footing starting from the worst affected states. The government can also consider cutting down income tax rates (preferably, the lower brackets) and GST slabs at least for some period to boost the revival of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Governor of the Reserve Bank of India (RBI), the Indian central bank, has also announced a slew of measures by employing the tools of monetary policy alongside the government’s fiscal measures. The RBI cut down the repo rate by 0.75% and Cash Reserve Ratio by 100 basis points to 3%. The Reserve bank estimates these measures would result in an injection of ₹3.74 trillion into the economy. However, this should not be taken as is. For we do not know if the banks will slash the lending rates even as the RBI slashed the repo rate. Additionally, the demand is bound to increase after the lockdown is lifted. However, the question one must ask is will the demand be sufficient for the businesses to borrow money from the banks. Hence, we do not know whether the reduced interest rates would lead to an increase in investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, one thing is clear. This crisis is not conventional in the sense that the economy cannot be rescued in these times. This is because the non-essential services are shut down and cannot be opened until the lockdown is lifted. Even if India reopens, many businesses might find it difficult to start production because of the disruption of supply chains owing to the lockdown in other countries. Hence, growth will slow down. All India can do is take measures to revive demand once the world settles down.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Coronavirus, a tiny virus, has been causing chaos across the world since January. Countries are going into lockdowns, international travel has been banned, businesses are shutting down and healthcare systems are coming under unprecedented pressure. The virus has led to a global standstill and thus, to a global slowdown of economic growth, if not a global recession. Policymakers are now considering or already taking quick large steps to both ease the health care challenges and stem the economic pain. The Economist Intelligence Unit (of The Economist magazine) estimates a negative growth rate of 2.2% of the GDP in countries of the G20 group for 2020. Amidst this crisis, one probably would have come across the talks about the trade-off between the lives of the people and the economy. No doubt, lives are of utmost importance, but not paying attention to the economy will critically affect the lives of the people once the crisis is over. The crisis will have an adverse impact on India which is already on the path of a slower growth rate. In this context, what has India done? And what can it do?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Calvin Coolidge: Libertarian Hero or Economic Assassin?</title><link href="/Calvin-Coolidge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calvin Coolidge: Libertarian Hero or Economic Assassin?" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Calvin-Coolidge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Calvin-Coolidge">&lt;p&gt;In the American right, there has been longing for a fiscal conservative. For years, the most touted example was Ronald Reagan, and although he presided over one of the nation’s largest tax cuts, he ran up major deficits. With the election of President Trump and the implementation of his multiple socially conservative policies, many conservatives have cast away Ronald Regan as their poster-child for a conservative icon. But as far as issues go, neither can hold a candle to the smallest-government libertarian in American history: Calvin Coolidge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coolidge was born in Vermont in 1872 (ironically, the same state as the current democratic-socialist Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders). His father was a farmer, small business-owner and politician. Tragically, his mother died when he was only twelve years old. For college, Coolidge moved to Amherst in Massachusetts, then went on to open up a law firm in 1898. Seven years later, he married Grace Goodhue, a talkative social butterfly. She was an incredible contrast to Coolidge’s notoriously quiet and serious demeanour. Eventually, he started running for public office while branding himself as a progressive Republican. He quickly moved up through local government, the Massachusetts state legislature, and eventually was elected Governor. By today’s standard, one would think a progressive Republican from Massachusetts would be radically leftist, after all, Massachusetts is one of the most far-left states. However, over a hundred years ago, a progressive was not someone who advocated for transgender rights or the Green New Deal, but someone who fought for woman’s suffrage and the civil rights of people of colour. Nevertheless, they also saw a bigger and more powerful government as a means of producing this society. So how did Coolidge become both a libertarian hero and a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/calvin-coolidges-surprise-contribution-to-progressivism/&quot;&gt;progressive Republican&lt;/a&gt;”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As stated earlier, he was notoriously restrained: both in personality and in government action. He believed it was progressive to restrain the government from restricting the liberty of others’ access to civil rights. This stood in stark contrast to a stream of previous progressive Presidents who sought to expand the reach and size of government as much as possible, such as Woodrow Wilson and Theodore Roosevelt. In spite of his silent personality, Coolidge was chosen to be the Vice President of the Republican Nominee, Warren Harding, for the 1920 Presidential race. In a twist of fate, his opponent — James Cox — had chosen the polar opposite to be his Vice President: the one and only Franklin Delano Roosevelt. In that election, Harding and Coolidge won. Although Harding did have a very conservative administration, his corrupt practices got ahead of him in what is known as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.history.com/topics/roaring-twenties/teapot-dome-scandal&quot;&gt;The Teapot Dome Scandal&lt;/a&gt;.” In the midst of members right and left of Harding being found riddled with corruption, Harding died. Yes, just like that. He died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for the country’s sake, Coolidge was not found to be corrupt and &lt;a href=&quot;http://press-pubs.uchicago.edu/founders/tocs/a2_1_6.html&quot;&gt;was supposed to succeed the President anyway&lt;/a&gt;. After Harding’s death in August, 1923, Coolidge finished Harding’s term and ran for a full term in 1924 and didn’t bother seeking re-election. But what was the Coolidge administration like? Again, it cannot be restated enough, Coolidge believed in as little government action as possible, in virtually all areas of life. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/budget-and-tax-lessons-from-president-calvin-coolidge/#_edn5&quot;&gt;In a speech&lt;/a&gt;, he once said, “Government extravagance is not only contrary to the whole teaching of our Constitution but violates the fundamental conceptions and the very genius of American institutions.” But how much did he enact this belief?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for policy, Coolidge still held too many old-time progressive ideals. On civil rights, he accomplished much for his time. During the height of the Jim Crow era, where government-sanctioned racial discrimination laws were prevalent, Coolidge didn’t appoint any member of the Ku Klux Klan to government or the judiciary, even though some Senators and Judges held strong ties to it. He also helped pass several anti-lynching laws. It should be no wonder that during the election of 1924, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/1924-election-conflicting-minority-endorsements/&quot;&gt;historian John Berry estimated&lt;/a&gt; that “well over 90% of northern blacks voted Republican.” In addition, he supported child labour laws and women’s rights, making the first female appointment to the federal judiciary whilst giving Native Americans &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/story/2017/06/02/coolidge-signs-indian-citizenship-act-june-2-1924-238983&quot;&gt;citizenship&lt;/a&gt;. He also fought in the most contested battle of freedom during the era: prohibition. Coolidge wasn’t known to be a major drinker, but as far as public policy goes, he was a bit of a mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On foreign policy, he refused to recognise the new Soviet Union. Also, much to the delight of modern-day libertarians, he refused to join the League of Nations. Overall, he attempted to have America do as little as possible in foreign affairs. His economic policies really did reflect the libertarian &lt;em&gt;Laissez-Faire&lt;/em&gt; philosophy. Even to this day, he has been the only Republican in the past 100 years to have a surplus budget in any year, and the only President to have had one every year he served. Compared to now, almost no federal regulations were in place. Coolidge cut taxes, and unashamedly fought against farm subsidies (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/well-farmers-never-have-made-much-money-coolidges-case-against-subsidies/&quot;&gt;a major issue at the time&lt;/a&gt;). In fact, perhaps Coolidge’s only fall from the libertarian’s grace is that he did favour tariffs to protect American manufacturing. But this was one of the major sources of revenue for the United States government &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/briandomitrovic/2018/03/09/when-tariffs-worked/#5a4dfd3770f9&quot;&gt;and had been the biggest&lt;/a&gt; until the income tax was instituted in 1913.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like his policy, Coolidge was a man of restraint. His nickname, ‘Silent Cal’, was given for a good reason. At a party, a woman once proclaimed that she had accepted a bet that she could get him to say three words. He curtly replied: “you lose.” During some periods of his Presidency, he would sleep for eleven hours and work only four hours a day. Some of that time was spent staring out of his window &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ozy.com/flashback/historys-laziest-leaders/6494/&quot;&gt;counting the cars&lt;/a&gt; that drove by. He would also hide in his office, then hit the emergency buzzer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historytoday.com/archive/silent-cal&quot;&gt;see how long it took&lt;/a&gt; for the guards to find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As light-hearted the President might have seemed, he did not have a joyous presidency. While his son, Calvin Jr., was playing tennis without socks, he got a blister that became infected and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@Anthony_Bergen/blister-the-day-calvin-coolidge-lost-his-favorite-son-and-his-passion-for-the-presidency-fe7b6b638f&quot;&gt;shortly resulted in his death&lt;/a&gt;. He was 16 years old. As this happened during the election year, Coolidge barely bothered to campaign. He still won overwhelmingly, but carrying out the duties of his Presidency was clearly painful. In his own autobiography, he wrote that once his son had died, “the power and the glory of the Presidency went with him.” Coolidge died of a broken man barely more than three years after leaving the Presidency at the age of sixty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Ronald Reagan hung a portrait of Coolidge in the Oval Office and claimed he was his favourite President. Perhaps Coolidge did inspire Reagan on many issues, but other than that, there are few traces of Coolidge’s administration today. Because he was so restrained on enacting legislation, we have few reminders of his presence, unlike Presidents who used the government to take action and left strong impressions generations after they left office. Lincoln’s victory over the South, Wilson creating the Federal Reserve, FDR’s New Deal, and LBJ’s Great Society all serve as living reminders of their legacies well after their deaths. But in Coolidge’s case, the conspicuous absence of grand schemes is what serves as a reminder of his brilliant legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till this day, there is still a great debate on what caused the Great Depression, and how much Coolidge was responsible for it. Those who oppose capitalism see him as the obvious culprit. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fee.org/articles/chaos-in-the-marketplace-don-t-believe-it/&quot;&gt;some economists&lt;/a&gt; credit tariffs to be the principal reason for the Great Depression, and since Coolidge did not remove them, he could be held partly responsible. Although most of the blame ought to fall on his Secretary of Commerce and successor: Herbert Hoover. Hoover was very much an interventionist in the economy and even expanded the tariffs by signing the Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this mean for us today? For one, it proves that there is no such thing as perfection or purity. As much as the American libertarian right would like to dream of a world without tariffs or silly government bans like prohibition, Coolidge was the best example of a libertarian President. But he also lived at a time when there was little government to restrain anyway. The United States was not entangled in virtually every region of the world, so there was little need to remove itself. There was no massive social safety net, nor sprawling government bureaucracy. Seven departments existed in the Executive Branch during Coolidge’s time and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_federal_executive_departments&quot;&gt;eight have been added since&lt;/a&gt;, not to mention so many government agencies within those departments: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/waynecrews/2017/07/05/how-many-federal-agencies-exist-we-cant-drain-the-swamp-until-we-know/#1205b8591aa2&quot;&gt;government itself isn’t sure how many are there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Coolidge was not perfect, he probably knew he couldn’t be. Perhaps that’s what made Coolidge so restraining. He knew he couldn’t do everything or be everyone. He simply did the best he could and allowed history to decide his fate. As all of us should.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Madajian</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In the American right, there has been longing for a fiscal conservative. For years, the most touted example was Ronald Reagan, and although he presided over one of the nation’s largest tax cuts, he ran up major deficits. With the election of President Trump and the implementation of his multiple socially conservative policies, many conservatives have cast away Ronald Regan as their poster-child for a conservative icon. But as far as issues go, neither can hold a candle to the smallest-government libertarian in American history: Calvin Coolidge.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Walk with Me, through Calcutta</title><link href="/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Walk with Me, through Calcutta" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta">&lt;p&gt;It’s almost every day that one takes a stroll down the memory lane, but even more so during a heart-wrenching pandemic and lockdown. This is unexplored territory for most of us millennials, who have been living their teens and adulthood through the golden period of India, in terms of economy and culture both. We never had to face the horrors of the 1984 riots, the Emergency or the grotesque wars fought by India, post-Independence. I wonder if we’ll come out of this pandemic a bit more mature and stable, or just more reliant on the virtual world for sustenance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find myself one early morning after the lockdown, woken up by the sheer tirelessness at 6 am; only to witness a swathe of cotton candy shaped clouds and the Sun so calm, for it is March in Delhi. It was unlike anything I had witnessed before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a good half hour of staring at the silence clinging to the walls of my house, I make myself my ritualistic cup of lemon tea and cross another day off of my calendar, until this is all over.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I sit and blow on my tea for the thousandth time, I hear a voice from a recorder coming from my neighbour’s house. They were playing a famous Satyajit Ray song, that they do often but is usually drowned out by the jingling utensils of the neighbourhood and the hasty vehicles. I can faintly put any words together, but the calming music makes me get off my bed and lean against the wall to listen a little more clearly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I clamber on my couch, with my black laptop and fiddle through the folders to finally find the one I was rummaging for, named Kolkata or Calcutta, as most snobby Kolkatans would insist. I look at the pictures nostalgically and I’m back in the streets of the city of joy, where I can almost smell the salty fragrance of fish and the rust adorning Victoria Memorial’s old doors. For a good five years of my life, in fact, for as long as I can remember, I have dreamed of going to Kolkata. Maybe it was &lt;em&gt;Gitanjali&lt;/em&gt; by Rabindranath Tagore, Anupam Roy’s sweet sitar music, the movie &lt;em&gt;Piku&lt;/em&gt;, Kolkata’s iconic yellow taxis or my love for &lt;em&gt;Mishti Doi&lt;/em&gt; (sweet yogurt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For someone hailing from Delhi, Kolkata hits you like the fresh respite of mint lemonade on a hot summer day. A lot more scanty and calmer than the fast-paced city of Delhi, Kolkata, for me, was a sight out of a Michelangelo painting, an architect’s candy land if you may. Wherever you look, across three-sixty degrees, beautiful colours adorn the old buildings; not one is left white. There is something about the buildings in that city - they’re as old as time, but they stand strong, bold and speak to you if you like all things old. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kolkata is one of the metropolitan cities of India, with the 7th largest population and a bustling cultural milieu, yet it feels as if time has not moved there. The city has heavy influences from its colonial past, which can be seen in the wide roads, intersections, pavements, and the touch of white on the big, stellar monuments and museums. There is a mix of old and modern Indo-Saracenic elements in Kolkata, but a huge part of it dates back to the late 19th century when it was the major cultural, economic and commercial capital of colonial India. From the old rusty doors on its buildings, the yellow taxis around the city, to the cramped markets and street vendors selling the famous street food called* Phuchka*, there are parts of Kolkata surviving still, as authentic to its culture as it could’ve been. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tradition of the &lt;em&gt;hand-pulled rickshaws &lt;/em&gt;is still going strong and extant in the tapered lanes of Kolkata’s &lt;em&gt;Bara Bazar&lt;/em&gt; (literally ‘big market’) where men labour all day long, pulling these rickshaws with people for survival. These rickshaws were introduced in Kolkata by the Chinese Traders around the 1900’s who inhabited the Bara Bazar area  primarily to carry goods. The present-day pullers are either third or fourth generation pullers carrying the colonial heritage with their heredity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government of Kolkata has tried time and again to eradicate this practice, which some consider vile and inhuman, by banning it throughout the city, however, the rickshaws can still be spotted across the town. They say it’s their heritage and legacy, and it’s the only work they know. Hence, Kolkata stands as the only city in India to still have hand-pulled rickshaws in a working environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When talking about a monopoly on things, Kolkata is also the city of the &lt;em&gt;Tram Car&lt;/em&gt;. These trams are the oldest operating electric tram system in Asia, which has been running since 1902. They are little yellow and blue carriages, usually in a pair of two that run on electricity from overhead lines and tracks laid down throughout the city; from right next to Park Street to the Fort William, their expanse is widely spread. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these trams are old and rough around the edges, they are still chosen as a means of transportation by a significant number of lower-middle-class people, as it costs less than rupees ten to travel in this delightful little vehicle. Sitting in a tram takes you back to the 70’s and you can suddenly hear an old Hindi song playing in your head. They’re slow yet still efficient and environment-friendly and sit right in the heart of Kolkata’s culture, defining the city since time immemorial. And if you’re in Kolkata, I promise you can tell by the metallic tracks hugging the road and the muffled ringing of its bell that you’re near one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, undoubtedly, Kolkata’s culture is what it is known for across the globe. During the late 19th and 20th centuries, Kolkata gave birth to what later came to be known as the Bengal Renaissance. It is said to be initiated by the famous social-religious reformer, Raja Ram Mohan Roy, who led Kolkata to greatness, along with fellow reformers from this period - Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar, Swami Vivekananda, and many others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the British authority over India was incrementing every day, Bengal decided to step out from this period of darkness and towards the light. Reconsideration and reassessment transpired in the culture and philosophy of Kolkata, which is the very soul of a renaissance. This renaissance increased the importance of Kolkata by folds when it became the capital of colonial British India. Education, literacy, and civilisation flourished throughout the city which led to the birth of Kolkata’s literary realm, producing impressive pieces of literature and concurrently writers like the Nobel Prize-winning legend Rabindranath Tagore or Rashsundari Debi who is considered to be one of the first Indian women to write an autobiography and the first Bengali woman to have ever written anything. The Bengal renaissance not only brought literature and knowledge but reforms, technology, science, and enlightenment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise in Bengali culture during the time of colonialism is a watershed for Indian feminism because of the remnants that some of the women have left behind. Kolkata has witnessed women like Begum Rokeya, the author of the feminist utopian story &lt;em&gt;Sultana’s Dream&lt;/em&gt;, Nobel Peace Prize recipient Mother Teresa, Bina Das and Aruna Asaf Ali who laid a firm foundation of a feminist example for India’s posterity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the streets of Kolkata, I was not only staggered by its beautiful museums and churches but the art that lives in every corner of that city. Be it music, books or food, Kolkata aces the chart on every ground. It houses India’s largest library - The National Library of India, which provides a serene environment for any bibliophile, and &lt;em&gt;College Street, &lt;/em&gt;a mile of bookshops and bookstalls spilling over each other, where a large majority of publishers are situated. It became the heart of all-things-books after the &lt;em&gt;Kallol *movement, started around the beginning of the 20th century, witnessed the arrival of postmodernism. One of the greatest achievements of the &lt;/em&gt;Kallol* group was in establishing a new generation of writers and thinkers in Bengal, especially Kolkata. This also gave rise to Kolkata’s cinematic scene theatre and by extension, art films, known worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember seeing the oldest building in Kolkata situated in the centre of a jostling market called Lalbazar, lost and unmarked, shown to me by an old man, a lawyer, whom I met in my Uber-pool. It had red bricks and white pillars with curved white-painted windows. Before he left, he told me the best time to enjoy all that Kolkata has to offer is mid-October, during the period of Durga Pujo, a time of week-long festivities and food. The city lights up like a cluster of fireflies and rejoices with music authentic to the soul of Kolkata. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city lost its colossal importance after the capital of the Indian subcontinent was shifted from Calcutta (back then) to Delhi on December 12, 1911. However, it still strives to mesmerise its inhabitants and travellers from across the globe. It’s unlike any other city, soaked deeply in immense history and culture, which is reflected in every building, every pavement, and every bite of its delectable &lt;em&gt;roshogollas&lt;/em&gt;. The sweet Bengali music from the house adjacent to mine stops as the world wakes up and dives into the everyday hustle of life again. I close the window into my memory jar of Kolkata, rush to the kitchen and pour my nostalgia into a hearty Sunday treat of &lt;em&gt;Mishti Doi.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">It’s almost every day that one takes a stroll down the memory lane, but even more so during a heart-wrenching pandemic and lockdown. This is unexplored territory for most of us millennials, who have been living their teens and adulthood through the golden period of India, in terms of economy and culture both. We never had to face the horrors of the 1984 riots, the Emergency or the grotesque wars fought by India, post-Independence. I wonder if we’ll come out of this pandemic a bit more mature and stable, or just more reliant on the virtual world for sustenance. </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are They Really Trying to Prevent?</title><link href="/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are They Really Trying to Prevent?" /><published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent">&lt;p&gt;Among the things Indians pride themselves on, tall stands the Indian Constitution. A beacon of everything that is right with the country. Not only does it carry the spirit of the nation’s freedom struggle, but it also is an amalgamation of what the founders of independent India thought were the solutions for the worries of a new India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dark and dogmatic flaw in this idealised document materialises in the form of Art. 22, which denies certain fundamental rights to those arrested or detained under laws of preventive detention. The concept of preventive detention is simple - a person is taken into custody if the state machinery sees in them the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; to commit a crime. After stating certain protections from arrest and detention in Article 22(1) and (2), the Constitution further states that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nothing in clauses (1) and (2) shall apply— (a) to any person who for the time being is an enemy alien; or (b) to any person who is arrested or detained under any law providing for preventive detention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preventive detention is one of the many laws that have a deeply-rooted colonial legacy. The laws date back to the early days of the colonial era when the Bengal Regulation III of 1818 was enacted to empower the government to arrest anyone for maintenance of public order without any judicial proceedings. A century later, the British government enacted the Rowlatt Acts of 1919 that allowed confinement of a suspect without trial. Now, the very makers of the Constitution had been repeatedly arrested under these laws. So, the expectation was that such laws would be completely eradicated when independence was attained. But alas! that did not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Constituent Assembly Debates of India have long served as a leading example for dissent, debate and discussion. However, on the matter of preventive detention, all members seemed to have solemnly agreed. Alladi Krishnaswamy Ayyar, a distinguished jurist, had described preventive detention as a “necessary evil” because, in his view, there were people determined to undermine the sanctity of the Constitution, the security of the state and even individual liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the members resorted to incorporating safeguards against its abuse. However, it was left to Parliament to prescribe the period of detention and even that limit was meaningless because a fresh detention order could easily be passed, and advisory boards had no power to evaluate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 1950, one month after the promulgation of India’s first self-governing Constitution, Parliament passed a Preventive Detention Act which provided for the arrest and detention of persons who, in the opinion of the government, “represented a threat to the social stability and economic development of the country”. The Act was piloted by Sardar Patel, who said that he had several “sleepless nights” in the process of introducing the bill. The courts were expressly forbidden to question the necessity for any order issued by the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after in 1950, under this Act, an eminent communist political leader, A K Gopalan, was arrested. Gopalan challenged his detention by stating that his civil liberty was being hampered as he had the right to equality of law. However, the Supreme Court examined that he was detained according to the procedure established by law and rejected his argument. Although this ruling was later repealed by subsequent judgments of the Supreme Court, this initial arrest set the stage for the kind of curbing of dissent that this Act would entail as well as the passivity of the courts on the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most famous case involved Sheikh Abdullah, former Prime Minister of the State of Jammu and Kashmir. Arrested in 1953, he was held in detention until January 1958. The Government of India released Sheikh Abdullah upon good behaviour. However, the experiment did not last long, and he was rearrested on April 30, having amply revealed in a number of public speeches and statements that his opinions about the political future of Jammu and Kashmir had not changed at all. His brief respite from detention had lasted just 96 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Preventive Detention Act, 1950 expired in 1969 and was followed by the Maintenance of Internal Security Act (MISA), 1971. MISA is infamous for the controversial arrests and detentions that it facilitated. The entirety of the period of the Indian Emergency (1975-77) was further darkened by the cloud of MISA hanging over all political opponents of the ruling government. It was repealed once the Janata Party came to power after the Emergency, in 1977. When subsequently Indira Gandhi came back to power, the National Security Act, 1980 was instated. Over the years, many preventive detention laws have similarly risen and been repealed, but many have also remained and left a significant mark on the democratic process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1978, the Jammu and Kashmir Public Safety Act (PSA) was passed, under which a person is taken into custody to prevent them from acting harmfully against “the security of the state or the maintenance of the public order”. Strikingly, it was introduced by the then-&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_chief_ministers_of_Jammu_and_Kashmir&quot;&gt;Chief Minister&lt;/a&gt; of Jammu and Kashmir, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheikh_Abdullah&quot;&gt;Sheikh Abdullah&lt;/a&gt;, in 1978 under the guise of stopping the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timber_mafia&quot;&gt;smuggling of timber&lt;/a&gt;, but subsequently was used to remove political opponents. Since its usage in the late 1970’s, it is still being used today for “the security of the state”. Even after the revocation of Article 370, which ended Jammu and Kashmir’s special status, the PSA was one of the state laws which was retained under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jammu_and_Kashmir_Reorganisation_Act,_2019&quot;&gt;Jammu and Kashmir Reorganization Act of 2019&lt;/a&gt; - another sign of the “normalcy” in the state. Would Sheikh Abdullah have thought that 40 years later his own son Farooq Abdullah would be a victim of that very law?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no official count of the number of people detained in Kashmir after the government imposed a lockdown on August 5, 2019. Not just post August 5, there is no proper record of detentions under the PSA since its inception itself. It is safe to say that no official count will even reflect the true number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent times, the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967 (UAPA), along with its numerous amendments, has been the choice weapon of the state. The insidious intentions and arbitrary nature of the Act can be seen through an example of its implementation - the Bhima-Koregaon violence on January 1, 2018. The backdrop was a conference called the Elgar Parishad. 3 million people had gathered, led by numerous Dalit (Indian ‘untouchables’) organisations in the state of Maharashtra to commemorate the 200th anniversary of the Bhima-Koregaon battle, believed by the Dalits to have been won by their ancestors to end the oppressive regime of Brahmin Peshwas (higher ‘castes’). It gave a call to “Bury the New Peshwai” of the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) seen by the Dalits and minorities as the revival of Brahminic rule. This did not sit right with Hindutva forces, which attacked the congregation at the obelisk at Koregaon. The police refused to act against the named culprits. Instead, they began insinuating that the violence was caused by the inflammatory speeches made in the Elgar Parishad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months following the event, a number of people present at the event were arrested under the UAPA including renowned Dalit scholars and human rights advocates. It was alleged by the Pune Police that the event was organised by members of the banned Communist Party of India (Maoist), hence making these arrests necessary. The 11 accused were Sudhir Dhawale, Shoma Sen, Mahesh Raut, Rona Wilson, Surendra Gadling, P Varavara Rao, Sudha Bharadwaj, Arun Ferreira, Vernon Gonsalves, Anand Teltumbde and Gautam Navlakha. Except Teltumbde and Navlakha, the others were arrested by Pune Police in June and August 2018 in connection with the violence. They were accused of having links with the banned Communist Party of India (Maoist), and are still in prison. Navlakha and Teltumbde were presented in front of a special court in Mumbai on February 28, 2020 and were denied anticipatory bail. They were, however, given four weeks of protection from arrest to file a plea in the Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A barrage of criticism can be found against the UAPA for its provisions as well as its implementation. The definitions in the act are vague, for example, “questioning the territorial integrity of India is an unlawful activity” according to s. 2. Similarly, it is also an unlawful activity to cause “disaffection against India”. All these terms do not find definition in the Act. The state also reserves the power to declare any organisation as a terrorist organisation and just a membership of the same could get you imprisoned. Membership has often been proven using evidence as flimsy as copies of the Communist Manifesto to prove Naxal or Maoist ties. Although the Supreme Court has established that membership does not provide enough ground for arrest, this directive is yet to find hold in ground reality. Additionally, it is near-impossible to get bail once booked under this Act, despite the lack of concrete evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 amendment to UAPA allows the State to now declare individuals as terrorists as well. The judicious use of this provision has been seen during the protests against the Citizenship Amendment Act which began in December 2019. The first arrest under the newly amended act was made in Assam. Akhil Gogoi, an activist and leader of the &lt;em&gt;Krishak Mukti Sangraam Samiti&lt;/em&gt; (Congregation of Farmers’ Freedom Fighters), was booked by the National Investigation Agency under the UAPA for participating in the anti-CAA protests in Assam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voices that stand opposed to the government are a blessing in disguise. They are a rich source- identifying missteps and rectifying them. However, this idealistic relationship between the ruling elite and the opposition has never been realised. What comes next, however, is the relationship between the opposition and the people. Though not perfect, this relationship is in many ways what it truly means to be a part of a democracy. Votes do not always materialise as fulfillment of interests, and that is where the opposition must step in, to further this materialisation, on the behalf of all sections of society. Here opposition does not mean merely the one in Parliament, but voices across society, like those who gathered at Elgar Parishad and those who spoke up against the CAA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy is often tiring. Governments come and go, but the status quo remains. Is there any real way to affect such large processes as a mere individual? Firstly, it would help us to recognise that democracy is not an end, it is a process in its conception. It is meant to be an endless cycle, and all we can do is improve and make the process as effective and inclusive as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition is at the heart of achieving such a democracy. The practice of demonising anyone who is opposed to the ruling elite is not a new one. It began with A K Gopalan and it continues to haunt us. At this crucial moment, it is the people who must reiterate their relationship with the opposition. Not in a partisan sense, but by remaining critical of whoever is in power and by collectively protecting those who actively do so. National security should no longer be able to act as a curtain hiding undemocratic and unconstitutional laws. We should be enraged at the idea of dissent being equated with terrorism. And we should be aware that fascist policies like preventive detention slowly steal our power as the people without us noticing. Let us not wait for the day that our voices are completely silenced.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Among the things Indians pride themselves on, tall stands the Indian Constitution. A beacon of everything that is right with the country. Not only does it carry the spirit of the nation’s freedom struggle, but it also is an amalgamation of what the founders of independent India thought were the solutions for the worries of a new India.</summary></entry></feed>