<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-22T19:31:54+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Economic Indicator 007</title><link href="/Football-for-Global-Influence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economic Indicator 007" /><published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Football-for-Global-Influence</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Football-for-Global-Influence">&lt;p&gt;I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What does Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logo belongs to Gazprom, a Russian natural gas company. Logo sponsorships are normal in football. Teams make money offering jersey spaces to sponsors selling things like credit cards, cars and cell phones but Gazprom isn’t like most sponsors, i.e. private companies with products that football fans can buy. Instead, it’s a company owned by the Russian government that makes money selling natural gas to foreign countries. Yet, it’s everywhere in European football. So, if football fans can’t buy what they are selling, why is Gazprom spending millions to sponsor football games? The answer is part of a larger story that’s changing the sport of football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d7/Major_russian_gas_pipelines_to_europe.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/russiangaspipes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia has the world’s largest natural gas reserves and most of them are located in the Arctic gas fields controlled by Gazprom. The company is led by Alexey Miller, a close ally of Russian President Vladimir Putin. Since 2005, the Russian government has owned a majority stake in Gazprom. This means that the company profits are under Putin’s control, and gas sellers, along with oil, account for around 50% of Russia’s annual budget. Eastern European countries like Finland, Estonia, Lithuania, Poland, Slovakia depend on Russian oil for 75-100% of their natural gas needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move further towards the West, the countries’ dependence begins to fall. At the end of the 20th century, Germany represented the biggest opportunity for Gazprom. German Chancellor Gerhard Schroeder had announced plans to phase out coal and nuclear power which meant Germany needed more natural gas to maintain their energy supply. Gazprom wanted to give it to them but there was a problem. To get to Germany, Russia’s gas needed to pass through pipelines crossing other countries that charged Gazprom transport fees. And most of them went through Ukraine, a country that has complicated political relations with Russia. Today, Ukraine still charges upwards of $3 billion each year to pump gas to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, starting back in 2005, Russia began working on a strategy to bypass Ukraine and ship their gas directly to Western Europe through the Nord Stream pipeline, a route through the Baltic sea straight to Northern Germany. In late 2005, Gazprom was in the final stages of financing the project and Germany’s Chancellor was preparing for an election. During his time in the office, Gerhard Schroeder had become friendly with Putin, and critics in Germany were increasingly concerned about the Russian leader’s growing influence. Just a few weeks before the election, Schroeder met with Putin signing an agreement officially approving the pipeline. Two months later, he lost his re-election. However, by March, he found a new job overseeing Gazprom’s pipeline to Germany. It also came out that, before leaving office Schroeder had approved a secret Gazprom loan that provided over a billion euros to finance the project. This led to Gazprom’s big project being called a “story of scandal, corruption, and the creeping influence of Russia in Germany”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in 2006 the story changed, Gazprom signed a deal to sponsor the German soccer team FC Schalke 04. At the time Schalke’s finances were worrying the team officials and Gazprom’s sponsorship provided money that the team desperately needed. At a press conference announcing the deal, a Gazprom chairman stated that Schalke’s connections with the German energy sector were the reason behind their decision to become its sponsors. Schalke played in Gelsenkirchen, a town in Germany’s Ruhr Valley, where much of the country’s energy industry is based. It’s also near the town of Rehden, a hub for pipelines to the rest of Europe and home to western Europe’s largest natural gas storage facilities. Schalke wasn’t Gazprom’s first football deal. The year before, they had bought a controlling stake in a team on the other end of the Nord Stream route: the Russian team Zenit St Petersburg. Gazprom’s investment made Zenit a major force in football. Two years after taking control, Zenit won their first-ever league championship. They’ve been able to sign expensive foreign stars like Axel Wetzel and Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, as Gazprom logos were revealed around Schalke’s stadium, German headlines were hailing the Russian gas giant for pumping millions into the German team and hence, creating a positive image in German minds for the company. And over the next few years, the Gazprom logo would become a team symbol displayed at Schalke’s games and printed on official merchandise. Schalke also won a championship in 2011. By then, Nord Stream had been completed and it had started pumping gas to Germany. There was also another struggling team whose jerseys started featuring Gazprom’s logo, the Serbian team: Red Star Belgrade. Red Star was about $25 million in debt when Gazprom signed to become their jersey sponsor and again, there was also another pipeline: the south stream would have bypassed Ukraine by going directly through Serbia to Southern Europe. That project closed in 2014, but Gazprom further increased its access to Europe by building Nord Stream 2, a second pipeline doubling the amount of gas flowing from Russia to Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years in addition to its pipeline empire, Gazprom has also expanded its influence over global football to include energy partnership with Chelsea football club, UEFA Champions League, and the sport’s most famous tournament: the FIFA World Cup. These sponsorships have made Gazprom’s logo familiar to not only the fans in Europe but across the world. It also did something which boosted the Russian economy. Russia became the world’s largest exporter of natural gas and provided for almost half of all the natural gas supply to Europe becoming a major player in the energy field in Europe. This created a reliance of other countries on Russia for the supply of natural gas, power and energy generation. The strategy adopted by Russia turned out to be a ‘game-changer’ and as of 2019, Russia supplied 199 billion cubic meters of natural gas to Europe. The oil-and-gas sector accounted for 16% of GDP, 52% of federal budget revenues, and over 70% of total exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Russia is the skipper when it comes to energy supply and generation in Europe and other countries are learning from their example. As the example of Gazprom shows, having prominent soccer sponsorship offers a way around bad publicity by winning approval on the field. Many companies such as Qatar Airways, Etihad Airways and Emirates Airlines have started sponsoring major teams in Europe such as AS Roma, Manchester City and AC Milan respectively. As an avid football supporter, I feel like it’s a big opportunity: their money helps teams win major championships and tournaments, but it is changing the sport itself. Now that it has become common to see a German team sponsored by Russia’s gas company facing off against an Italian team sponsored by Dubai’s state-owned airline, it is starting to seem like the field is hosting two competitions at once: a match between the two teams and larger play for a foreign influence that continues long after the final whistle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What does Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Economic Indicator 007</title><link href="/Economic-Indicator-007" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economic Indicator 007" /><published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Economic-Indicator-007</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Economic-Indicator-007">&lt;p&gt;Economic trends are inordinately erratic and display a tendency to react to the smallest stimulus. Unfortunately, the patterns manifested by these trends is all we have to predict the trajectory of the economic system. Going by the book, we have a predominant set of indices that are used to portray an economy’s state of affairs, overriding among them being the GDP, GNP, unemployment rate, inflation rate, rate of interest, consumer price index, etc. However, that’s not even the half of it, as there are a prodigious number of accurate indicators that are undermined by economic planners and analysts. Who thought James Bond would be one of them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know who James Bond is. His reputation as an international man of mystery, a guru of gadgets and espionage thrills, and as the one licensed to kill, precedes him. Since its creation in 1953 by Ian Fleming, the character has etched itself into pop culture and earned itself a spot on the Mount Rushmore of Hollywood. But that’s not the end of its legacy- turns out that it has established one of the most unusual precedents in the economic history of the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;em&gt;Casino Royale&lt;/em&gt; was first published in 1953, the US economy was greatly compromised. The US war spending had helped add $236 billion to the debt. It was a 1048% increase, the largest percentage increase to debt for any President. A recession also sprouted, owing to the demobilisation following the Korean war, and the unemployment levels reached their loftiest at 6.1% in 1954. The same could not be said for Bond, as the book became one of the hottest on the shelves. People started loving the persona of Bond: a dashing agent with seemingly limitless resources and abilities, and he unknowingly became a ridiculously accurate economic barometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first on-screen adaptation of Bond came with the release of &lt;em&gt;Dr No&lt;/em&gt; in 1962. The times were good, as the economy was exalted as a result of the post the Second World War expansion. President Kennedy had introduced various reforms to revive the economy from the 1960-61 recession. These comprised an increase in the minimum wage for a larger pool of workers, an increase in unemployment compensation plus increased aid to children of unemployed workers, increased social security benefits, emergency relief for feed grain farmers, area redevelopment, vocational training for displaced workers, federal funding for home building and slum eradication and tax cuts. Overseas investment also rose. The film was conferred with critical acclaim, but came up short in commercial success, and is ranked as one of the least earning Bond movies. Still, the film had a significance of its own, as it formed the bedrock for the dazzling success of future installments. What no one seemed to notice was that the success of Bond films and the state of economic well-being were displaying a nebulously accurate disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail of years that followed were not kind to America. President John F Kennedy, the man pivotal in uplifting the economy and perpetuating its growth, had been assassinated. The country’s economy was facing the corroding effects of the Vietnam War, the most famous highlight of which was ‘The Great Botch’ of 1966. The botch involved miscalculation of the war cost by the Defense Department under President Johnson’s administration. The budget was underestimated by a staggering 100%, which squandered the steady income and employment growth rate achieved post the Second World War. The budget deficit also escalated at an alarming rate, hitting the $23 billion mark in 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film franchise, on the other hand, unveiled to the world its most popular antagonist - a fat, decadent psychopath who covers everything in gold and is literally trying to steal all of America’s money - Auric Goldfinger. &lt;em&gt;Thunderball&lt;/em&gt; (1965), &lt;em&gt;Goldfinger&lt;/em&gt; (1964), and &lt;em&gt;You Only Live Twice&lt;/em&gt; (1967) were massive commercial blockbusters, grossing a whopping total of $1.5 billion. Actor Sean Connery got the biggest piece of the pie, as he received a great push towards a legendary career, accompanied by a big fat pay-cheque. The decade ended with a shift in the scales of power, as Richard Nixon took the reigns in 1969.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 70’s witnessed an oscillatory trend for Bond cinema, displaying perfectly negative parallelism to what the economy was enduring. When &lt;em&gt;Diamonds Are Forever&lt;/em&gt; hit the screens in 1971, the US was witnessing a decline in its economic power, and the economy was pegging away to recover from the 1970 recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Nixon fought the recession by turning the American dollar into a fiat currency, as a result of which the dollar was devalued and millions of foreigners holding dollars, including Arab oil barons with tens of millions of petro-dollars, saw the value of dollars slashed. He also imposed wage and price controls. As you can guess now, the movie was average. It made decent money and was fairly appreciated, but it was no &lt;em&gt;Goldfinger&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the arrival of 1973, the economy stumbled deeper into the trenches. The USA was facing the severest recession since the Second World War, with the rate of inflation at a deplorable 8.8% in the fourth quarter. The Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) was blamed for quadrupling oil prices, but that was just the tip of the iceberg. President Nixon’s price controls kept prices too high, reducing demand, while wage controls made salaries too high and forced businesses to lay off workers. Additionally, Nixon took the United States off the gold standard in response to a run on the gold held at Fort Knox, which led to inflation. The price of gold skyrocketed to $120 an ounce while the dollar’s value plummeted. Negative GDP growth of 2.1% was also observed in the third quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roger Moore’s &lt;em&gt;Live and Let Die&lt;/em&gt; came during the same year, and by now it shouldn’t be a surprise that it was the highest-grossing Bond movie of the 70’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came time for another turn of tables, with the release of &lt;em&gt;The Man with the Golden Gun&lt;/em&gt; in December 1974. Owing to its late release, its primary collection period was the year 1975, the same year American economy began emerging from recession. An upturn in GDP and industrial output was evident, alongside the dwindling rate of inflation (from 10.4% in 1974 to 6.5 % in 1975). The volume of shares traded on the New York stock exchange also rose from 3.5 to 4.7 billion shares. &lt;em&gt;The Man with the Golden Gun&lt;/em&gt; is still considered to be the most flawed and pointless addition to the Bond universe, loathed by critics and the audience alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climax for the 70’s economy came with another capricious change in economic trends, displayed by cascading economic growth. Inflation and unemployment were up again, and the economic system was slithering into another recession. The timing could not have been better for &lt;em&gt;The Spy Who Loved Me&lt;/em&gt; (1977) and &lt;em&gt;Moonraker&lt;/em&gt; (1979), as both of them grossed a stupendous $1.3 billion combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the year 1981 rolled in, the recession boomeranged back to plague the economy. The Regan government caused this recession by raising interest rates to curb inflation, which undesirably reduced business spending. The Iranian oil embargo added fuel to the fire, as it reduced US oil supplies, which drove up the prices. GDP growth was negative for the whole year, the worst being the second quarter at a negative 8.0%. Unemployment rose to 10.8% in November and December 1982, the highest level in any modern recession. President Reagan lowered the tax rate and boosted the defense budget, helping to end the recession. Summing it up, the economy was toiling to fend off the unemployment and inflationary outbreaks. The commercial struggle of &lt;em&gt;For Your Eyes Only&lt;/em&gt; (1983) epitomised a more complicated one going on in the economy. However, the film is the best Bond portrayal of the 1980’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining decade was all Reagan-show, as he painted a masterpiece on the economic canvas. The first step was signing the Economic Recovery Tax Act of 1981, which brought reductions in individual income tax rates, the expensing of depreciable property, incentives for small businesses and incentives for savings. So began the Reagan Recovery. A few years later, the Tax Reform Act of 1986 brought the lowest individual and corporate income tax rates of any major industrialised country in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers tell the story. Over the eight years of the Reagan Administration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• 20 million new jobs were created. Employment of African-Americans rose by more than 25% between 1982 and 1988, and more than half of the new jobs created went to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Inflation dropped from 13.5% in 1980 to 4.1% by 1988.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Unemployment fell from 7.6% to 5.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Net worth of families earning between $20,000 and $50,000 annually grew by 27%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Real gross national product rose by 26%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• The prime interest rate was slashed by more than half, from an unprecedented 21.5% in January 1981 to 10% in August 1988.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Growth in government spending plummeted from 10% in 1982 to just over 1% in 1987. With inflation factored in, federal spending actually went down in 1987– the first time that had happened in well over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the economy boomed, Bond got tanked again, facing consecutive low earning entries in the series. The decade leached away Bond’s persona as the charismatic spy who could always get the job done and turned him into a goofy, lethargic and confused man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 1995, the economy was recovering from the recession of 1990-91 and was turning increasingly healthy in performance as the 1990’s progressed. The fall of the Soviet Union and Eastern European communism in the late 1980’s opened up trade opportunities across the world. Technological developments brought a wide range of new, more efficient electronic products, and innovations in telecommunications and computer networking spawned a vast computer hardware and software industry. This, in turn, revolutionised the way many other industries operated. The growth rate and corporate earnings rose rapidly. A combination of desirable inflation, unemployment, and corporate profits sent the stock market surging. Moreover, the Dow Jones Industrial Average, which had stood at just 1,000 in the late 1970’s, hit the 11,000 mark in 1999, adding substantially to the wealth of many - though not all - Americans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An idiosyncrasy of the final decade of the century was the increasing speculation in online websites, also known as the ‘dot-com bubble’. People were rapidly dumping cash in online domains. Capital from venture capitalists was also easy to raise, as investment banks profited from the Initial Public Offers (IPOs). A combination of rapidly increasing stock prices in the quaternary sector of the economy and confidence that the companies would turn future profits created an environment in which many investors were willing to overlook traditional metrics, such as the price-earnings ratio, and base confidence on technological advancements, which ultimately led to a stock market bubble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar was the case with Bond movies. Almost all of the previous Bond films had an average budget of about $30 million. So 1989’s &lt;em&gt;License to Kill&lt;/em&gt;, which is still the worst-performing entry of the entire franchise, wound up earning almost four times its budget. Though 1999’s &lt;em&gt;Tomorrow Never Dies&lt;/em&gt; grossed way more, producers had dumped over $110 million into it and funneled even more cash into the next two installments. Such a large investment in movies led to the formation of an investment bubble of its own. However, filmmakers’ bulletproof investment bubble burst, just like all the dot-coms of the 90’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decade changed, but the story didn’t. Bond made millions whenever inflation and unemployment got the better of the economy. Be it &lt;em&gt;Quantum of Solace&lt;/em&gt; (2008) and the financial crisis 2007-08 or &lt;em&gt;Skyfall&lt;/em&gt; (2012) and the global economic crisis 2012, it’s always the same. Higher the severity of the crisis, the more dollars Bond films rake in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the phenomenon first got noticed, it was spurned as a mere case of coincidences. Till today, no one has been able to decipher the reason behind this absurd correlation. In my opinion, one aspect of it can be identified as what is known as the ‘butter popcorn effect’, which is an unconventional economic indicator. The rationale behind it is that during the initial stages of a recession, people show a greater inclination towards entertainment, as they want to escape the hardships of the real world. As this pushes more people into cinema halls, the sale of butter popcorn also increases. For instance, the box office posted one of its biggest years during the 2009 recession, before plateauing as markets eased. Still, there is no solid explanation about why Bond films fail during economic expansion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aryaman Dhiman</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Economic trends are inordinately erratic and display a tendency to react to the smallest stimulus. Unfortunately, the patterns manifested by these trends is all we have to predict the trajectory of the economic system. Going by the book, we have a predominant set of indices that are used to portray an economy’s state of affairs, overriding among them being the GDP, GNP, unemployment rate, inflation rate, rate of interest, consumer price index, etc. However, that’s not even the half of it, as there are a prodigious number of accurate indicators that are undermined by economic planners and analysts. Who thought James Bond would be one of them?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Voting for Bad Candidates isn’t a Privilege</title><link href="/Bad-Candidates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voting for Bad Candidates isn’t a Privilege" /><published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bad-Candidates</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bad-Candidates">&lt;p&gt;When Americans vote in November, they should be made to answer another question after casting their vote for President. Do you, in your heart of hearts, believe that either Donald Trump or Joe Biden can make the United States a better country for the people who live there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how honestly the electorate would answer this question, short of installing lie detectors in the voting booths. But I know how I would vote if I were American. I don’t think either of them could improve the country. And then, if it came out that eighty percent of the country agreed, any pretence of a mandate that the victorious candidate might have hoped to claim would have evaporated long before he raises his right hand on the steps of the Capitol next January. This would be a cathartic moment because neither man deserves to hold the office of President of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know why anyone has bothered reading John Bolton’s new book. It was already obvious to anyone neither blind nor deaf that Donald Trump is unfit for the Presidency, and he has demonstrated this beyond reproach in the past months. Nothing about his response to the coronavirus is surprising, from the hubris to the ineptitude and the self-aggrandisement. Little else needs to be said regarding the incumbent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Biden is pledging to build on the policies of the former President Obama, who ran an administration which sleepwalked into two conflicts with Russia, over Syria and Ukraine, forever destabilised Libya and the Mediterranean, tanked the healthcare insurance market and added trillions to the national debt. Biden has also been coy about disagreeing with those on the left of his party over defunding the police and abolishing immigration controls. Whether he will have the gall to shout down these voices from the Oval Office is by no means clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Biden might be more seasoned than his opponent, there’s the small issue that he’s barely campaigning. It’s almost as if Trump is running for the Presidency in 2020, and Biden in 1920. Although, at least Franklin Roosevelt campaigned from the carriage of a train. With the current hysteria surrounding public transport, is rail travel even an option for the elderly Mr Biden?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Trump can’t run the White House, and Biden can’t run the country. Upon seeing this, you will realise that the whole election is an expensive (and possibly rather violent) farce. Under these circumstances, the best thing you can do, if you are American, is to not legitimise this sham by refusing to take part in the election process. The scenario of a confidence vote which I set out at the start of the article is a nice idea, but it’s not going to happen. Democrats and Republicans both stand to lose far too much from it, or from a “none of the above” option on the ballot paper. If the state won’t budge on allowing the electorate to register their dissatisfaction at election time, then the American public must take it upon themselves to do this, and stay at home. Sorry, but voting for some third-party chump who barely knows where Albany is, let alone &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pcj8yJk87cs&quot;&gt;Aleppo&lt;/a&gt;, isn’t going to cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have heard all of the pro-voting arguments before. &lt;em&gt;“Voting is a privilege which people living under tyranny don’t have”&lt;/em&gt;, people say. This is nonsense; many people living without freedom can vote, and they get in serious trouble if they don’t. North Korea holds parliamentary elections. Vladimir Putin is an elected politician, but the citizens under his control can’t contest his dubious victories every six years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in any case, voting for candidates as bad as Trump and Biden isn’t a privilege, it’s a headache. Elections, if they are to be about anything, ought to be about getting good government. This now seems almost impossible in Western countries, because candidates (most of whom are either too square or too scary) must make ridiculous promises they can never keep if they are to have any hope of getting elected. Huge new spending commitments with no new taxes, limits on immigration without native people filling low paid jobs, efficient, state-provided broadband, and a government ‘guarantee’ of employment, all spring to mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know who is going to win the election in November. But in a sense, it doesn’t matter. What matters is that Americans realise that the right not to vote is just as important as the right to vote. Most people are anxious to signal to people they want to impress how much they dislike politicians, but they don’t realise that they have the power to strip them of their authority. Politicians derive their mandate to implement harmful policies from your vote. If you don’t give them legitimacy, they lose it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our governments have been desperate for us to stay at home for months. I doubt they’ll want you to shield or socially distance on election day, though. Don’t give them the satisfaction of turning up at the polling station. Stay at home, save the country, and do something worthwhile with your day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>.</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">When Americans vote in November, they should be made to answer another question after casting their vote for President. Do you, in your heart of hearts, believe that either Donald Trump or Joe Biden can make the United States a better country for the people who live there?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">China’s Five Finger Plan: In Full Steam Ahead</title><link href="/China-Five-Finger-Plan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Five Finger Plan: In Full Steam Ahead" /><published>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/China-Five-Finger-Plan</id><content type="html" xml:base="/China-Five-Finger-Plan">&lt;p&gt;Making a new addition to the long list of multifarious border disputes, China has now declared the Eastern region of Bhutan to be yet another victim of its ‘expansionist’ policy. The Sino-Bhutanese border dispute ranges back to 1984, since then the two countries have held 24 rounds of talks to resolve their border issues. Until now, the disputed region only consisted of the Central and Western sections of the boundary. The talks between the two were delimited to three areas of dispute, Jakarlung and Pasamlung Areas in Northern Bhutan and one region in the West. Thus, China’s new claim on the Sakteng region of East Bhutan was a bolt out of the blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Five Finger Plan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the annexation of Tibet by the People’s Republic of China, the Chinese leaders elucidated upon its Five Finger plan. In accordance with this, the Chinese believe Tibet to be the ‘palm’ with Ladakh, Nepal, Bhutan, Arunachal Pradesh, and Sikkim being the five ‘fingers’. China’s aggression in the Himalayas and its attempt at changing the status quo has been nothing but a clear adumbration of how China is all set to bring this plan into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does Bhutan come into the Picture?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With historically tense diplomatic ties, Bhutan’s border with Tibet has never been officially recognised. In 1959, in &lt;em&gt;A Brief History of China&lt;/em&gt;, China released a map that portrayed numerous territories of Bhutan as a part of China under the five finger plan. Later in the year, the annexation of Tibet by the People’s Republic of China began. During this process, The People’s Liberation Army (PLA) also captured several territories under the Bhutan region. These included regions of Gartok, Darchen, and several other monasteries that had been under the Bhutanese administration for more than 300 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tensions began to escalate in 1961 with the invasion of Chinese soldiers and herdsmen. A tensed Bhutanese nation imposed extensive border controls and a cross-border trade embargo in retaliation to the increasing incursions. In order to build a safety net in response to the rising tensions between the two nations, Bhutan began building strong diplomatic and extensive military ties with India. Thus, the strong Indo-Bhutanese ties were attributed to the deteriorating Sino-Bhutanese diplomatic ties. Though this soon turned into neutrality from Bhutan’s end with India’s defeat in the Sino-Indian war of 1962, as the loss put forth a question on India’s ability to defend Bhutan from the Chinese wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 1988, when the tensions between the two nations further escalated, Bhutan and China signed a bilateral peace agreement based on the Panchsheel Treaty (a treaty-based on diplomatic principles of India and China to ensure non-interference in others’ internal affairs and respect for each other’s territorial unity integrity and sovereignty). This treaty was later violated by the Chinese authorities on account of building roads in regions under the territory of Bhutan. This was later settled in 2002 with an interim agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Doklam Standoff&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plateau and a trijunction between China, India and Bhutan became the cause of a major uproar in 2017. Doklam was never a source of contention or interest. Even during the prior independence talks of border settlement between the British and the Chinese, neither of them placed any significance on the plateau. But, since 1962, Beijing has made numerous claims over the territory. What sprouted this sudden and ardent interest in the plateau was not the plateau region itself, but the area surrounding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Siliguri corridor often referred to as the ‘chicken’s neck’ is the Achilles heel of India. The corridor is of vital importance to India as it connects the Indian mainland to its north-eastern counterparts. Doklam’s proximity to the corridor is what makes the trijunction strategically immensely significant. Along with this, the plateau is surrounded by the Chumbi Valley, where the Chinese are militarily disadvantaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, China has been undertaking innumerable measures by building a network of roads to provide a smooth flow to increase its military presence in the region. Doklam, hence, would provide commanding access to both the Siliguri corridor and the Chumbi Valley. To ensure proper security to the region, when the Chinese officials came with a target to extend its road networks southwards in Doklam, in regions under the authorisation of Bhutan, India rose to action to stop the construction. The construction of the road directly violated the terms of the 1988 peace agreement. This led to a two-month-long standoff in the region. In August 2017, a mutual disengagement on the plateau was undertaken to bring an end to the face-off in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the border tensions and issues have long continued, Chinese claim over the Sakteng valley is a new amendment to the long list. But out of all the disputed territory between the Sino-Bhutan authorities, the Sakteng valley constitutes to be the single largest of them all, comprising 11% of the region under the Bhutanese administration. Some believe that this claim is a threat to India, pertaining to the current Sino-Indian tensions in the Ladakh region. The Sakteng valley borders the Indian state of Arunachal Pradesh, which is claimed in its entirety by the Chinese Government. Others also believe that this claim is targeted as a threat to Bhutan to tip the scale on other disputed land areas including Doklam in favour of China in the 25th round of border talks long after the 2017 standoff. It remains to be seen what happens in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it mean for India?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the world’s attention is diverted towards dealing with the COVID-19 pandemic, China is using this strategic time and is spreading its arm like an octopus: both in the Himalayan region and the South China sea. With neighbouring Nepal already an ally to China now and out of India’s orbit, India cannot afford to let loose its ties with Bhutan. With the growing attention of China towards the mountain kingdom, India is at a turmoil to be caught up in a bigger strategic ploy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tanisha Sukhija</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Making a new addition to the long list of multifarious border disputes, China has now declared the Eastern region of Bhutan to be yet another victim of its ‘expansionist’ policy. The Sino-Bhutanese border dispute ranges back to 1984, since then the two countries have held 24 rounds of talks to resolve their border issues. Until now, the disputed region only consisted of the Central and Western sections of the boundary. The talks between the two were delimited to three areas of dispute, Jakarlung and Pasamlung Areas in Northern Bhutan and one region in the West. Thus, China’s new claim on the Sakteng region of East Bhutan was a bolt out of the blue.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Whose Land Is It Anyway?: Charting The Kalapani Dispute and its Implications on Indo-Nepal Relations</title><link href="/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Whose Land Is It Anyway?: Charting The Kalapani Dispute and its Implications on Indo-Nepal Relations" /><published>2020-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We are working to ensure territorial integrity, national sovereignty, and freedom of our people. The kings of Nepal lost our territory, but today we republicans are restoring it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announced by Pushpa Kamal Dahal Prachanda, the co-Chair of the Nepal Communist Party on June 13, 2020, amid loud applauses at the Pratinidhi Sabha (the Lower House of the Nepalese Parliament), the declaration comes at the occasion marking the passage of the Second Constitution Amendment Bill which ensures legitimacy to the updated political map of Nepal. It had been at the eye of a diplomatic storm for including Indian territory within the periphery of Nepalese borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian territory of Limpyadhura, Kalapani, the strategically vital Lipulekh pass, all located in the Pithoragarh district of the Indian state of Uttarakhand have been shown as parts of Nepalese territory. The Indian Ministry of External Affairs has regarded the bill as an encroachment into the sovereignty of the Indian territory as they refer to it as an “artificial enlargement” in an official statement. The bill, which was passed by the approval of 258 members present and voting, out of the total strength of 275 members, has strained the otherwise good bilateral ties between India and Nepal. The upper house of the Nepalese Parliament, the National Assembly had been unanimous in its support for the bill, with all 57 members present voting in its favour on June 18, 2020. The die had been cast when the bill providing for the inclusion of Nepal’s new political map had been approved in its national emblem. The final move has sparked fierce criticism on a “sensitive issue”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The origins of the row&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that this diplomatic uncertainty was birthed through a 200-year-old treaty, the Treaty of Sugauli, that had formally established the boundaries of Nepal. The treaty had been signed on December 2, 1815, between the East India Company and Rajguru Gararaj Mishra with Chandra Sekhar Upadhyaya in the aftermath of the Anglo-Nepalese War of 1814-16. The interpretation of the treaty has been one of the primary causes of the present conflict. According to the treaty, the Eastern side of the river Kali falls within Nepal’s territory while the Western bank lies in India. The trouble brews from a common misinterpretation as Nepal considers Limpiyadhura as the origin of river Kali, thereby forwarding the claim that Limpyadhura, Lipulekh and Kalapani belong to their dominion. The advocates of the Indian cause, on the other hand, state that the origin of river Kali is Kalapani, which is an area located within Indian borders. The two regions of Susta and Kalapani cover 40 km of the Indo-Nepal border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cartographic dispute had earlier raised its ugly head, when on November 2, 2019, the Indian government had put up a new political map of the nation, depicting the reorganisation of Jammu and Kashmir, with a vivid depiction of the disputed Kalapani region exactly as it had been before. There had been allegations by the Nepalese government that in spite of twin reminders for restarting a foreign secretary-level dialogue mechanism between the two nations, India had not agreed to fix a date for the bilateral talks. Many quarters have regarded it as a fallout of the Nepalese Prime Minister KP Sharma Oli’s proximity to China. The Nepal government had expressed demands to publish their own new map which aimed at incorporating the disputed sites in their own fold. Oli had dismissed such claims on November 16 in the face of contrary claims put forward by Padma Aryal, the Nepalese cabinet minister for land and poverty alleviation who asserted that Nepal would soon come out with a new map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to a shift in priorities of both governments in the face of health security challenges imposed by COVID-19, the matter had been erased from public memory. But it resurfaced with a May 8 tweet by the Indian Defence Minister Rajnath Singh. Singh had laid emphasis on his inauguration of the blacktop road to Lipulekh pass, which had been under construction for 8 years. The Nepalese government in Kathmandu claimed that 19 km of the said road extended to Lipulekh, which according to their claims had been a part of Nepalese territory. It was seen as an attempt on the part of India to make an illegitimate claim on a nation’s territory, a violation of its absolute sovereignty. Populist rhetoric amplified the notion. The Chief of the Indian Army staff, M M Naravane (who is also the honorary General of the Nepal Army) went on to say that the Nepalese protests were being conducted under the behest of “another country” primarily indicating China. Nepalese Defence Minister Ishwor Pokhrel replied to this saying that the comments had been an “insulting statement”, resulting out of ignorance of Nepal’s history, freedom and social characteristics. He further made an allusion to the sentiments of Nepali Gurkha army personnel, a majority of whom are engaged in the Indian Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Diplomatic Ramifications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Nepali Parliament, Oli had reiterated the intention to reclaim the Indian territory, referring to it as being under the ‘occupation’ of the latter. However, his derogatory jibes at the Indian national emblem, manifesting in his controversial remark wondering if India subscribed to the physical aspect of the emblem - the Lion Capital of Ashoka - &lt;em&gt;“simhaev jayate’’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;“satyamev jayate”&lt;/em&gt; (truth alone prevails), led to a deepening of the diplomatic rife between the two otherwise conciliatory foreign policies pursued by the two nations. The issue had been in the priority list of the Nepalese Government ever since Oli’s second term in power began in 2018. New Delhi in spite of its repeated emphasis on the ‘Neighbourhood First’ policy had turned a blind eye. A dent in the mutual relationship between the two had begun to deepen since 2015 when Oli’s government had promulgated Nepal’s new Constitution, widely dubbed by India as flawed since it didn’t include the political aspirations of individuals from the Terai region - Madhesis and Tharus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The border blockade by the Madhesis that followed had allegedly received “Indian support”, according to Oli’s government. It is believed in diplomatic circles that although no evidence of Chinese connection or support has been found in the formulation of the border dispute, Oli is confident of Chinese support in further provoking India. Many believe this stance of his is a result of the turmoil in Nepal’s domestic policy. Oli may be trying to outdo his friend-turned-foe, Pushpa Kumar Dahal Prachanda, creating a scenario that might jeopardise a smooth diplomatic exchange with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need of the hour is to revive diplomatic channels between the two nations. Kalapani continues to be an important area of dispute due to the presence of an Indian military post present there. Kalapani has massive strategic importance to India as it shares a border on the North with the Tibet Autonomous Region of China, and Nepal in the East and South. It falls on the route to Mansarovar, a pilgrimage site in Tibet. It helps India in tracking Chinese movements in the region. The Lipulekh pass, on the other hand, had been an ancient route of trade and pilgrimage but had been temporarily closed following the Indo-China War of 1962. Options to ensure joint sovereignty can be taken as a way out, in times of such a major cartographic dispute. The idea of negotiation had been echoed in 1999, when the then Indian Prime Minister, I K Gujral had said &lt;em&gt;“If Nepal can prove Kalapani belongs to it, we will give it up”&lt;/em&gt;. However, the task of locating the source of a boundary river, coupled with a watershed, remains a Herculean task.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“We are working to ensure territorial integrity, national sovereignty, and freedom of our people. The kings of Nepal lost our territory, but today we republicans are restoring it.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Large Fiscal Deficits and No Defaults: Is it Possible?</title><link href="/Large-Fiscal-Deficits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Large Fiscal Deficits and No Defaults: Is it Possible?" /><published>2020-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Large-Fiscal-Deficits</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Large-Fiscal-Deficits">&lt;p&gt;Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is an unconventional economic theory that has been gaining traction recently. Though the theory has been in development for many years now, the coronavirus pandemic sparked a debate about the usefulness of the theory in the real world. So, this might be the right time to know what the theory is about and what are the implications of it. For better understanding, let us try to contrast this with conventional economic theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taxes and Inflation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MMT states that countries with a higher degree of monetary sovereignty can run large fiscal deficits without worrying about defaulting on the debt. A country is said to have monetary sovereignty if it prints its own currency, issues debt in its currency, and does not promise to convert it into, say, any other currency or gold. The theory asserts that governments are not dependent on taxes or borrowings to finance their expenditure. According to MMT, taxes are instruments through which governments create demand for their currency. This makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if the Indian government were to declare that taxes are to be paid in the form of rice crops from tomorrow, all the transactions would shift to being carried in rice crops and it would become the medium of exchange. Therefore, by ordaining the acceptable medium to settle one’s debt obligation, a country is essentially creating demand for that medium (dollars, rupees, etc.). The power to levy taxes and to issue currency makes the government a ‘money monopolist’. This is in contrast to mainstream economics which says that the government needs to borrow or increase taxes to bridge the government deficit. According to MMT, the only constraint on government expenditure is inflation and the availability of real resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MMT also says that as long as there is no (excess) inflation, the government can spend money to achieve full employment in the economy. It further supports the idea of a tax to control inflation: increase taxes to rein in inflation and decreases in taxes to boost aggregate demand. However, for tax cuts to work well, they should benefit people whose marginal propensity to spend is high. MMT rejects the idea of Non-Accelerating Inflation Rate of Unemployment (NAIRU), which is the level of unemployment below which inflation begins to increase. It is a theoretical concept which cannot be observed or calculated, and one can only find it when a further rise in employment (or fall in unemployment) raises inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What all the central banks across the world do today is that they set an inflation target and alter the interest rate to reach the target, withstanding any amount of unemployment in the process. Dr Stephanie Kelton, a proponent of MMT, observed in her book &lt;em&gt;The Deficit Myth&lt;/em&gt; that, &lt;em&gt;“to put it crudely, the [central banks] use unemployed human beings as [their] primary weapon against inflation.”&lt;/em&gt; Instead, MMT prescribes a universal job guarantee to combat unemployment. It believes that such a job guarantee will act as an automatic stabiliser that will promote both full employment and price stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interest Rates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventional economic theory states that huge government debts will lead to an increase in the interest rates in the long run, which is harmful to the economy. This idea, however, is rejected by MMT. According to MMT, since the central banks have control over the short-term interest rate and also significant influence over the long-term interest rates, large debts will not increase interest rates. Apart from this, MMT also notes that markets can always be stripped off of any influence over the interest rates. Japan is a case in point. With a debt-to-GDP ratio of 238%, highest in the world, the interest rates are near-zero. This is because, along with influencing the short-term interest rates, the bank of Japan (BoJ) had committed to maintaining the interest rates on ten-year government bonds near zero (which is done by buying government bonds on large quantities, i.e. buying government debt). Note how both long-term and short-term interest rates are influenced by the central bank of Japan. By doing this, the central banks anywhere in the world can prevent interest rates from rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could question whether this would not lead to inflation. (The answer is, no) Eric Lonergan, an economist and a hedge fund manager has an answer to this question. It goes like this. When BoJ buys the Japan government bonds and pays out cash, the investors, instead of government bonds, will now hold the same value (of that of bonds) in cash. While there is no effect on wealth, there is a loss of interest income. So essentially, paying off government debt will lead to a fall in interest income in the private sector. MMT further argues that there is no need for a government to buy bonds to finance its debt and it is only a choice the government makes. This is because the government can spend by crediting the appropriate bank account (through the central bank), without issuing any bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crowding Out Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conventional thinking is that the government will compete with the private sector from a limited pool of savings to fund its deficits. When the fiscal deficit increases, the government will have to borrow more; which will leave lesser funds available for the private sector, leading to the crowding out effect. This idea is also contested by MMT. According to MMT, government spending is self-financing. Government running deficits, in the first place, will put the money the private sector uses to buy bonds. Let’s understand this using some equations given by an important MMT figure, Wynne Godley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Y= National Income; C= Consumption; I=Investment; G= Government expenditure; X-M= net exports; S= savings; T= taxes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y = C + I + G + X - M — (1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y = C + S + T — (2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From (1) and (2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S + T = I + G + X - M&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reordering,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(S - I) = (G-T) + (X-M)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If (X-M) &amp;lt;= 0, there is no current account surplus,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For (S-I) to be positive, (G-T) must be positive. Therefore, government deficit means private surplus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, when the government issues bonds to bridge its fiscal deficit, the deficit itself is supplying the money necessary to purchase the bonds. For this very reason, MMT states that there will be no crowding out. It is also apparent from the above equations that government deficits will always lead to a fiscal surplus (surplus in financial assets) in the non-government sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indian Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now look at MMT from an Indian vantage point. Though India doesn’t have the monetary sovereignty as high as the US, UK or Japan etc., Indian government borrows in Indian rupees only. That leaves scope for implementation of MMT prescriptions. In fact, one study shows that despite &lt;a href=&quot;https://macromyths.blogspot.com/2018/02/mmt-at-work-case-of-india.html&quot;&gt;high fiscal deficits&lt;/a&gt; there has been ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncaer.org/free-download.php?pID=290&quot;&gt;crowding in’ effect&lt;/a&gt; rather than crowding out effect in India in the period 1980-2015. This is clearly in agreement with the MMT theory. The high fiscal deficits that India ran could very well be the reason for the faster growth that India achieved since the 1991 reforms. Also, India already has in place the job guarantee scheme advocated by MMT economists, MNREGA, although not universally. But there are some problems in India as far as MMT recommendations are concerned. First, the number of taxpayers in India is marginal. Second, the underground economy is prevalent in India. These two factors might not be very effective when it comes to using taxes to create space for fiscal expansion. However, there is also one &lt;a href=&quot;https://macromyths.blogspot.com/2018/02/mmt-at-work-case-of-india.html&quot;&gt;argument&lt;/a&gt; that India is already using MMT solutions unwittingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MMT essentially argues for a greater role of fiscal policy and subsidiary role of monetary policy. Prescriptions like a universal job guarantee, using taxes to cut inflation, etc. are cases in point. According to MMT economists, taxes (or borrowing) pay for nothing. However, taxes are important for other purposes like controlling inflation to create space for fiscal expansion, redistribution of wealth, ensuring not too much political power is concentrated in a few hands, and so on. For them, the universal job guarantee is an automatic stabiliser which will provide employment to all those who are unemployed by the private sector, and mitigate the pains for those who are fired from employment. The final result is that MMT wants everyone to focus on economic balance, full employment, and price stability. All that MMT asks from you is to concentrate on the economic outcomes rather than budget outcomes and economic balance rather than balanced budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more on MMT, you can read the following books:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1.  The Deficit Myth – Stephanie Kelton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2.  The Case for a Job Guarantee - Pavlina R. Tcherneva&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3.  Soft Currency Economics II: The Origin of Modern Monetary Theory – Warren Mosler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4.  Modern Money Theory: A Primer on Macroeconomics for Sovereign Monetary Systems - L. Randall Wray&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is an unconventional economic theory that has been gaining traction recently. Though the theory has been in development for many years now, the coronavirus pandemic sparked a debate about the usefulness of the theory in the real world. So, this might be the right time to know what the theory is about and what are the implications of it. For better understanding, let us try to contrast this with conventional economic theory.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">India-China Feud: To Boycott or Not?</title><link href="/India-China-Feud" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="India-China Feud: To Boycott or Not?" /><published>2020-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/India-China-Feud</id><content type="html" xml:base="/India-China-Feud">&lt;p&gt;As the world battles the wrath and economic standstill that has emanated from the COVID-19 pandemic, geopolitical tensions have soared in East Asia along the non-delineated borders of India and China. The altercations that ensued between the two nations, along the historically peaceful region of the Galwan River Valley, peaked in mid-June when China attempted to unilaterally change the status quo by violating the sovereignty of the Line of Actual Control (LAC). While the LAC, unlike the Line of Control (LoC) between India and Pakistan, remains non-demarcated and hasn’t been internationally agreed upon, it has ironically sustained relative peace. However, the 2020 skirmishes resulted in 20 casualties on the Indian side while China is said to have lost an unconfirmed number, despite the clash being restrained with no use of bullets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China has been globally targeted for its neocolonialist approach over the past decade, be it through cheque-book diplomacy as in the case of Sri Lanka, or through blatant expansionist policies, as in the current scenario. When India refused to participate in the first Belt and Road Initiative summit in May 2017, it practically refused to fall for the former approach and became a hindrance to China’s grand geopolitical strategy, resulting in the orchestrated Doklam standoff that followed a month later, in June 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bears weak resemblance to the current scenario, wherein the export consignment of faulty medical equipment by nationalised Chinese pharmaceutical companies and the possibility of COVID-19 being an engineered bioweapon has turned global sentiments against the Chinese economy in general. As a consequence, global investment portfolio rebalancing is expected. Additionally, many major MNCs realised that they had put too many eggs in one basket, and are looking to move their production units to South Asia, where India stands waiting in anticipation with lucrative policies. This speculation has prevailed since the US-China trade war began but has been concretised over the past quarter, leading many to believe that this was as much of motivation behind the violation of the de-facto border as the local territorial integrity. While peace is the prioritised goal, the primary objective for India remains to restore the status quo ante, leading to prolonged conflict. Since both nuclear powers ascribe to the ‘no first use’ policy, the dispute has permeated into the economic foreground leading to calls for a strategic boycott.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discord comes at an opportune time for China, as India closes to the peak of COVID-19 and faces a fragile and vulnerable state of affairs. The financial markets have rallied temporarily, and have, since February, gone through the Denial-FOMO (fear of missing out) cycle identified by Robert Shiller in the American markets, which can be loosely extrapolated to fit the Indian scenario. Once again, the stock market appears to be considerably decoupled from the state of the economy which is said to be headed towards depression. In such a situation, the escalation of bilateral tensions with a nation that accounts for over 16% of total imports and 9% of total exports of India is seemingly not a viable course of action. Although, as proclaimed by many, the boycott, if successful, will not be entirely harmless, and ironically, this is the best time to put it to action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India majorly imports organic chemicals and electrical machinery from China to be used as raw materials in the Indian industries. Both can be procured from separate sources, at slightly higher prices, which might interfere with pharmaceutical price control regulations in case of organic chemicals. But hiking import duties on non-essentials is definitely a doable move at this juncture when the fall in imports is much larger than the fall in exports due to slowdown in industrial activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as the nation proceeds to unlock and the economic cycle initiates, it is unlikely that businesses will be able to afford the switch and diversify their supply chains. Ideally, the graph of the India-China trade balance mapped as a function of the timeline since the initiation of a (successful) boycott should take a familiar tilted J-shape, with the curve beginning in the negative-Y (deficit for India) threshold. The initial crater of the J-curve is owed to the inelasticity of demand, and the deficits might worsen when the economy reopens and imports rise from their current low levels. Eventually, as the demand revives, and (if and only if) the businesses remain encouraged to diversify their supply chains, the boycott may be considered successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the argument remains that this will be more of a diplomatic win rather than an economic one. In order to play this strategically and move towards what Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calls an &lt;em&gt;‘Atma Nirbhar’&lt;/em&gt; (self-dependent) India, free of import dependence, one must play for the long haul. China became the world’s factory because of its extremely cheap wages, but it managed to remain so despite the 8,500% wage increase since the past 30 years, solely due to its simplified policy framework. Chapter - 6, Volume - 1 of the Indian Economic Survey 2020, elaborates poignantly how China fairs better than India in virtually all the parameters of the Ease of Doing Business Index by the World Bank. The complications involved in acquiring construction permits, licenses, and the magnitude of applicable rules and statutory laws for manufacturing are quite overwhelming for any business to venture into India. Although there have been underrated reforms like the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code of 2016 that have been revolutionary in disciplining the attitude of businesses towards their sources of finance, we still need a major revamping of the legal system of the nation in order to strengthen contract enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another pertinent question that we need to ask ourselves is that even if the global economy permits, are we ready to become net exporters even in the long run? India’s growth story has always been driven by local consumption power, which is also skewed towards import-intensive goods. That leaves little room for domestic savings, leaving us prying for FDI, and that demand is honoured since India is a favourable destination during prosperous periods owing to the lucrative emerging market grade returns. A country can have either a net current account surplus or a capital account surplus, we face the latter case. China faces the former, by its choice. It even resorted to the old currency devaluation tactic back in 2019, when the trade war with the US began to frustrate the officials with threats of taking away the current account surplus. This surplus is precious to China due to the grand strategy of foreign capital investment it has undertaken under its neocolonialist approach. But India cannot steal both the FDI and the exports of China, that would go against macroeconomic fundamentals. This is practically why many have opposed the idea of a boycott and called for more government focus on rearing natural competition while reaping the advantages of smooth FDI. It is eventually up to the government to prioritise and strike an ideal balance between diplomatic and economic victories, which may not go hand in hand in the short run.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">As the world battles the wrath and economic standstill that has emanated from the COVID-19 pandemic, geopolitical tensions have soared in East Asia along the non-delineated borders of India and China. The altercations that ensued between the two nations, along the historically peaceful region of the Galwan River Valley, peaked in mid-June when China attempted to unilaterally change the status quo by violating the sovereignty of the Line of Actual Control (LAC). While the LAC, unlike the Line of Control (LoC) between India and Pakistan, remains non-demarcated and hasn’t been internationally agreed upon, it has ironically sustained relative peace. However, the 2020 skirmishes resulted in 20 casualties on the Indian side while China is said to have lost an unconfirmed number, despite the clash being restrained with no use of bullets.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“I don’t belong here”</title><link href="/Dont-Belong-Here" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“I don’t belong here”" /><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Dont-Belong-Here</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Dont-Belong-Here">&lt;p&gt;With the latest lockdown extension, I am back to dilly-dallying and fraught musings. While I watch &lt;em&gt;House of Cards&lt;/em&gt; for the third time, I wonder how one can be so smart and manipulative and yet, question themselves. How the mind that makes us perform all the good, is also the one that makes us question each action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these times where we put ourselves to uses more than we can avail, where multiple to-do lists loom over our heads, it is easy to maintain a fail-safe, procrastinate, and be stressed. But there is another issue on the other side of the spectrum that we do not usually talk about. A fear, if I may call it that, of how we are being able to perform these tasks, and with suave too. The other day, I had just washed my hands of paint and stopped to see what I had painted. I actually liked it. On any other day, I just sit there and count flaws, but I did not. I could not. And, thus, I called it my lucky day, took a picture of it, and off went my Snapchat. Ah, a happy day. A happy day that brought in new questions. After my usual tip-dip-trip to Google, I found that there prevails a phenomenon that affects many - the ‘Impostor Syndrome’. It is a persistent feeling that causes someone to doubt their accomplishments despite evidence and fear they may be exposed as a fraud. It caught my interest and also managed to make me redirect my thought process on multiple occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times have we felt like we did not belong with the ones who excel, that we did not deserve the appreciation, that we had somehow managed to fool everyone around us? I sure have. Even on a day that I am sure I had prepared more than I needed to and did well in the task, I give about 70% of the credit to luck. Other times, when I do not score well, the very first thought in my head is, “See? You are not as smart as you’d like to believe you are.” Some have described their experience with impostor syndrome as a feeling of being trapped in a situation where you are well out of your depth and have no way out. People affected by this syndrome show a common behaviour: they are often remarkably successful, overachieving on a regular basis and are considered experts by others, but deep down they feel like frauds, scared of being unmasked anytime. It may seem hard to believe, but there is a huge discrepancy between the false image they own of themselves and what others see, they live an internal conflict. Psychologists Clance and Imes first described the impostor phenomenon in 1978; Kolligian and Sternberg in 2000 suggested that we should categorise this mental fraudulence experience as a category in personality disorder or pervasive mental disorder for it is known not as a symptom but a self-perception or self-referral ideation with cognitive and emotional-affective components. However, until today, the syndrome has not been acknowledged psychiatrically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The syndrome mind-trap prevents people from believing in themselves to the detriment of us all. Reading the cases (and oh, the famous!), the way it has been portrayed, I wondered if it was just low self-esteem or not having plenty of self-confidence. But self-doubt and low self-confidence levels are seen to be symptoms of impostor syndrome, and at its core, it is said to be a self-assessment problem. I’d say there are three ways to muster the syndrome, “Hello, I’m fake”; “Hello, I’m just lucky”; and my favourite, “Hello, this thing!? Oh, it’s nothing.” Now, you cannot tell me you haven’t uttered any of these, just like I can’t tell you having said any (or all) of this implies that you have the syndrome. Blimey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon looking up literature on the phenomenon, I was surprised to find that most of it revolved around women, while research has shown that there is no certain gender effect, seemingly people don’t believe so, and well, who are we to fault, but society? More on that, someday. The most important factor that influences this syndrome is found to be the connection link between family variables, personality variables, destructive beliefs, and the unpleasant consequences of progress. The family and child-rearing method along with the attribution styles really make the play. As a child, we are often taught not to be over-confident, or well, too self-serving. While, how you are brought up plays a huge role, let me just say, that is not the only factor. Your personality, your own disposition, and its marriage to how well your esteem was nurtured are what make the magic happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all the research about who is feeling what and why they did manage to find out certain types to this syndrome. Valerie Young suggested five types: The Perfectionist who piles up their own expectations and does most of them and still feels like a failure. The Experts feel the need to know every piece of information and, are always wanting to improve their skills, however, they continue to question it. The Soloist is someone who feels the need to do everything on their own and if they want for help, they count it as a failure. The Superwoman/man pushes themselves to work harder than those around them to prove that they are not imposters. And lastly, The Great Mind, or the Natural Genius, their problem is that if they have to struggle or work hard to accomplish something, they think it means they are not good enough. I suppose it says something about me that even putting myself in one of these boxes, is making me mildly anxious. Ha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting is that when individuals with this phenomenon face a competitive situation; they show two reactions: they either become negligent and make up excuses for doing the given task or spend excessive energy doing it. What should not come as a surprise is how strongly it is associated with psychological distress- depression and anxiety and is heavily linked to burnout too. Holding yourself to impossible standards, trying to control your environment and comparing yourself to others: these three are the silent triggers. They lead to self-assessment standards that are unreachable, making you feel like you will never measure up and that you don’t deserve what you have. Time and again, these feelings may flutter by, but are they only bad? Is there any good to it? I mean, at the end of the day, it does involve self-talk, and reflection, however negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Hermione (Emma Watson, to the uncultured), herself, has it, I would say there must be something to it. Amidst the 30 or so famous names that &lt;em&gt;InStyle&lt;/em&gt; shows me on a slideshow, with even Meryl Streep making a cameo, there is much to how one feels the fear. Just the statements made by someone who inhabits it can let you know. Most times, fear is considered weak, however, this could very well be a strength in its own right. The ones affected see flaws in their work where others do not and self-medicate against it by aiming for perfection, and when has perfection ever been less than (I apologise) perfect. Studies have shown that people perform at higher levels when they are worried about being (or seeming) incompetent. There is a paradoxical similarity between the self-views of people who are really competent and the self-views of those who are not. Would you say that feeling like a fraud when you should not is probably not as bad as not feeling like a fraud when you should?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people experience moments of doubt, and that is normal. The important part is said to be not to let that doubt control your actions and, well, to appease you, still, I have Bertrand Russell, telling us all- &lt;em&gt;“The whole problem with the world is that fools and fanatics are always so certain of themselves, and wiser people so full of doubts.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">With the latest lockdown extension, I am back to dilly-dallying and fraught musings. While I watch House of Cards for the third time, I wonder how one can be so smart and manipulative and yet, question themselves. How the mind that makes us perform all the good, is also the one that makes us question each action.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coughing Losses: Indian States Subject to Austerity</title><link href="/Coughing-Losses" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coughing Losses: Indian States Subject to Austerity" /><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Coughing-Losses</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Coughing-Losses">&lt;p&gt;As the number of COVID-19 cases continue to burgeon around the globe, most countries are experiencing an unprecedented slowdown with a shrinkage in economic activities. The already prevailing global slowdown in the pre-corona months has fused with the present-day scenario, resulting in an economic jolt. The ‘Great Lockdown’ as the IMF calls it, will give birth to economies with lowered interest rates and public debts reaching record levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India stands as the third worst-hit country globally with a tally nearing 700,000 cases. Looking deeper into the domestic circumstances, it is an unfortunate coincidence that the five gravely affected Indian states: Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu, Delhi, Gujarat and Uttar Pradesh, constitute 42% of India’s GDP. It is estimated that these five will make-up 48% of the total losses all the states will incur in 2020-21. Dried-up cash inflows have disconcerted both the Union and State Governments, however, as the actual battle is being fought by the State Governments and they are incurring the associated expenditure, the hardship is greater for them. With grave fiscal constraints, dealing with the loss of livelihoods has become a matter of concern for most states just as saving lives has. Cash handouts and provisions for subsidised food/ration have been put in place by states as humanitarian expenditure, not to ease the crisis. The return of migrant workers has exacerbated the problem with the disbursement on transport, quarantine facilities and rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite ironically, the ₹20.9 trillion stimulus package, which has been claimed to be 10% of the national GDP by the Union Government, is, in fact, an exiguous 0.8% of the GDP, as authenticated by a DSB Bank report and several other experts. This is one reason why the States have been demanding resources from the Union Government. The prime reason still lies in the fact that all the influential contributors (states) generated 60-70% of revenue from their own sources. These states gave us 75% of the GDP generated and hence, were the driving engines of the national economy—and therefore need and deserve more financial packages. Moreover, due to the already existing economic crunch that had affected the nation even before COVID-19, State Governments have been experiencing serious revenue impediments through the second half of 2019-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value Added Tax (VAT) on petroleum and excise duty on alcohol are the two predominant sources of revenue for states. Alcohol fosters the generation of ₹150 billion for states, on average, every month, along with ₹2 trillion brought in by petroleum products. The lockdown witnessed a plunge in the demand for petroleum and a collapse in the sale of alcohol, drying up the states’ revenues. The states generating a major portion of finances through their own resources are worst affected owing to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as the lockdown begins to ease out, relief is a far away dream for the states, liquor vendors are expecting a 25% fall in sales this year and bars have barely witnessed any footfall. Even though Delhi increased the excise duty on liquor, the gains weren’t fruitful enough to make good the deficit. Although oil prices in the international market stand truncated, the Union Government has continued to keep the prices high along with an escalation in the central excise duty to make good its deficit, so even if states increase VAT on petroleum, they are left with a very cramped taxing area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Goods and Services Tax (GST), which is collected by the Centre and then shared with the states comprises 43-44% of the revenue. Ever since its implementation, states have complained of revenue losses. One principal reason for this is the delayed and uneven release of the GST compensation. Compensation for December 2019 to February 2020 was released only in June, this led to much hue and cry as the states were starved of revenue during the lockdown. The Union Government’s assurance of a 14% annual growth for the next five years in the states’ GST revenue concoct mere dreams as the target is highly unachievable as they are likely to grow at a much lower rate. The only escape is borrowing, either the Centre borrows to issue grants to the states or the GST Council will have to borrow in order to keep pace with the share of compensation due to the states during these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crisis in hand, the Indian states have limited recourse. They can either cut down on their budgeted expenditure or increase tax buoyancy or increase their borrowings. Expenditure taps in the form of salaries, pensions, allowances, interests, etc. have already been turned off by many states as a cut in salaries, freezing of allowances and increments have been ordered by the State Governments. This compression of public expenditure is unlikely to provide the desired results. Borrowing from the market looks like candy to the eye and shall curb the issue of revenue in the short run, but states can’t afford to ignore the hindrances in borrowing, such as an expansion of the fiscal deficit in the long run. The second reason looks more political in nature, the Centre has inflicted four conditions on states – universalisation of ration cards, improvement in ease of doing business, reforms to make state-owned power distribution companies more profitable, and shoring up urban local body revenues. On the one hand, these conditions restrict the borrowing tendency of the states and on the other hand, the Centre has conveniently brimmed-up their coffer from ₹4.2 trillion to ₹12 trillion by inflating borrowings by 54% over the estimated budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation joins hands to fight the contagious virus but it seems that there is a grave disagreement between the States and the Centre when it comes to revenue generation, allotment and financial grants. The Centre curtails the income opportunities of the States through numerous constraints, yet expects States to fight the crisis on their own. The States look for grants in order to release the salaries of their employees and expects the Centre to reveal a package of at least 4-5% of the GDP. Many economists believe that an addition to the 15th Indian Finance Commission report, which allocates financial resources between the Centre and the states, in the form of a COVID-19 grant to states shall be a helping hand. A collaborative effort towards a common strategy aimed at rooting out the pandemic to ‘mask the losses being coughed by the states’ is the actual need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">As the number of COVID-19 cases continue to burgeon around the globe, most countries are experiencing an unprecedented slowdown with a shrinkage in economic activities. The already prevailing global slowdown in the pre-corona months has fused with the present-day scenario, resulting in an economic jolt. The ‘Great Lockdown’ as the IMF calls it, will give birth to economies with lowered interest rates and public debts reaching record levels.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Britain’s ‘New Deal’?</title><link href="/Britain-New-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Britain’s ‘New Deal’?" /><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Britain-New-Deal</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Britain-New-Deal">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Build, build, build”&lt;/em&gt; was the mantra set out by the British Prime Minister Boris Johnson last week in the town of Dudley. Infrastructure spending will be the way out of the current malaise. On the surface, his plan sounds bold. Using billions of pounds of public money to improve railways and hospitals sounds more like a traditional Labour pledge than a Tory one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intent is noble. Anyone journeying around this green and pleasant land can’t fail to realise that our towns are in need of more than just a lick of paint. But saying that infrastructure spending alone will return us to growth takes a stretch even the PM isn’t capable of. His plan to build the economy out of the crisis is reminiscent of a seven-year old’s understanding of how an economy works. &lt;em&gt;“Build more! Make more!”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the PM’s plan is that it is a clear attempt to keep unemployment as low as possible, whatever the cost. Employing people to build bridges and fill potholes is a good public service, but it won’t grow the economy. In bad times, what an economy needs is not jobs. It needs increased productivity and savings derived from those jobs. With the best will in the world, paying six people a pittance to repaint a double-yellow in Ipswich, for the sake of keeping down unemployment, won’t do this. In the Soviet Union, everyone had a job, but nobody was producing anything valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boris Johnson has been desperate to compare his own plan to Roosevelt’s fabled ‘New Deal’, which promised to save America from the Great Depression by laying down new highways and putting up countless public works. But Roosevelt found out the productive limits of infrastructure spending the hard way. Across the 1930’s, US industrial production and national income fell by around a third, and the public works programmes failed to put a dent in unemployment numbers, which stayed above 15% until 1940. It was supplying the Allies in Europe with domestically produced weaponry, as well as America’s Pacific war with Japan, which eventually rescued the US from the worst manufacturing slump in its history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all our countries, we will spend the next two or three years discussing how to recover from the fallout of the COVID-19 pandemic. I will wager now that few of the plans put forth by the political establishment at that time will address the most important question of this episode. And it’s this: &lt;em&gt;why did the governments of the developed nations have to intervene in their economies in such an extreme way?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that most of the state intervention carried out in Europe and America since March would not have been necessary if our households and our businesses had savings to fall back on. But they don’t. Before the pandemic, British household debt was almost £1.3 trillion, 30% of Americans had less than $1,000 in savings, and corporate debt in both countries was at record highs. No economy in such a shape can withstand a shock like a lockdown. Or any shock, in fact - if it hadn’t been the coronavirus, something else would have had the same effect: a cyber hack, an energy meltdown, financial collapse or a nuclear exchange in Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why it is so futile to suggest solutions as oversimplified as the one which the PM cooked up this week. Britain doesn’t need more low-paid jobs, or more welfare, it needs more assets. It needs to produce more and sell more. And most of all, people in the country have to save what they earn. That way, missing a paycheck is irritating, but it’s not a calamity. Any state solution, from left or right, which doesn’t acknowledge this glaring blind spot is a non-starter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I hear there are plenty of construction jobs in Bristol putting up new statues. I expect I’ll have company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>.</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">“Build, build, build” was the mantra set out by the British Prime Minister Boris Johnson last week in the town of Dudley. Infrastructure spending will be the way out of the current malaise. On the surface, his plan sounds bold. Using billions of pounds of public money to improve railways and hospitals sounds more like a traditional Labour pledge than a Tory one.</summary></entry></feed>