<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-29T11:01:17+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">US-Qatar F-35A Deal: A Bed of Diplomatic Nails</title><link href="/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="US-Qatar F-35A Deal: A Bed of Diplomatic Nails" /><published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal</id><content type="html" xml:base="/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We are going to move ahead, we hope, with designating Qatar a major non-NATO ally&lt;/em&gt;.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Announced Timothy Lenderking, US Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Gulf Affairs, in a conference call on September 17, 2020. The US Secretary of State Mike Pompeo and the Qatar Foreign Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman Al Thani met at Washington DC bestowing the status of a non-NATO ally on Qatar. This means that Qatar will gain preferential access to US military equipment and technology, free surplus material, prioritised cooperation on training and expedited export processing. The other Arab Gulf states including Kuwait and Bahrain are among the 17 states which enjoy Major non-NATO ally (MNNA) status, besides hosting the US Navy's Fifth fleet. However, the US recognition of Qatar has sparked off a series of rows in the aftermath of Qatar's bitter relations with nations like Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Bahrain and Egypt since 2017. The US, which enjoys strong diplomatic relations with all the powerful Middle Eastern states has been viewing the rift as an attempt to thwart the Trump administration’s efforts to contain Iran. A new united Middle East led by the United States seems to be the game plan to rain on Iran's parade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Quartet Blockade against Qatar&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Qatar-Saudi Arabia diplomatic tensions, often referred to as the Second Arab Cold War, had been the result of a fallout between Qatar and Saudi Arabia who shared a severely antagonistic relationship since the beginning of the Arab Spring Revolution, which had created a power vacuum in the region. David S Cohen, the then Deputy Director of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), had famously called Qatar a safe haven for “&lt;em&gt;terrorist financiers to operate with impunity&lt;/em&gt;.” Qatar had been supportive of the revolutionary wave,&amp;nbsp; while Saudi Arabia had opposed it tooth and nail. The fight on grounds of soft power has also escalated between the two nations - Qatar's broadcaster Al Jazeera supported the Arab Spring, which was construed by Saudi Arabia as attempts to topple its monarchy. The Saudis had also been wary of Qatar's stable relationship with Iran, thus, framing the conflict with Qatar as a ramification of the Iran-Saudi proxy conflict - all stemming from Saudi Arabia’s trouble with the infiltration by Iran and Iran-backed militant groups into the Arab Spring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates and Egypt have been steadfastly opposing any action by Qatar and Turkey and their support of democratic, Islamist and Salafi extremist groups during the Syrian Civil War. Post the Saudi execution of Nimr al Nimr in 2016, which drew worldwide condemnation from human rights groups and international organisations, Qatar severed all diplomatic ties with Iran. During the Yemeni Civil War in 2011-12, both Qatar and Saudi Arabia fought side-by-side against the alleged Iran-backed Houthi militants. It is important to note that the undercurrents of this fight may be traced to an ambition to gain regional hegemony, thus, in spite of being members of the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) the animosities continue to exist, resurfacing now and then. All hell broke loose in June 2017, when Saudi Arabia, the UAE, Bahrain, Egypt, Maldives, Mauritania, Senegal, Djibouti, Comoros, Jordan, the Tobruk based Libyan government severed diplomatic relations with Qatar and blocked Qatar's sea routes and airspace. Saudi Arabia went a step further blocking the only land route Qatar shared with Iran. The reaction came as a prompt response to Al Jazeera allegedly airing negative information pertaining to it's fellow GCC nations and its policy of “going soft&quot; on Islamist terror groups by allowing terror financiers to operate freely within its borders. Ron Prosor, an Israeli diplomat went so far to regard it as “the Club Med for Terrorists.” Thus, is it no surprise that close proximity between Qatar and the US has been a cause of concern for the other GCC members which includes UAE and Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;US-Qatar ties down the Age&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Qatar and US deal of 2020 shouldn't be treated as a case in isolation, rather a culmination of mutually beneficial ties handed over from decades ago. Since 1992, Qatar has been instrumental in building military ties and currently plays host to the US Central Command's Forward Headquarters and the Combined Air Operations Centre. It also has the Al Udeid Air Base and the As Sayliyah Army Base, among which the former is the largest American airbase in the Middle East. In 2014, the US sold $11 billion worth of arms to Qatar which also included the AH 64 Apache attack helicopters, Javelin and Patriot defence systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signing of the $12 billion deal regarding the purchase of 36F-15 QA strike aircraft imported from the USA in 2017 may also be treated as a milestone in the bilateral relationship of the two nations. The governments of the United States and the State of Qatar held their third Strategic Dialogue on September 14 and 15, 2020. The United States and Qatar signed a Memorandum of Understanding on education, culture and sports in addition to a Statement of Intent (SoI) designating 2021 as the US-Qatar Year of Culture and an Announcement of Intent for Qatar to host an investment forum in the United States in 2021. Furthermore, the United States also recognised Qatar’s effective leadership to establish peace and reconciliation among contending factions in Somalia and Sudan. The two nations noted an increase in bilateral trade where US exports to Qatar increased by 39% between 2018 and 2019. The United States remains Qatar’s largest foreign direct investor and largest trading partner. The two nations had also discussed the $26 billion Foreign Military Sales program which continued to increase the capability and capacity of the Qatar Armed Forces. The progress in these areas will be reviewed at the Policy Working Group meeting in Washington DC in the first quarter of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2020 Deal: A Bed of Nails&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US intervention in this area was evident in September 2020, when David Schenker, the State Department’s top diplomat for the Middle East stated that the three-year-old blockade might be lifted within a span of “weeks”. Thus, Kuwait and the United States have made an attempt to mediate a rift which was acting as a stumbling block in Washington's aim of uniting the Middle East against Iran. Schenker said, “&lt;em&gt;These are two sides that are dug in... and yet there is a recognition that this is a distraction from Iran&lt;/em&gt;.” However achieving diplomatic victory is a far cry as the boycotting nations set 13 demands which include the closing of Al Jazeera Media Network, downgrading ties with Iran and cutting links with Turkish Brotherhood. However, the Israel factor plays an important cameo. The United States is considering selling F-35s to Qatar as a side deal to the US-brokered agreement between Israel and UAE dubbed as the Abraham Accord. Israel, which had previously signalled stiff opposition to a UAE-US deal, is bound to express similar sentiments towards the deal with Qatar. The Qatari and UAE F-35 deals have to take into consideration the decade-old US-Israel deal that states any US weapons sold to the region must not impair Israel's “qualitative military edge”, thereby ensuring that US weapons furnished to Israel are “superior in quality” in comparison to the ones sold to its neighbours. However, the fifth-generation fighter jet F-35A which is estimated to cost around $80 million has its fate hanging in the air, influenced by the potential havoc it could wreck and alter diplomatic relations in the oil-rich Middle East. Thus it remains imperative for the US to take into consideration the geopolitics in this area lest it becomes a diplomatic graveyard of its ambitions in this region.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“We are going to move ahead, we hope, with designating Qatar a major non-NATO ally.”&amp;nbsp; Announced Timothy Lenderking, US Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Gulf Affairs, in a conference call on September 17, 2020. The US Secretary of State Mike Pompeo and the Qatar Foreign Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman Al Thani met at Washington DC bestowing the status of a non-NATO ally on Qatar. This means that Qatar will gain preferential access to US military equipment and technology, free surplus material, prioritised cooperation on training and expedited export processing. The other Arab Gulf states including Kuwait and Bahrain are among the 17 states which enjoy Major non-NATO ally (MNNA) status, besides hosting the US Navy's Fifth fleet. However, the US recognition of Qatar has sparked off a series of rows in the aftermath of Qatar's bitter relations with nations like Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Bahrain and Egypt since 2017. The US, which enjoys strong diplomatic relations with all the powerful Middle Eastern states has been viewing the rift as an attempt to thwart the Trump administration’s efforts to contain Iran. A new united Middle East led by the United States seems to be the game plan to rain on Iran's parade. The Quartet Blockade against Qatar&amp;nbsp; The Qatar-Saudi Arabia diplomatic tensions, often referred to as the Second Arab Cold War, had been the result of a fallout between Qatar and Saudi Arabia who shared a severely antagonistic relationship since the beginning of the Arab Spring Revolution, which had created a power vacuum in the region. David S Cohen, the then Deputy Director of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), had famously called Qatar a safe haven for “terrorist financiers to operate with impunity.” Qatar had been supportive of the revolutionary wave,&amp;nbsp; while Saudi Arabia had opposed it tooth and nail. The fight on grounds of soft power has also escalated between the two nations - Qatar's broadcaster Al Jazeera supported the Arab Spring, which was construed by Saudi Arabia as attempts to topple its monarchy. The Saudis had also been wary of Qatar's stable relationship with Iran, thus, framing the conflict with Qatar as a ramification of the Iran-Saudi proxy conflict - all stemming from Saudi Arabia’s trouble with the infiltration by Iran and Iran-backed militant groups into the Arab Spring.&amp;nbsp; Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates and Egypt have been steadfastly opposing any action by Qatar and Turkey and their support of democratic, Islamist and Salafi extremist groups during the Syrian Civil War. Post the Saudi execution of Nimr al Nimr in 2016, which drew worldwide condemnation from human rights groups and international organisations, Qatar severed all diplomatic ties with Iran. During the Yemeni Civil War in 2011-12, both Qatar and Saudi Arabia fought side-by-side against the alleged Iran-backed Houthi militants. It is important to note that the undercurrents of this fight may be traced to an ambition to gain regional hegemony, thus, in spite of being members of the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) the animosities continue to exist, resurfacing now and then. All hell broke loose in June 2017, when Saudi Arabia, the UAE, Bahrain, Egypt, Maldives, Mauritania, Senegal, Djibouti, Comoros, Jordan, the Tobruk based Libyan government severed diplomatic relations with Qatar and blocked Qatar's sea routes and airspace. Saudi Arabia went a step further blocking the only land route Qatar shared with Iran. The reaction came as a prompt response to Al Jazeera allegedly airing negative information pertaining to it's fellow GCC nations and its policy of “going soft&quot; on Islamist terror groups by allowing terror financiers to operate freely within its borders. Ron Prosor, an Israeli diplomat went so far to regard it as “the Club Med for Terrorists.” Thus, is it no surprise that close proximity between Qatar and the US has been a cause of concern for the other GCC members which includes UAE and Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp; US-Qatar ties down the Age The Qatar and US deal of 2020 shouldn't be treated as a case in isolation, rather a culmination of mutually beneficial ties handed over from decades ago. Since 1992, Qatar has been instrumental in building military ties and currently plays host to the US Central Command's Forward Headquarters and the Combined Air Operations Centre. It also has the Al Udeid Air Base and the As Sayliyah Army Base, among which the former is the largest American airbase in the Middle East. In 2014, the US sold $11 billion worth of arms to Qatar which also included the AH 64 Apache attack helicopters, Javelin and Patriot defence systems.&amp;nbsp; The signing of the $12 billion deal regarding the purchase of 36F-15 QA strike aircraft imported from the USA in 2017 may also be treated as a milestone in the bilateral relationship of the two nations. The governments of the United States and the State of Qatar held their third Strategic Dialogue on September 14 and 15, 2020. The United States and Qatar signed a Memorandum of Understanding on education, culture and sports in addition to a Statement of Intent (SoI) designating 2021 as the US-Qatar Year of Culture and an Announcement of Intent for Qatar to host an investment forum in the United States in 2021. Furthermore, the United States also recognised Qatar’s effective leadership to establish peace and reconciliation among contending factions in Somalia and Sudan. The two nations noted an increase in bilateral trade where US exports to Qatar increased by 39% between 2018 and 2019. The United States remains Qatar’s largest foreign direct investor and largest trading partner. The two nations had also discussed the $26 billion Foreign Military Sales program which continued to increase the capability and capacity of the Qatar Armed Forces. The progress in these areas will be reviewed at the Policy Working Group meeting in Washington DC in the first quarter of 2021. The 2020 Deal: A Bed of Nails The US intervention in this area was evident in September 2020, when David Schenker, the State Department’s top diplomat for the Middle East stated that the three-year-old blockade might be lifted within a span of “weeks”. Thus, Kuwait and the United States have made an attempt to mediate a rift which was acting as a stumbling block in Washington's aim of uniting the Middle East against Iran. Schenker said, “These are two sides that are dug in... and yet there is a recognition that this is a distraction from Iran.” However achieving diplomatic victory is a far cry as the boycotting nations set 13 demands which include the closing of Al Jazeera Media Network, downgrading ties with Iran and cutting links with Turkish Brotherhood. However, the Israel factor plays an important cameo. The United States is considering selling F-35s to Qatar as a side deal to the US-brokered agreement between Israel and UAE dubbed as the Abraham Accord. Israel, which had previously signalled stiff opposition to a UAE-US deal, is bound to express similar sentiments towards the deal with Qatar. The Qatari and UAE F-35 deals have to take into consideration the decade-old US-Israel deal that states any US weapons sold to the region must not impair Israel's “qualitative military edge”, thereby ensuring that US weapons furnished to Israel are “superior in quality” in comparison to the ones sold to its neighbours. However, the fifth-generation fighter jet F-35A which is estimated to cost around $80 million has its fate hanging in the air, influenced by the potential havoc it could wreck and alter diplomatic relations in the oil-rich Middle East. Thus it remains imperative for the US to take into consideration the geopolitics in this area lest it becomes a diplomatic graveyard of its ambitions in this region.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intervention by Sanction</title><link href="/Intervention-by-Sanction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intervention by Sanction" /><published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Intervention-by-Sanction</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Intervention-by-Sanction">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “&lt;em&gt;f*ck around with us&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Russia-and-Turkey&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Russia and Turkey&lt;/a&gt; could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Leeman</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “f*ck around with us”.&amp;nbsp; The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps. Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US. In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first. If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered. And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders. It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp; Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day. Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, Russia and Turkey could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip. Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lock &amp;amp; Load: Analysis of the Armenia-Azerbaijan War</title><link href="/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lock &amp; Load: Analysis of the Armenia-Azerbaijan War" /><published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War">&lt;p&gt;Since September 27, 2020, hundreds of people have died and thousands have been displaced due to the war being fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan, worsening the ongoing refugee crisis in the Middle East. Reports have noted the exchange of missiles, ballistics, artillery fire and high-tech drones between the neighbouring countries. Analysts and leaders across the globe have declared the less than a month old war as worse than the previous six-year-long war fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1994.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Azerbaijan and Armenia have, as of October 18, 2020, agreed to a second attempt at a cease-fire. This decision comes a week after their first failed attempt, wherein both parties breached the cease-fire within the first hour of its agreement.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it remains to be seen how long it takes for the two nations to violate this accord, considering the morning of their second agreement was rife with news of artillery fire from Armenia. The odds are not in the favour of a long-term peace accord during the second attempt, considering it took six years for them to call a truce the last time these two nations went to war against each other.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armenia and Azerbaijan recommenced the fight over the Nagorno-Karabakh region on September 27, 2020, after a decades-long truce. The Nagorno-Karabakh region has been a conflicting issue for the two nations since 1920. A region majorly-populated by ethnic Armenians, Nagorno-Karabakh lies within the geographical borders of Azerbaijan. Having been declared an independent state under Soviet Union rule in the 1920’s, it wasn’t until the collapse of the Bolsheviks that the Nagorno-Karabakh legislature passed a resolution to join Armenia in 1988, leading to an escalation of the conflict. The conflict accelerated into a full-blown war in 1991 leading to thousands of casualties and a refugee crisis. In 1994, Russia finally managed to broker a peace agreement but not until Armenia gathered control of the Nagorno-Karabakh region despite it still being located in Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the two nations had brokered a peace agreement, this did not stop either side from minor scrimmages and attacks and it was one such attack in July 2020 that resulted in the death of an Azerbaijani general that resulted in&amp;nbsp; a rising conflict in September 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major catalyst of the ongoing war is the involvement of Turkey and Russia. Turkey has been responsible for gathering troops, supplying manpower and highly dangerous technologies to Azerbaijan, whereas Russia has a defence pact with Armenia, which unsurprisingly has not stopped Russia from supplying arms to both Armenia and Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for Russian and Turkish involvement goes beyond neighbourly concern for Turkey and economic benefits from arms deals for Russia. Indeed, Nagorno-Karabakh is another notch in the proverbial belt of proxy wars being fought by Russia and Turkey. The fight over the oil-rich region in Libya and regional and political war over Syria are two of the most prominent examples of the proxy wars being carried out by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the international community including the United States, France, and the European Union have urged Armenia and Azerbaijan to call for a truce, their requests have fallen on deaf ears.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿Whether it be the state of Kashmir or the Israel-Palestine dispute over the Gaza Strip and West bank, innumerable conflicts can be seen arising due to a piece of land. However, consigning any piece of land the relevance of just a geographical location would be unfair. For the people living on that land, it is about home, safety and a sense of belongingness that is of the utmost importance to any society.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;And such is the case of Nagorno-Karabakh. The reason behind the war in 1991 was the land located in Azerbaijan’s geographical boundaries and the need for an ethnically Armenian-majority region to merge with the country they felt at home in. However, the war being fought by the two nations now is no longer about the land or the importance it holds for the people of Armenia but has become a matter of pride and perception.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both the nations have taken to fighting the war in an ostentatious display of power and arms, as corroborated by the videos being released by the government officials of their impressive drones and high-tech warcraft bombing the enemy soldiers and grounds. According to a recent publication by &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, Azerbaijan released a music video starring &lt;em&gt;“khaki-clad singers”&lt;/em&gt; juxtaposed with helicopters and tanks in the background to rouse public sentiments and morale. In a truly 21st century style, music videos and engagement on online platforms by citizens of Armenia and Azerbaijan commemorate the war currently responsible for the loss of more than ten thousand deaths since 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consequences of this war go beyond the loss of lives and livelihoods. The result of the ongoing tussle will determine the fate of 147,000 people, 95% of which are ethically Armenians. Although there are international committees such as the Minsk Group, established in 1994, formed especially to broker peace agreements, the involvement of international parties such as Turkey and Russia has made it next to impossible to broker an agreement without active military combat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it seems that political leaderships in Armenia and Azerbaijan are enjoying an increase in public popularity and favour due to the nationalist sentiments, while Russia enjoys increased profits from the arms sale in both the countries and Turkey hopes to use a possible Azerbaijan’s victory over Armenia as leverage to gain the upper hand over Russia in its proxy wars. Ultimately for the political leaders of Armenia, Azerbaijan,Turkey and Russia, the lives lost are a manageable opportunity cost of the political and economic benefits from the war.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point in time, it is difficult to predict where the victory lies but we can say for certain that it will not be with the people of Armenia or Azerbaijan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Since September 27, 2020, hundreds of people have died and thousands have been displaced due to the war being fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan, worsening the ongoing refugee crisis in the Middle East. Reports have noted the exchange of missiles, ballistics, artillery fire and high-tech drones between the neighbouring countries. Analysts and leaders across the globe have declared the less than a month old war as worse than the previous six-year-long war fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1994.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, Azerbaijan and Armenia have, as of October 18, 2020, agreed to a second attempt at a cease-fire. This decision comes a week after their first failed attempt, wherein both parties breached the cease-fire within the first hour of its agreement.&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, it remains to be seen how long it takes for the two nations to violate this accord, considering the morning of their second agreement was rife with news of artillery fire from Armenia. The odds are not in the favour of a long-term peace accord during the second attempt, considering it took six years for them to call a truce the last time these two nations went to war against each other.&amp;nbsp; Armenia and Azerbaijan recommenced the fight over the Nagorno-Karabakh region on September 27, 2020, after a decades-long truce. The Nagorno-Karabakh region has been a conflicting issue for the two nations since 1920. A region majorly-populated by ethnic Armenians, Nagorno-Karabakh lies within the geographical borders of Azerbaijan. Having been declared an independent state under Soviet Union rule in the 1920’s, it wasn’t until the collapse of the Bolsheviks that the Nagorno-Karabakh legislature passed a resolution to join Armenia in 1988, leading to an escalation of the conflict. The conflict accelerated into a full-blown war in 1991 leading to thousands of casualties and a refugee crisis. In 1994, Russia finally managed to broker a peace agreement but not until Armenia gathered control of the Nagorno-Karabakh region despite it still being located in Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp; Although the two nations had brokered a peace agreement, this did not stop either side from minor scrimmages and attacks and it was one such attack in July 2020 that resulted in the death of an Azerbaijani general that resulted in&amp;nbsp; a rising conflict in September 2020.&amp;nbsp; A major catalyst of the ongoing war is the involvement of Turkey and Russia. Turkey has been responsible for gathering troops, supplying manpower and highly dangerous technologies to Azerbaijan, whereas Russia has a defence pact with Armenia, which unsurprisingly has not stopped Russia from supplying arms to both Armenia and Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp; The reason for Russian and Turkish involvement goes beyond neighbourly concern for Turkey and economic benefits from arms deals for Russia. Indeed, Nagorno-Karabakh is another notch in the proverbial belt of proxy wars being fought by Russia and Turkey. The fight over the oil-rich region in Libya and regional and political war over Syria are two of the most prominent examples of the proxy wars being carried out by them. Although the international community including the United States, France, and the European Union have urged Armenia and Azerbaijan to call for a truce, their requests have fallen on deaf ears.&amp;nbsp; ﻿Whether it be the state of Kashmir or the Israel-Palestine dispute over the Gaza Strip and West bank, innumerable conflicts can be seen arising due to a piece of land. However, consigning any piece of land the relevance of just a geographical location would be unfair. For the people living on that land, it is about home, safety and a sense of belongingness that is of the utmost importance to any society.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;And such is the case of Nagorno-Karabakh. The reason behind the war in 1991 was the land located in Azerbaijan’s geographical boundaries and the need for an ethnically Armenian-majority region to merge with the country they felt at home in. However, the war being fought by the two nations now is no longer about the land or the importance it holds for the people of Armenia but has become a matter of pride and perception.&amp;nbsp;Both the nations have taken to fighting the war in an ostentatious display of power and arms, as corroborated by the videos being released by the government officials of their impressive drones and high-tech warcraft bombing the enemy soldiers and grounds. According to a recent publication by The Economist, Azerbaijan released a music video starring “khaki-clad singers” juxtaposed with helicopters and tanks in the background to rouse public sentiments and morale. In a truly 21st century style, music videos and engagement on online platforms by citizens of Armenia and Azerbaijan commemorate the war currently responsible for the loss of more than ten thousand deaths since 1991.&amp;nbsp;The consequences of this war go beyond the loss of lives and livelihoods. The result of the ongoing tussle will determine the fate of 147,000 people, 95% of which are ethically Armenians. Although there are international committees such as the Minsk Group, established in 1994, formed especially to broker peace agreements, the involvement of international parties such as Turkey and Russia has made it next to impossible to broker an agreement without active military combat.&amp;nbsp;Additionally, it seems that political leaderships in Armenia and Azerbaijan are enjoying an increase in public popularity and favour due to the nationalist sentiments, while Russia enjoys increased profits from the arms sale in both the countries and Turkey hopes to use a possible Azerbaijan’s victory over Armenia as leverage to gain the upper hand over Russia in its proxy wars. Ultimately for the political leaders of Armenia, Azerbaijan,Turkey and Russia, the lives lost are a manageable opportunity cost of the political and economic benefits from the war.&amp;nbsp;At this point in time, it is difficult to predict where the victory lies but we can say for certain that it will not be with the people of Armenia or Azerbaijan.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jewish Persecution Through the Ages</title><link href="/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jewish Persecution Through the Ages" /><published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages">&lt;p&gt;By our very nature, we humans have the tendency to adapt and mould everything to suit our purpose. We have razed mountains to rubble, developed sustainable civilisations, and harnessed various forces of nature to our service. We need to see the world in a way that makes sense to us because not knowing what’s out there is one of the worst fears of humankind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anomalously, this theory also explains both the cause of developments and the inevitable resistance a society poses to them. Some individuals through their efforts generate new and more plausible explanations of existing phenomena. However, society generally fixates on the traditional notions and feels somewhat threatened by the existence of a new answer - something they’re completely ignorant of.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, advancement in human society is also characterised by free-will and greater acceptance of one’s beliefs and perception. So, the only thing that needs to be decided upon is - do the benefits and costs of clinging onto traditionality and remaining in the comfort zone outweigh that of adapting to developments and being more receptive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after considering the sentiment of people and the factor of coincidence in the associated events and stories, all the scientific evidence points to the fact that religion is a product of human psychology. People want to make sense of the immeasurable number of interdependent or independent events that take place in the world around them and when they believe they have hit a dead end, they instinctively correlate them with the supernatural or the divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this theory in its own capacity poses a very interesting philosophical question - why are people willing to mortify, hurt, torture or even kill fellow human beings when there is a very high chance that the argument which they believe absolves them of these crimes may be rooted in ignorance?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿Jews, throughout history, have been one of the most abused communities around the world. The Greeks did it, the Roman did it, even fellow monothesitics like Christians and Muslims did it, but they were all eventually put to shame by Hitler.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;Monotheistic cultures are widely popular today. When it comes to suitability to the highly dynamic lifestyle of the modern world, they check almost all the boxes. Yet, the forerunners of the bunch - Christianity and Islam - made meagre efforts for upliftment of the Jewish community in their respective reigns over the Middle East and Europe. Also, an important point to mention is that Judaism, Christianity and Islam are highly analogous. Christianity revamped the Jewish ideologies and labeled them as their own, and Islam did the same to Christianity. The fundamental religious doctrine is the same in all three of them, and concepts like prophets, heaven, hell, etc. are fairly consistent. This further intensifies the nefariousness of the former's actions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it won’t be completely fair to blame this history of blatant inhumanity on poor governance as the laws of that time made no clear cut distinction between the state and the apex religious body. Therefore, it is the medieval thought process of these communities that is to be blamed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greek and Roman societies were governed by a class of strong believers in polytheism. They prayed to their gods in temples, made blood sacrifices, and tried their best to live their lives by the stories they heard about them. The arrival of monotheistic faith, whose beliefs and practices were not even remotely close to theirs, was not well received by them. Public executions, selective poll tax, and defilement of synagogues were a common method to overrule the other belief system. Jews were expelled from the city and some Roman emperors went to the length of declaring the possession of Jewish scriptures a capital crime. Such acts of hostility, though morally incoherent, can be justified rationally by the fundamental pattern of society's initial reaction to change in any case whatsoever. Moreover, Jews were not the only monotheists being harassed, the Romans reacted similarly to Christianity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moving up the timeline, Rome was Christianised in the late 300 AD and the capital of the Christian stronghold was established in Constantinople, Byzantine. In the late 600 AD, Islam came into being in the Arabian region of the Middle East and started growing rapidly owing to the expansionary crusades of Mohammad and the succeeding Muslim leaders. Jewish groups in Byzantine were treated as aliens for their disbelief in the absolution of Christianity. Their social standing and religious liberty varied with the ruler. Eventually, Islamic leaders reached the borders of Byzantine (Christianized Rome) and toppled the rule of Christians who retaliated with a series of crusades to reclaim the holy lands. All of the conflict lasted for about 200 years and the Jewish community was dishevelled as a byproduct. Muslim rulers aggressively imposed Islamic credo upon them and whenever Christians invaded as a result of the crusades, they wiped entire Jewish colonies off the map.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The situation was especially bad in Persia, as under the prejudice of being spiritually unclean, Jews were forced to live in ghettos outside of towns. They were not allowed to enter shops, and even if they managed to, they were not allowed to touch or inspect any item. If the latter was to happen, the laws clearly stated that the Jew was obligated to buy the product and the seller had an absolute right of charging as much as they wanted. Also, Jews were not allowed to roam the cities during rain, as it was believed that the&amp;nbsp; dirt of their spirituality would wash down with the raindrops and rub off on the locals who walked the same paths.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the middle ages rolled in, anti-semitic groups evolved their methods of suppression, as they started destroying the political standing of the Jews and catalysed it for their physical extermination. During the Black Death period, orthodox Crhritian and Muslim groups in the middle east accused Jews of poisoning the wells within cities and orchestrating the plague. These accusations were used to make initial arrests, upon which the prisoners were tortured and threatened into confessing to crimes that they never committed. Even for executions, slow death methods like public stoning &amp;amp; death by fire were used. As a final touch of cruelty, their respective properties and places of worship were seized without cause and converted into churches, mosques, and libraries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the 1940’s. Religious and racial fanaticism had poisoned Germany. Almost everyone is aware of the horrific ordeal that Hitler and his racial political agendas put Jews through - pogroms, mass shootings, concentration camps and the gas chambers. When the dust settled, two-thirds of the European Jewish population had been exterminated- “genocide” in the perfect sense of the word. The scapegoating does not end there, as Jews were also blamed for capitalism and excessively controlling the american financial market via their dominance of the premiere financial institutions of the time like Rothschilds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even today, the other communities prey on Jews for conversions. Their faith is still undermined and their rights as members of the society are still kept subservient to those of other cultures. It is imperative to understand that the concept of “sustainability”- a term which is amassing a lot of popularity lately- is not selective. Developing a world where everyone is willing to live their life of their own volition is the very foundation of the term. Therefore, security and free will for some and impositions on others is a betrayal to the very essence of sustainability as it makes the society more prone to implosion rather than consolidation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aryaman Dhiman</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">By our very nature, we humans have the tendency to adapt and mould everything to suit our purpose. We have razed mountains to rubble, developed sustainable civilisations, and harnessed various forces of nature to our service. We need to see the world in a way that makes sense to us because not knowing what’s out there is one of the worst fears of humankind. Anomalously, this theory also explains both the cause of developments and the inevitable resistance a society poses to them. Some individuals through their efforts generate new and more plausible explanations of existing phenomena. However, society generally fixates on the traditional notions and feels somewhat threatened by the existence of a new answer - something they’re completely ignorant of.&amp;nbsp; In retrospect, advancement in human society is also characterised by free-will and greater acceptance of one’s beliefs and perception. So, the only thing that needs to be decided upon is - do the benefits and costs of clinging onto traditionality and remaining in the comfort zone outweigh that of adapting to developments and being more receptive? Even after considering the sentiment of people and the factor of coincidence in the associated events and stories, all the scientific evidence points to the fact that religion is a product of human psychology. People want to make sense of the immeasurable number of interdependent or independent events that take place in the world around them and when they believe they have hit a dead end, they instinctively correlate them with the supernatural or the divine. Now, this theory in its own capacity poses a very interesting philosophical question - why are people willing to mortify, hurt, torture or even kill fellow human beings when there is a very high chance that the argument which they believe absolves them of these crimes may be rooted in ignorance?&amp;nbsp; ﻿Jews, throughout history, have been one of the most abused communities around the world. The Greeks did it, the Roman did it, even fellow monothesitics like Christians and Muslims did it, but they were all eventually put to shame by Hitler.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;Monotheistic cultures are widely popular today. When it comes to suitability to the highly dynamic lifestyle of the modern world, they check almost all the boxes. Yet, the forerunners of the bunch - Christianity and Islam - made meagre efforts for upliftment of the Jewish community in their respective reigns over the Middle East and Europe. Also, an important point to mention is that Judaism, Christianity and Islam are highly analogous. Christianity revamped the Jewish ideologies and labeled them as their own, and Islam did the same to Christianity. The fundamental religious doctrine is the same in all three of them, and concepts like prophets, heaven, hell, etc. are fairly consistent. This further intensifies the nefariousness of the former's actions.&amp;nbsp;Moreover, it won’t be completely fair to blame this history of blatant inhumanity on poor governance as the laws of that time made no clear cut distinction between the state and the apex religious body. Therefore, it is the medieval thought process of these communities that is to be blamed.&amp;nbsp;Ancient Greek and Roman societies were governed by a class of strong believers in polytheism. They prayed to their gods in temples, made blood sacrifices, and tried their best to live their lives by the stories they heard about them. The arrival of monotheistic faith, whose beliefs and practices were not even remotely close to theirs, was not well received by them. Public executions, selective poll tax, and defilement of synagogues were a common method to overrule the other belief system. Jews were expelled from the city and some Roman emperors went to the length of declaring the possession of Jewish scriptures a capital crime. Such acts of hostility, though morally incoherent, can be justified rationally by the fundamental pattern of society's initial reaction to change in any case whatsoever. Moreover, Jews were not the only monotheists being harassed, the Romans reacted similarly to Christianity.&amp;nbsp;Moving up the timeline, Rome was Christianised in the late 300 AD and the capital of the Christian stronghold was established in Constantinople, Byzantine. In the late 600 AD, Islam came into being in the Arabian region of the Middle East and started growing rapidly owing to the expansionary crusades of Mohammad and the succeeding Muslim leaders. Jewish groups in Byzantine were treated as aliens for their disbelief in the absolution of Christianity. Their social standing and religious liberty varied with the ruler. Eventually, Islamic leaders reached the borders of Byzantine (Christianized Rome) and toppled the rule of Christians who retaliated with a series of crusades to reclaim the holy lands. All of the conflict lasted for about 200 years and the Jewish community was dishevelled as a byproduct. Muslim rulers aggressively imposed Islamic credo upon them and whenever Christians invaded as a result of the crusades, they wiped entire Jewish colonies off the map.&amp;nbsp;The situation was especially bad in Persia, as under the prejudice of being spiritually unclean, Jews were forced to live in ghettos outside of towns. They were not allowed to enter shops, and even if they managed to, they were not allowed to touch or inspect any item. If the latter was to happen, the laws clearly stated that the Jew was obligated to buy the product and the seller had an absolute right of charging as much as they wanted. Also, Jews were not allowed to roam the cities during rain, as it was believed that the&amp;nbsp; dirt of their spirituality would wash down with the raindrops and rub off on the locals who walked the same paths.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;As the middle ages rolled in, anti-semitic groups evolved their methods of suppression, as they started destroying the political standing of the Jews and catalysed it for their physical extermination. During the Black Death period, orthodox Crhritian and Muslim groups in the middle east accused Jews of poisoning the wells within cities and orchestrating the plague. These accusations were used to make initial arrests, upon which the prisoners were tortured and threatened into confessing to crimes that they never committed. Even for executions, slow death methods like public stoning &amp;amp; death by fire were used. As a final touch of cruelty, their respective properties and places of worship were seized without cause and converted into churches, mosques, and libraries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Fast forward to the 1940’s. Religious and racial fanaticism had poisoned Germany. Almost everyone is aware of the horrific ordeal that Hitler and his racial political agendas put Jews through - pogroms, mass shootings, concentration camps and the gas chambers. When the dust settled, two-thirds of the European Jewish population had been exterminated- “genocide” in the perfect sense of the word. The scapegoating does not end there, as Jews were also blamed for capitalism and excessively controlling the american financial market via their dominance of the premiere financial institutions of the time like Rothschilds.Even today, the other communities prey on Jews for conversions. Their faith is still undermined and their rights as members of the society are still kept subservient to those of other cultures. It is imperative to understand that the concept of “sustainability”- a term which is amassing a lot of popularity lately- is not selective. Developing a world where everyone is willing to live their life of their own volition is the very foundation of the term. Therefore, security and free will for some and impositions on others is a betrayal to the very essence of sustainability as it makes the society more prone to implosion rather than consolidation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inflation Check!</title><link href="/Inflation-Check" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inflation Check!" /><published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Inflation-Check</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Inflation-Check">&lt;p&gt;The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) was established by the Reserve Bank of India Act in 1934. The Act vests in RBI the powers to operate the monetary policy framework of the country. It also defines the primary objective of monetary policy as “&lt;em&gt;maintaining price stability while keeping in mind the objective of growth&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Maintaining price stability, that is inflation, is pivotal for achieving sustained growth, and with the current conditions prevailing around the world, it has become all the more important to keep prices under check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools to Control Inflation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the pivotal functions of the RBI is that of the controller of credit. Credit money, the money lent out by the financial institutions, forms the most important part of the money supply. Money supply, in turn, has important implications for the economic stability of a country. For these reasons, the RBI can control inflation by controlling the credit in the economy. The first and foremost instrument that the RBI uses for inflation control is the ‘Policy Rate’ (popularly known as the Repo Rate). Repo rate is the interest rate at which the Reserve Bank provides overnight liquidity to banks (against the collateral of government and other approved securities). By setting the repo rate, RBI controls the borrowing rates of the banks. When RBI wants to control inflation, the rates are increased. Therefore, the borrowing costs for the banks and other lenders increase. They pass this increased cost on to their customers by charging a higher interest rate to lend money. This reduces the demand for money in the economy and helps in controlling inflation. Another tool is the ‘Reverse Repo Rate’. It is the rate at which RBI borrows money from commercial banks. An increase in this rate can drain money out of the banking system (i.e. reduce money supply). Another instrument is the ‘Bank Rate’, which is the rate at which RBI buys or rediscounts bills of exchange or other commercial papers. When the bank rate is increased, it will have a similar impact as the repo rate has on inflation control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central bank can also use variable reserve requirements, Cash Reserve Ratio&lt;em&gt; (CRR)&lt;/em&gt; and Statutory Liquidity Ratio&lt;em&gt; (SLR)&lt;/em&gt;, to control credit. CRR is the balance that a commercial bank is required to maintain with RBI in the form of cash reserves. SLR is the share of its total deposits that a bank has to maintain in the form of liquid assets, such as gold and government securities. By changing these ratios, RBI can control credit in the economy. If the Bank wants to, say, discourage credit, (so as to control inflation) it can increase these ratios. Raising these rates will reduce the surplus cash reserves that the banks could offer as credit. These two statutory requirements are vital. The repo rate will successfully manifest into an inflation controlling tool because of the existence of these requirements. A commercial bank will borrow from RBI when it has a dearth of funds to meet the CRR and SLR requirements. If the banks could meet the requirements without borrowing from the RBI, the transmission of the monetary policy becomes uncertain (commercial banks may not pass to their customers the benefits of rate cuts by the RBI). Another monetary policy tool is the ‘Liquidity Adjustment Facility’ (LAF). The LAF consists of overnight as well as term repo auctions. The aim of term repo is to develop “&lt;em&gt;an inter-bank term money market, which in turn can set market-based benchmarks for pricing of loans and deposits, and hence improve the transmission of monetary policy&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;RBI can also indulge in ‘Open Market Operations’ (OMO) to affect the money supply in an economy and thereby the inflation. These operations are direct sales and purchases of government securities so as to absorb or inject liquidity into the economy, respectively. OMOs help in altering the quantity of money in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Monetary Framework&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An agreement, which was later incorporated into the RBI Act, was signed in 2015 by the RBI and the Central government to formulate a new monetary framework. By this, India had adopted flexible inflation targeting as a mandate for RBI and the setting up of a Monetary Policy Committee (to set the policy rate). This new framework specified that the RBI should conduct inflation-targeting using the policy rate. This is a significant move away from the erstwhile approach of a multiple indicators approach where inflation control and economic growth were given equal priority. An inflation-targeting approach is one where the Central Bank tries to maintain inflation at a pre-decided level; or within a pre-decided band. However, this move has faced criticism. Concerns were raised as to how effective can the Reserve Bank be in controlling inflation and about the ramifications of attempting such control.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulapre Balakrishnan, a noted economist, points out that since 2008 inflation recorded an upward shift for about five years. He&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/opinion/lead/going-beyond-inflation-targeting/article7550932.ece&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/opinion/lead/going-beyond-inflation-targeting/article7550932.ece&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;It would be difficult to square this (the rise in inflation) with the suggestion that it reflects the Bank’s efforts to maintain growth, for growth has actually been lower in this period&lt;/em&gt;”. Dr V Anantha Nageswaran, a member of the PM Economic Advisory Council,&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livemint.com/news/india/why-rbi-s-inflation-regime-is-broken-11600269451733.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livemint.com/news/india/why-rbi-s-inflation-regime-is-broken-11600269451733.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;quoted&lt;/a&gt; how research from New Zealand indicated “&lt;em&gt;even firms did not form their inflation expectations based on the Central Bank’s inflation target and monetary policy framework&lt;/em&gt;”. He further added that Central Banks can neither control economic growth nor inflation, but only credit growth. He suggested that Central Banks should redefine their mandate to control the ‘overheating’, which manifests into credit growth, asset markets, trade deficits, and (sometimes) inflation; and consequently, return to the “multiple indicators approach”. There is also an increasing consensus among economists that the high inflation in India is primarily because of supply-side rigidities, food and fuel prices, and high fiscal expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One must understand that the Central Banks hold a greater sway on the financial and money markets; and by that, they can significantly influence these two markets. Therefore, they are better equipped to influence risk-taking behaviour in the asset market. However, monetary policy is less powerful in determining the long-term performance of an economy. Monetary policy, for instance, can hardly increase the aggregate demand in the economy over the long run. Former New Zealand Central Bank Governor Graeme Wheeler remarked, “&lt;em&gt;even in the shorter term, monetary policy’s influence may be low in an environment where debt levels are high and where there is considerable uncertainty about economic prospects&lt;/em&gt;”. It is, perhaps, time for India to find a new monetary framework.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) was established by the Reserve Bank of India Act in 1934. The Act vests in RBI the powers to operate the monetary policy framework of the country. It also defines the primary objective of monetary policy as “maintaining price stability while keeping in mind the objective of growth”. Maintaining price stability, that is inflation, is pivotal for achieving sustained growth, and with the current conditions prevailing around the world, it has become all the more important to keep prices under check. Tools to Control Inflation One of the pivotal functions of the RBI is that of the controller of credit. Credit money, the money lent out by the financial institutions, forms the most important part of the money supply. Money supply, in turn, has important implications for the economic stability of a country. For these reasons, the RBI can control inflation by controlling the credit in the economy. The first and foremost instrument that the RBI uses for inflation control is the ‘Policy Rate’ (popularly known as the Repo Rate). Repo rate is the interest rate at which the Reserve Bank provides overnight liquidity to banks (against the collateral of government and other approved securities). By setting the repo rate, RBI controls the borrowing rates of the banks. When RBI wants to control inflation, the rates are increased. Therefore, the borrowing costs for the banks and other lenders increase. They pass this increased cost on to their customers by charging a higher interest rate to lend money. This reduces the demand for money in the economy and helps in controlling inflation. Another tool is the ‘Reverse Repo Rate’. It is the rate at which RBI borrows money from commercial banks. An increase in this rate can drain money out of the banking system (i.e. reduce money supply). Another instrument is the ‘Bank Rate’, which is the rate at which RBI buys or rediscounts bills of exchange or other commercial papers. When the bank rate is increased, it will have a similar impact as the repo rate has on inflation control. The central bank can also use variable reserve requirements, Cash Reserve Ratio (CRR) and Statutory Liquidity Ratio (SLR), to control credit. CRR is the balance that a commercial bank is required to maintain with RBI in the form of cash reserves. SLR is the share of its total deposits that a bank has to maintain in the form of liquid assets, such as gold and government securities. By changing these ratios, RBI can control credit in the economy. If the Bank wants to, say, discourage credit, (so as to control inflation) it can increase these ratios. Raising these rates will reduce the surplus cash reserves that the banks could offer as credit. These two statutory requirements are vital. The repo rate will successfully manifest into an inflation controlling tool because of the existence of these requirements. A commercial bank will borrow from RBI when it has a dearth of funds to meet the CRR and SLR requirements. If the banks could meet the requirements without borrowing from the RBI, the transmission of the monetary policy becomes uncertain (commercial banks may not pass to their customers the benefits of rate cuts by the RBI). Another monetary policy tool is the ‘Liquidity Adjustment Facility’ (LAF). The LAF consists of overnight as well as term repo auctions. The aim of term repo is to develop “an inter-bank term money market, which in turn can set market-based benchmarks for pricing of loans and deposits, and hence improve the transmission of monetary policy”. RBI can also indulge in ‘Open Market Operations’ (OMO) to affect the money supply in an economy and thereby the inflation. These operations are direct sales and purchases of government securities so as to absorb or inject liquidity into the economy, respectively. OMOs help in altering the quantity of money in circulation. The Monetary Framework An agreement, which was later incorporated into the RBI Act, was signed in 2015 by the RBI and the Central government to formulate a new monetary framework. By this, India had adopted flexible inflation targeting as a mandate for RBI and the setting up of a Monetary Policy Committee (to set the policy rate). This new framework specified that the RBI should conduct inflation-targeting using the policy rate. This is a significant move away from the erstwhile approach of a multiple indicators approach where inflation control and economic growth were given equal priority. An inflation-targeting approach is one where the Central Bank tries to maintain inflation at a pre-decided level; or within a pre-decided band. However, this move has faced criticism. Concerns were raised as to how effective can the Reserve Bank be in controlling inflation and about the ramifications of attempting such control.&amp;nbsp; Pulapre Balakrishnan, a noted economist, points out that since 2008 inflation recorded an upward shift for about five years. He said, “It would be difficult to square this (the rise in inflation) with the suggestion that it reflects the Bank’s efforts to maintain growth, for growth has actually been lower in this period”. Dr V Anantha Nageswaran, a member of the PM Economic Advisory Council, quoted how research from New Zealand indicated “even firms did not form their inflation expectations based on the Central Bank’s inflation target and monetary policy framework”. He further added that Central Banks can neither control economic growth nor inflation, but only credit growth. He suggested that Central Banks should redefine their mandate to control the ‘overheating’, which manifests into credit growth, asset markets, trade deficits, and (sometimes) inflation; and consequently, return to the “multiple indicators approach”. There is also an increasing consensus among economists that the high inflation in India is primarily because of supply-side rigidities, food and fuel prices, and high fiscal expansion. One must understand that the Central Banks hold a greater sway on the financial and money markets; and by that, they can significantly influence these two markets. Therefore, they are better equipped to influence risk-taking behaviour in the asset market. However, monetary policy is less powerful in determining the long-term performance of an economy. Monetary policy, for instance, can hardly increase the aggregate demand in the economy over the long run. Former New Zealand Central Bank Governor Graeme Wheeler remarked, “even in the shorter term, monetary policy’s influence may be low in an environment where debt levels are high and where there is considerable uncertainty about economic prospects”. It is, perhaps, time for India to find a new monetary framework.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Contracting India</title><link href="/Contracting-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Contracting India" /><published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Contracting-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Contracting-India">&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy contracted by a drastic 23.9% in the April-June quarter of 2020-21 which is being stated as the most drastic fall in the Indian economy. What is more worrisome is the fact that this diminution is the worst amongst the world’s top economies and is an issue of immense concern for a major developing economy like India. The extent of the damage is expected to be manifold with the informal sector being the worst hit and revival looking like a prolonged journey. This can be supported by a statement made by Professor Arun Kumar of &lt;em&gt;New Delhi’s Institute of Social Sciences&lt;/em&gt; wherein he estimates the economic slide to be a negative 40% if the informal sector is taken into account. While the outbreak of COVID-19 is the prime cause of the gloomy economy, the already prevalent global economic slowdown and side-effects of the trade war cannot be overlooked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 25, 2020, India declared a complete national lockdown which was the world’s largest lockdown owing to the widespread pandemic. Apart from the limited movement of essential commodities, all businesses either came to a standstill with bleak immunity to have a revival spurt or they got wiped out. With people losing jobs in various sectors of the economy, the rise in unemployment has only deepened the strain. Experts analyse the figures and the trend as the onset of India’s largest recession since 1996.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For emerging economies, the prospects of a speedy recovery seem to be dim as per the International Monetary Fund (IMF), but the scenario is worst for India as the GDP contracted by a way larger margin than what was actually predicted. Adding to the crisis is the prediction by IMF which forecasted a contraction of 10.3% in the GDP in the fiscal year 2021, against the Central Bank’s prediction of 9.5%. The forecast in itself brings about a cloud of panic as this rate was predicted to be 4.5% in June 2020, the 5.8% leap is a near-indigestible figure for an economy of a great significance like that of India. The global economic significance that the nation has managed to engrave and give a stiff fight to its neighbour finds itself dwindling as China’s road to revival is far stronger than what was anticipated. While households and small businesses stand wrecked as an aftermath of the lockdown, the government has been continuously chalking out strategies to boost demand as a measure to curtail the downfall of one of the world’s major economies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quake in the economy shook all the sectors but the major contributors like construction, manufacturing and transportation were the worst hit. While agriculture did fairly well with an unexpected growth of 3.4%, it wasn’t strong enough to nullify the 39.3% contraction in the manufacturing sector, 23.3% in the mining sector, and 50.3% in the construction sector. Not only this, transportation along with trade, hotels, communication and broadcasting shrank by 47% in the first quarter. The pandemic forced the export shipments to dry out, people were locked at home with no eating out and no tourism. Businessmen had to either shut down their trade or put it to a halt. The prostration of the real-estate sector cannot be overlooked, which is clearly evident from the sharp fall in the rates and lack of demand for property. Along with this, tenants began emptying spaces already rented-out, as many started moving back to native places owing to no job in hand. Hence, the sectors that managed to keep themselves afloat in these troubled times could not stop the others from slipping down a sharp cliff.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the most profound problem that the Indian economy faces is that of its informal sector. While India’s large and a considerable proportion of workforce adjusts itself in the informal sector, fled back to its hometowns with a lesser impetus to come back. With no food to fill their stomachs, this downtrodden section of the society finds itself in a quagmire.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road to revival is definitely a tough one, but the government is gearing up itself in all and every way possible. With a systematic unlocking of the economy, the growth is finding its way back. While the experts call for a need to introduce a fresh stimulus package for the middle class, the government seems to be delaying its actions aimed at fighting the slowdown. But why a stimulus package for the middle class? The answer lies in the urgent need to revive the private consumption, that is to generate demand. The driving factor behind the slowdown remains a slowed consumption and lack of demand from the middle-class which forms an important chunk of the population consuming the most. A stimulus package to this sect of the population would mean kickstarting the revival process, and 85-90% of the population in this section is employed either in the government sector or in Public Sector Units (PSUs). It is evident that the government is functioning to the best of its capacity in these unprecedented times. Nevertheless, it is very important to clear state dues at the earliest in order to ensure revival in each and every part of the country. While the states and the Centre have been in a tussle over pending Goods and Sales Tax (GST) compensations, the Centre clearly stated that it cannot submit these pending compensations to the states owing to the medical and financial emergency and has, in fact, demanded the states to pay their GST dues for the year by borrowing, thus adding to the stress for the State governments who are already struggling to extract revenue. This is in complete contradiction to the ex-RBI Governor, Raghuram Rajan’s, statement who clearly stated in a recent article the dire need to replenish the state’s coffers as a crucial move towards recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With enough food for thought and tremendous scope to plan out recovery models, there is another contradiction this article will close itself with. At the beginning of 2020, while presenting the budget, the Honourable Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman had assumed a GDP growth of 10% for the fiscal year and moving closer to the target of a $5 trillion economy by 2024. On the contrary, the world’s fifth-largest economy in the pre-Covid era is believed to get 10% smaller as per economists across the world. The dire need to act real quick along with substantial stimulus packages is expected out of the government without any further delay, otherwise, the re-examination of the targets and goals stated in the budget for the financial year 2020-21 will be the last resort.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The Indian economy contracted by a drastic 23.9% in the April-June quarter of 2020-21 which is being stated as the most drastic fall in the Indian economy. What is more worrisome is the fact that this diminution is the worst amongst the world’s top economies and is an issue of immense concern for a major developing economy like India. The extent of the damage is expected to be manifold with the informal sector being the worst hit and revival looking like a prolonged journey. This can be supported by a statement made by Professor Arun Kumar of New Delhi’s Institute of Social Sciences wherein he estimates the economic slide to be a negative 40% if the informal sector is taken into account. While the outbreak of COVID-19 is the prime cause of the gloomy economy, the already prevalent global economic slowdown and side-effects of the trade war cannot be overlooked.&amp;nbsp; On March 25, 2020, India declared a complete national lockdown which was the world’s largest lockdown owing to the widespread pandemic. Apart from the limited movement of essential commodities, all businesses either came to a standstill with bleak immunity to have a revival spurt or they got wiped out. With people losing jobs in various sectors of the economy, the rise in unemployment has only deepened the strain. Experts analyse the figures and the trend as the onset of India’s largest recession since 1996.&amp;nbsp; For emerging economies, the prospects of a speedy recovery seem to be dim as per the International Monetary Fund (IMF), but the scenario is worst for India as the GDP contracted by a way larger margin than what was actually predicted. Adding to the crisis is the prediction by IMF which forecasted a contraction of 10.3% in the GDP in the fiscal year 2021, against the Central Bank’s prediction of 9.5%. The forecast in itself brings about a cloud of panic as this rate was predicted to be 4.5% in June 2020, the 5.8% leap is a near-indigestible figure for an economy of a great significance like that of India. The global economic significance that the nation has managed to engrave and give a stiff fight to its neighbour finds itself dwindling as China’s road to revival is far stronger than what was anticipated. While households and small businesses stand wrecked as an aftermath of the lockdown, the government has been continuously chalking out strategies to boost demand as a measure to curtail the downfall of one of the world’s major economies. The quake in the economy shook all the sectors but the major contributors like construction, manufacturing and transportation were the worst hit. While agriculture did fairly well with an unexpected growth of 3.4%, it wasn’t strong enough to nullify the 39.3% contraction in the manufacturing sector, 23.3% in the mining sector, and 50.3% in the construction sector. Not only this, transportation along with trade, hotels, communication and broadcasting shrank by 47% in the first quarter. The pandemic forced the export shipments to dry out, people were locked at home with no eating out and no tourism. Businessmen had to either shut down their trade or put it to a halt. The prostration of the real-estate sector cannot be overlooked, which is clearly evident from the sharp fall in the rates and lack of demand for property. Along with this, tenants began emptying spaces already rented-out, as many started moving back to native places owing to no job in hand. Hence, the sectors that managed to keep themselves afloat in these troubled times could not stop the others from slipping down a sharp cliff.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, the most profound problem that the Indian economy faces is that of its informal sector. While India’s large and a considerable proportion of workforce adjusts itself in the informal sector, fled back to its hometowns with a lesser impetus to come back. With no food to fill their stomachs, this downtrodden section of the society finds itself in a quagmire.&amp;nbsp; The road to revival is definitely a tough one, but the government is gearing up itself in all and every way possible. With a systematic unlocking of the economy, the growth is finding its way back. While the experts call for a need to introduce a fresh stimulus package for the middle class, the government seems to be delaying its actions aimed at fighting the slowdown. But why a stimulus package for the middle class? The answer lies in the urgent need to revive the private consumption, that is to generate demand. The driving factor behind the slowdown remains a slowed consumption and lack of demand from the middle-class which forms an important chunk of the population consuming the most. A stimulus package to this sect of the population would mean kickstarting the revival process, and 85-90% of the population in this section is employed either in the government sector or in Public Sector Units (PSUs). It is evident that the government is functioning to the best of its capacity in these unprecedented times. Nevertheless, it is very important to clear state dues at the earliest in order to ensure revival in each and every part of the country. While the states and the Centre have been in a tussle over pending Goods and Sales Tax (GST) compensations, the Centre clearly stated that it cannot submit these pending compensations to the states owing to the medical and financial emergency and has, in fact, demanded the states to pay their GST dues for the year by borrowing, thus adding to the stress for the State governments who are already struggling to extract revenue. This is in complete contradiction to the ex-RBI Governor, Raghuram Rajan’s, statement who clearly stated in a recent article the dire need to replenish the state’s coffers as a crucial move towards recovery. With enough food for thought and tremendous scope to plan out recovery models, there is another contradiction this article will close itself with. At the beginning of 2020, while presenting the budget, the Honourable Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman had assumed a GDP growth of 10% for the fiscal year and moving closer to the target of a $5 trillion economy by 2024. On the contrary, the world’s fifth-largest economy in the pre-Covid era is believed to get 10% smaller as per economists across the world. The dire need to act real quick along with substantial stimulus packages is expected out of the government without any further delay, otherwise, the re-examination of the targets and goals stated in the budget for the financial year 2020-21 will be the last resort.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Amazon: The Deal Breaker?</title><link href="/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazon: The Deal Breaker?" /><published>2020-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker">&lt;p&gt;The Reliance and Future Group deal has been in the headlines since a few days now. The recent development which involved Amazon sending a legal notice has spiced it up even more. We are all obsessed with conflicts especially when three multinational corporations are involved. To get a better understanding of the on-going feud, we need to look at the previous developments and understand what actually led to the present-day situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future Group, owned by Kishore Biyani, had been facing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Past-Future-Future-Group&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;crisis&lt;/a&gt; for a few years. They were in huge debt and the reason might have been the diverse and over-ambitious investments made by the company. The group started out with a unique idea that gained success and their retail stores like Pantaloons and Big Bazaar became common household names. The greed to expand business in diverse areas might have turned out to be a big mistake. The group was burdened under debts but still continued to invest and make useless purchases. As the debt accumulated over time, the only option left was to sell their retail chains and shut down useless businesses. At the same time, online platforms like Amazon and Flipkart had already established themselves in the Indian market as retail giants. This increased the threat to all retail businesses as people were switching to e-commerce quicker than ever. Biyani saw this as an opportunity to extend his business to online platforms as well and thus decided to launch '&lt;em&gt;Retail 3.0&lt;/em&gt;'. It was too late to enter as the market had already been saturated and was now under the control of corporations like Amazon and Flipkart. Things didn’t work out for the group as planned. As of March 31, 2019, the combined debt of the Future Group was valued at ₹1.2 trillion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only viable option left for Biyani was to sell off the entire group. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), which is looking to increase its presence in the retail business, acquired the retail and wholesale business as well as the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion in 2020. Soon after the announcement was made public, Amazon jumped in between and turned the tables around. It not only slapped a legal notice but also approached the Singapore International Arbitration Centre (SIAC) claiming that the Future Group had breached the contract according to which Amazon owns a 49% stake in the Future Coupons Pvt Ltd, the parent company which owns all the retail stores, and thus has the first rights to refuse or acquire an even larger stake in the Future Group (after 3 years and before 10 years). Amazon has requested the SIAC to halt the deal between RIL and the Future Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments in defence of the deal state that pre-conditions that exist in the Amazon deal only come into effect after 2022, thus the allegations do not stand. Also, it is claimed that Future Coupons has nothing to do with the Ambani-Biyani deal, and hence, the legal notice doesn’t matter and won’t affect the deal for long. Well, we can’t really be sure of these points and thus have the avenue to make an opinion about the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal was still awaiting completion by the authorities but now it seems to be kinda blurry! We know how prominent Amazon and RIL are in the Indian markets. They have expanded their businesses and the results have been profitable too. This deal definitely plays a crucial role considering the fact that the Future Group has a huge consumer base which will now benefit the new owner. Reliance Industries is owned by the richest Indian, Mukesh Ambani, and the company is in good shape and thus was looking forward to taking over the Future Group. It has plans to enter the e-commerce business via Jiomart. This will expand their business empire in the world of e-retail which will be beneficial in the long run. As we know, Amazon is the boss of e-commerce and won’t enjoy this new entrant in their arena. Thus, going ahead and flashing a legal notice which further halts the deal seems like a smart move to hamper the growth of RIL. We have grown up reading about business rivalries but we also know that profit is the only thing that matters at the end of the day. At this point in time, Amazon should be considerate of the fact that expansion within the subcontinent won’t be an easy task if they make RIL their rivals. The kind of control and authority RIL enjoys within the Indian markets is massive and thus the support will be of much help for expanding businesses. Amazon has the option to negotiate outside the courts and find a solution that satisfies the two parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever be the case, the Future Group has lost its shine and is now being juggled between two companies who only care about their profits and will prioritise their self-interests. Both Amazon and Reliance have been expanding their shares in the Indian markets. With or without the battle, both corporations are winning in a way that benefits them exclusively. The kind of power and authority they have is unbeatable so this case won’t really matter to them. For us, however, it is going to be an interesting battle to look forward to!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Reliance and Future Group deal has been in the headlines since a few days now. The recent development which involved Amazon sending a legal notice has spiced it up even more. We are all obsessed with conflicts especially when three multinational corporations are involved. To get a better understanding of the on-going feud, we need to look at the previous developments and understand what actually led to the present-day situation. Future Group, owned by Kishore Biyani, had been facing a crisis for a few years. They were in huge debt and the reason might have been the diverse and over-ambitious investments made by the company. The group started out with a unique idea that gained success and their retail stores like Pantaloons and Big Bazaar became common household names. The greed to expand business in diverse areas might have turned out to be a big mistake. The group was burdened under debts but still continued to invest and make useless purchases. As the debt accumulated over time, the only option left was to sell their retail chains and shut down useless businesses. At the same time, online platforms like Amazon and Flipkart had already established themselves in the Indian market as retail giants. This increased the threat to all retail businesses as people were switching to e-commerce quicker than ever. Biyani saw this as an opportunity to extend his business to online platforms as well and thus decided to launch 'Retail 3.0'. It was too late to enter as the market had already been saturated and was now under the control of corporations like Amazon and Flipkart. Things didn’t work out for the group as planned. As of March 31, 2019, the combined debt of the Future Group was valued at ₹1.2 trillion. The only viable option left for Biyani was to sell off the entire group. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), which is looking to increase its presence in the retail business, acquired the retail and wholesale business as well as the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion in 2020. Soon after the announcement was made public, Amazon jumped in between and turned the tables around. It not only slapped a legal notice but also approached the Singapore International Arbitration Centre (SIAC) claiming that the Future Group had breached the contract according to which Amazon owns a 49% stake in the Future Coupons Pvt Ltd, the parent company which owns all the retail stores, and thus has the first rights to refuse or acquire an even larger stake in the Future Group (after 3 years and before 10 years). Amazon has requested the SIAC to halt the deal between RIL and the Future Group. Arguments in defence of the deal state that pre-conditions that exist in the Amazon deal only come into effect after 2022, thus the allegations do not stand. Also, it is claimed that Future Coupons has nothing to do with the Ambani-Biyani deal, and hence, the legal notice doesn’t matter and won’t affect the deal for long. Well, we can’t really be sure of these points and thus have the avenue to make an opinion about the same. The deal was still awaiting completion by the authorities but now it seems to be kinda blurry! We know how prominent Amazon and RIL are in the Indian markets. They have expanded their businesses and the results have been profitable too. This deal definitely plays a crucial role considering the fact that the Future Group has a huge consumer base which will now benefit the new owner. Reliance Industries is owned by the richest Indian, Mukesh Ambani, and the company is in good shape and thus was looking forward to taking over the Future Group. It has plans to enter the e-commerce business via Jiomart. This will expand their business empire in the world of e-retail which will be beneficial in the long run. As we know, Amazon is the boss of e-commerce and won’t enjoy this new entrant in their arena. Thus, going ahead and flashing a legal notice which further halts the deal seems like a smart move to hamper the growth of RIL. We have grown up reading about business rivalries but we also know that profit is the only thing that matters at the end of the day. At this point in time, Amazon should be considerate of the fact that expansion within the subcontinent won’t be an easy task if they make RIL their rivals. The kind of control and authority RIL enjoys within the Indian markets is massive and thus the support will be of much help for expanding businesses. Amazon has the option to negotiate outside the courts and find a solution that satisfies the two parties. Whatever be the case, the Future Group has lost its shine and is now being juggled between two companies who only care about their profits and will prioritise their self-interests. Both Amazon and Reliance have been expanding their shares in the Indian markets. With or without the battle, both corporations are winning in a way that benefits them exclusively. The kind of power and authority they have is unbeatable so this case won’t really matter to them. For us, however, it is going to be an interesting battle to look forward to!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 and the Indian Labour Market</title><link href="/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and the Indian Labour Market" /><published>2020-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market</id><content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market">&lt;p&gt;The outbreak of coronavirus has resulted in an unparalleled public health and socio-economic crisis. COVID-19 has heavily impacted the daily lives of people and has thwarted their ability to earn their livelihood. The case is no different for India. With the view of maintaining social distancing and other preventive health measures followed, work-from-home has become the new normal. However, it is important to understand that not all the segments of the labour market are able to function this way. The dual shock of the lockdown and pandemic has thus resulted in major disruptions in the labour market, and job and income losses of millions of people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of coronavirus has been rampant in India, with a steep increase in the number of cases being reported on a daily basis. Before the outbreak of COVID-19, India had already been experiencing an economic slowdown, with the growth rate in GDP declining to 3.1% in Jan-March quarter 2020. However, in the Apr-Jun quarter of the financial year 2020-21, the GDP growth rate has fallen to a negative 23.9%, the worst ever in economic history. All the crucial parameters like manufacturing, construction, trade and the hotel industry have witnessed a steep decline, registering negative growth rates as well. According to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MOSPI), India's Industrial Production (IIP) fell by 16.7% year-on-year in March 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact on the Indian Labour Market&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the worst-hit in this situation has been the labour market. According to the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), a Mumbai-based think tank, during the period of lockdown (March-May), the unemployment rate went up from 8% to 24.3%. As of April 2020, 122 million people have suffered a job loss, with casual workers and self-employed accounting for a major proportion of this, pegging at 90 million. The effect of the shocks induced by the ongoing crisis has been particularly harsh for a specific group of people in the labour market. They can be identified as less educated individuals with low incomes who are engaged in risky and unstable working conditions. These individuals form a major portion of the informal sector. On the other hand, only a small share of the labour force is employed in salaried jobs with the perks of social security benefits. Hence, an outcome of this scenario will be a sheer rise in income inequalities. The most recent data available on the labour force is the Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS 2018-19). According to the survey, the labour force participation rate in 2018-19 stands at 37.5%. The share of people self-employed, as casual labourers and as regular salaried workers in rural and urban areas can be observed in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pib.gov.in/PressReleaseIframePage.aspx?PRID=1629366&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/periodiclabourforcesurvey.png&quot; /&gt;Source: Periodic Labour Force Survey 2018-19&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the regular salaried workers, white-collar professionals and other employees have witnessed the biggest loss of jobs. These include software engineers, physicians, teachers, accountants, analysts and the type who are professionally qualified and are employed in some private or government organisation. According to CMIE, the employment of these professionally qualified white-collar workers fell steeply to 12.2 million during the wave of May-August 2020. This is the lowest employment of these professionals since 2016. An unprecedented 21 million salaried employees had lost their jobs by the end of August. All the gains made in their employment over the past four years were washed away during the lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, those who are self-employed, only a minor proportion of them can be classified as employers. Of these 57.4% rural self-employed households, most of them are marginal cultivators and petty artisans, while 38.7% of self-employed households in urban areas are engaged in small shops, low-scale businesses or intermediation activities. Similarly, the casual labour households that make up almost 20% of the labour force are also extremely vulnerable and fragile in coping up with this economic downturn.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the people categorised as self-employed or as casual workers are faced with no income stability or job security and are outside the umbrella of the employment benefits offered by firms. Compared to them, the regular salaried workers do receive a salary on a periodic basis, but even then, not all of them have access to social security benefits or secure job contracts. It is thus these casual workers that are at the bottom of the hierarchy and are financially vulnerable. A sudden loss of income to these people will lead them to fall into deep poverty. The impact of the pandemic has been the worst for these sectors where the options for remote work are limited or negligible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the World Bank, the shock of the pandemic is expected to push 12 million people into extreme poverty in India. Some reports have suggested that poverty in India had started rising even before the COVID-19 crisis, therefore the above estimates might even be higher. With the cloud of uncertainty looming over their heads, and the loss of jobs and incomes, the poor and the illiterate do not have the option to stay unemployed or wait for a job which serves their needs. In rural areas, we still have Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) as a fallback employment option. But such a safety net doesn’t exist for the urban labourers, who are also faced with high costs of living. The ones rendered unemployed have taken up low income and low productivity jobs, while some have migrated back to their homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As was expected, with the declaration of a nationwide lockdown, there was an unprecedented large-scale reverse migration of labour wherein millions of workers travelled across the state borders amidst food shortages and uncertainty about their work prospects in the future. While the government schemes ensure the availability of rations, the distribution system failed to be effective. Penniless and stranded, workers left cities for their villages on foot or bicycles, cramped in trucks and later by trains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inter-state migration has thus put some of India’s biggest sectors at risk. Sectors such as manufacturing, retail and wholesale trade, mining and hospitality services are heavily dependent on migrants from other states, as analysed by India Ratings and Research. “A consequence of this is a labour crunch that might hit capacity utilisation for several firms. The manufacturing sector which employs over 6 million migrant workers from other states, highest as compared to other sectors, has started suffering. The sector contributes almost 8% of the country’s GDP. Thus the manufacturing sector might face a labour shortage in the near term if labourers do not return in the coming months. This will lead to an increase in wages in the short run and a fall in profits. Another obvious impact is on the mining sector, which has been observing a decline in the past few months.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amidst all this, many state governments have repealed labour laws. The government of the North Indian state of Uttar Pradesh has cleared an ordinance that suspends all the labour laws for a period of three years with the exceptions of laws related to the abolishment of bonded labour, ex gratia payments to workers in case of work-related diseases and disabilities and timely wage payments. Similar actions have been taken by the state governments of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat with a few variations. The decision has been taken to encourage new investments, setting up of new infrastructure, and for the upliftment of existing industries and factories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Lies Ahead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the latest estimates by CMIE, the unemployment rates have dropped to 6.4%, which is the lowest rate seen in a while, but this is hardly a cause for celebration. Other weekly labour metrics have only deteriorated, for example, the average labour participation rate fell down to 20.7% in the first three weeks of September as opposed to 40.96% in August. Similarly, the average employment rate during the first three weeks of August at 37.9% is substantially higher than the rates seen recently. But the slope is negative since the recovery is distinctly negative.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the country recently declared ‘Unlock 5.0’, the economy is still far from being on a path of recovery. The economy is still worse off as compared to the conditions before the lockdown. The recent labour statistics only highlight the fear of India slipping from this ‘incomplete’ recovery unless the government comes up with a well-calculated recovery plan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rajsi Sah</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The outbreak of coronavirus has resulted in an unparalleled public health and socio-economic crisis. COVID-19 has heavily impacted the daily lives of people and has thwarted their ability to earn their livelihood. The case is no different for India. With the view of maintaining social distancing and other preventive health measures followed, work-from-home has become the new normal. However, it is important to understand that not all the segments of the labour market are able to function this way. The dual shock of the lockdown and pandemic has thus resulted in major disruptions in the labour market, and job and income losses of millions of people.&amp;nbsp; The spread of coronavirus has been rampant in India, with a steep increase in the number of cases being reported on a daily basis. Before the outbreak of COVID-19, India had already been experiencing an economic slowdown, with the growth rate in GDP declining to 3.1% in Jan-March quarter 2020. However, in the Apr-Jun quarter of the financial year 2020-21, the GDP growth rate has fallen to a negative 23.9%, the worst ever in economic history. All the crucial parameters like manufacturing, construction, trade and the hotel industry have witnessed a steep decline, registering negative growth rates as well. According to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MOSPI), India's Industrial Production (IIP) fell by 16.7% year-on-year in March 2020.&amp;nbsp; Impact on the Indian Labour Market&amp;nbsp; One of the worst-hit in this situation has been the labour market. According to the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), a Mumbai-based think tank, during the period of lockdown (March-May), the unemployment rate went up from 8% to 24.3%. As of April 2020, 122 million people have suffered a job loss, with casual workers and self-employed accounting for a major proportion of this, pegging at 90 million. The effect of the shocks induced by the ongoing crisis has been particularly harsh for a specific group of people in the labour market. They can be identified as less educated individuals with low incomes who are engaged in risky and unstable working conditions. These individuals form a major portion of the informal sector. On the other hand, only a small share of the labour force is employed in salaried jobs with the perks of social security benefits. Hence, an outcome of this scenario will be a sheer rise in income inequalities. The most recent data available on the labour force is the Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS 2018-19). According to the survey, the labour force participation rate in 2018-19 stands at 37.5%. The share of people self-employed, as casual labourers and as regular salaried workers in rural and urban areas can be observed in the table below: Source: Periodic Labour Force Survey 2018-19 Among the regular salaried workers, white-collar professionals and other employees have witnessed the biggest loss of jobs. These include software engineers, physicians, teachers, accountants, analysts and the type who are professionally qualified and are employed in some private or government organisation. According to CMIE, the employment of these professionally qualified white-collar workers fell steeply to 12.2 million during the wave of May-August 2020. This is the lowest employment of these professionals since 2016. An unprecedented 21 million salaried employees had lost their jobs by the end of August. All the gains made in their employment over the past four years were washed away during the lockdown. Furthermore, those who are self-employed, only a minor proportion of them can be classified as employers. Of these 57.4% rural self-employed households, most of them are marginal cultivators and petty artisans, while 38.7% of self-employed households in urban areas are engaged in small shops, low-scale businesses or intermediation activities. Similarly, the casual labour households that make up almost 20% of the labour force are also extremely vulnerable and fragile in coping up with this economic downturn.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the people categorised as self-employed or as casual workers are faced with no income stability or job security and are outside the umbrella of the employment benefits offered by firms. Compared to them, the regular salaried workers do receive a salary on a periodic basis, but even then, not all of them have access to social security benefits or secure job contracts. It is thus these casual workers that are at the bottom of the hierarchy and are financially vulnerable. A sudden loss of income to these people will lead them to fall into deep poverty. The impact of the pandemic has been the worst for these sectors where the options for remote work are limited or negligible.&amp;nbsp; According to the World Bank, the shock of the pandemic is expected to push 12 million people into extreme poverty in India. Some reports have suggested that poverty in India had started rising even before the COVID-19 crisis, therefore the above estimates might even be higher. With the cloud of uncertainty looming over their heads, and the loss of jobs and incomes, the poor and the illiterate do not have the option to stay unemployed or wait for a job which serves their needs. In rural areas, we still have Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) as a fallback employment option. But such a safety net doesn’t exist for the urban labourers, who are also faced with high costs of living. The ones rendered unemployed have taken up low income and low productivity jobs, while some have migrated back to their homes.&amp;nbsp; As was expected, with the declaration of a nationwide lockdown, there was an unprecedented large-scale reverse migration of labour wherein millions of workers travelled across the state borders amidst food shortages and uncertainty about their work prospects in the future. While the government schemes ensure the availability of rations, the distribution system failed to be effective. Penniless and stranded, workers left cities for their villages on foot or bicycles, cramped in trucks and later by trains.&amp;nbsp; This inter-state migration has thus put some of India’s biggest sectors at risk. Sectors such as manufacturing, retail and wholesale trade, mining and hospitality services are heavily dependent on migrants from other states, as analysed by India Ratings and Research. “A consequence of this is a labour crunch that might hit capacity utilisation for several firms. The manufacturing sector which employs over 6 million migrant workers from other states, highest as compared to other sectors, has started suffering. The sector contributes almost 8% of the country’s GDP. Thus the manufacturing sector might face a labour shortage in the near term if labourers do not return in the coming months. This will lead to an increase in wages in the short run and a fall in profits. Another obvious impact is on the mining sector, which has been observing a decline in the past few months.&amp;nbsp; Amidst all this, many state governments have repealed labour laws. The government of the North Indian state of Uttar Pradesh has cleared an ordinance that suspends all the labour laws for a period of three years with the exceptions of laws related to the abolishment of bonded labour, ex gratia payments to workers in case of work-related diseases and disabilities and timely wage payments. Similar actions have been taken by the state governments of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat with a few variations. The decision has been taken to encourage new investments, setting up of new infrastructure, and for the upliftment of existing industries and factories.&amp;nbsp; What Lies Ahead? According to the latest estimates by CMIE, the unemployment rates have dropped to 6.4%, which is the lowest rate seen in a while, but this is hardly a cause for celebration. Other weekly labour metrics have only deteriorated, for example, the average labour participation rate fell down to 20.7% in the first three weeks of September as opposed to 40.96% in August. Similarly, the average employment rate during the first three weeks of August at 37.9% is substantially higher than the rates seen recently. But the slope is negative since the recovery is distinctly negative.&amp;nbsp; While the country recently declared ‘Unlock 5.0’, the economy is still far from being on a path of recovery. The economy is still worse off as compared to the conditions before the lockdown. The recent labour statistics only highlight the fear of India slipping from this ‘incomplete’ recovery unless the government comes up with a well-calculated recovery plan.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Spotlight on Indian-American Voters: 2020 US Presidential Elections</title><link href="/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters-2020-US-Presidential-Elections" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Spotlight on Indian-American Voters: 2020 US Presidential Elections" /><published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters--2020-US-Presidential-Elections</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters-2020-US-Presidential-Elections">&lt;p&gt;The 2020 US presidential election campaign has been heating up, with Americans set to vote on November 3, 2020. In the face of the coronavirus pandemic, this election is certainly going to be different. What remains the same is the age-old voter’s dilemma of whom to cast their vote for.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spotlight is on Indian-American voters this election. Though Indian-Americans constitute a mere 1.5% of the population, their impact on American politics is often disproportionate. Indian-Americans are among the wealthiest and most educated immigrant groups within the US. Their vote would be especially important in battleground states such as Michigan, Pennsylvania and Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a report by South Asian Americans Leading Together (SAALT),&amp;nbsp; the number of Indian-Americans increased from 29 million to 40 million between 2010 and 2017, nearly a 40% rise. In 18 states, the number of Indian immigrants is higher than any other immigrant group. According to the American Community Survey 2017, the largest number of Indians have settled in California (730,000) followed by New York (370,000), New Jersey (370,000), Texas (350,000), Illinois (230,000) and Florida (150,000). In terms of the proportion of the population, the largest number of Indians are in New Jersey (4.1%), Rhode Island (3.36%),&amp;nbsp; New York (1.88%), Illinois (1.81%), California (1.8%) and Delaware (1.61%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These numbers show the importance of catering to the interests of this section of the electorate because even a few thousand votes have the potential to turn the tables. So, will the Democratic Party’s Indian-origin Vice Presidential candidate win the hearts of these voters or will their affection towards Trump continue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US Senator Kamala Harris has become a focal point in the election, grabbing the attention of voters with her logical and opinionated speeches as well as her down to earth personality. While being immensely proud of her American identity, she has held on to her heritage and flaunts it with pride. Her mother, Shyamala Gopalan, was a biologist from Chennai while her father, Donald Harris, an economist, hailed from Jamaica. After her parents got divorced, her mother raised Kamala Harris and her sister as members of an African American Church but also took them to Hindu temples. Her history presents a chance of a deeper connection with the Indian American electorate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Donald Trump has expressed surety in the fact that Indian Americans will vote Republican, highlighting the good relationship that he has developed with Indian Prime Minister Narender Modi. Their twin events of ‘&lt;em&gt;Howdy Modi&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;Namaste Trump&lt;/em&gt;’ were just one of their many public shows of support for each other. In fact ‘&lt;em&gt;Namaste Trump&lt;/em&gt;’ which took place in Gujarat was also in anticipation of the 2020 election and was very carefully planned. According to the US census data, 20% of the entire population of Indian-Americans constitutes Gujaratis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a White House press conference, Trump said, “&lt;em&gt;We have great support from India. We've got great support from Prime Minister Modi. I might think that the Indian (American) people would be voting for Mr Trump.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;He did not miss a chance to reaffirm his bond with Mr Modi and continued to say,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Prime Minister Modi may be a friend of mine and he’s doing a really good job. Nothing easy, but he’s done a really good job&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic leaders are apprehensive that Mr Trump’s friendship with Modi might sway their traditional vote bank during the upcoming elections. These attempts to please Indian Americans have often led to slip-ups in public debates where Trump has ended up making a joke of his support for India. While praising the number of COVID-19 tests taking place worldwide, President Trump showered India with admiration for their vigilant testing, albeit with incorrect data and statistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite such great attempts to woo this section of voters, it would be presumptuous on the part of Trump to assume that he has their votes in the bag. This year, the Indian-American electorate is on the radar of both Democrats and Republicans. Around 56% of Indian-American registered voters told the AAPI data pollsters that they had been contacted by the Democrats within the past year and 48% said that they were approached by the Republicans. Surprisingly, a recent Asian American and Pacific Islanders (AAPI) data survey found that only 28% of Indian-Americans expressed support for Trump while two-thirds of them said that they are going to vote for Biden. In the face of this data, it seems that it would do India well to build the base of a relationship with Biden as well, lest they lose out on the favour of the most powerful country in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons for the support shown towards Biden. Firstly, the former Vice President’s long history as a supporter of India, dating back to his Senate days, has clearly left a mark on the minds of the Indian-American voters. Secondly, Trump’s approach to India, very similar to his approach to politics and governing, has primarily been one of rhetoric instead of consistency in terms of policy positions. Finally, Indian-Americans, similar to many other voters in the US, perceive the Trump Presidency as one of excessive chaos and confrontation for the US and consequently for India and the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aberjhani, an American historian,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;had succinctly put forth the responsibility that lies on the shoulders of an American voter. He said, “&lt;em&gt;The job facing American voters… in the days and years to come, is to determine which hearts, minds and souls command those qualities best suited to unify a country rather than further divide it, to heal the wounds of a nation as opposed to aggravate its injuries, and to secure for the next generation a legacy of choices based on informed awareness rather than one of reactions based on unknowing fear”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It must be kept in mind that the 2020 elections come at a time of great turmoil. The results will determine how the US deals with the ongoing issues of the pandemic as well as the uproar against racism and police violence. Additionally, owing to the centrality of the US in world politics, the election will cause a ripple effect throughout the world. Indian-Americans have an important role to play in determining this future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aniba Junaid</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The 2020 US presidential election campaign has been heating up, with Americans set to vote on November 3, 2020. In the face of the coronavirus pandemic, this election is certainly going to be different. What remains the same is the age-old voter’s dilemma of whom to cast their vote for.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The spotlight is on Indian-American voters this election. Though Indian-Americans constitute a mere 1.5% of the population, their impact on American politics is often disproportionate. Indian-Americans are among the wealthiest and most educated immigrant groups within the US. Their vote would be especially important in battleground states such as Michigan, Pennsylvania and Ohio. According to a report by South Asian Americans Leading Together (SAALT),&amp;nbsp; the number of Indian-Americans increased from 29 million to 40 million between 2010 and 2017, nearly a 40% rise. In 18 states, the number of Indian immigrants is higher than any other immigrant group. According to the American Community Survey 2017, the largest number of Indians have settled in California (730,000) followed by New York (370,000), New Jersey (370,000), Texas (350,000), Illinois (230,000) and Florida (150,000). In terms of the proportion of the population, the largest number of Indians are in New Jersey (4.1%), Rhode Island (3.36%),&amp;nbsp; New York (1.88%), Illinois (1.81%), California (1.8%) and Delaware (1.61%). These numbers show the importance of catering to the interests of this section of the electorate because even a few thousand votes have the potential to turn the tables. So, will the Democratic Party’s Indian-origin Vice Presidential candidate win the hearts of these voters or will their affection towards Trump continue? US Senator Kamala Harris has become a focal point in the election, grabbing the attention of voters with her logical and opinionated speeches as well as her down to earth personality. While being immensely proud of her American identity, she has held on to her heritage and flaunts it with pride. Her mother, Shyamala Gopalan, was a biologist from Chennai while her father, Donald Harris, an economist, hailed from Jamaica. After her parents got divorced, her mother raised Kamala Harris and her sister as members of an African American Church but also took them to Hindu temples. Her history presents a chance of a deeper connection with the Indian American electorate.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, Donald Trump has expressed surety in the fact that Indian Americans will vote Republican, highlighting the good relationship that he has developed with Indian Prime Minister Narender Modi. Their twin events of ‘Howdy Modi’ and ‘Namaste Trump’ were just one of their many public shows of support for each other. In fact ‘Namaste Trump’ which took place in Gujarat was also in anticipation of the 2020 election and was very carefully planned. According to the US census data, 20% of the entire population of Indian-Americans constitutes Gujaratis.&amp;nbsp; At a White House press conference, Trump said, “We have great support from India. We've got great support from Prime Minister Modi. I might think that the Indian (American) people would be voting for Mr Trump.” He did not miss a chance to reaffirm his bond with Mr Modi and continued to say, “Prime Minister Modi may be a friend of mine and he’s doing a really good job. Nothing easy, but he’s done a really good job”. Democratic leaders are apprehensive that Mr Trump’s friendship with Modi might sway their traditional vote bank during the upcoming elections. These attempts to please Indian Americans have often led to slip-ups in public debates where Trump has ended up making a joke of his support for India. While praising the number of COVID-19 tests taking place worldwide, President Trump showered India with admiration for their vigilant testing, albeit with incorrect data and statistics.&amp;nbsp; Despite such great attempts to woo this section of voters, it would be presumptuous on the part of Trump to assume that he has their votes in the bag. This year, the Indian-American electorate is on the radar of both Democrats and Republicans. Around 56% of Indian-American registered voters told the AAPI data pollsters that they had been contacted by the Democrats within the past year and 48% said that they were approached by the Republicans. Surprisingly, a recent Asian American and Pacific Islanders (AAPI) data survey found that only 28% of Indian-Americans expressed support for Trump while two-thirds of them said that they are going to vote for Biden. In the face of this data, it seems that it would do India well to build the base of a relationship with Biden as well, lest they lose out on the favour of the most powerful country in the world. There are many reasons for the support shown towards Biden. Firstly, the former Vice President’s long history as a supporter of India, dating back to his Senate days, has clearly left a mark on the minds of the Indian-American voters. Secondly, Trump’s approach to India, very similar to his approach to politics and governing, has primarily been one of rhetoric instead of consistency in terms of policy positions. Finally, Indian-Americans, similar to many other voters in the US, perceive the Trump Presidency as one of excessive chaos and confrontation for the US and consequently for India and the rest of the world. Aberjhani, an American historian, had succinctly put forth the responsibility that lies on the shoulders of an American voter. He said, “The job facing American voters… in the days and years to come, is to determine which hearts, minds and souls command those qualities best suited to unify a country rather than further divide it, to heal the wounds of a nation as opposed to aggravate its injuries, and to secure for the next generation a legacy of choices based on informed awareness rather than one of reactions based on unknowing fear”.&amp;nbsp; It must be kept in mind that the 2020 elections come at a time of great turmoil. The results will determine how the US deals with the ongoing issues of the pandemic as well as the uproar against racism and police violence. Additionally, owing to the centrality of the US in world politics, the election will cause a ripple effect throughout the world. Indian-Americans have an important role to play in determining this future.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19: RBI’s Take and What Now?</title><link href="/RBI-Take-What-Now" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19: RBI’s Take and What Now?" /><published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/RBI-Take-What-Now</id><content type="html" xml:base="/RBI-Take-What-Now">&lt;p&gt;The Central bank of a nation is tasked with multiple responsibilities to maintain the dynamic, complex and entangled macroeconomic variables with the sole objective of economic development of the country. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) follows the same pursuit of growth by working out the price and financial stability of the state. The gigantic wave of virus that swept the world in late 2019 and hit India in early 2020 has inevitably accelerated the socio-economic division, the footprint of which will be felt for years to come. With the advent of such unprecedented times, all eyes are turned to the Central bank and to the government for rescue from the ramifications of this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the late evening of March 24, 2020, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced a 21-day complete lockdown which got extended for months due to the rising number of COVID-19 cases in the country. This declaration meant an absolute halt for businesses leading to complete disruption of market forces of demand and supply, money creation, etc. In short, it was a difficult affair for the economy. Nonetheless, the RBI sailed through it almost effortlessly, supporting the economy through the various tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) &lt;strong&gt;Rate cuts&lt;/strong&gt;: To incentivise investments and loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) &lt;strong&gt;Liquidity Infusion&lt;/strong&gt;: Increasing the availability of funds in banks via various policy rates like CRR, Repo rate, Reverse Repo Rate, OMOs, and special windows for financial institutions to borrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) &lt;strong&gt;Regulatory Easing&lt;/strong&gt;: Via mechanisms like a moratorium, etc to support the borrowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps resulted in a liquidity spree in the banking system, drawing concerns of inflationary pressure in an already high inflation economy (CPI inflation rate in July was 6.93%). In addition to this, the influx of dollars in the country through Foreign Direct Investments (FDIs) and Foreign Portfolio Investments (FPIs) fuelled the additional circulation of Indian currency in the economy. This, supported by collapsing net imports, led to the pile-up of RBIs forex kitty to an all-time high of $541billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s language, it looks like a rosy picture. However from an economist’s point of view, this means appreciation of the Indian rupee with respect to the mighty US dollar. Thus, putting exports at a disadvantage. It adds to the already concerning topic of inflation as now excess money will be spent on the imported items, increasing our dependence on imported goods. At the same time, we will be letting go of the opportunity of utilising the liquidity available in the system which could have been used to build productive capacities like infrastructure that will lead to the creation of employment, income and welfare of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, inflation will only occur when the monetary surplus in the banking system actually reaches the hands of the consumers via businesses and loans, but banks are averse in lending out due to skyrocketing Non-Performing Assets (NPAs). Hence the overflowing liquidity is limited within these financial intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to an article published in &lt;em&gt;Business Today&lt;/em&gt;, despite the Central bank reducing the Reverse Repo Rate (RRR) from 4.9% to 3.35%, the number of deposits increased during the period of the pandemic. Unused funds in the financial system have further been increasing as businesses and firms are reluctant in taking loans for investments due to low production and capacity utilisation. Moreover, rising COVID-19 cases engulf the future with a blanket of uncertainty for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jump in the deposits with the RBI is a cause of worry as the excess money sitting idle with banks now requires the Central bank to pay interest on these deposits. Additionally, the money is never actually entering the productive sector for money creation, which was the prime motive of slashing the RRR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, governments too have a vital role in reviving the economy through its targeted expenditures. But the Union government’s fiscal deficit has soared to 109% of the budgeted target in just 5 months of the current financial year. State governments have been facing a shortage of funds owing to the shortfall of revenues due to sluggish economic activities and failure on part of the Union government to settle the compensation for Goods and Services Tax (GST). Hence, the governments’ bank stepped in to facilitate the reduction of that deficit by borrowing from the bond market. The Center has stuck to its borrowing plan of ₹12 trillion in 2020-21. The superfluity of funds in the financial system is managing to keep the yields in the bond market low, benefitting the borrowers in borrowing funds at low-interest rates. The Central government borrowed ₹7.66 trillion at a weighted rate of 5.82%, the lowest in 15 years, in the first half of the ongoing fiscal year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting the rate of economic expansion back on track is a daunting task and RBI has managed the situation quite decently, but the major chunk of work now lies on the government to use their borrowing for capital expenditure and revival of demand. Better demand sentiments would enable restoration of the market disruptions and lead to an expansion in the trade deficit which would perhaps reduce the balance of payment surplus and minimise the intervention by the Central bank to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest projection by the US Federal Reserve to keep its interest rate near zero till 2023 would result in a sustained flow of foreign funds into countries like India. Therefore, the bankers’ bank needs to be watchful and avoid unnecessary currency appreciation which will not only affect exports but also other macroeconomic variables, thus risking the financial stability of the nation. The biggest challenge will perhaps come when pandemic recedes and activity picks back up but for now, the Reserve Bank needs to maintain a fine balance between the intertwined variables of inflation, bond yields, and currency market for the economic interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The Central bank of a nation is tasked with multiple responsibilities to maintain the dynamic, complex and entangled macroeconomic variables with the sole objective of economic development of the country. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) follows the same pursuit of growth by working out the price and financial stability of the state. The gigantic wave of virus that swept the world in late 2019 and hit India in early 2020 has inevitably accelerated the socio-economic division, the footprint of which will be felt for years to come. With the advent of such unprecedented times, all eyes are turned to the Central bank and to the government for rescue from the ramifications of this situation.</summary></entry></feed>