<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-25T15:45:10+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Great (Millennial) Depression</title><link href="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great (Millennial) Depression" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Great-Millennial-Depression</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression">&lt;p&gt;If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the WHO, about 300 million people around the world are affected by depression. Nearly 800,000 people commit suicide every year. Suicide is second on the list of leading causes of deaths in 15 to 29 year-olds today. In spite of this, only 1 in every 5 depressed people receives treatment consistent with modern practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous TV series and films have been made, aimed at tackling this. Their failure, however, has been appalling. Season 1 of the TV series &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Wh&lt;/em&gt;y features a series of tapes left behind by a girl who commits suicide while in high school. In these tapes, she explains the 13 reasons behind her drastic step. No wonder this series became very popular; it was not just relatable to the very core but the drama of listening to a dead girl’s tapes, explaining why she committed suicide, was scintillating. Besides the wave of awareness, the series left behind one adverse impact. The number of suicides increased by almost a third, instead of going down, ever since the series aired. Within three weeks of being aired, searches about suicides increased by a staggering 20%. Many blame it on the very graphic depiction of how Hannah Baker, the protagonist, took her life by slitting her wrists at the very end of the series. This is not something that audiences have witnessed before on television, certainly not in programmes aimed at teenagers. The popularity of the series earned it two more seasons in the years that followed. However, amidst all the concerns, Netflix altered the 3-minute sequence, although convinced that the series had nothing to do with the increase in suicide rates in the USA, over 2 years after its initial release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has, however, been a decline in the stigma surrounding mental health. People do seek to talk about and actively treat depression and other mental health problems. Various online portals and helplines are active to give help to those seeking it. Earlier, they failed to recognise depression as a disease that needed treatment. Instead, they saw it as inadequacy or incompetence. Certain old asylums are often considered to be haunted because of the unspoken torture within its walls in the past. Hundreds have died in various such locations around the world, after being shunned by society for being mentally ill. Shock therapy, invented in the Italy of the 1930s, was commonly practiced to treat ‘madness’. Many, even today, believe in the effectiveness of electroconvulsive therapy, although it has been repeatedly tagged as medical abuse by different organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are convinced that they are but &lt;strong&gt;doomed&lt;/strong&gt;. And this conviction comes from a place of hyperawareness. There is near-constant exposure to news of thousands being beheaded in the name of religion or people committing suicide by bringing down an entire airbus full of people along with themselves. Or, maybe, that people are capable of democratically electing a person who doesn’t believe that Global Warming, which, by the way, can facilitate the extinction of humanity, is real, as the Leader of the Free World. We are always talking and making memes about Trump’s tweets, the melting ice caps or India’s water crisis. We see the expendability of human life in the deaths of our beloved Cameron Boyce, Stan Lee, Avicii, Stephen Hawking, Dolores O’Riordan, David Cassidy, Chester Bennington, Bill Paxton, Carrie Fisher, Harper Lee, and Alan Rickman. In fact, most Millennials do not even conform to the term ‘Millennial’, tagging it as &lt;em&gt;overly optimistic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media and its ultra-fast nature have made it clear to the Millennials that humans are irrevocable. Millennials are &lt;strong&gt;aware&lt;/strong&gt; that the Zodiac Killer was never caught, MH-370 was never found and that France experienced its highest ever temperature in recorded history, earlier this year. They are aware of students shooting down hundreds in schools, abortion being banned and trees being cut. We know how this is affecting us all as a species and yet, there seems to be nothing that we can do about it. The news of bad incidents looms over us every day along with the knowledge that it can happen to any of us too. The incredibly talented and very dead singer Kurt Cobain did tell us, “Just because you are paranoid, does not mean they are not after you.” Millennials are the first generation to grow up in an era of both overwhelming awareness and paralysing feeling of our incapability to be able to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know what is expected of us, the perfect job and the perfect partner, and we are aware of how it is just a pipe dream. They tell us it is social media reinforcements of everyone else living the perfect life that is making our generation depressed. That we are trying to reach for standards we will never attain. But I think there is more to the Great Millennial Depression than just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that you are Einstein-smart, devilishly beautiful and incredibly funny. Are you among the top 10 something? If you are not, well then, you do not matter. Let us assume that you are among the world’s top 10 most hilarious people. Will you hold the position forever? What happens next year? What if you face a decade-long writer’s block and go bankrupt? Perhaps you &lt;em&gt;succeed&lt;/em&gt; and go on a cruise with your soulmate and drown in your bathtub? We all will die one day and there will be nothing left of us in a few decades. No one will remember our sacrifices, pain, hard work or the embarrassing moments that we have shared with our crushes. The question is, are we important? Are our actions significant? Why is it that humans have had the privilege to even exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have asked these for long and today, Millennials are convinced that nothing has an explanation. There is nowhere a certain someone is meant to be or something they are meant to do. They just exist. The stars were not specially created to dazzle us. Neither are we at the centre of the solar system, the universe or Creation in general. Things just exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think I am right, well then, congratulations, you are a nihilist. It is highly likely that you are a Millennial too. Turns out, the term nihilism has a very simple meaning. It is the rejection of all religious and moral principles. Nihilists believe that life has absolutely no meaning and yet humans keep seeking a way to give it some meaning, some purpose, but eventually die and are forgotten. In Tyler Durden’s &lt;em&gt;immortal&lt;/em&gt; words: “We are the middle children of history, man. No purpose or place. We have no Great War, No Great Depression. Our Great War’s a spiritual war… Our Great Depression is our Lives.” Nihilism is hot today. The great success of Bojack Horseman, Rick and Morty, Hazel’s response to Augustus’ confession of the fear of oblivion and so on bear testimony to this very fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that depression and the popularity of nihilistic ideas have increased exponentially about the same time makes me wonder if they share some sort of a symbiotic relationship. If someone is depressed, the consolation that nothing really matters must help, surely? In fact, Optimistic Nihilism emphasises the notion that no one will ever remember one’s ill actions or embarrassing moments. Not all people who are depressed believe in nihilism though. But all nihilists may to some extent be sad. Everything productive that people do today is because they believe that it has meaning and life has a purpose. Nihilists dismiss this idea as nonsense. To them nothing has meaning and thus, there is no use doing anything. And the depressed do feel this way. Besides, I am sure you might have noticed the surge of suicidal and nihilistic memes’ pages on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilists do not care about anything because nothing makes sense or has any significance. And thus, nothing can make them sad. Embarrassing moments do not matter and so there is no need to overthink them. Mistakes and bad deeds do not matter and so, they can move on and do something better. Of course, life has no meaning. But we can try to give it one or at least try and be happy for the little time that we have on our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilism, however, contrary to popular opinion, is not the lack of hope. Life has no meaning. But, that does not mean that you cannot give it some purpose. Moreover, your failures do not count in anyone’s book and so, one should not be held back by them. Whether or not nihilism has been helping the depressed generation is up for debate. But, then again, there is no point in arguing. Alan Moore in &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; did very accurately say- “Why do we argue? Life is so fragile, a successful virus clinging to a speck of mud, suspended in endless nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a generation trapped in the growing realisation that they must face and solve the environmental, social and political crises of the day while lodged in the belief that nothing really matters. The same thing that causes our depression is also the source of our respite; how &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; it all matters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="millennial" /><summary type="html">If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime</title><link href="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime">&lt;p&gt;When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When determining what is preventing Arsenal from progressing as a club, it is now clear that there can no longer be a single scapegoat and accountability must be shared across different departments of the club. Wenger had an almost autocratic reign for 2 decades and it was going to take more than 1 man to replace him. Have Arsenal hired the right men?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural place to start is with Wenger’s direct successor, Unai Emery. When Arsenal announced the appointment of the Spaniard, the press release described his role as ‘head coach’, perhaps indicating that he wouldn’t have the same influence on matters such as transfers as his predecessor did and his role would be more focused towards on-pitch matters. From a results point of view, Emery improved Arsenal’s points total and league position by 7 points and 1 place respectively, although it wasn’t hard to improve on a season in which Arsenal lost a staggering 11 away league games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 2 difficult games to open the season, Arsenal had a strong first few months in terms of results, although the performances weren’t on par and stars Aaron Ramsey and Mesut Özil were noticeably less influential than they were during the Wenger years. As of yet, Emery has failed to maximise Özil’s ability. Since he moved to north London in 2013, the German world champion has regularly topped the stats for assists and chances created as he operated as the fulcrum of Wenger’s side, however there was a sharp decline in his output last season. Whilst Özil himself must shoulder most of the blame, he was sometimes bypassed by Emery’s system which saw a more direct way of chance creation. This was often through long passes to Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang and Alexandre Lacazette up front or through Bosnian wing-back Sead Kolašinac getting in behind the back-line, though his end product was often found wanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the reliance on Kolašinac as an attacking outlet caused problems at the back as Arsenal’s left side of the defence was often left exposed by his attacking charges. This contributed to a season where Arsenal conceded just as many league goals as they had the season prior, ending up with a worse defensive record than the likes of Newcastle and Everton despite Emery’s reputation as a pragmatic, defensive minded coach. After years of attractive attacking football under Wenger, it did seem as though a lot of the Arsenal fanbase were more than prepared to trade that off for a more conservative style if it yielded better results. Diego Simeone and Massimiliano Allegri were often (optimistically) touted as possible Wenger replacements, both men having league titles from the top 5 European leagues and multiple Champions League finals under their belts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was Unai Emery who eventually filled Wenger’s boots. The Spaniard came with a reputation as a Europa League specialist and as impressive as his 3 successive tournament victories with Sevilla were, they themselves are a sign of what an uninspiring appointment he was. Sevilla only had the chance to participate in the Europa League by virtue of not being good enough to get into the last 16 of the Champions League. Emery’s Sevilla won the Europa League in 2014 but finished 5th in La Liga, missing out on Champions League qualification and allowing them to win the Europa League the following year. That 2015 triumph guaranteed them qualification for the following season’s Champions League due to a new rule whereby the Europa League winners automatically qualified for Europe’s premier club competition the next season. However, Sevilla could only scrape 3rd in Group D, dropping down back into the EL and winning the competition again, beating Liverpool in the final. Emery was firmly established as a quality second tier manager, cemented further by a mediocre spell with a star-studded Paris Saint Germain team, making him a questionable choice. He was a known quantity; he wouldn’t be a disaster, but neither would he get more out of the squad than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a transfer policy that doesn’t seem to be prioritising youth, the club have signed experienced players such as Aubameyang, Sokratis, Henrikh Mkhitaryan and Stefan Lichsteiner in recent years. Arsenal are currently stagnating with little sign of improvement unless drastic changes are made. Having said all of that, the outlook on Arsenal as a whole would be vastly different if the club had managed to secure a top 4 place over a heavily criticised Maurizio Sarri-led Chelsea or Tottenham, who were distracted by their European run but still managed to stumble over the finishing line. In the end, Arsenal finished just 1 point behind Chelsea and 2 behind Tottenham. Arsenal’s failure to win any of their 4 games against Brighton, Leicester, Wolves and Crystal Palace in the final run-in proved to be the sticking point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seemingly prioritised the Europa League, Emery’s chance at salvaging the season went up in smoke as he was outclassed by Sarri and Chelsea in a humiliating defeat to the London rivals in Baku. With Unai Emery at the helm Arsenal are seemingly treading water and for that reason serious questions have to be asked about whether he is the man to take the club forward or whether a change is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of Emery’s faults, the majority of the blame has to lie within the higher echelons of the club. If we rewind a year (give or take), back to when it was announced Arsène Wenger’s tenure in north London would be coming to an end, Chief Executive Ivan Gazidis and Head of Recruitment Sven Mislintat were primed to be the figureheads of Arsenal’s rebuilding process. Gazidis made himself vocal around this time and spearheaded the search for a new manager, reportedly considering former Arsenal captain Mikel Arteta before settling on Emery. However, he departed for A.C Milan in September 2018, a puzzling decision that was soon followed by Mislintat leaving after barely 12 months in his role, having recruited the likes of Aubameyang, Matteo Guendouzi, Lucas Torreira and Bernd Leno.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal felt Gazidis was so influential that he couldn’t be replaced by one man, thus Vinai Venkatesham and Raul Sanllehi were brought in. The pair featured in a lengthy interview conducted on Arsenal’s social media platforms, a PR exercise in which they looked to assert their positions as the key directors at the club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mislintat, meanwhile, has been replaced by former Arsenal midfielder, Edu. The invincible left his role as general coordinator of the Brazilian national team following their Copa America triumph, being brought in as Arsenal’s first ever technical director with less than a month of the transfer window left. Arsenal’s window, so far, has been disappointing; pursuits of the likes of Kieran Tierney, William Saliba and Wilfried Zaha have been unsuccessful as of now. Once news broke that Arsenal reportedly had a transfer budget of just £45 million, expectations were lowered. With the season fast approaching, Edu will have to quickly re-accustom himself to his old surroundings and set off bargain hunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal owner Stan Kroenke has been extensively criticised for his frugality which, along with Arsenal’s high wage bill and their inability to maximise their assets, has led to this paltry budget. In recent years, the club has let key players such as Mesut Özil, Alexis Sanchez, Aaron Ramsey, Danny Welbeck, Jack Wilshere and Santi Cazorla run their contracts down to the final 6 months, with the latter four having left for free meaning Arsenal did not receive any money to help with finding replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite those inconveniences, the most crippling examples of poor asset management came with Arsenal’s 2 star players as they swapped Alexis Sanchez for (then 29 year old) Manchester United flop Henrikh Mkhitaryan in an attempt to extract some kind of value for the Chilean, reportedly giving Mkhitaryan a 4 year, £180,000 a week contract. Meanwhile, Arsenal retained the services of Özil for the small price of £350,000 a week over 4 years, with the club desperately trying to dump him just 18 months later. Furthermore, with big contract extensions reportedly being lined up for 30-year old Aubameyang and 28-year-old Lacazette, the club must decide whether they want to risk a situation where they again overpay players as they exit their prime. Conversely, the alternative could be to have a repeat of the Sanchez and Ramsey situations if they choose to let the attackers run down the remainder of their contracts, which expire in 2021 and 2022 respectively. It is a somewhat unenviable position for Arsenal management to be in as it must also be considered that any decision to sell either of these two fan favourites will be widely lambasted by the Arsenal faithful, not to mention the impact selling a star player would have on the team’s success. Signings such as 18-year-old forward Gabriel Martinelli represent the player profile that Arsenal should be targeting; young players with potential to improve and be sold for profit. This was the approach Arsenal took following their move to the Emirates Stadium when funds were restricted. Players such as Cesc Fabregas, Emmanuel Adebayor, Robin Van Persie and Alex Song put in years of good service before recouping high transfer fees. Arsenal are currently not in a position to contend for the Premier League or Champions League but could be in 5-8 years if they are patient and have a long-term plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a club has undergone such drastic change in such a short period of time, it is important that it has a clear vision about how to achieve its goals. When a club’s Chief Executive and Head of Recruitment leave in the same season, it makes said club look like an aimless mess. Arsenal’s transfer plans look to be uncreative to say the least. When former Borussia Dortmund scout Sven Mislintat was at the club, Arsenal signed 3 former players that he knew from his time at the German club in Aubameyang, Mkhitaryan and Sokratis. Interestingly, despite this, he was reportedly ‘dismayed’ when Unai Emery requested the signing of one of his former players, Denis Suarez, with the German leaving shortly after. There seems to be a worrying pattern here with several former Emery players such as Ever Banega, Christopher Nkunku and Thomas Meunier also being linked with a move to the Emirates. Furthermore, widely reported targets Kieran Tierney and Wilfried Zaha come with a premium added to their price due to their home grown statuses which isn’t optimal for a club with limited funds. The future looks bleak and will continue to look so until the club commits to a full scale rebuild where they prioritise the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal should be hiring a young manager that has a clear footballing philosophy with the potential to win major honours; Julian Nagelsmann and Mikel Arteta are possible options. The club must come to terms with the fact that the current squad is not close to being good enough to challenge for the league title and youngsters like Reiss Nelson, Hector Bellerin, Ainsley Maitland-Niles, Alex Iwobi, Guendouzi and Torreira should be considered the key to future success, along with any signings that have potential to grow into quality players. This is likely to be a slow process, but, due to the mess the club has gotten itself into, it is a necessary one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do Millennials Fetishise Productivity?</title><link href="/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Millennials Fetishise Productivity?" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity">&lt;p&gt;There’s always that one favorite cousin in the family, who wakes up at 5 AM to meditate and revise the previous day’s lessons, pays attention during all lectures, is up to date with social media and is going to intern at Microsoft for the coming summer. And then, there’s every other Millennial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials; who manage to sleep through eight alarms in a span of ten minutes, we are not eating healthy and we are definitely not performing well in college. But we are still quite there. Last I remember, we were thriving on self-deprivation, grinding through work and pulling off all-nighters just to submit that one assignment on time. We are most definitely not the ‘ungrateful, lazy, unambitious generation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obsession with maximising the resources at hand (case in point: time) goes beyond just textbooks on neoclassical economists’ theories of optimisation. It runs in our blood. Internalised capitalism or a fetish for productivity, call it what you want. We feel we must work hard all the time and rest should bring on a bout of guilt. We are relentless in the act of pursuing something, to the point that the fixation with pursuance takes precedence over asking ourselves what we truly want. We take ourselves too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our days are intricately scheduled because how else will we be content? The Starbucks way of life has inspired us to grind through the week to be able to enjoy the weekend. But that happy weekend never arrives. We work hard every weekend to better the next one. The drive to the movies is reserved for making calls, emails are catered to while waiting on a dinner date, backlog and future plans are left for vacations. All this with the hope of this professional development turning into essentially, what we call, a good life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anti-capitalism, social justice flag-waving, trying to embody ‘wokeness’ generation finds itself in a state of inner turmoil. Corporate lifestyles leave no time for leisure, ‘the basis of culture’ (courtesy: Josef Pieper, German philosopher). The normalisation of dissatisfaction with the existing work environment and of constant struggle is dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pervading uncertainty in our lives contributes to our anxiety. The rapid development of technology has added to the fear of being automated out, more so now than ever before, and adapting to the highly dynamic work environments in different sectors is not easy either. Moreover, with the dwindling employment rates, it is safe to say the economy has not particularly been a friend. The apprehensions cultivating from the need to pay off student debt means we cannot switch jobs in this exceedingly competitive job market. The Millennials have, therefore, resigned to working excruciatingly hard in college and grad school to avail, at least, a job with decent pay. As long as we need the money and real estate, we will learn to live with the misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just a mundane 9 AM to 5 PM job. There is also passion. Passion, because what is life without it? A reason to be fiercely alive, a way to be ferociously happy. Millennials spend a huge amount of their lives looking for a passion to offset the effect of stress. We love being unique, to do something different from the rest. So, we go the extra mile to stand out and outdo our peers. It is not called a hobby anymore, it is a skill. It is something we can have on our resume while being equally fascinating to qualify as something to post about on our social media. We attend galas, watch theatre, immerse ourselves in poetry, visit exhibitions and try extremely hard to keep up with pop culture. Even art is not for the sake of art anymore, it is something to be done; a territory waiting to be embarked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invasion of technology has wiped away the distinction between our personal and work lives in a way it had not happened for previous generations. With the convenience of always being able to send and receive emails, documenting at all times, we have brought the office back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are part of a society which has taught us that stagnancy is acceptable, but quitting is not. The romanticisation of stability has made us layout an entire plan for our life. Being the generation that has inherited soaring housing, education, and living costs, settling down becomes the ultimate goal. It is not something that has come to us as a matter of personal choice. Our childhoods were meticulously supervised. Regular homework, summer classes to learn a new hobby, timely school assessments, yada yada. Things that do not eventually lead to a bigger goal do not belong in our lives, which is why we are always expected to know what we want. What to study, where to get a job, which job after the current one. Moreover, there is a sense of finality in every decision; the first decision needs to be the right one, otherwise, everything goes downhill. Quitting jobs we do not like is a sign of ‘impulsiveness’ and ‘weakness’. We all wish to achieve stability, what we end up getting is monotonicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do life in bits and pieces. When we seek thrill, we resort to extreme sports (ah, passion). Finding a little bit of happiness to thrive on, in between life. In the fear of being left behind, we have reached so far ahead that we are blinded to all the life that’s happening outside of our work-home space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we hustle because we are uncomfortable. The discomfort arriving from the feeling of losing out on time; the same time we spend watching inspirational videos on YouTube and scrolling through Instagram feeds, constantly reiterating feelings of inadequacy and of not being ‘good enough’. And for the rest, we know the drill. The drill of the hustle. Panic, dissatisfaction, failure. Rather, the fear of failure. As a generation, we were built to not be akin to failure. We tell ourselves these marks matter the most, this social gathering I cannot miss, if I do not get this job…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The break down of the journey has vanished, there is an origin and destiny. A far fetched destiny that is so flawless, we tend to make the path longer and more and more dreadful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hrishita Sharma</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="millennial" /><summary type="html">There’s always that one favorite cousin in the family, who wakes up at 5 AM to meditate and revise the previous day’s lessons, pays attention during all lectures, is up to date with social media and is going to intern at Microsoft for the coming summer. And then, there’s every other Millennial.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Did We Let the World Down?</title><link href="/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Did We Let the World Down?" /><published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is fascinating to see how quickly we have moved from a phase of ultra-optimism about our future to, as Henry Kissinger described in his latest book, a state of disorder not seen since World War II.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990’s, it was the end of all negative ‘&lt;em&gt;isms’&lt;/em&gt;. Like the climax of a typical Bollywood movie, &lt;em&gt;Good&lt;/em&gt; was slowly prevailing over &lt;em&gt;Evil&lt;/em&gt;. The days of Communism and Colonialism were gone. Former authoritarian regimes had been gripped by democratic fever. Walls that divided us were being struck down. Half the world was developed, and the countries in the other half were accepting the ideals of globalisation, opening their economies to a more prosperous future. It finally looked that the world will be rich together. Francis Fukuyama called it the ‘End of History’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who was going to lead the world into this much-awaited future: a new, progressive-thinking generation, the millennials, for whom war was confined to history textbooks. They were already calling the world a &lt;em&gt;Global Village&lt;/em&gt; and themselves &lt;em&gt;International Citizens&lt;/em&gt;. Instead of declaring war on each other, humans started declaring war against terrorism and poverty. The chorus of the song, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GFGPSx6cPN0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Love&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” by Blue, seemed to sum up the mood of the times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the same song starts with the lines, “&lt;em&gt;It is kind of funny, how life can change. Can flip 180, in a matter of days!&lt;/em&gt;”. And so it did. Try time-travelling to the beginning of the 21st century and telling one of the many optimists of the era that come 2019, protectionism will be trumping globalisation, a major migrant crisis, ethnic conflict, and civil war will still be the call of the day, that a ‘rules-based international order’ will be a hope rather than a reality, that countries will choose conflict over co-operation, that international trade will slow as tariffs rise, and anti-establishment leaders will be coming to power across nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question: &lt;em&gt;how did everyone f&lt;/em&gt;ck up everything?* A synopsis of the Arab Spring might be a good parallel to draw. There was a social movement for political change, optimism was sky-high, some progress was made, and just when all pieces of the puzzle seemed to be coming together, due to &lt;em&gt;someone’s&lt;/em&gt; self-interest, everything went back to square one. That is where the world stands today: back to square one. It was much ado about nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we now rename the millennials as the “Lost Generation”? The ones who had the golden opportunity to firmly establish human civility but could not. Should the rest of this article be an apology letter on behalf of all millennials, for screwing it all up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming the driver for losing control of the car makes sense. Except, the millennial was never in the driver’s seat! Instead of making a scapegoat out of a whole generation (who also suffer from the same problems as the rest), it is time we ask some uncomfortable questions and come up with solutions which might disgruntle a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the millennials may not have united the world, one area where the world seems united against the millennials is denying them political participation. The global average age of an MP (Member of Parliament) is 53, and the global median age is 29. This means, there is a gap of 24 years (almost one whole generation) between the policymakers and the people affected by the policy. In other words, we live in a young world run by old ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 2.2% of MPs around the world are under 30. A staggering 76% of upper chambers of parliament have no MPs under the age of 30. The most absurd status quo in global democracy is the ‘waiting time’ between the eligible voting age and eligible participation age. On average, an eligible voter needs to wait for 5 years to become eligible for running for office. For example, in India, a person aged 18 can vote but cannot run for the lower house until he is 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more in-depth study reveals that, barring some honourable exceptions like Ecuador and Bhutan, every country, irrespective of region, has inadequate youth political representation. Remember, this is a generation whose idealistic bubble burst along with the housing bubble of 2008. Millennials caught themselves day-dreaming amid the worst economic crisis in 75 years. Coming at a time when most millennials were seeking jobs, the financial crisis ensured that they became the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019&quot;&gt;first generation to be earning less than their parents&lt;/a&gt;, despite having more qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While millennials around the world were kept busy by unemployment and underemployment, their representatives kept getting older. For instance, the average age of the US Congress has jumped from 49 in 1981 to 61 in 2014 (thankfully, the latest Congress is an exception to the trend, with the average age dropping by 10 years). Nigeria, with a median age of just 18, has never seen a leader less than 50 years old. No wonder, the potential African economic powerhouse witnessed a popular &lt;em&gt;#NotTooYoungToRun&lt;/em&gt; campaign before the 2019 elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair to our old politicians, millennials cannot expect to be politically represented if they do not turn up for voting in the first place! Globally, the average turnout amongst the youth is 30%, much lesser than the overall turnout. The theory on electoral participation suggests, with some credible research, that voting is habitual. If you vote once, you will likely vote again. As a corollary, if you do not vote, it is unlikely you will participate the next time. If millennials miss out early on, many of them will likely not participate ever. As per some estimates, the average youth turnout in mid-terms in the USA over the last 2 decades is a meagre 21.66%. Millennials in ageing societies are further dissuaded from voting, as they feel their vote ‘hardly matters’ when they form a small part of the electorate. In European elections, less than one-third of young voters participated in 2014 (in Finland, turnout was 10.4%). Japan, another ageing society, has been facing similar problems and had to lower its voting age to 16 to fight this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break these structural barriers, a few conventional and innovative ideas exist. The most common solution is reservation. Having youth quotas sounds reasonable enough (of course, subject to other socio-political considerations), given that empirical data suggests that they are politically marginalised. These quotas can also reduce inter-generational conflict in policymaking, as recent examples of ideological clashes on climate change and immigration suggest. Simply, if we are making policies for the future, the part of the population having the highest stake in it should be involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small but growing number of countries like Kenya, Egypt and Kyrgyzstan have youth quotas in their parliaments. Some of these countries also require a certain percentage of the youth getting elected through these quotas to be women. Having gender parity in youth quotas helps solve another problem in representational politics: women make up only 24% of parliamentarians worldwide. This imbalance is less pronounced amongst the young MPs, with a 60:40 ratio. Let’s not let another opportunity pass us by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other ideas around reservation include reserving seats in local elections (like Sri Lanka, Uganda and Peru) and political parties (like Vietnam, Sweden and Turkey). All forms have their benefits but progress can only be made when youth is defined as someone under the age of 30. Many countries introducing the youth quota have set the bar ‘too high’ at 35 or 40. Empirical research by the Inter-Parliamentary Union tells us that such policies do help in greater representation for people below 40, but the millennials are left out again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from reducing the eligible age to run in elections (as discussed above), another electoral reform can be the promotion of the Proportional Representation (PR) system. A PR system induces political parties to put up candidates from various backgrounds unlike a First-Past-the-Post system, where candidates are usually majoritarian, populist, and in most cases, NOT in their 20s. The share of young MPs is significantly higher in PR systems or a mix of the two systems. This is particularly useful in ageing societies where the young, aspiring politicians fail to get enough votes as their core support base is insignificant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next and a major step forward will be to check political funding in elections. In countries where political campaigning is influenced by private donations and limitless spending, the youth find themselves unable to raise such resources with little political and business contacts and self-worth (unless they are themselves heir to a political dynasty). Money cannot buy you happiness but as long as it can buy you power, do not expect youth political participation to go up. At the least, countries can set up recognized Youth Parliaments and integrate it with the national parliament (most “Youth Parliaments” that function today are currently through NGOs and private initiatives). This gives the youth a legitimate forum to express their opinions. Politics is not a science, it takes practice. Hence, promotion and mainstreaming of Youth Parliaments will prepare a larger number of youngsters with varied backgrounds for politics than any other means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be sure, age is not the only factor which makes people not want to participate politically. Education, unemployment, immigration background, marital status, and income are some other important influencing factors. However, it is the Millennial which is facing the brunt of a combination of these factors. In South Africa, where democracy is as old as a millennial, &lt;em&gt;#IWantToVoteBut&lt;/em&gt; trended hours before the polls opened, and was accompanied by reasons like limited job prospects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a millennial, I can guarantee that we are much more than a bunch of people who do not care about the larger good, as we are often made out to be. And there are positive signs around. The number of millennials in the recent US House of Representatives is up by 420%. Green parties in the EU are becoming a political force to reckon with, in large part because of rising millennial support. In Indonesia, the Indonesian Solidarity Party (PSI) has been formed to represent the millennial voice. Not bad for a country where 15 years ago, youth would shy away from public political participation as they were slowly transitioning to a democracy. Recent elections around the world have seen more MPs below 45 being elected. This article started by laughing off the 21st-century optimists, but a little hope of change from the most educated generation ever does not hurt, does it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidyarthi</name></author><category term="policy" /><category term="millennial" /><summary type="html">It is fascinating to see how quickly we have moved from a phase of ultra-optimism about our future to, as Henry Kissinger described in his latest book, a state of disorder not seen since World War II.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree</title><link href="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree" /><published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree">&lt;p&gt;The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some millennials, burdened by low-income jobs and debt obligations, living from paycheck to paycheck, are genuinely unable to finance stock purchases, the statistics tell us how even better-off millennials are straying away from investing and are preferring to save instead. Unfortunately, their risk-averse tendencies are miscalculated and are costing them precious returns, since the S&amp;amp;P 500 (adjusted for inflation and dividends reinvested) averaged a 7.92% return between 2007 to 2017, while the money market bank accounts averaged a 0.3% return during the same period. Nearly 42% of millennials are conservative investors, as opposed to 38% of GenXers and 23% of the Boomers. They are unwilling to fully embrace the financial markets, and when they do, it is only through a safer, less costly mechanism such as that of an Exchange Traded Fund (ETF), which is a type of fund that holds multiple underlying assets rather than a single stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worth noting is that their caution seems selective. Millennials’ risk-aversion appears to be more about scepticism when one realises how they have stayed away only from what they personally saw fail - the stock markets. They are still the ones responsible for inflating the crypto-market, despite its lack of intrinsic value or any ‘faith’ backing. The only argument in defense of their wild investment choice is perhaps the sophisticated distributed ledger technology used in the asset which makes the case for fostering technological innovation in the stock markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the politically correct environment, with encouragement from Hollywood, has put capitalism out of style for many. The ones still willing to invest have raised the bar over mere profitability when making an investment decision. Company ethics and transparency are a primary consideration for millennials when they choose to invest, and these additional filters reduce the overall amount invested. The rate of investment for women is in an even poorer state. The Harris Poll survey revealed that a staggering 79% of women do not invest at all, with 70% of them stating that the process is confusing to them, while 60% of them believing how they felt investing was ‘an old-white man’s game’. Clearly, the Millennials need a better education when it comes to managing their finances and getting over &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture is clear: Millennials are savers and not investors. 71% of Millennial workers are saving for retirement, and begin saving at the median age of 24, which puts the GenX’s median saving age of 30 to shame. And while they rely on the banks for saving, they try to keep away from availing any of the other services. A three year study from Scratch, an in-house unit of Viacom, as a part of the &lt;em&gt;Millennial Disruption Study&lt;/em&gt;, found that not only were banks among the ‘Most Hated’ brands, but a third of this demographic cohort believed that they’d be better off without them. This is a major concern for banks, who are now resorting to appeasement techniques. Providing special discounts on credit card bills and easing out the enrollment mechanism for loans are a few examples. This has also partially fueled the rise of fintech in the formal banking system and is encouraging the development of such technologies. Developing a system with a user-friendly interface and greater transparency by incorporation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning is an obvious solution to this issue. For instance,  a ZeroHedge survey revealed that one in three Millennials would rather invest in Bitcoin than in the stock market, simply because of the unconventional and futuristic technology involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that in traditional economics, the West had never been considered the saver’s economy, and this pattern is shifting for the better. The situation is quite akin to the rise in savings post the hyperinflationary periods in Germany after World War I, which incidentally was also a result of the psychological impact of the crisis. At the macro level, greater savings would imply lesser dependence on foreign investment. Lesser inflow of USD denominated investment in the USA implies lesser demand for the dollar. The consequent decline in appreciation of the USD is great for recovering the Current Account Deficit, which has been a primary long-term concern for the nation. But this advantage is dwarfed when growth concerns step in, as slowdowns are the projected case for the next few years. Additionally, with the rise of protectionist, right-wing governments around the globe, millennials are increasingly inclining towards what they think is socialism, which implies increased disinterest towards the financial markets. And that is a terrible prospect for growth. Hence, even though this demographic cohort has been through quite a lot at an impressionable age, they must put their concerns aside and take up a more rational approach. They have made a wise decision to save, considering the depleting ability of the burgeoning federal balance sheet to finance their post-retirement expenses. But they must learn to be comfortable with the idea of some risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riya Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><category term="millennial" /><summary type="html">The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Millennials and Meme Culture</title><link href="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials and Meme Culture" /><published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and the intent behind it shape the adaptability of art. Art can be used as a mouthpiece for personal vexation, for political propaganda, as a romantic sonnet, a rebellious speech, or even as satire. The possibilities are endless and the means to propagate them have a few malleable forms. The very beginning of art was through illustrations, statuettes, and fictional stories. As our ancestors developed their faculties, so did art. It has since then taken several forms, namely illustration, text, sculpting, acting, dance, song, cinema and now, memes. Like innumerable developments in the field of art, memes too betray a thing or two about the period to which they are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;meme&lt;/em&gt; originally comes from the Greek word ‘&lt;em&gt;mimema&lt;/em&gt;’, meaning imitation. The term was coined by Richard Dawkins in his book &lt;em&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;/em&gt; in 1976. Back then, however, the word didn’t gain a lot of recognition. A few decades later, after the emergence of the Internet, memes have surged to be an art form most characteristic of the millennials or Gen Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how a meme is a form of art, we need to understand other art forms. The key idea behind any art is to freeze or compress a particular thought or vision, a whole infinity into a finite space. It confronts our consciousness with matters that we miss out on due to activities essential to survival. If rendered well enough, it takes hold of our spirits and colonises it with whatever it wanted to. Consuming art is a conscious effort and has always been, until the arrival of memes. Memes have gone astray from this principle of art. Memes are consumed in an unstudied manner, seldom requiring cognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes are symbolic of millennials. They symbolise the hyperactive lifestyle of our generation. They betray the cultural degradation we are going through. A degradation that makes us ponder and say less and less and passively consume more and more. Our vocabulary is riddled with buzzwords which lose meaning with every passing day. Abundance has made us fall out of our practice of thinking. Time has shortened itself relatively, and we constantly seek to escape reality. On average, in a single day, a person goes through a hundred different thoughts, which are &lt;em&gt;not his own&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are losing the originality of thought, the creativity that we are born with. It is in the nature of words and of our human selves to make it difficult to say just about anything. It is momentous to experience the bittersweetness of struggling for words to express how we feel, to lose words just as they are clawing at the base of one’s throat. But with meme culture we lose that. My broken expression and my efforts give way to tagging my friends in memes and to what Buzzfeed tells me describes me and the culture of my generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The erosion of human cognition is alarming and evermore because of the manner of consumption. As mentioned before, memes are consumed quite absently not requiring a conscious effort. This leaves us unguarded, vulnerable to what the memes represent. And, as the practice of conscious thinking ebbs away, so does our consciousness towards life. We are gradually turning apathetic, normalising things that should evoke deep concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Phil Kaye tells us, “If you repeat something over and over again it loses its meaning.” The words ‘climate change’ turn into a category of memes you share, people’s mental traumas become a ‘&lt;em&gt;mood&lt;/em&gt;’ to us and bashing capitalist exploitation just something we do for the kick of feeling edgy. The outrageous loses the ability to outrage us anymore. We think we feel so much that we end up feeling very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A generation distinguished by a mental health crisis, an existential crisis, a crisis of faith, and a crisis of belief requires, above all, empathy and a careful understanding of the self to counter all our crises. But with the emergence of memes, the probability of countering them is plummeting. Memes that represent cultures and societies, on both micro and macro levels, qualify as phenomenal and path-breaking. Memes have helped us understand our kind better, they’ve taken away the alienation we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, memes have ended up normalising, without us realising, a lot that is worrisome. The apathy we feel towards ourselves and our actions is of grave concern. The manifestation of this apathy is seen in the increasing streak of nihilism in our generation. Memes are blurring the lines and lies constructed through fiction over the ages and slowly lifting our trust from certain systems of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough about the villainy of memes. Memes are an extension of postmodernism. One can’t discount all of the good that memes have brought. They’ve made us aware of things we otherwise would have remained oblivious of: culture, people, politics, ideologies, sports, our favourite celebrities. Memes are reaching to form a global culture, unparalleled by any art form before. Millennials understand diversity better than any of our previous generations. Millennials are aware of and understand the climate crisis, the water crisis and in general the humanitarian crisis breathing heavily down our necks. With the hyperactivity and the pace of things, it is difficult to take time out to be aware, to seek information, but with memes, it is no longer an arduous task. The simplicity of it is probably its greatest feature. It psychologically functions on the need to remain simple. Perhaps why we keep returning to memes in the face of rising complexities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes represent a milestone in the evolution of art, a point at which human art has transcended from a confrontation of our inner consciousness to an unguarded passive intake of what lies before one. For better or for worse, meme culture has a sinister ability to both reveal and shape the people who consume it the most, namely the Millennials.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="culture" /><category term="millennial" /><summary type="html">Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Future of Islamic Finance in the Global Economy</title><link href="/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Islamic Finance in the Global Economy" /><published>2019-07-18T00:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-18T00:10:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance">&lt;p&gt;Islamic banks do not have a long history. The first bank started its operations
in 1963 in Egypt. The main centres worldwide are in Iran, Saudi Arabia,
Malaysia, Europe, Great Britain and Switzerland. Islamic banking and religion
are correlated (shock!). However preposterous it may sound, it is a bank that
does not charge you interest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider that you want to start a manufacturing plant. A conventional bank will
provide you with the money and charge interest on it: the concept of
‘multiplying’ money. On the contrary, Islamic banks are forbidden from charging
interest. Instead, they will offer to be partners in your business and share
profits and losses. This strengthens the economy by reducing the burden from the
promoter’s shoulders and sharing it with financial institutions. In fact, their
peculiar business model helped Islamic banks largely avert the adverse impact of
the 2008 crisis. In particular, it was investment portfolios that were smaller
in size, partially deleveraged, and adherence to &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt; principles which
prevented Islamic banks from putting money in the kind of instruments that
affected their conventional competitors and helped limit the impact of the
crisis on them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A characteristic feature of Islamic banking is the role of the bank. The basic
mission is, surprisingly, not to generate profit for the bank or multiply the
income for customers but to support local development and entrepreneurship.
Everything in the Islamic banking system is made according to  &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt; law.
The things which are allowed in Islam are called ‘&lt;em&gt;halal&lt;/em&gt;’ and the things which
are forbidden are ‘&lt;em&gt;haram&lt;/em&gt;’. So, the bank is not able to invest any of their
money in the products or services forbidden in Islam. For example, in production
or trade of alcohol, nicotine, drugs, or in sectors related to pornography, the
defence sector, casino, and nightclubs. So, a customer of the Islamic bank can
be well assured that his money would not be invested in anything inconsistent
with Islam. The rule of ‘&lt;em&gt;Money makes Money&lt;/em&gt;’ does not exist in Islam because
money has no value in itself and cannot be multiplied just by rotating it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two key aspects of Islamic finance. First, it has the advantage of
being asset-backed which makes it inherently less risky than conventional
finance. Second, a prevalent risk-reward sharing arrangement exists. Apart from
this, there are some rules which guide such institutions. For example, retaining
surplus profit is unfair in this system, it is strictly related to usury -
&lt;em&gt;‘Reba’&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Reba&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important rules in the Islamic banking
system. The second rule is &lt;em&gt;gharar&lt;/em&gt;, which is related to risky or hazardous
sales and the fact that gambling is prohibited in the Islamic world. For
instance, you cannot sell the goods or services which are not yet produced. It
can be traded upon only once it comes into existence. Moreover, nothing can be
sold unless you acquire it. This essentially eliminates the risk of not
possessing the goods. All products offered in Islamic banks have to be observed
and accepted by the Council for Islamic Banks (by their lawyers and clergy). The
most popular transaction in Islamic banking is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/murabaha.asp&quot;&gt;‘Murabaha’-&lt;/a&gt; a cost-plus
financing structure where the client and the bank agree on the markup or
“cost-plus” price for the item being sold. In essence, the bank purchases the
item on behalf of the client and retains its ownership rights until the client
pays back the amount (which is the cost-plus profit on the item) to the bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic finance is growing rapidly but remains concentrated on a few
jurisdictions. Its strong growth reflects a tremendous interest on the part of
the Muslim population who have previously been underserved by the banking
industry. For the past two decades, many Islamic banks have witnessed
double-digit growth rates, surpassing their conventional peers. The industry’s
total worth, across its three main sectors (banking, capital markets, and
&lt;em&gt;Takaful&lt;/em&gt;), was estimated to be $2.05 trillion in 2017. At a mere glance, all
seems well for the Islamic banking industry. However, several potential markets
with a considerable quantum of the Muslim population remain largely unbreached,
including India and the Commonwealth of Independent States countries, made up of
the former Soviet republics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic finance holds great promise for promoting macroeconomic and financial
stability but to fulfil these promises three prerequisites really need to be
met: first, a further deepening of the standard and codes for the application of
Islamic finance and their consistent application globally. Secondly, it is
essential for &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt;-compliant money markets to be developed. This will allow
Islamic banks to manage their liquidity in a more effective way and free up
resources for them to invest in growth-enhancing projects. The Islamic financial
market is now facing increased competition due to the establishment of other
Islamic financial institutions and conventional banks who have established
Islamic subsidiaries or windows. Islamic banks also suffer from an overhang of
bad loans, and they lag behind their Western counterparts in technology and
expertise. The religious dimension adds an extra layer of problems with respect
to introducing new products that need to cater to both the Islamic law and the
needs of the general public. Lastly, there is a vital need for institutional
reforms in the areas of tax policy and capital markets development, which will
be needed for Islamic finance to fulfil its promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics consider Islamic banking similar to having a boiled ice cream-cream, it
cannot exist in real life without trickling down our confidence. For instance,
if you need a loan for purchasing a house, Islamic Banks will not charge you
interest on this money. Instead, they will buy the house for you and sell it
back to you at a higher price, demanding this amount from you in, say, 15 years,
of course, interest-free. This is a backdoor policy of interest collection. In
other words, it is interest-collection in all but name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to India, which will soon be the home to most Muslims in the
world, there has been a long-standing debate on Islamic banking. Currently, the
rules don’t allow it. Critics say it’s a bad idea because it goes against
India’s secular fabric. Is India ready for it? Will it open a Pandora’s Box?
Should we look at it through a religious prism? The opinions are sharply
divided. The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and the Banking Regulations Act,
1949 both prohibit the setting up of an Islamic banking system. Only an act of
Parliament can set up one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, growth has sparked optimism about the future of Islamic
finance. However, as competition intensifies, Islamic financial banks are still
left with work to do. Most Islamic banks need to function more efficiently along
the entire value chain, regardless of whether the strategy is aimed at entering
a niche market, at competing with traditional banks or at both. They need to
scrutinise strategic choices and focus on operational basics to grab unused
market opportunities and overcome the changing dynamics of the industry. In all,
Islamic finance is still at a nascent stage which is yet to meet its full
potential.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Islamic banks do not have a long history. The first bank started its operations in 1963 in Egypt. The main centres worldwide are in Iran, Saudi Arabia, Malaysia, Europe, Great Britain and Switzerland. Islamic banking and religion are correlated (shock!). However preposterous it may sound, it is a bank that does not charge you interest.  Consider that you want to start a manufacturing plant. A conventional bank will provide you with the money and charge interest on it: the concept of ‘multiplying’ money. On the contrary, Islamic banks are forbidden from charging interest. Instead, they will offer to be partners in your business and share profits and losses. This strengthens the economy by reducing the burden from the promoter’s shoulders and sharing it with financial institutions. In fact, their peculiar business model helped Islamic banks largely avert the adverse impact of the 2008 crisis. In particular, it was investment portfolios that were smaller in size, partially deleveraged, and adherence to Shariah principles which prevented Islamic banks from putting money in the kind of instruments that affected their conventional competitors and helped limit the impact of the crisis on them.  A characteristic feature of Islamic banking is the role of the bank. The basic mission is, surprisingly, not to generate profit for the bank or multiply the income for customers but to support local development and entrepreneurship. Everything in the Islamic banking system is made according to  Shariah law. The things which are allowed in Islam are called ‘halal’ and the things which are forbidden are ‘haram’. So, the bank is not able to invest any of their money in the products or services forbidden in Islam. For example, in production or trade of alcohol, nicotine, drugs, or in sectors related to pornography, the defence sector, casino, and nightclubs. So, a customer of the Islamic bank can be well assured that his money would not be invested in anything inconsistent with Islam. The rule of ‘Money makes Money’ does not exist in Islam because money has no value in itself and cannot be multiplied just by rotating it.  There are two key aspects of Islamic finance. First, it has the advantage of being asset-backed which makes it inherently less risky than conventional finance. Second, a prevalent risk-reward sharing arrangement exists. Apart from this, there are some rules which guide such institutions. For example, retaining surplus profit is unfair in this system, it is strictly related to usury - ‘Reba’. Reba is one of the most important rules in the Islamic banking system. The second rule is gharar, which is related to risky or hazardous sales and the fact that gambling is prohibited in the Islamic world. For instance, you cannot sell the goods or services which are not yet produced. It can be traded upon only once it comes into existence. Moreover, nothing can be sold unless you acquire it. This essentially eliminates the risk of not possessing the goods. All products offered in Islamic banks have to be observed and accepted by the Council for Islamic Banks (by their lawyers and clergy). The most popular transaction in Islamic banking is ‘Murabaha’- a cost-plus financing structure where the client and the bank agree on the markup or “cost-plus” price for the item being sold. In essence, the bank purchases the item on behalf of the client and retains its ownership rights until the client pays back the amount (which is the cost-plus profit on the item) to the bank.  Islamic finance is growing rapidly but remains concentrated on a few jurisdictions. Its strong growth reflects a tremendous interest on the part of the Muslim population who have previously been underserved by the banking industry. For the past two decades, many Islamic banks have witnessed double-digit growth rates, surpassing their conventional peers. The industry’s total worth, across its three main sectors (banking, capital markets, and Takaful), was estimated to be $2.05 trillion in 2017. At a mere glance, all seems well for the Islamic banking industry. However, several potential markets with a considerable quantum of the Muslim population remain largely unbreached, including India and the Commonwealth of Independent States countries, made up of the former Soviet republics. Islamic finance holds great promise for promoting macroeconomic and financial stability but to fulfil these promises three prerequisites really need to be met: first, a further deepening of the standard and codes for the application of Islamic finance and their consistent application globally. Secondly, it is essential for Shariah-compliant money markets to be developed. This will allow Islamic banks to manage their liquidity in a more effective way and free up resources for them to invest in growth-enhancing projects. The Islamic financial market is now facing increased competition due to the establishment of other Islamic financial institutions and conventional banks who have established Islamic subsidiaries or windows. Islamic banks also suffer from an overhang of bad loans, and they lag behind their Western counterparts in technology and expertise. The religious dimension adds an extra layer of problems with respect to introducing new products that need to cater to both the Islamic law and the needs of the general public. Lastly, there is a vital need for institutional reforms in the areas of tax policy and capital markets development, which will be needed for Islamic finance to fulfil its promise. Critics consider Islamic banking similar to having a boiled ice cream-cream, it cannot exist in real life without trickling down our confidence. For instance, if you need a loan for purchasing a house, Islamic Banks will not charge you interest on this money. Instead, they will buy the house for you and sell it back to you at a higher price, demanding this amount from you in, say, 15 years, of course, interest-free. This is a backdoor policy of interest collection. In other words, it is interest-collection in all but name. When it comes to India, which will soon be the home to most Muslims in the world, there has been a long-standing debate on Islamic banking. Currently, the rules don’t allow it. Critics say it’s a bad idea because it goes against India’s secular fabric. Is India ready for it? Will it open a Pandora’s Box? Should we look at it through a religious prism? The opinions are sharply divided. The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and the Banking Regulations Act, 1949 both prohibit the setting up of an Islamic banking system. Only an act of Parliament can set up one. In recent years, growth has sparked optimism about the future of Islamic finance. However, as competition intensifies, Islamic financial banks are still left with work to do. Most Islamic banks need to function more efficiently along the entire value chain, regardless of whether the strategy is aimed at entering a niche market, at competing with traditional banks or at both. They need to scrutinise strategic choices and focus on operational basics to grab unused market opportunities and overcome the changing dynamics of the industry. In all, Islamic finance is still at a nascent stage which is yet to meet its full potential.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Millennials, The Gentle Souls</title><link href="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials, The Gentle Souls" /><published>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls">&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely
home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and
sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting
truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our
realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media
has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to
a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to
discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our
parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is
not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions.
And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or
informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare
I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility
to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies
this chaos. What’s noble is that we care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about
how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which
tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the
fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for
themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our
fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We
face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other
in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media
activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the
moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own
endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful
is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives
up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care
about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious
millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring
about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is
nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified
moral compass we never inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply
intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the
picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess;
like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a
favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be
like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as
aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to
blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But
here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of
bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess.
We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more
courageously, also with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength,
for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our
generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces
the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of
daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together
stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian
women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot
f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is
to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to
be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you
hints at you being different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles.
We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with
each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures
humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous
selves, but finally talking about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short,
acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal
mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy
to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to
shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and
have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the
complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the
acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema
and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants.
Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of
motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials
will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it.
Let humans be human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving
through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that
solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a
meme rooted in self-deprecation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stuti Gupta</name></author><category term="millennial" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis. At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions. And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies this chaos. What’s noble is that we care. A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own endeavours. All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious millennials! ‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified moral compass we never inherited. Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation. Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess; like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess. We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more courageously, also with ourselves. The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength, for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud. Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you hints at you being different. But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles. We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous selves, but finally talking about them. The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short, acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed. In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants. Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it. Let humans be human. They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a meme rooted in self-deprecation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game</title><link href="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game" /><published>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</updated><id>/On-Codes-and-Ciphers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers">&lt;p&gt;“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will
miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and
you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are
and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen.
You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a1/Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer
scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War
II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The
Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the
Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the
Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s
original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German
movements during the War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/_dchris/19612913884&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//enigma-machine.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was
broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system
has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists
like Shamir and Bonhe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the
history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous
cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to
communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the
authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is
replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a
similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets
replaced by H and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://s4scoding.com/images/caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of
steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of
cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information,
using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the
very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of
people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone
to crack it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher.
A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages
or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication
even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time, 
being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the
throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code.
The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code,
is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you
guessed it, Samuel Morse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b5/International_Morse_Code.svg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//International_Morse_Code.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic
messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the
letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and
it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has
been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps;
tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed
it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if
masked properly that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements
in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most
talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have
talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that
age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the
Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher
replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous author David Kahn notes in his book &lt;em&gt;The Codebreakers&lt;/em&gt; that history
has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many
mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher
used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no
dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher
system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to
replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher)
to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without
the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human
comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no
matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused
to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an
inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to
Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule
the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest
concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex
and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract
concepts on the quantum nature of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting
up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we
are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build
and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only
for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is
truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be
brought down, thanks to humans themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of
the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into
effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen. You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - The Imitation Game, 2014. Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German movements during the War. The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists like Shamir and Bonhe. The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets replaced by H and so on. One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information, using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone to crack it. Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher. A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time,  being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code. The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code, is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you guessed it, Samuel Morse. For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps; tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if masked properly that is. Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text. The famous author David Kahn notes in his book The Codebreakers that history has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher) to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without the key. However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract concepts on the quantum nature of information. Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be brought down, thanks to humans themselves. Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into effect.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Wandering Wonder</title><link href="/The-Wandering-Wondar" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wandering Wonder" /><published>2019-07-12T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Wandering-Wondar</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Wandering-Wondar">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wandered off while sitting down―all in your head, all out of
wonder? Ever imagined multiple lives for yourself? Ever wondered how there are a
gazillion lives that are all affected by the interconnectedness of everything?
Has there been a time when you have wanted to exchange places, or be at multiple
places, living multiple lives at the same time? If you have, my friend, we are
aboard the same boat and I hope your frustration wards off just as soon as I
wish for mine to leave. Or maybe, just maybe, better yet, this wonder is what
keeps us afloat, keeps us from dreading the worst. We know there’s a lot that
exists, we know we may never know about it all, and maybe it’s this wonder that
keeps us excited to be alive. I may be rationalising here and I promise to get
rid of this defence mechanism as soon as I find a better one. But language is
funny in more ways than not. We feel liberated using it, and at the same time,
there is also a strange kind of entrapment. We cannot communicate without words,
and yet are words sufficient to voice everything we feel?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I did not know that the frustration of being limited to one
experience was a common dilemma, I had no idea there was even a name for it,
albeit none that one can use in their English essay. Onism, and we shall all
thank John Koenig for the same, is a word that tries to explain the frustration
of being stuck in just one body, that inhabits only one place at a time. It is
understood to be like standing in front of the departures screen at an airport,
flickering over with strange place names like other people’s passwords, each
representing one more thing you will never get to see before you die―and all
because, as the arrow on the map helpfully points out, you are here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can imagine how much more rich and satisfying it would be to have multiple
bodies, not just one―so one could escape themselves for a while and live on the
other side of the planet. Or take a step back and see themselves from someone
else’s point of view, in full context with the rest of the world, with their
face the right way around, their eyes un-flattened, just as vivid as one appears
to other people. It would be like knowing yourself like others do, judging our
own quirks but with much less self-loathing, just seeing them as unique factions
of our being. However absurd the idea may seem; it would bring so much more
clarity and joy. Of course, this may be coming from a place of bias, with myself
being someone who has felt this for a long time and only just recently found out
about the word that expresses it so well on an unanticipated night. A friend
introduced me to &lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt; and that’s when I met with
the genius work of John Koenig. This man is on a mission to fill the gaps
incurred in the English language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His dictionary includes words that describe emotions that one may feel but can’t
put into motion through speech or writing, it includes questioning the
limitations that language puts on us. One has to acknowledge that our bodies and
minds are bombarded with so many complex sensations throughout the day that it
would be impossible to assign a name to each. Feelings are a product of any
stimulation one can procure―the lack of it―a phenomenon in itself. Even though
&lt;em&gt;Merriam&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oxford&lt;/em&gt; haven’t made it yet, Koenig with his popular Tumblr Blog
and subsequent YouTube Channel and website is paving the way. &lt;em&gt;TDOBS&lt;/em&gt; is
intriguing because it presents a word that is obscure or completely invented and
then connects it to a stylised video to further enhance the definition of that
word. As Koenig indicates on his website, “Each original definition aims to fill
a hole in the language—to give a name to emotions we all might experience but
don’t yet have a word for.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koenig has said multiple times that the blog began with his desire to write
poems. He made up words to help frame the poems better. He insists that the
inception began at a dark time in his life. In his Ted Talk, Koenig recollects
the time when his own melancholy triggered him to compose the dictionary, and
how people later came up to him to thank him for his work. The graphic
designer/editor/voice performer speaks of how his sombreness gave him a penchant
for words. One should be aware of the fact that he makes sure that all his words
have etymological significance. That they all have sense and reason behind them.
&lt;em&gt;TDOBS&lt;/em&gt; gained popularity with the wilfulness of Twitter, someone tweeted out 23
of the words and then, boom! The crowd came rushing, in shared understanding of
the un-worded emotions. Words such as ‘sonder’ have made it to the bigwigs, with
companies using them to name products. A very prominent bar in New York has
named its drinks after the 23 popularised words; artists too have now started
naming their paintings with the help of these words, so as to express themselves
better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why out of every interesting word this man has invented, I
longed to make this word the winter sun―Onism. Onism is a portmanteau of monism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;onanism. In philosophy, monism is the view that a variety of things can be
explained in terms of a single reality or substance, or a distinct source. Onism
can be seen as a kind of monism, because one’s life is indeed limited to a
single reality, by virtue of being restricted to a single body, but something is
clearly missing. Meanwhile, onanism is another word for masturbation or
self-pleasure, transfixed inside our own menagerie of fantasies like going on a
sightseeing tour of our own apartment—frustrating in its closed-off familiarity.
Again, something is missing. What makes it even more special is that Onism was
born while Koenig was travelling in an airplane, across 6 countries, in the
process of moving places and struggling with the idea of a new life. To me, this
brings in the idea more so than anything else. It makes me think of Remedial
Chaos Theory: there are lots of me in other timelines who - collectively - have
done everything I have not. It is the awareness of everything you are giving up,
to be where you are right now. It is questioning the excuses we have invented to
explain why so much of our life belongs in the background. Koenig very well
expresses this in how he words his video transcripts- “We sketch monsters on the
map because we find their presence comforting. They guard the edges of the
abyss, and force us to look away; so, we can live comfortably in the Known
World, at least for a little while.” An analogy I came across may help you
visualise it better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we enter primary school, we have heard all about the planets in our
Solar System. As we grow older, we learn that the Solar System is just a speck
in the Milky Way Galaxy, and that there are thousands of galaxies out there,
peppering our universe with their glow and might. The celestial mysteries that
beckon to us are countless, but we resign ourselves to the fact that they are
limited to computer screens and observatories. We accept the fact that the stars
are too far away to take seriously, that Jupiter has a turbulent red spot over
twice the size of our planet, that the moon will always be a distant relative.
So instead, we look around at how far the horizon is and how hauntingly it
encircles us. That scircle is just a fleck of life, dotted on the surface of the
earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may think about the number of adventures we could be having, the divergent
memories we could be creating, the new people we could be meeting—within the
ring that encircles us. We have only one body, although our minds would surely
wish we had ten. The world becomes even more intriguing once we extricate
ourselves from that ring- there are mountains and slopes waiting to be climbed,
fields of snow waiting to be shaped into spheres and thrown, peaks that are
craving to be mounted, oceans with shadowy depths, beautiful creatures, and fish
that we still do not know exist. There are villages waiting to be visited, whose
culture is unlike anything we have ever witnessed. There are waterfalls,
rainforests, and glaciers still unknown to the human mind, foreign sunshine that
is waiting to infuse itself into our bloodstreams, caves that scream adrenaline
and excitement. There are airplanes, trains, cars, bicycles, and our own two
feet. But something stops us, limitations confine us. The lack of time, money,
and flexibility in our schedules. The fact that the seconds keep ticking by,
that so much of our time goes in useless endeavours we will never remember. And
the reality that we cannot be in two places at once. The fact that our two feet
are rooted in the same place, that there are millions of places we could be in
right now—but we are always forced to choose one. That when we are at the
airport, we have only one destination to go to—while the other cities flicker
like candlelight on a windy afternoon. When we drive a car, there are thousands
of alternate routes we could take. And yet, we do not—because we believe that we
are not meant to deviate from our predetermined route. In other words, we are
unknowingly ensnared. Onism is the frustration of knowing how little of the
universe we will be able to appreciate; the impatience of seeing the stars
twinkling at night, as if mocking our inability to escape the ground. But
somehow, it only makes us dream more. Our inability to traverse the Solar System
makes us imagine; it makes us envisage a universe that is probably more
beautiful and romantic than what it really is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may construe Onism as something that resembles sadness or sorrow, or one may
call it the Chi Force and what keeps us alive, but whatever it may be thought of
as- we are all affected by it, however it may come. I’d really encourage people
to go about looking for &lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt; and open their minds
to new words that express age-old emotions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the chance, I’d definitely like to end with a line from Koenig’s script- &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But if someone were to ask you on your Deathbed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it was like to live here on Earth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the only honest answer would be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know, I passed through it once, but I’ve never really been there.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Have you ever wandered off while sitting down―all in your head, all out of wonder? Ever imagined multiple lives for yourself? Ever wondered how there are a gazillion lives that are all affected by the interconnectedness of everything? Has there been a time when you have wanted to exchange places, or be at multiple places, living multiple lives at the same time? If you have, my friend, we are aboard the same boat and I hope your frustration wards off just as soon as I wish for mine to leave. Or maybe, just maybe, better yet, this wonder is what keeps us afloat, keeps us from dreading the worst. We know there’s a lot that exists, we know we may never know about it all, and maybe it’s this wonder that keeps us excited to be alive. I may be rationalising here and I promise to get rid of this defence mechanism as soon as I find a better one. But language is funny in more ways than not. We feel liberated using it, and at the same time, there is also a strange kind of entrapment. We cannot communicate without words, and yet are words sufficient to voice everything we feel? Personally, I did not know that the frustration of being limited to one experience was a common dilemma, I had no idea there was even a name for it, albeit none that one can use in their English essay. Onism, and we shall all thank John Koenig for the same, is a word that tries to explain the frustration of being stuck in just one body, that inhabits only one place at a time. It is understood to be like standing in front of the departures screen at an airport, flickering over with strange place names like other people’s passwords, each representing one more thing you will never get to see before you die―and all because, as the arrow on the map helpfully points out, you are here. One can imagine how much more rich and satisfying it would be to have multiple bodies, not just one―so one could escape themselves for a while and live on the other side of the planet. Or take a step back and see themselves from someone else’s point of view, in full context with the rest of the world, with their face the right way around, their eyes un-flattened, just as vivid as one appears to other people. It would be like knowing yourself like others do, judging our own quirks but with much less self-loathing, just seeing them as unique factions of our being. However absurd the idea may seem; it would bring so much more clarity and joy. Of course, this may be coming from a place of bias, with myself being someone who has felt this for a long time and only just recently found out about the word that expresses it so well on an unanticipated night. A friend introduced me to The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows and that’s when I met with the genius work of John Koenig. This man is on a mission to fill the gaps incurred in the English language. His dictionary includes words that describe emotions that one may feel but can’t put into motion through speech or writing, it includes questioning the limitations that language puts on us. One has to acknowledge that our bodies and minds are bombarded with so many complex sensations throughout the day that it would be impossible to assign a name to each. Feelings are a product of any stimulation one can procure―the lack of it―a phenomenon in itself. Even though Merriam and Oxford haven’t made it yet, Koenig with his popular Tumblr Blog and subsequent YouTube Channel and website is paving the way. TDOBS is intriguing because it presents a word that is obscure or completely invented and then connects it to a stylised video to further enhance the definition of that word. As Koenig indicates on his website, “Each original definition aims to fill a hole in the language—to give a name to emotions we all might experience but don’t yet have a word for.” Koenig has said multiple times that the blog began with his desire to write poems. He made up words to help frame the poems better. He insists that the inception began at a dark time in his life. In his Ted Talk, Koenig recollects the time when his own melancholy triggered him to compose the dictionary, and how people later came up to him to thank him for his work. The graphic designer/editor/voice performer speaks of how his sombreness gave him a penchant for words. One should be aware of the fact that he makes sure that all his words have etymological significance. That they all have sense and reason behind them. TDOBS gained popularity with the wilfulness of Twitter, someone tweeted out 23 of the words and then, boom! The crowd came rushing, in shared understanding of the un-worded emotions. Words such as ‘sonder’ have made it to the bigwigs, with companies using them to name products. A very prominent bar in New York has named its drinks after the 23 popularised words; artists too have now started naming their paintings with the help of these words, so as to express themselves better. One might wonder why out of every interesting word this man has invented, I longed to make this word the winter sun―Onism. Onism is a portmanteau of monism onanism. In philosophy, monism is the view that a variety of things can be explained in terms of a single reality or substance, or a distinct source. Onism can be seen as a kind of monism, because one’s life is indeed limited to a single reality, by virtue of being restricted to a single body, but something is clearly missing. Meanwhile, onanism is another word for masturbation or self-pleasure, transfixed inside our own menagerie of fantasies like going on a sightseeing tour of our own apartment—frustrating in its closed-off familiarity. Again, something is missing. What makes it even more special is that Onism was born while Koenig was travelling in an airplane, across 6 countries, in the process of moving places and struggling with the idea of a new life. To me, this brings in the idea more so than anything else. It makes me think of Remedial Chaos Theory: there are lots of me in other timelines who - collectively - have done everything I have not. It is the awareness of everything you are giving up, to be where you are right now. It is questioning the excuses we have invented to explain why so much of our life belongs in the background. Koenig very well expresses this in how he words his video transcripts- “We sketch monsters on the map because we find their presence comforting. They guard the edges of the abyss, and force us to look away; so, we can live comfortably in the Known World, at least for a little while.” An analogy I came across may help you visualise it better. By the time we enter primary school, we have heard all about the planets in our Solar System. As we grow older, we learn that the Solar System is just a speck in the Milky Way Galaxy, and that there are thousands of galaxies out there, peppering our universe with their glow and might. The celestial mysteries that beckon to us are countless, but we resign ourselves to the fact that they are limited to computer screens and observatories. We accept the fact that the stars are too far away to take seriously, that Jupiter has a turbulent red spot over twice the size of our planet, that the moon will always be a distant relative. So instead, we look around at how far the horizon is and how hauntingly it encircles us. That scircle is just a fleck of life, dotted on the surface of the earth. We may think about the number of adventures we could be having, the divergent memories we could be creating, the new people we could be meeting—within the ring that encircles us. We have only one body, although our minds would surely wish we had ten. The world becomes even more intriguing once we extricate ourselves from that ring- there are mountains and slopes waiting to be climbed, fields of snow waiting to be shaped into spheres and thrown, peaks that are craving to be mounted, oceans with shadowy depths, beautiful creatures, and fish that we still do not know exist. There are villages waiting to be visited, whose culture is unlike anything we have ever witnessed. There are waterfalls, rainforests, and glaciers still unknown to the human mind, foreign sunshine that is waiting to infuse itself into our bloodstreams, caves that scream adrenaline and excitement. There are airplanes, trains, cars, bicycles, and our own two feet. But something stops us, limitations confine us. The lack of time, money, and flexibility in our schedules. The fact that the seconds keep ticking by, that so much of our time goes in useless endeavours we will never remember. And the reality that we cannot be in two places at once. The fact that our two feet are rooted in the same place, that there are millions of places we could be in right now—but we are always forced to choose one. That when we are at the airport, we have only one destination to go to—while the other cities flicker like candlelight on a windy afternoon. When we drive a car, there are thousands of alternate routes we could take. And yet, we do not—because we believe that we are not meant to deviate from our predetermined route. In other words, we are unknowingly ensnared. Onism is the frustration of knowing how little of the universe we will be able to appreciate; the impatience of seeing the stars twinkling at night, as if mocking our inability to escape the ground. But somehow, it only makes us dream more. Our inability to traverse the Solar System makes us imagine; it makes us envisage a universe that is probably more beautiful and romantic than what it really is.  One may construe Onism as something that resembles sadness or sorrow, or one may call it the Chi Force and what keeps us alive, but whatever it may be thought of as- we are all affected by it, however it may come. I’d really encourage people to go about looking for The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows and open their minds to new words that express age-old emotions.  Given the chance, I’d definitely like to end with a line from Koenig’s script-  “But if someone were to ask you on your Deathbed What it was like to live here on Earth Perhaps the only honest answer would be, I don’t know, I passed through it once, but I’ve never really been there.”</summary></entry></feed>