<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-02T15:28:56+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hong Kong Protests: Understanding the Deeper Rifts Beneath the Masked Revolution</title><link href="/Hong-Kong-Protests" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hong Kong Protests: Understanding the Deeper Rifts Beneath the Masked Revolution" /><published>2019-08-31T02:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-31T02:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Hong-Kong-Protests</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Hong-Kong-Protests">&lt;p&gt;Since June 2019, Hong Kong has witnessed hundreds and thousands of people march
onto streets to fight for their depleting autonomy, and for their chance at true
democracy. The rallies have sustained for over twelve weeks, despite masked
demonstrations veering into violence with the police using tear gas and water
cannons to disperse the protesters. On July 1, the protesters stormed and
vandalised the HK Legislative Council to commemorate HK’s handover to China.
From 9 to 12 July, millions protested for the suspension of the extradition law
amendments. On August 6, a city-wide transportation shut down took place. On
August 12 and 13, the protesters took over the country’s airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are only some of the protests that have stood out in the past few months,
as Hong Kong has tried to reclaim its status of a ‘special administrative
region’ to protect its own independence, and the humanitarian rights and
liberties that its citizens enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The historical relationship between China and Hong Kong&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a GDP of over 34,000 crore USD, Hong Kong has fast grown into one of the
largest financial hubs of the world. But for over 150 years, HK was a British
colony. A part of it was ceded to the UK  in 1842 and later, China decided to
lease the rest of it, often termed as the ‘New Territories’, to the UK for 99
years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy began flourishing in the 1950s with HK emerging as a major port and
later, as a manufacturing powerhouse. With the deadline of the lease approaching
fast, the communist Chinese government began arguing for a complete return of
the HK territories to China. After significant deliberation, in 1997, the
territory on China’s southern coast gained independence from British imperial
rule and was “handed back” to China under a policy termed as ‘one country, two
systems.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, Hong Kong enjoyed a special federal status that allowed the region
its own system of government, laws and police force. All these clauses were
contained in a document called ‘Basic Rule’ which permitted for the existence
and implementation of a mini-constitution for the governance of HK. The Basic
Rule helped Hong Kong become a part of China while empowering HK citizens with
many liberties denied to citizens on the mainland, including free speech,
unrestricted internet access and the right to free assembly. It was agreed upon
by all parties that the system shall stay in place until at least 2047.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why are the “Hong Kongers” protesting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 Hong Kong anti-extradition bill protests started with a move by China
to propose amendments to HK’s extradition law that would allow case-by-case
extraditions to countries that lack formal extradition treaties with Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, one of the countries that lack formal extradition treaties with HK was
the People’s Republic of China itself, known for stifling and imprisoning any
dissenting citizens. Many critics have argued that the amendments were intended
as a powerful tool to detain Hong Kongers who spoke against the Chinese regime
or advocated pro-democracy sentiments. The amendments would have also applied
retroactively, which means that the hundreds of people who had fallen under the
scrutiny of China in the past for any crime would risk facing trial in the
mainland. One HK lawmaker called the amended bill- “dragnet over all of Hong
Kong.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After smaller protests that started in April and May, HK witnessed its first
gigantic protest on 9 June with over a million people peacefully taking to the
streets. On 12 June, more than two million residents of Hong Kong swarmed HK’s
legislature to delay the procedures that would’ve hastened the implementation of
the amendments. These protests were met with violence, with police firing tear
gas, rubber bullets and beanbags at the crowds. After these massive protests,
chief executive Lam was forced to “indefinitely suspend” the amendments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The underlying fractures in HK’s administration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Retake Hong Kong, Revolution of Our Times”: This is the slogan that has defined
this movement, which started from an extradition bill but has now expanded to
five demands. Before deeper examination of these demands, we must look at the
glaring loopholes in HK’s current system of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, a large portion of HK’s executive powers rest with its chief executive,
who, according to the Basic Rule, should be appointed on the basis of elections
or local consultations. But this process has been entirely taken over by China.
Currently the chief executive, Carrie Lam, who serves a five-year term, is
appointed by a 1200-member election committee, that is replete with
Beijing-loyalists. Thus, the representative of HK’s executive powers is often a
loyalist of China. This constitutes for “Hong Kong’s sham democracy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, there is a great degree of alienation felt by young Hong Kongers from
their Chinese regime. Surveys from the University of Hong Kong show that most
people identify themselves as “Hong Kongers” - only 11% would call themselves
“Chinese” - and 71% of people say they do not feel proud about being Chinese
citizens. Cultural differences that stem from their colonial past further
accentuate this alienation. And finally, China’s attempts to chip away their
autonomy and bring them under direct Chinese rule, have led to recurrent
protests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the residents of HK have five major demands. They, firstly, want the
extradition bill to be suspended. Secondly, they have demanded that the
government retract the word “riot” to denote this movement. Next, they want the
release of all those who have been arrested over the past few months in
association with these protests. Demand number four calls on the government to
convene a serious, independent inquiry into the Hong Kong police and their
tactics. Lastly, they want universal adult franchise, so that they can reclaim
their government and their rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What lies ahead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road ahead is neither safe for HK protesters nor easy for China. The
months-long protests in Hong Kong could usually be expected to invite a severe
crackdown from China, similar to the controversial 1989 Tiananmen Square
massacre. But the situation is significantly different now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong is a large financial capital of the world. The HK stock market is
bigger than that of London. Its citizens enjoy the freedom of expression on
several global media platforms, unlike other Chinese citizens. Any crackdown on
Hong Kong would cause heavy injury to the Chinese economy and the region’s
investments and trade relations may be tarnished for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing trade war between the US and China further complicates the
situation. Supporters from across the world have emerged in favour of the HK
protests against an authoritarian regime. The US President Donald Trump has also
hinted that no repeats of the 1989 Massacre will be tolerated, especially if
China wants to contain the trade war. Thus, with such vested interests, its
reputation as an emerging superpower is also at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Chinese government and police will continue to try to break and
dissolve the movement, perhaps, it is time for China to move the battle from the
streets to a round-table, where no one has to stifle their voices with a mask. A
negotiation between the protesters and the current HK and Chinese government is
clearly the best solution for all parties involved, so that the citizens’
freedoms can be safeguarded and HK’s status be regained, without tampering with
the Chinese economy or global status.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Since June 2019, Hong Kong has witnessed hundreds and thousands of people march onto streets to fight for their depleting autonomy, and for their chance at true democracy. The rallies have sustained for over twelve weeks, despite masked demonstrations veering into violence with the police using tear gas and water cannons to disperse the protesters. On July 1, the protesters stormed and vandalised the HK Legislative Council to commemorate HK’s handover to China. From 9 to 12 July, millions protested for the suspension of the extradition law amendments. On August 6, a city-wide transportation shut down took place. On August 12 and 13, the protesters took over the country’s airport. These are only some of the protests that have stood out in the past few months, as Hong Kong has tried to reclaim its status of a ‘special administrative region’ to protect its own independence, and the humanitarian rights and liberties that its citizens enjoy. The historical relationship between China and Hong Kong With a GDP of over 34,000 crore USD, Hong Kong has fast grown into one of the largest financial hubs of the world. But for over 150 years, HK was a British colony. A part of it was ceded to the UK  in 1842 and later, China decided to lease the rest of it, often termed as the ‘New Territories’, to the UK for 99 years. The economy began flourishing in the 1950s with HK emerging as a major port and later, as a manufacturing powerhouse. With the deadline of the lease approaching fast, the communist Chinese government began arguing for a complete return of the HK territories to China. After significant deliberation, in 1997, the territory on China’s southern coast gained independence from British imperial rule and was “handed back” to China under a policy termed as ‘one country, two systems.’ Essentially, Hong Kong enjoyed a special federal status that allowed the region its own system of government, laws and police force. All these clauses were contained in a document called ‘Basic Rule’ which permitted for the existence and implementation of a mini-constitution for the governance of HK. The Basic Rule helped Hong Kong become a part of China while empowering HK citizens with many liberties denied to citizens on the mainland, including free speech, unrestricted internet access and the right to free assembly. It was agreed upon by all parties that the system shall stay in place until at least 2047. Why are the “Hong Kongers” protesting? The 2019 Hong Kong anti-extradition bill protests started with a move by China to propose amendments to HK’s extradition law that would allow case-by-case extraditions to countries that lack formal extradition treaties with Hong Kong. Notably, one of the countries that lack formal extradition treaties with HK was the People’s Republic of China itself, known for stifling and imprisoning any dissenting citizens. Many critics have argued that the amendments were intended as a powerful tool to detain Hong Kongers who spoke against the Chinese regime or advocated pro-democracy sentiments. The amendments would have also applied retroactively, which means that the hundreds of people who had fallen under the scrutiny of China in the past for any crime would risk facing trial in the mainland. One HK lawmaker called the amended bill- “dragnet over all of Hong Kong.” After smaller protests that started in April and May, HK witnessed its first gigantic protest on 9 June with over a million people peacefully taking to the streets. On 12 June, more than two million residents of Hong Kong swarmed HK’s legislature to delay the procedures that would’ve hastened the implementation of the amendments. These protests were met with violence, with police firing tear gas, rubber bullets and beanbags at the crowds. After these massive protests, chief executive Lam was forced to “indefinitely suspend” the amendments. The underlying fractures in HK’s administration “Retake Hong Kong, Revolution of Our Times”: This is the slogan that has defined this movement, which started from an extradition bill but has now expanded to five demands. Before deeper examination of these demands, we must look at the glaring loopholes in HK’s current system of governance. Firstly, a large portion of HK’s executive powers rest with its chief executive, who, according to the Basic Rule, should be appointed on the basis of elections or local consultations. But this process has been entirely taken over by China. Currently the chief executive, Carrie Lam, who serves a five-year term, is appointed by a 1200-member election committee, that is replete with Beijing-loyalists. Thus, the representative of HK’s executive powers is often a loyalist of China. This constitutes for “Hong Kong’s sham democracy.” Further, there is a great degree of alienation felt by young Hong Kongers from their Chinese regime. Surveys from the University of Hong Kong show that most people identify themselves as “Hong Kongers” - only 11% would call themselves “Chinese” - and 71% of people say they do not feel proud about being Chinese citizens. Cultural differences that stem from their colonial past further accentuate this alienation. And finally, China’s attempts to chip away their autonomy and bring them under direct Chinese rule, have led to recurrent protests. Currently, the residents of HK have five major demands. They, firstly, want the extradition bill to be suspended. Secondly, they have demanded that the government retract the word “riot” to denote this movement. Next, they want the release of all those who have been arrested over the past few months in association with these protests. Demand number four calls on the government to convene a serious, independent inquiry into the Hong Kong police and their tactics. Lastly, they want universal adult franchise, so that they can reclaim their government and their rights. What lies ahead? The road ahead is neither safe for HK protesters nor easy for China. The months-long protests in Hong Kong could usually be expected to invite a severe crackdown from China, similar to the controversial 1989 Tiananmen Square massacre. But the situation is significantly different now. Hong Kong is a large financial capital of the world. The HK stock market is bigger than that of London. Its citizens enjoy the freedom of expression on several global media platforms, unlike other Chinese citizens. Any crackdown on Hong Kong would cause heavy injury to the Chinese economy and the region’s investments and trade relations may be tarnished for years to come. The ongoing trade war between the US and China further complicates the situation. Supporters from across the world have emerged in favour of the HK protests against an authoritarian regime. The US President Donald Trump has also hinted that no repeats of the 1989 Massacre will be tolerated, especially if China wants to contain the trade war. Thus, with such vested interests, its reputation as an emerging superpower is also at stake. Although the Chinese government and police will continue to try to break and dissolve the movement, perhaps, it is time for China to move the battle from the streets to a round-table, where no one has to stifle their voices with a mask. A negotiation between the protesters and the current HK and Chinese government is clearly the best solution for all parties involved, so that the citizens’ freedoms can be safeguarded and HK’s status be regained, without tampering with the Chinese economy or global status.    </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">51.9% to 48.1%- UK’s Super-close Vote to Leave: Legitimate or Not?</title><link href="/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="51.9% to 48.1%- UK’s Super-close Vote to Leave: Legitimate or Not?" /><published>2019-08-31T01:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-31T01:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave</id><content type="html" xml:base="/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave">&lt;p&gt;It was preposterous to observe the twist of events when back in the 2009 data
speech, the former Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, David Cameron,
described internet of things to be an ‘amazing pollinator’ that ‘turns lovely
fights into mass campaigns; transforms moans into movements; excites the
attention of hundreds, thousands, millions of people and stirs them into
action.’ This same power became a major concern for him when millions of people
were triggered, provoked and mobilized through this very medium to vote for
Brexit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a company that has worked with hacked material, this is a company that
will send out videos of people being murdered to intimidate voters, this is a
company that goes out and tries to illicitly acquire live internet browsing data
of everyone in an entire country.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ex-Cambridge Analytica employee, whistle-blower Christopher Wylie, made this
statement which only goes on to portray the tip of the iceberg which revolved
around the Brexit referendum and Cambridge Analytica’s utter ignorance for the
law. Cambridge Analytica Ltd. (CA) was a data analysis and mining entity that
had played an extremely controversial part in the &lt;em&gt;Leave European Union&lt;/em&gt;
campaign. They assisted the official &lt;em&gt;Vote Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign and skillfully found
a way to circumvent the campaign funding laws. Leaked documents disclosed that
the &lt;em&gt;Vote Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign, the official pro-Brexit group, headed by Michael Gove
and Boris Johnson, paid a hefty 625,000 pounds to a Canadian data organisation
named Aggregate IQ (AIQ). In contrast to the two companies’ statements of
denying a coordination during the referendum, Wylie testified that CA and AIQ
shared data with one another on a persistent basis. “You can’t have targeting
software that doesn’t access the database. Cambridge Analytica would have a
database and AIQ would access that database, otherwise the software wouldn’t
work,” Wylie said. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher Wylie, the whistle-blower who worked alongside Cambridge University
researcher Aleksandr Kogan to reap the data for Cambridge Analytica, told the
Observer that they had exploited Facebook to acquire millions of people’s
profiles. The unified intention of the company was to form a model which could
help them manipulate the targeted audience. The New York Times and UK-based
Observer reported that more than 50 million Facebook users had their data
harvested by Cambridge Analytica which has been called as the social media
platform’s largest data breach till date. It was disclosed that they used the
data to target users with customised political advertisements to further Trump’s
presidential bid and the pro-Brexit drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British journalist Carole Cadwalladr, in her Ted talk, highlights the specific
case of Ebbw Vale. Ebbw Vale, a small town in South Wales, had one of the cities
with the highest percentage of &lt;em&gt;leave&lt;/em&gt; votes (62%-38%) despite the fact that it
had several regeneration projects funded by the EU. However, much to the
surprise, the residents were of the view that the European Union had done
nothing for them. “Take back control”- one of the most widely used slogans in
the campaign backed this perspective, and this fire was further fuelled by the
supposed problem of refugees and immigrants contrary to which statistics showed
that the immigration rates in Ebbw were one of the lowest. All of these facts
didn’t add up together and did not provide the whole picture. Eventually,
everything that could be found out was insufficient, because everything took
place in ‘black boxes’- on Facebook, Google, YouTube. People testified that they
saw ads on Facebook like – “76m population of Turkey to join the EU”, and other
such statements, which lacked credibility. Such advertisements, feed, and posts
were shown to a specifically targeted tiny silver of persuadable people to tilt
their votes towards &lt;em&gt;Leave&lt;/em&gt;. Facebook, along with Cambridge Analytica was
responsible for leaking data from people’s profiles to the groups like Vote
Leave who in turn, illegally targeted them. The campaign had sabotaged the
opposition with more vociferous and aggressive supporters on all the social
media handles leading to the uprising of &lt;em&gt;leave&lt;/em&gt; supporters at the grassroot
level. They outnumbered and dominated platforms like Twitter, Instagram and
Facebook influencing and manipulating ambivalent voters who were made mere
puppets in their hands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On platforms like Twitter it was seen that people, not necessarily knowledgeable
about politics, were able to make huge decisions for the future of a country
based on hashtags and memes they have seen online. During the time leading up to
the referendum in 2016, the number of people supporting the &lt;em&gt;Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign
outnumbered the &lt;em&gt;Remain&lt;/em&gt; campaign on Twitter by 7 to 1 and the most used
hashtags were #Brexit, #Beleave and #VoteLeave.  When it comes to this
serious political issue, this could be potentially damaging as users are likely
to be influenced by whichever message appears most often or most prominent
rather than necessarily searching for the true facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media has changed the face of political campaigning and will inevitably
continue doing so playing an indispensable role in the future elections to come
all across the globe. It has been a commonplace to hypothesize that social media
is a vital medium for distorted facts which restricts citizens to mere echo
cubicles. The upside is that we get to participate in it like never before, we
comment, we share, we tweet but unfortunately, our favourite social media
networks have also slaughtered the essence of fair elections by distorting and
shaping the outcomes according to their whims and fancies. It has evolved as a
mighty force to aid the reach of political narratives. This election has taught
us that the boosting technology is open to all and the messy, multi-directional,
bottom up practices of diffusing and absorbing information will play an
ever-greater role in processes of public opinion formation– for better or for
worse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those people who still regard ‘Brexit’ as a conundrum for political thinkers and
politicians, it is time to comprehend that the referendum and the current
negotiations will persistently act as an element of impact on virtually every
aspect of society. Don’t believe us? Well, social media is often looked to as a
portrayal of world dynamics, none more so than with Britain’s expected departure
from the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">It was preposterous to observe the twist of events when back in the 2009 data speech, the former Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, David Cameron, described internet of things to be an ‘amazing pollinator’ that ‘turns lovely fights into mass campaigns; transforms moans into movements; excites the attention of hundreds, thousands, millions of people and stirs them into action.’ This same power became a major concern for him when millions of people were triggered, provoked and mobilized through this very medium to vote for Brexit.   This is a company that has worked with hacked material, this is a company that will send out videos of people being murdered to intimidate voters, this is a company that goes out and tries to illicitly acquire live internet browsing data of everyone in an entire country. An ex-Cambridge Analytica employee, whistle-blower Christopher Wylie, made this statement which only goes on to portray the tip of the iceberg which revolved around the Brexit referendum and Cambridge Analytica’s utter ignorance for the law. Cambridge Analytica Ltd. (CA) was a data analysis and mining entity that had played an extremely controversial part in the Leave European Union campaign. They assisted the official Vote Leave campaign and skillfully found a way to circumvent the campaign funding laws. Leaked documents disclosed that the Vote Leave campaign, the official pro-Brexit group, headed by Michael Gove and Boris Johnson, paid a hefty 625,000 pounds to a Canadian data organisation named Aggregate IQ (AIQ). In contrast to the two companies’ statements of denying a coordination during the referendum, Wylie testified that CA and AIQ shared data with one another on a persistent basis. “You can’t have targeting software that doesn’t access the database. Cambridge Analytica would have a database and AIQ would access that database, otherwise the software wouldn’t work,” Wylie said.  Christopher Wylie, the whistle-blower who worked alongside Cambridge University researcher Aleksandr Kogan to reap the data for Cambridge Analytica, told the Observer that they had exploited Facebook to acquire millions of people’s profiles. The unified intention of the company was to form a model which could help them manipulate the targeted audience. The New York Times and UK-based Observer reported that more than 50 million Facebook users had their data harvested by Cambridge Analytica which has been called as the social media platform’s largest data breach till date. It was disclosed that they used the data to target users with customised political advertisements to further Trump’s presidential bid and the pro-Brexit drive. British journalist Carole Cadwalladr, in her Ted talk, highlights the specific case of Ebbw Vale. Ebbw Vale, a small town in South Wales, had one of the cities with the highest percentage of leave votes (62%-38%) despite the fact that it had several regeneration projects funded by the EU. However, much to the surprise, the residents were of the view that the European Union had done nothing for them. “Take back control”- one of the most widely used slogans in the campaign backed this perspective, and this fire was further fuelled by the supposed problem of refugees and immigrants contrary to which statistics showed that the immigration rates in Ebbw were one of the lowest. All of these facts didn’t add up together and did not provide the whole picture. Eventually, everything that could be found out was insufficient, because everything took place in ‘black boxes’- on Facebook, Google, YouTube. People testified that they saw ads on Facebook like – “76m population of Turkey to join the EU”, and other such statements, which lacked credibility. Such advertisements, feed, and posts were shown to a specifically targeted tiny silver of persuadable people to tilt their votes towards Leave. Facebook, along with Cambridge Analytica was responsible for leaking data from people’s profiles to the groups like Vote Leave who in turn, illegally targeted them. The campaign had sabotaged the opposition with more vociferous and aggressive supporters on all the social media handles leading to the uprising of leave supporters at the grassroot level. They outnumbered and dominated platforms like Twitter, Instagram and Facebook influencing and manipulating ambivalent voters who were made mere puppets in their hands.  On platforms like Twitter it was seen that people, not necessarily knowledgeable about politics, were able to make huge decisions for the future of a country based on hashtags and memes they have seen online. During the time leading up to the referendum in 2016, the number of people supporting the Leave campaign outnumbered the Remain campaign on Twitter by 7 to 1 and the most used hashtags were #Brexit, #Beleave and #VoteLeave.  When it comes to this serious political issue, this could be potentially damaging as users are likely to be influenced by whichever message appears most often or most prominent rather than necessarily searching for the true facts. Social media has changed the face of political campaigning and will inevitably continue doing so playing an indispensable role in the future elections to come all across the globe. It has been a commonplace to hypothesize that social media is a vital medium for distorted facts which restricts citizens to mere echo cubicles. The upside is that we get to participate in it like never before, we comment, we share, we tweet but unfortunately, our favourite social media networks have also slaughtered the essence of fair elections by distorting and shaping the outcomes according to their whims and fancies. It has evolved as a mighty force to aid the reach of political narratives. This election has taught us that the boosting technology is open to all and the messy, multi-directional, bottom up practices of diffusing and absorbing information will play an ever-greater role in processes of public opinion formation– for better or for worse.  Those people who still regard ‘Brexit’ as a conundrum for political thinkers and politicians, it is time to comprehend that the referendum and the current negotiations will persistently act as an element of impact on virtually every aspect of society. Don’t believe us? Well, social media is often looked to as a portrayal of world dynamics, none more so than with Britain’s expected departure from the European Union.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploration of Ourselves</title><link href="/Exploration-of-Ourselves" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploration of Ourselves" /><published>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Exploration-of-Ourselves</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Exploration-of-Ourselves">&lt;p&gt;“What makes you, well, you?”- Michael Stevens, Vsauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plato in his thesis and conceptualisation of perfect beings, explored and introduced to us the concept of Forms and how the ‘World of Forms’ is the state of perfection of every being in our world, the achievement of which may be well beyond our capabilities, owing to the limitations that bound us. The World of Forms is a utopian disposition, a state of perfection, which exists only in the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the question which arises from it is: what kind of a being would be a perfect form of us? To understand this, we must question ourselves on our true nature and the most fundamentally important, yet unanswered question we are faced with. The question is: who are we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re probably thinking that this is another clichéd take on who you are, or on how who someone &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; is can never be defined and yet there will be attempts to explore this subject, leading to countless innovative and daring philosophical initiatives in order to reach a comprehensive definition of our being? Oh blimey! That’s some misplaced and crooked jugular, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, you could be right, this probably is another one of those inquiries that we dive into, modelling ourselves into the Thinker’s pose, trying to figure out what defines us, what it means to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; us. Rene Descartes once remarked, “I think, therefore I am”, posing keen albeit ambiguous arguments on the definition of a man, on the basis of his consciousness first, after which we can define our being. Sartre took his chance and played with “Cogito, ergo sum” to make his own phrase, “I am, therefore I think” and even though it may seem to be just a play of words which it is (maybe). It does, however, attempt to make more sense from Jean Paul’s version of existentialist propagation, prioritising our being over the form of mind. Note that there can be some valid arguments over the interpretations of what each of them meant when using these words in order to elucidate their thoughts, it is on us to interpret them in the way we like for the adoption of our own code to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of who we are is an intriguing one and even more so when we are to discuss one of the very interesting philosophical analogies of all time, which has been used as a plot device in several anime and movies such as &lt;em&gt;Ghost in the Shell&lt;/em&gt;. The concept is generalised and popularly known as the Ship of Theseus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of the argument is based on the historical and mythical artefact of the Ship used by Theseus in his journey. If the Ship of Theseus is displayed in a museum, it’s safe to assume that after some time, some parts will start rotting and will have to be replaced with new parts. Say, the rotten parts of the ship are preserved, in order to restore them when the adequate technology is available. Gradually, all parts of the original ship are replaced and they are kept in a store house. The question which arises, at this point of time, is if this Ship, the one which has been entirely replaced with new parts, is still the same ship which Theseus used for his journey?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say that thanks to technology, we can restore the rotten parts of the ship in a proper manner. If we gradually replace the ship with its original parts, can I consider this ship to be the original one? The question being explored is how can we still call it the same ship if it has none of its original parts. If after dismantling and reorganising, what makes the ship, the same original ship used by Theseus? Are we right in the way we approach this problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to this philosophical question has been debated and deliberated upon since the time of Plato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several arguments which have been made in order to determine what would be the consequence of such an action. There have been propositions, made on the basis of ‘forms’, by Aristotle, in which he argues that anything is formed out of four essential causes: the formal cause (on the basis of its form), material cause (on the basis of its constituent materials), efficient cause (on the basis of its principle) and the final cause (which is indiscrete in its mannerisms but is a part of all the above causes). He argues that the causes are more or less consistent in all the cases with only one divergence in every case, and therefore it is in principle the same ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another argument is that of the transitive property via which it relates to all the forms of the ship to be the representative of the ship itself. There is also the argument that there is loss of identity over time, and therefore, it is not the same ship anymore and can be regarded as a different ship in the frame of time. This theory, however, has been heavily criticised owing to the assumptions it makes on several fronts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of the Ship of Theseus is an intriguing one, and questions the understanding of ourselves from within, that if we are in the same position, being replaced, what makes us the same person as before? What makes us, us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Davidson in his paper, &lt;em&gt;Knowing one’s own mind&lt;/em&gt;, gives an example of The Ship of Theseus. He talks about the possibility of a clone being born out of his dead body in a thunderstorm. How will his family or anyone else differentiate between the actual him, who is dead, and the clone borne out of the thunderstorm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argues that ‘there will be an inherent difference’ but he does not further enunciate his point. It places us under a precarious and delicate situation. Does it benefit us if we define ourselves within some definition and make sense out of ourselves? Do we need to know the difference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identity crisis may be a philosophically daunting question, but from a stoic’s perspective, this will not matter because the world we live in will not change with the change in me, and thus it will still be us in some way. Which goes on to say that there is no need to think about it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, is it wrong to explore and understand ourselves better in order to develop the characteristics of self resolution within us? Maybe we will never know or maybe knowing the answer defeats the human purpose which is not to define but keep a limited form in order to open up more interpretation. Thus, knowing who we are is a small fragment of understanding our consciousness, the universe beyond us and our purpose in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section, I will dig deeper into the realm of our nature to find clues as to what makes me so different from you on the other side of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes me, me and you, you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay Tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">“What makes you, well, you?”- Michael Stevens, Vsauce.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Canada’s Climate Combat</title><link href="/Canada-Climate-Combat" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Canada’s Climate Combat" /><published>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Canada-Climate-Combat</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Canada-Climate-Combat">&lt;p&gt;Global warming and climate change: the two terms widely occupying public discourse in recent times. Something that the millennials would call upon as the mistakes of the past, that scares all the youth reminding them of sci-fi movies which show the looming dark days of the future. &lt;em&gt;Inevitable&lt;/em&gt; as some of us would put it across as. Thus, it is no surprise that movements and protests to combat climate change are picking up in many parts of the globe, especially in first world countries, where the youth is more empowered with knowledge of the future. The world has gone berserk over the issue, and reactions all across the globe seems to be mixed. While the American Government is making news by dismissing climate change and global warming as a hoax and ditching climate pacts, her northern neighbour, Canada is doing the exact opposite. The Prime Minister of Canada announced that the country will create protected marine areas in the Arctic region of the country. This decision comes across as a delight to most around the globe, and here’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arctic is one of the worst affected regions in the world. Deterioration of climate has led to a rise in the water level, becoming ominous to indigenous animals. Over the past three decades, the Arctic Ocean has lost an area of sea ice equivalent to Germany, France and Spain combined (2,00,000 sq km approx.). Major power players like the USA, Russia, Canada and China have long been competing to get a hold of the Arctic to extract minerals and petroleum resources promised by the region. In the wake of all these happenings, Canada’s announcement to create Protected Marine Areas (PMA) comes as new found hope. Canada has announced two PMAs namely Tuvaijuittuq (which means ‘ice never melts’) Marine Protected Area and Tallurutiup Imanga, covering an area of 427,000 square kilometres. The federal government and Qikiqtani Inuit Association (QIA) have signed Inuit Impact Benefit Agreement (IIBA) to that effect. QIA is a non-profit society that is designated to safeguard the interests of the minority Inuit community (Eskimos) and has played a key role in pulling off the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IIBA proposes a two-fold strategy. Firstly, it forbids any anthropogenic activity and the areas are entirely closed from deep-sea mining, oil and gas extraction, dumping, and fishing. Second, it targets at providing sustainable employment to the Inuit community. For this, the government is set to invest $143 million over the next 7 years. It includes the promotion of local arts and crafts, textiles, indigenous occupations and government jobs in research and data collection as well as investments in ship harbors and boating docks. Thus, one can see that the major beneficiary of this agreement is the Inuit community of northwestern Canada. Akeeagok, QIA president, said that by investing in Inuit, the government is paying the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main principles that Economics teaches us is that there is always a tradeoff, and so is there one between economic development and environmental sustainability. Development mostly succeeds at the expense of the environment and has a ravaging effect on it. Canada’s project, however, is an exception. The project protects 14% of the country’s total marine and coastal area, exceeding the original target of protecting 10% of the area by 2020. It also protects indigenous species like narwhal, polar bear, walrus, seal, beluga and the under-ice algae that form a very important base for the entire Arctic food web. Thus, the two notified PMAs will be pivotal biodiversity conservation regions. Further, the Canadian government is actively investing in research related projects so as to support the process to conserve PMAs. It has been announced that an investment of approximately 6 million will go into a scientific research on the impacts of potential oil spills, taken up under the country’s Coastal Environmental Baseline Program, which aims at identifying the long term changes in Canada’s coastal environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this policy is being criticised as a politically motivated move. One cannot dismiss these claims because they seem to be partially true. The Inuit community, on whose betterment the agreement primarily focuses, is afterall a minority group in the country who were the victims of discrimination for ages. Justin Trudeau, the incumbent PM of Canada is seeking re-election in October 2019. Thus, critics term the government’s decision as one to woo votes and win the confidence of the people. Apart from this, the agreement says that “no new human activities will be allowed to occur in the area for up to five years, with a few exceptions.” The question is if a 5-year ban on human activities would prove effective at all and whether the exceptions in the notified areas will be able to serve their true purpose. As it was noted earlier, the activities of the previous decades had deteriorated the condition of the area. While it is uncertain if the 5-year ban will be extended, this short span is not sufficient for a sustainable revival of the Arctic. Thus lies a risk of economic growth coming to a halt and simultaneously no significant development towards environmental restoration taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, one thing to be noted here is that prior to the announcement of PMAs, the Canadian government had announced that it would actively explore for oil and natural gas in the Arctic. It is estimated that the proposed area of PMAs contains 56 trillion cubic feet of natural gas and 8 billion barrels of oil. However, the government has banned all activities pertaining to the extraction of these resources. This shows the government’s integrity and sends the message that Canada is serious and determined to battle against climate change. At the end, no matter the motive, what counts is the result. The initiative is one which not only empowers a certain section of the country but also helps the world delay an impending climate crisis and take up arms to promote sustainable development. Yes, agreeing to the fact that PMAs are not a panacea to climate change, it is something to begin with. It will slow down global warming and mitigate the effects thereof. To ensure success, they must be taken up together with other measures to tackle global warming and climate change. PMAs should be notified by all countries that are a part of the Arctic region. Such countries should draw inspiration from Canada and ban maximum anthropogenic activities in the region. A ban on industrial and human affairs in the region will, most definitely, help revive and restore the lost biodiversity and reduce global warming. Thus, hoping for a better future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Global warming and climate change: the two terms widely occupying public discourse in recent times. Something that the millennials would call upon as the mistakes of the past, that scares all the youth reminding them of sci-fi movies which show the looming dark days of the future. Inevitable as some of us would put it across as. Thus, it is no surprise that movements and protests to combat climate change are picking up in many parts of the globe, especially in first world countries, where the youth is more empowered with knowledge of the future. The world has gone berserk over the issue, and reactions all across the globe seems to be mixed. While the American Government is making news by dismissing climate change and global warming as a hoax and ditching climate pacts, her northern neighbour, Canada is doing the exact opposite. The Prime Minister of Canada announced that the country will create protected marine areas in the Arctic region of the country. This decision comes across as a delight to most around the globe, and here’s why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘What Do You Believe?’ How Ideology Will Shape the Culture Wars of the 21st Century</title><link href="/What-Do-You-Believe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘What Do You Believe?’ How Ideology Will Shape the Culture Wars of the 21st Century" /><published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/What-Do-You-Believe</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-Do-You-Believe">&lt;p&gt;In a way, all of human history is an endless cycle of war and peace. As the old proverb goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hard times create strong men.&lt;br /&gt;
Strong men create good times.&lt;br /&gt;
Good times create weak men.&lt;br /&gt;
Weak men create hard times.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all at war – in some way or the other, with something or the other. We are all fighting, even for our daily bread. Whether it be bargaining with the local shopkeeper or actually taking up arms against an invader, conflict of some sort or the other pervades our very social existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In centuries past, certain nations decided that the best way to promote their own interest would be to colonise faraway lands located across the seas. This was the age of Conquest, the age of Empires. The result was that entire nations and civilisations came under the commercial and political dominance of unreachable overlords, living in another world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people of these subjugated races and tribes suddenly found themselves living as if on rent on the very land which their ancestors had tilled, ploughed and reaped for their own benefit. Hardship led to resentment. Resentment led to anger. Anger led to rage. Rage led to rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tired of being mocked, of being made to feel ashamed for the colour of their skin or the rhythm of their tongue or the lyric of their songs, they rose in revolt against the imperialist yoke. Those who were wise, left. But those who underestimated the fury of an oppressed race came to rue it to their very last breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nation fought nation; tribe fought tribe. People of one language ostracised those who spoke a different tongue. Those of a particular hue of skin detested those who looked different. These were the ways of a time when one’s loyalty and one’s pride was still rooted to the soil upon which one lived and toiled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that age is no more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War remains, perhaps ever more keenly than before. But it is a different kind of war. Out of the crucible of human conflict, a new world is being forged. There are several things which have led to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the shocking discovery that this Earth could indeed be tamed by the force of human ingenuity. We were told that only the sky is the limit – but even this has proven to be false. The Earth has shown itself to be a very small place indeed, and a new frontier has emerged – the great dark horizon of space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this contraction has only brought people closer together – geographically speaking. We are no longer bound to the soil on which our ancestors lived, moved and had their being. The coming together of continents, facilitated by the meteoric rise of modern transport, has led to the birth of multicultural and multi-ethnic societies around the world, where people of different beliefs and various walks of life have been forced to live their lives side-by-side. Seldom do we think of this, but the fact remains that what we see today – people of myriad ethnicities working together in the same office – would have been unthinkable even a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has led to the trivialisation of what originally divided mankind. The white man has come to see in the black man not an inferior creature, but a fellow human being. And the black man has come to see in his white neighbour not a fiendish oppressor from the pits of the underworld, but rather a mere man – with faults and flaws, just like everyone else. The close contact of daily interaction has ensured this. And this has led to a radical change in thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow’s battles will not be fought on the basis of race, language or ethnicity. Tomorrow’s wars will be wars of ideology, wars of belief, wars of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideology, you see, is not like skin colour or tribal identity. It cannot be as easily brushed aside. Abortion is either right or wrong. It cannot be both right and wrong. Pornography is either moral or immoral. Giving condoms to high school students is either a magnificent step forward in promoting safe sex and sexual freedom, or it is a sign of growing decadence and degeneracy in a society which shamelessly normalises the divorce of sex from marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when an unstoppable force meets an immovable mass? What happens when one belief system clashes with another? Two world views which are diametrically opposed to each other cannot coexist peacefully. One must prevail; the other must fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political scientist Samuel P. Huntington famously argued that what the post-Cold War era was about to see was not conflict between countries, but rather between cultures. He called it &lt;em&gt;The Clash of Civilizations&lt;/em&gt;, and hypothesised that ideology – and especially religion – would play a crucially important role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you lived, say, three thousand years ago, you would probably have been born in a monolithic homogeneous society, where there would have been one main philosophy of life, which would have answered all the big questions for you. And in all likelihood, you could have lived your entire life without questioning it – quite natural, given that everyone you knew believed the same things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that is no longer true. The confluence of cultures has resulted in people being exposed to a myriad of different philosophies and beliefs, each quite distinct from their own. Man can no longer be satisfied with accepting answers by faith alone. He has to think and rethink the big questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is his place in the world? Where does he come from? What does it all mean? And what ought one to do while one lives in this changing, transient world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are big questions, and this sudden clash of civilisations has forced the different camps to stop and regroup. And since interaction between different communities is all but inevitable, the conflict of ideas has begun anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result can easily be seen. Muslims are studying the New Testament and trying to understand what implications it might have on their own beliefs. Christians are studying Arabic and seeking to understand what the Quran actually says. Atheists are studying theology in universities and devout religious believers are devouring the works of Nietzsche and Russell with vigour. And this very happy situation is causing conversions on all sides, of the most lucrative and imaginative kinds. The clash certainly continues and democracy has played a crucial role in ensuring this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The struggle for power is natural to all human societies. In the Middle Ages, it was restricted mostly to the ruling class – aristocrats, nobles, princes, royal families and the like. But the advent of democracy has ensured that the vast citizenry have a vital and crucial say in who ultimately becomes King. And this means that people are much more informed and critical than ever before. Everyone has a vested interest. And everyone is trying to realize their own vision of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;belief&lt;/em&gt; plays a crucial role in all this. What do people &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; would be the best for their country, and for the world? Should abortion be legalised or criminalised? Is patriarchy real or is it a myth? Should borders be opened or closed? Is climate change real or is it a hoax? Should churches be taxed or should they be exempted? Should we seek to establish a one world government or do we support the idea of independent, autonomous nation states?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideology shapes the world we live in. And this naturally means that every election – which inevitably guarantees a victory for one side and a defeat for all others – is a microcosm of the great culture war playing out around the world. Whichever side wins, the other naturally feels aggrieved, oppressed and persecuted, and blames the ‘decadent’ victor for ruining the world. This is the sad, but unavoidable result, of a small world in which beliefs and philosophies of life are this varied and polarised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fruits of this are often surprising and, at times, humorous. Today, conservative white Christian folk would rather have fellow Christians of different ethnicities, races and cultures as their neighbours and citizens rather than those of their own race who don’t hold similar values. It’s the same with the Muslim community. Generally speaking, racial differences are becoming less and less relevant, and ideological differences are becoming more pronounced and prominent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, ironically, means that religion and philosophy will come to enjoy an influence they perhaps have not had in the immediate past. The new world war will not be over race or national identity, but over one’s vision for life. The main question our young people will be asked is not “Where do you come from?” but rather “What do you believe?”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">In a way, all of human history is an endless cycle of war and peace. As the old proverb goes:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt</title><link href="/Nefertiti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt" /><published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Nefertiti</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Nefertiti">&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so &lt;em&gt;special&lt;/em&gt; about her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camille Paglia would tell you- “Nefertiti is like Athena. Born from the brow of Zeus, a head-heavy armored goddess. She is beautiful but desexed.” Well, at least, that is how she sees it. My answer to the same, however, is multifold. For one, she was a powerful symbol of love in ancient Egypt. Never before were ancient Egyptian Kings and Queens portrayed in the writings, statues and inscriptions of the time as a couple madly in love. This was probably because most of the royal couples were siblings. But, this was not the case for Nefertiti and her husband, Akhenaten. They were not siblings. Absolutely nothing is known about Nefertiti’s parents. Many have speculated that she might have been the daughter of Ay, in line to the throne after Tutankhamun. Some have even linked her to a Mitanni princess, Tadukhipa. However, nothing exists to confirm either of the theories. In my opinion, given the amount of information we currently have, it is possible that she was a commoner. Remains from 14th century Egypt, however, show the couple publicly holding hands, embracing or riding chariots and kissing. In fact, Akhenaten even wrote a poem for his beloved Nefertiti. This adequately proves that they were indeed in love with each other and were certainly not, at least directly, related. This is rather surprising because incest was the norm among members of the royal family. Deviation from the norm did not, however, affect her position and Nefertiti soon became the principal wife and chief consort of Pharaoh Akhenaten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other beloved queen of the ancient world, Nefertiti was a symbol of great beauty. Her name literally translates to ‘the beautiful one has come’. Ideals of beauty were largely defined by what the rulers looked like at the time. Artefacts from this period of history, however, are vastly different from the reigns of other Pharaohs. This is because Akhenaten, his daughter Meritaten, and other members of the royal court are depicted with drastically elongated skulls, extremely narrow rib cages, chicken legs and protruding bellies. It goes without saying that that is very different from contemporary standards of beauty, they’d probably “ugly” and not regal today. Of course, it is possible that they took pride in what they looked like and did not want to be depicted any differently. As for the seemingly disfigured body parts, it wasn’t very uncommon because incest was a common practice. Lack of genetic diversity led to genetic deformations. The issue arises when we start inspecting Nefertiti, for she too was depicted with a long, bald head and a swan-like neck, and she was, almost certainly, not a product of incest. Many have questioned if her portrayal was so because Akhenaten and perhaps, Nefertiti herself wanted to be portrayed in this manner. Some pseudo-scientific theorists have also speculated the possibility of her being an extraterrestrial being. This would indeed explain her unusual looks. It is, however, in my opinion, likely that she was in fact a product of incest or that her elongated head was only a decorated head gear meant to give her a specific look. As for now, there is no direct evidence to support or reject any claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to how most historical characters of this period in Egyptian history are depicted, Nefertiti is showcased as much more ‘beautiful’. In fact she even meets modern standards of beauty. We know this because of one of the most famous finds of all time: the bust of Nefertiti. Currently housed in a museum in Berlin, the bust was found by German archaeologist, Ludwig Borchardt, on the 6th of December, 1912, in an artist’s studio in the then mostly unexcavated South-West Amarna. The British carried out expeditions in 1891 and 1892 in Tell-el Amarna, and concluded their endeavour with the statement that all that was left to be discovered had been retrieved by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bust is extremely beautiful and exceptionally well preserved, in stark contrast to the other busts found nearby that date back to the same time period. In fact, a bust of Akhenaten, found almost alongside that of Nefertiti’s, was found to be completely disfigured by nature. This raised some questions about the authenticity of the find. &lt;em&gt;Is the famous bust of Nefertiti even real?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What bothers me the most is how Nefertiti looks like a modern beauty- olive skin, impeccable eyebrows, long neck and high cheekbones. A missing eye has also led to speculation that she might have suffered from an ophthalmic infection. It is weird to even think of the sculpture as a 3,000 year old object because, as many Egyptologists say, ‘it is simply too beautiful’, both in terms of conservation and good looks. Careful investigation reveals something even more strange, the style is inconsistent with the time period. The shoulders, in the case of Nefertiti’s bust, are cut vertically as opposed to the usual horizontal cut along the shoulder line. However, another piece of work found during Borchardt’s excavation has the same kind of cut. Thus, there exists, at least one other bust from the same time period, sculpted in the same style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borchardt left behind extensive notes on his dig and findings at Amarna. He claims that the bust was found 50 cm under gravel. He explains that the artwork was sitting on a shelf, about 1.5 m from the ground, when the city was abandoned. As time passed, the walls decayed and the bust fell face down. The problem with this theory is that only the ears in the bust are damaged. If it did fall from such a height, that too face down, the nose would have been damaged, most definitely, especially because it is a delicate limestone sculpture. Is it possible that the bust was forged, then? Some modern experiments do reveal, however, that the plaster used in the bust is from the Amarna period. Although it is certainly possible that usable plaster, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign found in the same dig, was used if the bust is indeed fake. One thing that makes this theory less plausible, however, is the fact that the person who did forge the bust would have to have known all about ancient Egyptian hand and finger measurements. This is unlikely as the forger must have been a local Egyptian, probably not well versed with Egyptology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the question of why. &lt;em&gt;Why forge something like this?&lt;/em&gt; When Kaiser William realised that Germany was lagging behind in the field of Egyptology, he ordered German Egyptologists to get him something, whatever might be the cost, to shock the world. In addition, one of Germany’s princely families was in Egypt at the time of the dig. Borchardt, who specialised in the domestic lives of ancient Egyptians, might have hired an artist to work on the limestone and plaster, in an attempt to understand the process involved. When the German princely family arrived at the dig, he just couldn’t explain to them that the bust was fake, fearing that he might commit the crime of disrespecting the royalty and be prosecuted for it. As a matter of fact, he did not allow the sculpture to be displayed publicly for almost 10 years after it was found. As for now, it is difficult to be sure as to what exactly underwent on the 6th of December, 1912.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Nefertiti’s importance in the modern perception of ancient history is highly limited, it is undeniable that Nefertiti, in fact, commanded immense power and was incredibly important in her time. She quickly rose to the post of a co-regent; a position equivalent to that of a Pharaoh himself. In most paintings, she is shown to be of equal size as her husband. This is rather rare because size was often used as a metaphor for power. In a relic from a temple in Tell-el Amarna, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign, Nefertiti is even seen smiting a foreign enemy with a mace. She is often depicted wearing the regal crown. Such depictions were usually reserved for the Pharaoh alone. She did have a title that declared her as the Ruler of the Nile and the Daughter of Gods. But, the question is, &lt;em&gt;was she more than that?&lt;/em&gt; Perhaps, she might even have ruled as a Pharaoh for a while?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions like these are very difficult to answer, especially when it comes to the Amarna period (approximately 1353 to 1336 BCE- Akhenaten’s reign). A lot of events distinguish this particular period in Egyptian history from others. It all starts with Akhenaten’s decision to shift the capital to Tell-el Amarna, in the middle of the desert, in the second year of his roughly 17 year reign. Very soon, Amarna became a modern (for ancient times) city with 50,000 residents. Akhenaten and Nefertiti also started advocating a new monotheistic religion, Atenism. It is the worship of the Sun disc. Monotheism indeed sounds like an Anno Dominic concept. In fact, priests of the time weren’t very happy as the new religion failed to answer important questions about death, something that had been central to their religion for many years. Their successor, Tutankhaten was, however, unable to carry forward the legacy and eventually gave in to the priests. Upon their advice, he changed his name to Tutankhamun and embraced the polytheistic religion that everyone was used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystery surrounding Nefertiti is not just limited to her parentage. She disappears from all records in the 12th year of Akhenaten’s reign and no one seems to know why. Many believe that she died at this point, victimised by a plague that had claimed several lives around that time. Some Egyptologists fail to agree to such an explanation, especially since Nefertiti’s tomb was never found. In 2015, Nicholas Reeves came up with a highly debated and popular alternative theory. While going through some high resolution pictures, he noticed cracks that looked like doors in the northern and eastern walls of Tutankhamun’s burial chamber in the Valley of Kings. Infrared thermography revealed different temperature readings confirming two possible hidden passages. Reeves theorised that Tutankhamun &lt;strong&gt;inherited&lt;/strong&gt; the tomb of Nefertiti. In fact, Tutankhamun’s tomb is rather unusual: it is small and was made in a hurry. Close examinations reveal dripping marks of the paint, impressions of hasty brush strokes and mould, proving that the tomb was closed before the paint dried. A tomb needs to be sealed within 70 days of the Pharaoh’s death. Tutankhamun was only 19 when he passed away. Usually tombs take the entire lifetime of the pharaohs to be built. But Tutankhamun’s tomb decorations couldn’t have taken more than a week to be done with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Reeves, the hidden passage could lead to Nefertiti’s burial chamber. Zahi Hawas, the former Egyptian Minister of Antiquities, rejected this idea stating that Nefertiti was nothing more than a wife to Pharaoh Akhenaten and thus there was no reason for the priest of Amun to honour her by putting her to rest in the Valley of Kings. He further claims that a wall sealing the Queen’s burial chamber would restrict her passage to the afterlife. I, however, find this slightly problematic as all tombs are, in fact, sealed. Recently, however, Italian geophysicists used Ground Penetrating Radar to confirm the absence of a hidden chamber, putting all speculations to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that surprises many is the fact that Nefertiti is portrayed guarding Akhenaten’s granite sarcophagus; a position traditionally reserved for the female deities of Egypt, Isis, Nepthys, Selket and Neith. Her influence remained strong even after her death. Or did it? Did she really die in the 10th year of her residence in Amarna? Many believe that she did not. Right after Nefertiti’s name disappears from the records, a new figure appears; a co-regent with whom Akhenaten actively shared the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is speculated that Nefertiti might even have taken the throne as a female king, following the footsteps of previous female rulers, like Sobekneferu and Hatshepsut. Two such co-regents’ names have been associated with Nefertiti; Neferneferuaten and Smenkhkare. Surprisingly, the latter is male. But, then again, even Hatshepsut had to disguise as a man to rule. In fact, some even go to the extent of saying that Nefertiti took the throne for herself after Akhenaten’s death as Tutankhamun was too young to rule. Tutankhaten changed his name, capital and reverted back to the old religion only in the 3rd year of reign, around the time Nefertiti would have finally died. Nothing, however, is known with certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like a lot of other influential female personalities of the ancient world, Nefertiti’s name and contributions have largely been whitewashed by the future and patriarchy. Not much is known of her today. In fact, what we do know and understand is very little compared to even some of the oldest (male) Pharaohs. This implies that she is unable to boast of the popularity that she deserves. Zoe Saldana once said, “I would love to play Nefertiti or Cleopatra or the Queen of Sheba. We preserve more male history than we do female. We have to preserve [female history]. No more complaining. We have to do it.” We can only hope that one day everyone understands her worth, importance and contribution to our history. A search must start for the lost histories of womankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so special about her?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Will Arsenal’s New Signings Fit In?</title><link href="/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Will Arsenal’s New Signings Fit In?" /><published>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In</id><content type="html" xml:base="/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In">&lt;p&gt;Since the appointment of ex-Arsenal midfielder Edu as the club’s technical
director last month, the Gunners have accelerated their transfer plans after
initially making slow progress towards agreeing deals for the likes of Wilfried
Zaha and Kieran Tierney. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the little-heralded signing of Brazillian youngster Gabriel Martinelli,
the window really kicked off with the double announcement of Dani Ceballos on
loan from Real Madrid and the signing of £27 million William Saliba (who was
subsequently loaned back to Saint Étienne) on July 25th. This was soon trumped
by the surprise signing of Nicolas Pépé from Lille, with Arsenal defying the
reports of their £45 million transfer budget by securing the £72 million Ivorian
forward on a 5 year deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, deadline day saw the defence bolstered by the £25 million signing of
left-back Kieran Tierney from Celtic and the shock arrival of veteran
centre-back David Luiz from London rivals Chelsea for £8M on a two year deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Unai Emery now having added quality at his disposal, the question is how
each of the new boys will fit in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;William Saliba&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick mention of someone Arsenal fans won’t get to see for a while; teenage
defender William Saliba whose former club Saint-Etienne insisted on having him
loaned back to them this season. Despite not having played a game for the club,
he has already endeared himself to the Arsenal faithful after he reportedly
snubbed interest from North London rivals Tottenham before opting to join the
Gunners. Once Arsenal fans do get to see him in action, they will see an
accomplished modern centre-back, capable of surging forward from the back whilst
also being a dependable defender, especially in 1v1 situations. His rangy stride
and 6’3 frame make him a physically excellent prospect and when looking at the
market for the likes of Harry Maguire, £28 million could be a bargain for an 18
year old that was starting for the fourth best team in France.  Saliba, along
with Rob Holding and Calum Chambers, looks set to be the future of Arsenal’s
central defence as Sokratis and David Luiz advance into their 30s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signing of 18 year old Brazillian winger Gabriel Martinelli has
understandably been forgotten about by many after the 5 higher profile signings
that followed. Signed from Brazillian side Ituano for a reported fee of £6
million, Martinelli made his debut in a short cameo against Newcastle last
weekend and, with the sale of Alex Iwobi to Everton, could be in for some
minutes as a rotation player this season. With Pépé and Henrikh Mkhitaryan now
the only established wingers at the club there’s a route to the first team for
Martinelli, but he’ll face fierce competition from fellow teenage wingers Reiss
Nelson, Emile Smith-Rowe and Bukayo Saka. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dani Ceballos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talented midfielder Dani Ceballos played a crucial role in Spain’s triumph at
the European U21 Championship in Italy this summer, and he will now embark on a
short stint in North London before he likely cements himself as a Real Madrid
regular for years to come. A player as gifted as Ceballos is seldom available on
loan and Arsenal should thank the likes of Luka Modric and Toni Kroos for
blocking his path to regular minutes at the Bernabeu, allowing Arsenal to
acquire a player who will slot right into their first XI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Ceballos being the only addition to Arsenal’s midfield this summer, it
would be natural to think he would be tasked with replacing the void left by
Aaron Ramsey’s departure to Juventus. However, Ceballos is more similar to a few
of Ramsey’s former midfield partners: Jack Wilshere and fellow Spaniard Santi
Cazorla. Wilshere and Cazorla both averaged over 2 dribbles a game throughout
their Arsenal careers, but since their departures in 2018 no Arsenal midfielder
averaged more than Mattéo Guendouzi’s 0.7 dribbles a game last season. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ceballos averaged 2.7 dribbles per game in his last league season of regular
football at Real Betis in the 2016/17 season and should contribute to some much
needed technical support in the centre of the park, giving Arsenal a ball
carrying outlet from deep to evade pressure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-01.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-02.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-03.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ceballos’ immense skill set and versatility means he is capable as a deep-lying
playmaker, a tireless box-to-box CM, or in the number 10 role. Given Ramsey’s
departure and Özil’s recent off-the-pitch adversities, Emery is likely to deploy
Ceballos as the furthest forward midfielder. The 23-year old’s outstanding
performance on his home debut against Burnley earned him rave reviews and the
MOTM award, showcasing his masterful ability as he began the game behind the
striker but switched to a deeper role later in the game. Wherever he plays, the
former Real Betis man is a superb addition to Arsenal’s midfield for this
season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicolas Pépé&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£72 million man Nicolas Pépé is the most hyped up of Arsenal’s summer signings
for good reason; the Ivorian was one of only two players in the top 5 European
leagues to score at least 20 times and record over 10 assists, with the other
being Lionel Messi. Only Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang (22) and Alexandre Lacazette
(13) managed more than 6 league goals for Arsenal last season so Pépé’s arrival
should easen the load for the pair while forming a potent 3-pronged attack to
try to match those at Liverpool and Man City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though playing in a weaker league last year, Pépé regularly got into goal
scoring positions and had no hesitation in pulling the trigger, averaging 3.1
shots a game from wide, which is a welcome attribute to a team that had less
shots than Crystal Palace and Southampton last season. Pépé will add value as a
ball carrier and an outlet in the final third, fitting a profile Arsenal have
been missing since the departures of Alex Oxlade-Chamberlain, Theo Walcott and
Alexis Sánchez. Pépé’s dribbling stats last season were comparable to those of
Chamberlain’s and Sánchez’s during their time at the Emirates, and if he can
combine that with Walcott and Sánchez’s goal tallies then Arsenal have found a
real gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, however, questions as to how he will fit into Arsenal’s front line
with the likes of Lacazette, Aubameyang and Özil. Based on Unai Emery’s
pragmatic approach last season, it seems unlikely the 4 will line up together
often, especially away from home. Pépé should nevertheless be a fixture on the
team sheet along with Aubameyang due to their counter attacking potential. With
Pépé being a right sided player and Aubameyang, Özil and Lacazette usually
playing centrally it seems difficult to play them all without one of them being
out of position. Özil prefers to operate on the right rather than the left which
could cause Pépé to be forced to the left in pursuit of playing the two
centre-forwards in their natural positions. Needless to say, this would not be
an ideal situation for a player new to the Premier League so it’ll be up to
Emery to manage his team rotations and come up with a fluid attack to get the
best out of all his star forwards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-11.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-12.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-13.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kieran Tierney&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most important Arsenal signings were made on deadline day as the
Gunners brought in some much needed defensive reinforcements. 22-year-old
Tierney has already captained Celtic and Scotland, fulfilling the criteria of
being a leader, a quality that many pundits, such as Gary Neville, have long
been saying Arsenal miss. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he recovers from his hernia operation, Tierney will be tasked with fighting
off competition from fellow left-backs Nacho Monreal and Sead Kolašinac to make
the position his own. Tierney predominantly featured in a back 4 at Celtic but
has also played on the left of a back 3 for Scotland, with Liverpool’s Andy
Robertson playing as a wing back ahead of him. Whilst this may just have been a
way to shoehorn two of Scotland’s best players into the same XI, it could be an
option for Arsenal going forward with Sead Kolašinac lining up alongside
Tierney. Nacho Monreal has been deployed in a similar way over the last few
years and the benefit of this would be adding another ball playing centre-half
to bring the ball out from the back, as well as ideally having improved
defensive security with 5 defenders playing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should Tierney start in a back 4, he should act as a good counter balance to
Hector Bellerin on the opposite flank, with the Scot being the more reserved,
technically proficient of the pair whilst Bellerin utilises his athleticism to
make off ball runs and try and get in behind the opposition’s defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-21.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Luiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By crossing the divide between West and North London David Luiz followed the
path that several players have trodden in the last 20 years, and if he can
emulate the very reasonable Arsenal career of William Gallas then by all
accounts he should be considered a success. Whilst Gallas was 3 years younger
than Luiz when he left Stamford Bridge for the Emirates, he was a reliable (on
the pitch, at least) performer for the club, playing 142 times for Arsenal and
being named club captain after just one season at the club ahead of established
veterans such as Jens Lehmann and Gilberto Silva. Luiz will likely form an
experienced central defensive partnership with Sokratis, replacing Laurent
Koscielny after the Frenchman’s 9 year residency at the club came to an end. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-31.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luiz entered the Premier League the same year Koscielny did, with both rightly
considered error-prone during their formative years in England before becoming
quality centre-backs. Both are proactive defenders who defend on the front-foot,
frequently stepping up to intercept dangerous passes. They are also both adept
at bringing the ball out of defence and into midfield. However, Luiz is a much
more accomplished passer, completing more through balls than any other Premier
League player last season. If Luiz can replicate that form this season, Pépé and
Aubameyang will thoroughly enjoy themselves in behind opposition backlines.
Luiz’s fine passing repertoire may be best served in a back 3, like in the
2016/17 season where he made the PFA Team of the Year, where he can venture
forward into midfield whilst still having two central defenders to cover for
him. Seeing the Brazillian in an Arsenal shirt will take some getting used to,
but, at £8 million, he could prove to be one of the most astute signings of the
summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal’s window surpassed most people’s expectations and, though nothing is
certain in football, right now has to be tentatively considered a success.
Sanllehi and co. added 5 players ranging from 18-24 years of age along with a 32
year old with years of Premier League experience. Arsenal now have a good mix of
youngsters who can grow together in the next few years whilst also having
several seasoned veterans. The departures of Ramsey, Iwobi, Koscielny and Danny
Welbeck appear to have been well replaced whilst lowering the average squad age
as Arsenal begin a new era. Having said that, we can only review how good a
transfer window has been after seeing how the signings actually perform on the
pitch. There was lots of optimism following Arsenal’s 2016 window in which they
spent around £90 million on Shkodran Mustafi, Granit Xhaka, Lucas Pérez and Rob
Holding though the first 3 have all disappointed to varying degrees. It’s now up
to the team to prove the new signings have brought them back to the level where
Arsenal strive to be. However, fans do have reason for optimism as it seems that
after a few tumultuous years with Sven Mislintat and Ivan Gazidis at the helm,
the new management regime are capable of putting together a squad that looks set
to contend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*pictures are from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot;&gt;www.buildlineup.com&lt;/a&gt; and stats are from
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whoscored.com&quot;&gt;www.whoscored.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Since the appointment of ex-Arsenal midfielder Edu as the club’s technical director last month, the Gunners have accelerated their transfer plans after initially making slow progress towards agreeing deals for the likes of Wilfried Zaha and Kieran Tierney.  After the little-heralded signing of Brazillian youngster Gabriel Martinelli, the window really kicked off with the double announcement of Dani Ceballos on loan from Real Madrid and the signing of £27 million William Saliba (who was subsequently loaned back to Saint Étienne) on July 25th. This was soon trumped by the surprise signing of Nicolas Pépé from Lille, with Arsenal defying the reports of their £45 million transfer budget by securing the £72 million Ivorian forward on a 5 year deal.  Finally, deadline day saw the defence bolstered by the £25 million signing of left-back Kieran Tierney from Celtic and the shock arrival of veteran centre-back David Luiz from London rivals Chelsea for £8M on a two year deal.  With Unai Emery now having added quality at his disposal, the question is how each of the new boys will fit in. William Saliba A quick mention of someone Arsenal fans won’t get to see for a while; teenage defender William Saliba whose former club Saint-Etienne insisted on having him loaned back to them this season. Despite not having played a game for the club, he has already endeared himself to the Arsenal faithful after he reportedly snubbed interest from North London rivals Tottenham before opting to join the Gunners. Once Arsenal fans do get to see him in action, they will see an accomplished modern centre-back, capable of surging forward from the back whilst also being a dependable defender, especially in 1v1 situations. His rangy stride and 6’3 frame make him a physically excellent prospect and when looking at the market for the likes of Harry Maguire, £28 million could be a bargain for an 18 year old that was starting for the fourth best team in France.  Saliba, along with Rob Holding and Calum Chambers, looks set to be the future of Arsenal’s central defence as Sokratis and David Luiz advance into their 30s.  Gabriel Martinelli The signing of 18 year old Brazillian winger Gabriel Martinelli has understandably been forgotten about by many after the 5 higher profile signings that followed. Signed from Brazillian side Ituano for a reported fee of £6 million, Martinelli made his debut in a short cameo against Newcastle last weekend and, with the sale of Alex Iwobi to Everton, could be in for some minutes as a rotation player this season. With Pépé and Henrikh Mkhitaryan now the only established wingers at the club there’s a route to the first team for Martinelli, but he’ll face fierce competition from fellow teenage wingers Reiss Nelson, Emile Smith-Rowe and Bukayo Saka.  Dani Ceballos Talented midfielder Dani Ceballos played a crucial role in Spain’s triumph at the European U21 Championship in Italy this summer, and he will now embark on a short stint in North London before he likely cements himself as a Real Madrid regular for years to come. A player as gifted as Ceballos is seldom available on loan and Arsenal should thank the likes of Luka Modric and Toni Kroos for blocking his path to regular minutes at the Bernabeu, allowing Arsenal to acquire a player who will slot right into their first XI. With Ceballos being the only addition to Arsenal’s midfield this summer, it would be natural to think he would be tasked with replacing the void left by Aaron Ramsey’s departure to Juventus. However, Ceballos is more similar to a few of Ramsey’s former midfield partners: Jack Wilshere and fellow Spaniard Santi Cazorla. Wilshere and Cazorla both averaged over 2 dribbles a game throughout their Arsenal careers, but since their departures in 2018 no Arsenal midfielder averaged more than Mattéo Guendouzi’s 0.7 dribbles a game last season.  Ceballos averaged 2.7 dribbles per game in his last league season of regular football at Real Betis in the 2016/17 season and should contribute to some much needed technical support in the centre of the park, giving Arsenal a ball carrying outlet from deep to evade pressure.  Ceballos’ immense skill set and versatility means he is capable as a deep-lying playmaker, a tireless box-to-box CM, or in the number 10 role. Given Ramsey’s departure and Özil’s recent off-the-pitch adversities, Emery is likely to deploy Ceballos as the furthest forward midfielder. The 23-year old’s outstanding performance on his home debut against Burnley earned him rave reviews and the MOTM award, showcasing his masterful ability as he began the game behind the striker but switched to a deeper role later in the game. Wherever he plays, the former Real Betis man is a superb addition to Arsenal’s midfield for this season. Nicolas Pépé £72 million man Nicolas Pépé is the most hyped up of Arsenal’s summer signings for good reason; the Ivorian was one of only two players in the top 5 European leagues to score at least 20 times and record over 10 assists, with the other being Lionel Messi. Only Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang (22) and Alexandre Lacazette (13) managed more than 6 league goals for Arsenal last season so Pépé’s arrival should easen the load for the pair while forming a potent 3-pronged attack to try to match those at Liverpool and Man City.  Though playing in a weaker league last year, Pépé regularly got into goal scoring positions and had no hesitation in pulling the trigger, averaging 3.1 shots a game from wide, which is a welcome attribute to a team that had less shots than Crystal Palace and Southampton last season. Pépé will add value as a ball carrier and an outlet in the final third, fitting a profile Arsenal have been missing since the departures of Alex Oxlade-Chamberlain, Theo Walcott and Alexis Sánchez. Pépé’s dribbling stats last season were comparable to those of Chamberlain’s and Sánchez’s during their time at the Emirates, and if he can combine that with Walcott and Sánchez’s goal tallies then Arsenal have found a real gem. There are, however, questions as to how he will fit into Arsenal’s front line with the likes of Lacazette, Aubameyang and Özil. Based on Unai Emery’s pragmatic approach last season, it seems unlikely the 4 will line up together often, especially away from home. Pépé should nevertheless be a fixture on the team sheet along with Aubameyang due to their counter attacking potential. With Pépé being a right sided player and Aubameyang, Özil and Lacazette usually playing centrally it seems difficult to play them all without one of them being out of position. Özil prefers to operate on the right rather than the left which could cause Pépé to be forced to the left in pursuit of playing the two centre-forwards in their natural positions. Needless to say, this would not be an ideal situation for a player new to the Premier League so it’ll be up to Emery to manage his team rotations and come up with a fluid attack to get the best out of all his star forwards.  Kieran Tierney Perhaps the most important Arsenal signings were made on deadline day as the Gunners brought in some much needed defensive reinforcements. 22-year-old Tierney has already captained Celtic and Scotland, fulfilling the criteria of being a leader, a quality that many pundits, such as Gary Neville, have long been saying Arsenal miss.  When he recovers from his hernia operation, Tierney will be tasked with fighting off competition from fellow left-backs Nacho Monreal and Sead Kolašinac to make the position his own. Tierney predominantly featured in a back 4 at Celtic but has also played on the left of a back 3 for Scotland, with Liverpool’s Andy Robertson playing as a wing back ahead of him. Whilst this may just have been a way to shoehorn two of Scotland’s best players into the same XI, it could be an option for Arsenal going forward with Sead Kolašinac lining up alongside Tierney. Nacho Monreal has been deployed in a similar way over the last few years and the benefit of this would be adding another ball playing centre-half to bring the ball out from the back, as well as ideally having improved defensive security with 5 defenders playing.  Should Tierney start in a back 4, he should act as a good counter balance to Hector Bellerin on the opposite flank, with the Scot being the more reserved, technically proficient of the pair whilst Bellerin utilises his athleticism to make off ball runs and try and get in behind the opposition’s defence.  David Luiz By crossing the divide between West and North London David Luiz followed the path that several players have trodden in the last 20 years, and if he can emulate the very reasonable Arsenal career of William Gallas then by all accounts he should be considered a success. Whilst Gallas was 3 years younger than Luiz when he left Stamford Bridge for the Emirates, he was a reliable (on the pitch, at least) performer for the club, playing 142 times for Arsenal and being named club captain after just one season at the club ahead of established veterans such as Jens Lehmann and Gilberto Silva. Luiz will likely form an experienced central defensive partnership with Sokratis, replacing Laurent Koscielny after the Frenchman’s 9 year residency at the club came to an end.  Luiz entered the Premier League the same year Koscielny did, with both rightly considered error-prone during their formative years in England before becoming quality centre-backs. Both are proactive defenders who defend on the front-foot, frequently stepping up to intercept dangerous passes. They are also both adept at bringing the ball out of defence and into midfield. However, Luiz is a much more accomplished passer, completing more through balls than any other Premier League player last season. If Luiz can replicate that form this season, Pépé and Aubameyang will thoroughly enjoy themselves in behind opposition backlines. Luiz’s fine passing repertoire may be best served in a back 3, like in the 2016/17 season where he made the PFA Team of the Year, where he can venture forward into midfield whilst still having two central defenders to cover for him. Seeing the Brazillian in an Arsenal shirt will take some getting used to, but, at £8 million, he could prove to be one of the most astute signings of the summer. Summary Arsenal’s window surpassed most people’s expectations and, though nothing is certain in football, right now has to be tentatively considered a success. Sanllehi and co. added 5 players ranging from 18-24 years of age along with a 32 year old with years of Premier League experience. Arsenal now have a good mix of youngsters who can grow together in the next few years whilst also having several seasoned veterans. The departures of Ramsey, Iwobi, Koscielny and Danny Welbeck appear to have been well replaced whilst lowering the average squad age as Arsenal begin a new era. Having said that, we can only review how good a transfer window has been after seeing how the signings actually perform on the pitch. There was lots of optimism following Arsenal’s 2016 window in which they spent around £90 million on Shkodran Mustafi, Granit Xhaka, Lucas Pérez and Rob Holding though the first 3 have all disappointed to varying degrees. It’s now up to the team to prove the new signings have brought them back to the level where Arsenal strive to be. However, fans do have reason for optimism as it seems that after a few tumultuous years with Sven Mislintat and Ivan Gazidis at the helm, the new management regime are capable of putting together a squad that looks set to contend. *pictures are from www.buildlineup.com and stats are from www.whoscored.com</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Houston, Are We Finally Clear for Takeoff?</title><link href="/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Houston, Are We Finally Clear for Takeoff?" /><published>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff">&lt;p&gt;Houston has, perhaps, been one of the most perplexing franchises over the past three seasons because of their seemingly non-existent presence come playoff time. This second installment of breaking down the path to the Larry O’Brien Trophy will discuss the steps the Houston Rockets will need to take in order to finally get over the hump of their recent string of postseason woes, as well as why the Rockets have a strong chance of coming out on top of the 10-team gauntlet that is the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s turn the clock back to the 2016/17 season in which the Rockets went 55-27. Up to this point, James Harden had put up strong performances, however this was the season in which the Rockets finally found their identity: give Harden the ball and allow him to go to work against opposing defenses.With Harden averaging a strong stat line of 29.1/11.2/8.1 (points/assists/rebounds per game), the Rockets were able to secure the third seed in a historic season in which the Golden State Warriors went 67-15. Despite otherworldly offensive talent, Harden was only able to propel the Rockets to the second round of the playoffs, losing a series against the San Antonio Spurs 4-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the second round exit, GM Darly Morey actively pursued several top talents across the NBA that he could pair up with Harden to help carry the load. Out of this search came the (at the time) huge acquisition of Chris Paul. On paper this seemed like a match made in heaven, as Chris Paul is easily one of the top-five passing point guards to have ever played in the association. Having a player of this caliber to accompany Harden causes defenses to draw up on a different defensive scheme, which would, hypothetically, leave players (Eric Gordon, Trevor Ariza, Clint Capela, etc.) open for easier looks, as teams would now have to hone in the Harden/Paul duo out of the backcourt. This trade reaped instant benefits, as the Rockets easily claimed the first seed in the Western Conference, with the Golden State Warriors claiming the second seed 7 games behind the leading Rockets. The year also saw James Harden, once again, astonish the world with his mesmerizing offensive prowess and earn the honor of being crowned the NBA MVP for the 2017/18 regular season. While the Rockets obtained, what was in their eyes, the best possible outcome in the regular season, they again came up short losing to the Golden State Warriors in the Western Conference Finals after being 3-2 up in the series and having the home-court advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This frustration carried over into the 2018/19 season, as the Rockets were unable to consistently stay above the 500 mark into mid-December, largely due to the injury of Chris Paul which sidelined him for roughly half of the season. Despite the slow start, the Rockets saw themselves in the 4th seed, due to the play of James Harden, who seems to have elevated his offensive arsenal to the point that holding him to under 25 points is considered a defensive victory. The Rockets, once again, fell to their foe (the Golden State Warriors) in 6 games in the Western Conference Semifinals, marking yet another early exit. Emotions ran extremely high following the devastating loss, as the Warriors were without Kevin Durant and were expected to lose the series to the Rockets. Soon thereafter, strong disgruntled feelings were reported between James Harden and Chris Paul. Despite the constant dismissal of these reports, this ultimately lead to another blockbuster acquisition by the Rockets this past season, as Harden was reunited with fellow MVP Russell Westbrook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reunification of a backcourt duo of Westbrook and Harden is extremely intriguing given their past playing experience with each other, as well as how their individual playing styles line up very similarly. It is difficult, and misleading, to look at the stats from the three seasons that they were teammates in Oklahoma City because Harden was more of a role-player, and neither had fully reached their offensive potentials that make them top-20 talent players in the current NBA. We, as fans, have learned from the Chris Paul experiment that the success of this acquisition will largely depend on the willingness of James Harden to share the ball. The purpose of the Paul trade in the 2017 offseason was to help take the pressure off of Harden, however, due to injury and ego, Harden put up 1909 field goal attempts, which is nearly 300 more shot attempts than the next highest season, which spans back to times when James Harden was the only offensive power helping the Rockets stay afloat. Harden’s game thrives off of his ability to handle the ball from the second it is inbounded, so the acquisition of another player (especially one that plays the point guard position by nature) that thrives off of holding the ball and making something happen slightly resembles the trade for Paul in the 2017 season, which never came to full fruition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the skepticism, Harden and Westbrook have a different relationship than that of Harden and Paul. Westbrook has the potential to thrive playing off the ball, something that Paul widely struggled with. If Harden and Westbrook are able to create a system in which neither are suffering from not being able to get their shots up, then the Rockets have the potential to bring the Larry O’Brien Trophy back to Houston for the first time since the back-to-back championships in 1994 and 1995. Eric Gordon, PJ Tucker and Clint Capela will most likely round out the rest of the starting five and place their respective starting rotation among the likes of every other top team in the league (Lakers, Clippers, Bucks, 76ers, etc.). With potential contributions off the bench from Tyson Chandler, Austin Rivers, Danuel House and Gerald Green, the Rockets are set-up well to ride the wave when Westbrook and Harden are getting breathers. The talent is definitely present in Houston, as it has been for several seasons. The large looming question is whether the acquisition of Russell Westbrook is more of the same, or if it is the start of a new Warrior-esque dynasty in the West. If good health and cohesion are present in the Rockets locker room, then so will be the Larry O’Brien Trophy come June 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gavin Olson</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="basketball" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">Houston has, perhaps, been one of the most perplexing franchises over the past three seasons because of their seemingly non-existent presence come playoff time. This second installment of breaking down the path to the Larry O’Brien Trophy will discuss the steps the Houston Rockets will need to take in order to finally get over the hump of their recent string of postseason woes, as well as why the Rockets have a strong chance of coming out on top of the 10-team gauntlet that is the Western Conference.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Marvel of Mediocrity</title><link href="/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Marvel of Mediocrity" /><published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A prisoner’s affliction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might contest this by speaking of war-torn Syrians or the muddle of mental health, but Gen Y and Gen Z are sufferers of the worst kind of affliction; the affliction of &lt;em&gt;mediocrity&lt;/em&gt;. What makes this affliction so bad is its non-threatening nature. And I beg your pardon, we are not sufferers of this affliction, we are its prisoners. But what has made us prisoners? And why is this such a big issue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tales from the West&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West has always had an influence, directly or indirectly, over the entire world. We have adopted many of their cultural idiosyncrasies and even live them out everyday, without consciously realising it. One such Western quirk we’ve embraced is &lt;em&gt;individualism&lt;/em&gt;. I am not claiming that the West holds prerogative of it, but they are the ones to have so earnestly sermonised the concept of individualism. Western literature preaches the purpose and value of individual worth; how the world is every individual’s oyster. To permeate the consciousness with a sense of personal worth, they even went a step ahead and materialised it through architecture, giving almost every member of the family a room of their own. Think of the sense of autonomy and powerfulness you feel when you sit in your room, sip coffee or whatever, and ask for nudes. You feel the illusion of having control over your life and that of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Indian subcontinent too, we have had literature that spoke of princes being born with a divine purpose, be it the Tiger King or the Buddha. For a layman back then, however, to have acquired such works was a rarity, and even if he did find himself with one, the stories held little relevance in his life. These factors prevented popularisation and consequentially, realisation of individualism through architecture. As the communal form of existence in families continued through the generations, the concept of individualism never bloomed. We believed in a person’s societal worth rather than personal worth, in caste values rather than personal value, in purpose according to status in society rather than according to an individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A global distress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this changed when globalisation happened. After decades of being hungover on colonialism, once again we got a whiff of the West, and couldn’t get enough of it. Since then, we’ve consumed it like opium until the concept of individualism solidified through material means, i.e. architecture. Today, an average suburban household has separate rooms for almost everyone in the family. This is an embodiment of the privileges which, earlier, we only got to see in films and books of the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how does any of this make us prisoners of mediocrity? The feeling of not being good enough stems from the inability to actualise the personal worth or capability that popular discourse and architecture tell us we’re born with. To begin with, the very sense of personal value gives birth to an ill child called mediocrity. Since birth, we have been taught that we are unique, that we have a purpose to fulfil and that there’s a special place for us in the grand scheme of things. While growing up, we started to realise that perhaps we aren’t as special as we once believed. Right then, along comes someone like Aamir Khan, convincing an entire generation to reinstate their belief in uniqueness. Our existence could exude confidence and hope, once again! Don’t get me wrong, I am not against hope or anything that his films have taught us, in fact, I am most grateful for those films. However, along with everything good comes a bad and possibly, even an ugly. Even though, we are yet to see the ugly one, we very much have seen the bad one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mediocre beginnings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have come too far, the concept is too distilled in our souls to now have an exorcism. We simply have to accept that we aren’t unique geniuses. Maybe, a moderate, uneventful life will be all that we ever get. Maybe, we will never be anyone’s first choice, but there are great benefits to being an average that must not be discounted. To begin with, if you’re mediocre, most people can relate to you. Sure, a genius is looked up to, but up there he’s all alone. A great example of this is the film &lt;em&gt;Green Book&lt;/em&gt;, based on a trip taken to the south of the Mason-Dixon Line by Don Shirley, a famous black classical pianist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a remarkable scene, Mahershala Ali who plays Don Shirley says to his valet, Tony Lip, “Yes, I live in a castle, Tony. Alone! And rich people pay me to play piano for them because it makes them feel cultured, but as soon I step off that step, I go back to being just another n&lt;em&gt;**** to them. Because that is their true culture. But I suffer that slight alone because I am not like by my own people ‘cause I am not like them either.” This is a classic example of the kind of isolation a genius feels and it is common people like Tony Lip, the classic mediocre who lives a more fulfilled life, which is not to say that being a genius is bad and you should avoid it all costs (but if you were one you probably wouldn’t be reading this article right now). Taking a bit more from the example of *Green Book&lt;/em&gt;, Tony Lip lived a life of equilibrium, where he earned sufficiently, had the love of his friends and family, and was well received by the people around him. That kept him happy. At the end of the day, we cannot deny our most basic urge of socialising and wanting to be loved. Being a genius, more often than not, creates a distance between the admirer and the admired. As a mediocre, it is easier to strike a balance in life and to keep a clear and simple vision of it, something most geniuses struggle with. Leaf through the pages of history, and you’ll see that the most revered personalities also suffered the most through their lifetime. Your name living on, hundreds of years after your death, might sound like a golden prospect but what is the point, if your life has been nothing but suffering and despair? Look at it from a different angle, as a genius, you could have been the next Hitler. Hitler was an extremist with strong beliefs and it doesn’t matter if we agree to it or not, he was a genius; a genius too caught up in his own ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The complaisant man&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it is not easy to be a genius, but it also isn’t easy to be mediocre. A genius progresses in life and eventually finds meaninglessness. We, on the other hand, are mostly stagnant, and have to generate and believe in meanings to live by. We need to be ignorant, sometimes knowingly, to our conditions because being aware is not of much help. The genius, however, gets to be enlightened. He is a Sisyphus, aware of the futility of his actions, yet forced to carry the burden of changing the course of history. Whenever history is reshaped, by a single force, there live people who partake in that change and, in a way, make that change possible. They are the average Joes, the mediocres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take no shame in being a mediocre. Unlike a genius, being average requires denying a lot of our basic wants as curious beings and I am willing to trade those curiosities for a more fulfilled life. In the end, we’re all ignorant, what matters is how you exercise your ignorance to live more pleasantly. Just as the world needs the greats, it needs the averages. So, do not fret about not having a personal worth, because you do. Life is not short, as some say, it’s long enough to fill our lives with misery. It is, however, not in the pursuit of excellence but in the pursuit of absolute happiness, which albeit unattainable, that we can find liberation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">A prisoner’s affliction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age</title><link href="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age" /><published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age">&lt;p&gt;The first of The Pangean’s &lt;em&gt;pubcasts&lt;/em&gt; is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirandamowbray/&quot;&gt;Dr Miranda Mowbray&lt;/a&gt;, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/harsh.tiwari/&quot;&gt;Harsh Tiwari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/reuben.pritchard/&quot;&gt;Reuben Pritchard&lt;/a&gt; sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology as a replacement for human interaction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(60)&quot;&gt;01:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology in business and politics&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(1203)&quot;&gt;20:03&lt;/a&gt;), or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The accessibility of technology&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2142)&quot;&gt;35:42&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast1-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-1&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>the.pangean</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The first of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Dr Miranda Mowbray, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data. In this podcast, Harsh Tiwari and Reuben Pritchard sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest: Introduction (00:00), Technology as a replacement for human interaction (01:00), Technology in business and politics (20:03), or The accessibility of technology (35:42). Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary></entry></feed>