<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-18T18:31:47+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Circle of Fire: A Lament and Lesson for Europe</title><link href="/Circle-of-Fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Circle of Fire: A Lament and Lesson for Europe" /><published>2019-04-11T04:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-11T04:29:00+00:00</updated><id>/Circle-of-Fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Circle-of-Fire">&lt;p&gt;1818, in a dusty, dawn-cast attic of a stately home, a statue begins to turn
from the grey of shaped limestone to the radiant gold of marble. It is a copy of
a very old Roman copy, of a Greek sculpture: “The Dying Gaul”, as commissioned
by Attalus I of Pergamon while celebrating his victory over the Celts of Turkey
in the 3rd Century BCE. In the dusty room, at daybreak, an amber light shines on
the torque tightly clasping the statue’s neck, a circle somehow proud, yet
broken, beneath his downcast brow. The “Dying Gaul” is depicted as so dismal, so
dejected a thing that many observe an inherent sadness in him. Admiring the
skill of the artist, even Lord Byron himself writes about the pathos engendered
by the scene. However, he dubs him &lt;em&gt;The Dying Gladiator&lt;/em&gt;, and so even as an art
piece, this lost, false picture of a man is, like his race, truly forgotten.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many miles away, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan, a Sikh wears a “Chakram” as he
prepares for a wedding ceremony. These metal rings recalling the mythological
weapon of the Hindu god Krishna, the disc-bearer. Despite having lost their
practical functionality after the British arrived, “chakrams” retain their
symbolic importance. Even in a Punjabi wedding, Indo-European Vedic traditions
remain, as a bride to be wedded has her feet painted in Mehndi by a woman older
than herself and already happily married.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So telling, how these traits of myth may endure, even through the ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of mythology, of all “divine poetry”, is to act as superlative verse to
the layman’s consideration of the passing day, to act as sacred words which fill
colour into the profane of our world. In fact, we might see our culture itself
as a sort of divine consort, as a partner to our existence, and determine that
an individual divested of culture is lonely. Our cultural identity is,
therefore, our spouse and it is given to us by our heritage. Ultimately, the
only thing which separates one group of people from another is the place they
are situated in, and religious beliefs are formed dependent on the surroundings
of said people. You would only pray for the sorts of things your lands made
plentiful or precious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, what follows is this: all mythology encompasses the relationship of a
people with their geological environment. This makes all religion, all cultural
heritage an ontological understanding of one’s surroundings. We process the
existence we know. That is the truly pagan way of being in oneself, that is the
truly human way. Nature will teach you; it will teach you everything. Nature has
many faces, but one voice and we must remember that Mother Nature has no
obligation to be fair to you. Neither do natural forces. But you can try to
understand them. Even, dare I say, try to communicate with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All religion serves to reconcile the distance between the earthly and the
heavenly, and it seems one patch of Earth, lived upon by one people in
opposition to another, becomes a different Earth. And the force which marries us
to our geographically-defined culture, religion, etc., is the same which would
bind one person to another. Once, what was called Sati in one place was observed
in different forms in others. Accounts from Ibn Fadlan and the verses from the
&lt;em&gt;Sigurðarkviða hin skamma&lt;/em&gt; assert that Norse people would offer up a wealthy
Chieftain’s &lt;em&gt;thralls&lt;/em&gt; or slaves, to his funeral pyre after his passing, and
Julius Caesar says the same of the Celts in &lt;em&gt;De Bello Gallico&lt;/em&gt;. This Roman
account is the origin of the ‘Wicker Man’ stereotype, where beloved ‘dependants’
of the deceased are given up along with other offerings to be purified into
something others would call &lt;em&gt;Agni&lt;/em&gt;, the sacred fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be more virtuous to plaster all discourse pertaining to such things
with comments on the barbarous vestiges of a less appropriately enlightened
past, but it might be more useful still to understand why people would do such
things. And so go from “ignorance to truth, darkness to light, and death to
immortality,” as per that enigmatic mantra echoed in Hindu Yagna rituals, it
would seem. If truth could be light. If that light could be immortality, it
would take the shape of a fire fed by and specified by one’s very beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how our belief ties us to our people, to our lands. We live and die by
them. We do not simply have our culture follow us into the fire. We go because
of it. And whether that is ethically speaking without blemish or not, it is
certainly powerful. We do things which seem illogical, which other animals do
not do. A culture is a truth, it is an understanding of the world. In such a
way, it considers rules and identifies what is to be prized in this
understanding of the world, and what is to be deemed more unsightly. And this is
the nature of our identities, as humans, as ethnicities. This is how we are
married to our cultures, not in bondage, but in heritage, as per a hypernatural,
proto-legal contract. This is us. &lt;em&gt;Alive&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Europe is becoming even less alive itself, because it is becoming less
Christian, which in and of itself would not necessitate unfortunate
circumstances, if only it did not entail the rise of Atheism. As a consequence,
Europe becomes ‘more lonely’. It manages the extraordinary feat of being somehow
formed of so many countries which remain so impossibly isolated from each other.
Yet, indeed, it is natural that this continent should have no faith, and no
faith in itself, for such things were bored out of it by the Romans and
Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my customary finding that things usually succeed in doing what they were
designed to do, and Christianity was designed to make the European people
complacent and easy to control. No wonder that as it falls, as the Church
awakens to every nightmare about paedophilia accusations in this hypocritical
bed it has made for itself, Europeans are not only impossible to control, but
they are directionless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity is more impactful from a cultural perspective than a spiritual one;
it served as a device of enforcing the Roman rule and extending the duration of
their Empire, supplanting an enduring (arguably militant) presence in their
lands as an oppressive crushing of culture on a local scale, imposing a single
identity-defining dogma. It was applied to control, and now the people are
uncontrollable, and inconsolably unruly since the Roman rule has decayed. Yet,
it is the state of the dominated to retain their chains after their master has
met their demise. It is surprising Europe has taken so long to throw off the
very yoke of Christendom in the first place. Albeit, Christianity had been
unknowingly preserving truly European, pagan culture. And, as it falls, so does
its inherited identity. Atheism has come and it brings with it a cold, stark
divestment of the European spirit from the European body. This makes every man
and woman less than human, for all different world cultures, all at least have a
notion of the spirit, and a cornered animal lashes out because it is afraid,
outnumbered, perhaps. &lt;em&gt;Alone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a time of division. Even as we speak, conversations are cracking open
about the consequences of Brexit in regards to Ireland’s relationship with
Northern Ireland, and while a united Éire may seem like a step forward, it also
indicates the breaking down of a much older order. One thing upon which we all
can agree is that changes are afoot. For better or for worse, it seems this
great and old continent will never be the same again. The end of individual
difference, so surely the end of our differences altogether, no? Ultimate unity
through ultimate, violent equity. Of course, it is rather beneficial for Church
and State alike to have its people be without identity; they are so much easier
to pra(e)y upon! And so, behold the touted saviour: &lt;em&gt;Socialism&lt;/em&gt;. It is at the
heart of globalisation, but socialism was purely and only an advent of chaos, a
machine designed to destroy. Karl Marx did not want to help the working classes,
but he did want to make them kill people, often each other.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marx believed a great change was on the horizon, but the problem with his ideas
was that he believed the change could only and must be reached via great
conflict. He believed society was on the verge of collapse, he never incited
peaceful resolution or the empowerment of workers and always sought only to arm
them rather than communicate with them. When he visited the German Workers’
Education Society of London in 1845, he found self-educated, self-made men. They
were anti-liberal, anti-bohemian and practically-minded, and he saw them as
lowly for not sharing his apocalyptic ambitions for the future. They engaged in
practical discussion, though without academic training in philosophy (which is
why he disliked working men and thought them beneath himself). This was not what
he wanted. He wanted revolution and chaos, for as he stated: “Socialism cannot
be brought into existence without revolution”. When his father died in 1838, he
spent much of his inheritance of 6000 ₣ on arming Belgian workers with guns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, the violent revolutions of the country I grew up in, France, have a
long history indeed of upheaving everything and distracting from the country’s
problems until they go away, but they ultimately benefited slightly wealthier
men seizing power, only to be deposed by men slightly less wealthy than
themselves. Every time, it is the slightly less hard-working man who gains
leadership at the expense of the slightly harder working man. The same can be
seen in the French-backed American Revolution, a systematic upheaval which
allowed wealthy English landowners in the New World to detach themselves from
their colonial control of ‘The British’ under the new identity of ‘The
American’, and they profited and suffered immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, marrying oneself to a new culture, a new identity, will dictate one’s
destiny. And so come into focus the fires of modern-day Paris, lit by the Gilets
Jaunes. Fire once more presides the times of chaos, the times of change. So how,
I ask, can this, revolution, be the answer? I cannot agree that Marx was right
in the larger sense that it is necessary, but I must wonder as to his related
belief that it is inevitable. Visions of fire, revolution and chaos, and one
must think of the Wheel of Fire, a Greek mythological image originating in the
punishment of Ixion after his lusting for Zeus’s divine consort, Hera. It
signifies a torturous chain of events leading to dire consequences, in result of
personal actions or flaws which are ultimately the victim’s fault. It provides a
caveat to be considered, in matters of want and misplaced ambition. It is the
fall from grace, and it is engendered by the foreboding betrayal of a sacred
matrimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I attend a concert by the folk-rock band Faun, at the end, a skaldic
lutist/mandolin player speaks as a grandiose orator, transforming from the
humble, weaselly man he has been every other time we hear him speak into
something approaching the divine musician we have seen play, as when he
performs, as when he sings. His band’s spectacle reaches an emotive pinnacle as
he speaks, almost preaching now, but with such zeal the likes of which a
hurricane could not bring any modern Christian priest to muster, with the
passion not seen since they were not merely excused by the burning of our wise
women but corralled it. The kind of power not seen unless truth and conviction
bolster the rightful in their unextinguished focus; he says we must remember who
we are. Remember nature. Our own nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he speaks in his complete form, finally, but only once, is mentioned the
creature who is the namesake of the band, the faun, the Pan figure, who just
like Krishna plays the flute and sits surrounded by the animals, a Master of
Beasts. And then he says how it was known by another name to the Celts, as
Cernunnos. Thus begins the cycle. A vision of a devil. A vision of nature,
personified. A herald of flame to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I contemplate this apple of my eye which I see on the horizon. Knowledge
of paganism is the knowledge of how to live and connect with our environment of
Europe, and so I say that, for the West, to transcend Christendom via the
produce of the trees of knowledge is the only way that we will be able to live
in this garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The serpent penetrates the apple. Perhaps, it is to be seized, like the
Snake-Witch Stone shows, perhaps it is to be defeated like the biblical
Leviathan. But it is no primitive return to nature which will save us now, but a
mature and learned taking into oneself the ways of yore. We must make of
ourselves ergonomic beings. A form of cultural bio-mimicry will be observed in
ancient lore, and this will tell us how to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, there are philosophies and facts to be observed in the natural
world, echoed in mythology, which can inform us on how to live our lives, so we
can be healthier, but also on how we should think, so we can be &lt;em&gt;holier&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I think on this vision, I must wonder what ‘true spiritual sun’ will be
unveiled to us, ‘hidden by a disc of golden light’. What truth will be known,
what duty done? What sacred feet, anointed now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking to the future, for Europe, for the world? &lt;em&gt;Fire&lt;/em&gt;. But will it be a wheel
or a dawn? This will depend on the nature, the aspect and, I fear, upon the
reception of this, the &lt;em&gt;Truth&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tales of myth and history weave in and out of each other, they remind us
of our inherent shared heritage defined not as humans, but as people. For, in
commiseration with history, mythology serves not only to grant us stories from
the past where we may learn how to rise, but also stories of the soul, that we
may learn not to fall. And what these similarities do tell us is that Europe
should be united under common ground, regardless of any Union - so long as it
remains European. As such, it is time Europe decided to whom it would be married
and what is to be the philosophical companion to its destiny, what identity will
accompany it towards an uncertain future. Some would say we look outside, or
without. I merely say we look within.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Morgan Black</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">1818, in a dusty, dawn-cast attic of a stately home, a statue begins to turn from the grey of shaped limestone to the radiant gold of marble. It is a copy of a very old Roman copy, of a Greek sculpture: “The Dying Gaul”, as commissioned by Attalus I of Pergamon while celebrating his victory over the Celts of Turkey in the 3rd Century BCE. In the dusty room, at daybreak, an amber light shines on the torque tightly clasping the statue’s neck, a circle somehow proud, yet broken, beneath his downcast brow. The “Dying Gaul” is depicted as so dismal, so dejected a thing that many observe an inherent sadness in him. Admiring the skill of the artist, even Lord Byron himself writes about the pathos engendered by the scene. However, he dubs him The Dying Gladiator, and so even as an art piece, this lost, false picture of a man is, like his race, truly forgotten.   Many miles away, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan, a Sikh wears a “Chakram” as he prepares for a wedding ceremony. These metal rings recalling the mythological weapon of the Hindu god Krishna, the disc-bearer. Despite having lost their practical functionality after the British arrived, “chakrams” retain their symbolic importance. Even in a Punjabi wedding, Indo-European Vedic traditions remain, as a bride to be wedded has her feet painted in Mehndi by a woman older than herself and already happily married. So telling, how these traits of myth may endure, even through the ages. The role of mythology, of all “divine poetry”, is to act as superlative verse to the layman’s consideration of the passing day, to act as sacred words which fill colour into the profane of our world. In fact, we might see our culture itself as a sort of divine consort, as a partner to our existence, and determine that an individual divested of culture is lonely. Our cultural identity is, therefore, our spouse and it is given to us by our heritage. Ultimately, the only thing which separates one group of people from another is the place they are situated in, and religious beliefs are formed dependent on the surroundings of said people. You would only pray for the sorts of things your lands made plentiful or precious. Therefore, what follows is this: all mythology encompasses the relationship of a people with their geological environment. This makes all religion, all cultural heritage an ontological understanding of one’s surroundings. We process the existence we know. That is the truly pagan way of being in oneself, that is the truly human way. Nature will teach you; it will teach you everything. Nature has many faces, but one voice and we must remember that Mother Nature has no obligation to be fair to you. Neither do natural forces. But you can try to understand them. Even, dare I say, try to communicate with them. All religion serves to reconcile the distance between the earthly and the heavenly, and it seems one patch of Earth, lived upon by one people in opposition to another, becomes a different Earth. And the force which marries us to our geographically-defined culture, religion, etc., is the same which would bind one person to another. Once, what was called Sati in one place was observed in different forms in others. Accounts from Ibn Fadlan and the verses from the Sigurðarkviða hin skamma assert that Norse people would offer up a wealthy Chieftain’s thralls or slaves, to his funeral pyre after his passing, and Julius Caesar says the same of the Celts in De Bello Gallico. This Roman account is the origin of the ‘Wicker Man’ stereotype, where beloved ‘dependants’ of the deceased are given up along with other offerings to be purified into something others would call Agni, the sacred fire. It might be more virtuous to plaster all discourse pertaining to such things with comments on the barbarous vestiges of a less appropriately enlightened past, but it might be more useful still to understand why people would do such things. And so go from “ignorance to truth, darkness to light, and death to immortality,” as per that enigmatic mantra echoed in Hindu Yagna rituals, it would seem. If truth could be light. If that light could be immortality, it would take the shape of a fire fed by and specified by one’s very beliefs. This is how our belief ties us to our people, to our lands. We live and die by them. We do not simply have our culture follow us into the fire. We go because of it. And whether that is ethically speaking without blemish or not, it is certainly powerful. We do things which seem illogical, which other animals do not do. A culture is a truth, it is an understanding of the world. In such a way, it considers rules and identifies what is to be prized in this understanding of the world, and what is to be deemed more unsightly. And this is the nature of our identities, as humans, as ethnicities. This is how we are married to our cultures, not in bondage, but in heritage, as per a hypernatural, proto-legal contract. This is us. Alive. But Europe is becoming even less alive itself, because it is becoming less Christian, which in and of itself would not necessitate unfortunate circumstances, if only it did not entail the rise of Atheism. As a consequence, Europe becomes ‘more lonely’. It manages the extraordinary feat of being somehow formed of so many countries which remain so impossibly isolated from each other. Yet, indeed, it is natural that this continent should have no faith, and no faith in itself, for such things were bored out of it by the Romans and Christianity. It is my customary finding that things usually succeed in doing what they were designed to do, and Christianity was designed to make the European people complacent and easy to control. No wonder that as it falls, as the Church awakens to every nightmare about paedophilia accusations in this hypocritical bed it has made for itself, Europeans are not only impossible to control, but they are directionless. Christianity is more impactful from a cultural perspective than a spiritual one; it served as a device of enforcing the Roman rule and extending the duration of their Empire, supplanting an enduring (arguably militant) presence in their lands as an oppressive crushing of culture on a local scale, imposing a single identity-defining dogma. It was applied to control, and now the people are uncontrollable, and inconsolably unruly since the Roman rule has decayed. Yet, it is the state of the dominated to retain their chains after their master has met their demise. It is surprising Europe has taken so long to throw off the very yoke of Christendom in the first place. Albeit, Christianity had been unknowingly preserving truly European, pagan culture. And, as it falls, so does its inherited identity. Atheism has come and it brings with it a cold, stark divestment of the European spirit from the European body. This makes every man and woman less than human, for all different world cultures, all at least have a notion of the spirit, and a cornered animal lashes out because it is afraid, outnumbered, perhaps. Alone. This is a time of division. Even as we speak, conversations are cracking open about the consequences of Brexit in regards to Ireland’s relationship with Northern Ireland, and while a united Éire may seem like a step forward, it also indicates the breaking down of a much older order. One thing upon which we all can agree is that changes are afoot. For better or for worse, it seems this great and old continent will never be the same again. The end of individual difference, so surely the end of our differences altogether, no? Ultimate unity through ultimate, violent equity. Of course, it is rather beneficial for Church and State alike to have its people be without identity; they are so much easier to pra(e)y upon! And so, behold the touted saviour: Socialism. It is at the heart of globalisation, but socialism was purely and only an advent of chaos, a machine designed to destroy. Karl Marx did not want to help the working classes, but he did want to make them kill people, often each other.   Marx believed a great change was on the horizon, but the problem with his ideas was that he believed the change could only and must be reached via great conflict. He believed society was on the verge of collapse, he never incited peaceful resolution or the empowerment of workers and always sought only to arm them rather than communicate with them. When he visited the German Workers’ Education Society of London in 1845, he found self-educated, self-made men. They were anti-liberal, anti-bohemian and practically-minded, and he saw them as lowly for not sharing his apocalyptic ambitions for the future. They engaged in practical discussion, though without academic training in philosophy (which is why he disliked working men and thought them beneath himself). This was not what he wanted. He wanted revolution and chaos, for as he stated: “Socialism cannot be brought into existence without revolution”. When his father died in 1838, he spent much of his inheritance of 6000 ₣ on arming Belgian workers with guns. Certainly, the violent revolutions of the country I grew up in, France, have a long history indeed of upheaving everything and distracting from the country’s problems until they go away, but they ultimately benefited slightly wealthier men seizing power, only to be deposed by men slightly less wealthy than themselves. Every time, it is the slightly less hard-working man who gains leadership at the expense of the slightly harder working man. The same can be seen in the French-backed American Revolution, a systematic upheaval which allowed wealthy English landowners in the New World to detach themselves from their colonial control of ‘The British’ under the new identity of ‘The American’, and they profited and suffered immensely. Again, marrying oneself to a new culture, a new identity, will dictate one’s destiny. And so come into focus the fires of modern-day Paris, lit by the Gilets Jaunes. Fire once more presides the times of chaos, the times of change. So how, I ask, can this, revolution, be the answer? I cannot agree that Marx was right in the larger sense that it is necessary, but I must wonder as to his related belief that it is inevitable. Visions of fire, revolution and chaos, and one must think of the Wheel of Fire, a Greek mythological image originating in the punishment of Ixion after his lusting for Zeus’s divine consort, Hera. It signifies a torturous chain of events leading to dire consequences, in result of personal actions or flaws which are ultimately the victim’s fault. It provides a caveat to be considered, in matters of want and misplaced ambition. It is the fall from grace, and it is engendered by the foreboding betrayal of a sacred matrimony. As I attend a concert by the folk-rock band Faun, at the end, a skaldic lutist/mandolin player speaks as a grandiose orator, transforming from the humble, weaselly man he has been every other time we hear him speak into something approaching the divine musician we have seen play, as when he performs, as when he sings. His band’s spectacle reaches an emotive pinnacle as he speaks, almost preaching now, but with such zeal the likes of which a hurricane could not bring any modern Christian priest to muster, with the passion not seen since they were not merely excused by the burning of our wise women but corralled it. The kind of power not seen unless truth and conviction bolster the rightful in their unextinguished focus; he says we must remember who we are. Remember nature. Our own nature. As he speaks in his complete form, finally, but only once, is mentioned the creature who is the namesake of the band, the faun, the Pan figure, who just like Krishna plays the flute and sits surrounded by the animals, a Master of Beasts. And then he says how it was known by another name to the Celts, as Cernunnos. Thus begins the cycle. A vision of a devil. A vision of nature, personified. A herald of flame to come. And so I contemplate this apple of my eye which I see on the horizon. Knowledge of paganism is the knowledge of how to live and connect with our environment of Europe, and so I say that, for the West, to transcend Christendom via the produce of the trees of knowledge is the only way that we will be able to live in this garden. The serpent penetrates the apple. Perhaps, it is to be seized, like the Snake-Witch Stone shows, perhaps it is to be defeated like the biblical Leviathan. But it is no primitive return to nature which will save us now, but a mature and learned taking into oneself the ways of yore. We must make of ourselves ergonomic beings. A form of cultural bio-mimicry will be observed in ancient lore, and this will tell us how to be. Simply put, there are philosophies and facts to be observed in the natural world, echoed in mythology, which can inform us on how to live our lives, so we can be healthier, but also on how we should think, so we can be holier. As I think on this vision, I must wonder what ‘true spiritual sun’ will be unveiled to us, ‘hidden by a disc of golden light’. What truth will be known, what duty done? What sacred feet, anointed now? Looking to the future, for Europe, for the world? Fire. But will it be a wheel or a dawn? This will depend on the nature, the aspect and, I fear, upon the reception of this, the Truth. These tales of myth and history weave in and out of each other, they remind us of our inherent shared heritage defined not as humans, but as people. For, in commiseration with history, mythology serves not only to grant us stories from the past where we may learn how to rise, but also stories of the soul, that we may learn not to fall. And what these similarities do tell us is that Europe should be united under common ground, regardless of any Union - so long as it remains European. As such, it is time Europe decided to whom it would be married and what is to be the philosophical companion to its destiny, what identity will accompany it towards an uncertain future. Some would say we look outside, or without. I merely say we look within.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The (Un)faithfuls</title><link href="/The-Unfaithfuls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The (Un)faithfuls" /><published>2019-04-10T11:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-10T11:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Unfaithfuls</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unfaithfuls">&lt;p&gt;I recently had a breakdown of sorts, and the stifling confines of my room
tightened its shadows on me, as I desperately tried to get out of that place.
But where would I have gone? I certainly had no means to a Tesla or the unending
country roads to hit like BoJack Horseman, so I ended up quietly muffling my
screams in my pillow. And while I was grappling with desperation to end my life,
my eyes met God’s. Before I venture any further with the narrative, I must tell
you that I am the son of a devout Hindu, so it is quite natural for the walls of
my room to be installed not with posters of cool bands and stuff but with
posters of cool swagger Gods. My mother, who I dearly adore, has tried her fair
share and beyond to turn me into a devout as herself, but has not fared so well
yet. The least I could do was not frustrate her attempt at installing Durga’s (a
Hindu Warrior Goddess) poster in the most visible spot in my room. Initially,
her belief was that it would aid me to gradually turn into a god-fearing inmate
as herself, but now she has given up all hopes on me and doesn’t care as long as
I do no harm to her or society in general―especially by spreading or committing
blasphemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when my eyes met God’s, I felt the excruciating urge to ask for her
help–putting myself in another struggle with my rational self–which clearly has
not yet accredited any credibility to the existence of any such deity and
considers it a sham. There, in the midst of this struggle, both my selves
settled on a critical question: why is faith important if it is a scam? To
answer this, I had to first address the victims of atheism: the millennial or
Generation Y. As evidenced by memes, a more than qualified instrument to gauge
the collective mindset of the globalised culture of the millennial, we are all
pseudo-nihilists and pseudo-existentialists with no particular belief system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This culture of disbelief is a stark characteristic of this generation and is so
as a consequence of science, which has with all its enigma deinstitutionalised
the notion of religion or anything that it entails. Now, what I have to ask here
is, if it has deinstitutionalised the institutions of faith, what does it
provide us in return? What does it offer us to cling on to when we are at our
worst? Does it offer itself us a replacement or does it offer the idea that we
are apex beings and nothing is higher than us? Now, although I am not in denial
of science’s contributions towards human society, what my problem is that
science is at the end of the day esoteric, exclusive. It is not everyone’s club
to join, and so the multitude with all its disillusionment is without a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science has taught us that we exist for no purpose and our existence is more of
a chance happening than something in the blueprint of a god. Science has since
its birth marshalled forward to perish existing belief systems, appropriating
the office of the apex belief system to itself. No wonder why such extreme
efforts are made for space expeditions, it is because science has run out of
things to unravel; science has run out of purpose as well but is simply
continuing with the faith in its purpose of serving mankind in ways greater than
itself. Ironically enough, while science has robbed us of the notion of faith
and belief and has left us naked to the vile truth of the universe, it has
itself nestled in the belief of something greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we understand the importance of faith or communal belief systems. I am not
a student of theology so pardon my ill-service towards what I am going to say,
but, in my belief, communions or religions have existed since societies were
conceived for a very real reason. A society just like any organisation is
unmanageable without a fixed set of rules and morality that everyone who is a
part of such has to adhere to. This fixed set of rules and conduct of morality
has with time festered into unquestionable beliefs called religions. Now, where
religions came in handy back in the day was that they gave men a sense of
purpose. And, as is evident, man needs a purpose to go on in life. The piety
towards those set of rules existed because men believed that we exist for a
purpose and by following those rules we would have served that purpose and at
last be in the hands of Nirvana or whatever it is called around the world. I am
not at all bailing religion out of the many evils it has committed, but what
good it has reaped has to be stated. Religion’s greatest victory was that it
took the human psyche into consideration, unlike science, and pandered to our
greatest need, the need for validation. Now, this might seem like a coarse
conclusion, but this is what it is. Human species, in general, has the vehement
need to be validated, of our deeds in particular and existence in general. It is
this need for validation that gave birth to the question of “What is the purpose
of life?” And that is where many irrational beliefs of religion come into aid.
Reason gives us the validation we require in life and also places us in the
hands of faith which can get us through our most devastating times—giving us
meaning and purpose throughout all of it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it may seem like I am antagonising science and making religion the
protagonist, but that is not the case. I am simply defending the case of
religion where it is due: it has given men a purpose and a belief in the fallacy
that there is something higher than us who is watching over us in our thinnest
of times. Some might argue here that it is better to be out of the shackles of
religion and feel liberated at being able to create our own purpose as Nietzsche
proposed, I argue otherwise.  What Nietzsche has proposed doesn’t apply to the
multitude; the multitude isn’t capable enough to create their own purpose in
life and requires a master to guide them. Imagine a herd of sheep bound by
fences - they stay in it, they work in it, and one day, a novel sheep kills the
master and breaks the fence and opens the sheep to an unending expanse. Although
at first, the change might enthral them, slowly they’d start feeling lost and
purposeless, because now they do not serve anything or anyone and are simply
roaming free. After a while, they scamper in insanity to find a purpose, but due
to their limited intelligence and faculties, they fall short. It goes fairly
Orwellian from there, the sheep, tired of such liberty again hands themselves
over to a new master, and that master in our case is science. Although science
has done great services to the society and we have enjoyed such for a long time,
we now have come to a standstill where nothing makes sense anymore and our
existence is boiled down to absurdity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, although religion has propagated many evils, it has time and again given men
purpose and a much needed coping mechanism to deal with their problems. And now
that we are disillusioned and hopeless, it might not do us much harm to commit
the psychological suicide that Albert Camus proposed, because unlike those
thinkers, we are a herd of simpletons with limited faculties. But that is not
possible at this stage, so I guess we are simply doomed with depression. All we
can simply do is stall our time by looking at memes.  &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">I recently had a breakdown of sorts, and the stifling confines of my room tightened its shadows on me, as I desperately tried to get out of that place. But where would I have gone? I certainly had no means to a Tesla or the unending country roads to hit like BoJack Horseman, so I ended up quietly muffling my screams in my pillow. And while I was grappling with desperation to end my life, my eyes met God’s. Before I venture any further with the narrative, I must tell you that I am the son of a devout Hindu, so it is quite natural for the walls of my room to be installed not with posters of cool bands and stuff but with posters of cool swagger Gods. My mother, who I dearly adore, has tried her fair share and beyond to turn me into a devout as herself, but has not fared so well yet. The least I could do was not frustrate her attempt at installing Durga’s (a Hindu Warrior Goddess) poster in the most visible spot in my room. Initially, her belief was that it would aid me to gradually turn into a god-fearing inmate as herself, but now she has given up all hopes on me and doesn’t care as long as I do no harm to her or society in general―especially by spreading or committing blasphemies. Now, when my eyes met God’s, I felt the excruciating urge to ask for her help–putting myself in another struggle with my rational self–which clearly has not yet accredited any credibility to the existence of any such deity and considers it a sham. There, in the midst of this struggle, both my selves settled on a critical question: why is faith important if it is a scam? To answer this, I had to first address the victims of atheism: the millennial or Generation Y. As evidenced by memes, a more than qualified instrument to gauge the collective mindset of the globalised culture of the millennial, we are all pseudo-nihilists and pseudo-existentialists with no particular belief system. This culture of disbelief is a stark characteristic of this generation and is so as a consequence of science, which has with all its enigma deinstitutionalised the notion of religion or anything that it entails. Now, what I have to ask here is, if it has deinstitutionalised the institutions of faith, what does it provide us in return? What does it offer us to cling on to when we are at our worst? Does it offer itself us a replacement or does it offer the idea that we are apex beings and nothing is higher than us? Now, although I am not in denial of science’s contributions towards human society, what my problem is that science is at the end of the day esoteric, exclusive. It is not everyone’s club to join, and so the multitude with all its disillusionment is without a purpose. Science has taught us that we exist for no purpose and our existence is more of a chance happening than something in the blueprint of a god. Science has since its birth marshalled forward to perish existing belief systems, appropriating the office of the apex belief system to itself. No wonder why such extreme efforts are made for space expeditions, it is because science has run out of things to unravel; science has run out of purpose as well but is simply continuing with the faith in its purpose of serving mankind in ways greater than itself. Ironically enough, while science has robbed us of the notion of faith and belief and has left us naked to the vile truth of the universe, it has itself nestled in the belief of something greater. Here we understand the importance of faith or communal belief systems. I am not a student of theology so pardon my ill-service towards what I am going to say, but, in my belief, communions or religions have existed since societies were conceived for a very real reason. A society just like any organisation is unmanageable without a fixed set of rules and morality that everyone who is a part of such has to adhere to. This fixed set of rules and conduct of morality has with time festered into unquestionable beliefs called religions. Now, where religions came in handy back in the day was that they gave men a sense of purpose. And, as is evident, man needs a purpose to go on in life. The piety towards those set of rules existed because men believed that we exist for a purpose and by following those rules we would have served that purpose and at last be in the hands of Nirvana or whatever it is called around the world. I am not at all bailing religion out of the many evils it has committed, but what good it has reaped has to be stated. Religion’s greatest victory was that it took the human psyche into consideration, unlike science, and pandered to our greatest need, the need for validation. Now, this might seem like a coarse conclusion, but this is what it is. Human species, in general, has the vehement need to be validated, of our deeds in particular and existence in general. It is this need for validation that gave birth to the question of “What is the purpose of life?” And that is where many irrational beliefs of religion come into aid. Reason gives us the validation we require in life and also places us in the hands of faith which can get us through our most devastating times—giving us meaning and purpose throughout all of it.   Now, it may seem like I am antagonising science and making religion the protagonist, but that is not the case. I am simply defending the case of religion where it is due: it has given men a purpose and a belief in the fallacy that there is something higher than us who is watching over us in our thinnest of times. Some might argue here that it is better to be out of the shackles of religion and feel liberated at being able to create our own purpose as Nietzsche proposed, I argue otherwise.  What Nietzsche has proposed doesn’t apply to the multitude; the multitude isn’t capable enough to create their own purpose in life and requires a master to guide them. Imagine a herd of sheep bound by fences - they stay in it, they work in it, and one day, a novel sheep kills the master and breaks the fence and opens the sheep to an unending expanse. Although at first, the change might enthral them, slowly they’d start feeling lost and purposeless, because now they do not serve anything or anyone and are simply roaming free. After a while, they scamper in insanity to find a purpose, but due to their limited intelligence and faculties, they fall short. It goes fairly Orwellian from there, the sheep, tired of such liberty again hands themselves over to a new master, and that master in our case is science. Although science has done great services to the society and we have enjoyed such for a long time, we now have come to a standstill where nothing makes sense anymore and our existence is boiled down to absurdity. So, although religion has propagated many evils, it has time and again given men purpose and a much needed coping mechanism to deal with their problems. And now that we are disillusioned and hopeless, it might not do us much harm to commit the psychological suicide that Albert Camus proposed, because unlike those thinkers, we are a herd of simpletons with limited faculties. But that is not possible at this stage, so I guess we are simply doomed with depression. All we can simply do is stall our time by looking at memes.  </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Golan Heights: Will the Six-Day War Ever Come to an End?</title><link href="/Golan-Heights" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Golan Heights: Will the Six-Day War Ever Come to an End?" /><published>2019-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Golan-Heights</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Golan-Heights">&lt;p&gt;“The Golan Heights will forever remain in Israel’s hands. Israel will never come down from the Golan Heights”: With these words, the Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu commenced his cabinet session on March 24, 2019. Israel and Syria have been contesting over the region since the Six-Day War in June 1976. His speech, in which he repeatedly reinforced Israel’s claim over the Golan Heights, went ahead to eclipse all public forums and debates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that his speech was either intended as an election gimmick, to woo the general masses towards the strength of their leader, or, more ominously, an indication to propagate Israel’s powerful foreign policy. Many viewed it as a move to draw focus from a global audience - not just Syrian or Arab, but Russian and American as well. As the withdrawal of U.S. forces from Syria continues, the old and new players must change their stakes and claims, to better position themselves for the butchering of Syria’s decaying sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This calculated move by King Bibi, as he is called in Israel, dropped the first domino in a chain of events that ultimately resulted in Trump’s declaration of Israeli sovereignty over the Golan Heights. Changing the status quo of the annexation holds significant value for the relationship between the United States and Israel. With the movement of the US embassy to Jerusalem, and with the recognition of Israel’s right over a deeply disputed territory, Netanyahu is trying to cement strong ties with the US. But the history and strategic importance of the Golan Heights in the Middle East stands in his way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the end stages of the 1967 War, Israel seized the majority of the Golan Heights region which was until then a plateau in southwestern Syria. Most of the Syrian and Arab inhabitants fled the area during the conflict. Syria’s attempt to recapture the region in the 1973 Middle East War failed. Both countries signed an armistice in 1974 and the UN observer force has been in place on the ceasefire line since then. However, things got rougher when Israel unilaterally annexed the Golan Heights in 1981. Until Trump’s recent recognition of the annexation, there had been no change in the status quo of the region. Over the last fifty years, the scars of the Six-Day War haven’t healed and despite Israeli settlements in the region, neither side is willing to give up its claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of strategic importance and national security, Golan Heights is vital for both the nations involved. Southern Syria and Damascus are clearly visible from the top of the Heights. On the other hand, the northern part of Israel is exposed to the Golan Heights, and it was used regularly by Syrian artillery units for shelling, between 1948 and 1967, back when Syria controlled the Heights. The Heights give Israel an excellent vantage point for monitoring Syrian movements. The topography provides a natural shield against any military thrust from Syria. In an arid region, the Golan Heights offers both fertility and freshwater resources, and essentially the rainwater from the Golan’s catchment goes into the Jordan River which provides a third of Israel’s water supply. Thus, the historic, geographic and strategic vitality of Golan Heights for both Syria and Israel makes it sufficiently clear that neither country is easily going to give up its claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace talks to resolve the issue have been going on for a long period as well. In the US-brokered peace talks of 1999-2000, a significant amount of progress was made when Israel agreed to return most of the captured territory to the Syrian administration. However, the demand of Syria for a full Israeli withdrawal to the pre-1967 border didn’t make the deal a success. This would have given Damascus control of the eastern shore of the Sea of Galilee - Israel’s main source of freshwater. Naturally, this was too large a sacrifice for Israel and the possibility of resolution completely collapsed. Indirect talks between Israel and Syria resumed in 2008, through Turkish government intermediaries, but were abruptly suspended following the resignation of Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Olmert over a corruption inquiry. The Obama Administration, once again, tried to forge peace but failed as the Syrian civil war engulfed the nation in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the election of Benjamin Netanyahu as Prime Minister, for the first time, most experts expected Israel’s stance to become harder on the Golan Heights issue. So far, in all its peace endeavours, Israel had actively sought the cooperation of Syria for resolution and the former had also agreed to the giving up of certain portions of the contested areas for peaceful settlement of the decades-old issue. However, with these announcements, the foundational policy of Israel’s foreign policy is changing. Instead of going for bilateral resolution, Israel is structuring its decisions to enhance its prowess on the global stage. And the vested interests of the US in Israel have made it reverse years of its own stance. For decades, the United Nations and the United States have refused to recognise Israel’s seizure of the Golan Heights and the West Bank in 1967, arguing that the contours of Israel must be negotiated diplomatically. But President Trump tweeted that “it is time for the United States to fully recognize Israel’s Sovereignty over the Golan Heights,” adding that it was of critical importance to Israel and stability in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the US withdrawal from the Syrian crisis is changing both the power dynamics and policy decisions of the Middle East. The United States has already reversed its opinion on the sovereign rights of Israel over the Golan Heights, even though its allies, mainly Canada and the European Union, have not followed suit. Most Arab countries also disagree with the change in the status quo. With the US and Russia coming into the equation, Israel is rising as a country, which is outward-looking and integrated with the global system. Such hard stances will, quite incontrovertibly, lead to rising tensions. But the silver lining is that these stances help Israel in extensive adaptation to the role of a strengthened US ally, which has a geographical advantage, with the power to dominate the overpopulated and confused Middle Eastern stage. Thus, if everything goes as planned, coming back into the office, PM Netanyahu has more to gloat over than to sulk about. As the administration stays the same, so does the policy, and Middle East has a few more battles coming it’s way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“The Golan Heights will forever remain in Israel’s hands. Israel will never come down from the Golan Heights”: With these words, the Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu commenced his cabinet session on March 24, 2019. Israel and Syria have been contesting over the region since the Six-Day War in June 1976. His speech, in which he repeatedly reinforced Israel’s claim over the Golan Heights, went ahead to eclipse all public forums and debates.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘Halloween’ in 2018: Missing the Point of Its Predecessor’s Pointed Social Criticism</title><link href="/Halloween-In-2018" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Halloween’ in 2018: Missing the Point of Its Predecessor’s Pointed Social Criticism" /><published>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Halloween-In-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Halloween-In-2018">&lt;p&gt;Director David Gordon Green’s 2018 sequel to John Carpenter’s 1978 classic splattered across big screens last fall, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slashfilm.com/halloween-box-office-opening-slasher-records/&quot;&gt;breaking&lt;/a&gt; box office records for opening weekends for the long-running franchise and for the slasher genre as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But financial success is rarely a barometer for artistic success, and a film as rich in meaning as the original &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; deserves a comparative review alongside its shiny sequel. As we shall see, Green’s film stays faithful to the original’s atmosphere and structure but does little with the film’s underlying social commentary on sex and suburbia, opting instead to play it safe and only offer a few, mainly cosmetic feminist reversals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, this sequel does not in any way address the controversial topic of sex like its predecessor did. Although John Carpenter has gone to great pains to insist that his 1978 film does not offer commentary on teenage sexuality, countless film critics have spilled much ink on the original’s unique relationship to sex. Michael Myers kills his naked sister after she has sex; he also kills babysitters and their paramour boyfriends as they engage in lovemaking or immediately after it (harkening back to an earlier association between sex and murder made in Italian thrillers known as &lt;em&gt;Gialli&lt;/em&gt;, most prominently Mario Bava’s 1971 picture &lt;em&gt;Bay of Blood&lt;/em&gt;). Many critics have seen Myers’ killings as allegorical of Middle-American and middle-class anxiety over burgeoning teenage sexuality, unleashed by the Sexual Revolution a decade before the original film’s release. Myers appears in the absence of parental supervision, acting as a nightmarish father figure in addition to being the boogeyman. By making Myers both a symbol of society’s condemnation of premarital sex and its superego, Carpenter’s film also makes teenage sexuality not just “problematic” (to use contemporary academic lingo) but transgressive, something that must be repressed by any means necessary–even violent ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Green’s &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; dispenses entirely with the transgressive teenage sexuality of the late 1970’s, instead importing contemporary America’s lax moral strictures on the subject. Allyson (granddaughter of female protagonist Laurie Strode) and her boyfriend Cameron Elam break up because Cameron drunkenly kisses another girl at a Halloween-themed dance at their high school; their mutual friend Drew Scheid drunkenly tries to hit on her afterwards and fails; babysitter Vicky begins making love with her boyfriend Dave but never gets anywhere with it. The last two episodes are interrupted by the appearance of The Shape, who promptly kills the men and the babysitter. But make no mistake, the movie offers no special Freudian connection between sex and death, eros and thanatos–the sex is incidental to the killings, and nothing more. More often than not humour interrupts otherwise romantic or steamy scenes, making it seem like the movie has nothing important to say on the subject of sex. In fact, sex features so little in the film, you would be forgiven if you mistook this &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; for a sanitised version of the original. The newest installment in the franchise merely includes sex because it was a feature of the original, which it mistook for a bug rather than an integral part of the film. The updated sexuality of Green’s film is in all likelihood an attempt to make it relatable to younger audiences, who rarely sleep with a guilty conscience–or the fear of being killed by the boogeyman–just because they’ve slept with someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of society which Green’s &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; refuses to comment upon is the decline of social trust in American society and suburbia. The original &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; was so shocking to 70’s theatregoers because of the sleepy suburb of Haddonfield, Illinois―a microcosm of Middle America, and some might say ‘real’ America―was ravaged by a faceless killer who weaved through unlocked door after unlocked door. None of the residents of Haddonfield expected the intrusion of evil into their &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; night precisely because they were embedded in a social system where neighbours not only looked out for one another but babysat each other’s children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contemporary Americans no longer trust their neighbours. Americans’ trust in their fellow citizens and trust in government have &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/trust&quot;&gt;reached&lt;/a&gt; all-time lows. One University of Minnesota &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3792177?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; suggested that “materialistic values may be undermining young people’s views about the trustworthiness of others.” The researchers found that “the rapid rise of materialistic value orientations that occurred among American youth in the 1970s and 1980s severely eroded levels of social trust.” This is in line with the theories of French sociologist Emile Durkheim and especially French political theorist Alexis de Tocqueville, who predicted in &lt;em&gt;Democracy in America&lt;/em&gt; that democracy impels people to materialistic worldviews and pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent spurt in widely publicised mass shootings, as well as the continuous coverage of assaults and rapes and all manner of affronts to civil society by an increasingly negative news media, has eroded that trust. (If anyone doubts this trend, they need only look at the media’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2017/10/02/555092743/study-news-coverage-of-trump-more-negative-than-for-other-presidents&quot;&gt;coverage&lt;/a&gt; of Donald Trump alone, which is three times as negative as the coverage of the Obama and Bush presidencies.) But instead of taking note of and commenting upon this decisive social change, the new &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; film thoughtlessly assumes the social situation of its 1978 forbearer. True, cosmetically the film boasts the reversal of gender roles by its characters―Allyson and Cameron dress as Bonnie and Clyde with the genders reversed, and Laurie Strode hunts Michael Myers in the final act of the film. But it tellingly leaves its premise–the violation of social trust–unmodified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Green’s film pathologises Laurie Strode’s prepper mindset as paranoia and a trauma which she can only work through by confronting and killing Michael Myers, when in fact in contemporary America, Strode’s fears are not so far beyond the pale as the director would like us to think. Americans, especially mothers, do fear for the safety of their children, especially in an age of widely televised mass shootings and terrorist attacks. Fewer and fewer children use public transportation and fewer and fewer states &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/29/well/family/utah-passes-free-range-parenting-law.html&quot;&gt;allow&lt;/a&gt; the “free-range parenting” of children. The state instead criminalises the very act of allowing one’s children to play outside unsupervised. Laurie Strode is the modern helicopter mom par excellence, and can we begrudge her for her fears given our own times and perceptions? Of all the characters in this ostensibly feminist-themed sequel, Laurie Strode and her particular brand of psychology is done the least justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green appears far more interested in merely perpetuating a franchise and duplicating its financial success, rather than actually engaging with the original film were it counts, that is, at the level of setting. The setting of &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; is what makes the idea of Michael Myers possible; gender roles have little to do with the horror of The Shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put things simply, Michael Myers would be a lot less scarier if the film had placed him in contemporary American suburbia, helicopter moms and all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Troy Worden</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Director David Gordon Green’s 2018 sequel to John Carpenter’s 1978 classic splattered across big screens last fall, breaking box office records for opening weekends for the long-running franchise and for the slasher genre as a whole.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Indian Handicrafts Industry: Craft Beyond the Label</title><link href="/Craft-Beyond-The-Label" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Handicrafts Industry: Craft Beyond the Label" /><published>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Craft-Beyond-The-Label</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Craft-Beyond-The-Label">&lt;p&gt;India has always been a land of diversity. It has always welcomed various cultures and traditions. It is a country which has mixed its rich cultural diversity with the economy and markets. The handicraft industry is one of such industries. In India, the industry means more than just work, they are an expression of a particular community, ethnicity, or tradition, employing local craftsmanship and locally sourced materials. The handicrafts have evolved over the centuries, acquiring its present form which is aesthetically pleasing and culturally valuable. The folklores, the dialects, and the tribal lifestyles have inspired the prints. These handicrafts have, thus, shaped the value systems and the vision of the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the Indian traditional crafts flourished as a result of noble patronage. During the Gupta Period of Indian History (mid-3rd century-5th century), crafts were highly demanded even outside the country. Under the Mughal rule, all kinds of crafts reached their zenith. However, the glory of the Indian handicrafts industry came to the end by the mid-19th century. This was attributed to the ‘Discriminatory tariff policy’, wherein heavy duties were charged on Indian goods entering Britain, India’s colonial masters, while English goods to India were charged nominal duties. This price discrimination, coupled with the growing popularity of machine-made goods was the last nail in the coffin. After India’s Independence in 1947, the emphasis was laid on heavy industries so as to tap the country’s manufacturing potential. Though not on a priority basis, efforts were still made to restore the lost legacy of Indian handicrafts, especially since they were used by Gandhi as part of India’s freedom struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The All-India Handicrafts Board was established in November 1952 to identify the problems hampering the development of handicrafts. And the Handicraft and Handloom Export Corporation of India Ltd. was established for the promotion of handicrafts exports. While the institutional structure was apt, the vision was misleading. These institutions focused on promoting the handicrafts, without really improving the productivity of artisans through various incentive models. As a result, the exports grew, however, not up to their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doha Round negotiation of the WTO, in 2005, mandated the removal of quotas for at least 97% of goods from the least-developed countries. Post the negotiation, the Indian handicraft export was expected to improve. And the exports did rise from 155,876 to 170,000 in 2006. But in 2008-09, the exports fell to 80,000 as a result of a global meltdown. India’s share in the world handicraft market is an appalling 2%, as compared to the 17% market share of China. India is home to 6.8 million artisans, but local artisans and traditional craftsmen have failed to crack into the international market. The exports have been controlled by already flourishing designers and a handful of master weavers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handicrafts industry is largely cottage-based, predominantly located in villages and small towns. Based on Hirschman’s arguments, it is can be easily concluded that the success of any industry depends on the strength of its forward and backward linkages. For the handicraft industry, the diseconomies of scale occur in two forms: (i) high cost of access to markets for raw material (poor backward linkage), and (ii) high cost of access to output market (poor forward linkage). Poor transport infrastructure and facilities cut access to organised input markets. As a result, if the artisans wish to continue, they have to rely on middlemen, who charge higher prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Textbook economics tells us that the seller would sell his produce only in the market which offers the highest possible remuneration. In the handicrafts industry, the local artisans often get a much lower remuneration due to inaccessibility to the highest paying market. For example, jute handicrafts are gaining popularity in the cities (especially after plastic bans). However, an artisan producing in Murshidabad, West Bengal would not be able to take advantage of this due to lack of perfect information. He would be compelled to sell the produce at a lower price to a local trader. However, the trader exploits asymmetric information to earn higher profits in the cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultural Entrepreneurship entails creating organisations of arts, by and for artists, that are financially sustainable and viable and have a cultural and societal impact. This would enrich the artist’s work by providing support and services and generate more opportunities for collaboration and cooperation. For example, Bhu:sattva, a natural garment brand sources its garments from women self-help groups (SHG) in four districts of the Indian state of Gujarat. Here, community participation through SHGs improved the bargaining power of the artisans and made their businesses profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community participation can help revive a system more inclusive but similar to what is called the ‘jajmani’ system, credited for the evolution of crafts in the pre-British era. Promoting cluster development for skill training, quality improvement and policy support has been the objective of the SFURTI (Scheme of Fund for Regeneration of Traditional Industries). Reducing tariffs (such as 18% GST on Handicrafts) and giving subsidies will lower average costs, and certainly improve the ease of doing business for the handicraft industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success story of the Japanese craft of ‘basket weaving’, gives us an example of how branding can help an industry survive. Product differentiation did not just save it from extinction, but also elevated it to an art form. The Indian handicrafts industry has failed to carve a niche in the international market as it has failed to effectively utilise branding and marketing techniques. Despite the finesse, their reach is extremely limited. On the other hand, US-based Lisa Fine and John Robshaw have gained recognition by branding the same crafts well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the Indian government is focusing on the skills training of rural artisans under the ‘&lt;em&gt;Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Grameen Kaushalya Yojna&lt;/em&gt;’, a policy for rural empowerment. Designers from the National Institute of Design (NID) and National Institute of Fashion Technology (NIFT) have developed courses to upskill Self-Help Groups (SHGs) and individual artisans. Soft skills training programmes in export marketing, packaging and technology are organised as well. With certification, artisans see a hike in their earnings. A unique initiative by the Union Ministry of Minority Affairs, Hunar Haat (literally, skilled hands) display the rich heritage and skills of master craftsmen from minority communities. This serves several objectives: social and financial inclusion, skill development and the preservation and marketing of cultural traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we wish to keep up a high price, a high supply has to be matched by high demand. In order to increase the demand, dissemination of information to potential buyers is the key. This can be achieved through better marketing techniques in print and electronic media. In India, the Ministry of Culture is responsible for the promotion of folk and traditional arts through micro-regional targeting via zonal cultural centers. The idea behind education is simple: make people feel connected to indigenous traditions and in turn, make them practitioners or consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing up a new generation of Art patrons is an innovative approach towards increasing demand. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wt5_mdW6vTw&quot;&gt;TED Talk&lt;/a&gt;, Joanna Taft shares her idea of establishing a unique high school in Philadelphia. In this school, the curriculum was crafted around Art and Languages along with conventional Science and Social Sciences. Taft’s idea can be applied in the Indian context by designing suitable interventions in the education sector. It is important that young minds do not learn facts in isolation and also learn how art and science developed in tandem. In this way, next-gen leaders, appreciative of art, can be nurtured. This one step would open immense potentials for the handicrafts industry in the long run whilst making a more cultured populace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-Commerce and the Internet have opened new opportunities for the handicraft industry. The online market has helped local artisans meet their prospective buyers, eliminating the need for middlemen. Government initiatives such as BharatNet for improving internet connectivity in rural areas would have socio-economic impacts for the sector. Conceptualising and implementing needed social, economic and technological interventions can help the handicraft industry reach a sweet spot in the international market, a place that is rightfully deserved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gurleen Kaur</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">India has always been a land of diversity. It has always welcomed various cultures and traditions. It is a country which has mixed its rich cultural diversity with the economy and markets. The handicraft industry is one of such industries. In India, the industry means more than just work, they are an expression of a particular community, ethnicity, or tradition, employing local craftsmanship and locally sourced materials. The handicrafts have evolved over the centuries, acquiring its present form which is aesthetically pleasing and culturally valuable. The folklores, the dialects, and the tribal lifestyles have inspired the prints. These handicrafts have, thus, shaped the value systems and the vision of the society.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament</title><link href="/March-Madness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament" /><published>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/March-Madness</id><content type="html" xml:base="/March-Madness">&lt;p&gt;The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past season the Duke Blue Devils were on center stage due to their three phenomenal freshmen: Zion Williamson, RJ Barrett, and Cam Reddish; all three are projected to be drafted among the top ten players this upcoming June. When the ACC tournament was played, all media attention was put on Duke basketball and Zion Williamson, and the  Duke Blue Devils were heavily favored coming into the NCAA tournament as the number one overall seed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Zion Williamson and company were in the spotlight for the first and second rounds, a few breakout stars carried their teams and shocked the world. Ja Morant, a sophomore guard from Murray State, is now being regarded as the second best player in the upcoming draft, right behind Williamson. Morant opened up round one with a victory over Marquette with an impressive triple-double where he had 16 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the regular college season, the only programs that receive coverage from the media are the universities with large national followings such as Duke and Kentucky. However, the upside of  The March Madness tournament is that it allows for athletes at smaller Division 1 schools to make an impact. A good example of this is Warriors point guard Steph Curry, who was severely under recruited due to his small size. The eventual three-time NBA champion’s introduction to the national media happened back in 2008 when he scored 40 points and led the Davidson Wildcats in upsetting the number 7 seed, Gonzaga. Curry ended up leading his team to the elite eight where they were knocked out by number 1 seed Kansas. As a result, Curry was later drafted in 2009 by the Golden State Warriors as the 7th overall pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides such a large platform for college players to make their mark and be noticed, and the benefits can be enormous. Kemba Walker, for example, was not a highly regarded point guard when he led his UConn Huskies to the National Championship in 2011. Walker and the Huskies entered as a 3 seed where they ultimately beat Butler and claimed their third national championship. During their championship run, Walker played sensationally and was awarded the tournament’s Most Outstanding Player Award. Walker was later drafted 9th overall by the Charlotte Hornets and has been on three all-star teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides opportunities for players in smaller programs to showcase their talent on a national level. The media will always follow the athletes and programs that dominate in the regular season, and this is why March Madness is so special. Players like Steph Curry, Kemba Walker, and Ja Morant all have a place in NCAA history where their names were made.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tyler Pesavento</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="basketball" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bike-Sharing: Ending Soon?</title><link href="/Bike-Sharing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bike-Sharing: Ending Soon?" /><published>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Bike-Sharing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Bike-Sharing">&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, what scholars term the ‘sharing economy’ has attracted tremendous attention and massive venture capital. Prominent platforms such as Airbnb  and Uber  are experiencing explosive growth, which has led to both virtues and detriments. Advocates of the sharing economy claim the system yields positive outcomes such as empowerment of ordinary people, efficiency in commerce and even lower carbon footprints. On the other hand, critics accuse it of promoting economic self-interest rather than sharing and decry it as being exploitative and predatory. Today, bike-sharing services are among the most prevalent start-up business models purportedly constituting the sharing economy. Comparable to other businesses of its kind however, bike-sharing companies have begun encountering issues ranging from regulatory hurdles to unethical business practices, vandalism and theft to uncooperative customers and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing remains a routine practice even today: families sharing the rewards of their labour, communities sharing access to resources and countries sharing intelligence, among other examples. While ‘sharing’ is as old as humankind, the ‘sharing economy’ in its current understanding is a fairly recent concept. However, despite its instant growth and enormous popularity among consumers, it is extremely perplexing to propose a universally applicable definition for ‘sharing economy’, especially one that reflects clarity whilst also addressing the variety of ways in which the term is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generic meaning of ‘sharing’ omits methods of exchange that involve a monetary connotation, which means schemes based on peer-to-peer (P2P) asset dealings should be excluded from the sharing economy. However, if we elucidate that access to an asset can be shared instead of the asset itself, the attachment of a monetary implication becomes irrelevant and activities based on peer-to-peer asset sharing should be included in the sharing economy. Due to its ambiguous definition, scholars today consider ‘sharing economy’ an umbrella term with a variety of meanings. It is, however, most appropriate to think of it as a marketplace that connects individuals on a peer-to-peer basis, enabling them to share assets that are otherwise underutilised and idling in exchange for a price. A sharing economy, thus, offers an economical and convenient alternative to actually purchasing the asset, since the cost of sharing is considerably lower than the cost incurred on owning the asset. Hence, this model can also be called a ‘collaborative economy’ or a ‘peer economy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of this ‘peer economy’ has been highly transformative over recent years. It has altered the way we commute, lodge, holiday and borrow, by employing ‘dead capital’ in more productive fashions. Accredited with altering the way we commute, among other examples, is the bike-sharing industry. It has received increasing spotlight in recent years for enlarging mobility options and lowering transportation costs for consumers. The bike-sharing industry has augmented the use of public transport, reduced traffic congestion and fuel consumption, delivered health benefits and improved environmental awareness among the public. It also acts as a resort to the ‘first mile-last mile’ problem of transit. Bixi, a bike-sharing company,  proudly professes that it has helped reduce over 3 million pounds of greenhouse gases in Montreal in 2009. Another such program that began in France in 2005 or so claims it has saved the equivalent of 18.6 million pounds of carbon dioxide pollution from the atmosphere in a year. In 2008, 28% of Vélib’s  customers, a bike-sharing company based out of Paris, stated they were less likely to use their personal vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the question is, is the bike-sharing industry truly a part of the sharing economy? Undertakings in the sharing economy are immensely diverse. TaskRabbit, an errands site, is considered a part of it but Mechanical Turk, Amazon’s online labour market, is not. Airbnb  is virtually synonymous with the sharing economy, but conventional bed and breakfasts are rarely included in it. Even though they serve similar agendas, public libraries, community centers and parks are not counted in the sharing economy. When Juliet Schor, Professor of Sociology at Boston College, presented these puzzles to a few scholars, they gave a pragmatic response rather than an analytical one: “self-definition by the platforms and the press defines who is in and who is out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, most bike-sharing companies function as business-to-peer organisations rather than peer-to-peer organisations. This stands in violation of the ‘peer-to-peer sharing’ characteristic of a sharing economy that we established earlier in this article. Technically, an ideal model of the peer economy involves a company, customers and non-company owners of the physical asset providing customers a service, in this case, bikes. My view is that bike-sharing companies contravene &lt;em&gt;marketing ethics&lt;/em&gt; by advertising themselves as part of the sharing economy. These companies themselves own the physical asset. Furthermore, these bikes are neither underutilised assets, nor are they idling: they are perpetually available for customers. Therefore, the honest approach would be to label it a ‘bike-renting’ business rather than a ‘bike-sharing’ business, because bikes are actually rented out to consumers and not peer-shared. Take Uber  or Airbnb  as examples to compare bike-sharing with the true model of a sharing business. We find that genuine sharing-companies work as aggregators of vendors and partners who are simply connected to customers, in exchange for a commission for this straightforward networking service. On the contrary, bike-sharing companies act as vendors themselves, and instead of a commission, charge the entire price upon renting the bikes independently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of ethical conduct and positioning of these companies as a part of the sharing economy further deepens on evaluating their core strategy. Given the public affinity to the current wave of peer-sharing, bike-sharing companies, or perhaps more appropriately now, bike-renting companies, are attempting to build a consumer behaviour of routine and habitual renting, leveraging the sentiment of people who find peer-sharing trendy to be the ‘in thing’, or the only resort to the miseries of mankind. This has led to speculations of inflated company valuations, rendering a scar on the industry’s &lt;em&gt;financial ethics&lt;/em&gt;, besides forming a bubble waiting to burst as the demand dips after the initial euphoria is over and more players enter the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another bane of the bike-sharing industry is its eagle-eye for big data and metadata, an agenda that endangers user privacy. Over the last few years, bike-sharing companies have received billions of dollars in funding, but have failed to generate consequential revenue. There is widespread concern as billions are being invested in loss-making bike-sharing companies that have no profit model. These companies consume cash just to build vast user networks in order to justify higher valuations in subsequent fundraising. Despite marginal returns, investors are constantly investing in these companies, with increased frequency and greater magnitude. The real objective for these investors is securing access to millions of ‘tech-savvy’ customers, and surprising enough is their ability to go to any extent to achieve this objective. In fact, Ofo  gave away rides for free when they launched in Chongqing, China. Users were merely required to register on the online app, and free rides they got. As a result of technological advancements and innovations, most bike-sharing companies today operate through online applications. External players like investors and content creators, are hungry for access to online user information from as many sources as possible, so as to build a massive customer network for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Chinese e-commerce giant Alibaba, whose financial affiliate, Ant Financial, is an investor for the bike-sharing company Ofo, are exploring opportunities to deliver other products and services to these digital customers they are monitoring on the aforementioned applications. “They are keen to access valuable data on users’ commuting habits and rental history”, says Zhou Wei, founder of China Creation Ventures. “These bike services are of high strategic importance to Alibaba and Tencent. It is an indispensable way to get data on frequent users”. Access to user data also provides information on a person’s credit history, social media conduct, and online shopping habits. Surveillance like this reveals our individual details to unidentified players who establish ‘&lt;em&gt;echo chambers&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;filter bubbles&lt;/em&gt;’ on our network so as to create custom content and influence our online buying and selling activities, news feeds and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another allegation that social activists and governments always shower bike-sharing companies with is the ‘bring-your-own-helmet’ practice, which helps these companies evade liability towards the safety of their customers. In a recent case, an 11-year old boy riding an Ofo  bike met with a fatal accident in Shanghai when he was hit by a bus. Road safety laws in China prohibit children under the age of 12 from riding bikes on public roads. However, bike-sharing companies have been flouting this law openly. Despite its lapse in allowing an 11-year old to rent their bike, Ofo simply expressed condolences over the mishap but failed to take responsibility for the event. As part of an example from outside China, we may note that only 20% of Hubway riders in Boston bike wear helmets. This means only &lt;strong&gt;two out of ten shared-bike riders riding in heavy traffic are likely to survive in the event of an accident&lt;/strong&gt;. Absence of helmets in bike-sharing services also conflicts with insurance laws, wherein injuries or fatalities may not be covered by insurance companies. The Hangzhou bike-sharing system in China is one of the very few systems of its kind to cover any injuries that riders sustain while using their bikes. The Cambridge Cycling Campaign has also raised concerns over the absence of lights in front of most shared-bikes in China. They are apprehensive over the legal permissibility of the commercial use of such bikes. During the dark, if streets lack sufficient lighting, riders can meet with accidents and the same argument on liability is repeated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the problem of traffic congestion, bike-sharing companies are also accused of using ‘bike visibility’ as a mode of marketing. They are heavily investing in a model that perpetually releases bikes into the market but abandons their maintenance and upkeep. In terms of ‘fleet size’, 17 of the world’s top 20 bike-sharing schemes are based out of China. Despite truncated demand, China currently has over 10 million shared-bikes on its streets, 1.5 million of which are active in Shanghai alone. The industry is engaging in cut-throat competition, with the winner title supposedly going to the company that has most bikes on the road. This has aggravated traffic congestion and hence reduced road-safety. Companies are attempting to make regional monopolies of their own: Ofo  operates 2.2 million bikes across China, Mobike,  about a million, and then there are over forty other startups expanding in different parts of the Mainland. “Piles of bikes dumped outside subway stations are now a common sight”, says Yang Fengchun, a professor at Peking University’s School of Government. This is happening due to the lack of docking facilities in urban cities. Bike-sharing companies are saving costs by not installing adequate docking stations. Even if the companies operate on a dock-less model, they have dusted their hands off the responsibility to manage bikes that clog public streets, parks, condominiums, sidewalks and office areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-cooperating communities also play a major role in the theft and vandalism of shared-bikes. In an interesting case recently, bike-sharing went on to symbolise inequality and discrimination for the economically backward black community residing in peripheral parts of San Francisco. The launch of the Ford GoBike  scheme became a scapegoat for people who were distressed due to the housing crisis and troubled by the problem of rising income inequalities. They identified the bike-sharing trend as an indulgence of rich techies, hipsters and young professionals, who used them to commute to popular coffee shops and high-end food joints. Bike-sharing has hence been criticised in localities that lack efficient and organised city services. In such an environment, the industry produces more adversaries than peers, thus encouraging unethical practices and inappropriate conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, several bike-sharing companies have had to seal operations from time to time. Wukong Bicycle  lost 90% of its bikes to theft and vandalism, hence having to end operations in June 2017. In a similar case in November 2017, Bluegogo  declared bankruptcy since most of its bikes had either been stolen or wrecked, leaving no other option for the company but to shut down operations. Outside China, the state of affairs is no better. Seattle ended its Pronto  scheme this March; a bike-sharing program in Melbourne also ended in failure when its demand dipped after the enforcement of a law that mandated wearing helmets while riding. Spain seems to have suffered the highest casualties: 65 of the 130 schemes that began in Spain back in 2010 have shut down, half of them concluding operations within three years of opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it is also important that we examine the morals of governments. Why are cities being designed only for cars? Why does urbanisation involve more automobiles and not more ‘thought-o-mobiles’? Is it not unfair to disregard people who perhaps choose to cycle due to financial constraints or health motivations? The world is tirelessly discussing climate change and the impact it will have on future generations. Governments themselves are pledging to relegate pollution in a variety of ways. One of these ways is to reduce motorised vehicles on the road. While governments do advocate the necessity of owning lesser cars and using them less often, they end up sponsoring hypocrisy by failing to provide and support alternative measures. The bike-sharing industry could have structured a new way of life by now, where the main mode of transport for citizens was a shared-bike. But, consistent with their neo-capitalistic propaganda, governments are busy building highways and expressways to facilitate motorised commute while resource allocation to boost bike-sharing barely seems existent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can cogently affirm that the bike-sharing industry is not a true manifestation of the sharing economy. In reality, it is modelled more on a rental service than a peer-sharing facility. Further, all evidence presented throw light on a spectrum of problems: several people have lost their jobs and perhaps still remain unemployed with bike-sharing companies having to shut down operations; land, plant and machinery have gone largely underutilised on account of the same; the industry has witnessed numerous regulatory hurdles that include infringement of current legislations and the imperative need for new and more comprehensive ones; the government has been unsuccessful in extracting benefits of the industry for the public; and finally, criminal activity by society has gone largely unpunished. The bike-sharing industry can hence be identified with more negatives than positives today. Bike-sharing companies, the society and governments, all have a role to play in its flawed model of business and sheer disregard for ethics. Though seemingly pacing ahead with consistent innovation and expansion, the bike-sharing industry has begun its gradual decline. It will soon meet its end lest all its stakeholders pedal to survive…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivang Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">In the past few years, what scholars term the ‘sharing economy’ has attracted tremendous attention and massive venture capital. Prominent platforms such as Airbnb and Uber are experiencing explosive growth, which has led to both virtues and detriments. Advocates of the sharing economy claim the system yields positive outcomes such as empowerment of ordinary people, efficiency in commerce and even lower carbon footprints. On the other hand, critics accuse it of promoting economic self-interest rather than sharing and decry it as being exploitative and predatory. Today, bike-sharing services are among the most prevalent start-up business models purportedly constituting the sharing economy. Comparable to other businesses of its kind however, bike-sharing companies have begun encountering issues ranging from regulatory hurdles to unethical business practices, vandalism and theft to uncooperative customers and communities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Not Peace but a Sword: The New Religious War in Ukraine</title><link href="/Religious-War-In-Ukraine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not Peace but a Sword: The New Religious War in Ukraine" /><published>2019-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Religious-War-In-Ukraine</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Religious-War-In-Ukraine">&lt;p&gt;The year is 2014. Violent protests have erupted across Ukraine. President Viktor Yanukovych’s perceived pro-Russian policies have angered a large section of the population, who have firmly come out in support of closer ties with the European Union. However, the predominantly Russian-speaking East is not that happy about the prospect of a European alliance. Unfortunately for them, Yanukovych is soon ousted from power by a violent revolution. This new development is not, however, universally acclaimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly afterwards, armed revolutionaries seize control of the Crimean Parliament and allegedly install a pro-Russian Prime Minister, who quickly calls upon Vladimir Putin for military assistance. Cries of “Putin is my President!” are now commonly heard in the streets of Crimea. Eventually, a referendum is held and the results indicate that the people of Crimea have overwhelmingly voted for union with Russia. Crimea then becomes a part of the Russian Federation, a development condemned by the European Union, the United States and much of the rest of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia and Ukraine share a long inter-woven history. Both of them look upon Kievan Rus as their cultural ancestor – the monarchy that once included much of the East Slavic and Finnic peoples of Europe, and which lasted from the late 9th to the mid-13th century. However, over time, their relationship has grown steadily worse. The events of 2014 are but a modern manifestation of a long-festering division that has only been exacerbated as the years have passed by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Ukraine is a part of Eastern Europe, a region many people consider to be the heartland of the Eastern Orthodox Church. Known for its hardline stances on many issues of faith and morals, this ancient federation of ecclesiastical communities claims a line of unbroken continuity with the Church of the Apostles. Proponents call it a relatively pure Church, undefiled by the erroneous ideologies of the modern world. Critics call it a reactionary, patriarchal organisation, which still refuses to ordain women and considers abortion to be immoral and sinful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the vast majority of Western European culture and society – the historic stronghold of the Roman Church – has been usurped by the forces of liberalism, secularism and the sexual revolution, the same cannot be said about Eastern Orthodoxy. This is highly ironic, given that the Russian Orthodox Church, in particular, was strongly persecuted by the Soviet Union, as were as the other Slavic Orthodox Churches, such the Serbian, Bulgarian and Romanian Patriarchates. However, since the fall of the USSR, the Orthodox Church has come to wield a level of influence over local politics unseen since the time of the Tsars. While the Russian Federation continues to claim non-affiliation with any religious body as such, the alliance between Putin and the Moscow Patriarchate is the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is a very strong preserver. After all, the Roman Catholic Church – the world’s largest, most powerful and longest-running monarchy – is, in many ways, the only remaining bastion of medieval Western culture. This is easily apparent especially if you visit traditionalist monasteries which still follow the rules in all their strictness. It is, of course, true that even many Roman Catholic priests and bishops don’t practice their faith well and have become lax, but there are still many strongholds of conservatism within that Church―despite the forces of liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true also of the Eastern Orthodox Church, which, in general, suffers much less from the plague of liberals within their hierarchy. Some observers have noted the remarkable similarity between the alliance of Putin and Patriarch Kirill of Moscow today and the traditional diarchy of Byzantium, in which the Emperor and the Patriarch would be the most powerful political figures in the land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while the Russian Federation may no longer possess the territorial jurisdiction of Kievan Rus, the Patriarchate of Moscow has a much stronger boast to that. The Russian Church claims jurisdiction not merely over Russia but also over all of Ukraine. In fact, the single largest Church in Ukraine continues to be under the jurisdiction of Moscow. It is called the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Moscow Patriarchate. It is autonomous, but not autocephalous. In other words, it is mostly self-governing, but not wholly independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, many of the nationalists of Ukraine have despised what they see as the continued intrusion of Russian imperialist influence in their homeland. And it is precisely such sentiments as these that were responsible, in part, for the splintering of the Orthodox Church in Ukraine into two new denominations – the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Kievan Patriarchate and the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, there is the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, which looks like the Orthodox Church, prays like the Orthodox Church, smells like the Orthodox Church, but is – in fact – a Catholic Church in full communion with Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the Kiev Patriarchate and the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church were considered by the rest of the Orthodox world to be nationalist fanatics and schismatics who have damaged the unity of Orthodoxy. The Metropolitan Onufriy, under the authority of the Moscow Patriarch, was considered to be the rightful primate of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, quite recently, the situation has taken a sharp turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Patriarch of Constantinople Bartholomew I, long considered the “first among equals” of the Orthodox Patriarchs has taken it upon himself to grant the Church of Ukraine (specifically the two splinter groups from Moscow) complete independence from Russia. While it is true that the Patriarch of Constantinople does not enjoy the same authority in Orthodoxy that the Pope does in Catholicism, he does have some prerogatives – among them is the responsibility of hearing appeals from the rest of the Orthodox world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has led to the Patriarchate of Moscow excommunicating the Patriarch of Constantinople. And the vast majority of the Orthodox Churches have sided with Moscow. Bartholomew, however, has been undeterred. As a result of his efforts, the two splinter groups have now been united as the “Orthodox Church of Ukraine” with the full blessing and support of Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko. Their new leader calls himself Metropolitan Epiphany (Dumenko). As of now, no Orthodox Church has given recognition to this new Church apart from Constantinople itself, and it has received heated condemnation not only from Moscow but also from the Primate of Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What implications could this have for the political situation? First of all, it is almost without question that the new Orthodox Church will come to represent the face of Ukrainian nationalism against “Russian imperialism”. It is no wonder that President Poroshenko is such an avid supporter of the move. Millions of Ukrainians still consider the Patriarch of Moscow to be their spiritual leaders. This new move represents an opportunity to break that perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the new Church has also received surprising support from sectors of the Roman Catholic Church. It is very ironic indeed – four centuries ago, nationalism played a very important role in rousing extreme opposition to the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, members of which were looked upon as traitors who had defected to Rome. Now, it is the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religious freedom still remains strongly restricted in many parts of Eastern Europe. Russia, for instance, has banned the Jehovah’s Witnesses. There was also a famous attempt to ban the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad Gita As It Is&lt;/em&gt; in 2011. In 2016, the premises of a Vedic monastery in Nizhny Novgorod were demolished by local authorities, after having been declared illegal a year back. Meanwhile, the Russian Orthodox Church is busy rebuilding Churches demolished during the time of the Soviet Union and is enjoying the presence of Putin at Church services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does the future hold for Russia and Ukraine? Will Russia try to resurrect its orthodox heritage, perhaps even, as some suggest, restore the monarchy? Will we see a new cold war, between Russia and the West, with Ukraine caught in the middle? What is the future for the Orthodox faithful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, my friends, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The year is 2014. Violent protests have erupted across Ukraine. President Viktor Yanukovych’s perceived pro-Russian policies have angered a large section of the population, who have firmly come out in support of closer ties with the European Union. However, the predominantly Russian-speaking East is not that happy about the prospect of a European alliance. Unfortunately for them, Yanukovych is soon ousted from power by a violent revolution. This new development is not, however, universally acclaimed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Mueller Report is a Damp Squib, What Do The Democrats Do Now?</title><link href="/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mueller Report is a Damp Squib, What Do The Democrats Do Now?" /><published>2019-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now">&lt;p&gt;It was meant to be liberal Christmas, the day of the revelations, when the Messiah would come and smite the Antichrist. Robert Mueller is everything Trump isn’t, a modest do-gooder who was awarded the ‘Purple Heart’ and a public servant with a formidable 20-year record of true service to America. He would save us all from the tyranny of the ‘orange Hitler’, a draft dodging, bumptious braggart who has earned a life of privileged excess by the virtue of his name. The Republic would be saved from his tyranny, and the office of Washington, Jefferson, and Lincoln redeemed of this brief stain. ‘Russiagate’ may have sounded too good to be true, but after losing the first female president to a pervert, goddamit that b*tch karma owed us this one. But as Trump’s favourite rally anthem goes, “you can’t always get what you want”. So what do the Dems do now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mueller has given America a scrupulously researched report into the 2016 Trump election campaign, which found a lack of significant evidence for any criminal proceedings against the President or his family. At the moment, some Democrats are banking on the fact that the report doesn’t fully exonerate Trump, hoping and praying that a full release of the report will give them the nuggets they need to build a criminal case against the President. But they miss the point of the Special Counsel’s report. It wasn’t to prove that the Donald was some kind of crook, any American could tell you Trump’s business dealings have been sketchy for decades, it was to find a case for criminal proceedings and, later, impeachment. Without concrete evidence of such wrongdoing, the leader of the world’s greatest power cannot be toppled. If you come for the king, you best land a s*cker punch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sad irony in that if the roles were reversed, one could imagine Special Counsel Donnie using every dirty trick in the book to bring President Mueller down. But as the Democrats must soon learn if they want any hope of making Trump a one-term President, we live in the real world [sad :(]. Any further attempts by the Democrats to impeach Trump will merely ensure his reelection. They will confirm the suspicions of many middle Americans that a distant coastal elite can’t stomach their decision to exercise their constitutional right to vote for any d*mn fool they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Democrats still have hope. In 2020, they will have several key advantages that they lacked in 2016. Instead of an establishment fix up by the Clinton crime family in the upcoming elections, the Democrats will have an open primary, in which dozens of talented candidates will have their chance to win the nomination. Currently, the strongest candidates are Bernie Sanders and Joe Biden (the progressive party looks set to elect another straight white male dinosaur). Despite coming from opposite ends of their parties ideological spectrum, they share many of the same qualities: an easy-going working-class charm, the ability to empathise with rust belt voters whom Hillary alienated in 2016, and the good sense to not call millions of American ‘deplorables’. Of the two, Biden probably has the edge, the Obama connection gives him a hefty poll boost with African-American voters who dominate the Democrats’ southern primaries. He currently polls higher than both the declared African-American candidates, Cory Booker, and Kamala Harris, combined. Although recent “sexual assault” allegations against Biden could seriously undermine him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the wings of the Democratic primaries, there’s a plethora of has-beens and never-weres. Julian Castro and Kirsten Gillibrand missed their moment if there ever was one. Elizabeth Warren’s desperate attempts to prove that she is a Native American, smacks of an ugly white guilt that repulses minority and white voters alike. Corey Booker’s a progressive poser who isn’t fooling anyone but his New York donors. Beto O’Rourke, the Kennedy for gym buddies, could have clinched it had he won his Senate race last year. Kamala Harris is the strongest candidate outside of the big two, but her career as a prosecutor alienates her from the progressives, and picking a Californian candidate isn’t exactly a smart tactic when the state has been overwhelmingly Democratic for the last 20 years. My personal crushes are Tulsi Gabbard and Pete Buttigieg, both of whom are exciting fresh candidates with innovative ideas, but they lack the profile to win. I’d say look out for them in 2024, but they’re both so young that they could still run in 2040–when they are 70–after all it worked so well for Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, the Mueller report might actually strengthen the Democrats in the 2020 election. By ending their foolish crusade to impeach Trump, they could focus on the issues that matter to American voters: the economy, healthcare, civil rights, and national security. In just seven months, we will be a decade from Obama’s 2008 triumph, in which the Democrats swept the rust belt. That 2008 coalition of disaffected white working-class voters, young progressives and minorities hoping for a better future is still out there. Millions of these voters chose Obama in 2008 and 2012, and then Trump in 2016. These were Democratic voters, and then the Democrats nominated the establishment standard-bearer with the charisma of a damp rag, Hillary Clinton. In 2020, the Democrats have the chance to win back these voters, but a campaign focusing on Russia will make that impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russiagate was meant to be the 21st century’s Watergate. Instead, it now seems more like this generation’s hunt for the WMDs in Iraq. After years of media speculation and major hype that promised a revelation which would legitimise radical action to topple a leader, nothing has been found. However, this time, rather than undermining the administration, it’s the opposition and the media who have embarrassed themselves. For the past two years, senior Democrats and media pundits have promised the American people that Trump colluded with Russia. This won’t be forgotten by American voters coming into the 2020 elections. When Trump will yell that the media is nothing but fake news, far more Americans will now be inclined to agree with him. If the Democrats want to win in 2020, they will need a strong candidate and a message focused on the real anxieties affecting American voters. Russiagate has served to distract many from Trump’s actual failures as President, his inability to pass healthcare reform, a tax cut which overwhelmingly benefits the rich and muddled foreign policy which has alienated America’s allies. Can they do it? If past performance is anything to go on, the rest of the world may have to get ready to put up with four more years of Trump. Nonetheless, it would be a critical race determining America’s future. The people must decide whether they want a unified world with America at the helm or a bunch of bickering nations who at the end will lose all that they have built over the years.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reuben Pritchard</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">It was meant to be liberal Christmas, the day of the revelations, when the Messiah would come and smite the Antichrist. Robert Mueller is everything Trump isn’t, a modest do-gooder who was awarded the ‘Purple Heart’ and a public servant with a formidable 20-year record of true service to America. He would save us all from the tyranny of the ‘orange Hitler’, a draft dodging, bumptious braggart who has earned a life of privileged excess by the virtue of his name. The Republic would be saved from his tyranny, and the office of Washington, Jefferson, and Lincoln redeemed of this brief stain. ‘Russiagate’ may have sounded too good to be true, but after losing the first female president to a pervert, goddamit that b*tch karma owed us this one. But as Trump’s favourite rally anthem goes, “you can’t always get what you want”. So what do the Dems do now?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Earth to the Robots: Fourth Industrial Revolution</title><link href="/Earth-to-the-robots" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Earth to the Robots: Fourth Industrial Revolution" /><published>2019-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Earth-to-the-robots</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Earth-to-the-robots">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you book something from your favourite food outlet online. A robot cooks the food and it is then delivered by a driverless van or a drone. A world where humans are being replaced by robots no longer seems to be a scene from a Sci-Fi film. Recently, a British online supermarket, ‘Ocado,’ successfully developed a completely automatic system of picking up grocery items for its customers. This is representative of the fact that we are moving towards a &lt;em&gt;Digital Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, which is generally termed as the ‘Fourth Industrial Revolution’ (IR 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to policy makers, the world economy has been on a continuous decline for the last three-four years and a revolution seems to be imperative. In the past, a phase of substantial growth has always been preceded by a revolution. The first such instance dates back to the 1760’s, when Industrial Revolution 1.0 began and was called a &lt;em&gt;Mechanical Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. It revolved around the production of machines that were powered and driven by water and steam. The &lt;em&gt;Technological Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, which was the Second Industrial Revolution, entailed the usage of electrical energy in the manufacturing process, helping in voluminous production. The launch of the internet was the third revolution, which was termed the &lt;em&gt;Virtual Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. The information technology sector had a boom, which promoted the use of electronics to automate the production line and achieve economies of scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry Revolution 4.0 and its impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What sets IR 4.0 apart from the earlier revolutions is the speed at which the revolution is approaching the world, and how its effects will be intangible. Industrial Revolution 4.0 is where the lines between the physical, digital and biological spheres get merged. Production, management and governance systems are likely to be revamped. And policies aligning Artificial intelligence (AI), drones and blockchain technology are already being implemented. Taking up AI technology helps in reducing the operational costs that are involved in the production process, increasing not only efficiency but also revenue. Improvement in the customer experience is also a benefit AI brings with itself. Only 15% of the enterprises in the world are using AI as of today, but 31% are expected to start making use of it in the coming 12 months, according to Adobe. The Fourth Industrial Revolution will allow hyper-connection. This will help connect not only one person to another person, but also machines to people. Amazon’s Alexa works using this technology and is representative of the hyper-connectivity between devices and humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will have an impact on a lot of sectors. The recruitment industry will be impacted in multiple ways. Firstly, less people will be required to be employed as robots will be prevalent. Secondly, the time taken to screen all CVs will get drastically reduced due to the invention of AI softwares, like Ideal, which will help recruiters. Increased automation is already phasing out the role of humans in the manufacturing industry and agriculture sector. It might even affect the pharmaceutical industry by replacing doctors with applications, and chemist with robots. Thirdly, the transportation sector will flourish with applications which help people to track their cab and ensure safety. The retail sector will also receive a lot of traffic as AI technology advances, where these online stores will already know what you want before you even place the order. With cashlessness taking over the globe, the banking sector will face a setback as everything will be online. With a substantial impact on each of these sectors, it surely will lead to digitising the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenges posed to policy makers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data forms the base of the revolution, and for a digital economy, exchange of data holds utmost significance. Facebook’s data breach took everybody by surprise. Security of the IT sector, privacy of data, maintenance of the integrity of the production process and excessive investment are few of the challenges associated with the transformation. Another challenge is the availability of AI talent. These people are in high demand, and the demand-supply ratio is quite skewed. The skill set required by the companies isn’t readily available in the job seekers currently. The maximum supply gap is at the middle-level. If these professionals get lured by high salaries being offered by companies in the developed world, it would not help to bridge the technological gap between developing and developed nations. Further, cities across the world are already grappling with parking space issues. The situation is likely to get worsened as by the end of the next decade, large fleets of drones will be very common and would need parking space. Policy makers have to equip themselves to solve these issues, both big and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are we moving towards a “jobless future”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dystopian future where robots are ubiquitous and humans are merely power sources may be the norm in the coming decades. It is important for humans to change the complexion of the job market. A recent research by McKinsey says that 45% of the current jobs can be automated. Few beginnings have already been made in this direction. Japan has already taken the first step towards this advancement and there are companies that are in the business of “saying sorry.” They hire people to apologise on behalf of others. Not far behind, in China, one can hire boyfriends who can help ladies with shopping and take perfect selfies. Robots that have been created to help humans, may become job creators for humans in future. They will require an entire ecosystem of support staff to optimise their performance and to avail services such as robot maintenance and robot monitoring. Robot ethicists may also be in great demand. But what we need to understand is that AI as whole could be a big benefit to entire humanity if used in the proper direction. What a lot of experts believe is that to make a productive future, it is pertinent for humans to work alongside robots to make the process faster. Therefore, it wouldn’t be a surprise to see robots doing the work which requires mindless skills whilst humans work on managing the system and adding a creative touch to the process. Their jobs would transform, and re-skilling themselves and expanding their skill set is the need of the hour. This goes on to prove that jobs are changing, but not going away, humans simply need to change and keep evolving to fit in society better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manya Manushi</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Imagine you book something from your favourite food outlet online. A robot cooks the food and it is then delivered by a driverless van or a drone. A world where humans are being replaced by robots no longer seems to be a scene from a Sci-Fi film. Recently, a British online supermarket, ‘Ocado,’ successfully developed a completely automatic system of picking up grocery items for its customers. This is representative of the fact that we are moving towards a Digital Revolution, which is generally termed as the ‘Fourth Industrial Revolution’ (IR 4).</summary></entry></feed>