<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-03-13T02:24:11+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Can Minimum Wage Reduce Poverty?</title><link href="/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Minimum Wage Reduce Poverty?" /><published>2019-03-08T23:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-08T23:45:00+00:00</updated><id>/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A guide to its effective implementation…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimum wage in the United Kingdom is considered one of the most successful
government policies ever implemented. It was intricately planned and structured
over a significant length of time. And with one of the lowest unemployment rates
in Europe, Britain, at first sight, appears to illustrate an accurate balance
between executing a minimum wage policy and preserving the uniform availability
of job opportunities (even if Brexit could change that drastically). Apart from
Britain, even Hong Kong has witnessed an upward trend in median monthly wages of
unskilled workers by 43% in money terms and 20% in real terms between 2010 and 2014. Synchronously, the 2014 Report on Annual Earnings and Hours Survey
published by The Census and Statistics Department outlines inputs from the
Minimum Wage Commission that indicate a fall in the unemployment rate for
elementary occupations from 4.4% in 2010 to 3.3% in 2014. Advocates of minimum
wage legislation argue that it can alter the income distribution in favour of
the low-paid labour force by attenuating the bottom tail of the distribution
model. Opponents criticise its “Disemployment Effect” and emphasise that it
might shrink the share of earnings going to the impoverished and destitute
workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A higher minimum wage, evidently, increases costs for firms. This may curtail
them from hiring the exceptionally low-wage, low-skill workers. David Neumark,
an American labour economist, terms this the “Disemployment Effect”. It is
characterised by the loss of jobs, reduction in working hours, automation, or
the struggle to enter into new jobs. The Disemployment Effect, if necessitated
by a minimum wage, invalidates the purpose of bringing in such a policy in the
first place. But this effect can be overcome. Firms can be offered economic
incentives such as subsidies and grants, to compensate for their increased
costs. Lower taxes and excise duties could also serve as economic incentives,
ensuring more cash is available for businesses to absorb the costs of paying a
higher minimum wage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Disemployment Effect is not the only uncertain outcome of a minimum
wage policy, especially in developing countries. As the minimum wage and poverty
lines are closer to each other in developing nations, an increase in minimum
wage could lift workers out of destitution. Yet, several minimum wage workers in
developing countries are young, work part-time, and belong to high-income
households. Correspondingly, most households in poverty seldom have anyone in
the workforce&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Hence, more often than not, a minimum wage ends up helping
the privileged and ignoring the needy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end poverty, a minimum wage should be determined for households and not
individuals. This will facilitate the redistribution of income to poor families
over low-earners of rich families. Simultaneously, governments must increase
spending on education and skill development to build an economy with a speedily
employable workforce, hence fostering growth and development. A minimum wage
policy also needs to tackle the problem of incomplete and irregular legal
coverage. Although minimum wages seem to be extensively applicable, in several
cases the coverage is ineffective and disregards those most in need of social
security, such as domestic workers or homeworkers. By neglecting a few crucial
sectors of the economy, we fail to fully utilise the potential of minimum wage
legislation. Even though legal coverage of the minimum wage developed from the
mid-2000’s to the late 2000’s in India and South Africa, it covered only about
70% of low-paid workers by late 2000’s; in Peru, domestic workers were barred
from the statutory minimum wage&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Research suggests that weak legal coverage
may at times ignore around one-third of all wage earners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may confront this perplexity by undertaking comprehensive legislation that
gratifies all sectors of an economy, and by ensuring that such legislation is
strictly enforced. This, while a herculean task, can be accomplished by the
extensive and intensive consultation of all stakeholders and a thorough analysis
of a variety of socioeconomic and employment data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimum wage is fast becoming a universally adopted policy today and the
principal question is how to operate the system in order to maximise its
benefits. A conscientiously devised minimum wage policy can relegate low pay,
inequalities, and poverty, at little or no adverse cost to employment. Yet, the
minimum wage either continues to be low in many countries, or applies solely to
certain select sectors. But with a little more fine-tuning, as I have suggested,
I believe it is possible to shape an effective minimum wage policy that
successfully reduces poverty and income inequalities across countries without
hurting the job market.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shivang Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">A guide to its effective implementation… The minimum wage in the United Kingdom is considered one of the most successful government policies ever implemented. It was intricately planned and structured over a significant length of time. And with one of the lowest unemployment rates in Europe, Britain, at first sight, appears to illustrate an accurate balance between executing a minimum wage policy and preserving the uniform availability of job opportunities (even if Brexit could change that drastically). Apart from Britain, even Hong Kong has witnessed an upward trend in median monthly wages of unskilled workers by 43% in money terms and 20% in real terms between 2010 and 2014. Synchronously, the 2014 Report on Annual Earnings and Hours Survey published by The Census and Statistics Department outlines inputs from the Minimum Wage Commission that indicate a fall in the unemployment rate for elementary occupations from 4.4% in 2010 to 3.3% in 2014. Advocates of minimum wage legislation argue that it can alter the income distribution in favour of the low-paid labour force by attenuating the bottom tail of the distribution model. Opponents criticise its “Disemployment Effect” and emphasise that it might shrink the share of earnings going to the impoverished and destitute workforce. A higher minimum wage, evidently, increases costs for firms. This may curtail them from hiring the exceptionally low-wage, low-skill workers. David Neumark, an American labour economist, terms this the “Disemployment Effect”. It is characterised by the loss of jobs, reduction in working hours, automation, or the struggle to enter into new jobs. The Disemployment Effect, if necessitated by a minimum wage, invalidates the purpose of bringing in such a policy in the first place. But this effect can be overcome. Firms can be offered economic incentives such as subsidies and grants, to compensate for their increased costs. Lower taxes and excise duties could also serve as economic incentives, ensuring more cash is available for businesses to absorb the costs of paying a higher minimum wage. However, the Disemployment Effect is not the only uncertain outcome of a minimum wage policy, especially in developing countries. As the minimum wage and poverty lines are closer to each other in developing nations, an increase in minimum wage could lift workers out of destitution. Yet, several minimum wage workers in developing countries are young, work part-time, and belong to high-income households. Correspondingly, most households in poverty seldom have anyone in the workforce. Hence, more often than not, a minimum wage ends up helping the privileged and ignoring the needy. To end poverty, a minimum wage should be determined for households and not individuals. This will facilitate the redistribution of income to poor families over low-earners of rich families. Simultaneously, governments must increase spending on education and skill development to build an economy with a speedily employable workforce, hence fostering growth and development. A minimum wage policy also needs to tackle the problem of incomplete and irregular legal coverage. Although minimum wages seem to be extensively applicable, in several cases the coverage is ineffective and disregards those most in need of social security, such as domestic workers or homeworkers. By neglecting a few crucial sectors of the economy, we fail to fully utilise the potential of minimum wage legislation. Even though legal coverage of the minimum wage developed from the mid-2000’s to the late 2000’s in India and South Africa, it covered only about 70% of low-paid workers by late 2000’s; in Peru, domestic workers were barred from the statutory minimum wage. Research suggests that weak legal coverage may at times ignore around one-third of all wage earners. We may confront this perplexity by undertaking comprehensive legislation that gratifies all sectors of an economy, and by ensuring that such legislation is strictly enforced. This, while a herculean task, can be accomplished by the extensive and intensive consultation of all stakeholders and a thorough analysis of a variety of socioeconomic and employment data. The minimum wage is fast becoming a universally adopted policy today and the principal question is how to operate the system in order to maximise its benefits. A conscientiously devised minimum wage policy can relegate low pay, inequalities, and poverty, at little or no adverse cost to employment. Yet, the minimum wage either continues to be low in many countries, or applies solely to certain select sectors. But with a little more fine-tuning, as I have suggested, I believe it is possible to shape an effective minimum wage policy that successfully reduces poverty and income inequalities across countries without hurting the job market.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities</title><link href="/Micro-Economies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities" /><published>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/Micro-Economies</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Micro-Economies">&lt;p&gt;Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less
than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce,
University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a
population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present,
there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of
countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are
prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite
their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of
the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic
systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or
island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they
are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as
the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several
countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods
produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports
costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected
to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces
labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work.
Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of
labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face
‘&lt;em&gt;diseconomies of size’&lt;/em&gt; due to low demand and high production costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence,
these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited
range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to
poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact
that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more
than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted
poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low
GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a
GNP per capita of less than $500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It
is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to
providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as
well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge
amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as
well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population.
This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the
case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is
low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on
building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways,
and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign
investment never comes into these countries, creating a &lt;em&gt;chakravyuh&lt;/em&gt; (vicious cycle) of poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies
are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service,
in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population,
the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are
ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over
the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident
from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40%
in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact,
imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these
countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to
international events and shocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering
paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial
crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an
impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two
years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the
standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means
that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as
compared to the world average of 3.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the
parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is
beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African
island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific
depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried
out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as
well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the
fate of these micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their
children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund,
the International Development Association and various other regional and
international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for
developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies
provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these
grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different
micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and
increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains
of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and
the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete
disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is
necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to
look towards the international community and the United Nations for their
sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk
management. &lt;em&gt;Debt bells ringing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as
well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access
to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have
Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant
foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources
from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of
income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on
their territory (China and India are watching closely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and
multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most
prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the
mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by
deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation,
including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax
haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no
exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Alberto Alesina said in his book &lt;em&gt;Size of Nations&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s
degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they
wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single
commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which
have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their
economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers
or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception
than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop,
progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence
of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way
in bringing a change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhishek Sancheti</name></author><category term="economics" /><category term="headline" /><category term="trending" /><summary type="html">Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce, University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present, there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world. These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies. Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work. Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face ‘diseconomies of size’ due to low demand and high production costs. Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence, these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a GNP per capita of less than $500. Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population. This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways, and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign investment never comes into these countries, creating a chakravyuh (vicious cycle) of poverty. With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service, in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population, the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over the rest of the world. Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40% in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact, imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to international events and shocks. Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as compared to the world average of 3.2%. These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the fate of these micro-economies. However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund, the International Development Association and various other regional and international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different micro-economies. One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to look towards the international community and the United Nations for their sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk management. Debt bells ringing. In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on their territory (China and India are watching closely). Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation, including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits. As Alberto Alesina said in his book Size of Nations: “Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.” Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop, progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way in bringing a change.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Corbyn to Podemos, Don’t Forgive Maduro’s Cheerleaders</title><link href="/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Corbyn to Podemos, Don't Forgive Maduro’s Cheerleaders" /><published>2019-03-07T04:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-07T04:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos</id><content type="html" xml:base="/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos">&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is on fire. Two decades of mismanagement by a corrupt regime has left
its people starving, fleeing, and cowering from government death squads. Venezuela,
the world’s most oil-rich state is in ruins. The extent of the spoil has been so
thorough that it now imports more oil from the United States than it produces.
Much of this is because of the severe deficiency of refinement infrastructure.
In addition, hyperinflation has been a major battle for the administration. For
a nation which does not print its own currency, this surely is a cruel fate.
Cash money has become a rare sight. Probably due to the fact that the government
can barely afford to buy new currency. Last Christmas, a plane from Basingstoke
(a quaint Hampshire town) touched down in Caracas, filled with newly printed
Bolivars. The lowest valued note onboard was already worth less than a single US
cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the problems for the Venezuelans weren’t just limited to financial setbacks.
It includes corruption, violence, and extreme disparity within the economic
classes―which fueled tensions. In 2016, the incumbent President, Nicolas Maduro
created a new wing of the police, the Special Action Force or FAES. Various
human rights groups have accused them of acting as Death Squads. They have
allegedly entered low-income neighbourhoods to harass and, sometimes, execute
the rivals and competitors of the regime. Since the beginning of the year,
forty-three protestors have been confirmed to have died in clashes with the
police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicolas Maduro and his predecessor, Hugo Chavez have taken actions that have had
a tragic effect on the lives of ordinary Venezuelans. Over 3.4 million people
now live as refugees, desperately trying to flee poverty. The wealthiest nation
of South America, just a few decades ago, is now a page out of a book and
nothing more. But what makes the Maduro regime so unique is the support it gets
from many useful idiots across the developed world. While dictators like Robert
Mugabe in Zimbabwe and Bashar Al-Assad in Syria have arguably committed far more
heinous crimes against their own people, neither can boast such a committed fan
base in wealthy nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Corbyn, the leader of the UK Labour Party and Her Majesty’s Most Loyal
Opposition is an avid fan of the Chavez-Maduro regime. He has personally called
Maduro to congratulate him on an election victory in 2016. This is the very
election which was decried as unfair by Human Rights Watch. The Labour Party is
the second largest party in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the
largest political movement in Europe by the membership. Its prominent members
include Owen Jones who wrote in 2012, “Chavez’s critics in the West are entitled
to passionately disagree with him. But it’s time they stopped pretending he is a
dictator”. That was 4 years after Chavez expelled Human Rights Watch from the
country. In 2014, Corbyn’s top lieutenant John Mcdonnell said, “Here you had the
contrast between capitalism in crisis, and socialism in action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this article isn’t about the asinine debate on whether the Venezuelan
economy can truly be considered socialist or not. I personally doubt a regime as
corrupt as Chavez’s could have ever carried out the necessary reforms to
institute a socialist economy. But we should remember the man who may soon be
the UK Chancellor of The Exchequer (Finance Minister), lauded Venezuela a
‘socialist’ regime, saying it was a nation worth emulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greek Prime Minister, Alexis Tsipras, was the only European head of
government who had attended Hugo Chavez’s funeral, way back in 2012. There he
praised Venezuela as an anti-capitalist model country, and has since remained
friendly with the Venezuelan regime. This has continued over the current crisis.
It should be noted that Tsipras hasn’t instituted the type of authoritarian
reforms of the Chavez and Maduro regimes for his own country. But his fondness
for their government begs the question: what would he have done if Syriza had
achieved a majority in the Greek Parliament or if he didn’t have the European
Union overseeing his administration ready to sanction it for anti-democratic
policies. Jean-Luc Melancon, the leader of the French Left, also in the past,
praised the Chavez regime. In 2013, he described it as a “source of
inspiration”. However, since then, he has changed his mind claiming that he
doesn’t “support dictatorship”, and that he has “never supported dictatorship
anywhere in the world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is Podemos, the Spanish Left-wing party. Since, its foundation, it
has had a special relationship with the Bolivarian regime in Venezuela. Several
of its founders, including its leader Pablo Iglesia, have been economic advisors
to the Venezuelan government. Iglesia once called Venezuela “one of the most
consolidated democracies in the world”. According to a think tank, which is
close to the party, Podemos has received millions in funding from the regime, as
published in the Spanish newspaper ABC. Nevertheless, Iglesia has now u-turned
on his support for the dictatorship. Earlier this year, he was caught on record
saying, “I don’t agree with some of the things I said in the past, and I believe
that the political and economic situation in Venezuela is disastrous. To rectify
in politics is a good thing”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few months, voters all across Europe will have the chance to vote, in free
and fair elections, for who they want as their representatives in the European
Parliament. Voting is a hard-fought privilege held by far less than half of the
world’s population. It was once the right that the people of Venezuela had. If
the European Left’s radical leaders, who supported Chavez and Maduro, win the
elections they are, of course, unlikely to institute the authoritarian policies
as seen in Venezuela. This is because Europe’s civic institutions are strong and
it’s people remember what a dictator looks like. Having said that though, we
must remember that the support of the radical Left for the Venezuelan regime is
a cause for grave concern to the lovers of democracy. It resonates the hard
truth, as to what type of policies all these leaders would like to introduce, if
only they had the power they believe they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reuben Pritchard</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Venezuela is on fire. Two decades of mismanagement by a corrupt regime has left its people starving, fleeing, and cowering from government death squads. Venezuela, the world’s most oil-rich state is in ruins. The extent of the spoil has been so thorough that it now imports more oil from the United States than it produces. Much of this is because of the severe deficiency of refinement infrastructure. In addition, hyperinflation has been a major battle for the administration. For a nation which does not print its own currency, this surely is a cruel fate. Cash money has become a rare sight. Probably due to the fact that the government can barely afford to buy new currency. Last Christmas, a plane from Basingstoke (a quaint Hampshire town) touched down in Caracas, filled with newly printed Bolivars. The lowest valued note onboard was already worth less than a single US cent. But the problems for the Venezuelans weren’t just limited to financial setbacks. It includes corruption, violence, and extreme disparity within the economic classes―which fueled tensions. In 2016, the incumbent President, Nicolas Maduro created a new wing of the police, the Special Action Force or FAES. Various human rights groups have accused them of acting as Death Squads. They have allegedly entered low-income neighbourhoods to harass and, sometimes, execute the rivals and competitors of the regime. Since the beginning of the year, forty-three protestors have been confirmed to have died in clashes with the police. Nicolas Maduro and his predecessor, Hugo Chavez have taken actions that have had a tragic effect on the lives of ordinary Venezuelans. Over 3.4 million people now live as refugees, desperately trying to flee poverty. The wealthiest nation of South America, just a few decades ago, is now a page out of a book and nothing more. But what makes the Maduro regime so unique is the support it gets from many useful idiots across the developed world. While dictators like Robert Mugabe in Zimbabwe and Bashar Al-Assad in Syria have arguably committed far more heinous crimes against their own people, neither can boast such a committed fan base in wealthy nations. Jeremy Corbyn, the leader of the UK Labour Party and Her Majesty’s Most Loyal Opposition is an avid fan of the Chavez-Maduro regime. He has personally called Maduro to congratulate him on an election victory in 2016. This is the very election which was decried as unfair by Human Rights Watch. The Labour Party is the second largest party in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the largest political movement in Europe by the membership. Its prominent members include Owen Jones who wrote in 2012, “Chavez’s critics in the West are entitled to passionately disagree with him. But it’s time they stopped pretending he is a dictator”. That was 4 years after Chavez expelled Human Rights Watch from the country. In 2014, Corbyn’s top lieutenant John Mcdonnell said, “Here you had the contrast between capitalism in crisis, and socialism in action.” Now, this article isn’t about the asinine debate on whether the Venezuelan economy can truly be considered socialist or not. I personally doubt a regime as corrupt as Chavez’s could have ever carried out the necessary reforms to institute a socialist economy. But we should remember the man who may soon be the UK Chancellor of The Exchequer (Finance Minister), lauded Venezuela a ‘socialist’ regime, saying it was a nation worth emulating. The Greek Prime Minister, Alexis Tsipras, was the only European head of government who had attended Hugo Chavez’s funeral, way back in 2012. There he praised Venezuela as an anti-capitalist model country, and has since remained friendly with the Venezuelan regime. This has continued over the current crisis. It should be noted that Tsipras hasn’t instituted the type of authoritarian reforms of the Chavez and Maduro regimes for his own country. But his fondness for their government begs the question: what would he have done if Syriza had achieved a majority in the Greek Parliament or if he didn’t have the European Union overseeing his administration ready to sanction it for anti-democratic policies. Jean-Luc Melancon, the leader of the French Left, also in the past, praised the Chavez regime. In 2013, he described it as a “source of inspiration”. However, since then, he has changed his mind claiming that he doesn’t “support dictatorship”, and that he has “never supported dictatorship anywhere in the world”. Then there is Podemos, the Spanish Left-wing party. Since, its foundation, it has had a special relationship with the Bolivarian regime in Venezuela. Several of its founders, including its leader Pablo Iglesia, have been economic advisors to the Venezuelan government. Iglesia once called Venezuela “one of the most consolidated democracies in the world”. According to a think tank, which is close to the party, Podemos has received millions in funding from the regime, as published in the Spanish newspaper ABC. Nevertheless, Iglesia has now u-turned on his support for the dictatorship. Earlier this year, he was caught on record saying, “I don’t agree with some of the things I said in the past, and I believe that the political and economic situation in Venezuela is disastrous. To rectify in politics is a good thing”. In a few months, voters all across Europe will have the chance to vote, in free and fair elections, for who they want as their representatives in the European Parliament. Voting is a hard-fought privilege held by far less than half of the world’s population. It was once the right that the people of Venezuela had. If the European Left’s radical leaders, who supported Chavez and Maduro, win the elections they are, of course, unlikely to institute the authoritarian policies as seen in Venezuela. This is because Europe’s civic institutions are strong and it’s people remember what a dictator looks like. Having said that though, we must remember that the support of the radical Left for the Venezuelan regime is a cause for grave concern to the lovers of democracy. It resonates the hard truth, as to what type of policies all these leaders would like to introduce, if only they had the power they believe they deserve.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Most Hated Religion in the World</title><link href="/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Hated Religion in the World" /><published>2019-03-07T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-07T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World">&lt;p&gt;If you were to ask the Joe on the street “Which is the most
hated/persecuted/marginalized religious group in the world?” you would probably
get a range of different answers, depending upon the interviewee’s political
orientation(s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People leaning towards the left would most likely say, “Islam. Islamophobia is a
big problem in the West. Definitely.” Others leaning towards the right would
probably say “The Jews. They have suffered the most and even now, Israel is
under threat from Islamic fundamentalists. We must stand with Israel.” In India,
it would probably be, “The Hindus! Just look at the Kashmiri Pandits.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t deny that each of these groups has suffered immensely in the past. I
sympathise strongly with anyone who has been persecuted or discriminated against
in the secular sphere on the basis of their race, religion, economic status or
sex. It goes without saying that I condemn all forms of religious bigotry. But
in my humble opinion, neither Islam nor Judaism can claim the title. In my mind,
the most hated religion in the world today is Catholic Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What?!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know. It sounds strange. But spare me the incredulous look, because I am just
about to back up my claims with extraordinarily strong evidence. But before I do
that, let me tell you my story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself was raised in the Hindu community, but after a decade-long search for
the truth, I lost faith in the faith of my forefathers. I am now making my way
across to Christianity, and in all likelihood, I will end up either Roman
Catholic or in Eastern Orthodoxy. I have studied more religions and
denominations than I can remember – from the Ahl-e-Hadith (and the lesser known
Ahl-e-Qur’an) to the long-extinct Zurvanism – and I will soon begin an
undergraduate degree in Theology at the University of Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends, I can testify with all my heart that there is no religious group
that is more maligned, slandered and attacked in popular culture than the
Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every worldview is built upon some major controlling narrative or the
other. Modern society is the offspring of three great ideological uprisings in
the past, all of which are overtly and vehemently anti-Catholic, either
prominently or tangentially. You might have guessed two of them, but the third
one may surprise you. I am speaking of the Enlightenment, the Protestant
Reformation and the rise of Marxism. Now let’s consider their controlling
narratives one by one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Enlightenment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world had great and immense potential since the evolution of the &lt;em&gt;homo
sapiens&lt;/em&gt;. A great example of this was Europe, which in the classical world was a
great hub of learning, philosophy, art, and science. Great thinkers and minds
arose who tirelessly “stretched forward their hands towards perfection” in
Greece and Rome. All of this was happening – until the rise of Christianity, the
most intolerant branch of which is the Catholic Church. Led by the theocratic
impositions of Constantine, the Catholic Church brought all of Europe under
their tyrannical captivity. Superstition reigned; science was stifled; the
freedom of the heart was curbed; man was put into chains. The growth and
progress of Europe were stunted… until the great Renaissance dawned upon
mankind, and Europe was reborn – a phoenix rising from the ashes. The captivity
of Rome was overthrown and the great continent emerged, to build its future on
its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Protestant Reformation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, Christ and the Apostles built up the Church and commanded them
to preach the Gospel far and wide. All was going well… but over the centuries,
slowly but gradually, pagan influence began to creep into the Church.
Superstition and idolatry gradually came to cloud the Gospel, and eventually, it
was lost for good! The situation was especially bad in Western Europe, where the
Pope presided in the place of God, reigning down his ungodly tyranny upon the
masses, chaining the Christian and denying him his rightful freedom. The Spirit
of God departed for a while from the pagan Roman church… until at last, the
seeds laid by the great martyrs Wycliffe and Hus bore fruit, and the heroes of
the faith – Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin – emerged. These luminaries showed us
the path and helped us break the chains of Roman tyranny. The Reformation was a
glorious cleansing of the church, and countless souls were freed from the
captivity of the Roman harlot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marxism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History is marked primarily by class-struggle. From ages past, the privileged
(the haves) have oppressed the have-nots. A prime example of this is seen in the
decadent, superstitious Catholic Church. This is an organisation that has
promoted colonialism (the Crusades being a great example) and continues to have
an authoritarian patriarchal structure of clericalism and privilege that
oppresses the common man. To this day, the Pope and his henchmen participate in
the oppression of the masses, by opposing abortion, contraception and denying
women equality by not ordaining them to the priesthood. This organisation must
change, or perish. The common people must arise out of the chains of this
tyranny!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you have been studying the three movements I describe, you will quickly
see that absolutely nothing I have written is an exaggeration. For example, if
you are acquainted with Protestant polemical literature (as I am), you will
notice that many of the terms I have used – “Roman harlot”, “Roman [Babylonian]
captivity”, “freedom of the Christian”, “chains of bondage and superstition”,
“false gospel”, etc. – are not mine, but the exact terms used by Protestants to
this day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice also, another thing: though these movements all originated in Europe,
they have since then been widely disseminated. There are more than 900 million
Protestants around the world (almost an eighth of the world population). The
philosophy of the Enlightenment has spread around the globe as well, as
evidenced by the fact that most of the countries in the world are (or, at least,
claim to be) liberal secular democracies. And, of course, Marxism has claimed
the most populous country in the world as its own and continues to have a loud
presence around the world (particularly among the students and youth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me? Am I just seeing it this way because I myself strongly lean RC?
(Well, technically, I began leaning RC after I saw its theology being vastly
misrepresented and slandered in Protestant fundamentalist circles on the
internet). But it’s not just me by any stretch of the imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what pro-life activist, journalist and Orthodox Jew Ben Shapiro had to
say at a conference in Dana Point, CA: “Unfortunately, the attacks [by radical
leftists] on Catholics have come first and foremost […] It’s really fascinating
to watch, not just from a Jewish perspective. Usually, we’re the first on the
hit list. Now it’s you guys.” Shapiro went on to note several instances of
anti-Catholic prejudice in the popular media. But one could also note the
attitude of contempt several Democrat politicians displayed towards conservative
Catholicism as we see, for example, US Senator Diane Feinstein’s bluntly stated
to the Catholic judicial nominee Amy Barrett, “The dogma lives loudly within
you”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the historical data? Don’t they prove that the Catholic Church
is, indeed, so to speak, “guilty as charged”? Not so, says non-Catholic
sociologist, University of California Berkeley scholar and Pulitzer
Prize-winning author Rodney Stark, who has written many books on Christian
history, including several defending Catholicism from what he says as unfounded
attacks and slanderous misrepresentations. Among his many works are &lt;em&gt;God’s
Battalions: The Case for the Crusades&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Reformation Myths and Bearing False
Witness: Debunking Centuries of Anti-Catholic Lies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America, of course, is historically extremely anti-Catholic. And with the
worldwide dominance of American culture as well as the proliferation of
American-style Evangelicalism, anti-Catholicism too has spread around the world.
But don’t take my word for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Reeves is Cambridge scholar and a professor of Church history at
Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, one of the eminent Protestant institutions
in the USA. Several of his lectures are available on his YouTube channel (in my
opinion, an invaluable contribution to public education). I highly recommend his
lecture &lt;em&gt;Catholics in America&lt;/em&gt;. In it, Reeves discusses how, historically, large
sections of the Protestant population in America have always tried to,
especially in the face of Catholic immigration, “slander and to mock and to
lampoon Catholics, in an effort to demoralize and ideally to get them to convert
to Protestantism”. (Since Professor Reeves is teaching at a well-respected
Protestant institution, I will similarly assume that he is a Protestant and has
no dog in this fight.) He goes on to discuss historically famous instances of
anti-Catholic propaganda, including the ghost-written 18th century bestseller
autobiography of “Maria Monk”, which claimed to expose scandalous debauchery and
immorality within Catholic convents, and which – according to Dr. Reeves - we
now know to be a complete hoax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-evidently, hatred against Catholics must change due to the simple social
rule that one ought not to be persecuted for one’s beliefs. Here are three
things which I think need to happen in order to help the situation change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, people need to better appreciate and understand the Catholic Church’s
rich and vibrant intellectual history, especially the glories of the Middle Ages - figures like Aquinas, Anselm, Ockham, Peter Abelard, Duns Scotus and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the anti-fideism of Catholic theology needs to be properly recognised
as well (I’m looking at you, Christopher Hitchens). The doctrine of the
interplay and complementary nature of faith and reason, popularised by Aquinas
and officially adopted by the Catholic Church at the First Vatican Council, will
only lead the devout Catholic to a deeper admiration of and respect towards the
sciences, not a fear of them. Hence, we have great Catholic scientists like
Gregor Mendel, George Lemaitre, Roger Bacon, Albertus Magnus and – of course –
Nicolaus Copernicus (who, by the way, was respected and admired by several
Catholic clergymen of his time, including Pope Clement VII). For example, on
November 1, 1536, Cardinal Nikolaus von Schönberg, Archbishop of Capua, wrote to
Copernicus expressing profound admiration, and requesting him to tell him more
about his new cosmology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, people need to remember the mistakes made by Catholics in the past.
Yes, Catholics are not, and have never been, perfect people. They have made
mistakes, like any other group. We must not repeat the errors of antiquity, and
we must remember and learn from them. But, at the same time, we must also
recognise the fact that the Catholic hierarchy (I’m talking about folks like
Popes John Paul II and Francis I) has publicly apologised for many of the past
excesses and sought forgiveness for the same. An institution that is ready to
own up to its mistakes in such a public manner shines a ray of hope for the
world. And it is only such an attitude of humility, repentance, and desire to
change that will help contemporary Catholics overcome the ecclesiastical abuses
and errors of the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">If you were to ask the Joe on the street “Which is the most hated/persecuted/marginalized religious group in the world?” you would probably get a range of different answers, depending upon the interviewee’s political orientation(s). People leaning towards the left would most likely say, “Islam. Islamophobia is a big problem in the West. Definitely.” Others leaning towards the right would probably say “The Jews. They have suffered the most and even now, Israel is under threat from Islamic fundamentalists. We must stand with Israel.” In India, it would probably be, “The Hindus! Just look at the Kashmiri Pandits.” And I don’t deny that each of these groups has suffered immensely in the past. I sympathise strongly with anyone who has been persecuted or discriminated against in the secular sphere on the basis of their race, religion, economic status or sex. It goes without saying that I condemn all forms of religious bigotry. But in my humble opinion, neither Islam nor Judaism can claim the title. In my mind, the most hated religion in the world today is Catholic Christianity. “What?!” I know. It sounds strange. But spare me the incredulous look, because I am just about to back up my claims with extraordinarily strong evidence. But before I do that, let me tell you my story. I myself was raised in the Hindu community, but after a decade-long search for the truth, I lost faith in the faith of my forefathers. I am now making my way across to Christianity, and in all likelihood, I will end up either Roman Catholic or in Eastern Orthodoxy. I have studied more religions and denominations than I can remember – from the Ahl-e-Hadith (and the lesser known Ahl-e-Qur’an) to the long-extinct Zurvanism – and I will soon begin an undergraduate degree in Theology at the University of Oxford. My friends, I can testify with all my heart that there is no religious group that is more maligned, slandered and attacked in popular culture than the Catholic Church. Each and every worldview is built upon some major controlling narrative or the other. Modern society is the offspring of three great ideological uprisings in the past, all of which are overtly and vehemently anti-Catholic, either prominently or tangentially. You might have guessed two of them, but the third one may surprise you. I am speaking of the Enlightenment, the Protestant Reformation and the rise of Marxism. Now let’s consider their controlling narratives one by one. The Enlightenment The world had great and immense potential since the evolution of the homo sapiens. A great example of this was Europe, which in the classical world was a great hub of learning, philosophy, art, and science. Great thinkers and minds arose who tirelessly “stretched forward their hands towards perfection” in Greece and Rome. All of this was happening – until the rise of Christianity, the most intolerant branch of which is the Catholic Church. Led by the theocratic impositions of Constantine, the Catholic Church brought all of Europe under their tyrannical captivity. Superstition reigned; science was stifled; the freedom of the heart was curbed; man was put into chains. The growth and progress of Europe were stunted… until the great Renaissance dawned upon mankind, and Europe was reborn – a phoenix rising from the ashes. The captivity of Rome was overthrown and the great continent emerged, to build its future on its own. The Protestant Reformation In the beginning, Christ and the Apostles built up the Church and commanded them to preach the Gospel far and wide. All was going well… but over the centuries, slowly but gradually, pagan influence began to creep into the Church. Superstition and idolatry gradually came to cloud the Gospel, and eventually, it was lost for good! The situation was especially bad in Western Europe, where the Pope presided in the place of God, reigning down his ungodly tyranny upon the masses, chaining the Christian and denying him his rightful freedom. The Spirit of God departed for a while from the pagan Roman church… until at last, the seeds laid by the great martyrs Wycliffe and Hus bore fruit, and the heroes of the faith – Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin – emerged. These luminaries showed us the path and helped us break the chains of Roman tyranny. The Reformation was a glorious cleansing of the church, and countless souls were freed from the captivity of the Roman harlot. Marxism History is marked primarily by class-struggle. From ages past, the privileged (the haves) have oppressed the have-nots. A prime example of this is seen in the decadent, superstitious Catholic Church. This is an organisation that has promoted colonialism (the Crusades being a great example) and continues to have an authoritarian patriarchal structure of clericalism and privilege that oppresses the common man. To this day, the Pope and his henchmen participate in the oppression of the masses, by opposing abortion, contraception and denying women equality by not ordaining them to the priesthood. This organisation must change, or perish. The common people must arise out of the chains of this tyranny! Now, if you have been studying the three movements I describe, you will quickly see that absolutely nothing I have written is an exaggeration. For example, if you are acquainted with Protestant polemical literature (as I am), you will notice that many of the terms I have used – “Roman harlot”, “Roman [Babylonian] captivity”, “freedom of the Christian”, “chains of bondage and superstition”, “false gospel”, etc. – are not mine, but the exact terms used by Protestants to this day! Notice also, another thing: though these movements all originated in Europe, they have since then been widely disseminated. There are more than 900 million Protestants around the world (almost an eighth of the world population). The philosophy of the Enlightenment has spread around the globe as well, as evidenced by the fact that most of the countries in the world are (or, at least, claim to be) liberal secular democracies. And, of course, Marxism has claimed the most populous country in the world as its own and continues to have a loud presence around the world (particularly among the students and youth). Is it just me? Am I just seeing it this way because I myself strongly lean RC? (Well, technically, I began leaning RC after I saw its theology being vastly misrepresented and slandered in Protestant fundamentalist circles on the internet). But it’s not just me by any stretch of the imagination. Here is what pro-life activist, journalist and Orthodox Jew Ben Shapiro had to say at a conference in Dana Point, CA: “Unfortunately, the attacks [by radical leftists] on Catholics have come first and foremost […] It’s really fascinating to watch, not just from a Jewish perspective. Usually, we’re the first on the hit list. Now it’s you guys.” Shapiro went on to note several instances of anti-Catholic prejudice in the popular media. But one could also note the attitude of contempt several Democrat politicians displayed towards conservative Catholicism as we see, for example, US Senator Diane Feinstein’s bluntly stated to the Catholic judicial nominee Amy Barrett, “The dogma lives loudly within you”. But what about the historical data? Don’t they prove that the Catholic Church is, indeed, so to speak, “guilty as charged”? Not so, says non-Catholic sociologist, University of California Berkeley scholar and Pulitzer Prize-winning author Rodney Stark, who has written many books on Christian history, including several defending Catholicism from what he says as unfounded attacks and slanderous misrepresentations. Among his many works are God’s Battalions: The Case for the Crusades, Reformation Myths and Bearing False Witness: Debunking Centuries of Anti-Catholic Lies. America, of course, is historically extremely anti-Catholic. And with the worldwide dominance of American culture as well as the proliferation of American-style Evangelicalism, anti-Catholicism too has spread around the world. But don’t take my word for it. Ryan Reeves is Cambridge scholar and a professor of Church history at Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, one of the eminent Protestant institutions in the USA. Several of his lectures are available on his YouTube channel (in my opinion, an invaluable contribution to public education). I highly recommend his lecture Catholics in America. In it, Reeves discusses how, historically, large sections of the Protestant population in America have always tried to, especially in the face of Catholic immigration, “slander and to mock and to lampoon Catholics, in an effort to demoralize and ideally to get them to convert to Protestantism”. (Since Professor Reeves is teaching at a well-respected Protestant institution, I will similarly assume that he is a Protestant and has no dog in this fight.) He goes on to discuss historically famous instances of anti-Catholic propaganda, including the ghost-written 18th century bestseller autobiography of “Maria Monk”, which claimed to expose scandalous debauchery and immorality within Catholic convents, and which – according to Dr. Reeves - we now know to be a complete hoax. Self-evidently, hatred against Catholics must change due to the simple social rule that one ought not to be persecuted for one’s beliefs. Here are three things which I think need to happen in order to help the situation change. Firstly, people need to better appreciate and understand the Catholic Church’s rich and vibrant intellectual history, especially the glories of the Middle Ages - figures like Aquinas, Anselm, Ockham, Peter Abelard, Duns Scotus and so on. Secondly, the anti-fideism of Catholic theology needs to be properly recognised as well (I’m looking at you, Christopher Hitchens). The doctrine of the interplay and complementary nature of faith and reason, popularised by Aquinas and officially adopted by the Catholic Church at the First Vatican Council, will only lead the devout Catholic to a deeper admiration of and respect towards the sciences, not a fear of them. Hence, we have great Catholic scientists like Gregor Mendel, George Lemaitre, Roger Bacon, Albertus Magnus and – of course – Nicolaus Copernicus (who, by the way, was respected and admired by several Catholic clergymen of his time, including Pope Clement VII). For example, on November 1, 1536, Cardinal Nikolaus von Schönberg, Archbishop of Capua, wrote to Copernicus expressing profound admiration, and requesting him to tell him more about his new cosmology. Thirdly, people need to remember the mistakes made by Catholics in the past. Yes, Catholics are not, and have never been, perfect people. They have made mistakes, like any other group. We must not repeat the errors of antiquity, and we must remember and learn from them. But, at the same time, we must also recognise the fact that the Catholic hierarchy (I’m talking about folks like Popes John Paul II and Francis I) has publicly apologised for many of the past excesses and sought forgiveness for the same. An institution that is ready to own up to its mistakes in such a public manner shines a ray of hope for the world. And it is only such an attitude of humility, repentance, and desire to change that will help contemporary Catholics overcome the ecclesiastical abuses and errors of the modern world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Picture of Dorian Gray – Final Thoughts from the Composer’s Desk</title><link href="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Picture of Dorian Gray – Final Thoughts from the Composer’s Desk" /><published>2019-03-07T03:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-07T03:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2">&lt;p&gt;It strikes me that whenever I announced to people that I had set about writing
an opera, I never actually received that reaction I expected. I was certain I’d
be met with derision – “What makes you think YOU can write one, Bowes?” Up to
the point that I began working on &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;, I had only really written choral
music and a few songs. My only forays into purely instrumental music consisted
of a piano quintet I concocted for my A-level coursework, an arrangement of a
school song (&lt;em&gt;Bedford by the River&lt;/em&gt; – won a cash prize for it, to be fair), and
a frankly ridiculous setting of the &lt;em&gt;Requiem Mass&lt;/em&gt;, which I hope will never be
performed in its current state. Yet, the reaction, especially when I told
everyone of the subject-matter of this opera, Wilde’s seminal novella &lt;em&gt;The
Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt;, was unanimously positive. A few more knowledgeable
friends asked whether it had been done before, to which I ask: how many versions
of &lt;em&gt;Faust&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt; are there? Answer: frankly too many, not that I
wouldn’t consider doing a &lt;em&gt;Faust&lt;/em&gt;-related one at some point – indeed, one can
see &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; itself as a Faustian tale. Nevertheless, the reception to the idea
was that I ought to push on, and so I did. Thus, I have reached the end of the
compositional process (barring edits after the fact) and I have more than enough
time to sit and worry about the show. Which I do – all too often, in fact. And
which also led me to write this pair of articles for &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray&quot;&gt;last
article&lt;/a&gt;, I had reflected on
the music of the first Act, but I came to realize after its publication that I
had failed to actually discuss compositional process, which I suppose is far
more interesting than simply taking you, arm-in-arm, on a promenade through what
you will, in just a matter of months, be able to hear for yourself. Therefore,
while I will still move chronologically through the final Act, wouldn’t you
rather hear about how I did the composing, rather than what composing I did?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all honesty, I have not been composing for long enough to have entirely
unified a process. Different pieces require different things from me. Some
pieces can go from just the little scribblings in a notebook straight into my
computer, where I will transform them from the idea into an actual functioning
piece. Others, such as the song-cycle I am currently working on, &lt;em&gt;Crow&lt;/em&gt;, needed
to be mapped out in full-score on paper first, and in ink – it felt particularly
necessary for &lt;em&gt;Crow&lt;/em&gt;, as it lent a sparseness to the writing that was very
helpful (although, I must say that it has been an absolute b*tch to write up on
my computer.) These are the two ends of a sliding scale upon which &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; sat
somewhere in the middle. Or, in fact, off of either end. Some scenes, such as
the theatre scene in Act One went straight from my brain into the computer, as
the nature of the scurrying accompaniment made it a real bore to hand-write,
without the joy of copy-and-paste and editing after the fact. Others, such as
the entire last scene, were almost entirely drafted on paper first and then
written up – although I admit that at least part of the reason for hand-writing
the entire last scene was that my laptop was on the blink and I was 3,000 miles
from home. But, it keeps the romantic notion of the composer scribbling away
with pen and ink alive, so I’ve got to keep up appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we come to the last Act. Although much of this was drafted last, the
prelude to the first scene was, in fact, finished long before most of Act One,
as it gave me, frankly, a nice compositional break from the Prologue. My
librettist Jamie and I had to come up with some way to symbolise several years
of debauchery that the audience missed by swanning out for their interval drinks
in the bar. I assume that the debauched years will be lived through in the minds
of our performers during this interval; it would be nicely ‘method’ of them. But
how to illustrate it in music? I gave the audience a brief, slow moment in which
to mourn Basil and Sybil, both brutally killed at the end of the first Act,
before setting about the musical debauchery. Decadence and wild abandon are
often achieved in music through the use of rowdy dances. Ravel was a master of
this, especially in the finale of &lt;em&gt;La Valse&lt;/em&gt;, or consider Stravinsky’s &lt;em&gt;Rite of
Spring&lt;/em&gt; – the poor girl dances herself to death at the end. But, as those of you
who know me can testify, I am no dancer. So how should I go after the same
effects? It’s actually fairly obvious: the thing that makes a dance a dance is
the rhythm, with which I have very little issue (getting the legs to do what
they’re told on the other hand…). Therefore, I took one of the rhythmic motifs
that described the den of iniquity that was the theatre in Act One, and laid it
underneath a pulsating Yoruba-inspired cross-rhythm from a pair of drums to
create a heady mix of open fifths and driving rhythms that symbolises Dorian’s
embracing of Harry’s lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the segue into the first scene, which itself takes place in an opium
den, takes its influences from Debussy’s use of the quartal harmony to lend an
air of intentionally fake orientalism, with added xylophonic twinkling. This is
undercut by the following chorus ‘number’ – Dorian, his mind full of a romantic
poems, hallucinates that the other patrons of this establishment all begin
singing, in French, about the beauty of Venice, at odds with both the Chinese-y
music of the den, as well as with the general dinginess of London at the end of
the 19th century. And, as a unifying feature of this scene, the music is still
Debussy-inspired. With a French poem, especially by a poet such as Théophile
Gautier, one can’t not look to Debussy, I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Sur une gamme chromatique, &lt;br /&gt;

Le sein de perles ruisselant, &lt;br /&gt;

La Vénus de l’Adriatique, &lt;br /&gt;

Sort de l’eau son corps rose et blanc.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the first scene is dominated by the one appearance of Sybil’s
brother James, who rages like a bull in a china-shop while attempting to pursue
Dorian. His aria was one for which I did the most planning – James had to be
able to arrive on the scene and make enough of an impact to make him feel like a
threat for the remainder of the show, despite not having been seen in the
previous acts. Thus, he demanded a full-on show-stopper of an aria. What makes
music sound angry? It’s much the same as that which makes music sound debauched,
as both violent anger and wild abandon stray from the comfortable emotional
spectrum. Thus, I focused on rhythm again. I wrote out his words, some of the
most violent I have read in Wilde, and began to speak them to myself over and
over again. Individual lines became something of a rapid chant, savagely
thumping away, until I was able to write down specific rhythms I had associated
with them. The aria became very caballetic, with compound rhythms driving
underneath the singer’s howling. And then I worked out the melody. It’s not
greatly complicated, just arpeggiating through the chords underneath. Far more
important is the tessitura: James was, in my head, a Bass, albeit one with a
very solid top range, and this aria is one that exploits it, as I push the
singer to the upper extreme, bellowing away in righteous fury, while the
orchestra churns away tempestuously around him, until he disappears into the
night to hunt his sister’s ‘killer’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second scene, the last scene to be written, and not appearing in the
novella, we return to Lord Henry’s house. Yet the house has a much darker aspect
than when we had seen it in the first Act. For one thing, it is about three in
the morning. But, more importantly, Henry’s wife has made a decision that will
cast a pall on the man for the rest of the show. To give a sense of this
foreboding, I searched back through her brief appearance in Act One for melodies
associated with Lady Victoria, finally picking the languorous downwardly
meandering tune she uses to describe her enjoyment of pianists to manipulate
into a mournful prelude to the scene, descending through the strings in a canon,
before a quote from Tchaikovsky’s &lt;em&gt;Eugene Onegin&lt;/em&gt; foreshadows the fateful letter
that she has written for Harry. Harry’s music, on the other hand, is much
brighter and jolly – he’s drunk, and he sings in a drunkenly twisted patter,
while Victoria drums up the courage to tell him she is leaving. When she finally
pours forth all her upset, we move from twisted patter into a driving
baroque-esque raging, reminiscent of Handel’s more overtly furious moments, most
particularly Dejanira’s aria, &lt;em&gt;Where Shall I Fly&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Hercules,&lt;/em&gt; in which the
overwrought Dejanira is driven mad by guilt, having caused the death of her
god-like husband. But, for me, there was a deeper meaning behind the baroque
façade that I had Victoria put up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie and I discussed this scene at great length, deliberating over how to stop
Victoria from seeming like a shrewish, nagging wife, and more like the bright,
free woman she ought to be. Neither of us understand women (or, in my case,
people in general) as well as we’d like to think, I suspect, but I truly believe
we have drawn here a very human event: Victoria pretends, in her baroque raging,
that her divorce is for all sorts of moral and societal reasons, citing Harry’s
insalubrious behaviour as more than enough reason for her to leave him. Yet, she
ultimately confesses that this is a pretence. She married him because that
behaviour, fuelled as it was by his Byronic intelligence, was highly attractive.
However, he has now ceased being Byronic, and is simply being indulgent and
destructive whilst ignoring her as a wife. All the romance has gone from his
behaviour. It’s a far more interesting character that Jamie has drawn through
this dichotomy than what could have been there: a shrew reprimanding a wastrel
for his wastefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally return to Dorian, still suffering shock from his encounter with James
Vane, on retreat in the country. We find him alone in the grounds of the Duchess
of Monmouth’s house, musing on the events of the previous few days. For this
scene, we took full advantage of the non-linear storytelling we had introduced
with the appearance of Sybil at the end of Act One. There is, in Wilde’s
original, a scintillating scene of witty repartee between Harry and several
other pillars of society after a dinner hosted by the Duchess. However, in
streamlining the show, we feared we would lose this in order to focus more
clearly on Dorian himself. That is, we feared until one of us realised we could
just do another pseudo-flashback, as Dorian recalls the events of the previous
evening. Therefore, we have another moment of lighthearted patter from Harry,
who is joined by the chorus – I felt I was channelling all of my love for &lt;em&gt;Die
Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or even the great Victorian partnership of Gilbert and Sullivan,
trying to create some feeling of effervescence in the midst of the terror that
is consuming Dorian here. This continues into the next big chorus moment, after
the flashback, when these society lords and ladies enter the field in which
Dorian has been sitting in order to go shooting, singing words by Rudyard
Kipling, from his &lt;em&gt;Verses on Games&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Peace upon Earth, Goodwill to men” &lt;br /&gt;

So greet we Christmas Day! &lt;br /&gt;

Oh, Christian, load your gun and then &lt;br /&gt;

Oh, Christian, out and slay.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This joyful entrance is set to a reharmonisation of Sullivan’s tune Noel, known
to most of us as &lt;em&gt;It Came Upon A Midnight Clear.&lt;/em&gt; At the same time, something of
RVW’s &lt;em&gt;Antiphon&lt;/em&gt; or Bruckner’s &lt;em&gt;Te Deum&lt;/em&gt; was never far from my mind, in terms of
the orchestration. It may have become obvious to you that I am always thinking
of other things to relate my music to. It is a problem I run into occasionally –
am I being influenced, which is fine: music does not exist in a vacuum; or am I
simply copying? Quoting things is fine, especially in such a long work as this
(there are many quotes in &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;, most of which I have not pointed out, but
all of which make me irrationally, self-indulgently happy), but copying is not
just plagiaristic but, personally, pointless – even if my original thought, at
the inception of this opera, was that “I wish Britten had written a Dorian
Gray.” Hopefully, my style has become distinct enough from just “a kid copying
Britten”. Hopefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, there is so much to point to in the final scene. Therefore, I will
keep my comments limited to two particular moments. In this last scene, we see
Dorian and Harry finally alone in Dorian’s living room. Dorian is by now
incredibly stressed – Vane hunted him all the way to the Duchess’ estate, and,
in trying to creep up on him, was shot by one of the Lords on their morning
shoot – which Dorian took as a terribly ill omen. Returning to London, Harry has
been keeping tabs on his young protégé, making sure the fear and stress doesn’t
get to him. Therefore, he ups the levels of inane babble. The treatment of his
final moment of inane babble is possibly one of my favourite bits of composition
I’ve done to date. I say my composition, but actually, Harry’s last aria is
founded entirely upon a piece by Alexander Scriabin, who, although I mention him
very infrequently, is one of my favourite composers, if only for his absolutely
insane theories about the end of the world (and attempts to bring said end
about) and his pretence at having synaesthesia, which he tried to use to create
a light-organ or ‘&lt;em&gt;clavier à lumières&lt;/em&gt;’ with which to compose for the
colour-spectrum―which is, I think you’ll agree, fairly bonkers. Nevertheless, I
got it into my head to use this moment at the end of the piece to highlight
musically a big change in Dorian: before we meet Dorian in the Prologue, we hear
him from offstage, playing a snippet from Schumann’s &lt;em&gt;Waldszenen&lt;/em&gt;, a very calm,
nature-themed work for the piano – a piece of innocence, if you will. But now,
at the end of the evening, many years later for the two remaining characters,
Dorian returns to the piano to ignore Harry’s inanities, and plays Scriabin’s
&lt;em&gt;Nocturne&lt;/em&gt; for the left hand. This highlights a change in Dorian in several
ways. Firstly, it is significantly more technically and harmonically challenging
than the Schumann, in part because it is specifically for the left hand, but
also because of Scriabin’s tense, dense harmonic language, which is
significantly more discordant and much less innocent than Schumann’s. Moreover,
Schumann published &lt;em&gt;Waldszenen&lt;/em&gt; in 1849, whereas the &lt;em&gt;Nocturne&lt;/em&gt; was composed in
1894; there is nearly half a century of musical development, pushing the
boundaries of tonality and taste, between the two, indicative of the passage of
time within the show, perhaps, and certainly indicative again of the corruption
of Dorian’s innocence over that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we come to the grand collapse that is the ending. I shan’t spoil the
last few pages by discussing exactly how the show closes, because that would
undoubtedly be a travesty. What I would like to discuss is the allegorical use
of the story of &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar&lt;/em&gt; in the closing moments. In my first plan of the
end, I had refused the idea of an off-stage chorus as too ‘operatic’ for an
intimate close to this show, much too close to the end of &lt;em&gt;Don Giovanni&lt;/em&gt; or the
countless other shows that copied that dramatic close, with the lecher dragged
into hell by an immaterial chorus. However, one chat with Jamie transformed my
conception entirely: I was not overly keen on my first draft’s ending, and he
wrote some new words to close the show – they were splendid. In a tangent to
Dorian’s flashback or his vision of Sybil, Jamie brought up an off-stage chorus,
symbolic perhaps of Dorian’s frantic brain or of heavenly judgement (I’m
inclined to think one particular way, but others may disagree), singing the
&lt;em&gt;“writing on the wall”&lt;/em&gt; that appeared at &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar’s Feast&lt;/em&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;Mene Mene Tekel
Upharsin&lt;/em&gt;” or, as Jamie put it, “&lt;em&gt;Thou art in the balances, and art found
wanting.&lt;/em&gt;” Dorian, in his desperate bid to redeem himself after his years of
immorality, cannot help but hear these words, directly paralleling the
condemnation that is his own portrait hanging upon the wall. Thus, in
composition, I had to avoid not just the links to Don Giovanni but also to
Walton’s own &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar’s Feast&lt;/em&gt;, again a favourite work of mine. Fortunately,
context saved me here, as the chorus slowly makes itself known, crescendoing slowly to become just about audible on-stage, before making a final fortissimo
statement and leaving Dorian to contemplate his fate – with little over a minute
left of the opera.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Olly Bowes</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">It strikes me that whenever I announced to people that I had set about writing an opera, I never actually received that reaction I expected. I was certain I’d be met with derision – “What makes you think YOU can write one, Bowes?” Up to the point that I began working on Dorian, I had only really written choral music and a few songs. My only forays into purely instrumental music consisted of a piano quintet I concocted for my A-level coursework, an arrangement of a school song (Bedford by the River – won a cash prize for it, to be fair), and a frankly ridiculous setting of the Requiem Mass, which I hope will never be performed in its current state. Yet, the reaction, especially when I told everyone of the subject-matter of this opera, Wilde’s seminal novella The Picture of Dorian Gray, was unanimously positive. A few more knowledgeable friends asked whether it had been done before, to which I ask: how many versions of Faust or Romeo and Juliet are there? Answer: frankly too many, not that I wouldn’t consider doing a Faust-related one at some point – indeed, one can see Dorian itself as a Faustian tale. Nevertheless, the reception to the idea was that I ought to push on, and so I did. Thus, I have reached the end of the compositional process (barring edits after the fact) and I have more than enough time to sit and worry about the show. Which I do – all too often, in fact. And which also led me to write this pair of articles for The Pangean. At the end of my last article, I had reflected on the music of the first Act, but I came to realize after its publication that I had failed to actually discuss compositional process, which I suppose is far more interesting than simply taking you, arm-in-arm, on a promenade through what you will, in just a matter of months, be able to hear for yourself. Therefore, while I will still move chronologically through the final Act, wouldn’t you rather hear about how I did the composing, rather than what composing I did? In all honesty, I have not been composing for long enough to have entirely unified a process. Different pieces require different things from me. Some pieces can go from just the little scribblings in a notebook straight into my computer, where I will transform them from the idea into an actual functioning piece. Others, such as the song-cycle I am currently working on, Crow, needed to be mapped out in full-score on paper first, and in ink – it felt particularly necessary for Crow, as it lent a sparseness to the writing that was very helpful (although, I must say that it has been an absolute b*tch to write up on my computer.) These are the two ends of a sliding scale upon which Dorian sat somewhere in the middle. Or, in fact, off of either end. Some scenes, such as the theatre scene in Act One went straight from my brain into the computer, as the nature of the scurrying accompaniment made it a real bore to hand-write, without the joy of copy-and-paste and editing after the fact. Others, such as the entire last scene, were almost entirely drafted on paper first and then written up – although I admit that at least part of the reason for hand-writing the entire last scene was that my laptop was on the blink and I was 3,000 miles from home. But, it keeps the romantic notion of the composer scribbling away with pen and ink alive, so I’ve got to keep up appearances. And so we come to the last Act. Although much of this was drafted last, the prelude to the first scene was, in fact, finished long before most of Act One, as it gave me, frankly, a nice compositional break from the Prologue. My librettist Jamie and I had to come up with some way to symbolise several years of debauchery that the audience missed by swanning out for their interval drinks in the bar. I assume that the debauched years will be lived through in the minds of our performers during this interval; it would be nicely ‘method’ of them. But how to illustrate it in music? I gave the audience a brief, slow moment in which to mourn Basil and Sybil, both brutally killed at the end of the first Act, before setting about the musical debauchery. Decadence and wild abandon are often achieved in music through the use of rowdy dances. Ravel was a master of this, especially in the finale of La Valse, or consider Stravinsky’s Rite of Spring – the poor girl dances herself to death at the end. But, as those of you who know me can testify, I am no dancer. So how should I go after the same effects? It’s actually fairly obvious: the thing that makes a dance a dance is the rhythm, with which I have very little issue (getting the legs to do what they’re told on the other hand…). Therefore, I took one of the rhythmic motifs that described the den of iniquity that was the theatre in Act One, and laid it underneath a pulsating Yoruba-inspired cross-rhythm from a pair of drums to create a heady mix of open fifths and driving rhythms that symbolises Dorian’s embracing of Harry’s lessons. Similarly, the segue into the first scene, which itself takes place in an opium den, takes its influences from Debussy’s use of the quartal harmony to lend an air of intentionally fake orientalism, with added xylophonic twinkling. This is undercut by the following chorus ‘number’ – Dorian, his mind full of a romantic poems, hallucinates that the other patrons of this establishment all begin singing, in French, about the beauty of Venice, at odds with both the Chinese-y music of the den, as well as with the general dinginess of London at the end of the 19th century. And, as a unifying feature of this scene, the music is still Debussy-inspired. With a French poem, especially by a poet such as Théophile Gautier, one can’t not look to Debussy, I feel. “Sur une gamme chromatique, Le sein de perles ruisselant, La Vénus de l’Adriatique, Sort de l’eau son corps rose et blanc.” The remainder of the first scene is dominated by the one appearance of Sybil’s brother James, who rages like a bull in a china-shop while attempting to pursue Dorian. His aria was one for which I did the most planning – James had to be able to arrive on the scene and make enough of an impact to make him feel like a threat for the remainder of the show, despite not having been seen in the previous acts. Thus, he demanded a full-on show-stopper of an aria. What makes music sound angry? It’s much the same as that which makes music sound debauched, as both violent anger and wild abandon stray from the comfortable emotional spectrum. Thus, I focused on rhythm again. I wrote out his words, some of the most violent I have read in Wilde, and began to speak them to myself over and over again. Individual lines became something of a rapid chant, savagely thumping away, until I was able to write down specific rhythms I had associated with them. The aria became very caballetic, with compound rhythms driving underneath the singer’s howling. And then I worked out the melody. It’s not greatly complicated, just arpeggiating through the chords underneath. Far more important is the tessitura: James was, in my head, a Bass, albeit one with a very solid top range, and this aria is one that exploits it, as I push the singer to the upper extreme, bellowing away in righteous fury, while the orchestra churns away tempestuously around him, until he disappears into the night to hunt his sister’s ‘killer’. In the second scene, the last scene to be written, and not appearing in the novella, we return to Lord Henry’s house. Yet the house has a much darker aspect than when we had seen it in the first Act. For one thing, it is about three in the morning. But, more importantly, Henry’s wife has made a decision that will cast a pall on the man for the rest of the show. To give a sense of this foreboding, I searched back through her brief appearance in Act One for melodies associated with Lady Victoria, finally picking the languorous downwardly meandering tune she uses to describe her enjoyment of pianists to manipulate into a mournful prelude to the scene, descending through the strings in a canon, before a quote from Tchaikovsky’s Eugene Onegin foreshadows the fateful letter that she has written for Harry. Harry’s music, on the other hand, is much brighter and jolly – he’s drunk, and he sings in a drunkenly twisted patter, while Victoria drums up the courage to tell him she is leaving. When she finally pours forth all her upset, we move from twisted patter into a driving baroque-esque raging, reminiscent of Handel’s more overtly furious moments, most particularly Dejanira’s aria, Where Shall I Fly from Hercules, in which the overwrought Dejanira is driven mad by guilt, having caused the death of her god-like husband. But, for me, there was a deeper meaning behind the baroque façade that I had Victoria put up. Jamie and I discussed this scene at great length, deliberating over how to stop Victoria from seeming like a shrewish, nagging wife, and more like the bright, free woman she ought to be. Neither of us understand women (or, in my case, people in general) as well as we’d like to think, I suspect, but I truly believe we have drawn here a very human event: Victoria pretends, in her baroque raging, that her divorce is for all sorts of moral and societal reasons, citing Harry’s insalubrious behaviour as more than enough reason for her to leave him. Yet, she ultimately confesses that this is a pretence. She married him because that behaviour, fuelled as it was by his Byronic intelligence, was highly attractive. However, he has now ceased being Byronic, and is simply being indulgent and destructive whilst ignoring her as a wife. All the romance has gone from his behaviour. It’s a far more interesting character that Jamie has drawn through this dichotomy than what could have been there: a shrew reprimanding a wastrel for his wastefulness. We finally return to Dorian, still suffering shock from his encounter with James Vane, on retreat in the country. We find him alone in the grounds of the Duchess of Monmouth’s house, musing on the events of the previous few days. For this scene, we took full advantage of the non-linear storytelling we had introduced with the appearance of Sybil at the end of Act One. There is, in Wilde’s original, a scintillating scene of witty repartee between Harry and several other pillars of society after a dinner hosted by the Duchess. However, in streamlining the show, we feared we would lose this in order to focus more clearly on Dorian himself. That is, we feared until one of us realised we could just do another pseudo-flashback, as Dorian recalls the events of the previous evening. Therefore, we have another moment of lighthearted patter from Harry, who is joined by the chorus – I felt I was channelling all of my love for Die Fledermaus or even the great Victorian partnership of Gilbert and Sullivan, trying to create some feeling of effervescence in the midst of the terror that is consuming Dorian here. This continues into the next big chorus moment, after the flashback, when these society lords and ladies enter the field in which Dorian has been sitting in order to go shooting, singing words by Rudyard Kipling, from his Verses on Games: “Peace upon Earth, Goodwill to men” So greet we Christmas Day! Oh, Christian, load your gun and then Oh, Christian, out and slay.” This joyful entrance is set to a reharmonisation of Sullivan’s tune Noel, known to most of us as It Came Upon A Midnight Clear. At the same time, something of RVW’s Antiphon or Bruckner’s Te Deum was never far from my mind, in terms of the orchestration. It may have become obvious to you that I am always thinking of other things to relate my music to. It is a problem I run into occasionally – am I being influenced, which is fine: music does not exist in a vacuum; or am I simply copying? Quoting things is fine, especially in such a long work as this (there are many quotes in Dorian, most of which I have not pointed out, but all of which make me irrationally, self-indulgently happy), but copying is not just plagiaristic but, personally, pointless – even if my original thought, at the inception of this opera, was that “I wish Britten had written a Dorian Gray.” Hopefully, my style has become distinct enough from just “a kid copying Britten”. Hopefully. Moving on, there is so much to point to in the final scene. Therefore, I will keep my comments limited to two particular moments. In this last scene, we see Dorian and Harry finally alone in Dorian’s living room. Dorian is by now incredibly stressed – Vane hunted him all the way to the Duchess’ estate, and, in trying to creep up on him, was shot by one of the Lords on their morning shoot – which Dorian took as a terribly ill omen. Returning to London, Harry has been keeping tabs on his young protégé, making sure the fear and stress doesn’t get to him. Therefore, he ups the levels of inane babble. The treatment of his final moment of inane babble is possibly one of my favourite bits of composition I’ve done to date. I say my composition, but actually, Harry’s last aria is founded entirely upon a piece by Alexander Scriabin, who, although I mention him very infrequently, is one of my favourite composers, if only for his absolutely insane theories about the end of the world (and attempts to bring said end about) and his pretence at having synaesthesia, which he tried to use to create a light-organ or ‘clavier à lumières’ with which to compose for the colour-spectrum―which is, I think you’ll agree, fairly bonkers. Nevertheless, I got it into my head to use this moment at the end of the piece to highlight musically a big change in Dorian: before we meet Dorian in the Prologue, we hear him from offstage, playing a snippet from Schumann’s Waldszenen, a very calm, nature-themed work for the piano – a piece of innocence, if you will. But now, at the end of the evening, many years later for the two remaining characters, Dorian returns to the piano to ignore Harry’s inanities, and plays Scriabin’s Nocturne for the left hand. This highlights a change in Dorian in several ways. Firstly, it is significantly more technically and harmonically challenging than the Schumann, in part because it is specifically for the left hand, but also because of Scriabin’s tense, dense harmonic language, which is significantly more discordant and much less innocent than Schumann’s. Moreover, Schumann published Waldszenen in 1849, whereas the Nocturne was composed in 1894; there is nearly half a century of musical development, pushing the boundaries of tonality and taste, between the two, indicative of the passage of time within the show, perhaps, and certainly indicative again of the corruption of Dorian’s innocence over that time. Finally, we come to the grand collapse that is the ending. I shan’t spoil the last few pages by discussing exactly how the show closes, because that would undoubtedly be a travesty. What I would like to discuss is the allegorical use of the story of Belshazzar in the closing moments. In my first plan of the end, I had refused the idea of an off-stage chorus as too ‘operatic’ for an intimate close to this show, much too close to the end of Don Giovanni or the countless other shows that copied that dramatic close, with the lecher dragged into hell by an immaterial chorus. However, one chat with Jamie transformed my conception entirely: I was not overly keen on my first draft’s ending, and he wrote some new words to close the show – they were splendid. In a tangent to Dorian’s flashback or his vision of Sybil, Jamie brought up an off-stage chorus, symbolic perhaps of Dorian’s frantic brain or of heavenly judgement (I’m inclined to think one particular way, but others may disagree), singing the “writing on the wall” that appeared at Belshazzar’s Feast: “Mene Mene Tekel Upharsin” or, as Jamie put it, “Thou art in the balances, and art found wanting.” Dorian, in his desperate bid to redeem himself after his years of immorality, cannot help but hear these words, directly paralleling the condemnation that is his own portrait hanging upon the wall. Thus, in composition, I had to avoid not just the links to Don Giovanni but also to Walton’s own Belshazzar’s Feast, again a favourite work of mine. Fortunately, context saved me here, as the chorus slowly makes itself known, crescendoing slowly to become just about audible on-stage, before making a final fortissimo statement and leaving Dorian to contemplate his fate – with little over a minute left of the opera.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Hard Reality of Hardcopies</title><link href="/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hard Reality of Hardcopies" /><published>2019-03-07T03:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-07T03:15:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies">&lt;p&gt;Spring, which has almost become non-existential in Calcutta, is a much revered
and coveted time of the year for any of us living in the tropical zone,
especially when it precedes a season of pig-like sweating. The breezy streets
are a delight to the souls dampened by the winter, and a walk through those
streets with an old friend hits just the right note on the Spring Symphony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An old friend and I have shared a long, uneven but all the more enjoyable
friendship over the years, and our unending love for books has still, with old,
straining strings, held our friendship. Here, I must mention, with much
gratitude, that she was the person to introduce me to the vast, unending, and
marvellous land of books, lending me the first book I ever read by Sidney
Sheldon. When I raised my reservations about the unappealing demeanour of a
book, she just asked me to read for only thirty minutes every day before sleep,
and stated that if after a week I still found it ‘uninteresting’, I could drop
it and return it to her, with her promising to never again insist that I read a
book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprise! Surprise! I finished the book within a week, returned it to her, told
her I finished it and was prized with a look of priceless shock from her. I am
not such an active reader anymore, but what occurred to me then was how
immensely romantic holding the spine of a book is; and of the many sins that our
education system and technology has caused, one is causing a holocaust on the
romance of holding a book. Needless to say, books, since then, became an
inseparable part of my regime and my birthday gifts. But I must confess, after
my first read, I was still sceptical whether this enchantment I felt was
ephemeral or actually enduring. It persisted. Even though initially, I raised
doubts about the ‘unappealing’ demeanour of a book, it was that which drove me
most to the habit of reading books: the mellow chirps of the pages, the letters
marching on the beige field, the weaving and unravelling of tales, and the
hundreds of lives coming to life on those very seemingly lifeless pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, coming back to the spring evening of breezy streets: it was an occasion of
me returning my friend her long-given books, and as we were merrily discussing
things of grave concern to us, something graver ambushed us – what is the future
of hardcopies? I have always been troubled by the growing popularity of ebooks,
but it did not hit harder than when I heard her saying that she has to do her
college’s research work from an ebook. The general argument here would be that
an ebook offers almost everything that a book does, but god forbid the day when
writers romanticise reading an ebook by the window on a rainy day in their
novels or their Instagram posts per se. Leaving aside the romantic values, how
would an ebook ever satiate the bourgeois need of the book-hoarding class? Who
do you think would be impressed by your listless list of books on your device,
instead of the piles of webbed and tattered books with missing pages and
crumpled edges? How can looking up from your well-lit Kindle be the same as a
distracted stare into the distance as Tolstoy drones on in a thick copy of &lt;em&gt;War
and Peace&lt;/em&gt;? What would be more charming, lending book by just a few taps, or
rummaging through the hundreds of dust sprinkled books, whilst being cast under
the perverse magic of nostalgia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a not so recent finding in 2017, it was published that the United States of
America recorded a greater sale of ebooks compared to hardcopies. I became
fairly unstable after reading this and looked with greater awe than ever at my
meagre collection of whatever hardcopies I possess. I, too, am guilty of
possessing ebooks. Of course, I am not all against ebooks (this article is being
published online, after all), it does provide many the opportunity to read
things that otherwise would be inaccessible to them and it certainly is a great
aid when travelling. Although the emergence of ebooks feels like a personal
defeat to me, I concede to the importance of ebooks in times of such great
distress to nature and society. And in fear that I might be misconstrued as a
privileged brat, let me tell you, I buy books using fees earned from part-time
teaching, which most assuredly isn’t much. Yet, still, for me, books and their
essence lies in their old-school charm that keeps us turning actual pages.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrei Tarkovsky once said that artists are there because the world is not
perfect, and such imperfection is reminded to us by those hardcopies that seem
frayed and old and decaying just like our world. The ebook is too perfect a
vessel for works that are born out of imperfection. It swerves us into a path
away from nature, away from reality into a dark realm of complete machine
dominance. In the end, maybe I am simply a hopeless romantic stuck in the past
when the world is aggressively progressing into the future, but I hope my voice
of unreason reaches a few romantic hearts so that we can keep the lineage of
hardcopies from dying a most ignominious and unromantic death.  &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Spring, which has almost become non-existential in Calcutta, is a much revered and coveted time of the year for any of us living in the tropical zone, especially when it precedes a season of pig-like sweating. The breezy streets are a delight to the souls dampened by the winter, and a walk through those streets with an old friend hits just the right note on the Spring Symphony. An old friend and I have shared a long, uneven but all the more enjoyable friendship over the years, and our unending love for books has still, with old, straining strings, held our friendship. Here, I must mention, with much gratitude, that she was the person to introduce me to the vast, unending, and marvellous land of books, lending me the first book I ever read by Sidney Sheldon. When I raised my reservations about the unappealing demeanour of a book, she just asked me to read for only thirty minutes every day before sleep, and stated that if after a week I still found it ‘uninteresting’, I could drop it and return it to her, with her promising to never again insist that I read a book. Surprise! Surprise! I finished the book within a week, returned it to her, told her I finished it and was prized with a look of priceless shock from her. I am not such an active reader anymore, but what occurred to me then was how immensely romantic holding the spine of a book is; and of the many sins that our education system and technology has caused, one is causing a holocaust on the romance of holding a book. Needless to say, books, since then, became an inseparable part of my regime and my birthday gifts. But I must confess, after my first read, I was still sceptical whether this enchantment I felt was ephemeral or actually enduring. It persisted. Even though initially, I raised doubts about the ‘unappealing’ demeanour of a book, it was that which drove me most to the habit of reading books: the mellow chirps of the pages, the letters marching on the beige field, the weaving and unravelling of tales, and the hundreds of lives coming to life on those very seemingly lifeless pages. Now, coming back to the spring evening of breezy streets: it was an occasion of me returning my friend her long-given books, and as we were merrily discussing things of grave concern to us, something graver ambushed us – what is the future of hardcopies? I have always been troubled by the growing popularity of ebooks, but it did not hit harder than when I heard her saying that she has to do her college’s research work from an ebook. The general argument here would be that an ebook offers almost everything that a book does, but god forbid the day when writers romanticise reading an ebook by the window on a rainy day in their novels or their Instagram posts per se. Leaving aside the romantic values, how would an ebook ever satiate the bourgeois need of the book-hoarding class? Who do you think would be impressed by your listless list of books on your device, instead of the piles of webbed and tattered books with missing pages and crumpled edges? How can looking up from your well-lit Kindle be the same as a distracted stare into the distance as Tolstoy drones on in a thick copy of War and Peace? What would be more charming, lending book by just a few taps, or rummaging through the hundreds of dust sprinkled books, whilst being cast under the perverse magic of nostalgia? In a not so recent finding in 2017, it was published that the United States of America recorded a greater sale of ebooks compared to hardcopies. I became fairly unstable after reading this and looked with greater awe than ever at my meagre collection of whatever hardcopies I possess. I, too, am guilty of possessing ebooks. Of course, I am not all against ebooks (this article is being published online, after all), it does provide many the opportunity to read things that otherwise would be inaccessible to them and it certainly is a great aid when travelling. Although the emergence of ebooks feels like a personal defeat to me, I concede to the importance of ebooks in times of such great distress to nature and society. And in fear that I might be misconstrued as a privileged brat, let me tell you, I buy books using fees earned from part-time teaching, which most assuredly isn’t much. Yet, still, for me, books and their essence lies in their old-school charm that keeps us turning actual pages.   Andrei Tarkovsky once said that artists are there because the world is not perfect, and such imperfection is reminded to us by those hardcopies that seem frayed and old and decaying just like our world. The ebook is too perfect a vessel for works that are born out of imperfection. It swerves us into a path away from nature, away from reality into a dark realm of complete machine dominance. In the end, maybe I am simply a hopeless romantic stuck in the past when the world is aggressively progressing into the future, but I hope my voice of unreason reaches a few romantic hearts so that we can keep the lineage of hardcopies from dying a most ignominious and unromantic death.  </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review : The Darjeeling Distinction: Labour and Justice on Fair-Trade Tea Plantation in India</title><link href="/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review : The Darjeeling Distinction: Labour and Justice on Fair-Trade Tea Plantation in India" /><published>2019-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction">&lt;p&gt;One of the most labour-intensive industries in India are the tea plantations. These plantations play a crucial role in profit generation. Thus, providing the much-needed financial support and stability to the Indian economy. However, the dismal condition of the tea plantations and the labour working in these plantations is an established fact, this needs no retelling. Sarah Besky, in this context, adopts an empirical (ethnographic) approach to critically examine this lacuna. The book is written from the perspective of the labourers working in the tea plantations of the Darjeeling Hills (subdivisions of Sadar Darjeeling, Kalimpong and Kurseong). It exposes the readers to the complexities that determine the functioning of such sectors of the economy, providing a much deeper understanding of their deplorable condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the book suggests that the distinction of Darjeeling, as a place, comes from its globally acclaimed Champagne of tea - the Darjeeling tea. A distinction is not only based on market value but also social value. While assessing the social value of this commodity of distinction, the author advocates the need for the recognition of the moral relation between the tea labourers and the tea plant as a filial relation between a mother and child. This line of thought becomes pivotal to grasp the labourer’s view of the plantation. The labourers expect the management to adopt a similar notion of care towards the plantation landscape, which the management fails to. It is this moral expectation that creates instability and insecurity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besky, while subtly exploring the beautiful relationship that the plantation labourers share with their landscape, also throws light upon three major developments in these plantations in the 21st century: Fair-Trade, Geographical Indication (GI) status and the Resurgence of the Gorkhaland movement. However, these developments have only been partially successful in bettering the lives of the labourers. The author takes her readers on a historical journey starting right from the inception of these tea plantations and explores the way it stands today. The ideas and values associated with these plantations, and the social justice issues were a dictum of the colonial masters. Thus, in a way these plantations have always been considered as a materialistic symbol of British imperialism. But the global market structure demanded that these colonial structures be altered in tandem with the neoliberal policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the eyes of the author, the term plantation refers to a space where the labourers are essentially tied to the land, where they work, for their livelihood. The sustenance of these plantations has been firmly rooted in this ‘moral’ economy which ties the planter and the labourers in an unequal economic bond of reciprocity. Besky refers to this setup as ‘a Tripartite Moral Economy among the land, labour and the management’. This points to existence of subjugation, marginalization and exploitation that goes on unchecked in these plantations. Besky, in this regard, also refers to the non-monetary incentives (housing et al) which are supposed to be provided by the management as established under the Plantation Labour act of 1951. In fact, these incentives are the rationale behind the existence of the generational plantation labour. The Tripartite Moral Economy has internalised an intense bond of the land, labour and the plant. This has helped the tea plantations to survive the deteriorating phase since the late 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besky considers the 21st century to be crucial for the revitalization of the degrading Tea plantations. The neoliberal policies of (GI) tag and the Fair-Trade policies of the late 1990s, despite the laxities, have undoubtedly helped in this resurgence. The GI (an international label for the product), linking the product to its place of origin and production, has prevented counterfeit. Moreover, under the GI Act of 1999, the Tea Board of India has ownership over Darjeeling tea. Many such tea plantations of Darjeeling hills are established as Fair-trade farms. This neoliberal policy seeks to provide social justice to the small farmers of the developing countries by fetching a ‘fair’ price for their product by way of directly linking the producers to the global consumers and getting rid of intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the reason why the social and economic conditions of these labourers have not been improved to the desired level needs to be addressed. The root of the problem, according to Besky, is the inability of the neoliberal proponents to understand the complex landscape that Darjeeling tea plantation is. Besky describes these global policies as ‘Third World Agrarian Imaginary’. The romantic and aesthetic portrayal of the hills to make tea palatable to the global consumers naturalizes the exploitative relationship of tea labour, tea plant and its environment. The tea plant brought from China, the immigrant labour force from Nepal and the colonially designed labour relation and production process are naturalised into a heritage craft in 21st century Indian tea plantations of the Darjeeling hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novelty of Besky’s work lies in linking the second phase of the resurgence of the Gorkhaland movement (2007-2011) with the stability of the hills’ tea plantations. Gorkhaland movement, demanding a separate statehood under the Indian union, is essentially an identity assertion movement. For Besky, the Gorkha’s Indian-Nepali identity essentially bears an identity either of tea plantation labourer or that of a military man. Therefore, the tea plantation identity makes the Gorkha identity. Thus, the movement’s territorial sovereignty claims centre upon the material and symbolic attachment to the plantations which covers most of the Darjeeling district. Therefore, both the labourers and the movement share the same moral concern for the land. However, like the GI and Fair-Trade policy, the Gorkhaland movement naturalizes the Gorkha identity to the landscape. They naturalize the unjust production relation between the management and the labourers and mask its exploitative nature. They draw upon the timeless indigenous belonging of the Gorkhas to the land, completely negating the historical reality of the immigration of Nepali workforce in India. Therefore, this primordial claim to the land detaches the movement from tea plantation labour, who very well acknowledge the historical reality of the people and the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the developments of the modern times have been unsuccessful to provide justice to the tea plantation labour. This is because of the failure to understand the notion of social justice and the plantation life from the labourer’s point of view. Besky’s scholarly book stands significant as it attempts to provide a complex understanding of the tea plantations both as an enterprise and landscape as conceived by the tea plantations labourers of the Darjeeling hills.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">One of the most labour-intensive industries in India are the tea plantations. These plantations play a crucial role in profit generation. Thus, providing the much-needed financial support and stability to the Indian economy. However, the dismal condition of the tea plantations and the labour working in these plantations is an established fact, this needs no retelling. Sarah Besky, in this context, adopts an empirical (ethnographic) approach to critically examine this lacuna. The book is written from the perspective of the labourers working in the tea plantations of the Darjeeling Hills (subdivisions of Sadar Darjeeling, Kalimpong and Kurseong). It exposes the readers to the complexities that determine the functioning of such sectors of the economy, providing a much deeper understanding of their deplorable condition.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy?</title><link href="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy?" /><published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths</id><content type="html" xml:base="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths">&lt;p&gt;From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least  400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the criminal context, this leads to some bold and difficult questions that have left even the Behavioral Science Unit of the FBI scratching their heads. How could we, by asking the right set of questions, successfully identify what kind of person is likely to commit a crime? How can we understand his possible motive behind his crime? And, most importantly, can we preempt the criminal’s future course of action? In examining these questions, the term this Behavioral Science Unit coined for the perpetrators of repeated crimes, i.e. ‘serial killer’ is now cult famous. These were the people who would go on a certain form of a spree, committing possibly similar or even dissimilar acts in order to prevent any trace leading up to them. The Unit was exploring how to connect these actions and how to develop a fool-proof method of doing so. Moreover, the Unit wanted to distinguish someone who just kills people and someone who does that because he believes the devil commands him to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were too many questions which could have been asked and none of them could have had any proper answers. But John E Douglas, a member of the Behavioral Science Unit, notes that there was a lot of fruit borne out of their investigations and rightly so. Douglas and his colleagues spent years interviewing criminals across penitentiaries all over the country in a span of more than a decade. Their subjects included Ted Bundy, the killer of several innocent girls, John Wayne Gacy, the infamous “Killer Clown”, who is also thought of to be the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;IT&lt;/em&gt;’s antagonist—a killer clown called Pennywise. The Unit interviewed the “Son of Sam”, David Berkowitz, who claimed that he shot people in cold blood because his cat – a manifestation of Satan himself – asked him to do so. They also interviewed Ed Kemper, a ‘giant’ in all literal senses with an extraordinary IQ of 145, who was convicted of killing his own mother, grandparents and 3 others whilst engaging in necrophilia with their bodies. The insight the Behavioral Science Unit gained from these studies influenced criminal profiling and psychopathic documentation over the years, giving rise to new fields within psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinctive features, John Douglas noted, that were possessed by most of these subjects was an incessant amount of ego. Douglas compared Ted Kaczynski, the Unabomber who was an extraordinarily intelligent criminal, and Dennis Rader, a comparatively less-educated one, and said that both their downfalls were due to their narcissism. Douglas contended that a heightened sense of ego, a lack of remorse and all such associated feelings, innate aggression, a traumatic childhood, and a poor, sexually malignant upbringing were all factors that could contribute to a person’s choices of insanity and crimes. He wrote his critically-acclaimed book, &lt;em&gt;The Mindhunter&lt;/em&gt;, on his studies which till date serves as a manual for some at the Quantico, which is the training ground for FBI agents in the US. This book explores all of his findings and delves deeper into the psyche of how a psychopath could possibly be thinking in accordance with Freudian psycho-sexual stimulation or violence-induced arousal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting fact, however, is that Douglas points out that it is wrong to believe that all psychopaths are just remorseless, guiltless, killing machines. He says that there is more complexity to them than that. Psychopaths have a lopsided view of emotions and morality, it’s not that they don’t ‘feel’, just that they feel very differently from the way most people do. Their ability to take cold, completely unemotional decisions is one that is cherished by most CEOs in today’s world. The only difference between psychopathic killers and corporate executives is the presence of external factors like a tough childhood, poverty, trauma etc., which makes the former a threat to society. As it is posed by another psychopath, albeit fictional in this case, Hannibal Lecter from the series of books by Thomas Harris, the human mind has an unfathomable level of variability and complexity. Who knows for sure what makes the Bundys and the Kempers the people they are? All we know is that they’re not born so, they are made to be so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least 400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People’s Pain</title><link href="/Cry-Me-A-River" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People's Pain" /><published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Cry-Me-A-River</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Cry-Me-A-River">&lt;p&gt;While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have to look much further, one search on Google and I was met with my favourite word ever: Schadenfreude. Oxford Dictionary defines Schadenfreude as pleasure derived by someone from another person’s misfortune. The word is borrowed from German and is a compound of Schaden, “damage, harm”, and Freude, ‘joy’. “Harm-Joy”, that’s the only equivalent in English one can find for this word. In fact, in 1926, a journalist in &lt;em&gt;The Spectator&lt;/em&gt; asserted that “there is no English word for Schadenfreude because there is no such feeling here.” We shall see about that, UK, we shall. One can mistake Sadism for it, but sadism has an implication of infliction, while Schadenfreude is about merely observing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English might be falling behind on finding a word for this feeling, others? Not so much. The Japanese have a saying: “The misfortunes of others taste like honey.” The French speak of ‘joiemaligne’, a diabolical delight in other people’s suffering. The Danish talk of ‘skadefryd’, and the Dutch of ‘leedvermaak’. In Hebrew, enjoying other people’s catastrophes is ‘simcha la‑ed’, in Mandarin, ‘xìng‑zāi‑lè‑huò’, in Serbo-Croat it is ‘zlùradōst’, and in Russian ‘zloradstvo’. More than 2,000 years ago, Romans spoke of ‘malevolentia’. Earlier still, the Greeks described ‘epichairekakia’ (literally epi, over, chairo, rejoice, kakia, disgrace). “To see others suffer does one good,” wrote the philosopher Friedrich Nietzsche, “To make others suffer even more so. This is a hard saying, but a mighty, human, all-too-human principle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about the emotion, how does it even manifest itself? Exactly like joy does: gleam in our eyes, a wide smile, or perhaps a small one, one may even consider it a smirk. In a laboratory in Würzburg in Germany in 2015, thirty-two football fans agreed to have electromyography pads attached to their faces, which would measure their smiles and frowns while watching TV clips of successful and unsuccessful football penalties by the German team, and by their arch-rivals, the Dutch. The psychologists found that when the Dutch missed a goal, the German fans’ smiles appeared more quickly and were broader than when the German team scored a goal themselves. The smiles of Schadenfreude and joy are indistinguishable except in one crucial respect: we smile more at the failures of our enemies than at our own success. We have used humiliation and the failures of other people to make ourselves happy for a long time. We often use said emotion to work in our favour, people use self-deprecating stories in novice situations to evoke ease amongst the rest and present themselves as non-threatening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word was first mentioned in German in the 1740’s, and in English writing in 1853. Richard Chenevix Trench mentioned it in his book on philology &lt;em&gt;On the Study of Words&lt;/em&gt;. For Trench, however, the mere existence of the word Schadenfreude was unholy and fearful, a “mournful record of the strange wickednesses which the genius of man, so fertile in evil, has invented.” Ever since, several have spoken it and have eagerly adopted the word, associating it with a range of pleasures, from hilarity to self-righteous vindication, and from triumph to relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five common themes to be found in the idea of Schadenfreude. The first being that Schadenfreude is usually thought of as an opportunistic pleasure, felt when we stumble across another’s misfortune which we have not caused ourselves. The Hollywood villain gloating when Bond is caught by his dastardly plot is not experiencing Schadenfreude, but sadistic pleasure. By contrast, the sidekick who sniggers as a Hollywood villain is accidentally foiled by his own dastardly plot when he trips and presses the self-destruct button is enjoying Schadenfreude. The second is as a furtive emotion, outbursts of merriment at another’s catastrophes are generally a sign of great villain-ness. Shylock can barely contain himself on learning that his rival Antonio has lost a cargo ship at sea: “I thank God, I thank God. Is’t true, is’t true?” We might be worried not just about looking malicious, but that our Schadenfreude exposes our other flaws too—our pettiness, our envy, our feelings of inadequacy. However, the third feature is that we often feel entitled to it when the other person’s suffering can be construed as a comeuppance—a deserved punishment for being smug or hypocritical or for breaking the law. While it is unlikely that we’d enjoy our moral superiority to their face, gloating is generally permissible at a safe distance. Fourth, we may see it as a form of respite—the failures of others appease our own envy and inadequacy and give us a much-needed feeling of superiority. And just as satire is only funny when it punches up, we are most comfortable sniggering at the failures of those more wealthy, attractive and talented than us. Fifth, often thought of as glee at minor discomforts and gaffes rather than at dire tragedies and deaths, we are willing to see celebrities, or people from the remote past, endure horrors that would dismay us if they were happening now or to our friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, Schadenfreude has been talked about more often than ever. Now I don’t know what it says about our generation, i.e. if we’re more aware than ever or if Schadenfreude is a ‘problem’. A great multitude of researches exist to explain to us how it works, what ages experience it more, is it okay to experience it in the first place, and if not, how not to feel it? As somewhat of a researcher, I can conclude that the latter questions are yet to receive a clear answer. While everybody experiences it every now and then, the literature shows that people with the traits of Machiavellianism, narcissism, or psychopathy, together known as the “dark triad”, feel Schadenfreude more often. Some researchers propose that feeling Schadenfreude requires us to dehumanise the person whose failure we are laughing at. They further suggest dehumanisation might be the fundamental aspect of this emotion, though further research is needed before that can be proven. They sure sound dark, especially because Schadenfreude is such a universal emotion (this had me sweating, I can’t lie). But they justify it by suggesting that dehumanisation occurs more often than most would like to think. The researchers explain that people with low self-esteem are more likely to feel Schadenfreude when they see other people fail. This is because the success of others can be a threat to their sense of self and seeing the mighty fall can be a comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s age, Schadenfreude is all around us, it’s in the way we do politics, how we treat celebrities, and in online fail videos. We felt it when NASA lost a $125 million Mars orbiter because half the team was using imperial measurements, and the other half, metric. We felt it when Trump walked the ramp to his private flight with toilet paper stuck to his right shoe. We feel it when the self-righteous satisfaction of hypocrites is thoroughly exposed, when a celebrity is caught cheating on his/her significant other. You hear it when Bob Dylan sings ‘Like a Rolling Stone’, or when Jessie J flaunts her success in ‘Who’s Laughing Now’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Arthur Schopenhauer called Schadenfreude “an infallible sign of a thoroughly bad heart and profound moral worthlessness,” the very worst trait in human nature. There are often comparisons to how the emotion is on the flip side of empathy. Debates muster up enough evidence for the same but not enough for the debate to be over. Twenty-first-century humanists who regard empathy as a “natural” response under threat in a frenetic, atomistic modern world find Schadenfreude awkward too. It has variously been called the “absence of empathy,” the “opposite of empathy” and “empathy’s shadow,” casting the two as fundamentally incompatible. Some suggest that only a few of us enjoy other people’s pain for its own sake, but more often because we have judged it deserved or useful in some way, evidence not strictly of malice but of our desire to preserve a moral balance. Schadenfreude has been told to be beneficial by some, a quick win which alleviates inferiority or envy; a way of bonding over the failure of a boss or smug senior colleague. And above all, it is a testament to our capacity for emotional flexibility, as opposed to moral rigidity, and our ability to hold apparently contradictory thoughts and feelings in the mind simultaneously. If asked, I’d say Schadenfreude and sympathy are not either/or responses as is sometimes suggested, but can be felt all at once, but, that is for all of us to seek for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schadenfreude has become a part of how we are engaging with everyone online – it creates camaraderie and political momentum. The big question for moral philosophers, now, is whether by enjoying Schadenfreude you are endangering empathy, trust, and a good society. Both ancient and early modern descriptions of comic enjoyment acknowledge proximity to cruelty, but they usually stop short of admitting kinship. The same goes for Schadenfreude, it may well be rested in the bed of cruelty but what connections may we retain? We may well be living in an Age of Schadenfreude, and fear that this emotion is leading us astray. But as with all emotions, condemning it only gets you so far. What we really need is to think afresh about the work this much-maligned emotion does for us, and what it tells us about our relationships with ourselves and each other. The brain will always choose pleasure over fear, always. Understanding why you feel what you feel creates an advantage and opportunity to respond with more thought than impulsivity. As a very smart lady once said, &lt;em&gt;“Don’t reach for the halo too soon. You have plenty of time to enjoy yourself, even a little maliciously sometimes, before you settle down to being a saint.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World</title><link href="/Christendom-Today" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World" /><published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Christendom-Today</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Christendom-Today">&lt;p&gt;There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity certainly is a house divided. The Protestant Reformation played a major role in this (and the proliferation of Protestant denominations continues to prove this) but it also made the Catholic Church wake up from centuries of semi-stagnation, resulting in a major resurgence of traditionalism, as we see in the great world missions of the Counter-Reformation. Indeed, the Jesuits – zealous evangelists and promoters of the Roman faith – probably wouldn’t have existed hadn’t it been for the polarising catalyst that was Martin Luther.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those divisions haven’t yet come to an end, rather Christianity is even more diverse than it was in the 17th century. Thankfully, the different bodies calling themselves Christian are reaching out to each other in a spirit of sincerity and dialogue and are repenting the terrible sectarian bloodshed that so often categorised post-Enlightenment Europe. But the various Christian ‘sects’ are still very different and continue to operate and influence the world in their own unique way. Let us begin with the largest group of all – the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The Spirit of Vatican II”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-20th century, the Catholic Church held a worldwide pastoral council called the Second Council of the Vatican, or – to put it simply – “Vatican II” (hereafter referred to as V2). Unlike previous councils, V2 never chose to define dogma or clarify church teaching – rather it wanted to bring about ecclesiastical reforms to be able to better respond to the new world of the 20th century. But many Catholics agree that V2 was an absolute disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V2 resulted in the sharp splintering of the Church. The liberals and the ‘modernists’ complain that it didn’t go far enough in eroding “medieval superstition”, while the conservatives argue that the ambiguous language in its documents creates a great danger for doctrinal error to be spread. In addition to these two groups, there are more than half-a-million traditionalist Catholics who reject it altogether, calling it a non-infallible “robber’s council” – the best example of this is the Priestly Society of St Pius X, with supporters around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, V2 has resulted in a change of attitude among many believers. Today, Catholics are much more focused on preaching about “social justice” than before. This is best seen in the lives of Mother Teresa and Oscar Romero, both saints of the Catholic Church, as well as in the current Pontiff, Pope Francis. The rise of the so-called “Liberation theology” has created a great impact in Latin America (particularly Brazil), with some calling it the “Marxist version of Catholicism”. The “left-wing Church” in this part of the world has played an instrumental role in protesting against totalitarian right-wing bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberation theologians contend that the root cause of poverty and social injustice is sin (the implication being that social justice cannot return unless people begin to lead saintly lives) and that the poor, the oppressed and the marginalized are the “privileged channels of God’s grace”. The result is that a direct link has been made between theology and social activism. To be a good Christian, one must fight against and oppose oppressive structures of power, say the Liberation theologians. While Liberation theology is certainly not a branch of Communism in any formal sense of the word, the similarity with Marxist rhetoric has, at times, concerned many conservatives, not least among them being Pope Emeritus Benedict XVI. This is very ironic because the Catholic Church of the 20th century was one of the most powerful anti-Communist forces in the world, with many (including New York Times bestselling author and scholar Paul Kengor) crediting Pope St John Paul II as having played an instrumental role in the fall of the Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luther’s Revenge: The Worldwide Resurgence of Evangelicalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelical Christianity is by far the most powerful and dynamic religious force in the world today. Evangelicalism is converting people by the hundreds of thousands. The best example of this is the late Baptist missionary Billy Grace, who preached to more than 3 billion people during his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelicalism is characterised by both simplicity and zeal. There is no Pope or central authority structure to dictate dogma – the Bible is the only rule. There is no long and boring liturgy as we see in Catholic and Orthodox Churches – rather, church services tend to have contemporary music that is very appealing to the youth. They are not led by old and haggard clerics barely able to even speak a word – on the contrary, their leaders tend to be charismatic, scholarly and lively. The sacramental emphasis is replaced by a much freer and fluid form of spirituality, and it is not uncommon to hear the phrase “Christianity is a relationship, not a religion”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the Christian apologists defending the veracity of Christian truth in the academia are also Evangelicals. William Lane Craig, Ravi Zacharias, NT Wright, Richard Bauckham, Michael F Bird, Craig Keener, Craig Blomberg, James DG Dunn, Alvin Plantinga – the list is very impressive indeed. Not only are these devoted (Evangelical) Christians eager to convert souls, they also represent the top brass of scholarship in their respective fields. For instance, William Lane Craig and Alvin Plantinga are one of the most cited scholars in the philosophy of religion, while Wright and Bauckham have both had an association with universities like Oxford and Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, Evangelical Christianity is very American, and very, very Republican. So, while Catholics seem to veer leftward, Evangelicals are solidly in support of capitalism and the notion of a culturally advanced Western Civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holy Mother Russia: The Re-Baptism of Rus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the fall of the USSR, the resurgence of Eastern Orthodoxy was all but inevitable. Today, the Moscow Patriarchate can be called the unofficial state religion of the Russian Federation. Now operating with Vladimir Putin’s open consent and cooperation, they are rebuilding Churches long destroyed and reconstructing schools that had been annihilated by anti-religious sentiment. In fact, some Orthodox followers and clergy are actively advocating the restoration of a Christian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodox Christians are very, well, ‘orthodox’. When the Pope visited Serbia, he was greeted by sloganeers protesting “the Papist heresy”. Even the Patriarch – while having met the Pope at the airport – refused to offer Mass with him. Similarly, Russia is cracking down on “fringe groups” – not least among them being the non-Trinitarian Jehovah’s Witnesses, who have had to face fierce persecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What animates these people? It a vision of the legendary Byzantium, an empire so wonderful that it may be fittingly called the kingdom of God on earth. When the ambassadors of Prince Vladimir of Kiev first saw the Latin Mass, they were not too impressed, but when they witnessed the Byzantine Divine Liturgy, they wrote back exclaiming that this was the most heavenly thing they had ever seen. In the Orthodox narrative, the Church of Rome fell into heresy when it started claiming for itself ecclesiastical supremacy. It was then excommunicated and replaced by the Church of Constantinople, the New Rome. And when Constantinople fell under the sword of Islam, God raised up Moscow – the “Third Rome”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that if there will ever be a Christian state in the 21st century, it will exist mainly in Orthodox-dominated lands (and perhaps in Catholic Poland). For the rest of the Christian world, political Christendom is dead and gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atheists and critics of religion sometimes contend that Christianity is on the decline. But is this true? While it is without a doubt correct to say that Europe and the Western World is secularising at an exponential rate, this does not hold true with regard to the rest of the world. There is an explosion of Christian growth in the global south, particularly in Africa which has proven to be a fertile mission field for the Christian message. As far as academia is concerned, the resurgence of orthodox Christian scholarship in recent years is also a sign of life. However unpopular the faith may be among young white people, it certainly has a long and bright future ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Soham Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.</summary></entry></feed>