<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-17T18:22:08+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey</title><link href="/Russia-and-Turkey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey" /><published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Russia-and-Turkey</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-and-Turkey">&lt;p&gt;The story of relations between Turkey and Russia has mostly been one of conflict rather than of peace. This could, of course, be said of Russia’s relations with most countries. But  this relationship merits a new examination since the pair is going through something of a détente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thawing of relations has been relatively quick. Four years ago, things were frosty. In Syria, Russia had just intervened on the side of the Assad government, whereas Turkey backed various rebel groups in the conflict. In 2015, the downing of a Russian fighter jet by the Turkish Air Force saw Russian President Vladimir Putin impose trade sanctions. The assassination of the Russian Ambassador to Turkey in Istanbul a year later, probably caused by Turkish Muslim objections to Putin’s intervention in Syria, exposed the deep rift between the nations with respect to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, though, the countries have shown greater willingness to cooperate. Putin and Turkey’s President Erdogan met regularly (a veritable &lt;em&gt;Guess Who&lt;/em&gt; of world tyrants), Russia ended its sanctions and visa restrictions against the Turks in May 2017, and Turkey purchased the S-400 missile system from the Russian government later that year. In spite of their differences over Syria, the two countries negotiated a ceasefire in Idlib province in March. Such a rapprochement, if it is to continue, will have important implications for Europe and the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Russia and Turkey are clearly a hybrid of the two continents they straddle, the relationship between them has always impacted Europe more than it has impacted Asia. The Crimean War was caused in large part because the Britain and France feared Russian encroachment on the crumbling Ottoman Empire. In the modern-day, the West looks upon the Russian-Turkish rapprochement with bewilderment because Turkey is a North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) member fraternising with the alliance’s traditional adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pertinent question to ask, then, is why the two countries are getting closer. Certainly, with regards to Syria, the countries have little reason to be cuddling with each other. My argument would be that the thawing of relations tells you little about what Russia and Turkey think of each other, but that it does show what both of them think about America, NATO and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin and Erdogan, like all great chauvinists, don’t just claim to rule nation-states, but entire cultures and civilisations. They are the Tsar and the Sultan reanointed. Among other things, this has meant that both have touted the idea of acting unilaterally on the world stage, and a central plank of this foreign policy has been bashing the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncomfortable truth is that NATO and the US have at times given the two leaders ample opportunities to paint the West as a bad-faith actor, especially in the case of Russia. NATO has been expanding eastwards into Russia’s sphere of influence since the end of the Cold War, not just into the Baltics but even into Georgia. US sanctions against Russia and Turkey, imposed in 2014 and 2019 respectively, hurt the economies of the countries and turned ordinary Russians and Turks even more firmly against the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may say that you don’t care much for either Putin or Erdogan, and that you don’t care if the two countries are turning towards each other. It turns out, however, that isolating these countries means that they look elsewhere in the world for allies. Not phased by Turkey? How about by China? Or Iran? Russia now enjoys a relatively friendly relationship with the Chinese, underpinned by trade. It has also moved closer to Tehran, shown earlier this year when the killing of Qasem Soleimani by the US prompted a deeply negative response from Vladimir Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If diplomacy is about anything, it is about choosing allies to support you against your enemies. The US evidently sees China and Iran as threats to the world’s international system. In the fight to contain these countries, Russia and Turkey could have been key allies, especially considering that the history of Russia and China isn’t friendly. In pushing Putin and Erdogan away, the US and NATO have bolstered their adversaries in the world. If the US wishes to intervene in Iran in the future, it will surely face opposition from Russia and Turkey. NATO is now powerless to influence events in Syria, having ostracised Turkey, the one member of the alliance capable of intervening quickly in the Levant. The US and Russia could have collaborated on containing China, in a manner reminiscent of how Nixon and Kissinger courted Mao to contain the Soviets. Sadly, China and Russia now seem to be beating the Americans at their own game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is that the US and NATO cannot stand alone in the world. They need allies. Russia and Turkey seem to understand what the US has forgotten: sometimes, you need to make deals with imperfect actors in order to heap pressure on genuinely malevolent ones. From the West’s perspective, I would put Putin and Erdogan in the former category, and the Chinese Communist Party and the Ayatollahs in the latter. In spurning Russia and Turkey, the US has made its objectives in the world much more difficult to achieve and has made these potential allies look much more adversarial and dangerous than they actually are.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guest</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The story of relations between Turkey and Russia has mostly been one of conflict rather than of peace. This could, of course, be said of Russia’s relations with most countries. But this relationship merits a new examination since the pair is going through something of a détente.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?</title><link href="/Stocks-Rallying-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?" /><published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Stocks-Rallying-Again</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Stocks-Rallying-Again">&lt;p&gt;Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus outbreak got worse day-by-day and even now cases are rising every day although if you see the popular stock market indices, they are again back to the point where they were before March lows. A rally is bringing the indices back to their pre-March levels. Are the economies getting better? No. Have we recovered from the virus? No. Is GDP growth recovering? NO, instead most of the nations have announced contraction in GDP and are further expecting it to contract till 2021. Why have stocks been moving up again then? Let’s find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries worldwide went under complete lockdown. People tried looking for sources of income during this time and as the stock market never sleeps people turned to stocks to earn something in their free time. Everyone became a trader. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z&quot;&gt;Robinhood&lt;/a&gt; trading app, the most popular stock trading app in the US that charges zero commission, saw a rise in new account openings during the lockdown. The revenues of Robinhood have doubled in a quarter which clearly shows that retail participation has risen and is continuing to rise as we speak. Retailers with no knowledge of stocks, futures and options are trading just for the sake of earning some extra income during their free time and are buying stocks like grocery items, which is one of the main reasons for the rally of stock indices. All market indicators show that the market is overbought and a second wave of crash is due. Big retailers on seeing a big fall in the market start selling stocks to average out their price, and when they enter the market after a fall, it helps the market to regain again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the big question arises: where do we invest our money right now? Seeing a crash due in the market again, and positive signs not being visible in the short term for the economy, it is best to have a diversified portfolio. Over the years, the investment that is the most promising is gold but becoming wealthy through gold is almost unheard of. Seeing the current scenario one must have around 15-20% of his/her investment in gold, paper gold is preferred as you don’t have to keep it safe and don’t have to worry about it. Around 30% of the portfolio should be in mutual funds (Systematic Investment Plan) and 25% should be allocated to equities that too in ‘blue-chip’ stocks because right now profitability of companies is not important, the most important thing is survival and these companies have a huge amount of capital backing. If you want higher returns then you can switch to mid-caps and small-caps too, but your risk increases as well. 10% should be invested in very safe investments like fixed deposits for safe and a minimum guaranteed return. The remaining portfolio can be kept as cash-in-hand, and then one can wait for dips and add stocks of their choice. This portfolio investment has been advised for people who want to take moderate risk with decent returns. If you wish, you can go for high risk by allocating more to equities and if you want less risk then decrease your dependence on equities. Therefore, investing in such turbulent times depends totally on a person’s risk appetite and the depth of his pockets. No one can predict the movement of markets in such unprecedented times. It would be better to have a well-diversified portfolio and not expose yourself too much to a particular type of investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rachit Kumar</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Past and Future of the Future Group</title><link href="/Past-Future-Future-Group" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Past and Future of the Future Group" /><published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Past-Future-Future-Group</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Past-Future-Future-Group">&lt;p&gt;Kishore Biyani, the retail maverick of India, was the man who took the retail industry by storm. He realised the potential of retail, which oligarchs like the Ambanis and Birlas could not appreciate, and therefore came up with household names like Pantaloons, FBB and Big Bazaar. He is often referred to as the Sam Walton (the owner of Walmart) of India. However, recently, Reliance Industries (RIL) bought Biyani’s Future Group for a whopping ₹247 billion. Let’s understand why Mr Biyani had to sell off his dream, but for starters, let’s get acquainted with his story of rags-to-riches before getting onto the bad part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kishore Biyani, the current pin-up kid of the Indian retail industry, has assumed numerous jobs, however in the long run, he settled to turn into an inventive retailer. In contrast with numerous others of his class, Kishore wasn’t brought into the world with the proverbial silver spoon in his mouth and has, without any help, ascended the halls of India’s business elite. Nevertheless, coming from a family of businessmen, business flowed in his blood. He always knew that he would end up becoming a businessman because of his mindset and his ability to understand the customer. In order to understand the real world and to interpret the consumer’s nerve, he was often seen spending time visiting various shops rather than studying. His career actually started when he neared the end of his graduation by joining his family business Bansi Silk Mills, which traded fabrics. Though he used to go to his office, he wasn’t getting the kick which he wanted. He was unable to feel the enthusiasm and opportunity and was feeling quieted by the organisation’s moderate business culture and used to leave within 2 or 3 hours. He was totally against the manner in which the organisation worked and felt that their demeanour and approach towards the business wasn’t right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he was meeting his friends, he noticed them wearing ‘stonewashed’ fabric, he promptly acted on this new information and contacted a few mill owners and sold it to the garment dealers. Kishore had tasted blood and now he wanted more! He frantically began to search for something new, something other than what’s expected. He launched his own brand of fabric for men’s trousers called, WBB – White, Brown, and Blue. In 1987, he started his own garment manufacturing company, Manz Wear Private Ltd, which he sold under the brand name Pantaloons (he chose the name Pantaloons because it gave the feel of an Italian Fashion House and secondly because it was closer to &lt;em&gt;patloon&lt;/em&gt;, an Urdu word for trouser). During the preliminary stages, Biyani went through a difficult phase as banks didn’t want to extend him loans, family and friends were also sceptical about the business. But &lt;em&gt;“it was fun”&lt;/em&gt; for him as he steered through the rough phase like a sailor with unbridled confidence and faith in himself. In 1992, he entered the stock market to fuel the car. After raising money, he went on a spree to open Pantaloons stores pan India along with some marketing campaigns and by the end of 1994 Pantaloons laid eggs worth ₹6 million annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After tasting initial success with Pantaloons, he forayed into the supermarket business with the brand name Big Bazaar, wooing its core customers into large self-service supermarkets and leveraging his own supply and logistics chain to offer across-the-board discounts on maximum retail prices. Big Bazaar was formed on three pillars of Kishore’s ideology- Food, Fashion, and FMCG. You went to get a few vegetables, yet you needed to go through walkways of kurtas and dresses, and were enticed to purchase them. For budget clothing, Biyani launched the FBB design brand. Future Groups Home Center stores were also launched to force people to redesign their homes with the Future Group. The group also forayed into the tech retail sector with the e-zone varying media item stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the offset of the story, everything seems spick and span but on the inside, the finances weren’t going great. He produced a few films between 2002 and 2003 which turned out to be huge flops. While he was growing at break-neck speed and success seemed to be touching his feet, all the acquisitions and the more than frequent opening up of stores, took him into bucket loads of debt. In fact, in 2012 he sold his flagship Pantaloons retail format to Aditya Birla Group for an estimated ₹16 billion at a time when the group had accumulated a consolidated debt of ₹78.50 billion. In 2014, Future Group acquired the south-based Nilgiris chain of markets for ₹3 billion. In 2011, Foodhall, an upmarket food store, found in luxurious shopping malls, was conceptualised by Biyani’s elder daughter, Avni Biyani. In 2016, a couple of years after Walmart and Bharti Airtel  headed out in different directions and failed to set up retail stores as was agreed under their deal, the Future Group took a plunge and purchased the Bharti Airtel’s Easyday chain of supermarkets. A year ago, it trimmed more than 100 Easyday stores, in an endeavour to cut costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is imperative to think that Mr Biyani tried to put his hands in almost everything from insurance to fashion. But the fact is that it was the fashion outlets which outdid every other business he had. Had he stuck to what he was good at, he would not have had to see these days. It’s not that he shouldn’t have diversified but at a steady pace rather than foraying into every other segment at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon, which had announced an Indian war chest of $5.54 billion, and Flipkart, which further got strengthened after its buyout by Walmart, were wooing customers across all retail segments. Biyani tried to stick with his core competence customers: the middle-income Indians who preferred to shop in physical stores. Sadly, the customer had tasted the best of both worlds, and were swiftly moving online. Future Group tried but missed the e-commerce opportunity largely because of the promoter’s scepticism of making money on selling goods online. In 2017, the Future Retail also unveiled its ‘Retail 3.0’ platform that would enable tech to merge with offline retail. But it was too late as players were already established and people were happy buying from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we can say the speed of expansion, acquisition of several retail assets — both regional and national, a chase to build more private labels and in-house manufacturing capabilities have left the company burdened with debt, and caused rating downgrades across the group’s listed entities. As of September 30, 2019, the combined debt of Future Group’s listed companies increased to ₹127 billion from ₹109 billion as of March 31, 2019. His debt woes were further exacerbated by the lockdown, wherein businesses were stalled but he had to keep servicing his debt. Finally, RIL acquired the retail and wholesale business, and the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot can be said about Mr Biyani but he believed in the ‘Indian Dream’; he always wanted to help the Indian dream fly high and wanted to ensure that the &lt;em&gt;‘Sone Ki Chidiya’&lt;/em&gt; (Golden Bird) soared once again. We’re left with one question: will Biyani bounce back? Too early to tell. He is a brand and I’m optimistic enough that he’ll come back sooner and much stronger!!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aditya Khandelwal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Kishore Biyani, the retail maverick of India, was the man who took the retail industry by storm. He realised the potential of retail, which oligarchs like the Ambanis and Birlas could not appreciate, and therefore came up with household names like Pantaloons, FBB and Big Bazaar. He is often referred to as the Sam Walton (the owner of Walmart) of India. However, recently, Reliance Industries (RIL) bought Biyani’s Future Group for a whopping ₹247 billion. Let’s understand why Mr Biyani had to sell off his dream, but for starters, let’s get acquainted with his story of rags-to-riches before getting onto the bad part.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century</title><link href="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century">&lt;p&gt;The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fintech company incorporated in 1999, joined the Frankfurt stock exchange in 2005 and ascended to the ranking of Germany’s 30 leading companies, also known as the DAX Index. It claimed to have subsidiaries across the globe, with payments being processed for more than 200,000 merchants and clients including major European supermarket chains and airlines. It attracted notable investors such as SoftBank. Wirecard was like any other payment processing company that facilitated transactions between consumers and merchants, and earned a certain percentage per transaction. However what set the company apart from its competitors was its rapid expansion in Asia for the reason that it marketed itself as the leader in this system, claiming to have superior technology and highly capitalising on the shift to a cashless society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, the first allegations of accounting irregularities against the firm came to light and in the wake of the attack, the company appointed Ernst &amp;amp; Young (EY), one of the largest accounting enterprises in the world, to conduct a special audit on these claims. EY soon then became the Chief Auditor of the organisation for the next 10 years, signing off the firm’s balance sheet. As allegations against the firm of inflating its operational numbers in Asia continued to surface over the years, a pattern emerged with how the company dealt with these criticisms. They would aggressively deny any wrongdoings and announce that it was an attempt to manipulate their stock prices. However, the stock prices kept rising, undeterred by any negative news coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As claims of malpractice mounted, BaFin- the German financial regulator, during its probe focussed more on the accusers rather than the claims against the enterprise. Various analysts believe that authorities’ protection stemmed as it was a huge moment to see a European home-grown company competing against tech titans of Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the regulator announced an unprecedented 2-month ban on short-selling of the company’s shares due to its stock price plummeting below €100, citing its importance to the economy and serious threats to market confidence. Some also point to Germany’s corporate culture being wary of foreign speculators, since many allegations were brought forward by the British newspaper &lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt;). However, the regulators denied all allegations against the organisation and even filed a criminal investigation against &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; for colluding with short-sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wirecard mainly functioned by buying shell companies that acted as third party payment processors for the organisation. In return, these companies paid them a commission. However, instead of funds flowing into their Munich bank, it was all transferred to escrow accounts. These are special accounts where multiple parties can use them, hence convincing the public that large sums of money existed in them and were used by its subsidiaries. These accounts held more than $2 billion, all of Wirecard’s profit of more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; published an article after being alerted by a whistle-blower, that the organisation was cooking accounting books, hiking up its sales and profit numbers of Asia and Pacific operations. Hence, to put an end to these allegations, the company, in 2019, hired Klynveld Peat Marwick Goerdeler (KPMG) to conduct a special audit. The audit report stated that it could not verify the authenticity of these escrow accounts. As more events unfolded, the company stated that all of the money was stored in the Philippines, and not in these escrow accounts. When EY went to examine these claims from the Philippines bank, the former was notified that the documents submitted by the company were all spurious and money never really entered their financial system, thus the $2.1 billion never existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This announcement led to the arrest of Markus Braun, CEO and CTO of Wirecard since 2002, on June 23, 2020, on suspicion of inflating the value of the company through feigning business with third parties. Two days later, the company filed for insolvency, making it the biggest accounting scandal in post-war German history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disclosure of malpractice of such a magnitude has eroded the trust in the country’s authorities, giving a heavy blow to Germany’s reputation as a financial centre - impacting its businesses and the confidence of market participants. This revelation has increased the scrutiny of not only accounting firms, especially EY, for failing to inspect the legitimacy of such an account, but also on regulators for their inadequacy. Various critics argued that Germany’s regulatory system is neither equipped to handle large scale processing enterprises like Wirecard nor does it have the power to oversee the investigation of potential malpractices. This highlights the need for transparency in financial systems and various regulatory reforms such as incentives for whistleblowers, a better framework for fintech companies, etc. With the expansion of inquiry, more details are yet to come, nonetheless, investigators worldwide are trying to comprehend how the company used the loopholes to present itself as a profitable business for more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushboo Pandey</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trump’s Drastic Changes to Drug Prices: Genuine Concern or an Election Feat?</title><link href="/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trump’s Drastic Changes to Drug Prices: Genuine Concern or an Election Feat?" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices">&lt;p&gt;Franklin D. Roosevelt had once said “&lt;em&gt;In politics, nothing happens by accident. If it happens, you can bet it was planned that way&lt;/em&gt;”. Amidst a global pandemic, lingering economic issues, and fatally injured healthcare systems, a lot of things have changed. Countries have closed down their borders; Russia miraculously came up with a drug, while India continues the battle to flatten the curve. With all the confusion, chaos, and uncertainty, US politics in the hands of President Donald Trump keeps making the headlines, this time around with drastic changes in the prices of drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Trump recently announced that he was signing four executive orders with the aim to lower the prices of prescription drugs paid by fellow Americans. One order aims to allow for legal imports of cheaper prescription drugs, while another requires discounts from drug companies which usually remain captured by middlemen before they are passed on to the patients. “&lt;em&gt;Under this transformative order, Medicare will be required to purchase drugs at the same price as other countries pay&lt;/em&gt;”, Trump said at the signing. However, he noted that he would delay the executive order by a month “&lt;em&gt;hoping that the pharmaceutical companies will come up with something that will substantially reduce drug prices&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many, Trump’s sudden concerns over drug prices seem nothing more than an election stunt and a means to cover up the mishaps, the limitations, and the failures that have come around the corner with his leadership, be it, bad governance, intolerance for diversity of colour and religion, inability to regulate police violence, and the mishandling of the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America very recently stated that the move was nonetheless “&lt;em&gt;a reckless distraction that impedes the ability to respond to the current pandemic – and those we can face in the future&lt;/em&gt;”. Although the rising public debate seems to question this move in the very first place, what one needs to be aware of is that even though President Trump repeatedly calls for lowering the cost of prescribed drugs, the Congress has not yet passed a major drug public reform.  Many people are of the opinion that such dramatic changes are ‘bizarre’ and ‘disturbing’ because such proposals have been in the public realm of debates and negotiations for years because they come with extremely serious implementation challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For writers like Jon Healey in his article in the &lt;em&gt;StarTribune&lt;/em&gt;, the act is not to say that the ideas are bad. “&lt;em&gt;The goals are solid, even if the means to reach them are debatable. The issue is the legal basis Trump is citing for them. I’ll just note here that the distance between these proposals and the usual free-market-centric Republican approach is vast. So vast, in fact, that the Wall Street Journal’s editorial board, which spends much of its time apologising for Trump’s policies, blasted the executive orders Monday in a piece titled “Trump’s Drug Price Panic.” Although I don’t share the Journal board’s abundant faith in free-market forces to cure the manifest ills in the healthcare industry, I do share its scepticism about the effectiveness of price controls.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CEOs of Pfizer, Sanofi, GlaxoSmithKline, and Eli Lilly responded with concerns. Pfizer’s Albert Bourla said that the orders “pose enormous distraction” to the biopharma industry as it fights COVID-19. Pfizer would reconsider US expansions or possibly cut jobs if the measures are implemented. Sanofi CEO Paul Hudson said he’s “&lt;em&gt;not expecting any impact from these conversations this year&lt;/em&gt;” and that the International Pricing Index (IPI) is a “&lt;em&gt;very convenient subject matter&lt;/em&gt;” right before the election. The IPI is a “&lt;em&gt;blunt instrument&lt;/em&gt;” that doesn’t use a “&lt;em&gt;truthful comparison&lt;/em&gt;” of differences between various healthcare systems, including innovation and access. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Eli Lilly And Co which remain highly engaged in the drug manufacturing business claim that such an order has consequences- too negative, and too underestimated for President Trump to fathom. This time most drug manufacturers and investors have been taken by surprise, while Trump and his supporters reiterate the move as an electoral promise that he has managed to keep and a means to hold his electorate together. Nevertheless, Trump’s international pricing order attracted the most pushback from the drug industry, with CEOs saying that the proposal ignores differences between healthcare systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what remains interesting is that President Trump, with this attempt, aims to keep such companies on his side. Soon after he made an official statement regarding a meeting involving him and several other companies which remained a headline for days. However, surprisingly, as he was departing for Wisconsin, Trump said he was meeting with drug companies during the first week of September to discuss drug prices. A spokeswoman for the industry’s trade group PhRMA said the group was “&lt;em&gt;not aware of any meeting&lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Such instances have raised several questions about the policy mentioned and according to Bernstein analyst Ronny Gal, the proposal does offer Trump the “&lt;em&gt;opportunity to declare victory ahead of the elections&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;em&gt;Politico,&lt;/em&gt; PhRMA claims its plan would save consumers $100 billion over the next 10 years. The industry group also reportedly pledged to work with the White House on additional reforms to Medicare. Still, even if these details hold true, much of the plan’s specifics remain unknown, including which drugs would be covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madelaine A Feldman, MD, President of the Coalition of State Rheumatology Organisations and Clinical Assistant Professor of medicine at Tulane University School of Medicine in New Orleans, told &lt;em&gt;Healio Rheumatology&lt;/em&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;If it were to go through rule-making, not only does that take time but there are lawsuits that could happen which could extend the process into next year before we even find out if it could become a finalised, legal rule. Whereas if it were something coming directly from the manufacturers, that could be instituted before the election, which is what the administration is looking for.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aniba Junaid</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Franklin D. Roosevelt had once said “In politics, nothing happens by accident. If it happens, you can bet it was planned that way”. Amidst a global pandemic, lingering economic issues, and fatally injured healthcare systems, a lot of things have changed. Countries have closed down their borders; Russia miraculously came up with a drug, while India continues the battle to flatten the curve. With all the confusion, chaos, and uncertainty, US politics in the hands of President Donald Trump keeps making the headlines, this time around with drastic changes in the prices of drugs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Game of Oil</title><link href="/The-Game-of-Oil" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Game of Oil" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Game-of-Oil</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Game-of-Oil">&lt;p&gt;On April 21, 2020, the world witnessed an unprecedented swing in the financial markets since the COVID-19 pandemic broke out, and nothing else has been more jaw-dropping than the West Texas Intermediary (WTI) trading at negative $37.63 per barrel. That’s right, sellers are paying buyers to take the stuff off their hands! The main reason for this? Probably the coronavirus. This pandemic has ravaged global economies, bringing all industrial and economic activities to a halt. As billions of people were advised to stay put at their homes to slow the spread of disease, the physical demand for oil had dried up. And on top of it, airlines and industries weren’t helping much either. Thereby, we can say that the demand was close to nil. But coronavirus might have decreased the prices by a lot, though not to the extent of it trading at a staggering negative of $37, right? So, what caused it then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst the coronavirus pandemic, came the unexpected oil price war between Russia and Saudi Arabia. Oil prices were already tumbling due to scarce demand. Taking into account the plummeting demand, the Organisation of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) nations decided to cut the production by 1.5 million barrels per day (BPD), on top of the existing cuts. However, to everyone’s surprise, Russia backed out of the deal. This move was a response to the declining share of OPEC+ countries (OPEC + Russia) to the US shale producers; supposing OPEC+ reduced their supply, US shale producers would step in and rope all the customers of OPEC+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia’s response agitated the oil-rich nations and the repercussions involved an announcement to flood the market with oil by producing 12.3 million BPD. Thereby, almost all the nations went on the offensive and ramped up their production. The story seemed interesting until now, to see how the two countries fought with each other through crude oil. But as countries’ production ascended, the storage avenues started to fill at an unprecedented rate and this was when the real problem came to light. The prices dipped below zero not because of scarce demand and excess supply but due to ‘oil futures’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s understand the concept of ‘oil futures’. To put it simply, a future means deciding the price for a commodity now but delivery and payment at a future pre-determined date. Let’s say you have futures of crude oil worth $40 and the delivery is anytime between May 1 and May 31. You need to get rid of the futures contract by April 20, according to the rule by the New York Mercantile Exchange, otherwise, you end up taking the actual delivery of goods. As a futures dealer, you might have thought that as the price of crude oil will rally, it would be profitable to sell them at a discount on current market price and earn a hefty profit later on. But the situation turned upside down and there was no taker for the futures contract. And your heart started thumping heavily, suddenly you see the futures chart falling to zero and as the time started to come closer, the price decreased as there was anxious selling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re in a dilemma about your course of action: either you take actual delivery of crude oil or you sell it at a negative price, in either case, you suffer a heavy setback. Now, we cannot just think of storing the oil in our garden as it is a bare minimum requirement to buy at least 1,000 barrels, or if you’re thinking to store it in the shipping yard, we’d have to shell another set of dollars, but the shipping yard was almost full and on top of it, they were charging exorbitant prices for it. Therefore, it was better to tick off the former option. Being left with the latter, we try to sell it at the least possible price, just to get rid of it. Due to panic selling, the prices dipped below zero which thereby caused a once-in-a-lifetime moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we write, crude oil prices have registered three weekly gains in a row, amid efforts by top producers to cut production due to concerns about recovery from the damage caused by the coronavirus pandemic and resultant lockdowns. Saudia Arabia has a history of waging oil price wars that have created ruckus all around the country. Increasing or decreasing production of oil might seem like a pinch to the Saudis but the repercussion is that various companies are filing for bankruptcy. The oil price war is rather synonymous with an actual war: wherein valiant soldiers die. But in this case, hard-working businessmen are turning bankrupt, just because they have to give in to the conditions dictated by the big and mighty, which causes them to incur losses. This puts up a very important question: is it the time to decentralise this power?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aditya Khandelwal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">On April 21, 2020, the world witnessed an unprecedented swing in the financial markets since the COVID-19 pandemic broke out, and nothing else has been more jaw-dropping than the West Texas Intermediary (WTI) trading at negative $37.63 per barrel. That’s right, sellers are paying buyers to take the stuff off their hands! The main reason for this? Probably the coronavirus. This pandemic has ravaged global economies, bringing all industrial and economic activities to a halt. As billions of people were advised to stay put at their homes to slow the spread of disease, the physical demand for oil had dried up. And on top of it, airlines and industries weren’t helping much either. Thereby, we can say that the demand was close to nil. But coronavirus might have decreased the prices by a lot, though not to the extent of it trading at a staggering negative of $37, right? So, what caused it then?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Countering China</title><link href="/Countering-China" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Countering China" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Countering-China</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Countering-China">&lt;p&gt;After the Second World War, the world was divided into countries that could largely be categorised as liberal democracies or authoritarian communist nations. But interestingly, contemporary China doesn’t fit in either of these categories. It is an authoritarian market economy. Even as it adopted free-market policies and allowed private companies to grow, there were still a large number of state-owned enterprises. The Chinese Communist Party has invested a huge amount of money in these enterprises, which led to the debt-to-GDP ratio of the country to soar high (most of it, though, was domestic debt). Corruption was also rampant across various public institutions and among public servants. All this led to the above-said conclusions about the China model being weak, and it would crack down and pave the way for a democracy in the country. Xi Jinping has, however, changed this; even as he has turned to rule the country Mao-style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principal ingredients of Xinomics are a muscular state and technology. After he took control, Xi took steps to create a more business-friendly environment; giving them space to grow. For instance, his reform measures today mean that it only takes 9 days to set up a new company. Unlike in the past, where public officials ruled in case of civil disputes, courts are now given the responsibility to rule in all such matters (in non-political matters, to be precise). Since Xi assumed power, administrative lawsuits have doubled. The same can be observed in cases related to intellectual property rights and insolvency. Local officials, among whom the disobedience of court rulings was prevalent, were forced by the government to comply. Xi has, therefore, brought order to the markets. He has also made it easier for companies to raise funds through the use of equity shares. All these measures certainly enhance the ease of doing business in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with this, he has tried to make state enterprises increase productivity. For instance, the success of these enterprises was redefined to be measured by their net profitability. On the other hand, party committees are beginning to play a crucial role in the functioning of private enterprises. Party committees are parallel bodies to the Board of Directors that consist of members from the China Communist Party (CCP). It is said that the investment decisions are being taken by these committees. What is important to note is that as long as companies abide by the party guidelines, they receive massive support from the state. But if they don’t, the state makes things painful for them. There is a strange dichotomy that exists at the heart of this plan. Xi Jinping wants public enterprises to comply and adhere to the market principles and private enterprises to adhere to the party principles. Essentially Xi wants to blur the distinction between private and public firms, which is why he is advocating for a mixed model of public and private enterprises; at least in industries that are identified as the key (eg: information technology, semiconductors) for the country’s success in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is technology. One of the key imports into China includes electric machinery and equipment (semiconductors, vehicle parts, etc). To reduce this dependency on the world, Xi Jinping gave a clarion call for ‘Made in China 2025’. This was a new industrial policy that had a strong focus on industries that require technologies to be imported. Under this, a huge sum of money is being spent on research and development to indigenously develop key technologies. State enterprises are being used for this purpose. While this is one part of the technology, the other is soft technology. Chinese information technology firms are increasingly expanding their presence across the world. These firms restrict the information their users’ access, catering to the needs of the party, and sometimes share data with the party. WeChat is a case in point. Though it is mostly used by Chinese people, it is estimated that there are about 100-200 million international users of the app. The app is used to plant fake news and exercise censorship. It has also become a platform where Chinese spies &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/international/business/forget-tiktok-chinas-powerhouse-app-is-wechat-and-its-power-is-sweeping/articleshow/77943656.cms&quot;&gt;communicate&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from WeChat, there are companies like Huawei, Baidu, Xiaomi, whose bosses have close ties with the party and will certainly oblige to all the “requests” from the party. Chinese tech is today ubiquitous and serves as an instrument to promote and protect the interests of the party across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an opinion that is increasingly being voiced from many circles that the world (or at least major economies like the US, Japan, India) could hit China where it hurts the most – trade. They also point out that China has, quite successfully, used trade as leverage to get its way. Cutting meat imports from Australia after the country demanded a probe into China for the COVID-19 pandemic; threatening Canada after a key Huawei official was arrested are cases in point. However, this strategy might not prove effective against China because the country has been diversifying (the composition of GDP, by end-users). China is wise to expect retaliation from other major powers, owing to its cheap and dishonest actions. There has been a gradual &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/256591/share-of-chinas-exports-in-gross-domestic-product/#:~:text=China's%20share%20of%20exports%20in,17.23%20trillion%20yuan%20that%20year.&quot;&gt;reduction&lt;/a&gt; in the share of exports in its GDP. This has been the trend since 2010. As of 2017, the share of exports as a percent of GDP was only 20% (while that of investment was approximately 43%). Also, China could very well use its economic might and soft power to do exactly what the United States has been doing for a long time now – condition its aid on a mandatory adaptation of the ‘China Model’, where it forces the countries to adopt its state-capitalism model. It very well serves China if there is no opposition (both political and public) in the countries it tries to bring under its sphere of influence. This is evident from the fact that more than 50 countries agreed to join the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank, in which China holds a 30% stake. This is only reinforced by research that indicates, “a majority in the developing world and in many middle-sized, non-Western powers prefer the authoritarian model”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing is clear: the assumption of the US foreign policy, under Obama and Bush presidencies, that the integration of China into the international system would change its domestic politics towards democracy and liberalism was wrong. However robust China may be, one must not forget that democracies are always better than authoritarian regimes. Democracies hold their leaders accountable to their people. There has been emerging, from leading think-tanks around the world, the idea of the alliance of Democracy-10 (G7 countries plus India, South Korea, and Australia) to counter China. Though there have been no official talks, US President Donald Trump’s invitation to Indian Prime Minister Modi to join G7 (it still requires the consensus of all the members of G7) is a step in a positive direction. One country may not be able to take on China. But an alliance of a group of powerful democracies certainly can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">After the Second World War, the world was divided into countries that could largely be categorised as liberal democracies or authoritarian communist nations. But interestingly, contemporary China doesn’t fit in either of these categories. It is an authoritarian market economy. Even as it adopted free-market policies and allowed private companies to grow, there were still a large number of state-owned enterprises. The Chinese Communist Party has invested a huge amount of money in these enterprises, which led to the debt-to-GDP ratio of the country to soar high (most of it, though, was domestic debt). Corruption was also rampant across various public institutions and among public servants. All this led to the above-said conclusions about the China model being weak, and it would crack down and pave the way for a democracy in the country. Xi Jinping has, however, changed this; even as he has turned to rule the country Mao-style.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Call for Concord to Capitalise</title><link href="/Concord-to-Capitalise" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Call for Concord to Capitalise" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Concord-to-Capitalise</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Concord-to-Capitalise">&lt;p&gt;Peace is a term of our lexicon that has been a part of the discourse vis-a-vis our mind, between communities, within nations, and across boundaries. It is defined as a concept of societal camaraderie in the absence of hostility and violence. We’re well acquainted with the ironic word ‘peace-keeping forces’ which entail and propagate the use of force and coercion to maintain the virtue of peace, which should come naturally to us otherwise. Correlation between peace and other disciplines like political science, psychology, geography, cognitive science, anthropology and sociology is prevalent. However, little do we know that there is a strong nexus between peace and economics. They are central to each other and act as catalysts in each other’s process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start from the beginning. The austerity of the post-Second World War world isn’t unknown to us. The cost of human lives and their intangible grief is a deep loss that can neither be redressed nor measured using a statistical tool. Talking in monetary terms, the governments of both the axis and allied forces lost about $1 trillion in a war. Here comes the importance of peace and peace enabling structures from a financial point of view as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a discipline that acts as a bridge between development and harmony. ‘Peace Economics’ is a specialised division of economics. It focuses on the creation of the landscape’s political, economic, and cultural institutions and aims at preventing, alleviating, and reconciling the violent conflict between and within societies using relevant policies. Violent conflict can both be latent or active. Peace Economics talks about the benefits of rebuilding and restoring societies based on our presumed knowledge of the cost of violence. Peace Economics has a sweeping view of attaining stable and irrevocable peace. The use of economics here is to comprehend the causes and the repercussions of hostility thereafter in the international system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another definition of the subject has been furnished by Jan Tinbergen, a Nobel prize winner in Economics. As per his scrutiny economic science is made use of to preclude war. It is used as an instrument to settle the disputes among nations and design a world order where warfare is punished. It encircles the concept of negative peace which is a word coined by Johan Galtung that equals the absence of aggression and not the presence of peace. To throw a little more light on this through a simple question, does the absence of poverty in a nation necessarily indicate the presence of opulence? A major exclusion from these definitions is the reference to international relations and no mention of civil war or violence at the individual level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a recognition that Peace Economics forms a part of both positive and normative economics. For those who are alien to these rather heavy-sounding terms, the former simply studies economic phenomena with the ‘what is’ backdrop, that is with facts and figures of the current situation. Whereas the latter as the name suggests covers the ‘what ought to be’ perspective by furnishing corrective recommendations and solutions. Contemporary economists prefer positive economics to evaluate the policies as they are and give relevant suggestions thereafter. On the other hand, normative economics sets the ‘norm’ for peace and then looks for systems that help realise this norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable economic growth can’t be achieved without peace and peace is at risk without sustainable economic growth. The above quip safely interlaces the two subjects. When governments, for instance, make sure to eradicate youth radicalisation by investing in labour-intensive public projects, it leads to full and efficient utilisation of potential, thereby assuring their operation as resources on the Production Possibility Curve (PPC) and not inside it. They become an asset for their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quoting an example of trade here. A free trade zone is created and a treaty signed not just with the goal of bettering bilateral or multilateral relations but also facilitating the promotion of peace. The trail of this link can be traced from the 19th century, a classic case of the English Tory rebels. A modern-day illustration of the same is the South Asian Free Trade Area which ensures non-belligerent relations in the region and promises peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dating back to 1914, during the First World War there was a peace conference held in Paris. A book titled &lt;em&gt;The Economic Consequences of the Peace&lt;/em&gt; by John Maynard Keynes came into being and stated how the terms of the allies regarding truce were financially impossible to achieve for Germany and how those acted as a stimulant in encouraging them to stand steadfast, again. Keynes’ theory also very explicitly mentioned the high rise in employment being conducive to peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crunching some numbers and putting facts into the picture, the global economy is liable to pay more than $14 trillion a year owing to conflict according to the World Economic Forum. The breakdown includes spending on the military, internal security, conflict losses, and crime. India, to be specific, forfeited 9% of its GDP due to friction in 2018. It was on the 136th rank in the Global Peace Index out of 163 nations. Down at the bottom was the war-torn Syria which had to lose a massive 68% of its GDP. Iceland is at the top of this list. Another intriguing certitude is that the countries which are placed higher on the Global Peace Index have observed trends of per capita GDP growing thrice as fast as those which are not as peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important for international organisations like the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund (IMF) to bolster the presence of an infrastructure that ameliorates the livelihoods of those indulged in any sort of clash. Governments need to take affirmative actions with peacebuilding attempts at the core, philanthropists and businesses should contribute and comply with the directives. An instance of the same from the new world order is of Colombia. Over 100 companies in the country marched forward towards peace by coupling their own advertising with the national peace campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crucial reform would be to ensure domestic violence between intimate partners, workplace violence and even self-harm forms the nucleus of present-day research for peace studies. This will go a long way in delivering positive solutions and will make resorting to violence inconceivable. The Institute for Economics and Peace, a think tank is developing a yardstick to analyse peace and quantify its economic value. This will act as a concrete step in laying a firm association between peace and prosperity. Let’s hope for a world in which this theme is self-explanatory and doesn’t have to be this persuasive. Let’s live for the day when world peace isn’t a pipe dream anymore.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Khushi Kaul</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Peace is a term of our lexicon that has been a part of the discourse vis-a-vis our mind, between communities, within nations, and across boundaries. It is defined as a concept of societal camaraderie in the absence of hostility and violence. We’re well acquainted with the ironic word ‘peace-keeping forces’ which entail and propagate the use of force and coercion to maintain the virtue of peace, which should come naturally to us otherwise. Correlation between peace and other disciplines like political science, psychology, geography, cognitive science, anthropology and sociology is prevalent. However, little do we know that there is a strong nexus between peace and economics. They are central to each other and act as catalysts in each other’s process.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution</title><link href="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution" /><published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important debates raging in American society and polity for decades has been the issue of Gun Control. The nature of the resultant deaths has varied from 21,175 suicides, 11,208 homicides, and 505 deaths due to accidental or negligent discharge of a firearm used with “undetermined intent”. These statistics signify a deep-rooted problem plaguing the question of ownership and control of a gun. A genuine question may arise as to whether this problem is individually only affecting the United States. Seems like it is indeed a cause of concern as compared to 22 other high-income nations, the US Gun-related homicide rate is 25 times higher. Among them, the phenomenon of ‘school shootings’, leading to students preparing for active shooter drills, is huddling in silence as if hiding from an imaginary gunman is a regular phenomenon. This has also been responsible for eleven assassination attempts on the US Presidents, with four “successful” encounters. These heinous incidents have a racist undertone also as research indicates that African Americans, who were only 13% of the US population, were 55% of the victims of gun homicide. Surprisingly, the roots of this problem can be located in the US Constitution itself. The arguments gain a fresh lease of life before every Presidential election with the Democrats demanding stricter gun laws and the Republicans pointing to the Second Amendment and self-defence shooting. President Donald Trump had said that he favoured background checks in the days immediately following shootings in El Paso and Dayton, however, Republican majority opinion regards gun control as a dangerous infringement of personal liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Locating the Origin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the root of this controversy, one needs to travel back in time to the ratification of the Second Amendment to the US Constitution ratified on December 15, 1791. It states “&lt;em&gt;A well-regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep or bear arms, shall not be infringed&lt;/em&gt;.” It is the wording of this very statement from which most of the controversy has been generated. While a section of Americans believes that the phrase “the right of the people to keep and bear Arms” aligns with the individualist notion, they think that any legislative body prohibiting firearm possession is unconstitutional. On the other hand, the opposition believes in the “Collective Rights Theory” which states that citizens do not have an individual right to possess guns and that local, state, and federal legislative bodies possess the authority to regulate firearms without the infringement of a constitutional right. Most US Courts had until the early 21st century understood it to guarantee the right of states to maintain militias or the right of individuals to keep or bear arms. However, this was to be strictly in connection with their service in a state militia, an interpretation that was consistent with a wide variety of existing restrictions on individual gun ownership and use. The 1939 judgment in the case of &lt;em&gt;United States v Miller&lt;/em&gt; too spoke in the same tune. The US Supreme Court held that the Second Amendment didn’t prohibit laws requiring the registration of sawed-off guns under the clause “reasonable relationship to the preservation or efficiency of a well-regulated militia”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2008 &lt;em&gt;District of Columbia v Heller&lt;/em&gt; judgment is considered to be a landmark. The plaintiff in &lt;em&gt;Heller&lt;/em&gt; had challenged the constitutionality of the Washington DC handgun ban. In a turn of events that shook global consciousness, the court delivered a 5-4 decision reiterating the history of the Second Amendment establishing an individual right for US Citizens to possess firearms and struck down the DC handgun ban as a violation of that right. It additionally stated that the Court would not disallow regulations prohibiting criminals and the mentally ill from firearm possession. In the 2010 decision of &lt;em&gt;McDonald v The City of Chicago&lt;/em&gt;, the plaintiff challenged the constitutionality of the Chicago Handgun ban which prohibited handgun possessions by almost all private citizens. The Court held that this interpretation of the Amendment was applicable against state and local gun control laws as well as against federal statutes. Thus, one can trace how over the course of time, gun control laws have undergone a complete transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Current American Scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common argument in favour of the unregulated possession of firearms includes the idea that law-abiding citizens can defend themselves against armed criminals. After the mass shootings at a Walmart Store in El Paso, Texas which left 20 individuals dead, there was a marked change in the attitude of young Americans towards Gun Control. A study conducted by Pew Research Centre in 2019, after the Parkland School Shooting in 2018, said that support for gun control was the highest among 18 to 29-year-olds. These findings further suggest that one-third of over 50s admitted to owning a gun. The rate of gun ownership was lower for younger adults at 28%. The Las Vegas attack in 2017 is regarded as one of the deadliest in American history marked by the death of 58 individuals. One of the reasons for these mass shootings can be attributed to the cheap prices at which firearms are available all over the US. The handguns used by Stephen Paddock, the Las Vegas shooter, were priced at $200 while assault rifles come at a price of $1500. Some states have taken measures to lessen this social menace. One such example is California which has banned around 75 types and models of assault weapons. There is a divide among the Republicans and the Democrats on the issue of “concealed carry policy”. This refers to the idea of whether allowing ordinary citizens increased rights to carry concealed weapons. One of the most stringent oppositions to gun control comes from the National Rifle Association (NRA), a very powerful interest group in the US. Interestingly, these groups also possess a substantial budget to influence members of Congress on gun policy. A significant Republican section in the United States is reported to be members of the NRA. This corroborates with NRA’s spending going uphill- from $3 million per year to more than $5 million in 2017. The NRA also supports the election campaigns of political candidates who oppose gun controls. They propagate against all forms of gun control arguing that more guns make the country safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gun Control laws are expected to reduce the societal costs associated with gun violence. More than 100,000 people are shot in the United States every year, and they generate emergency room and hospital charges of nearly $3 billion. Barack Obama in response to the January 2013 Sandy Hook Elementary School Shooting had announced a 4-parter for reducing gun violence: closing background check loopholes, banning assault weapons and large-capacity magazines, increasing access to mental services, and making schools safer. One of the important ideas behind gun safety laws include conducting a thorough background check-up of the person to whom the gun is being sold. Individuals with mental health problems or criminal backgrounds shouldn’t be allowed to possess weapons. Only a dozen of the US’ 50 states require purchase permits (Federal Firearms License - FFL) for handguns. Of those states, only California, Connecticut and Hawaii require permits for the purchase of rifles and shotguns. However, there is a major loophole in the entire body of Gun Control law. According to the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (ATF), anyone can sell a gun without an FFL from their home, online, or even at a flea market or at a gun show as long as he or she is not conducting the sale as part of regular business activity. Thus, selling a firearm from his or her personal collection or gifting a gun is beyond the reach of the law. The baseline being, only those individuals whose “principal motive” is to obtain a profit via the sale will be bound to obtain an FFL. Thus children under the age of 18, a person with felony charges, and mentally ill individuals may also possess guns that were given to them by their parents as gifts. This corroborates with a 2017 survey conducted by Harvard University which estimates that one in every five transactions occurs without a proper background check. It is the need of the hour to amend the constitution with regard to the Second Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the US awaits its Presidential elections in 2020, the Biden-Trump clashes rise again on the issue of Gun Control, dividing opinions and voices for and against a gun-free America. It gains relevance as a burning issue as on September 2, 2020, two seventeen-year-olds were killed in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. This has become a malady with its tentacles spread across America.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Role of Caste in Indian Elections</title><link href="/The-Role-of-Caste" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Role of Caste in Indian Elections" /><published>2020-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Role-of-Caste</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Role-of-Caste">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Jaati na Poocho Sadhu ki, Pooch lijiye gyaan’&lt;/em&gt; is a part of a &lt;em&gt;doha&lt;/em&gt; (couplet) by an Indian mystic, poet and saint Kabir Das, which directly translates to – ‘Do not judge a saint by their caste, but ask for their knowledge’. Yet, this &lt;em&gt;doha&lt;/em&gt; is categorically ignored in Indian elections, when the most-asked question during an election is about the candidate’s surname, caste or religion and not what they have to offer or the values they will bring to the table. From political analysts to voters, everyone has this question on their mind, which is why the candidates standing in an election want to play their caste game right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think of, when you first hear the word &lt;em&gt;caste&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be anything, literally. Albeit in the contemporary world, it mostly has a negative connotation attached to itself; being the sole reason for many ills which impair the world’s largest democracy. And, what is the caste system? It is an old social-stratification system that provides a hierarchy of social roles which hold inherent characteristics and, more importantly, are supposed to remain fixed throughout life. Even though Indian politicians didn’t create the mighty caste system, they surely know how to exploit this fault-line, exacerbating the caste animosities to build vote banks. In India, caste (and religion) is something people are very sensitive about and hence political parties face a difficult choice – they try to woo the oppressed castes in order to collect more votes. And in doing so, they antagonize some of the upper castes. Religiosity and tradition expect them to respect the caste boundaries, which is way too tempting to not exploit. A large number of parties draw up their poll strategies on the basis of the constituency’s caste demographic. Messages in the election speeches are tailored to suit the dominant caste of that constituency, and ideological coherence is sacrificed. And that’s why, while making the decision of choosing a candidate to represent them, voters tend to focus on caste and tend to overlook how adequately he/she would be able to represent them and focus on key issues. If a candidate belongs to caste X, his rival belonging to caste Y fields dummy candidates of caste X to divide the opponent’s votes. Caste determines the nature, organisation and working of most political parties, interest groups, and their functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of caste for gaining political popularity is not a new phenomenon and pre-Independence Indian politics also involved the use of caste, in different ways. The British Imperialists used religion as well as caste for political division of the nation. Unfortunately, even after Independence, India could not stop caste from becoming a factor that would influence politics. Even though the scenario is changing in urban India as voters are becoming more educated and aware about important issues, a large part of India still resides in rural areas, where people are not so much aware; for them, caste still plays a very important role in the election processes. Now, what can be the reason that people prefer to choose someone for their representation who belongs to their own caste rather than choosing someone who guarantees good work, amenities and development? It is because of an emotion – the feeling of belongingness. People tend to have an inherent desire to belong and be an important part of something that is greater than themselves; a relationship that is greater than simple acquaintance. This is a strong and inevitable feeling that exists in human nature. And due to this feeling, people have a strange natural trust that someone from their community, from their social group would be the apt representative for them; that he/she would protect them, provide them with opportunities and take care of them because after all, they belong to one big family, right? Sadly, that is not the case. Most of the times, this trust is taken for granted. Many political parties take advantage of these sentiments and fracture the society in such a manner that they gain from the divisions hence created; not to forget how deeply these divisions can damage the society. Politicians appeal to the sentiments of the voters of their respective caste groups and try to mobilize votes on that basis so as to capture and retain political power. Not only this, politicians have also managed to divert the attention of voters from issues relating to jobs, development, education, etc. by portraying caste as the paramount metric they should keep in mind while voting. The biggest harms of caste being involved in India’s electoral processes? There are many – incompetent leadership, ineffective governance, failed public policies, and most importantly, stagnancy. In a country where more than half of its population lives on less than 2$/day, it becomes highly important to make people realise the importance of proper representation and how it can change their lives. However, people are beginning to understand how such superficial factors are good for nothing and only poison the society at large. As is the case with any social evil, this is something which will require a lot of time and effort to be flushed out from the society, but that doesn’t mean it is impossible at all, right?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">‘Jaati na Poocho Sadhu ki, Pooch lijiye gyaan’ is a part of a doha (couplet) by an Indian mystic, poet and saint Kabir Das, which directly translates to – ‘Do not judge a saint by their caste, but ask for their knowledge’. Yet, this doha is categorically ignored in Indian elections, when the most-asked question during an election is about the candidate’s surname, caste or religion and not what they have to offer or the values they will bring to the table. From political analysts to voters, everyone has this question on their mind, which is why the candidates standing in an election want to play their caste game right.</summary></entry></feed>