<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-09T00:58:07+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data</title><link href="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data" /><published>2019-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use
individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData,
#MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt; have brought
the issue to the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data,
I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for
&lt;em&gt;‘nefarious’&lt;/em&gt; -  I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual -
purposes on a whole, the tool known as &lt;em&gt;data analytics&lt;/em&gt; has brought far more
benefits than harm to society. Fake news and data analytics are separate tools
which though used simultaneously need to be separated. Whilst data analytics is
instrumental in the distribution of fake news, it is not the cause of it.
Gossiping, fear mongering and rumours have been used long before data analytics
even existed. Though I must add that fake news is completely illegal and should
never be condoned. Now that I have set the stage, let’s dive right into this
hidden world of data analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//data-sharing-fb-avi.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt; An example of the ads section on Facebook.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook- A name that triggers a whole array of feelings for everyone. A tool
for communicating, connecting and gathering for like-minded people or long-lost
friends, or  a tool to gather our personal data, process it and sell it to the
highest bidder. Not many of us know that we can ourselves see if Facebook is
being &lt;em&gt;‘mischievous’&lt;/em&gt; with us. Open the ads section under settings to see where
your data has been used. So let’s say Spotify received your data from Facebook,
based on that, they would be able to provide you with music that will most
likely fit your taste. It seems trivial but in this day and age where content is
being created at an exponentially increasing rate, it would be impossible to go
through everything to find something we like. To put perspective on that,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessofapps.com/data/youtube-statistics/#4&quot;&gt;YouTube is estimated to upload 500 hours of content every minute. That
essentially means that a lifetime of content is uploaded every 2
days.&lt;/a&gt; It may be
online shopping, holiday booking, travel planning and they all have one goal… to
make our lives easier so we continue using their platforms. In the case of
Facebook, we have a friend that ensures that we get the best options to choose
from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably, Spotify, YouTube and Facebook are luxury goods, however this is also
prevalent in healthcare. Let’s dive into a hospital to see how data is changing
the way we work. Most hospitals, nowadays, have some sort of digital
ticketing/queuing system which still requires you to wait for hours for your
treatment. With the increased amount of data and software as a Service Business
Intelligence (SaaS BI) tool, hospitals will be able to predict the busiest parts
of the day and staff accordingly to deal with these peaks. This will allow
hospitals to handle more patients more effectively and hence save more lives in
the long run. After getting into your appointment, doctors would be able to have
a full view of your entire medical history, if it was shared. This will, in
turn, allow them to better understand your history which saves time and provides
a more accurate diagnosis. These are two very simple examples which only can
work effectively when medical data is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third and less obvious example; &lt;em&gt;what if the medical data was given to
insurance companies?&lt;/em&gt; The fear is that with access to medical data, we will be
charged additionally for all the problems they will find out about. But I argue
differently. With more data available using analytical tools, insurance
companies would be able to better personalize insurance offers which could
actually lead to cheaper premiums due to the removal of unnecessary coverage. On
top of that, insurance companies will be able to better reward people for taking
steps to maintain good health. Lastly, with access to medical data, insurers
will be able to better identify insurance fraud leading to more applicants being
able to claim insurance when required. There is always a risk that some
companies will implement some unfair practices leading to increased premiums.
However, with the growing digital economy and a multitude of options, these
companies are likely to be outcompeted in the free market, making them
unsustainable in the long run. Whilst this is something that will arise in the
future, let’s look at it in a very contemporary context - data analytics in
Political Campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the data analytics of campaigning, I want to highlight that a
campaign is defined as ‘a planned group of especially political, business, or
military activities that are intended to achieve a particular aim&lt;em&gt;.’ &lt;/em&gt; In the
case of political campaigns, the focus is to convince those who are on the fence
to support your party. Long before the infamy of Cambridge Analytica,
campaigners have been collecting polling data to decide how to target their
campaigns. So why are we suddenly so afraid? Well, mostly it is thanks to our
favourite six-inch toy that we never stop playing with. Due to advancements in
smartphone technology, we are becoming far more connected to the internet, which
in turn leads to more data collected on us. This was the cost of a &lt;em&gt;‘free’&lt;/em&gt;
internet. The free internet came with the major benefit of allowing everyone a
chance of getting access. That meant that companies needed a different way to
make money online, hence the rise of data collection. Initially, starting out as
a harmless tool to provide advertisers with the attention of relevant
potential-customers. It has now evolved into a behemoth that not only provides
the things we may like but also tries to shift our preferences ever so slightly.
Doesn’t seem so bad, but these subtle nudges to shift our opinions slowly push
us further and further down the extreme path we are on - which is proven by the
increased polarization (shown in multiple studies
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~gentzkow/research/PolarizationIn2016.pdf&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apsanet.org/portals/54/Files/Task%20Force%20Reports/Chapter2Mansbridge.pdf&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/2019-03/Polarisation_and_the_news_media_in_Europe.pdf&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/115/37/9216&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;) around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Donald Trump’s 2016 digital campaign director claimed to have run 5.9 million
visual ads on Facebook, in contrast to Hillary Clinton’s 66,000”- The Great
Hack.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This statement made at the end of &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt; further highlights
that this negative opinion on data analytics is also due to some tactics of fear
mongering and misrepresentation of information&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Without any context, it seems
like Donald Trump paid to win an election. Then you consider the fact that in
total Hillary Clinton spent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/politics/2016-election/campaign-finance/?noredirect=on&quot;&gt;1.4 Billion compared to Trump’s 957.6
Million&lt;/a&gt;
on their respective campaigns. The main reason Trump spent more on online ads
was that his fundraising had lagged behind Hillary Clinton, so he had missed out
on the opportunity to spend on TV ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many examples of data being used to make our lives better, but at
the end of the day, data analytics is just a tool. In the hands of the right
person, it could bring unprecedented benefits to society. If we go down the
extreme path of fearing the tool, we have lots to lose. That being said, I still
highly recommend everyone to find out what is happening with your data.
Knowledge is power, and we can learn a lot about ourselves from the way our data
is being used.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Avinash Naidu</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData, #MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary The Great Hack have brought the issue to the limelight. In this article, I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data, I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for ‘nefarious’ -  I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual - purposes on a whole, the tool known as data analytics has brought far more benefits than harm to society. Fake news and data analytics are separate tools which though used simultaneously need to be separated. Whilst data analytics is instrumental in the distribution of fake news, it is not the cause of it. Gossiping, fear mongering and rumours have been used long before data analytics even existed. Though I must add that fake news is completely illegal and should never be condoned. Now that I have set the stage, let’s dive right into this hidden world of data analytics. An example of the ads section on Facebook. Facebook- A name that triggers a whole array of feelings for everyone. A tool for communicating, connecting and gathering for like-minded people or long-lost friends, or  a tool to gather our personal data, process it and sell it to the highest bidder. Not many of us know that we can ourselves see if Facebook is being ‘mischievous’ with us. Open the ads section under settings to see where your data has been used. So let’s say Spotify received your data from Facebook, based on that, they would be able to provide you with music that will most likely fit your taste. It seems trivial but in this day and age where content is being created at an exponentially increasing rate, it would be impossible to go through everything to find something we like. To put perspective on that, YouTube is estimated to upload 500 hours of content every minute. That essentially means that a lifetime of content is uploaded every 2 days. It may be online shopping, holiday booking, travel planning and they all have one goal… to make our lives easier so we continue using their platforms. In the case of Facebook, we have a friend that ensures that we get the best options to choose from. Arguably, Spotify, YouTube and Facebook are luxury goods, however this is also prevalent in healthcare. Let’s dive into a hospital to see how data is changing the way we work. Most hospitals, nowadays, have some sort of digital ticketing/queuing system which still requires you to wait for hours for your treatment. With the increased amount of data and software as a Service Business Intelligence (SaaS BI) tool, hospitals will be able to predict the busiest parts of the day and staff accordingly to deal with these peaks. This will allow hospitals to handle more patients more effectively and hence save more lives in the long run. After getting into your appointment, doctors would be able to have a full view of your entire medical history, if it was shared. This will, in turn, allow them to better understand your history which saves time and provides a more accurate diagnosis. These are two very simple examples which only can work effectively when medical data is shared. A third and less obvious example; what if the medical data was given to insurance companies? The fear is that with access to medical data, we will be charged additionally for all the problems they will find out about. But I argue differently. With more data available using analytical tools, insurance companies would be able to better personalize insurance offers which could actually lead to cheaper premiums due to the removal of unnecessary coverage. On top of that, insurance companies will be able to better reward people for taking steps to maintain good health. Lastly, with access to medical data, insurers will be able to better identify insurance fraud leading to more applicants being able to claim insurance when required. There is always a risk that some companies will implement some unfair practices leading to increased premiums. However, with the growing digital economy and a multitude of options, these companies are likely to be outcompeted in the free market, making them unsustainable in the long run. Whilst this is something that will arise in the future, let’s look at it in a very contemporary context - data analytics in Political Campaigns. Before diving into the data analytics of campaigning, I want to highlight that a campaign is defined as ‘a planned group of especially political, business, or military activities that are intended to achieve a particular aim.’  In the case of political campaigns, the focus is to convince those who are on the fence to support your party. Long before the infamy of Cambridge Analytica, campaigners have been collecting polling data to decide how to target their campaigns. So why are we suddenly so afraid? Well, mostly it is thanks to our favourite six-inch toy that we never stop playing with. Due to advancements in smartphone technology, we are becoming far more connected to the internet, which in turn leads to more data collected on us. This was the cost of a ‘free’ internet. The free internet came with the major benefit of allowing everyone a chance of getting access. That meant that companies needed a different way to make money online, hence the rise of data collection. Initially, starting out as a harmless tool to provide advertisers with the attention of relevant potential-customers. It has now evolved into a behemoth that not only provides the things we may like but also tries to shift our preferences ever so slightly. Doesn’t seem so bad, but these subtle nudges to shift our opinions slowly push us further and further down the extreme path we are on - which is proven by the increased polarization (shown in multiple studies [1] [2] [3] [4]) around the world. “Donald Trump’s 2016 digital campaign director claimed to have run 5.9 million visual ads on Facebook, in contrast to Hillary Clinton’s 66,000”- The Great Hack. This statement made at the end of The Great Hack further highlights that this negative opinion on data analytics is also due to some tactics of fear mongering and misrepresentation of information. Without any context, it seems like Donald Trump paid to win an election. Then you consider the fact that in total Hillary Clinton spent 1.4 Billion compared to Trump’s 957.6 Million on their respective campaigns. The main reason Trump spent more on online ads was that his fundraising had lagged behind Hillary Clinton, so he had missed out on the opportunity to spend on TV ads. There are so many examples of data being used to make our lives better, but at the end of the day, data analytics is just a tool. In the hands of the right person, it could bring unprecedented benefits to society. If we go down the extreme path of fearing the tool, we have lots to lose. That being said, I still highly recommend everyone to find out what is happening with your data. Knowledge is power, and we can learn a lot about ourselves from the way our data is being used.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Can England Make the Most of Their Upcoming Golden Generation?</title><link href="/England-Golden-Generation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Can England Make the Most of Their Upcoming Golden Generation?" /><published>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/England-Golden-Generation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/England-Golden-Generation">&lt;p&gt;English football has been going through a resurgence in recent years. Along with the likes of Liverpool flying the flag high for England, the national team has excelled at various levels as the World Champion U20 and U17 teams were followed by the senior side achieving their best finish at a World Cup for 28 years. It’s evident that the raw talent coming through the ranks is something special, but now the attention turns to whether the England national team can harness this potential and produce a side good enough to compete for major honours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;English Excellence - Young Players on the Rise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Goalkeepers&lt;/em&gt;: Mark Travers, Dean Henderson, Aaron Ramsdale&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Centre-backs&lt;/em&gt;: Joe Gomez, Fikayo Tomori, Axel Tuanzebe, Rob Holding, Ben Godfrey, Marc Guehi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fullbacks&lt;/em&gt;: Aaron Wan-Bissaka, Trent Alexander-Arnold, Ben Chillwell, Ryan Sessegnon, Reece James, Jamal Lewis, Max Aarons, James Justin, Ainsley Maitland-Niles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Central midfielders&lt;/em&gt;: Declan Rice, Morgan Gibbs-White, Ruben Loftus-Cheek, Hamza Choudhury, Joe Willock, Lewis Cook, Oliver Skipp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Attacking midfielders&lt;/em&gt;: Phil Foden, Mason Mount, James Maddison, Angel Gomes, Emile Smith-Rowe, Todd Cantwell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wingers&lt;/em&gt;: Ademola Lookman, Jadon Sancho, Reiss Nelson, Callum Hudson-Odoi, Harvey Barnes, Dwight McNeil, Bukayo Saka&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strikers&lt;/em&gt;: Eddie Nketiah, Tammy Abraham, Rhian Brewster, Mason Greenwood&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As these players’ abilities is not in doubt, continued hunger to be the best and staving off injuries while maximising gametime for their clubs will be the pivotal factors as to whether these young players are able to sustain long-term success. Complacency in major tournaments has been an issue for England teams in the past, and it was also manifest during the recent U21 European Championships in which many of the players mentioned above were involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England can look at how recent World Cup winners were able to make the most of their talented generations and try and replicate certain aspects of their successes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spain (Euro 2008 &amp;amp; 2012, World Cup 2010 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain were widely considered perennial underachievers on the international stage before their triumph in 2008, as they had produced talented players, such as Raúl, Fernando Hierro and Emiliano Butragueño, but hadn’t won a major honour since 1964.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think of the all-conquering Spain team, technically outstanding players such as Xavi, Andrés Iniesta and Cesc Fàbregas immediately spring to mind. It was no coincidence that Spain produced such an array of small, talented midfielders that Santi Cazorla and Juan Mata could barely get any game time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain worked from the ground up to establish a footballing culture centred around players that were comfortable on the ball and could dominate possession. This philosophy set them apart from other contenders at the time as they suffocated possession, making their opponents have to drastically change their gameplans. Such was this team’s influence that there has been a rise in ‘Spanish style’ English midfielders, such as Phil Foden, who differ from the stereotypical English midfielder. The use of St. George’s Park National Football Centre in 2012 would have hopefully got some of the current youngsters to grow together following a similar footballing philosophy which may now be applied to the senior team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Germany (World Cup 2014 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it’s hard to argue that a nation with 4 World Cups and 3 European Championships has one single golden generation, the group that propelled Germany to 2014 glory are certainly a good example of a close-knit group of players that all progressed lineally. Key players like Mats Hummels, Mesut Özil, Sami Khedira, Manuel Neuer, Jerome Boateng, Toni Kroos and Thomas Müller were all born between 1986 and 1989 and had grown up playing together from a young age for both club and country. Five of the aforementioned players started the U21s Euro 2009 final where they got a taste of victory as they trounced England 4-0. All were subsequently involved in the 2010 World Cup where the youngsters impressed on their way to the semi-finals, putting 4 past both England and Argentina in the knockout stages before succumbing to eventual winners Spain. Although they fell short, this was a resounding success for this young team as Thomas Müller won the Golden Boot and Mesut Özil and Sami Khedira both earned moves to Real Madrid off the back of the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did this generation’s experience hold them in good stead for their 2014 World Cup win, but a group of players born from 1983-1985 had preceded the 2010 class by reaching the semis of the 2006 World Cup. Phillip Lahm, Per Mertesacker, Lukas Podolski and Bastian Schweinsteiger were all 22 years or younger during this tournament and played starring roles which they used to build on their international careers. Lahm and Mertesacker retired from international football immediately after their 2014 World Cup triumph in Brazil whilst Podolski and Schweinsteiger did so a few years later with the quartet accumulating 468 caps between them. That level of experience is invaluable when trying to win major honours and England can try and emulate this template to some degree. Jordan Henderson, Raheem Sterling, Dele Alli, John Stones, Harry Kane et al. have already experienced tournament football with England and can use their experiences, both positive and negative, to try and guide the new crop of U23 talent in the same way the Germans did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;France (World Cup 2018 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that England can take away from France’s World Cup 2018 winning side is how manager Didier Deschamps didn’t just cram all the most talented players into the starting XI, but rather opted for the most balanced team. After starting mercurial winger Ousmane Dembele in their World Cup opener against Australia, Deschamps eventually settled on a team with target man Olivier Giroud favoured over a more prolific striker like Alexandre Lacazette whilst box-to-box midfielder Blaise Matuidi started on the left side of midfield over more creative players like Dembele, Thomas Lemar and Nabil Fekir. This new lineup was very well balanced, complimenting star players Paul Pogba, Antoine Griezmann and Kylian Mbappe. Deschamps was famously called “the water carrier” during his playing days by Eric Cantona, and just as he allowed the likes of Zinedine Zidane to flourish, he found the winning formula for France as manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, after France’s disastrous, mutinous 2010 World Cup campaign, the French Football Federation prioritised good squad harmony. Despite mediocre showing in the subsequent 2 tournaments, the FFF were happy with the job Deschamps had done having replaced Laurent Blanc. It should be noted that neither Franck Ribery (retired) nor Karim Benzema played for France after 2015 and despite being arguably the nation’s two most talented players, the team thrived. Benzema was still an elite centre-forward but after his blackmail scandal involving French teammate Mathieu Valbuena, the Real Madrid striker wasn’t considered for selection again. Both him and Ribery had careers riddled with controversy and could have disrupted the excellent squad chemistry and morale in the French dressing room. Due to their triumph in Russia, no one involved in French football will have any regrets over their omissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;England 2000-2010&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England’s previous ‘golden generation’ were notorious underachievers. Despite boasting players who were world-class for their clubs such as Rio Ferdinand, David Beckham and Wayne Rooney to name but a few, they consistently flattered to deceive on the international stage, never advancing past the quarter-finals of a major tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, this side provides an excellent example of how not to maximise the potential of a golden generation and what Southgate and co. should look to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the obvious downfalls was Sven-Göran Eriksson putting out an XI of all the most ‘talented’ players and the team that looks the best on paper, but not the best team in reality. Steven Gerrard and Frank Lampard infamously struggled to play together in midfield in a 4-4-2 formation with neither player’s quality being fully utilised. Lampard and Gerrard often played alongside the likes of Javier Mascherano and Claude Makelele at club level, allowing the English duo more freedom but English holding midfielders such as Gareth Barry, Michael Carrick and Owen Hargreaves started intermittently so there was no real chemistry that could be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shoehorning players out of position was also a theme for this England team with Paul Scholes and Steven Gerrard often deployed wide left, and whilst this worked for France when they moved Matuidi wide, Matuidi is naturally left-footed and France played a 4-2-3-1 / 4-3-3 hybrid, an entirely different system than the 4-4-2 used by Sven-Göran Eriksson. When you add in Frank Lampard, England had 3 elite centre-midfielders yet their midfield never seemed to really stand out as a collective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue was that, due to fierce club rivalries, there was some tension between England’s stars. Rio Ferdinand stated that once he and then close friend Lampard went their separate ways after leaving West Ham, they stopped speaking to each other due to the ferocity of the Chelsea-Manchester United rivalry with both clubs regularly vying for titles. Whilst selecting players who play for rival clubs isn’t a barrier to international success, as Spain showed with a team largely comprised of Barcelona and Real Madrid players, it’s essential that Southgate’s England don’t let petty rivalries bring down their morale and derail their potential success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current England (2018 - present)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably the most significant feature of Southgate’s reign is that he has harmonised the England setup so that club rivalries do not infringe on the national team’s unity. It is no longer the case that England players only spend time with their clubmates on national duty and, as many English pundits, fans and players have noted since the 2018 World Cup, there is a real sense of togetherness now with England’s senior team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although man-for-man the current England XI can’t compete with Eriksson’s 2000’s team, it does seem as though the current England set up will help England’s talented next generation to succeed in a way that Eriksson’s didn’t. The FA should now be aware of what to avoid and what to do when assembling a team for contention. England have the talent, now it’s time to use it correctly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Hogan</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">English football has been going through a resurgence in recent years. Along with the likes of Liverpool flying the flag high for England, the national team has excelled at various levels as the World Champion U20 and U17 teams were followed by the senior side achieving their best finish at a World Cup for 28 years. It’s evident that the raw talent coming through the ranks is something special, but now the attention turns to whether the England national team can harness this potential and produce a side good enough to compete for major honours.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To Walk Again: On Love In Shinkai’s Anime</title><link href="/To-Walk-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Walk Again: On Love In Shinkai’s Anime" /><published>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/To-Walk-Again</id><content type="html" xml:base="/To-Walk-Again">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narukami no sukoshi toyomite&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(A faint clap of thunder)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sashi kumori&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(Clouded skies)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ame mo furanu ka?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(Perhaps rain comes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kimi wo todomemu&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(If so, will you stay here with me?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fate, sometimes, begets in itself the funniest stories as well as the most
melancholic ones. It writes its own comedies and tragedies. The way we interpret
it, however, is what finalises the effect fate has on us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makoto Shinkai is a giant in the world of anime. Deservedly and frequently does
he get compared to Miyazaki; a genius in the field. I do not wish to compare two
of the most amazing anime directors. Their work and their storytelling have
always touched a chord in my heart; a reaction spanning all of the people who
have watched their movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shinkai is, however, criticised due to his lack of versatility in approaching
the themes of stories. &lt;em&gt;Most&lt;/em&gt; of his stories pertain to separation and love,
requited or otherwise. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt;, one of his works, is not any
different. However, the multitude of perspectives that went behind the making of
the story’s concept is what makes the story stand out, in the midst of a
plethora of influential anime films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; sets up an atmosphere which most of us can relate to on a
superficial level. Shinkai has never been afraid to work on stuff he personally
connects to, as a result of which three things come forth in his films as
defining motifs: train, rain, and pain, strangely enough they rhyme too. &lt;em&gt;Garden
of words&lt;/em&gt; interweaves a beautiful love story between the two protagonists and
despite their mutual feelings for each other, they remain visibly disconnected
from each other. They remain separated by the immense difference in age that
exists between the two of them. 27-year-old, Yukari Yukino is a teacher in the
same school as the 15-year-old Takao Akizuki, albeit unbeknownst to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fine rainy day, both of them chance upon each other in a Japanese-themed
garden where they both had sought refuge from the rain. The two share a moment
of connectedness. Yukino leaves him, after sharing with him a cryptic &lt;em&gt;tanka&lt;/em&gt; (a
short Japanese poem). Yukino and Takao end up forming a connection and start
meeting each time it rains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things turn topsy-turvy when Yukino is wrongfully accused of being involved in a
relationship with a student. She is in a soup herself, left with feelings of
remorse and shame even though she had done no wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Takao is an aspiring shoemaker. He comes from a broken family; having been
abandoned by their mother, he and his elder brother lived together. Takao is a
responsible human despite being a mere high school student, he assumes a
part-time job in order to ensure ends meet. Takao, helps Yukino ‘to walk again’
and get back up on her feet. His affection and bond with Yukino make him resolve
to make a shoe for her, a project he works passionately and dedicatedly for.
&lt;em&gt;Love&lt;/em&gt; is the central theme that runs throughout the story. Ultimately, the
rainy season is over and despite wanting each other’s company, they both
hesitate to meet. Takao still continues to work on the shoe. On one particular
day, he realises how Yukino is a teacher in his school and has been wrongfully
accused of something that she did not even commit. Takao decides to take it upon
himself to resolve the issue, and ends up getting involved in a fight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One certain day, Takao and Yukino get a chance to meet up again. In the midst of
a conversation, Takao confesses his love for her. Yukino, unable to process it,
makes him realise that she is still technically his teacher. Takao and Yukino
share their feelings with each other but realise the limitations of their own
understanding and that of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; provides a unique perspective, a tale of love, which is
unrequited and beautiful in its own way. It was Takao’s behaviour towards her,
and his compassion, respect and love that ultimately heals Yukino. This story
makes one introspect upon a form of love that was much popularised by the
philosopher Plato himself: platonic love. There are no boundaries, no
restrictions and no limitations in platonic love and every form of expressing
this love is pure, considerate and understandable. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; gives us a
look into a world of people to whom we can relate, beings we can understand and
sympathise with. It makes us realise the harshness with which society conditions
us and shapes our views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separation is the ultimate form of connection because it provides a &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; for
two people to connect, and know each others’ places in their lives better than
ever. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words,&lt;/em&gt; with its sensitively structured soundtracks and
breathtaking animation, helps us make a connection in separation. A separation
of ages does not restrict a human from pacifying and helping the other person
‘learn to walk again’. Japanese culture is founded on the principles of mutual
respect, understanding and love. The story provides us with that and more. One
must learn to enjoy the things one takes for granted, take the opportunity to
understand someone better and maybe heal them as well as ourselves in the
process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the world is a cold place and all we have is ourselves, and the crucial
key to understanding our own selves is to understand the ones who need our help.
Maybe we are all Takao, living in a broken, mundane, disjunctive world but we
can still always try to find someone like ourselves, broken and battered and
unable to walk, and learn to walk together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to search for the love that we seek all our lives, we can try
to help one another and seek acceptance within ourselves. After all, “We all are
humans, we all have our own quirks, don’t we?”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Udayon Sen</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Narukami no sukoshi toyomite (A faint clap of thunder) sashi kumori (Clouded skies) Ame mo furanu ka? (Perhaps rain comes) Kimi wo todomemu (If so, will you stay here with me?) Fate, sometimes, begets in itself the funniest stories as well as the most melancholic ones. It writes its own comedies and tragedies. The way we interpret it, however, is what finalises the effect fate has on us. Makoto Shinkai is a giant in the world of anime. Deservedly and frequently does he get compared to Miyazaki; a genius in the field. I do not wish to compare two of the most amazing anime directors. Their work and their storytelling have always touched a chord in my heart; a reaction spanning all of the people who have watched their movies. Shinkai is, however, criticised due to his lack of versatility in approaching the themes of stories. Most of his stories pertain to separation and love, requited or otherwise. Garden of Words, one of his works, is not any different. However, the multitude of perspectives that went behind the making of the story’s concept is what makes the story stand out, in the midst of a plethora of influential anime films. Garden of Words sets up an atmosphere which most of us can relate to on a superficial level. Shinkai has never been afraid to work on stuff he personally connects to, as a result of which three things come forth in his films as defining motifs: train, rain, and pain, strangely enough they rhyme too. Garden of words interweaves a beautiful love story between the two protagonists and despite their mutual feelings for each other, they remain visibly disconnected from each other. They remain separated by the immense difference in age that exists between the two of them. 27-year-old, Yukari Yukino is a teacher in the same school as the 15-year-old Takao Akizuki, albeit unbeknownst to him. On a fine rainy day, both of them chance upon each other in a Japanese-themed garden where they both had sought refuge from the rain. The two share a moment of connectedness. Yukino leaves him, after sharing with him a cryptic tanka (a short Japanese poem). Yukino and Takao end up forming a connection and start meeting each time it rains. Things turn topsy-turvy when Yukino is wrongfully accused of being involved in a relationship with a student. She is in a soup herself, left with feelings of remorse and shame even though she had done no wrong. Takao is an aspiring shoemaker. He comes from a broken family; having been abandoned by their mother, he and his elder brother lived together. Takao is a responsible human despite being a mere high school student, he assumes a part-time job in order to ensure ends meet. Takao, helps Yukino ‘to walk again’ and get back up on her feet. His affection and bond with Yukino make him resolve to make a shoe for her, a project he works passionately and dedicatedly for. Love is the central theme that runs throughout the story. Ultimately, the rainy season is over and despite wanting each other’s company, they both hesitate to meet. Takao still continues to work on the shoe. On one particular day, he realises how Yukino is a teacher in his school and has been wrongfully accused of something that she did not even commit. Takao decides to take it upon himself to resolve the issue, and ends up getting involved in a fight.  One certain day, Takao and Yukino get a chance to meet up again. In the midst of a conversation, Takao confesses his love for her. Yukino, unable to process it, makes him realise that she is still technically his teacher. Takao and Yukino share their feelings with each other but realise the limitations of their own understanding and that of society. Garden of Words provides a unique perspective, a tale of love, which is unrequited and beautiful in its own way. It was Takao’s behaviour towards her, and his compassion, respect and love that ultimately heals Yukino. This story makes one introspect upon a form of love that was much popularised by the philosopher Plato himself: platonic love. There are no boundaries, no restrictions and no limitations in platonic love and every form of expressing this love is pure, considerate and understandable. Garden of Words gives us a look into a world of people to whom we can relate, beings we can understand and sympathise with. It makes us realise the harshness with which society conditions us and shapes our views. Separation is the ultimate form of connection because it provides a reason for two people to connect, and know each others’ places in their lives better than ever. Garden of Words, with its sensitively structured soundtracks and breathtaking animation, helps us make a connection in separation. A separation of ages does not restrict a human from pacifying and helping the other person ‘learn to walk again’. Japanese culture is founded on the principles of mutual respect, understanding and love. The story provides us with that and more. One must learn to enjoy the things one takes for granted, take the opportunity to understand someone better and maybe heal them as well as ourselves in the process. Perhaps the world is a cold place and all we have is ourselves, and the crucial key to understanding our own selves is to understand the ones who need our help. Maybe we are all Takao, living in a broken, mundane, disjunctive world but we can still always try to find someone like ourselves, broken and battered and unable to walk, and learn to walk together.  Instead of trying to search for the love that we seek all our lives, we can try to help one another and seek acceptance within ourselves. After all, “We all are humans, we all have our own quirks, don’t we?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On TikTok and The Breathlessness of Social Climbing</title><link href="/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On TikTok and The Breathlessness of Social Climbing" /><published>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing">&lt;p&gt;As he fishhooks his worn-out khaki &lt;em&gt;jhola&lt;/em&gt; (bag) for keys and reaches out arm
deep to the floor of his bag, the peculiar lines on his forehead curl up into a
sweaty keyhole around his sandalwood &lt;em&gt;tilak&lt;/em&gt;, and it is with some pensive
exertion that he says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“You cannot ever erase your caste. But you sure can pretend to change it. &lt;br /&gt;
The rules of the game are pretty simple back in my village. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and nothing else, you count on god. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and a cow, you can negotiate with your god. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and a cow and a land, you are your own god.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ronge Kumar is a 39-year-old sweeper and errand guy at the local temple near my
place of domicile in North Delhi, India. His favourite sport, second only to
knowing all the Hindu gods’ genealogy trivia like the back of his hand, is
stealing time for his almost ritualistic TikTok consumption in the slimy
contours between the work-home binary at the temple.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I conjecture up an introduction for him in foresight of a biographical
essay I might someday write about him, he overruns my train of thought to
continue his monologue: “One of the greatest pieces of unwitting disclosure is
your father’s name. Your father might not leave you an inheritance but he sure
will leave you a family name as a mortgage against your self respect. How do you
go on pretending to be a different person while carrying your family tree on
your shoulder? The city, with all its noise, is easy on you, because it does not
have time to care.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all identity is indeed a performance, Kumar’s predicament really leaves me
questioning the semantics of visibility in a society that, at once, implicates
us as performers of our everyday identities and an audience to others’. This, I
intend not as much in a Shakespearean sense of the word as much in a social
constructionist sort of way. The fact that I ‘pass’ as a normal, functional unit
of the social context, is but a deliberate, concerted project of everyday
performance. However, when the context is all too familiar and the performer too
visible, it is hard to ‘pass’ without being held to public scrutiny for
everything you do. Thus, the respite Kumar attributes to the city is the
relative autonomy that his anonymity here can afford for him. This anonymity is
only augmented when he enters the internet, to a point of discord, if not
dissociation from his identities back home and in the city. This is not to say
that the internet exists in a social vacuum, free from the social categories
that define our identity on the ground, but that it offers every new entrant a
clean slate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumar’s TikTok profile, then, is an embodiment of his existential anxieties of
upward social mobility. His TikTok username, ‘Pandit’ Ronge, above everything,
enables him to attach a Brahminical prefix to his name, something that is
inaccessible to him in the material world. What we see with Kumar then is a more
universal tendency to use the virtual world to live one’s aspirations
vicariously, as in when a 5-year-old chooses a conventionally attractive gaming
avatar to represent themself to the other players, but more so, a social desire
for upward movement. The caste system in India, like most hierarchies, can be
understood as a classic game of Jenga, wherein each participant takes a turn
removing one of the blocks not located on the top three levels and places it on
top of the tower without knocking it down. One’s participation in the game not
only presupposes but also actively ensures that the larger structure of
hierarchical arrangement of the blocks stays in place. An inevitable consequence
of the mobility of the blocks, however, is that the base of the tower
progressively becomes more unstable and struggles to support its heavy top until
it eventually collapses, with the loser being the participant who pulled the
block that caused the demolition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How caste operates in India is much like the rules of Jenga, in that it is as
self preservatory as it is self-destructive. This is to say that while the rules
of the game ensure that the larger structure stays in place, acting out those
very rules also creates possibilities of change within it. But nobody wants to
be singled out as the loser who upset the structure. Thus, mobility desires, if
not demands, anonymity. Most social systems, in that sense, are a long
negotiation of social position within the structure. In negotiating this place,
it puts forth its end of the bargain, creates new fiction to support its claim,
and gradually acquires cultural practices of those above it in the hierarchy.
Social mobility is a cumbersome summit. You spend most days social climbing and
other days catching your breath from all the climbing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the true Foucauldian sense, what Pandit Ronge also does is that in order
of being represented, ends up subjectifying himself by the very presupposition
of representation. That is, while you start with a clean slate, the moment you
start representing yourself, you also start creating fiction about yourself and
the group people associate you with. This idea approximates the terrain this
essay attempts to explore. Most of what I am trying to say then lies in the
contours of being the butt of a joke and cracking a joke, which is to say, “Are
we laughing at a person or with a person?” or “Is the person less subject, more
object of humour?” This is not to say that performance of humorous content
cannot be funny but the fact that something that is being performed diligently
by one, comes across as funny to another, is an act of violence to the
performer’s diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ways in which TikTok is consumed today, like most entertainment, is an idiom
for our social existence. For the uninitiated, TikTok is a video app for
creating and sharing short lip-sync, comedy, and talent videos. Previously known
as ‘Musical.ly’, it was acquired in 2018 by a Chinese tech firm and merged with
its Asian counterpart to become TikTok. Currently, with over 800 million active
users, the app has snowballed into an online entertainment giant with popular
creators on the app burgeoning into social media influencers. How then is TikTok
any different from its American short-form video counterpart ‘Vine’, except that
it is not shutting down anytime soon? Social context, mostly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TikTok in India has seeped into Indian houses through the creaks in our
ceilings, and the damp in our walls, strumming the iron bars on our windows like
an amateur guitarist mindlessly learning to toy around with a guitar. From the
iconisation of the Indian mother butting out her kid from the frame to invite
people for tea with her catchphrase, “Hello friends, chai peelo”, to
impassioned, young, brown men, bawling their eyes out in classic misogynistic
Bollywood bereavement fashion; from drought-hit farmers in Maharashtra
lip-syncing to colloquial protest songs and unionising on the internet to
teenagers turned lip-syncing social media influencers, landing modelling
contracts, TikTok has captured the popular imagination in India, with no
precedent. While humour is one of the top genres of content creation on the app,
a larger source of humour is that which is unintended. While the content of most
of these videos reinstates heteronormative, fat-phobic, often hyper nationalist
semantics of Indian households, the performers are also, more often than not,
rampantly fat-shamed and trolled in casteist, classist ways by the elite, the
ignorant, the woke and the conservative, alike. Meme pages on Facebook and
Instagram create targeted content laughing away what they call the ‘chapri’
TikToker. ‘Chapri’, as defined by the urban dictionary is a colloquial slur in
Bombay for ‘low-tier wannabe fuckboys, characterised by ripped jeans, neon
flip-flops, coloured hair, and speeding motorcycles. Mostly found within the
Bandra-Kurla-Andheri triad.’ Given how hyperlocal it is, the context of the
‘chapri’ performers is that the Kurla- Andheri region houses some of the
largest, most densely populated slums in the country. We cannot thus, begin to
understand the violence of humour without politicising identities. TikTok in
India is as much about entertainment and trolling, characteristic of the rest of
the internet, as it is about reclamation and ownership of entertainment. While
it lets some live a Bollywood dream or a social mobility dream, it is also
implicated in the meanings that construct it. This is to say that the liberation
it affords comes from a presupposed bargain of socio-cultural capital, where a
17-year-old with a ring light and an iPhone will pivot an influencer career, &lt;em&gt;in
spite&lt;/em&gt; of trolls, while a 19-year-old ‘gully boy’ becomes a one-hit wonder
&lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of trolls or is jettisoned in the hyperspace of the internet. But,
again, it is not as binary as my last sentence makes it sound and the
eclecticism is where the heart of internet democratisation lies. As I sit musing
the politics of humour in the temple backyard, the large clock in the temple
ticks six and Ronge calls me out from through the large iron gate of the temple
asking if I want to watch him record his prayers for TikTok. I relent and call
it a day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Yashna Arora</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">As he fishhooks his worn-out khaki jhola (bag) for keys and reaches out arm deep to the floor of his bag, the peculiar lines on his forehead curl up into a sweaty keyhole around his sandalwood tilak, and it is with some pensive exertion that he says, “You cannot ever erase your caste. But you sure can pretend to change it.  The rules of the game are pretty simple back in my village.  If you have a hearth and nothing else, you count on god. If you have a hearth and a cow, you can negotiate with your god. If you have a hearth and a cow and a land, you are your own god.” Ronge Kumar is a 39-year-old sweeper and errand guy at the local temple near my place of domicile in North Delhi, India. His favourite sport, second only to knowing all the Hindu gods’ genealogy trivia like the back of his hand, is stealing time for his almost ritualistic TikTok consumption in the slimy contours between the work-home binary at the temple.   While I conjecture up an introduction for him in foresight of a biographical essay I might someday write about him, he overruns my train of thought to continue his monologue: “One of the greatest pieces of unwitting disclosure is your father’s name. Your father might not leave you an inheritance but he sure will leave you a family name as a mortgage against your self respect. How do you go on pretending to be a different person while carrying your family tree on your shoulder? The city, with all its noise, is easy on you, because it does not have time to care.” If all identity is indeed a performance, Kumar’s predicament really leaves me questioning the semantics of visibility in a society that, at once, implicates us as performers of our everyday identities and an audience to others’. This, I intend not as much in a Shakespearean sense of the word as much in a social constructionist sort of way. The fact that I ‘pass’ as a normal, functional unit of the social context, is but a deliberate, concerted project of everyday performance. However, when the context is all too familiar and the performer too visible, it is hard to ‘pass’ without being held to public scrutiny for everything you do. Thus, the respite Kumar attributes to the city is the relative autonomy that his anonymity here can afford for him. This anonymity is only augmented when he enters the internet, to a point of discord, if not dissociation from his identities back home and in the city. This is not to say that the internet exists in a social vacuum, free from the social categories that define our identity on the ground, but that it offers every new entrant a clean slate. Kumar’s TikTok profile, then, is an embodiment of his existential anxieties of upward social mobility. His TikTok username, ‘Pandit’ Ronge, above everything, enables him to attach a Brahminical prefix to his name, something that is inaccessible to him in the material world. What we see with Kumar then is a more universal tendency to use the virtual world to live one’s aspirations vicariously, as in when a 5-year-old chooses a conventionally attractive gaming avatar to represent themself to the other players, but more so, a social desire for upward movement. The caste system in India, like most hierarchies, can be understood as a classic game of Jenga, wherein each participant takes a turn removing one of the blocks not located on the top three levels and places it on top of the tower without knocking it down. One’s participation in the game not only presupposes but also actively ensures that the larger structure of hierarchical arrangement of the blocks stays in place. An inevitable consequence of the mobility of the blocks, however, is that the base of the tower progressively becomes more unstable and struggles to support its heavy top until it eventually collapses, with the loser being the participant who pulled the block that caused the demolition. How caste operates in India is much like the rules of Jenga, in that it is as self preservatory as it is self-destructive. This is to say that while the rules of the game ensure that the larger structure stays in place, acting out those very rules also creates possibilities of change within it. But nobody wants to be singled out as the loser who upset the structure. Thus, mobility desires, if not demands, anonymity. Most social systems, in that sense, are a long negotiation of social position within the structure. In negotiating this place, it puts forth its end of the bargain, creates new fiction to support its claim, and gradually acquires cultural practices of those above it in the hierarchy. Social mobility is a cumbersome summit. You spend most days social climbing and other days catching your breath from all the climbing.  But, in the true Foucauldian sense, what Pandit Ronge also does is that in order of being represented, ends up subjectifying himself by the very presupposition of representation. That is, while you start with a clean slate, the moment you start representing yourself, you also start creating fiction about yourself and the group people associate you with. This idea approximates the terrain this essay attempts to explore. Most of what I am trying to say then lies in the contours of being the butt of a joke and cracking a joke, which is to say, “Are we laughing at a person or with a person?” or “Is the person less subject, more object of humour?” This is not to say that performance of humorous content cannot be funny but the fact that something that is being performed diligently by one, comes across as funny to another, is an act of violence to the performer’s diligence. The ways in which TikTok is consumed today, like most entertainment, is an idiom for our social existence. For the uninitiated, TikTok is a video app for creating and sharing short lip-sync, comedy, and talent videos. Previously known as ‘Musical.ly’, it was acquired in 2018 by a Chinese tech firm and merged with its Asian counterpart to become TikTok. Currently, with over 800 million active users, the app has snowballed into an online entertainment giant with popular creators on the app burgeoning into social media influencers. How then is TikTok any different from its American short-form video counterpart ‘Vine’, except that it is not shutting down anytime soon? Social context, mostly.  TikTok in India has seeped into Indian houses through the creaks in our ceilings, and the damp in our walls, strumming the iron bars on our windows like an amateur guitarist mindlessly learning to toy around with a guitar. From the iconisation of the Indian mother butting out her kid from the frame to invite people for tea with her catchphrase, “Hello friends, chai peelo”, to impassioned, young, brown men, bawling their eyes out in classic misogynistic Bollywood bereavement fashion; from drought-hit farmers in Maharashtra lip-syncing to colloquial protest songs and unionising on the internet to teenagers turned lip-syncing social media influencers, landing modelling contracts, TikTok has captured the popular imagination in India, with no precedent. While humour is one of the top genres of content creation on the app, a larger source of humour is that which is unintended. While the content of most of these videos reinstates heteronormative, fat-phobic, often hyper nationalist semantics of Indian households, the performers are also, more often than not, rampantly fat-shamed and trolled in casteist, classist ways by the elite, the ignorant, the woke and the conservative, alike. Meme pages on Facebook and Instagram create targeted content laughing away what they call the ‘chapri’ TikToker. ‘Chapri’, as defined by the urban dictionary is a colloquial slur in Bombay for ‘low-tier wannabe fuckboys, characterised by ripped jeans, neon flip-flops, coloured hair, and speeding motorcycles. Mostly found within the Bandra-Kurla-Andheri triad.’ Given how hyperlocal it is, the context of the ‘chapri’ performers is that the Kurla- Andheri region houses some of the largest, most densely populated slums in the country. We cannot thus, begin to understand the violence of humour without politicising identities. TikTok in India is as much about entertainment and trolling, characteristic of the rest of the internet, as it is about reclamation and ownership of entertainment. While it lets some live a Bollywood dream or a social mobility dream, it is also implicated in the meanings that construct it. This is to say that the liberation it affords comes from a presupposed bargain of socio-cultural capital, where a 17-year-old with a ring light and an iPhone will pivot an influencer career, in spite of trolls, while a 19-year-old ‘gully boy’ becomes a one-hit wonder because of trolls or is jettisoned in the hyperspace of the internet. But, again, it is not as binary as my last sentence makes it sound and the eclecticism is where the heart of internet democratisation lies. As I sit musing the politics of humour in the temple backyard, the large clock in the temple ticks six and Ronge calls me out from through the large iron gate of the temple asking if I want to watch him record his prayers for TikTok. I relent and call it a day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Even is Happening?</title><link href="/What-Even-is-Happening" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Even is Happening?" /><published>2019-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/What-Even-is-Happening</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-Even-is-Happening">&lt;p&gt;Hello, I’m Harshita and I’m addicted to this phenomenon called ‘web surfing’,
which sounds like the closest adventure sport I could ever be into and oh well.
Today, I bring to you a new question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, perhaps not as new as I’d like it to be. About an hour or two ago, on a
podcast I heard a 15-year-old say and I quote, “… in previous eras, they had
wars with guns and gas, and in ours, we war with our own self.” To give you more
context, she reinstated what we all can see but perhaps are unable to
acknowledge- we’re all in an epidemic, one which is not as visible as we think
it to be- mental health issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more than 10 million posts on Instagram with the hashtag ‘mental_health’
and about ten times more of blogs on Tumblr, it’d be wrong of me to say we don’t
talk about it enough. I know that we do, hell, we more than just talk about it.
And yet, it’s an epidemic with no foreseeable solution. I can sit here and go on
and on about how maybe we are more aware of these mental issues now because
people are more knowledgeable of the same, maybe because the stigma is being
fought against, perhaps, we just are more courageous than the ones who came
before us. What I can’t give up on are the words by my 15-year-old muse, is she
right in believing that just as every era is to go through one huge
debilitation, we’ve been destined to fall into the chasm of mental health chaos?
Would it be wrong of me to assume that there are more factors than just
awareness that are making us all a little more troubled than ever?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t give you a solid number for the amount of times I’ve said ‘Same!’
when someone around me said, ‘I can’t live this life no more’ or, ‘Ugh! I’m so
depressed’ or something akin to it. I know I’ve uttered the words ‘I want to
die’ on multiple accounts, once because I couldn’t bear the heat. Albeit the
fact that I know it’s asinine to have claimed the same, it is difficult not to
do the same. I could tell you it’s because it’s ingrained, because I’ve been
conditioned and been rewarded quite positively or, perhaps, because everyone
around me does it and if Bandura had anything to say for it, he’d agree. All
around us- in the spaces we most frequent, there’s a strong prevalence of (and I
say this off of my personal disposition) romanticisation of mental illness.
Somehow our move to ‘delete the stigma’ has drastically changed towards a trend
to ‘romanticise the stigma’. While it’s not something that one should be ashamed
of, it also isn’t something one should aspire for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that on Tumblr, #Thinspo is always trending, why is it that not
sleeping and being perpetually tired has become a way of popular culture? How
did self-inflicted scars come to be called art? When did the ‘Sad Girls Club’
become the new ideal, often propagated by the VSCO girls or the new e-girls?
What about #proana? I remember reading &lt;em&gt;Looking for Alaska&lt;/em&gt; and being astounded
by how easily the teenage girl said, and oh, ‘with delight of a kid on a
Christmas morning’- “Y’all smoke to enjoy it. I smoke to die.” If you’ve ever
gone down the Instagram explore page, you’ve definitely been acquainted with Sir
R.M. Drake and his well-fonted, honey-coloured quotes such as that of, ‘We
desire to keep the pain close, close enough to destroy us.’  Upon learning more,
I found out about how a popular jewellery brand conceived a new line of
necklaces with the words- ‘depression’, ‘anxiety’ and ‘bipolar’ inscribed on
them. Twitter has multiple accounts such as that of &lt;em&gt;So Sad Today&lt;/em&gt;. I guess what
I’m trying to allude to is- The Sad Online Culture. You can’t tell me you’ve
never seen a post where someone is staring into the distance, the picture tuned
to darker shades, and a caption with something negative/sad. There is a new
culture of equalling beauty to tragedy. Pain, melancholy are seen as artsy. It’s
not to say I don’t like my fair share of Lana Del Rey or I don’t appreciate all
the API trimmed sappy content Instagram throws at me. In fact, if you’ve got
time- you really ought to check out this feminist philosophy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://believermag.com/in-conversation-with-mira-gonzalez/&quot;&gt;Sad Girl
Theory&lt;/a&gt;, penned by
artist Audrey Wollen, who, by the way, goes by ’&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/audreywollen/?hl=en&quot;&gt;Tragic
Queen&lt;/a&gt;‘ on Instagram. There’s the
complicated concept of creativity and mental illness, but that requires a long,
let’s get cookies and milk/wine (whatever’s your poison), sit down. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Withstanding all that I’ve mentioned above, I’m still well aware of how social
media has allowed mental health issues to become more widely known and accepted,
how they have allowed us all to share personal stories and accounts of many a
psychological disorder. They’re often seen as support systems to encourage and
inform others of one’s own personal experiences and yet, it also comprises an
entire added bonus of trivialising these disorders. Sites that allow anonymous
posting end up becoming group therapy sessions with no therapist to take charge
of the situation. This is where one may find people suffering the same way that
they are but it is highly likely that instead of improving their situation, it
ends up becoming a constant, painful cycle of reinforcement. All of this leads
to people expressing their emotions and hardships which end up looking like an
effort to romanticise the ordeals. It is noteworthy, however, to know that one
might just be unaware that one is romanticising something. People feel that they
are merely sharing their thoughts and feelings. For the vulnerable mind, these
online spaces become communities that seemingly provide the ideal solution:
support, understanding, acceptance. To be accepted by this community, it is
almost as if one has to advertise one’s suffering. Thus, subconsciously a choice
is made- to suffer, to fit in and get acceptance. “Adaptability is what makes us
both wonderful and terrible. We can easily forget what’s healthy- can adapt to
really unhealthy environments quickly. And it so often feels somehow right even
when it’s not,” said Whitlock. This is not a ‘you’ or ‘me’ situation, this is a
complete trajectory of a ‘we’ situation. More often than not, we invest in this
world, consciously or not- and help it prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might have made a lot of foes for saying all that I have, but once in a while,
one’s bound to have a curious case of ‘What even is happening?’ I don’t come
here with ways to live one’s life, I only come here with questions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">Hello, I’m Harshita and I’m addicted to this phenomenon called ‘web surfing’, which sounds like the closest adventure sport I could ever be into and oh well. Today, I bring to you a new question. Okay, perhaps not as new as I’d like it to be. About an hour or two ago, on a podcast I heard a 15-year-old say and I quote, “… in previous eras, they had wars with guns and gas, and in ours, we war with our own self.” To give you more context, she reinstated what we all can see but perhaps are unable to acknowledge- we’re all in an epidemic, one which is not as visible as we think it to be- mental health issues. With more than 10 million posts on Instagram with the hashtag ‘mental_health’ and about ten times more of blogs on Tumblr, it’d be wrong of me to say we don’t talk about it enough. I know that we do, hell, we more than just talk about it. And yet, it’s an epidemic with no foreseeable solution. I can sit here and go on and on about how maybe we are more aware of these mental issues now because people are more knowledgeable of the same, maybe because the stigma is being fought against, perhaps, we just are more courageous than the ones who came before us. What I can’t give up on are the words by my 15-year-old muse, is she right in believing that just as every era is to go through one huge debilitation, we’ve been destined to fall into the chasm of mental health chaos? Would it be wrong of me to assume that there are more factors than just awareness that are making us all a little more troubled than ever? I couldn’t give you a solid number for the amount of times I’ve said ‘Same!’ when someone around me said, ‘I can’t live this life no more’ or, ‘Ugh! I’m so depressed’ or something akin to it. I know I’ve uttered the words ‘I want to die’ on multiple accounts, once because I couldn’t bear the heat. Albeit the fact that I know it’s asinine to have claimed the same, it is difficult not to do the same. I could tell you it’s because it’s ingrained, because I’ve been conditioned and been rewarded quite positively or, perhaps, because everyone around me does it and if Bandura had anything to say for it, he’d agree. All around us- in the spaces we most frequent, there’s a strong prevalence of (and I say this off of my personal disposition) romanticisation of mental illness. Somehow our move to ‘delete the stigma’ has drastically changed towards a trend to ‘romanticise the stigma’. While it’s not something that one should be ashamed of, it also isn’t something one should aspire for. Why is it that on Tumblr, #Thinspo is always trending, why is it that not sleeping and being perpetually tired has become a way of popular culture? How did self-inflicted scars come to be called art? When did the ‘Sad Girls Club’ become the new ideal, often propagated by the VSCO girls or the new e-girls? What about #proana? I remember reading Looking for Alaska and being astounded by how easily the teenage girl said, and oh, ‘with delight of a kid on a Christmas morning’- “Y’all smoke to enjoy it. I smoke to die.” If you’ve ever gone down the Instagram explore page, you’ve definitely been acquainted with Sir R.M. Drake and his well-fonted, honey-coloured quotes such as that of, ‘We desire to keep the pain close, close enough to destroy us.’  Upon learning more, I found out about how a popular jewellery brand conceived a new line of necklaces with the words- ‘depression’, ‘anxiety’ and ‘bipolar’ inscribed on them. Twitter has multiple accounts such as that of So Sad Today. I guess what I’m trying to allude to is- The Sad Online Culture. You can’t tell me you’ve never seen a post where someone is staring into the distance, the picture tuned to darker shades, and a caption with something negative/sad. There is a new culture of equalling beauty to tragedy. Pain, melancholy are seen as artsy. It’s not to say I don’t like my fair share of Lana Del Rey or I don’t appreciate all the API trimmed sappy content Instagram throws at me. In fact, if you’ve got time- you really ought to check out this feminist philosophy called Sad Girl Theory, penned by artist Audrey Wollen, who, by the way, goes by ’Tragic Queen‘ on Instagram. There’s the complicated concept of creativity and mental illness, but that requires a long, let’s get cookies and milk/wine (whatever’s your poison), sit down.  Withstanding all that I’ve mentioned above, I’m still well aware of how social media has allowed mental health issues to become more widely known and accepted, how they have allowed us all to share personal stories and accounts of many a psychological disorder. They’re often seen as support systems to encourage and inform others of one’s own personal experiences and yet, it also comprises an entire added bonus of trivialising these disorders. Sites that allow anonymous posting end up becoming group therapy sessions with no therapist to take charge of the situation. This is where one may find people suffering the same way that they are but it is highly likely that instead of improving their situation, it ends up becoming a constant, painful cycle of reinforcement. All of this leads to people expressing their emotions and hardships which end up looking like an effort to romanticise the ordeals. It is noteworthy, however, to know that one might just be unaware that one is romanticising something. People feel that they are merely sharing their thoughts and feelings. For the vulnerable mind, these online spaces become communities that seemingly provide the ideal solution: support, understanding, acceptance. To be accepted by this community, it is almost as if one has to advertise one’s suffering. Thus, subconsciously a choice is made- to suffer, to fit in and get acceptance. “Adaptability is what makes us both wonderful and terrible. We can easily forget what’s healthy- can adapt to really unhealthy environments quickly. And it so often feels somehow right even when it’s not,” said Whitlock. This is not a ‘you’ or ‘me’ situation, this is a complete trajectory of a ‘we’ situation. More often than not, we invest in this world, consciously or not- and help it prosper. I might have made a lot of foes for saying all that I have, but once in a while, one’s bound to have a curious case of ‘What even is happening?’ I don’t come here with ways to live one’s life, I only come here with questions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Greying World: An Opportunity for India</title><link href="/The-Greying-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Greying World: An Opportunity for India" /><published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Greying-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Greying-World">&lt;p&gt;In his Independence Day address to the Indian nation, Prime Minister Narendra Modi flagged the challenges posed by population explosion. He suggested that keeping a small family was patriotism in the truest sense. Surely, this had to do with the UN forecast of India overtaking China as the most populous country by 2027. Thus, an analysis of the demographic trends would be essential to understand the issue in-depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic development studies course would tell you that a sustained increase in per capita income is necessary to bring about economic growth. However, when the rate of growth of population overtakes the growth in the GDP, per capita income starts falling. At present, Sub-Saharan Africa is witnessing a negative per capita economic growth because of the same reason. Thus, highlighting the importance of population studies for comprehensive economic planning. Academicians believe that an indispensable indicator in comparative population studies is the &lt;strong&gt;Total Fertility Rate (TFR)&lt;/strong&gt;. It measures the number of children born to a woman at the end of the child-bearing age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sample Registration System (SRS) under the Registrar General of India, the sole authority responsible for analysing and collecting demographic surveys of the country, pegged the TFR at 2.2. This is marginally higher than the replacement rate (2.1), which is the average number of children per woman to keep the population size constant. The latest figures are a sign of relief, as the birth rate is moving closer towards stabilisation levels. Total Fertility Rates declined from 5.2 in 1971 to 4.5 in 1981. The decade in discussion was infamous for coercive population control measures, unveiled during the Emergency of 1975-77, imposed by the then-Prime Minister Indira Gandhi. BBC described this as a gruesome campaign to sterilise poor men, with police cordoning off entire villages and forcefully taking men for the surgery. From 1991 to 2017, TFR gradually declined from 3.6 to 2.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven Indian states - Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan, Assam, Chhattisgarh and Jharkhand - account for 45% of the total population in 2011 Census. Some of these are part of the BIMARU (translates into ‘sick’ in English; acronym for the Indian states of Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan and Uttar Pradesh) states and lag behind on most socio-economic and health parameters. The latest data found TFR being higher than the national average in all the states, with Bihar topping the charts with a TFR of 3.2. While relatively well-off states - Kerala, Tamil Nadu, Karnataka, Maharashtra, Andhra Pradesh and Telangana - demonstrate fertility rates below the replacement level. An intimate relationship between economic development and fertility rates can thence be established. The difference in fertility rates would result in an ageing population in the South, while the North would host a significantly younger population. This polarity would result in interesting economic implications - the South would open caregiving-related jobs for the young workforce of the North, fueling migration southwards and remittance flow northwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In urban areas, TFR declined from 4.1 in 1971 to 1.7 in 2017. The rural areas also witnessed a decline in TFR from 5.4 in 1971 to 2.4 in 2017. The fertility rate of urban areas is lower than the replacement level, while it is quite higher than the replacement level in the rural areas. This disparity indicates a population pressure in the rural areas, which would further accentuate rural-urban migration in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s TFR, which is marginally higher than the replacement rate, will help evolve a demographic profile that is more favourable to economic growth. The UN Population Fund (UNFPA) estimated India’s working age population to reach a maximum of 65% in 2030, and then decline thereafter. The report further estimated that the demographic dividend would be available for 5 decades, from 2005 to 2055, longer than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China, on the other hand, witnessed a TFR of 1.62 in 2016. By 2050, a third of its population would be above the age of 60, which has the potential to derail the economic powerhouse of the world. Alarmed by the possible consequences, the Chinese establishment dropped the One-Child Policy in 2013, and unveiled a plan to incentivise couples to have a second child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further East, in Japan, TFR stood at 1.41 in 2016. There is a societal problem behind falling birth rates in Japan. Fewer opportunities for young people creates a class of men who do not want to marry and have kids, simply because they cannot afford to. Longer work hours and absence of job security are quoted to be the main issues. The vicious cycle of low fertility and lower spending has led to a loss in the GDP and a population decline of 1 million people. If left unchecked, a severe economic downturn due to ageing population and rising social security costs is imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In European countries such as France, Denmark, Ireland and Sweden, TFR is in the range of 1.7-2. However, in Czech Republic, Lithuania, Poland and Slovenia, TFR is much below 1.3. The trend of ‘demographic ageing’ is observed in the Western and Central Europe, and will worsen the economic situation of EU27 in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Road Ahead for India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There lies a definite opportunity for India to be the next economic powerhouse in the greying world. But it needs to concentrate on promoting family planning to retain the gains and accelerate fertility decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important challenge that family planning (FP) programmes face is funding. The FP component gets only 4% of the total budget available under the National Health Mission. In the financial year 2016-17, only 60.7% of the funds available for family planning were utilised. Underutilisation of funds hinders expansion of family planning services. The news of the death of several women in sterilisation camps, such as that in Chhattisgarh in 2014, demotivates the couples. Only 56% of married women in India report contraception usage. Access to safe contraceptive methods is a fundamental right. India’s neighbour Bangladesh implemented a fairly effective, non-coercive family planning programme which led to a dramatic reduction in fertility in a short time, from TFR being 7 in 1971 to 2.2 in 2011. There is a high level of awareness about family planning matters and higher reported usage of contraceptive techniques. India, similar to Bangladesh, can employ its ASHA workforce to spread awareness about these. Recently, an initiative by USAID (United States Agency for International Development) and the Government of India led to a campaign promoting usage of oral contraceptive pills titled “Hai Goli Mein Vishwas (Trust the pill).” Such awareness programmes at the micro-regional rural areas can go a long way in fulfilling the above objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain policies have not rewarded the states which have taken effective measures for controlling population growth. Population growth in North and Central India is far greater than Southern India. Between 1971 and 2011, the population of Kerala grew by 56%, while there was a 140% rise in case of Bihar, Uttar Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh. The 15th Finance Commission has retained 2011 population census for Centre-State revenue allocations as its term of reference. This formula, if used, would lead to higher flow of funds to the North-Central states at the expense of the Southern States, leaving them feeling penalised for better performance in reducing fertility. Using 1971 population numbers for State allocations of Central resources could be a better formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female education is yet a very important move to fight population explosion. Data from the Sample Registration System shows that a class 10-pass or GCSE equivalent qualified woman produces 2 children on average. The TFR further falls to 1.8 in case a woman clears Class 12 exam or the A-level equivalent. A woman with education levels of a graduate or above has a TFR of 1.4. Thus, the total fertility rate falls with the increase in levels of education. And an educated mother is a prerequisite for population stabilisation as she is able to play an active role in family planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of the family planning programme should continue to be ‘voluntary’, as suggested by the National Population Policy in 2000. Recently, an eminent Congress leader called for a law on population control. A BJP Rajya Sabha MP introduced a private member’s Bill seeking to enforce a two-child norm. A prominent businessman-yoga guru called for a law ‘disenfranchising’ the third child to prevent larger family size. The fact that 23 states and union territories have fertility rates below 2.1 shows that support works rather than control. In addition, we have the Chinese example to tell us that coercive methods might take things out of control. “The people who have maintained small families need to be honoured, and by setting them as examples, we need to inspire the segment of the society who are still not thinking on those lines,” said PM Modi. Though we have come a long way, still a lot needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gurleen Kaur</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In his Independence Day address to the Indian nation, Prime Minister Narendra Modi flagged the challenges posed by population explosion. He suggested that keeping a small family was patriotism in the truest sense. Surely, this had to do with the UN forecast of India overtaking China as the most populous country by 2027. Thus, an analysis of the demographic trends would be essential to understand the issue in-depth.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Indian Economic Downturn: A Critique</title><link href="/Indian-Economic-Downturn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Economic Downturn: A Critique" /><published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Indian-Economic-Downturn</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Economic-Downturn">&lt;p&gt;The recent economic downturn in India has been the talk of the hour. The state of Indian economy is at its worst phase since the Modi Government came back to power in 2019. Having lost its coveted title of world’s fastest growing economy to China, India’s GDP growth rate has slipped to a six year low at 5% during the April-June quarter of 2019-20, putting the Reserve Bank of India’s projected GDP growth rate of 6.9% in grave danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decrease in the growth prospects of the Indian economy is largely due to the decline in manufacturing output and lack of consumption demand. This is clearly evidenced by the miserable state of Indian automobile sector, with an 18% dip in overall sales in July, 2019 alone. The worst hit was the passenger vehicles category, which saw a 35% decline in sales, followed by a decline in the sales of commercial vehicles by 25% and two-wheelers by 16%. Many automakers like Tata Motors and Ashok Leyland temporarily shut down their factories and suspended production so as to reduce excess inventories in a situation of weak demand. More than 300 dealerships have been closed and a mammoth of 230 thousand jobs have been lost in the sector. This heavy decline in sales has been caused due to a basket of factors, catalysed by upcoming changes related to environmental regulations and electric cars, and a lack of financing. India’s move to adopt new emission norms from April 1, 2020 has caused consumers to delay their consumption temporarily, partly because of the apprehension regarding validity of registration. A drop in rural demand is also evident from the reduced sale of tractors and two-wheelers in the country. In case of commercial vehicles, an increase in the freight carrying capacity of trucks has shrunk demand for new trucks. Further, an increase in the price of vehicles due to manufacturers having to comply with stringent safety regulations (airbags, anti-lock braking system and other crash norms) has weakened demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has tried to kick start the auto sector by taking steps such as lifting the ban on the purchase of vehicles by government departments, allowing additional 15% depreciation on vehicles acquired from mid-August till March 2020 to lower taxable profits and deferring the increase in one-time registration fee of vehicles until June 2020. However, many economists believe the downturn in auto sector to be cyclical caused by recent developments in the Indian economy which will eventually fade away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real problem comes in when people do not even have the money to buy things of everyday use like soaps, biscuits, tea, spices. The Fast Moving Consumer Goods (FMCG) market is in a lull with slowed down volume growth (number of packs sold) of companies like HUL, Daabur, Britannia during first quarter of the current financial year. On the other hand, the real estate sector is experiencing a downward trend in demand, with 1.28 million unsold houses as of March 2019, a 7% increase in the number from the previous year-end. This slowdown has affected more than 250 ancillaries that have forward and backward linkages with the housing sector, ranging from steel and cement to furnishings and paints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underlying cause of the poor performance of the manufacturing sector is a fall in private consumption and investment. While turbulence in the world economy has impacted India’s exports, the slump in internal demand is a result of falling rural and urban wages. From having high double digit figures, growth rates of both rural and urban areas has plunged to dismal single digit figures, largely due to structural changes like demonetisation and GST in the country as well as a poor monsoon affecting the agricultural income in rural areas. This has resulted in stagnant per capita income (in real terms) and to keep the consumption expenditure at the same level, the household savings have declined, resulting in a subsequent decline in investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a slow growth in retail loans such as home loans, vehicle loans and personal loans granted by banks and non-banking financial companies (NBFCs) during the first quarter of 2019-20. After the DHFL and IL&amp;amp;FS crisis, banks and mutual funds are reluctant to lend out to these institutions. This liquidity crunch of NBFCs has decreased their lending capacity. Borrowers too are apprehensive of their ability to repay loans in a period of decreasing real income and employee layoffs. Further, an inverted yield curve in the US, a symbol of long term lending rates being less than short term rates, is taken as an indicator of impending global recession. This is because banks borrow at short term rates and lend at long-term rates and the downward sloping curve means that the loans of these banks will become unprofitable, forcing banks to reduce their lending in the market, resulting in decreased economic activity globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Modi Government has been quick in initiating a recovery process to bring back the economy on track and undoing the damage done by its Budget 2019. The government recently unveiled the mega plan to merge ten public sector banks into four, reducing the number of public sector banks to merely 12 in the country, as part of plans to create fewer and stronger global-sized lenders to boost economic growth. The Union Budget 2019 also talked about injecting ₹70 trillion for recapitalisation of public sector banks to increase credit offtake in the economy. The Reserve Bank of India has also cut the repo rate for the fourth time in a row in 2019 by 35 base points to peg it at 5.4% giving commercial banks a nudge to reduce their lending rates, thus passing on the benefit to customers and attracting them to borrow more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another smart move off late is certainly the transfer of surplus funds of the central bank, worth ₹176 trillion to the Indian government, which will not only reduce the government’s dependence on external borrowings to finance its fiscal deficit target of 3.3%, but also increase per capita income and job creation via increased government expenditure at a time of weakening private investment. However, this transfer will reduce the wide gap between estimated revenue and expenditure by merely ₹580 billion in this fiscal year, because an amount equivalent to ₹900 billion has already been proposed by the Budget 2019 and an interim dividend worth ₹280 billion has been transferred to the government in FY19. The government has further announced the rollback of enhanced surcharge on foreign portfolio Investments (FPIs) as well as exemption to startups and investors from paying an ‘angel tax’ so as to reverse the outflow of money from the Indian stock market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This current contraction in the Indian economy is neither wholly cyclical that is bound to eventually fade away nor is it wholly structural that will result in a massive recession. It is rather a combination of both, with lower per capita income, especially in rural areas, and low job growth being major structural issues plaguing the economy; and low consumer demand and liquidity crunch being the prime cyclical problems. The government has wisely used both monetary and fiscal measures to combat this slowdown, but there is still a lot that needs to be done like new infrastructure projects, affordable housing schemes, modified GST rates, better irrigation facilities and enhanced liquidity of NBFCs. In a time when the private sector is wary of investment, it is only the government that can nudge the economy out of the rock bottom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The recent economic downturn in India has been the talk of the hour. The state of Indian economy is at its worst phase since the Modi Government came back to power in 2019. Having lost its coveted title of world’s fastest growing economy to China, India’s GDP growth rate has slipped to a six year low at 5% during the April-June quarter of 2019-20, putting the Reserve Bank of India’s projected GDP growth rate of 6.9% in grave danger.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Iceland’s Tourism Story</title><link href="/Iceland-Tourism-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Iceland’s Tourism Story" /><published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Iceland-Tourism-Story</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Iceland-Tourism-Story">&lt;p&gt;Iceland, a small island nation, situated in the Northern Atlantic went from being the 4th richest nation during its economic rise to occupying the center stage role in the financial controversy of 2008. And now, it has become infamous among the economists as an example of “what countries shouldn’t do”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most astonishing part of its journey is that until the 1990’s, the country had very little economic growth, with fishing being its primary source of employment. In 1991, there was a significant shift in the power tectonics of the country and David Oddsson was elected as the new Prime Minister. His ascent to the country’s Prime Ministership changed the fate of the country forever. His Government had inherited an economy built on huge debts, lacking the means of paying them back. This was a result of immense accumulation of unproductive investments made by the earlier governments and to worsen the situation further, the nation’s inflation rate was as high as 20% (which was unbelievably high when compared to other western countries). The stocks of fish, then a major source of income for the economy, began to deplete at an increasing rate. Thus, it called for a change and people voted for it. And oh, what a change did their votes bring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Government rolled out extensive liberalisation policies: the state-owned enterprises were privatised, taxes were slashed and that paved the way for the rise of the private sector in the country. Fortunately, the economy started to revive gradually, and inflation was brought under control. Thus, began an era of growth and it exploded in the 2000’s. Most significant of all was the deregulation of the finance industry which helped the banks to expand and grow at an unbridled speed. They started holding and managing billions of dollars. An exponential progression from the past. Shockingly, the banks dealt with an enormous amount of money, which was almost ten times the country’s GDP. By early 2007, the country had successfully emerged as the 4th richest nation in the world, and Reykjavik, the nation’s capital, had become a financial power hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the rise curve was steep and the short term growth misled people to think that they were invincible. However, as swift the rise to power is, the harder is the fall from grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everything was going well for the country, the financial crisis of 2008, which affected almost every west-world country, took a massive toll on Iceland’s economy. As the global recession started, the value of &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt;, the currency of Iceland, began to plummet and their banks failed the country. Because the banks dealt in enormous volume of money, it proved hard for the government to bail out the big players of the market. Amidst the chaos and tragedy, the country managed to find its way out of the recession far earlier than many of its partners-in-crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we know, some countries grow off manufacturing and the others off services. Likewise, Iceland decided to grow off the latter. They captured a part of the already gigantic worldwide tourism industry and built up a feasible strategy for much-needed economic development. The country leveraged tourism effectively to bounce back from the worst financial crisis that the world has witnessed since the Great Depression of 1929.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iceland has a serene and pure natural beauty with plentiful waterfalls, lakes, glaciers, geysers: pretty much everything that could attract tourists from all over the world. It has one of the most spectacular natural environments in the world, the country is only a few flight hours away from the richest countries like the UK, the US and others. Accessibility and affordability are two major aspects that tourists look for when travelling. Iceland has been very focused on addressing these two primary concerns to boost its tourism sector. The issue of affordability needed no attention as the fall in the value of &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt; made it cheaper for tourists to travel and avail various services in the country. To resolve the issue of accessibility, Iceland had Iceland Air, the national carrier, which by providing attractive fares to the flyers had grown in the trans-Atlantic area, and acted as a boon to the country. This well-reputed airline started more service routes and expanded to different parts of the world. A second airline based in Iceland, Wow Air, was soon launched. The two airlines carried more than half the visitors every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Crisis, word about Iceland spread across the world and grabbed the interest and attention of tourists. This has helped the Nordic nation tremendously in attracting foreign tourists. In one way, the event that crashed the economy had paved the path for its revival. By 2010, the tourism industry was growing by an enormous 20% per annum. As the industry grew, so did the hospitality sector. New hotels began to spring up. Car rentals expanded to carry people all across the pristine country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, Iceland’s real GDP started to grow at almost 7.5% by 2016. Tourism contributed about 10% to the GDP and 30% of the total export revenue of the country. Another central reason for the sudden boom in the tourism sector was immigration. The number of immigrants steadily rose into the country because of the labour shortage and economic boom in the country. They now make up for 32% of the total workforce employed in the tourism industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is one side of the coin, let’s now look at the other side. The tourism industry is highly seasonal and therefore, can’t be expected to generate revenue and employment throughout the year. This largely curtails the period of growth making it difficult for those employed in the sector to find stable employment. Tourism is an industry where most of the people are low-wage workers with limited scope of growth. Tourism also hasn’t exactly been the go-to industry for those white-collared employees who were out of jobs after the crisis. Then there are the negative effects on the environment due to the excessive usage. As heavy infrastructure is needed to accommodate the exponential growth in tourist visits, they come at the expense of damaging the environment. It has reached a level that excess tourism has become a serious concern for the country. The tourism industry has its dark sides, such as illegal employment, paying workers below the minimum wage and human trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this boom did not last for long. The tourism sector began to experience downfall since the third quarter of 2018. Since last December there has been a substantial fall in the number of tourists in the country. Since December 2018, Iceland started reporting negatives in the growth rate of incoming tourists. In April 2019, this had reached a level of negative 26%. There are many reasons for this sharp and sudden downfall. One of the first reasons is the collapse of Wow Air. Albeit being the second-largest airline of the nation, it had collapsed as it never saw profits and ran out of financials. Consequently, the growth estimates for 2019 were revised to -0.4% from the earlier 1.8%. Unemployment was predicted to reach 3.9% as against the earlier 3.1%. The collapse also meant that the thousands of tourists that were supposed to come were suddenly non-existent. Apart from Wow Air’s collapse, the fall of tourism can also be attributed to Iceland becoming expensive as a result of the appreciating &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt; owing to increased GDP growth. If one were to make an intelligent guess, it can also be is simply that Iceland isn’t appealing to people anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it was noted earlier, the tourism boon had devastating effects on the environment. On the other hand, the country did not have the structural capacity to support the huge influx of tourists. Optimistically speaking, Iceland can utilise this period to rebuild itself to expand infrastructure and to restore the lost natural beauty. It can also utilise this time to make plans for revitalising the sector and transforming it into one that can sustain a huge number of tourists and think of a solution to provide year-long stable income stream to the workers involved in this business.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Iceland, a small island nation, situated in the Northern Atlantic went from being the 4th richest nation during its economic rise to occupying the center stage role in the financial controversy of 2008. And now, it has become infamous among the economists as an example of “what countries shouldn’t do”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Hate You Like I Love You: Demythologising The Indian Mother</title><link href="/The-Indian-Mother" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Hate You Like I Love You: Demythologising The Indian Mother" /><published>2019-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Indian-Mother</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Mother">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve cringed at the Mother’s Day wishes that flooded social media a few weeks ago, which were basically variations of ‘she is the world’s smartest, strongest punching bag’, (go Leslie Knope!) you’ll probably see a valid point in what I have to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers are strange creatures. But do you know what’s stranger? The myth of motherhood, carefully curated by patriarchy and capitalism in India. What’s in it for them? Well, everything. This myth furthers their profiteering ventures through the sinister exploitation of a sentiment. They show mothers as goddesses, whose only joy lies in serving you, and her family well. She has no personal wishes, and her sexuality can very well be forgotten about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertisements portray women with ten hands (and I do not mean this figuratively), happily cooking up idlis, dosas, and parathas to serve a perfect breakfast to each member of the family. The grandfather nonchalantly reads the newspaper, the three petulant children complain (among whom is her husband, complaining the loudest about the late breakfast, so go figure), when the mother magically appears with trays full of scrumptious food. The mother is supposed to flutter her eyelashes and cry tears of joy when her husband decides to make her breakfast once a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian mother is supposed to selflessly love and consistently deliver. The ‘progressive’ advertisements are no better. The mother has short hair, works outside the house but god forbid if she comes home and lies down on the sofa after a long day. The ‘woke’ ads are packaged to comfortably suit our definition of empowerment without radically questioning it or demanding any action. The mother must juggle office work and domestic duties dexterously because, well, human fatigue does not apply to mythological beings, and this is what motherhood has mostly been depicted as in popular culture. A myth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m choosing to bypass Bollywood because that would require a separate article of its own, but I am sure you can make the connections. I choose standard examples from advertising because they’re made specifically to appeal to consumers, to make them relate to its essence. The mother usually applies oil to the daughter’s scalp, or some lotion on her skin, or they’re exchanging recipes because what else can mothers and daughters talk to each other about except skin care and cooking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our relationships with our mothers is not one only of careless laughter and light banter. It is the core love story of our lives till adulthood, and it is a burden and a duty. Thankfully, there exist refreshing counter narratives to the myth of motherhood that question the iconic status of motherhood in popular culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rituporno Ghosh’s &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt; is the story of Urmila (played by Aparna Sen) and Rohit Roy (played by Mithun Chakraborty) who were lovers in their youth. Urmila was married off at 20 to a tea estate manager, and Titli is their daughter. Blowing bubblegums and restlessly shaking her legs, the 17 year old Titli develops a massive crush on Rohit, who is now a Bollywood film star. In the beginning of the film, Titli is seen hovering around her mother, asking her to dress her up or put on a specific perfume. There is clear admiration and longing in her voice. This longing is something the myth dare not acknowledge; the physical envy between the mother and the daughter. While the daughter struggles through awkward breasts, menstruation and pimples, the mother is a graceful lady comfortable in her womanhood and her sexuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Titli wistfully asks her mother, “Ma, why can’t I marry someone 20 years older? Grandpa was 20 years older than Grandma. Was grandma unhappy?” Urmila casually replies, “My mother wouldn’t dream of asking her mother this question”, the conversation shows the shift between the mother-daughter dynamic over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a chance meeting, where Titli and Urmila meet Rohit, Titli learns of her mother’s past and the adoration she had changes to jealousy and malice. Titli can not bear that fact that prior to her, her mother had a romantic past. To her, this feels like an intense betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is seen in Ghosh’s film &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; (19th April), where the mother, Sarojini, a renowned classical dancer, is always elegantly dressed in sarees and jewelry. The daughter, Mithu, training to be a doctor, despises dressing up and covers herself in baggy t-shirts and long skirts. She holds the grief of her father’s death against her mother. Her grief makes her powerful, and in her eyes, a better person who &lt;em&gt;conforms&lt;/em&gt; to traditional norms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During her father’s funeral, the other female relatives of the house, while serving tea to guests also spill some gossip. “Sarojini is in Madras…or Mumbai. Who knows? If she wanted to become a famous dancer so badly, she should have just limited herself to that. Why would you marry and have a daughter as well?” There is a tinge of jealousy in this woman’s moralising; Sarojini is living the life she probably was too afraid to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, eighteen years later, on the father’s death anniversary, Sarojini receives a National award, which sets off a chain of reactions between her and Mithu. One can sense the constant ego tussle between the mother and the daughter, but the audience knows that this is due to miscommunication. When Mithu sits and cries in front of the telephone because her boyfriend has refused to marry her (because her mother is a dancer), Sarojini interprets this as her daughter’s jealousy towards her success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I loved the most about these films were their explorations into two important facets of the mother-daughter relationship: envy and miscommunication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt;, Urmila comes into Titli’s room to shut the windows as there is a storm raging outside. In the wind, her shawl falls off and Titli watches her mother’s body, clad in a strappy nightgown, and there is a distinct recognition of her mother as a sexual being in her eyes. She tells her mother, “Whatever idea I had of you, has changed after tonight.” This might seem like an emotionally exaggerated response, but it is something to think about. Why would there be such reluctance to accept the mother as a sexual being? The simple answer is because it makes us uncomfortable. Of course, these conversations are uncomfortable, but that’s verily why they are all the more necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mother is acceptable as long as she lives her life vicariously through others - her husband’s promotion, her son’s academic performance, but never her own achievements or her personal desires. Women’s sexuality is acceptable as long as it comfortably services a man within acceptable social customs. The daughter isn’t supposed to have any knowledge of her mother’s seductive charm. Titli realises she has crossed a line, and Urmila opens up to her about her past relationship. For the first time, they converse as equals. The film &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt; ends with the daughter requesting her mother to recite a poem she knew Urmila recited for Rohit. The envy has faded away, the lines of miscommunication have been bridged. We remember what Urmila had told Rohit during their meeting. “When Titli watches you, I watch her. For as long as she watches you, I watch her. When you fight villains on stage, she chews her gum faster. When you dance with your heroine, envy and anger cloud her face.” The audience realises what the film was always about: the love story between a mother and her daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; too, we have a similar reconciliation. Sarojini returns home to find Mithu has decided to commit suicide on the day of her father’s death, heartbroken by the rejection of her marriage proposal. The constant friction in their conversation fades away as Mithu breaks down and asks her mother “Why didn’t you ever ask me to join your dance class?” This is her deepest grievance, laid bare before us. All the intense tension between the two has been building up to this moment. Mithu never felt needed by her mother, and her way of coping was to immerse herself in books and be a doctor like her father. Sarojini, in between her sobbing, replies, “I did not understand you wanted to. I never asked, Mithu. I’m sorry.” The remarkable aspect of &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; is how Sarojini is unapologetic about her decisions. She offers an explanation for her actions but stands by them. In the end, we find Mithu writing her a prescription to help with her knee pain while Sarojini requests her to accompany her to Madras, to meet her dance guru, making an active effort to include her in her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers make mistakes. This is something mainstream culture refuses to accept. The standards motherhood is held to are unbelievably high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Gilmore Girls&lt;/em&gt;, Lorelai and Rory come across as sisters in the first scene. Rory is often the ‘mother’ in the relationship, asking Lorelai to think through practical decisions, consume a liquid that isn’t Luke’s coffee, and managing the intense drama between her grandmother Emily and her mother. Lorelai makes mistakes, but she makes a significant effort to acknowledge and make up for them. When Rory wanted to drop out of Yale and moved out to live with her grandparents, Lorelai and her get into a huge fight. However, when Rory reconsiders and rejoins Yale, and comes home to apologise, Lorelai says “I should have pulled you out of there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Greta Gerwig’s &lt;em&gt;Lady Bird&lt;/em&gt;, the only moment of peace is perhaps the beginning where Christine “Lady Bird” McPherson and her mother sleep on the same bed. Two minutes later in the movie, Lady Bird jumps out of moving car as her mother tells her, “You know, with your work ethic, you should probably go to City College, then to jail, then back to City College.” From the moment the movie starts, to its very end, their relationship is one of constant pushes and pulls. Her mother reminds her of their financial status when Lady Bird wants to buy a magazine, “that’s what rich people do, we’re not rich people.” When they’re in a thrift store, Lady Bird drags her feet and her mother says “Are you tired? I couldn’t really say, because you were dragging your feet”, to which Lady Bird replies “You are SO INFURIATING!” In the very next second her mother pulls out a dress which both of them begin gushing over, completely forgetting the argument. Lady Bird is fiercely individualistic, dramatic, driven, confident, but she struggles because she wants her mother to &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; her, so bad. You have to love Greta Gerwig for getting it so well. Lady Bird’s mother writes and throws away a dozen letters because she felt she would judge her writing capability. Envy and miscommunication again. This gap is bridged, when after getting super drunk after moving away to college, Lady Bird calls her mother to say, “I love you. Thank you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common thread that runs through &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lady Bird&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Gilmore Girls&lt;/em&gt;, connecting the stories across timelines and countries is a simple one: daughters want to feel validated and acknowledged by their mothers. However, these emotions of envy, jealousy, doubt, resentment and anger that our characters feel &lt;strong&gt;need&lt;/strong&gt; to be celebrated. Why? Because the myth of motherhood says unconditional love and care should come naturally. It makes no space for other healthy human emotions. Since our mothers are inherently programmed to want the best for us and see the best in us, there should be no conflict. These counter narratives show that this path towards a stable, loving relationship is not a linear one. It requires careful negotiation between power dynamics, emotions (of which, not all are pleasant) and effort, just like any other relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is rather unfortunate, even unfair, that we need a demythologising of the mother figure in popular culture in the first place. To put it reductively, I’m glad that women are finally telling their imperfect and messy stories. What we need is more of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ayantika Nath</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">If you’ve cringed at the Mother’s Day wishes that flooded social media a few weeks ago, which were basically variations of ‘she is the world’s smartest, strongest punching bag’, (go Leslie Knope!) you’ll probably see a valid point in what I have to discuss.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?</title><link href="/Greener-Pastures" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?" /><published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Greener-Pastures</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Greener-Pastures">&lt;p&gt;Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem absurd in general terms, how would you be an asset to a team that has already won? However, in politics, numbers are everything. If you defect to the majority, they increase their percentage points and maintain their majority. Each defector is like an additional layer of bubble wrap to the fragile glass of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a realist perspective, defection makes sense. If politics is all about power, then why would a politician willingly remain without any? At the end of the day, what good is ideological and partisan loyalty if you cannot make a dent in the political arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has a long (and borderline funny history) with defection. The phrase ‘&lt;em&gt;Aaya Ram, Gaya Ram&lt;/em&gt;’ (‘God came, God left’) was coined after an MP from the northern state of Haryana, Gaya Lal changed parties thrice on the same day in 1967. The period of continuous defections in the 1980’s is what led to the institution of the Anti-Defection Law in 1985 during the tenure of Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi’s government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anti-defection Law in India disqualifies members of the legislature under any one of the two conditions. Firstly, if they voluntarily give up membership of the party. And secondly, if they go against the party whip. The party whip is a command that comes from the party organisation, usually regarding which bills to pass and which to vote against. Interestingly enough, the first condition subsumes things other than simple resignation from the party. According to court judgments, the giving up of membership can be inferred from conduct. So, if a legislator was to speak against his party or in favour of the opposition, a case could be made against him against this law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many arguments against this law have been formulated in the past years. A major concern is the curbing of the freedom of expression. The defence to this freedom of expression argument is that differing opinions within parties leads to instability in the body politik. Just as defection makes sense for individual interest, the law makes sense for structural interests. However, at the end of the day, it means that if the legislator’s constituency is negatively affected by a certain policy or decision that his party is promoting, he doesn’t have the right to express dissent. The politician stands separated from his conscience. The second condition goes further to impair the legislator from taking any action or even abstaining to act for his party. Consent is dubious in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue was raised in the Supreme Court in 1992, to which it said, “the anti-defection law seeks to recognize the practical need to place the proprieties of political and personal conduct… above certain theoretical assumptions.” There is no right way of reacting when the apex court in your country calls the freedom of speech a “theoretical assumption”, but a bit of shock is valid. It is true that most cases of defection are about being on the winning team, about seeking out greener pastures. However, in situations such as post-poll alliances with an ideologically opposite party, the legislator must remain completely in favour of party decisions even at the cost of disappointing his constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stance of the court clearly states the assumption that the party is always right. While ideological compatibility is the basis for party formation, it is impossible for an entire party to have the same vision even under the same umbrella ideology. Many identities are embraced in a party and most of the times, these identities determine individual priorities. Denying a voice to any legislator goes directly against the spirit of democracy and multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this note, we can look into some of the structural and implemental loopholes that allow defection to continue despite the 1985 law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an exception that protects legislators from disqualification. If two-thirds of the legislators from a party agree to a “merger” with a different party, then this does not fall under the purview of the Anti-Defection Law. Using this loophole, 12 MLAs from the Congress party “merged” with the Telangana Rashtra Samithi, the ruling party in the southern state of Telangana, in June 2019. When read closely, the law provides this exception only when the original party merges with the party being defected to. Also, following certain court judgments, this decision of merger could only have been made by the All India Congress Committee and not the Telangana Pradesh Congress Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Presiding officer of the presiding party decides the verdict on defection cases. This officer is almost always a part of the ruling party. This means that defections &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party will be blocked but the ones &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party never will. Since the latter is the wave that defectors tend to ride, this provision effectively reduces the chances of defectors being disqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom, defection causes expulsion from the party but the legislator retains her seat. They are also only a result of defying a three-line party whip (the most urgent type of whip issued) as a sign of voluntarily giving up membership of the party. In Australia, some minor penalties such as barring of access to party resources is the punishment for defying party whips. It is the mildest in the USA where parties cannot expel their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark increase in defections paints a grim picture of political ethics in India. The Karnataka debacle, where Congress-JD(S) alliance MLAs defected to the BJP in the southern state after the party’s sweeping success in the national elections also reflects the blurred lines of the federal system of governance. 17 MLAs were disqualified after the incident in July 2019, allegations of bribery were thrown at the ruling party. The Indian Parliament’s upper house proceedings were repeatedly adjourned as Congress MPs demanded that the BJP government resign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only solution that seems to be in tandem with the political values that India’s Constitution embodies is that once there is defection to a new party, elections in that legislator’s constituency should be reheld. Admittedly this is a long and tedious process, but the provision might itself act as a deterrent for defection itself. There is a very small chance of a defector to be reelected by his people who most likely will hold feelings of betrayal and contempt for him. No legislator would want to face his constituency so soon after defecting. On the other hand, people would get a fair chance to elect someone with clear and full information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications relating to corruption have not even been discussed above as dissecting the role of money and muscle deserves a whole another article. However, it must be stated at least once that along with power, almost all defections involve promises of money and positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, welcome to the seven-decades old Indian democracy. Here, parties are oligarchic and legislators are for sale.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.</summary></entry></feed>