<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-25T09:14:37+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Racism in the Time of Corona</title><link href="/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Racism in the Time of Corona" /><published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona">&lt;p&gt;Racial discrimination and prejudice aren’t novel for this world, unlike the COVID-19. Race and ethnicity have been the two major building blocks of our society. We can trace its origin back to the slavery of the Africans and African-Americans in the United States during the 18th century, the anti-Semitism that blew up in Germany during the Second World War or Islamophobia post 9/11; &lt;em&gt;new disease, old story.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society has always found it comforting and easy on their minds to deflect their insecurities and frustrations onto a group, a minority or a defined culture. This is what is generally referred to as the Scapegoat Theory, that is, the tendency to blame someone else for one’s problems, a process that often results in feelings of prejudice toward the group that one is blaming. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When struck with this unforeseen disease that no one thought would erupt and set alight the world, with no prospects of fizzling out any time soon, people turned to the old blame-game. The uncertainty, the fear, the anger and frustration, although no justification for such acts of racism, led to a huge rise in Sinophobia (or Anti-Chinese sentiment). It also led to xenophobia and violence against people of East Asian and Southeast Asian descent around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coronavirus that originated in Wuhan, China has not only infected people physically but mentally and as stereotypically as it could. Draconian comments such as “wipe the Chinese people out” and “hope this virus gets all of them” etc. have been expressed throughout the world, apathetically. However, this discrimination isn’t a result of just the pandemic, or the lockdown frustration because that would be a fairly a simple explanation for the centuries of entrenched racism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Race Conflict Theory, the race came about as a tool to justify and maintain the economic and political power held by those of European descent ages ago. The prejudice that we hold against certain communities, is, by and large, an extension of the stereotypes we create with an implicit bias that comes into play while making judgments about them. And this chain of stereotype leading to prejudice creates discrimination-unequal treatment of different groups of people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The matter in question today is the virus and its origin in China that has led us to fabricate a stereotype and deplorable feelings towards the Chinese and Asian people. This includes incidents of Northeast-Indian students facing odious and hurtful remarks in colleges, more than 1,000 South Korean tourists being instructed to avoid public places and remain in isolation in their hotels, and even being rejected by hotels and forced to spend nights at the airport, a woman being called “coronavirus”, threatened, and spat on by youths in Schaerbeek and a French newspaper &lt;em&gt;Le Courrier Picard&lt;/em&gt; featuring an Asian woman wearing a mask on its front page on January 26, 2020 with a headline “Yellow Alert”. The paper also titled an editorial “A New Yellow Peril”. These instances are overlooked every day by most of us as they are not considered undignified or moralistically unrighteous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yellow, a term mindlessly anointed to the Asians isn’t new. Segregation based on colour has been a rite as archaic as the Old Testament itself. To think that Racism is not a 21st century paradigm would be a self-delude, a ‘Racism without Racists’, because even though the explicit views might have become less prominent due to their social condemnation and fewer people’s willingness to say them, doesn’t mean that this racism doesn’t exist. It has morphed into a more structural and anchored form of racism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has manifested some economic repercussions too, as nations are withdrawing their faith in China, particularly the United States, whose President Donald Trump has been ramping up his censure of Beijing and threatening new tariffs on China. The United States is considering retaliatory measures against China over the outbreak. A commentator from a US news channel even went so far ahead as to criticise the country for selling virus-infected bats in open-air marketplaces and have business and tourist travel between “that country” and the “civilized world”. These slurs and scorn are touching new bottoms of impropriety across the world, emanating their ideas of what is civilised, as we just saw. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this sentiment hasn’t been restricted to just the Chinese people. Sinophobia was an antechamber into a spur of punitive sentiment against many communities, like the Muslims and the Jews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamophobia reinforced its clutches in India after an incidence of Muslim gatherings organised by the Tablighi Jamaat that resulted in large increased cases in India, which has triggered Islamophobic reactions and increased communal tensions. Fabricated videos falsely claiming to show members of the missionary group spitting on police and others quickly went viral on social media, hospitals refused to treat Muslim patients which led to the deaths of at least two newborn babies, and the Indian media hopped onto the bandwagon of anti-Muslim stories and headlines like a moth to fire.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a country already beset with 70 years of friction between the Hindus and Muslims following the partition of the Indian subcontinent in 1947; gory wars, terrorist attacks and the recent CAA-NRC bill, this new information spread animosity across the country like a wildfire. Instead of dealing with the issue of the virus getting out of hand, due to unequivocal carelessness on the part of certain people, the quandary shifted seamlessly from the economic and social situation of the country to the incongruous matter of factitious religious sentiments. This hate-mongering has ignited the ember of aversion that is already extant in this nation, making hashtags like #CoronaVirusJihaad viral. It’s both shocking and commonplace at the same time for India to spew such hatred against the Muslims amidst a larger issue of a threatening pandemic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authoritarian societies tend to see the societal structure as people who are naturally superior (as they say), having the right to power over others (minorities). It’s a perpetual cyclical motion of various ideas that lead to something grave. A difference based on racial heritage, called ’Pluralism’ gives birth to this pattern which then leads to what sociology refers to as cultural ’Assimilation’ and further ’Segregation’. However, this cycle doesn’t cease until it reaches the point of ’Genocide’. This is a theory, but it cannot be discredited as purely abstract because history has given us enough &lt;em&gt;corpus delicti&lt;/em&gt; to believe that such a heinous crime can occur. The Holocaust and the Rwandan Genocide are testaments to the exacerbated results of racism and pluralism into something inconceivably ghastly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pandemic has shed light not only on the flaws of our societal structure but the general hierarchy of the Capitalist nature of the economic and political organisation that we follow in the 21st century, necessitating a huge change in both our attitudes and the way we function at large. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s prejudice has blinded them, making them ignorant of the fact that this virus is affecting everyone equally, affecting &lt;em&gt;‘them’&lt;/em&gt; as much as it is distressing any other person; that it is us against the malady and not each other. But hasn’t that always been the human folly? &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Poorvi Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Racial discrimination and prejudice aren’t novel for this world, unlike the COVID-19. Race and ethnicity have been the two major building blocks of our society. We can trace its origin back to the slavery of the Africans and African-Americans in the United States during the 18th century, the anti-Semitism that blew up in Germany during the Second World War or Islamophobia post 9/11; new disease, old story.  </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis</title><link href="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis" /><published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 China Financial Stability Report published by the People’s Bank of China officially deems 586 out of 4,379 Chinese lenders to be ‘high-risk’. The figures came into light only after the failure of a third bank within three months as national economic growth manifested a 30-year low. The Hengfeng Bank has become the third bank, after Baoshang Bank and Bank of Jinzhou, to suffer an economic collapse after a $40 trillion debt. But the Chinese government isn’t exceedingly famous for its honesty and transparency, thus the reported figure is likely masking the true extent of the banking quandary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has bailed out many of the high risk lenders. Precarious private shareholders have been effectively replaced by the ones backed by the state, often weaker in terms of their finances. The fact that bailouts are offered only for companies whose bankruptcy has a grave adverse impact on the economy as a whole and not just on a specified sector, cannot be ignored. Moreover, any amount of bailout allocated to this sector will have a domino effect on the Chinese economy which will be several times greater. For instance, the banking system calls for a 5-6% bailout which is equal to 20-24% of the Chinese GDP. A bailout of 20% of the GDP is a non-viable deal for any economy, even if it is China. The numeric is a statement of the fact that any pebble aimed at the banking sector shall bring ripples to the entire economy that in turn will shake China’s status of being a global economic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The People’s Bank of China conducted a stress test in the first half of 2019 on 1,171 commercial banks, 7.7% were stated to be at ‘extreme risk’ and deemed incapable of absorbing even a light shock, 13.6% will probably not be able to endure the financial crisis that shall follow. In November, Yingkou Coastal Bank and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/economy/china-economy/article/3035596/wechat-rumour-sparks-run-rural-chinese-bank-fresh-sign&quot;&gt;Yichuan Rural Commercial Bank&lt;/a&gt; – despite boasting healthy capital adequacy ratios – suffered bank runs as customers rushed to withdraw cash, fearing that the banks would close down, displaying a lack of confidence in banking institutions. The current situation is very similar to the one that cropped up in the late 1990’s. Towards the end of 1997, 20% of the main banks were non-performing, which was equivalent to a value of ¥1.19 trillion on the books of state-owned banks, which was deemed to be equal to 15.6% of the GDP. In order to resolve these crises and recapitalise the banks, ¥270 billion of special government bonds were issued and injected by August 1998. Walking on the same rope, the Chinese government is peddling its way through the crisis by adopting a somewhat similar technique. Today, the interbank market has been injected with around ¥2 trillion by the People’s Bank of China after the Baoshang Bank collapse. Along with this, a helping hand of the sovereign fund, China Investment Corporation, the Central Huijin Investment Company is injecting ¥60 billion into Hengfeng Bank. One of the 12 nationwide joint-stock banks in China, Hengfeng Bank is stacked up with non-performing loans and the situation became grimmer as the bank’s former president was handed out a death sentence for purloining funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, overlooking the different macroeconomic situation shall prove fatal to the Chinese economy in the present scenario. The key antidote for the crisis back then was the spurt of hyper economic growth in the early 2000’s. If China wants to avoid tormenting its economy with the inevitability of bad loans and its weakening banking structure, it will have to aim for a masterful economic growth. However, this stands as a challenge with the outbreak of COVID-19 and its likely aftermath on the global economy. Secondly, continuous evolution over the years has resulted in an entwined and fragile banking structure. The financial system in modern times has given rise to an integrated market that ensures banking transactions are speeded up and are facile in nature. Since the speed of transactions and their impact on the economy is brisk, it also means that any kind of shock in the structure is transmitted faster than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate and interbank customers suffer heavy losses, the volume of negotiable certificates of deposit—which are securities traded between financial institutions for short-term liquidity—has plunged by 90%. The situation threatens to cause the entire banking system to seize up as small and medium-sized banks are heavily dependent on liquidity in the interbank market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crisis should be an eye-opener for the administration as it calls for reforms in the entire financial system which has been overreliant on its banking sector for channeling funds. The fact that the financial structure has changed barely in the last fourteen years is an explanation for the crisis at hand. The world continues to keep a close watch on China, as this crisis is far too big to ignore because any large scale disruption in the driving engine of the global economy will lead the other economies into recession.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Know Your Worth</title><link href="/Know-Your-Worth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Know Your Worth" /><published>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Know-Your-Worth</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Know-Your-Worth">&lt;p&gt;I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But how do I know if the details of my income or personal life will be taken into account when I am standing in the court of law?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when ‘Forensic Economics’ comes into play. Conceived as economics applied to legal matters, forensic economics assesses major issues regarding economic damages in the context of litigation. It is a broad discipline that applies economic theories and methods to matters which are subject to legal review. A forensic economist creates an alternative world with assumptions, wherein the particular citizen is not faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand better where Forensic Economics can be applied in a citizen’s daily life, we will use the most widely accepted defining factor of an individual’s life, that is, ‘work’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worth of a citizen, economically, can be found out by measuring his/her human capital. In order to measure that, one is required to estimate the work-life expectancy of an individual. Now the question is: &lt;em&gt;What is work-life expectancy?&lt;/em&gt; As the word itself suggests, it is the number of years an individual is expected to be in the workforce. The factors that affect each individual’s work-life expectancy include education attained, race, marital status, parental status, and, most importantly, gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists resort to the approach of Forensic Economics to be able to measure an individual’s work-life expectancy, which is contingent on the underlying factors of the individual’s personal life. Under this, they establish the fact that work is not restricted to being involved in only paid employment, but also unpaid non-market work, which also holds certain economic value, thereby, defining ‘total work-life expectancy’ as a sum of market work and non-market work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us establish two imaginary individuals to make our observation simpler: Sheila, a woman, and Joel, a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gender as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The idea that taking care of a household or family is actual work is uncontested and women lead men in that activity. Many times the reason people usually cite for not participating in market work is taking care of household or family. Let’s consider here that both Joel and Sheila are between the ages of 18 to 24. Using the approach of forensic economics, it is found out that the maximum number of men who take care of their households belong to the age group of 18 to 24. However, as we start moving up the total percentage of men participating in non-market work reduces. On the contrary, the percentage of women participating in non-market work starts rising from 18 to 24 and reaches its peak in the age group of 30 to 34, after which it starts to decline. Therefore, a 25-year-old Joel would have about 35 years of market work-life and 1 year of non-market work-life remaining, whereas a 25-year-old Sheila would have about 30 years of market work-life and 6 years of non-market work-life. Both their ‘total work-life expectancy’ would equal 36 years but the difference lies in the market and non-market work based on their gender. This conclusion has been drawn from the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Race, education, and marriage as factors of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The factors of race, education, and marital status of an individual are inherently intertwined in determining his/her work-life expectancy. Let us assume that Sheila is a 30-year-old white woman and X is a non-white woman. If both, Sheila and X, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree then, Sheila’s work-life expectancy will exceed that of X by only a year. Conversely, if both Sheila and X are employed and have high school degrees, the work-life expectancy of Sheila will exceed that of X by over two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we consider Joel to be a 30-year-old white man and Y to be a non-white man, we get different results. If both, Joel and Y, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree, they get the same result as Sheila and X. However, if Joel and Y (both single) have high school degrees, then the work-life expectancy for Joel exceeds that of Y by around 4 years; and by 3.5 years if both men were married. This acute difference between white and non-white men is essentially because men tend to face more discrimination on the basis of their race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a negative relationship between marriage and the work-life expectancy of women. Generally, women of all races face a setback in their market work participation post-marriage. Women with higher degrees face a larger setback than those with lower or no degree at all. This is largely because of two reasons– (a) women tend to be more productive in non-market or household work, and (b) women have a lesser dilemma to face in terms of opportunity cost because women already get lesser pay in comparison to their male counterparts. This leads me to establish the fact that the relationship between marriage and work-life expectancy for men is essentially positive. The work-life expectancy of a married white man exceeds that of an unmarried white man by about 3 years, and a married non-white man has a work-life expectancy of about 4 years more than an unmarried non-white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parental status as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: Let us suppose that Sheila wants to bear a child, but she also wants to keep her work-life expectancy high. To achieve that, she turns to Forensic Economics and realises that the work-life expectancy of a single mother exceeds that of a married mother by 2-3 years. On the contrary, Joel realises that a married man’s work-life expectancy changes negligibly in the case of a child but changes considerably if he chooses to be a single father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having analysed the most basic underlying factors to the work-life expectancy of individuals, it is imperative to establish the fact that the aforementioned observations were made using the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID) under Forensic Economics. This brings us to the conclusion that when the productivity of non-market work is recognised, the work-life expectancy of women is negligibly different than that of men, which busts the myth that men are more productive than women. Therefore, we come to where we started off: the worth of a citizen is measured only after taking into account what I, as an individual citizen, possess with regard to my personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hence, the deliberation ends.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Plato, Pythagoras and Liturgy: The Argument for the Wealth Tax</title><link href="/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Plato, Pythagoras and Liturgy: The Argument for the Wealth Tax" /><published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax">&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greece was known for its military, culture, architecture and many important contributions to science, philosophy and astronomy. However, what was ignored under the discoveries of Pythagoras (yes, that triangle guy) and Plato was its innovative and frankly very sly system of taxation, which could be attributed to the beauty of the liturgy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally, the term Liturgy means a form of public worship, which in ancient Greece meant that the authorities did not tax consumption, instead all public services and development, from building roads to fighting wars, depended upon the &lt;em&gt;benevolence of the rich&lt;/em&gt;. The rich paid taxes voluntarily because the greater the tax, the higher prestige and honour your name and family would get. The rationale behind this was that the rich should shoulder the expense because of the unequal wealth distribution and simply because &lt;em&gt;they can&lt;/em&gt;. While the rich who paid higher taxes enjoyed a greater sway in decision-making and more respect, the poor benefitted by free and quality essential services. Consequently, ancient Greece grew and flourished economically and their citizens lived happily until, of course, the Romans came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only imagine if the same system was implemented today and the same idea of benevolence ruled instead of our usual money and patriarchy. It may seem impossible, yet there are people who are working to (re)introduce a taxation system built on the same ideas of the rich paying for development, if not wholly then at least substantially. Except this time, it is not because of benevolence but because of the dominant and staggering wealth inequality and insane accumulation of wealth by the few people who managed to hack the capitalist system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we go further exploring this idea of taxing the rich, we need to understand who exactly do we mean when we talk about the rich. The answer is simply the super rich who account for more that 70% of a particular country’s wealth and assets. Which surprisingly, or not if you’ve ever studied about wealth distribution, is less than 2% of the population of any country. For example, in America the super rich are 0.5% of the population, while in India they are 1% of the population. This means people like Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and Beyonce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping this in mind, Elizabeth Warren proposed the ‘wealth tax’ which if implemented would tax as little as 2-4% of the wealth above a fixed point. Walking along a similar line, demands for wealth tax are being raised in countries like India, South Africa and Argentina. The International Monetary Fund (IMF) also recommended considering the wealth tax especially after the financial crunch that all countries are facing due to COVID-19. This pandemic has revealed the crumbling structure of public healthcare and services. Additionally, countries would require massive influx to be able to survive and then recover from this pandemic. Furthermore, the overall population demographic is changing and increasing exponentially, hence, the cost of basic necessary services like healthcare, education and housing is skyrocketing, and considering the wealth inequality and poverty rates, a huge majority of the population won’t be able to afford them if the government does not subsidise them, if not make them completely free. And the one possible way for any and all governments to do this is through tax revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, governments can tax income, consumption or wealth. Most countries tax only the first two, in essence, the income you earn through income tax and consumption of goods and services through sales tax, service tax, value added tax and GST etc. However, this is pretty unfair because according to studies conducted by prominent think tanks like Brookings Institution, the lower income group spend more on day-to-day items as compared to the rich; consequently, they bear the brunt of consumption tax far more than the rich, furthering the divide between rich and poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason why wealth tax is a good idea because the people who belong to the category of the super rich, have earned that money not primarily because of hard work, but because of exploiting systems, institutions and people for their benefit. Take Amazon owner Jeff Bezos for example; he became the richest man on earth by predatory pricing and exploiting his workers without paying the basic wages for overtime work. Hence, it makes sense for people who have benefitted from society and the people to give back to the same people and institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant point of conjecture is whether the wealth tax is enough? And whether it would change anything? And the answer is yes. According to Vox, had Elizabeth Warren’s proposed wealth tax been implemented, the collected tax revenue would have been sufficient to pay for public college three times over, all food assistance programs two times over and reduce poverty by 60%, and that is only for America. One can only imagine the extent towards which public services can be improved and poverty reduced if wealth tax was collected along with the usual tax revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only reason why countries and governments shy away from the idea of wealth tax is that they are controlled and dependent upon these super rich people. Their wealth is proportional to the power and sway they hold with the authorities. And the reason why many people don’t demand and argue for the same is because we live in a world that is shrouded by the farcical garb of productivity, where people believe that cheaper or free public services makes people lazy and incompetent instead of the idea that basic healthcare and education is a fundamental right that every individual deserves regardless of their &lt;em&gt;productivity and contribution&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this belief is not carried to the post pandemic world. COVID-19 has made us all painfully aware of the deficiencies in the existing system and structures. The fact that we need to change our priorities is inevitable, the awareness of the privilege of wealth and overwhelming wealth disparities is apparent and one can only hope that this awareness brings forth a change towards a kinder and more benevolent world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Ancient Greece was known for its military, culture, architecture and many important contributions to science, philosophy and astronomy. However, what was ignored under the discoveries of Pythagoras (yes, that triangle guy) and Plato was its innovative and frankly very sly system of taxation, which could be attributed to the beauty of the liturgy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Longer Forgotten</title><link href="/No-Longer-Forgotten" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Longer Forgotten" /><published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/No-Longer-Forgotten</id><content type="html" xml:base="/No-Longer-Forgotten">&lt;p&gt;Despite witnessing one of the bloodiest wars and being the only region in the world divided by the Cold War, the Korean Peninsula and its history, until recently, has failed to make its way into the mainstream. It’s only in the last 20 years that the peninsula has gained the world’s attention: the notorious Northern part has become infamous for its nuclear weapons while the South is taking over the world with its Hallyu wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 36 years of the ruthless Japanese colonisation, the Korean Peninsula was liberated on August 15, 1945. It was a joyous occasion for the peninsula, for the Koreans were now independent, and the pain and humiliation of the Japanese invasion were over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Second World War ended and Japan surrendered, the Korean peninsula fell into the hands of the winners of the World War, i.e. the Allied powers. While the Soviet Union spread its communist propaganda in the North, the US vouched for democracy in the South. The peninsula was divided along the 38th parallel in 1948 due to these ideological differences, forming two nations, the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK) in the North and the Republic of Korea (ROK) in the South. For the rest of the world, they might be North and South Korea, but both believe they are the only legitimate Korea. Initially, blessed with more heavy industries, the communist DPRK’s economy rose, while the South struggled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next two years, North and South Korea were heavily militarised with the help of the Soviet Union and the US, respectively. While the US and the Soviet Union had been regarded as key reasons in the peninsula’s division, the military troops acted as deterrents and prevented war between the two Koreas. However, as the troops started withdrawing, it left the Koreas on their own, making the prospects of war more imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 1950, North Korea invaded South Korea swiftly overtaking much of the country. The South Korean army was unprepared and inadequately equipped to face a sudden attack. In September, however, the UN force, led by the US, launched a counter-attack and advanced into the North. China, then, sent in troops to aid the North, shifting the balance of the war. In 1953, the fighting ended with an armistice that approximately restored the original boundaries between North and South Korea. This armistice inaugurated an official ceasefire but did not lead to a peace treaty, and so, the two are still at a cold war against each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the war, a buffer zone called the demilitarised zone (DMZ) was set up along the 38th parallel to prevent another war from taking place and to prevent people from reuniting or escaping. Since the war didn’t end officially, the US kept its bases in South Korea and there are about 23,500 personnel stationed there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//north-south-korea-divide.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peninsula that was once ‘one’ was now divided on ideological differences. In the years after the war, the two Koreas competed for legitimacy and international recognition abroad. DPRK and ROK continued to view each other as potential threats and propaganda against each other was rampant in the peninsula. The inter-Korean relations, however, worsened with the increasing provocations by the North. In 1968, North Korean commandos attacked the South Korean Blue House. In 1976, North Korean soldiers killed two US Army officers in the truce village of Panmunjom. Later, in 1987, two North Koreans bombed a Korean airliner carrying over 100 passengers to hinder the 1988 Olympic Games that were scheduled to be held in Seoul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South Korea’s first democratically elected President, Roh Tae-woo launched a diplomatic initiative known as ‘Nordpolitik’, proposing the development of a ‘Korean Community’. As part of the policy, South Korea established diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union and China. Additionally, it led to direct inter-Korean trade and started inter-Korean sports exchanges. In 1991, both countries signed the Agreement on Reconciliation, Non-Aggression, Exchanges, and Cooperation and the Joint Declaration of the Denuclearisation of the Korean Peninsula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1998, the ‘Sunshine Policy’, or as it is formally known, the ‘Comprehensive Engagement Policy towards North Korea’ was announced by the then President of South Korea, Rho Moo-hyun. The policy aimed at loosening containment on North Korea, embracing North Korea, and eventually making the North Korean government denuclearise itself. The objectives of the Sunshine Policy were more specific and substantial than any of the previous policies towards North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sunshine Policy prompted a reduction of military tension and improved inter-Korean relations. It led to increased economic and cultural interactions between not only the leaders but also the people. These regular interactions created a sense of safety and stability in the Korean peninsula and rekindled the prospect of unification. The policy also led to the spread of South Korea’s soft power in North Korea, shaking their faith in their communist government. South Korean Choco Pies and Dramas spread like wildfire, and people started getting and consuming these illegally. Soon it started changing the way North Koreans viewed South Korea as they realised that the South wasn’t the poor, struggling country their leaders had them believe. Instead, they were the ones living in a poor, struggling country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of the policy, a breakthrough in the inter-Korean relations came at the start of the century with the first Inter-Korean Summit of 2000 as the leaders of both countries met in Pyongyang (capital of North Korea). The summit resulted in a joint peace declaration, with Kim Jong-Il and Kim Dae-Jung agreeing to promote unification and humanitarian and economic cooperation. The meeting resulted in a series of reunions of families separated by the Korean War, as well as a joint factory park in the North’s border town of Kaesong in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy, however, was riddled with criticism. Despite its benefits, the policy failed to change North Korea’s behaviour. Many accuse the policy not only of being ineffectual but also immoral, giving North Korea access to money to develop nuclear weapons, instead of the humanitarian purpose it was supposed to serve. Some conservatives believed that the policy weakened the US-South Korea alliance. By continuing to help the North with financial aid even after 9/11, South Korea offended the US, which had placed North Korea on its ‘Axis of Evil.’ This stopped the ROK-US relations from advancing further, thus, blocking the South Korean economy’s potential to grow during the early 2000’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, North Korea conducted its first nuclear test and with the worsening international sentiment towards North Korea, the South decided to hold an inter-Korean summit. This led to the second meeting in 2007 between President Roh Moo-hyun of the Republic of Korea and Kim Jong-il of the DPRK, in Pyongyang. The summit culminated in an eight-point agreement as the two leaders pledged to promote and expand joint economic, military and family reunion projects. The declaration also expressed its willingness to replace the existing armistice agreement with a permanent peace regime. But the agreement didn’t lead to concrete results as the North continued to carry out a series of nuclear and missile tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lee Myung-bak’s presidency (2008-13) heralded a major change in inter-Korean relations as he decided to abandon the Sunshine policy (in 2010) and take a more hard-line stance against the North. Upon taking office, the Lee administration curtailed aid to the North. As a result of the shooting of a South Korean tourist in a restricted zone of Mt Geumgang in 2008, they ordered a suspension of tourism in the area. Inter-Korean relations continued to deteriorate in 2009, with North Korea nullifying the past inter-Korean agreements. South Korea retaliated by condemning nuclear and missile tests by the North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tension between the two remained high as North Korea attacked South Korea almost 20 times post the attack in 2009. Peace in the Korean Peninsula seemed impossible to reach in the following years and it was only in 2018 that the situation took a turn for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As South Korean President Moon Jae-In revived the Sunshine Policy in 2017, North Korean leader Kim Jong-Un proposed to send a delegation to the upcoming Winter Olympics in South Korea in his New Year address for 2018. This olive branch led to the Seoul-Pyongyang hotline being reopened, a K-pop concert in North Korea, and propaganda no longer being broadcasted on both sides. At the Winter Olympics, North and South Korea marched together in the opening ceremony and fielded a united women’s ice hockey team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 27, 2018, North Korean leader Kim Jong-Un met with South Korean President Moon Jae-In in the Demilitarised Zone at Panmunjom. It was a historical moment as this summit marked the first time a North Korean leader entered South Korean territory since the Korean War. Their discussions centred on the denuclearisation of the Korean peninsula and a peace settlement. The summit ended with both countries pledging to work towards complete denuclearisation of the Korean Peninsula and to declare an official end to the Korean War within a year. Moon and Kim also pledged to reconnect east and west coast roads and railroad tracks and reopen the inter-Korean Kaesong Industrial Complex (KIC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, many US and ROK experts are sceptical because North Korea didn’t disclose the composition and/or size of its nuclear material or warhead stocks and facilities. They also didn’t agree upon what constitutes ‘denuclearisation’, nor did they agree upon a timeline or verification measures for dismantlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post the summit, North Korea adjusted its time zone to match the South’s, and South and North Korea fully restored their military communication line on the Western part of the peninsula. In November 2018, a South Korean train crossed the DMZ border with North Korea marking the first time a South Korean train entered North Korean territory since 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny Town, the assistant director of the US-Korea Institute at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, explained North Korea’s behaviour by saying, “Kim Jong-un is trying to repair the relations that have deteriorated over the last few years while they developed nuclear weapons.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2019, South Korea’s President, Moon Jae-In vowed to achieve the unification of the Korean peninsula by 2045, a century after the liberation of the peninsula. However, despite the proclamations and friendly summits, reunification seems a distant dream. DPRK has given a formal commitment to unification, but it likely does not want unity. Reunification would come at the cost of NK’s demise, with the North Korean elite being implicated in human rights abuses and corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural gap between the two countries has been widening, and a cultural shock and unrest for North Koreans would be inevitable. Like any other developed capitalist country, South Korea is fast-paced and fosters a competitive environment. South Korea is also a highly globalised country with English being used by many. North Korea, on the other hand, is a poor isolated country, where food has been scarce and praising the Supreme Leader has been abundant. North Korean defectors have historically struggled to assimilate. They usually suffer from depression and cannot find work, leading to a few of them returning to the North. On a nation-wide level, it will become more difficult to balance out these differences and to allow for assimilation of the two cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of such differences, people don’t identify with each other despite being ’Koreans’. The older people, who’ve grown up in the peak of ‘the sunshine era’, support reunification in a more historical and humanitarian context. The younger, who grew up in the more conservative era have grown indifferent to their ‘brothers’. According to a 2017 survey conducted by the Korean Institute for National Unification, 14% of South Koreans in their 20s, and around 63% over-50, wanted reunification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are economic problems to consider too in this ordeal. DPRK’s GDP is less than 1% of ROK, which is the world’s 11th biggest economy. The South Korean population believes their hands are already full of domestic problems of unemployment among the youth, an ageing population, sluggish growth, and corruption scandals involving the nation’s highest office to take an additional burden of absorbing the North Korean economy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the nuclear program deters South Korea and American intervention. DPRK, a small, half-country, built these elite weapons for the sole purpose of standing tall against its enemies and routinely asserts that the United States pursues a ‘hostile policy’ towards it. In 2018, Kim Jong-un stated that he would abandon his nuclear weapons only if the US agreed to formally end the Korean War and promised not to invade his country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea’s marriage of convenience with China acts as another hurdle in unification. American influence has been increasing in East Asia over the past few years, with North Korea remaining the only country that hasn’t succumbed to the US yet. Unification of the Korean Peninsula would lead to a further increase in the US’ influence in the region. Until, however, China changes its threat evaluation of the US, North Korea is relatively secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the North Korean commoners, however, reunification remains the only hope for access to a better life. The only other way is by risking their lives and crossing the border, thus, defecting. While the rich and elite enjoy the current state, it’s the people belonging to lower classes who want this unification, especially the youth. With the growing access to South Korean and Chinese media, they are becoming more cognizant of the opportunities that lie outside of the DPRK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, on May 3, 2020, North and South Korea exchanged gunfire around the South’s guard post. Despite the South Korean military believing the gunshots by North Korea to be accidental, it is still unclear if that is the case or if a bigger strategy is at play post-Kim Jong-Un’s much-awaited appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, a deescalation of military troops from the demilitarised line and nuclear weapons from both sides would be a prerequisite for any peace talks to take place. This, however, is just the starting point. The road to unification is long. The gap between the two sides would need to be balanced out by exposing the people to each other’s cultures and lifestyles gradually. Nevertheless, unification is becoming necessary with each passing day as North Korea continues to control the rights and lives of its people. It is important to do it sooner rather than later, for the gap between the countries will only widen, increasing the cost of unification and making the South Koreans believe it to be unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Despite witnessing one of the bloodiest wars and being the only region in the world divided by the Cold War, the Korean Peninsula and its history, until recently, has failed to make its way into the mainstream. It’s only in the last 20 years that the peninsula has gained the world’s attention: the notorious Northern part has become infamous for its nuclear weapons while the South is taking over the world with its Hallyu wave.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India’s Tryst with Autocracy</title><link href="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India's Tryst with Autocracy" /><published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence">&lt;p&gt;It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the declaration of a national emergency in mid-1975, in accordance with Article 352 of the Indian Constitution, Mrs Gandhi instigated the nation’s total suspension of fundamental rights and every outlet of democratic expression. The Indian Emergency refers to the 21-month period that continues to be recounted as one of the darkest chapters in the modern political historiography of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What led to the imposition of the Indian Emergency?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency shouldn’t be considered an overnight development, but rather a culmination of a significant number of factors. Throughout the end of the 1960’s and the early 1970’s, there had been a gradual rise in the predominance of Parliamentary Sovereignty in India over the judiciary. Besides this, the early 1970’s had been characterised by widespread political unrest. The Naxalbari movement in West Bengal had met with severe state oppression through ‘The Operation Steeplechase’ among other government measures, the Nav Nirman movement in Gujarat (December 1973 - March 1974) led to the imposition of Central Government-rule on the state under Article 356 of the Indian Constitution. Amidst the prevailing political turmoil, there had been widespread dissatisfaction against the agents of the ruling order, particularly the Union Ministers, who are in many ways the most direct representatives of the ruling regime. Lalit Narayan Mishra, the Union Rail Minister was killed by a bomb on January 3, 1975.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most significant political mobilisation took place in April 1974, when a student agitation by the Chatra Sangharsh Samiti (Student Agitation Organisation) led by the Gandhian Socialist Jayaprakash Narayan and his call for “total revolution” to sweep away corruption, gained mass popularity. A significant ramification of the JP movement had been the nationwide strike organised by the railway employees union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raj Narain verdict had been the final nail in the coffin of the Indira Gandhi government which had been in power since 1966, almost 10 years. Mrs Gandhi had defeated Raj Narain in the 1971 Parliamentary elections from the constituency of Rae Bareily. He had filed cases accusing the Prime Minister of election fraud and malpractice along with the use of state machinery for election purposes in the Allahabad High Court. On June 12, 1975, Mr Justice Jagmohan Lal Sinha found Mrs Gandhi guilty of the said charges. The Supreme Court upheld the verdict and ordered a steady withdrawal of all privileges that Mrs Gandhi had received as a member of the Indian Parliament whilst depriving her of the right to vote in the lower house. The following day Narain had organised a rally in Delhi where he had reportedly proclaimed that the instruments of the state machinery, particularly the police, must reject the orders of a government which were immoral, corrupt and unethical. Widely interpreted as an instigation to spark a rebellion, it led to Mrs Gandhi declaring the Emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency was marked by an absolute suspension of the Fundamental Rights mentioned in Part III of the Indian Constitution. Mrs Gandhi had devised a ‘25-point economic programme’ which aimed at, inter alia, poverty eradication, restructuring of the public services, boosting agricultural and industrial production. Mrs Gandhi’s heir apparent and a leader of the Indian National Congress, Sanjay Gandhi, had contributed to it with his own programme of literacy, family planning, planting of trees, literacy promotion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Emergency, the opposition leaders were placed under preventive detention including Jayaprakash Narayan, Charan Singh and Atal Vihari Vajpayee (later Indian Prime Minister in 1997), Lal Krishna Advani, Arun Jaitley, Gayatri Devi, Queen Mother of the erstwhile princely state of Jaipur, Morarji Desai (later 4th Prime Minister of India in 1977-1979). Some prominent leaders of the Indian National Congress including Chandra Sekhar, who had resigned from Mrs Gandhi’s cabinet, were arrested and placed under detention as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, the 42nd Amendment Act which had rewritten the Indian Constitution was also passed. The amendments so introduced sought to reduce the power of the Supreme Court and the High Courts all over the nation, and inserted the words ‘Socialist’ and ‘Secular’ to the preamble of the Constitution. Under this amendment act, the Indian Parliament was bestowed with unlimited, unrestrained power to amend each and every section of the Constitution without judicial review. Thus, the doctrine of separation of powers and the Indian federal structure was negated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forced sterilisation program, undertaken under the leadership of Sanjay Gandhi with the aim of family planning, led to 8.3 million sterilisations within the time frame of 1976-1977 according to &lt;em&gt;India’s Population Reality: Reconciling Change and Tradition&lt;/em&gt;. The primary accounts of the brutality are evident in The Sanjay Story by an eminent Indian political journalist when he recounts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hawa Singh, a widower from the village of Pipli had been taken from a bus against his will and sterilised. The infection that emanated from the vasectomy took his life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government used Doordarshan, the government-owned television network, for its own political propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Turkman Gate demolition and firing which took place on April 18, 1976, a fallout of the drive to clear slum areas in Delhi, resulted in indiscriminate firing and police brutalities, which the popular media wasn’t permitted to report. Unofficial accounts put the figure at 9 deaths from among the ones who resisted the usurpation and bulldozing of their settlements. Later, the Shah Commission report stated that 20 individuals had been killed. The censorship of the press had begun from the night of the declaration of the Emergency itself with the electric supply of Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg being cut off, within 3 hours of the announcement. Most of the publishing houses of newspapers and national magazines were located on the same street. A number of newspapers had published a blank page or a black space in its editorials as an attempt to convey that the news had been tampered with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 18, 1977, Mrs Gandhi called for fresh elections followed by the release of all political prisoners. The Indian Emergency ended on March 23, 1977. The Congress was routed in the General Elections with Janta Dal assuming power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is that one thing about Indira’s India of 1975, inhabited by my grandfather’s generation that resonates with a world so different from ours, 45 years later, in a post-privatisation, liberal democracy? Surprisingly the answer doesn’t take a minute longer to appear so clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amnesty International in 2015 had stated that there was a “total blackout of information” in the state of Chattisgarh. And today, a complete shutting down of information transmission from Kashmir has continued for more than 5 months with major leaders of the state being placed under preventive detention. The idea of placing government loyalists to moot out majority opposition parties from power in the states finds uncanny parallels: Gandhi dismissed the Ajoy Mukherjee-led government in West Bengal in 1969 while Modi used Governors as loyalists to deny the single-largest party to come to power in Manipur, Nagaland and Meghalaya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Gandhi’s Emergency declaration was approved by her Cabinet only after its imposition. Similarly, Modi’s implementation of the demonetisation was known only to a handful in the Cabinet prior to its formal declaration. Additionally, Modi’s appointment of Army Chief Bipin Rawat, superseding two senior officers is reminiscent of Gandhi’s appointment of Mr Justice A N Ray as Chief Justice of India by superseding three others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signs are clear and “those who do not learn from history are doomed to repeat it”. The Indian Emergency only grows in importance during our times to educate us on how a state can go from mere political upheaval to an authoritarian regime.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Test of the West III</title><link href="/The-Test-of-the-West-III" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Test of the West III" /><published>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Test-of-the-West-III</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Test-of-the-West-III">&lt;p&gt;This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-I&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-II&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-III&quot;&gt;III&lt;/a&gt;). The third chapter is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 3—Final thoughts on cultural evolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John, you made very interesting points and I really like the way you recorded the history of postmodern ideas that are now poisoning the West. I recently became aware of an extremely interesting philosopher and theorist called Ken Wilber and I have to say that I really find his work fascinating. His ideas were influenced by people like the developmental psychologist Piaget, and his Integral Theory fits in what you said in the last paragraph about moving forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His Integral Theory was that ‘a system’ like culture requires two things if it hopes to move forward and to progress. First, is transcendence, and by that, he meant an update from the old culture, though the second principle is ‘to include’ the previous culture. So the model goes something like this: In order for culture to progress and to prevent it from fragmentation, it needs to transcend and include the previous culture. In practicality, this means that some ideas of the past will be rejected and some new ones will be inserted. However, a new system must include the previous ones, because otherwise, you get a culture war, where people’s first principles are widely different. This is where we are right now as postmodern culture is acting like the Freudian superego, repressing the previous cultures that came before it. This produces nothing but polarisation, cultural fragmentation and a serious suspension of progress, or perhaps even a move towards regression. However, as Integral Theory suggests, we are also to be grateful for some postmodern ideas such as ‘diversity and inclusion’, not in the sense of what it means now but merely in our change of attitude towards ‘those who are not like us’ to feel included. The fact that there is less hatred for these groups is also something that the postmodern movement has contributed to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I could not agree with you more on your comments on how to move forward. I also think that the spoken truth (the logos) is the antidote to this chaos, hence why I am in the process of creating a youtube channel for Oxford Students to come forward and speak their minds. Equally, your emphasis on the interconnectivity of the self with the past is very insightful. When we read the great works of the past, we are, in a sense, resurrecting the souls of those who came before us and shaped who we are today. And, this is, I think, extremely important as if we do not know ‘them’, we do not know ‘ourselves’, and if we ignore what they had to say, we end up in this empty and materialistic universe where the self is no more than consciousness due to chemicals reacting in our brains. And, what replaces our sense of self is the product of this technological environment where consciousness and Instagram are in an unholy union. We have, in essence, given up our true essence and the ground of our being for the sake of pleasure which only produces dopamine and leaves us in an empty state of inertia and meaninglessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as a note to finish this enjoyable dialogue, what is your view for the next ten to twenty years; will we be able to redeem ourselves or are we headed for disaster? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with the notions of Ken Wilber in that they remind me of how McLuhan spoke of culture. He would say that as we move forward in time we often retrieve ideas from different periods. There have been several cycles in which ‘classical’ ideas have been brought back to light the way forward. I am thinking for example of Werner Heisenberg, winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics, who stated “some statements of ancient philosophy are rather near to those of modern science.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important news for us who have seen the many problems with postmodernism, particularly its complete abandonment of transcendence, in favour of subjectivism—full stop.  The past is ‘still here’ and just as brilliant as before. Important ideas are not made obsolete by the mistaken notions that the present must be better than the past and that we must be wiser than those who have gone before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally I believe the way forward is by adopting some of the medieval courage to consider all ideas as worthy of examination, not just the ones we have been told are politically correct. We might also benefit from the medieval notion that we are pilgrims upon the earth not masters and power seekers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there is a bizarre hubris in those who think a new system of ideas is possible without including the leading insights of the past. Clearly, thinkers of the pedigree of Werner Heisenberg, are stating as much in their reflections on, for example, advanced science. There is no law that says that as we move forward in time the quality of our thinking gets better. McLuhan and others called this out long ago. He suggested we look at history as a collective consciousness, a mosaic made up of different independent notions which also combine into a kind of whole. And there is the warning that those who ignore history are condemned to repeat it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the next ten to twenty years, we need to go in the opposite direction to the ‘exclusive humanism’ and ‘immanentism’ of many in academia. We must humbly hold up the value of being pilgrims not masters—of listening to those who accept reality as it is rather than those who think reality can be magically constructed based on our desires and dreams. We need to challenge the obscurantism of those who claim questions about the ultimate meaning of it all cannot be answered, and should never be taken seriously. We need to champion the civilising structures that have been the great gifts to humanity, and acknowledge their spiritual roots, without lapsing into psychologism or sociological whimsy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been noted how philosopher-theologians like Bernard Lonergan “showed how the methods of modern empirical science - once stripped of their extra- scientific assumptions of exclusive humanism and naturalism - imply an open-ended, non reductive, emerging universe which integrates the natural and human domains and is dynamically oriented to a transcendent reality beyond it.”  (Michael McCarthy)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either we think of ourselves as icons reflecting a deeper light and truth than we can fathom, or we succumb to some idol or other, trying to convince ourselves of some half-truth that hollows rather than hallows our deepest yearnings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an authentic self-examination and self-appropriation, why not look at our talents and gifts, not as ‘subjective’ traits, but as ontologically necessary for making life to be what it is meant to be? In the depths of our hearts, is there not a still small voice, pointing to all the transcendent realities that we hope are true, and can we find the voice to make them real - here, now, and forever? &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Omidvar</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (I,II and III). The third chapter is as follows:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Test of the West II</title><link href="/The-Test-of-the-West-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Test of the West II" /><published>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Test-of-the-West-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Test-of-the-West-II">&lt;p&gt;This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-I&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-II&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-III&quot;&gt;III&lt;/a&gt;). The second chapter is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 2—the solution to the excessive chaos of post-modern ideas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My theology and spirituality has a lot to do with the Jesuit notion that God is directly accessible to consciousness, but we have to learn discernment - a practice involving all of our conscious agencies: feelings, imaginings, reasoning and mystical encounter to experience God’s personal call in one’s life. We all have a call, a purpose that unfolds, no matter what life brings us, good things or bad. You might think that your study habits brought you to university, but the spirit played a role as well. A Higher Power, a grace deeper than the conceptual, but integrative with thought and reason. The secular night-life, on the other hand, will leave you bored and drained, what the mystics call ‘desolation’. But where the Spirit leads you will produce the opposite effect—joy, rather than pleasure—what they call consolation. So, as a practical matter, be a pilgrim rather than a tourist. Visit sacred places: the Taize and L’ Arche communities in England and on the continent. The great cathedrals and monastic centres. Wherever you feel the deeper promptings. Discern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your description of the postmoderns sucking the life out of people is deeply insightful. They are psychologists not philosophers and they don’t even understand psychology all that well. Sartre’s “hell is other people’’ is based on his own narcissism in my view.  Here is freedom without responsibility to anything other than self. When he wrote &lt;em&gt;Existentialism as a Humanism&lt;/em&gt;, there was something of the grandeur of the human. But without something other to engage with, one is thrown back on self-gazing. No wonder there are so many ‘flaneurs’ in France!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here is where spirituality comes in. My view is that absence of God produces self-hatred. Closed in on the self, post-moderns claim this is some kind of virtue. So, individuals try desperately to attain the unattainable, falling into intellectual despair. I saw your video with your philosophy teacher who kept saying “probably there is no God”. But if that is the case, why go on repeating the phrase? I am sure that many bright people who were taken over by fundamentalism, need this revolt to regain their sanity. But revolt is just the first step. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thinking about writing a paper to be called ‘Human beings: animals or icons?’ Sartre was unconsciously projecting his inner ‘hell’ onto others – hating others because he hated himself. God is what first produces self-love. It can be a struggle but I see myself as an icon reflecting transcendent beauty, and I come to see this in others, in nature, etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christian philosophers look at revelation and then see how philosophy helps deepen our understanding of the notions given in the revelation. If you want a good text, look at Joseph Owens, &lt;em&gt;An Elementary Christian Metaphysics.&lt;/em&gt; He is from the generation that read ALL the relevant sources and can summarise them with authority and depth. So, I would encourage you to turn from reading the “flavour of the month”  (Nietzsche and friends) and find the real scholars. If anybody at Oxford is offering a course or talk on Aristotle’s metaphysics, check it out. Also, see if there is a Lonergan Centre there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In later scribs I can show you the philosophical problems that come from Descartes, Hume and Kant and why their false understanding of the self helped bring us to where we are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of discernment is very interesting, and I would like to think about it practically for the sake of it being an accessible argument for those who are not part of any community of faith. And your analysis very much reminds me of Jung’s idea of circumambulation. Indeed, this idea describes that during a person’s lifetime, there are individual meaningful phenomena that occur that points one to a fraction of his destination or ‘Being’ and the sum total of a set of significant experiences could lead one to pursue a certain path in life towards the completion of their ‘Telos’. I think your very insightful notion of discernment can be shown practically and without the requirement of any sort of faith. In short, one needs to become aware of his experiences, and also to become a master of his own self, if that person is to attain anything approximating his Telos. And the tool that allows you to become fully aware and deeply conscious of your experiences; that enables you to understand why they are happening to you, as well as that which frees you from the shackles of your own misapprehensions is discernment. And indeed, one needs a source of divine inspiration (literal or metaphorical) or divine sense of direction to discover one’s own deep Telos whilst becoming strong enough spiritually and mentally to move towards the completion of one’s essence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your comments on the postmodern thinkers; that they have created or at least strongly influenced the current narcissistic culture is something I strongly agree with. So far, the student committee at Oxford has tried their best to impose their ideologies onto us in the most aggressive and reprehensible manner, including a compulsory workshop on ‘Consent’ and a compulsory talk on Diversity and Inclusion which included doctrines such as micro-aggression and cultural appropriation. The very fact that they were compulsory signals to me a disease that far exceeds the narcissism of the typical kind because, to begin with, they presented their ideologies as facts and explained that anything contrary to these beliefs is morally abhorrent and will be met with consequences. So it is not only that they are narcissistic for using this sort of activism to feel virtuous or good about themselves, but that we also must do this too if we are not to be identified as the ‘other’, the unknown that lurks in the background and is nothing but a reprehensive and morally repugnant being. An important caveat is that this is not unique to this wonderful university with its rich history and amazing education but that this post-modern, resentful and tribal culture has infiltrated deeply the collective unconscious soul of the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your comment that “Sartre was unconsciously projecting his inner “hell” onto others—hating others because he hated himself” is extremely insightful. This is similar to the sort of idea that you read into situations your own toxic ideas or experiences. Why? I believe the feeling of having the upper moral hand is overwhelmingly motivating and Nietzsche’s notion of resentment is also a strong possibility; that people hate those who are better than them along any dimensions (e.g. economic, social relations and status). Moreover, finding an enemy seems very much convenient as a tool to escape responsibility, but even stronger than all motivations is the one that seeks to demolish all that is noble and beautiful as an act of revenge that is morally justifiable (from their eyes) and perhaps even virtuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last section of this dialogue, can you put forward your analysis of the philosophical problems that come from Descartes, Hume and Kant and why their false understanding of the Self helped bring us to where we are today? I also think a good way to end this dialogue is to provide a practical solution to this desolated and resentful culture that is filled with narcissism, nihilism and nothing beautiful or transcendent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John A Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Alex for your reflections. I want to begin by agreeing with you about the philosophical aspects of discernment. Consciousness, and I am speaking about particular or existential consciousness, is caught up with history. All of us know our lives will end, and so we are constantly in touch with the “arc of one’s own life”. Beginning with Socrates, we have a well thought out record of what one must do with this knowledge. The Greeks, and I am thinking of Socrates, Plato and Aristotle, point to the ethical as a conscious response to this awareness of human finitude. But ethics is understood from the angle of metaphysics. These thinkers argued that our self-knowledge, and indeed our scientific knowledge is ‘going somewhere’. No need to put a lot of religious names to it. They left us with an insight. They knew that the study of the physical world is a study of mechanisms, but there was an intuitional sense that the explanation of all these mechanisms, can’t be more mechanisms. For Aristotle, the summit of meaning for humans is contemplation. This contemplation is a ‘habit of thought’ for those who practice it. This ‘habit’ is grounded in the desire of consciousness to go beyond itself. It is intuitional but not outside the intellectual activities of rational knowers. A modern Aristotelian, Andrew Beards, points to the multiple referentiality of thinking that forces us to consider some “whole” for which all this complexity tends. Metaphysics is the wisdom which develops in the pursuit of the whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the backdrop for understanding modern philosophy, and the turn to the Self that begins with Descartes and continues to challenge us today. Descartes claimed that the intuition to go beyond the self which founded Western philosophy should not be trusted. Ironically he substituted a subjectivist intuition for a realist/existential one. His intuition came from the clean lines and unambiguous concepts of geometry. However his notion of clear and distinct ideas is neither clear nor distinct. Even if I were to concede that some ideas are clearer, better, more rational than others, why should I insist that such things can prove anything about those ideas that are neither clear nor distinct? Werner Heisenberg won a Nobel Prize for proving that the foundations of the material universe are not at all clear and distinct notions; and he explains that the ‘Uncertainty Principle’ had much in common with Aristotle’s notion of ‘substantial principle’, which is both actually existing and potentially something more than it appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hume is equally captivated by intuitions leading to a similar dead-end as Descartes. Perhaps the self is being controlled by cleverly constructed fictions like causality, confused notions that are psychologically grounded but not rationally defensible. I simply have a ‘feeling’ that A causes B, but this is not ‘because’ of knowledge of the material world. But we can level the same criticism here as applies to Descartes, namely, why should the ‘feeling’ that I can’t know causality be more reliable than the scientific knowledge that comes from studying the reasons behind things and their behaviour? Why is this psychological intuition more reliable than the reasons offered for saying ‘smoking causes cancer’? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Hume and Kant claim that they have knowledge based on rational argument. But rational argument is based on the notion of something following from something else. And it is through judgement that we know when such connections are justified and when they are not. Hume is using the idea that something follows from something else to discredit causality (the idea that something follows from something else). Kant is claiming that we have no real knowledge beyond appearance, but this is a self-contradiction. It amounts to saying: a) All knowledge is appearance. b) Knowledge of ‘a’ is not appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, post-moderns have their own set of ‘intuitions’ that they see as somehow self-evident. Their focus on language as ultimately subjective is based on the mistake of taking a tool for studying reality, to constitute reality. I can use language to structure reality but only because I am not structured by it. Language is a tool, nothing more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joseph Owens in &lt;em&gt;An Elementary Christian Metaphysics&lt;/em&gt; points out that phenomenological studies of consciousness (forms of “know thyself”) are the source and substance of philosophy, but many phenomenologies choose to ignore one of the phenomenological givens that cannot be ignored for long—EXISTENCE. When I study the apple on my desk and attend to the course of thoughts and perceptions in this conscious activity, one very clear intuition is EXISTENCE. This apple is not just a mass of subjective impressions; actual existence is one of the biggest impressions of the exercise. It cannot be bracketed because ‘to be’ is irreducible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a practical programme for going forward, one needs to become involved in curriculum development. The ‘telos’ for all conscious activities should be ‘truth’. But truth is a historically motivated study. Curriculum must return to the historical component of self-knowledge. Humans need to re-assert the value of knowing how we have come to the place where we are today. This involves truth-telling, the vocation of ‘the witness’. The great error of the philosophers that I have criticised is their complete abandonment of history. They have taken the Self to be a non-historical psychological entity without any ontological significance. As Gabriel Marcel noted, &lt;em&gt;“Thought far from being a relation with itself, is on the contrary essentially a self-transcendence.”&lt;/em&gt; There is more to existence than self. This fundamental intuition is the foundation of human beings. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Omidvar</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (I,II and III). The second chapter is as follows:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Test of the West I</title><link href="/The-Test-of-the-West-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Test of the West I" /><published>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Test-of-the-West-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Test-of-the-West-I">&lt;p&gt;This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-I&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-II&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-III&quot;&gt;III&lt;/a&gt;). The first chapter is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter I - the fundamental values of the West&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we first articulate and clearly define the most fundamental principles that the ‘West’ has recently subscribed to? For the sake of this dialogue, we shall speak about trends, as I think culture is a rather complex term made up of various elements. And for this reason, this dialogue I think should focus on major trends and cultural phenomena. So to begin this dialogue, what do you think are those key fundamental principles? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John A Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the ‘West’ has identified freedom as its most essential principle. There are to be few constraints on our individual decisions allowing the individual to choose any set of norms within the law. The philosophical or ethical backdrop for this principle is Utilitarianism, and the implied assumption that no one set of ethical principles is better than any other. There is also the belief that I should be allowed to develop principles out of my own subjectivity because universals do not exist or should be considered “dogma” rather than rationally defensible imperatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, freedom to choose principles around end of life decisions must take precedence over professional principles, which in the past, were seen as important breaks on imbalanced power relationships. A woman may choose to have as many abortions as she desires despite concerns by her physician that harm increases with each procedure. That is, a doctor can lay aside her oath to “do no harm” if a patient requests a procedure that is legal and without restriction. In countries where assisted suicide is legal, medical colleges are tacitly agreeing with the idea that freedom of conscience for professionals cannot override a patient’s reception of a medically assisted death. High court decisions that support such laws base their judgements on three principles : 1) absolute autonomy over self;  2) relativism of personal or professional ethics; 3) the presumed calculus that benefits of such principles and practices outweigh potential harms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with you John that it seems as though individual freedom is the most fundamental principle of the West. And as I see it, individual freedom has many benefits as it keeps the government limited for the advancement of individual sovereignty. However, recently, I also see a negative aspect to freedom. A naive and narcissistic claim that defines freedom as having the ability to do whatever one wants. One need not give examples of this as the current culture screams of such patterns of behaviour such as the so-called sexual freedom that both men and women supposedly enjoy. Similarly, I identify a couple of things as hanging upon our culture. First is the claim for group and individual rights, and second is an overload of postmodern ideas that are simply about ‘deconstruction’ that are taken so dramatically as though we are to take them, ironically, as ‘truths’. And the third fundamental principle is freedom as you identified. However, there seems to be a serious clash between individual freedom (the positive aspect) and the postmodern thinking that sees everything and everyone as motivated by power. So John, can we talk about some of those points that I think are important for this discussion? I would really like to know how you see our culture unravelling in this so-called postmodern era? Also, can we expand a little bit on what I identify as the clash between individual freedom and the post-modern thought such as that of Michel Foucault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the post-modern notion that truth is a cultural construction is the source of the narcissism of the current secular culture. Foucault and Derrida show the problem with objective claims but then use this to discredit much of the history of thought. Imagine a physicist who said we cannot know much with certainty about subatomic particles, so physics is a waste of time. This is blatant arrogance, a form of intellectual hubris where only Foucault and Derrida understand what is really going on. Postmodernism also came into its own on the coat-tails of Freudian psychology whose reduction of meaning to little more than the frustration of erotic instincts is almost humorous for those of us who lived through the last half of the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional cultures never deify instincts or claim that meaning needs to be constructed out of individual sentimentality. Martin Buber notes in &lt;em&gt;Eclipse of God&lt;/em&gt; that the Enlightenment (and post-modern) motif of “deifying instincts instead of hallowing them in faith” is a replay of ancient Gnosticism, the notion that intellectual humility and self-questioning is a kind of naivety. Nietzsche and Marx are also contributors to the grand illusion that the transcendental is an illusion perpetrated to keep people in line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the cultural backdrop for the modern notion of individual freedom. Freedom cannot be expected to be ordered to a specific religious or ethical code because this means denying INSTINCT. But this does not mean we are all petty animals. We can use our instincts to create meaning for ourselves which is genuinely one’s own. And society must not interfere with this marvellous creative process with any appeals to any ‘higher’ principles than those which I create for myself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome is what appears to be a culture so boring that people discuss tattoos but not books or nature, because boredom is what you get when nothing matters but ME, ME, ME. Meaning, real meaning, is only possible when you acknowledge something other than the self. Medieval masons did not read theology, but they built cathedrals out of a sense of profound mystery. Many knew that the work would not be finished in their lifetimes. They sensed that life had a horizontal and a vertical dimension and that holding both in mind made life bearable even in the face of poverty or other challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t agree anymore with your analysis of the intellectual facade of Foucault and Derrida. I am yet to discover why this intellectual discipline is so attractive amongst intellectuals and especially in our universities. Many might not have even read or heard anything about postmodern thinkers but are the partial embodiment of those ideas. For instance, the idea that everything in nature including human intention is motivated by power (in the negative sense) started with Nietzsche originally when he wrote the book &lt;em&gt;Beyond Good and Evil&lt;/em&gt;. His claim was that most philosophers did not have an ‘instinct for knowledge’ but that essentially their philosophy was a tool to further their instinctual interests in some way or the other. And that I think is partly true but the hunger for generalisation is greed. And this idea, as it occurs to me, was expanded by Foucault when he institutionalised it in the political arena while generalising it into every domain of human life. I see this doctrine or ideology as the ‘vampire’ who sucks the life out of things that are noble, beautiful and transcendent. And, as scary as it seems, I do think that this ideology is embodied in many people as I see it acting out in our culture in a way that it is hard not to identify and its role is to ‘deconstruct’ and destroy. Metaphorically, John 10:10 is perfect to demonstrate this: “The thief comes only to steal and kill and destroy; I have come that they may have life, and have it to the full.” And I think all postmodernism as a doctrine and as a cultural phenomenon (important to make the distinction) is concerned with is to steal, kill and destroy while sucking all life out of the beautiful and the transcendent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder as you correctly pointed out that people have deified their instinctual desires as we have metaphorically and literally killed the soul. And in Platonic terms, we have killed the white and noble horse and have enabled the black and ignoble one to fully take over the charioteer. I suppose that our culture has gone a step further and developed the third horse of mirrors. It is a horse of mirrors as all you see is ‘yourself’ and the direction of the charioteer of our culture seems to be under the full control of the horse of mirrors which is even stronger in our world of ‘social media’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, when I am thinking about the clash between the idea of individual freedom and the post-modern thought, what screams at me is that for the postmodernist, there is no individual that is transcendent of his desires and especially the ones associated with power and dominance. And therefore, there cannot be an individual who is free. And this has two important implications. First is that you are always a victim of others or of ideas attempting to take power over you, which I think fully destroys all human relationships as you are constantly under threat. And there is no possibility of a healthy relationship with anyone. And this is, I think, why Simone de Beauvoir and Sartre agreed that their relationship was all about their own self-interests. And, I think, the second implication is that there is no redemption for you as you too are a perpetrator or a potential one as you are not an individual, but a sort of an AI that is coded to achieve a certain self-interested function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have talked about the madness in which we have drained ourselves, John. What do you think is the solution to all this, since people seem to think that this culture has figured it all out? I mean, I am starting university in a few days and what struck me was how much the university used the nightlife culture as a tool to convince students why Oxford is a good place to study. I am not against partying but I see the problem much deeper that there are an enormous amount of other reasons why one should study there and the nightlife should not be something that the University encourages as there are other forms of enjoyment, but what are they? Have we forgotten those? Again, what is the practical and real solution to all these, John?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Omidvar</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (I,II and III). The first chapter is as follows:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Rational Pirates</title><link href="/The-Rational-Pirates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rational Pirates" /><published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Rational-Pirates</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rational-Pirates">&lt;p&gt;So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I would like to share the riddle with you and try to explain the solution and how game theory can help us in various situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good day to be a pirate. Andrew and his 4 mates, Brandon, Christian, David and Edmund have struck gold, a chest with 100 coins. But now, they must divide up the treasure according to the pirate code. The code is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the captain, Andrew gets to propose first about how to distribute the coins. Then, each pirate including Andrew himself gets to vote either ‘yes’ or ‘no’. If the vote passes, or if there is a tie, the coins are divided according to the plan proposed by Andrew, but if the majority votes ‘no’, Andrew must walk the plank into the deep sea and Brandon becomes the captain. Then, Brandon gets to propose a new distribution and all remaining pirates would vote again. If his plan is rejected, he walks the plank too and Christian takes his place. This process repeats with the captain’s hat moving to David and then to Edmund until either a proposal is accepted or there is only one pirate left.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each pirate’s primary objective is to stay alive while getting as much gold as possible. But since they are pirates, none of them trust each other so they can’t really collaborate in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If anyone thinks they will end up with the same amount of gold in two different scenarios, they will vote to make the captain walk the plank just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, each pirate is excellent at logical thinking and knows that the other pirates are too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question here is, what distribution should Andrew propose to make sure he lives and gets as much gold as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we follow our intuition, it seems like Andrew should try to bribe other pirates with most of the gold to increase the chances of his plan being accepted or maybe to propose a distribution like 40-30-20-10-0 or any other combination for that matter and hope for the best, but it turns out Andrew can do much better than that. Let’s have a look at the solution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you know, the pirates know each other to be top-notch logicians. So, when each one votes, they won’t just be thinking about the current proposal but about all the possible outcomes down the line. Moreover, because the rank order is known in advance, each one of them can accurately predict how others would vote in any situation and adjust their own votes accordingly. Since Edmund is last, he has the most outcomes to consider so let us start by following his thought process. He would reason out by working backward from the last possible scenario with only him and David remaining. David would obviously propose to keep all the gold and Edmund’s one vote would not be enough to override it. So, Edmund wants to avoid this situation at all costs. Now, we move to the previous decision point with three pirates left and Christian making the proposal. Everyone knows that if he is outvoted, the decision shifts to David who would then get all the gold while Edmund gets nothing. So to secure Edmund’s vote, Christian only needs to offer slightly more than nothing, that is, one coin. Since this ensures his support, Christian doesn’t need to offer David anything at all. What if there were 4 pirates? As captain, Brandon would still only need one other vote for his plan to pass. He knows that David wouldn’t want the decision to pass to Christian so he would offer David one coin for his support with nothing for Christian or Edmund. Going forward with other possible scenarios, now we’re back at the initial vote with all 5 pirates standing. Having considered all the other scenarios, Andrew knows that if he goes overboard, the decision comes down to Brandon which would be bad news for Christian and Edmund, so he offers one coin each to them, thus, keeping 98 for himself. Brandon and David vote ‘no’, but Christian and Edmund grudgingly vote ‘yes’, knowing that the alternative would be worse for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pirate game involves some amusing concepts from game theory. One is the concept of ‘common knowledge’ where each person is aware of what the others know and uses this to predict their reasoning and final distribution. Had it been the case where the pirates didn’t know the intellectual capabilities of each other, the situation would flip altogether and there would have been no accurate solution to the riddle but fortunately that wasn’t the case. This is a classic example of ‘Nash-equilibrium’, where each player knows every other player’s strategy and chooses them accordingly. Even though it may lead to a worse outcome for everyone than cooperating would, no individual player can benefit by changing their strategy. So, it seems like Andrew gets to keep most of the gold coins (98 to be precise) and the other pirates might need to find better ways to use those impressive logic skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole intention behind this article was to explain to you how a simple concept of game theory can help you gain more in life. The example here was not an appropriate one for you to relate to in real life (unless you obviously decide to become a pirate) but there are several other instances in which it might help you. The decision involving whether to go for a movie or a concert with your friends also involves game theory where we know what the other person wants and we try to manipulate the final result so as to do what we want. Also, in financial markets, the decision to invest in a certain bond or a stock after having all the relevant information about the company involves game theory as well. By investing in the company, you become a player and what the company does with that investment determines your gain or loss. These are just some cases where you can utilise game theory, the scope of it is wide-ranging and unexplored, and left for you to discover. As the British writer Charles Lamb rightly said, “Man is a gaming animal. He must always be trying to get better in something or other.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.</summary></entry></feed>