<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-02-19T16:43:09+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The ‘Generality’ of the Indian Civil Service?</title><link href="/Indian-Civil-Service" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 'Generality' of the Indian Civil Service?" /><published>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Indian-Civil-Service</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Civil-Service">&lt;p&gt;Indian Administrative Service (IAS) is considered the most prestigious of all the civil services in India. It is also the most sought-after service out of the 25 services for which the Indian Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) recruits every year. The attraction towards this service, which is one of the three All India Services, is justified because the service entails many social and economic perks along with the enormous responsibilities. However, only a micro fraction (less than 0.1%) of the candidates that appear for the exam are able to become IAS officers and rest (of the selected candidates) end up in other services. This is where the real problem starts. In what follows, I discuss how the IAS completely dominates the Civil Services in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first posting of an IAS is at the district level in their allotted state cadres as the District Magistrate (DM) holding the rank of Under Secretaries to the Government of India. As DMs, they are practically responsible for every administrative decision in the district. Be it pensions, land-related issues or any other schemes implemented by the state governments, the files are put up and routed through the DM. They are also chairpersons for 70-100 (the precise number varies across the states) odd committees at the district level. It is worth noting that even as the Indian Police Service officers, who also constitute the All India Services, are posted as Superintendent of Police at the district level, so the IAS officers are technically their bosses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes as no surprise to learn that the IPS has to report to the IAS at the district level (and, of course, at other levels too). After their stint as DMs, they go on to get promoted to high-level ranks in the government becoming Joint Secretaries, Additional Secretaries and then eventually Secretaries to the Government of India. According to a petition submitted by Group ‘A’ officers to the 7th Pay Commission, which is an administrative system/mechanism that the government of India set up in 1956 to determine the salaries of government employees, 75% of all the Joint Secretaries, 85% of all Additional Secretaries and Secretaries are IAS officers. Of the 88 Secretaries in various ministries as of February 3, 2020, 69 are from the IAS only, 10 are scientists, 4 are from the IFS (Indian Foreign Service), 2 are from the ILS (Indian Legal Service) and one of each is from the IPS and IPoS (Indian Postal Service).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One never finds an officer from Indian Revenue Service heading the Ministry of Finance; an officer from Indian Economic Service becoming the Governor of the Reserve Bank of India; an Indian Information Service officer heading the Department of Information and Broadcasting; an officer from the IA&amp;amp;AS (Indian Audit and Accounts Service) becoming the Comptroller and Auditor General of India or, for that matter, an IPS heading the Ministry of Home Affairs. Why is this happening? There seem to be some strong reasons for this. One of the main reasons is that the empanelling and selection authorities, the Department of Personnel Affairs is entirely manned by IAS officers. IAS officers get promoted faster than any other service officer and generally there is a 2 year gap between the promotion of an IAS and a non-IAS officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason dates back to pre-independent India. The British had in place an institutional arrangement called the Indian Civil Services, to which only the British were recruited (barring few exceptions). The ICS was solely responsible for land administration, collection of taxes and maintaining law and order in the allotted jurisdiction. ICS officers had absolute power in their jurisdiction and controlled almost everything in the country. They completely dominated in every aspect. After independence, however, the ICS was renamed as IAS and was continued as is, with not much reform taking place. The powers that the ICS had were almost completely transferred to the IAS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, historically, politicians preferred the IAS over other services because of ‘merit.’ There are only a limited number of posts for every service each year as notified by the UPSC, the body responsible for recruiting the civil servants. The selected candidates, though given a preference, are allotted the particular posts in the order of their ranking in the Civil Services Examination (CSE). Conventionally, the order of allotment would start from the IAS and consequently, this perception was developed that the IAS officers are the most ‘brilliant of the minds’ in the country. It is forgotten that brilliance at academics (or one single test) cannot be a parameter to judge the efficiency of a person. Unfortunately, there is hardly any component or test for the problem-solving or efficiency of a person in the CSE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘administration’ is too vague and the service is too generalist and the IAS officers are not specialists in one domain. Note also that the candidates selected for the IAS are from different backgrounds. It is not fair that an IAS with an engineering degree is placed in charge of the environment ministry. It is not fair to say that an IPS officer who has dedicated his life to the service cannot handle the duties of the Ministry of Home Affairs. While not discrediting the service or the members that are a part thereof, it needs to be pointed out that not all officers from such diverse backgrounds can understand clearly the intricacies of, say, economic policy and thus, cannot be put in charge of formulating such policy. This is the root of the problem that is vehemently demanding for some action to be taken and reform to be brought in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding what the problem is, now let us look at what could be some potential solutions to this problem. First is the restriction, if not abolition, of the archaic Administrative Service for appointment of officers for general administration at the district level and for heading the Public Sector Units. Second, the subject domain should be taken as a criterion, not just the ‘experience’ of the IAS officers, while promoting the officers to the Secretary level and appointing them in ministries. The current government has brought in an initiative for the recruitment of experts through lateral entry into various levels of the governments. This is, however, a bad move considering that there are officers from various civil services with the same kind of experience. Their services should be used, instead of recruiting new people. Finally, the structure of the CSE should be reformed to include criteria that test the efficiency and problem-solving skills of a person in place of the existing lengthy descriptive papers. The weightage of the interview should be increased in the overall score of a person. The dominance of the IAS is neither good nor desirable for the country, economically and socially. Reform has to happen and it has to happen very fast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Indian Administrative Service (IAS) is considered the most prestigious of all the civil services in India. It is also the most sought-after service out of the 25 services for which the Indian Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) recruits every year. The attraction towards this service, which is one of the three All India Services, is justified because the service entails many social and economic perks along with the enormous responsibilities. However, only a micro fraction (less than 0.1%) of the candidates that appear for the exam are able to become IAS officers and rest (of the selected candidates) end up in other services. This is where the real problem starts. In what follows, I discuss how the IAS completely dominates the Civil Services in India.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Unending Battle of Keeping Trade Secrets a Secret</title><link href="/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Unending Battle of Keeping Trade Secrets a Secret" /><published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret">&lt;p&gt;Ever heard of the secret recipe of the most popular drink in the world – Coca Cola? Or the algorithm Google uses to rank various websites in its search engine results pages? You would have heard rumours disclosing the special ingredients used to make Coke or the data used by Google to rank websites based on relevance to users. But, none of them would have the backing to be true, neither the practical applicability nor the affirmation from the companies themselves. These secrets are known as &lt;em&gt;trade secrets&lt;/em&gt;. As the name suggests, any sensitive information such as a formula, pattern, compilation, program, device, method, technique or process that needs to be protected from the general public comes under the purview of trade secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why Coca Cola and Google chose not to file for a patent instead. The obvious reason here is that the highly confidential information would have been disclosed to the public, despite giving the companies an exclusive right to the patented process, design or invention for a designated period. Unlike other intellectual property rights, trade secrets protect a much wider range of subject matter such as a business strategy, a new product roadmap, or lists of suppliers and customers and are not limited to set terms of protection. However, they can’t be enforced against anyone who independently discovers the secret. They are actionable only when there is any unlawful acquisition, disclosure or misuse either under breach of confidence or theft. Under such circumstances, the proprietor of the trade secret is eligible to get compensation from the party who committed this unlawful act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With growing cases of infringement of trade secrets, both the organisations and governments worldwide have responded by amending and introducing increasingly robust rules to protect trade secret owners and their rights. On the flip side, it must be ensured that the companies themselves do not misuse the protection provided to them by law and defraud the public by not disclosing harmful information that might lead the company to lose the competitive advantage it has earned due to the trade secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic example of a company engaged in this malpractice has been Theranos – the blood-testing startup with the big vision of testing patients for over 200 conditions off just a small sample of blood from the fingertip, thus saying goodbye to the big, bad needles. The innovative technology soon gained momentum, with the company valuing at $9 billion in 2015 and its CEO Elizabeth Holmes, the darling Stanford dropout of the Silicon Valley, continuously featuring in the lists of top global executives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before Theranos reached its peak in 2015, questions were raised regarding the reliability of the technology and the honesty of the company. The first decade of inception of Theranos in 2003 saw several collaborations such as partnering with Walgreens as well as Safeway to run health clinics, however, things started getting tense gradually when experts started showing concerns of discrepancies in blood test results of patients. The events that followed were clearly indicative of the secrets frauds committed by the company, with the chief scientist of Theranos committing suicide in 2013, President Sunny Balwani leaving the company in 2016 and an end to the partnerships with Walgreens and Safeway leading to the shutting down of wellness centres and clinical labs combined with the laying-off of employees and the piling up of lawsuits filed by investors, patients and collaborators. Such cases prove that although trade secrets give a competitive advantage to the owner of such confidential information, it can also result in misuse by way of not disclosing significant facts – the process of conducting tests in case of Theranos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries, like India, do not have sufficient laws to protect businesses from increasingly sophisticated infringers and at the same time to ensure that the companies make use of the protection provided to them by the state. The scenario is changing with the US and Europe, two of the most prominent markets, taking a step forward and implementing new laws that make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protection of trade secrets was addressed by individual states in the EU before the implementation of Directive in 2016, which led to the harmonisation of laws across all EU member nations. The countries were given the autonomy to go beyond the minimum requirements and level of protection set out by the directive. The aim was not of full harmonisation, but rather to ensure that every EU nation at least achieves the bare minimum safeguard against the illegal acquisition, disclosure and use of trade secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government introduced The Trade Secrets (Enforcement, etc.) Regulations in 2018 as a complement to the already existing Trade Secrets Directive applicable in the entire EU. The Directive was adopted by the UK so as to ensure that UK-based businesses having offices in other countries of the EU can rely on equivalent protection to their trade secrets in the local jurisdictions of other nations. Even post Brexit, the Directive will be applicable, regardless of where the secret holder is domiciled, provided the damage took place in a Member State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per UK law, the cases are solved in a court of law wherein the plaintiff has to prove that the relevant information had the quality of confidence in the sense of not being generally known and not being of trivial nature. It has to be shown that the information was disclosed to the defendant in circumstances of confidence, and the defendant used or disclosed the information without permission or had threatened to do so. However, the Directive has placed restrictions by mandating the organisation to prove that it has taken reasonable steps to safeguard their secret, failing to do so results in loss of protection to the organisation. That apart, the Directive has scaled back the earlier system of confidential hearings and redacted publication of court documents, which may disincentivise companies to actually engage in litigation due to the fear of their trade secret becoming public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other countries, the Defend Trade Secrets Act, 2016 of the US offers the parties the option of settling disputes under either state or federal laws. The parties have the option to choose from three different forums for litigation related to trade secrets – Federal District Courts, US state courts or the US International Trade Commission. These forums deal with any sensitive information acquired by “improper means” namely theft, bribery, misrepresentation, breach or inducement of breach of duty to maintain secrecy, espionage through electronic or other means. Although the laws at the state and central levels differ in some aspects, there is a great deal of similarity among state laws as the majority of them have adopted certain variations of the Uniform Trade Secrets Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prime onus to prevent misappropriation of trade secrets lies on the shoulders of the organisation itself, and not on the government. The business must clearly identify and classify its trade secrets, restrict access and educate employees on the importance of adhering to confidentiality. The employees must be made to sign Non-Disclosure Agreements (NDAs), legally restricting the employees from disclosing private information either to the competitor or the public at large. Exit interviews with outgoing employees can also be used to reinforce the organisation’s trade secret policy. Some special tactics of preventing data leak include &lt;em&gt;read-only&lt;/em&gt; files; password and firewall protection; check-in and check-out procedures; document destruction policies; and review of publications, presentations, at trade shows, on websites, etc. Wherein information is exorbitantly sensitive and would result in immense losses, the companies must segregate this precious information, under lock and key, designated as &lt;em&gt;confidential&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With rampant cybercrime, easier and faster decryption of data by hackers, the cases of data leak and misuse are growing day-by-day. In such an era, this serious yet undiscussed issue of trade secrets can be solved only by nudging the countries across the globe for the adoption of laws with stricter consequences of committing such crimes at international platforms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Ever heard of the secret recipe of the most popular drink in the world – Coca Cola? Or the algorithm Google uses to rank various websites in its search engine results pages? You would have heard rumours disclosing the special ingredients used to make Coke or the data used by Google to rank websites based on relevance to users. But, none of them would have the backing to be true, neither the practical applicability nor the affirmation from the companies themselves. These secrets are known as trade secrets. As the name suggests, any sensitive information such as a formula, pattern, compilation, program, device, method, technique or process that needs to be protected from the general public comes under the purview of trade secrets.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nationalism Through the Lens of a Love Triangle</title><link href="/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nationalism Through the Lens of a Love Triangle" /><published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghare Baire&lt;/em&gt; was one of Bengali cinematic maestro Satyajit Ray’s last films and the last one to be adapted from the works of Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore&lt;em&gt;, The Home and the World&lt;/em&gt;. The film is set around the Indian ‘Swadeshi’ movement of 1905 (which arose as a response to the Partition of Bengal in the same year). It offers a complex insight into the relationship between the home and the world, the status of a liberated woman during that period and the various facets of nationalism. Bimala, our liberated woman, is an equal in her marriage and when encouraged to interact with Sandip, an activist friend of Nikhil, Bimala’s rich landowning husband, by Nikhil himself, she ends up forming an emotional bond with Sandip and commits adultery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the story does not deal with a love triangle only—it shows the fragility of marriage, patriotic ideals and society. The affair and opposing ideologies stir up conflicts both in the marriage and in the society around the characters. The happy marriage eventually breaks down and communal riots break out in the province. Tagore and Ray end the tale on a tragic note. Through the course of the film, Ray effectively portrays Tagore’s ideals through the institution of marriage, and shows how conflicting ideologies create dissent and discord in the marriage and in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tagore once wrote, “Nationalism is a great menace. It is the particular thing which for years has been at the bottom of India’s troubles.” It is this critical thought which he implements while writing the novel in 1916. What Ray deals with is a multi-faceted outlook on nationalism by the Nobel laureate. Is nationalism solely concerned with pride and love for one’s country? If that is true, then perhaps Sandip’s perspective justifies this ideal. However, as Tagore wrote, pride can transform into toxic vanity and hatred for others. This pride “breeds blindness at the end”. Ray also realises that Tagore upholds the importance of Western education and influence, especially in uplifting women and the marginalised sections of society. The movie presents both sides of the issue through Bimala. She abhors the Partition but has conflicting opinions about the radical Swadeshi and Boycott movements. She herself uses foreign goods, perfume and furniture. She admires Miss Gilby, her governess, and is shocked when she is assaulted by Amulya (a teenager who joins Sandip’s radical group). When she finally steals from her husband, Ray makes his audience infer that her ‘home’ is a part of this ‘world’, and no nationalistic ideals can be adhered to if one is unfaithful to one’s home and roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikhil, on the other hand, tries to balance both sides, believing nationalism is not radical and overtly extremist, but an idea upholding liberty and equality. He maintains nationalism cannot be practiced at the expense of marginalised communities. Tagore’s views are somehow mirrored through Nikhil’s character. The poet was quite anti-colonial himself but never supported militant nationalism and vigilantism. Sandip represents the latter, showing everything wrong with toxic nationalism. To quote Tagore, “I have no hesitation in saying that those who are gifted with the moral power of love and vision of spiritual unity, who have the least feeling of enmity against aliens, and the sympathetic insight to place themselves in the position of others will be the fittest to take their permanent place in the age that is lying before us, and those who are constantly developing their instinct of fight and intolerance of aliens will be eliminated.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting aspect is the use of the institution of marriage. Marriage, unlike most other social structures, is sensitive and dynamic. Ray and Tagore centre their tale around a marriage which is advanced, compared to the contemporary matrimonial laws and customs. The very existence of a Western-educated, socialite wife who indulges in infidelity is bold, and the stakes are further raised when the criteria for the woman choosing the man becomes his views and not mere lust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikhil practices what he believes in: equality and empowerment of women and the poor. Sandip, the marriage-breaker, is a hypocrite who, under the garb of his nationalistic view, is exploitative and flat-out selfish. Nikhil recognises that for any nation to prosper, the home must prosper. He lets his wife make the choice and happily accepts her when she realises her mistake and apologises for her delusional activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics have argued about the equality presented in the marriage. Some believe that Tagore keeps the setting real by showing that despite the intention to attain equality, the husband’s ideas and views have a pervasive and effective influence upon the wife’s thinking (in this case, his opinionated nationalism). The woman (Bimala) also gets influenced by another man’s opinions (Sandip), and not the other way round. The depiction that, during the period, most women were intellectually dependent on men is haunting yet real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film ultimately boils down to the relation between the ‘home’ and the ‘world’. The ‘home’ will prosper when there is absolute harmony among the members. The ‘world’ is, after all, a conglomeration of homes on a large scale. What is largely practiced across several homes magnifies to a world level. When Bimala realises that she is cheating on her ideals of nationalism by stealing from her own home, she breaks down and seeks reconciliation. Ray proves that nationalistic ideals have no significance if they are not followed at ‘home’ or at any personal level. Ray effectively depicts the reciprocal relationship between the home and the world. What happens in the former affects the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the extra-marital affair hurts Sandip’s ego and he instigates the riots in the province as an act of revenge on Bimala and also to coerce the Muslim workers to conform to his political ideologies. The ‘world’ also enters the affairs of the ‘home’. Tagore and Ray also show a juxtaposition by having two major themes as the backdrop of the story: liberty and freedom of women in the ‘home’ and freedom of the nation in the ‘world’. Both struggles to attain freedom are depicted in the film. Bimala goes beyond the boundaries of marriage in her quest to attain her ideals and struggles to restore her marriage and mental peace. The nation is struggling to achieve freedom via nationalistic movements that do not cater to or benefit all sections of society. Neither Tagore nor Ray deal with a definite conclusion by the end; there is no remark about the outcome of the struggles. It is the emotional and social struggle with which they are concerned, not the outcome. The film is not an argument for how gender equality in society can be successfully attained; nor does it show how the Swadeshi movement led to Indian independence. But it is an insightful account on what repercussions these struggles can lead to and how lives can be drastically affected. The discord in the marriage and society are the examples of such repercussions, and Tagore and Ray caution their audience to take heed to the darker side of such struggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the issues presented through the film adaptation are universal. Virtually every polity across the world has as its foundation some ideology of national self-assertion. Whenever there is an idea, there are conflicting perspectives on that idea. Varying opinions on a matter like nationalism can often lead to polarisation, which in extreme cases can even lead to violence and the disruption of peace and harmony. The representation of nationalistic leaders like Sandip is also significant. Sandip represents all those leaders who under their garb of selflessness, are unconcerned, conniving, exploitative hypocrites masquerading as philanthropists full of care and concern. Just like Sandip who used Bimala for his personal interests, several leaders treat their subjects as pawns and exploit them to their advantage. Thus Ray, through the adaptation of Tagore’s novel, proposes his audience to make a choice - a choice between violent, oppressive nationalism, and a balanced, compassionate and harmonious patriotism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sarbesh Chaudhury</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Ghare Baire was one of Bengali cinematic maestro Satyajit Ray’s last films and the last one to be adapted from the works of Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore, The Home and the World. The film is set around the Indian ‘Swadeshi’ movement of 1905 (which arose as a response to the Partition of Bengal in the same year). It offers a complex insight into the relationship between the home and the world, the status of a liberated woman during that period and the various facets of nationalism. Bimala, our liberated woman, is an equal in her marriage and when encouraged to interact with Sandip, an activist friend of Nikhil, Bimala’s rich landowning husband, by Nikhil himself, she ends up forming an emotional bond with Sandip and commits adultery.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Enemies of the People: a Study of the Libyan Conflict</title><link href="/Enemies-of-the-People" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enemies of the People: a Study of the Libyan Conflict" /><published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Enemies-of-the-People</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Enemies-of-the-People">&lt;p&gt;Foreign intervention is a domino. Behind which are aligned hundreds of dominos, often not of the development and prosperity they promise, but of more foreign intervention. Libya is a perfect example. The recent Berlin Conference on Libya, which gathered world leaders to ‘decide’ the fate of Libya, is an irony in itself. It is an* intervention to cure an intervention*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand Libya (and arguably to understand anything), there is a need to historicise and contextualise the current situation. The conflict didn’t start in 2011 or 2014 but has much deeper roots in Libya’s history. For this reason, we can study the Libyan conflict in two stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libya before 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For much of its history, Libya was not a single unified land. Its three territories:Tripolitania, Cyrenaica and Fezzan were separated for much longer than they were united. Libya has continuously faced occupation by almost every power in history including the Greeks, the Romans and the Turks. It was only after the Italian occupation in 1911 that the three territories were unified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to their brutal treatment, the colonisers were inevitably faced with the discontent of their subjects. This gave rise to a Sufi movement, known as the Senussi order, which led the resistance. During the Second World War, Italy lost Libya to Britain and France and during this switch of colonisers, the Senussi order gained ground. In 1951, Libya was the first country to be granted independence by the United Nations. King Idris became the first Libyan monarch to rule the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 1959, everything changed. As rich oil reserves were found, Libya witnessed the transformative powers of oil. The West strategically increased its sphere of influence in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a bird’s eye view of this part of the world at the time, Arab countries were experiencing a wave of what came to be known as ‘Nasserism’. The word itself is based on the former Egyptian President Nasser, and represents an anti-imperialist and pan-Arab nationalist movement. Therefore, in the 1960’s, the Arab world was hit by a wave of Nasserist coups aimed at changing regimes that were reactionary and pro-West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libyan students began to agitate against the monarchy and on September 1, 1969, the revolution deposed King Idris. This revolution was led by a man whose name would define Libya for years to come, the 27-year-old General Muammar Gaddafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the coup, 12 Free Officers proclaimed themselves the Revolutionary Command Council, the government of the new republic, and Gaddafi was the de-facto head. Gaddafi was a man of the people, and his regime was extremely popular. He undertook large-scale nationalisation and rested his policy on three pillars, “Freedom, Socialism and Unity”. As a disciple of Nasser, he set out to tackle the unfair legacy of Western economic interference. By dismantling the influence of foreign companies and seizing complete control of the National Oil Corporation in 1970, he made Libya the first developing country to secure a majority share of the revenues from its own oil production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi used the income from oil to fund social welfare. While using the sharia law as a basis for social reform, he worked extensively for women’s empowerment, healthcare, education and house-building programs. He also used the money to fund revolutionary movements against injustice and colonialism all across the world. From helping those fighting apartheid to Marxist Palestinian liberation groups, the Irish Revolutionary Army as well as left-wing groups across Europe and Latin America, Gaddafi extended his hand of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A turning point in his rule came in April, 1973 with his “5 points” at a conference at Zuwarah. He proclaimed the beginning of a ‘Popular Revolution’. People’s committees were set up and he gave up his position only to remain as what he called the ‘Brother Leader’ to guide them through. The bureaucracy was to be removed and all opponents to the revolution were to be removed. This rang similar to the Great Cultural Revolution in China. Libya was renamed the &lt;em&gt;Great Socialist People’s Libyan Arab Jamahiriya,&lt;/em&gt; meaning a “state of the masses”, as conceptualised by Gaddafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to Mao’s &lt;em&gt;Red Book&lt;/em&gt; Gaddafi formulated a Third Universal Theory in his &lt;em&gt;Green Book&lt;/em&gt;. He saw both the USA and USSR as imperialist and set out to create a theory that took an Islamic Socialist standpoint. This revolution quickly became a witch hunt, either you were a revolutionary or a counter-revolutionary. Gaddafi was the centre of everything: all roads of power led to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Egypt’s new President Anwar Sadat began to fall in line with the Western powers in the 1970’s, Gaddafi’s pan-Arab ideal seemed further away. His staunch anti-American stance, as well as his undying support for revolutions against imperialism, labelled him “a supporter of worldwide terror”; Ronald Reagan called him the “Mad Dog of the Middle East”, to which Gaddafi retorted that America was the real terrorist. The USA bombed the Libyan capital in a clear attempt to kill Gaddafi but ended up killing civilians. After all, it was typical of the ‘leader of the free world’ to assassinate someone just because they didn’t like him. Further, severe sanctions were imposed on Libya after Gaddafi was alleged to be involved in an aeroplane crash in Scotland and the Berlin discotheque bombing (despite the lack of conclusive evidence). The Abu Salim prison massacre also drew flak from the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another turning point for Gaddafi came after the US invasion of Iraq and the death of Saddam Hussein. It was allegedly the fear of meeting a similar fate, and fear for the safety of his family, that brought a shift in Gaddafi’s attitudes. Libya began to pander to Western powers, like many nations who were earlier forced to do so. Reform programs were conducted, political prisoners were released and eventually, sanctions were lifted. Libya was officially invited back to the international fold, gaining levels of legitimacy that Gaddafi had never experienced in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, alienated him from the Arab world. Parrying with the powers who were supporting the Arab enemy, Israel, was not acceptable. In this situation, still wanting to be a part of a larger territory-based movement, Gaddafi moved from pan-Arabism to pan-Africanism. He became Chairman of the African Union in 2009. It also began to show that his alliance with the West did not align with his personal beliefs. This was seen clearly in 2009 when Gaddafi went to the UN for the first time and called the UN Security Council a “terror council”. American media said that he had shown his “true colours”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libya after 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Arab Spring uprisings across North African and Central Asian Arab states began to surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi’s stronghold was in the West of Libya and the East always felt wronged by him. The families of those killed in the Abu Salim massacre were planning a ‘day of rage’ on February 17 in Benghazi, a city in the East. However, the leader of the movement was arrested two days before the protests and his supporters clashed with security forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These protests quickly turned into protests against Gaddafi and his repressive regime. It moved on to other cities and attracted a growing number of militias, who were fighting against state power. The protests turned to armed rebellion, but Gaddafi decided not to use force, which is why the revolution grew without restraint and could not be suppressed once he decided to respond. The protests then reached his stronghold in Tripoli, the capital of Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2011, a group of military officials and ministers defected and set up a National Transitional Council (NTC). Working with the Arab League, they urged the UN to intervene in Libya. Many accusations of mass rapes, bombing and extrajudicial killings were put on Gaddafi forces. However, these were never proven. In fact, even many Western human rights NGOs visited Libya and found no proof of these allegations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a push for NATO action, and world leaders saw this as an opportunity for fulfilling personal vendetta. A no-fly zone was established over Libya and NATO declared that they would undertake “all necessary measures to protect civilians”. Under this guideline, NATO countries trained rebels and flooded them with weapons from the West despite the weapons embargo. Rebels divided by region and objectives joined hands against Gaddafi. Posters of freedom fighter Omar Mukhtar and flags of independent Libya flew again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August of 2011, the rebels took Tripoli without the fierce resistance that people had anticipated. The National Transitional Council took over control and Gaddafi went back to his hometown in Sirte. On October 20, with the help of NATO, the rebels found Gaddafi. What ensued was televised torture and murder, with the rebels showing no mercy and videotaping the entire scene. Gaddafi’s last words caught on camera were broken: “What did I do to you?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who fought for Gaddafi were killed or tortured and paraded around Tripoli. Many went missing and remain so till this day. Foreign leaders rejoiced. Hillary Clinton was caught on camera joking about his death, “We came, we saw, he died”. Gulf states were also relieved as Libya’s development threatened to put Central Asia in second place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed, however, was a power vacuum and violent in-fighting between militias as the differences had resurfaced once their common goal to get rid of Gaddafi was met. Although formally under NTC control, Libya was a patchwork of competing militias. In fact, the militia life became attractive to the youth as it paid much more than any other job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2012, parliamentary elections were hurried through, pressured by the international community. The NTC transferred power to the General National Congress (GNC) who were to rule only for 18 months. A series of decisions by them further reinforced the militancy culture. A state salary was given to those who fought in the revolution. Further, GNC gave into federalist demands from the East which set the precedent that force, or threat of force, would lead to concessions. Violence became a political currency. The most outright power grab was the 2013 Political Isolation Act which stated that if you were working under Gaddafi you could no longer hold a government post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GNC extended its term even though it was supposed to end in 2013. Simultaneously, General Khalifa Haftar rose in the East. He was abandoned by Gaddafi in Chad and subsequently rescued by the CIA and given citizenship in the USA. Upon his return in 2011, he formed the Libyan National Army in the East. He launched a ‘dignity war’ against the terrorist militias in Benghazi in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the June 2014 elections, an environment of violence had already been normalised. A party called the House of Representatives, backed by Haftar, won the majority and the government was shifted East to the city of Tobruk. However, the old government refused to give up power and there were two governments in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that during this civil war, the Tripoli controlled National Oil Corporation, as well as the Central Bank, continued to function under international pressure. So, militias were funded by the Central Bank on both sides with no national institutions or public services and oil sales boosted cash further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the UN tried to resolve the conflict by creating the Government of National Accord in Tripoli to act as an interim government of Libya, but they were not recognised by the Haftar-backed House of Representatives. Haftar slowly took control of Eastern oil ports and today controls most of Libya’s territory. Haftar aims to eventually take Tripoli and establish his regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which countries are invested and why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haftar is supported by Gulf countries like United Arab Emirates, Saudi Arabia as well as Egypt simply because they wish to curb the spread of ‘political Islam’, something that they believe the GNA stands for. These countries are largely responsible for the provision of arms, air support and troops to Haftar’s forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Turkey has been a foremost supporter of the GNA. President Erdogan has even promised military help to the GNA against Haftar’s Tripoli campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US, having arguably been the cause of this mess, has chosen to remain silent while officially supporting the UN efforts of a ceasefire. France and Russia, although officially supporting UN efforts, have also shown their vested interests by blocking an EU attempt to stop Haftar’s campaign. In fact, they have both been accused of providing weapons to Haftar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berlin Conference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Berlin conference was a last-minute attempt by Germany to salvage what little political process is left in Libya. Held on January 19, 2020, it was timed to defer Haftar’s ‘final assault’ on Tripoli. Germany, the only country in Europe with enough political clout to summon important players, came to everyone’s rescue - at least for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference ended with a 55-point communique calling for a permanent ceasefire, the implementation of a UN arms embargo, the dismantling of militias, and the resumption of the political process. However, this is impossible to implement and, honestly, a little ironic, considering that many of the conference member states are themselves suppliers of arms that keep the conflict afloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that this account brings is who is safeguarding the interests of the people? Protests from the grassroots have spread like fire in Libya, condemning the violence and the disrupting effects it has on everyday lives. Has international power politics gone so far that domestic populations do not even receive cursory importance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question we can ask is what did the death of Gaddafi really achieve? Many Libyans still mourn his death and hail his regime as a haven with free healthcare and education. Was his policy of using Libya’s oil for the Libyan people too much for the West to handle? One thing is clear - whichever foreign actor supported the revolution by way of arms or by way of silence, they remain enemies of the people.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Foreign intervention is a domino. Behind which are aligned hundreds of dominos, often not of the development and prosperity they promise, but of more foreign intervention. Libya is a perfect example. The recent Berlin Conference on Libya, which gathered world leaders to ‘decide’ the fate of Libya, is an irony in itself. It is an* intervention to cure an intervention*.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Russia Heralds a New Dawn: Power to the People or the Lurking Shadow of a Dictatorial Regime?</title><link href="/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russia Heralds a New Dawn: Power to the People or the Lurking Shadow of a Dictatorial Regime?" /><published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&quot;I truly believe that it is time to introduce certain changes to our country's main law.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; 
-Vladimir Putin, January 2020
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 15, 2020, the Russian Government headed by Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev resigned en masse, immediately after the State of the Union address. Within six hours of Medvedev’s resignation, Putin offered the post to Mikhail Mishutshin who had formerly been the head of the Russian Tax Service. It is of significance that the governmental revamp has been preceded by a proposed nationwide referendum on constitutional changes which will ensure the shift of the balance of power from Putin’s successor (the future Russian President) to the Parliament and the newly-appointed Prime Minister, even though Putin has limited the term of the Russian President to two terms. All 432 legislators in the Duma, the lower house of the Russian Parliament, have approved of the amendments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the amendments, 14 articles of the Constitution are to be changed. The State Duma will possess the right to approve a Prime Minister’s candidacy, followed by that of the Deputy Prime Ministers and Federal Ministers. A prospective Presidential candidate has to be an inhabitant of Russia for a minimum of 25 years (earlier it was 10 years). The upper house of the Russian Parliament, the Federation Council, will be able to send a proposal to the President to dismiss Federal Judges. This is an elevation of the Council’s importance, whose significance was previously restricted to being an advisory body. The President will appoint the superior officers of the law enforcement agencies only in consultation with the Federal Council. The individuals who hold important positions for ensuring the country’s security (President, Ministers, Heads of Regions) are forbidden from holding foreign citizenship or residence permits of other nations during their term in office. The Constitutional Court has the competence to ensure the constitutionality of laws which the Parliament of the Russian Federation adopts, by the request of the President, before him signing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That apart, one of the important parts of the amendment includes a clear statement of the priority of the Russian Constitution over international law and the global human rights regime, which many believe is a reflection of Kremlin’s annoyance with the European Court of Human Rights’ declarations that Russia is responsible for gross human rights violations, including the Chechnya disappearances, and the Court’s rulings against Russia’s Federal Security Services in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The otherwise innocuous amendments tend to have latent implications for Russia, in particular, and international politics in general. A cursory analysis reveals that there shall be a surge in the importance of the country’s Parliament: both the upper and lower house. The President’s candidature for the post of Prime Minister would require a formal confirmation from the Duma. The actual centre of power shall shift to the State Council which is being vested with a heightened legal authority. Many believe that it is the future landing gateway for Putin, post-2024, as it will ensure that he retains ultimate power post-retirement from the Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amendments will bestow the Security Council (headed by Putin, it includes the heads of the lower and upper house of parliament, the President’s envoys in Federal Districts and regional Governors) with the status of an official state organ that shall chart the domestic and foreign policies of the Russian Federation. There is an opportunity of the Security Council receiving executive authority that it previously hasn’t possessed. Putin may continue to manipulate foreign and domestic affairs through his pivotal role in this Security Council, in spite of not retaining his presidential post within 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The present amendments may be compared to that of the Kazakhstan President Nursultan Nazarvaev, who formally stepped down from the post of the President last March but continued to enjoy hegemony over the decision-making hierarchy of the nation by capturing important positions in the Security Council whose authority had been strategically heightened before Nazarnaev’s ascendancy. Hints of such parallels find resonance in the words of Pavel Krasheninnikov, Chairman of a Duma committee telling the official Government newspaper &lt;em&gt;Rossiiskaya Gazeta&lt;/em&gt;, “Scores of proposals have been received including one to create an official post of Supreme Leader.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of February, 2020, one may state that the unanimous support of the Duma to the constitutional amendments bill is reminiscent of the Soviet vote on Stalin’s adoption of the December, 1936 Constitution or Brezhnev’s 1977 Doctrine. A national plebiscite on the amendments is due in April and planning for it has already been initiated by the Central Election Commission. However, the opposition aims at converting the plebiscite into a no-confidence vote of the ruling regime. More than 40,000 people have signed a manuscript urging the Russian public to blatantly reject the “constitutional &lt;em&gt;coup&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;d’etat&lt;/em&gt;”. Meanwhile, the fate of Russia swerves in the uncertainty of major constitutional upheaval.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">&quot;I truly believe that it is time to introduce certain changes to our country's main law.&quot; -Vladimir Putin, January 2020</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part I)</title><link href="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part I)" /><published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I">&lt;p&gt;When we look at the Middle East, we see chaos, war and violence, and usually have no idea why it is so. The Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception — in fact, it may be the poster-child for a Middle Eastern conflict. Although the history of the conflict goes back thousands of years, the modern conflict effectively started 72 years ago. The question is: why is it still going on? Why hasn’t a peaceful solution been reached? After spending several days in Israel and the West Bank studying the conflict and listening to journalists, politicians and other people from both sides, there are a couple things the West needs to understand as to why peace hasn’t been achieved. But first, some context must be given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand any conflict in the Middle East, one must take note of the Middle Eastern mind. Although I was born and raised in America, I can speak on this, as my ancestry is Middle-Eastern from the country of Armenia. Obviously, people from the Middle East are not monolithic (the British and French cartographers never understood this), there are hundreds, if not thousands of cultures and co-cultures in the Middle East and greater area — such as North Africa and Western Asia. Among those cultures, there are a variety of ethnic groups, languages and customs. So, this is more of a general guideline to understand the mindset, not a hard rule, but it is often neglected from consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Middle East, the two most important things in life are the land you live on and your traditions. What makes the land important is the same thing that makes tradition important: It is where your ancestors lived and died for generations. Some people were more nomadic, but many ethnicities (especially the Jews and Palistinians) see the land as a part of their culture and identity. If you take away their land, you take away what makes them. So as you can imagine, they’ll fight tooth and nail to keep it. In America or Europe, it’s not uncommon to move from city to city, state to state, or even country to country. But this is not the case here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as for the conflict itself, why is it still going on? The truth of the matter is simple, but it’s the reality that is complex. The truth is that the majority on both sides want peace, but the reality is both also want control over all of the disputed land. In other words, it is a paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it gets even more complicated when you consider that this is not simply the Israeli-Palistinian conflict, this is the Arab-Israeli conflict. If the typical American has parents who do something the former doesn’t like, they usually won’t continue. But typically in the Middle East, you continue doing what your parents did and learn to love it. Other than the land, there may not be anything more important than traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, tradition and homeland are deeply rooted in the Middle-Eastern mind. Part of what that means is fighting for your people. Israel is surrounded by countries who hate it: Egypt, Lebanon, Syria, Jordan and Iran, to name a few.  Conversely, because there is a worldwide diaspora of Jewish people, they will often lobby and petition their governments to support &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; people. Yet, of all the actors mentioned (and the many that were unmentioned), their agenda is not so simple as either supporting the Jewish people or the Palistinian people. Each one has a complex relationship with both and with the other aforementioned neighbors, in addition with multiple internal groups who also have competing ideologies. Some of them see the Israelis or the Palestinians as pawns in their own game to protect their own land and traditions against another actor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aside from all this, if the principal parties — as well as the majority of the international community — really want peace, why hasn’t it been resolved yet? For one thing, there is corrupt leadership on both sides. The Israeli government is motivated by fear, so they continuously impose more expansive security measures on the Palistinians. However, these security measures are economically inhibiting and they usually infringe on the civil rights — and sometimes human rights — of the Palistinians. This oppression breeds extremism and sympathy towards violent action within the Palistinian community. This, in turn, makes Israel more afraid, and it responds by imposing more security measures, thus, perpetuating the downward spiral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the governing body over the Palistinians, known as the Palistianian Authority (or PA) handles it poorly as well. They make little effort to de-radicalise the Palestinians, and if anything, encourage hatred towards the people they claim they want to have peace with. On one hand, the PA does encourage peaceful resistance to the Israeli government and promises democratic reforms, but on the other hand, they have not had an election in over a decade. This is because the last election in 2006 was held in the Gaza strip and it led to the takeover of the terrorist group Hamas. Israel feels that Hamas will also takeover the West Bank if there is another election, causing even more violence and instability. Furthermore, if peace and prosperity comes to the West Bank, the PA officials currently in power won’t have an easy pitch to ask for foreign aid. Once foreign aid dries-up, their life gets affected badly. Thus, they are more motivated to not back down and hold their position. Even if it is at the cost of the innocent Palistinians who live under them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there an easy solution to the conflict? For people who are living far away and unaffected by it: yes.  But for the people involved, it is a resounding: no. Now that is not to say that people outside of the affected area cannot help with the peace process, there is a place for good-hearted help from the West. But the conflict will not be solved by the West.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Madajian</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">When we look at the Middle East, we see chaos, war and violence, and usually have no idea why it is so. The Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception — in fact, it may be the poster-child for a Middle Eastern conflict. Although the history of the conflict goes back thousands of years, the modern conflict effectively started 72 years ago. The question is: why is it still going on? Why hasn’t a peaceful solution been reached? After spending several days in Israel and the West Bank studying the conflict and listening to journalists, politicians and other people from both sides, there are a couple things the West needs to understand as to why peace hasn’t been achieved. But first, some context must be given.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Corruption and Coercion on the Digital Silk Road</title><link href="/Corruption-and-Coercion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corruption and Coercion on the Digital Silk Road" /><published>2020-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Corruption-and-Coercion</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Corruption-and-Coercion">&lt;p&gt;The squalid conditions of the Xinjiang region of Northwestern China, in which Uighur Muslims, Khazakhs and Uzbeks are forced to surrender DNA and blood samples, remain a stark reminder of the extent to which civil liberties can be assailed in the name of ‘counter-terrorism’. 47-year old Bakitali Nur, a fruit and vegetable exporter from Khargos, &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5735411/china-surveillance-privacy-issues/&quot;&gt;told &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt; magazine&lt;/a&gt; that he and seven other inmates were forced to sit still on plastic stools for seventeen consecutive hours as their movements were monitored by security cameras. In Xinjiang, 2.5 million citizens have their whereabouts tracked by CCTV whilst being subjected to a punitive social credit system that discourages behaviour not approved of by the Chinese State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dystopian scenes are a microcosm of a much broader and more complex web of technological and economic strategies through which the Chinese State is attempting to construct a digital panopticon that ensnares Central Asia and large parts of Africa and Latin America in its grip. Announced in a 2015 Government White Paper, the Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) attempts to enhance digital connectivity, impose high-level technologies and Artificial Intelligence on neighbouring countries, and to establish China as a regional hegemon and world leader in physical and digital infrastructure. The Digital Silk Road, which involves State-owned enterprises and private companies developing fiber optic cables that can monitor and divert data traffic, has led to a $79 billion investment in 80 different countries. The implications of fiber optic expansion and data centres are immense: the ability of the CCP to monitor and control foreign citizens, to proliferate State propaganda and quell ideological dissent is augmented through the process of data localisation, which requires foreign corporations to maintain data in China, where the State has access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collusion between the Chinese State and the technological corporations responsible for accessing civilian data and implementing everything from facial recognition cameras to traffic control devices is most strikingly expressed in the 2017 National Intelligence Law, which promulgated that Chinese corporations had to support the values of Chinese Intelligence Agencies. Within the context of this Law, it seems all the more disturbing that Hikvision, a company whose controlling shares are owned by the Chinese government, has installed facial recognition cameras in Kazakhstan and facilitated surveillance in Uzbekistan’s educational system. In February 2019, the Tajik government &lt;a href=&quot;https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/11/15/huawei-xinjiang-kazakhstan-uzbekistan-china-surveillance-state-eyes-central-asia/&quot;&gt;announced an identification system&lt;/a&gt; requiring phone users to provide fingerprints and privacy-invasive medical information when buying SIM cards. The potential for China to establish itself as a global superpower by harvesting data and establishing e-commerce is limitless, particularly in an era in which our economies are increasingly based around digital information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the rise of China has frequently been touted as an event of epochal significance, which threatens to overthrow the established global order and is driven by an implacable hostility to every aspect of modern economics, the reality is that China seeks to maintain many elements of globalisation and free trade. The regimentation of large corporations behind a bureaucratic state apparatus instead represents the degeneration of modern capitalism: where once it was associated with freedom, liberal democracy and pluralism, and contrasted with ‘authoritarian’ communist regimes, modern capitalism arguably works most effectively and efficiently when under the auspices of a centralised, technocratic state apparatus. That China remains keen to promote areas of digital ‘e-commerce’ and free-trade areas to reduce costs of international shipments and cross-border trade indicates that capitalistic imperatives still govern much of the productive process, in an ostensibly Hegelian synthesis of authoritarian politics and liberal economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the imperialistic nature of the Digital Silk Road, which involves putting countries into debt by proliferating infrastructural projects and making them dependent on loans from the Chinese State, mirrors tactics used after the 1970’s Third World debt crisis caused by the World Bank and the IMF. For instance, in 2017, 95% of Sri Lankan government spending went to paying off debt, much of which was issued to China. These foreign loans function as a means of subordinating neighbouring countries economically, facilitating Chinese access to natural resources and opening markets to offset domestic overproduction. The case of Chinese involvement in Africa is another example of how the neo-mercantilist formulations of the modern Chinese economy are not socialistic as some on the hard-right (in addition to a small minority of communists) claim; rather, it is reminiscent of European colonialism. Sino-African trade increased by $169 billion between the 1980’s and 2018, mainly composed of crude oil and agricultural products. Raw materials are converted into finished goods and resold to African nations at high prices, increasing their dependency on China. The monopolisation of data is a major part of this; &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepeninsulaqatar.com/article/27/02/2019/Egypt-to-host-Huawei-s-first-MENA-cloud-platform-Cairo&quot;&gt;Huawei opened its first cloud data centre in Egypt in February 2019&lt;/a&gt;, and Algeria and Tunisia continue to host Chinese tech firms intent on harvesting consumer data. In Morocco, ‘smart city’ Tangier Tech is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globalconstructionreview.com/news/tangier-tech-city-plans-revived-selection-chinese-/&quot;&gt;soon to host 200 Chinese companies.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Mason, writing in &lt;em&gt;Postcapitalism: A Guide to Our Future&lt;/em&gt;, argued that “today, the main contradiction in modern capitalism is between the possibility of free, abundant socially produced goods, and a system of monopolies, banks and governments struggling to maintain, control of over power and information.”  The emergence of a bureaucratic, unaccountable Chinese Empire which seeks to monopolise and patent information can therefore be contextualised within a wider phenomenon: the attempts by capitalistic institutions to apply market dynamics to otherwise freely-exchangeable data. Information is a public good: it is non-rival and non-excludable, freely replicable and devoid of the scarcity that enables markets to capture and commodify it in the way that other things can be easily commodified. Therefore, it circumscribes the ability of markets to form prices; infinite supply means that prices will fall close to zero unless giant tech monopolies can maintain patents on information which artificially create scarcity. The function of the Chinese tech monopolies is to do precisely this: Huawei has issued 1,500 5G patents as of 2019, and Chinese companies own 36% of all 5G patents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates what can be referred to in Marxist terms as a contradiction between the forces and relations of production. Karl Marx wrote that “from forms of development of the productive forces, these relations turn into their fetters,” a point clearly demonstrated by observing modern reality; the productive forces have developed to the point where we can share socially-produced information freely, yet market forces capture and privatise this information. The Chinese State’s attempts to combine economic and technological imperialism, shoring up hegemony on the world stage, have also allowed it to save capitalism from its own contradictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expansion of the social credit system, which has seen citizens submit personal data about their personal lives and shopping habits to the Chinese government in an attempt to gain a favourable rating, is emblematic of how the commodification of information entails separating data from people and diminishing the amount of control they have over confidential, personal information. The removal of direct access to information as a pretext to its subjection to market imperatives parallels the way in which 17th Century English peasants were deprived of direct access to their land holdings so that it could be privatised and contractually regulated by entrepreneurial landlords, a point succinctly summarised by Mark Andrejevic, who stated, “If land enclosure helped produce the spatial conditions for the exploitation of wage labor, digital enclosures enable the exploitation of information generated by users as they go about their daily lives.” The enclosure (via digital means) of what legal scholar James Ball refers to as the  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dhi.ac.uk/san/waysofbeing/data/citizenship-robson-andrejevic-2007.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“intangible commons of the mind”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; constantly extends the boundaries of what is available for patenting and copywriting, allowing a restrictive legal infrastructure determining “intellectual property rights” to accompany the new forms of alienation engendered by the privatisation and monopolisation of data. While this may seem to be a mere marketing strategy for companies to sell products based on already established information about consumers from their Google searches, the social credit system indicates that the implications are altogether more sinister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our present epoch is defined by the waning of the American Empire and the rise of Chinese hegemony, as the two powers compete in an ongoing technological Cold War that accompanies the already existing trade war. In 1980, US share of world income was 24.6%, but had fallen to 19.1% by 2011. China, by contrast, has seen a meteoric rise from 2.2% in 1980 to 14.4% in 2011. The United States, recognising this shift in the balance of power, has attempted to dissuade other countries from using Huawei to develop their 5G networks. Yet the Digital Silk Road has allowed China to establish itself as a world leader in exporting digital infrastructure, attempting to use this as a conduit for the maintenance of ‘sharp’ power, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pacforum.org/sites/default/files/issuesinsights_Vol19%20WP8FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;“manipulation of ideas, political perceptions and electoral processes”.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Men make history, but not as they choose”,  stated Karl Marx in &lt;em&gt;The Eighteenth Brumaire of Louis Napoleon&lt;/em&gt;. Underlying forces and wider contexts determine the conditions that allow certain powers to establish geopolitical dominance at certain times. For the American Empire, financial power and military muscle forged a new American century in the aftermath of World War I, the nominally victorious Entente dependent upon American loans for many of the offensives of 1918, lying prostrate before America’s export-driven economic boom. For China, it is the collapse of globalisation, recurring crises of the neoliberal model, and the increasing importance of data that have heralded a new Chinese century, as the Digital Silk Road carves out a new sphere of influence. The pendulum has swung to the Far East, as with opened wallets and closed minds, we may all soon be subjects of Xi Jinping.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">The squalid conditions of the Xinjiang region of Northwestern China, in which Uighur Muslims, Khazakhs and Uzbeks are forced to surrender DNA and blood samples, remain a stark reminder of the extent to which civil liberties can be assailed in the name of ‘counter-terrorism’. 47-year old Bakitali Nur, a fruit and vegetable exporter from Khargos, told Time magazine that he and seven other inmates were forced to sit still on plastic stools for seventeen consecutive hours as their movements were monitored by security cameras. In Xinjiang, 2.5 million citizens have their whereabouts tracked by CCTV whilst being subjected to a punitive social credit system that discourages behaviour not approved of by the Chinese State.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are You Bored Enough?</title><link href="/Are-You-Bored-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are You Bored Enough?" /><published>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Are-You-Bored-Enough</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Are-You-Bored-Enough">&lt;p&gt;A happy new year, yeah, um, happy? From what I’ve been told, we’re unsubscribing from Jan’20, so, I hope for a good, uneven eleven-month’d year ahead. There has been a huge lapse on my end: I’ve been unable to pen down anything for the longest time. Not because I’m lacking the resources, definitely not the time―what it is, may only be described as dissatisfaction. Dissatisfaction in everything that, I, as an individual of a certain age- living in the country that I live in, belonging to the state I belong to, have had to see. The ghastly past few days and the subsequent coming days, all of it seems too much to bear and I’ve decided I am not to write on it. The awareness that this entire fascist regime (or, situation) in India deserves is beyond anything I can measure, and I can’t remotely do it justice, in no specific way. My bias holds too high and is nowhere near close to being over, not anytime soon. Hence, I’ll use this as a ‘breath of fresh air,’ with how polluted the air I breathe is. In more ways than one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I type this, I’ve Billie crooning in my ears about how she’s so bored, and well, let’s run with it, shall we? Billie deserves her answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bored? Boredom? Equivalent to disinterest? Or, is it a conditioned, negative feeling that shrouds us upon being unproductive? I’ve often felt awful after a day spent watching Netflix. But does that mean I was bored? I wouldn’t say so. But has the binge been productive? I wouldn’t say that, either. So, I go surfing, web surfing and find out what this damned concept entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several authors from Pascal to Schopenhauer, from Kierkegaard to our very favourite Nietzsche, and Baudelaire, and Dostoevsky―everyone seems to have dropped a cent on this everyday phenomenon. Well, is it an everyday phenomenon all? It almost seems like the closer we get to the present day, the more destructive boredom becomes, compelling creative types—from writers and artists to rock musicians (Slash!!)—to reflect on this theme. Nevertheless, it remains a difficult psychological state to define, more so today, than ever. Kierkegaard equates boredom with the devil and defines it thus: “The demonic is that which is without content, boring.” According to Dostoevsky, boredom is “a bestial and indefinable affliction.” One of the present-day researchers, Elizabeth Goodstein, labels it “experience without qualities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I agree. I mean, she’s clearly influenced by Robert Musil’s &lt;em&gt;The Man Without Qualities&lt;/em&gt;. The book is simply a diagnosis of everyday life and thrives on the concept of boredom. If one were to read Lars Svendsen’s (pretty much the father of boredom, and one who serves quite a heavy read) &lt;em&gt;A Philosophy of Boredom&lt;/em&gt;, one’ll find out that boredom is a social construction of the era that began in the middle of the 18th century. ‘Interesting’ as a concept came to light simultaneously with that of boredom. It was not up to then accepted practice to classify things as being either “boring” or “interesting.” Understandably, such a classification contrasted ‘boring’ with ‘interesting’. That which was interesting was attractive. To be interesting meant not being boring (I’d suggest you read that over a couple of times, I definitely did.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can definitely claim that boredom is a state of discomfort. The most common terms I can substitute it with may be uninteresting, a growth flowered by disinterest and detachment. It is often understood as a catch-all term. It may be understood in its simplicity, termed ‘simple boredom’, a product of temporarily unavoidable and predictable circumstances (being stuck in a bad date? A sad lecture? An awful movie?) as well as ‘existential boredom’ wherein underlies an unrelieved sense of isolation, emptiness, alienation and even helplessness. The main relationship between these two conditions is probably the loose use of the term ‘boredom’. Another close related concept, ‘chronic boredom’, is, one could guess, more like simple boredom, albeit not temporary. If simple boredom is the result of the circumstances we find ourselves in, chronic boredom is a symptom of a lower than normal level in the system of the neurotransmitter dopamine. The notion of chronic boredom is something that is especially the preserve of psychologists. It is measured in a famous test called the Boredom Proneness Scale (BPS) that was devised in 1986 by the now-retired psychologist Norman D Sundberg. Now that you know types of boredom and how fellow psychology enthusiasts are measuring the same, do you still have an unclear picture? Because I sure do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What of a nuanced concept such as this is so difficult to understand? In his book &lt;em&gt;The Will to Meaning&lt;/em&gt;, Viktor Frankl recorded that contemporary man suffered from a deep sense of loss of meaning; a state that he diagnosed as “existential vacuum.” This sense of loss of meaning characterises post-traditional man who cannot make up his mind as to what he wants and what he must do, since tradition no longer dictates what is necessary. If this way is the right way, boredom appears to be the polar opposite of what Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi has famously termed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2012/02/27/purpose-work-love/#flow&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—a state of intense focus one enters whilst absorbed in an enthralling task, when one loses track of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen, if someone were to ask me to spend any more than 10 minutes by myself, with nothing else to think of, I’d go insane, and that brings me to the question: are we as a generation more or less bored than the ones who came before us? Now, every day brings a new article about how to stop the demon of lassitude, or a new invention designed to keep us from ever being at loose ends again. Come to think of it, phones got smart, and so did we, with easy access to more information and entertainment than ever before. Now, every moment one spends being bored—while riding an elevator, or waiting at the doctor’s office, or biding time until your date returns from the restroom—is a moment one doesn’t spend reading a book, skimming the news, or catching up on social media. What I may be suggesting is that, being bored in 2020, might just be a slap in the face of technology. Never again will we have nothing to do. This should be a good thing… Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What in the world goes on in our brains when we get bored? Not just physically, but psychologically? And pray tell, what would go on in our brains if we were to never get bored?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers such as Mashuq Ally have led to a whirlwind romance between authors and the idea of boredom. It has been suggested that something super repetitive that doesn’t need one’s brain to be engaged, that’s when one ignites a network in their brain, one called the ‘default mode’. Neuroscientists have claimed that the default mode is when one does their most original thinking: problem-solving, imagination, empathy, all reside in the house of original thinking. The mind is told to be working as somewhat of a time traveling machine. One goes back and thinks of things that have already conspired and makes sense of them and then extracts lessons from them. They call it autobiographical planning. The unthinking mind-wandering that happens when one is bored takes all the information that has ever entered the brain and makes use of it in innovative ways. In other words: being bored is the difference between being good at &lt;em&gt;Jeopardy!&lt;/em&gt; and being someone who actually &lt;em&gt;uses&lt;/em&gt; the knowledge that one has learned to come up with solutions to fix problems (both of the personal and societal kind).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, boredom is good!? However, boredom too, like other fruits of modernity, has its geography. Despite the fact that no one is safe against boredom, the luxury of being bored is not equally accessible to all societies and strata. And that’s just that. The amount of information we feed ourselves, in this tech driven world, is absurd. No number of hard drives could ever retain all the information I gather from Instagram, or heck, a Buzzfeed video binge. So, why wouldn’t the idea of feeding ourselves more and more information and then never actually doing anything with it seem just perfect? Isn’t that what we’ve been taught ever since we were a kid? I have an art degree and I only have my mum’s concern towards my boredom to thank for it. I mean, I could leave social media, give away my joys in boredom, all so I could self-regulate my thoughts, use the knowledge I’ve previously gained and make the most of it, but wouldn’t that make me Joe from &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; and I don’t reckon he was liked by many. Sketchy Joe is no good, friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a culture obsessed with productivity, boredom seems like a sin, not to mention impossible when so much of the everyday stimuli we take for granted—email, ads, Instagram, Netflix, YouTube (God, I can go on, and on and on)―is bent on robbing us of our attention. But sitting back and doing nothing is, ironically, exactly what you need to do in order to get more done. We were so scared of being bored at all that we failed to appreciate the frightening repercussions of not being bored enough. And I only have Billie to thank for this insight. So, next up (on my playlist and search engine): &lt;em&gt;Where do we go when we fall asleep?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Jain</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="from-the-horses-mouth" /><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">A happy new year, yeah, um, happy? From what I’ve been told, we’re unsubscribing from Jan’20, so, I hope for a good, uneven eleven-month’d year ahead. There has been a huge lapse on my end: I’ve been unable to pen down anything for the longest time. Not because I’m lacking the resources, definitely not the time―what it is, may only be described as dissatisfaction. Dissatisfaction in everything that, I, as an individual of a certain age- living in the country that I live in, belonging to the state I belong to, have had to see. The ghastly past few days and the subsequent coming days, all of it seems too much to bear and I’ve decided I am not to write on it. The awareness that this entire fascist regime (or, situation) in India deserves is beyond anything I can measure, and I can’t remotely do it justice, in no specific way. My bias holds too high and is nowhere near close to being over, not anytime soon. Hence, I’ll use this as a ‘breath of fresh air,’ with how polluted the air I breathe is. In more ways than one.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Premier League’s 2019/20 Rising Stars</title><link href="/PL-Rising-Stars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Premier League’s 2019/20 Rising Stars" /><published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/PL-Rising-Stars</id><content type="html" xml:base="/PL-Rising-Stars">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another example of Brazil’s extraordinary footballing talent, Martinelli was playing in the fourth tier of Brazilian football before moving to north London. He’s as tenacious and fearless as a freeclimber and although he may lack height and stature, his quick feet, range of finishes and mature decision-making are evidence of precocious ability. Still only 18, he’s already scored 3 goals in 5 league starts this season. Clearly, Arsenal have unearthed a gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brandon Williams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The departure and decline of Ashley Young and Luke Shaw respectively has enabled this Manchester United academy graduate to break into the first-team. Rather than looking out of place or short of confidence, which would be typical of a teenager appearing in the most watched league in the world, Williams’ excellent showings have caught the eye. Proficient with both feet, quick, good technically and able to hold his own against the very best, he is the epitome of the modern fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams had no trouble counteracting the threat of Adama Traore, one of the most powerful and skillful wingers in the league, so much so that Adama was forced to switch flanks in the repeat 3rd round FA Cup fixture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emiliano Buendia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Argentine’s stats this season are something to behold. He’s completed the 3rd most take-ons (78) and the 2nd most chances created (68) in the division, with only Kevin De Bruyne having created more goal scoring opportunities. He’s also the only player in the league to have completed 50+ tackles, take-ons and chances created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stats are evidence of his tremendous quality; he works as hard as anyone, while also having the close control and passing ability of an elite playmaker. With Norwich almost certain to go down, the 22-year-old should be at the top of many clubs’ shopping lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Todd Cantwell&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The England U21 international has been another bright spark for a side who’ve been bottom for most of the season, having popped up with 6 goals and 2 assists so far. Born and bred in Norfolk, and a product of the Norwich academy, he’s a talented dribbler with clever passing and movement which makes him a real handful for defenders. He is another Norwich player who’s been linked with a move away pending their imminent relegation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tammy Abraham&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After scoring 25 goals in the Championship with Aston Villa last season, the 22-year-old returned to his parent club this season and has donned the number 9 shirt for Chelsea accordingly. Tall, quick and skillful, his quality is undoubted after scoring 13 goals in 23 appearances so far this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His clever movement in addition to fine link-up play means he will always pose a threat, and his performances this season have deservedly led to an England call-up. With Harry Kane facing a long injury layoff, Abraham will relish the opportunity to lead the line for the Three Lions at the upcoming European Championships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Japhet Tanganga&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanganga had to wait patiently to be given his first league start for Tottenham after impressing in pre-season against the likes of Real Madrid and Juventus. After being thrust in for his Premier League debut against Liverpool earlier this month, the 20-year-old followed it up with another outstanding display against Middlesbrough in the FA Cup in which he was named Man of the Match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily a centre-back, he’s so far been deployed at right-back and left-back in addition to his favoured role, and some have even gone so far to suggest that he could be an option in defensive midfield. His positional sense fused with his astute reading of play makes him a top-class centre back, but his speed and comfort on the ball makes him adept in both fullback positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing the elite Belgian centre-back pairing of Vertonghen and Alderweireld will be no easy task but supporters and staff alike are confident that Tanganga can cement himself in the Spurs backline for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dean Henderson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 22-year-old is a stalwart of Chris Wilder’s Sheffield United team and has been key to their success over the last 2 seasons. With current England ‘keeper Jordan Pickford flattering to deceive, many fans are calling for the in-form Blades goalie to replace Pickford between the sticks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The on-loan Manchester United ‘keeper has conceded just 20 goals in 23 appearances this season, racking up 8 clean sheets. This trumps both Pickford and Nick Pope, who are Henderson’s main rivals for the England number 1 jersey - Pickford has conceded 35 in 24 appearances with 6 clean sheets, while Pope has let in 38 in 23 with 7 clean sheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henderson’s save percentage is superior too. Of the 15 Premier League goalkeepers to have saved 50+ shots this season, Henderson has the highest save percentage (74.68%). Meanwhile, Pickford and Pope’s save percentages are 64% and 60% respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main gripe with Henderson is that his passing stats are not particularly attractive. While Pickford has completed 56.77% of his passes this season, Pope has completed 38.29%, but Henderson’s passing accuracy is just 33.72%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southgate is a keen proponent of playing out from the back and it seems unlikely that he will replace Pickford between the sticks, whom he’s trusted for the last 2 years, but there’s certainly a strong case for Henderson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reece James&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This youngster is a phenomenon; it’s rarely the case that a player is able to combine technical excellence with physical power and strength, but James is a special case. Though he’s just 19, James plays well beyond his years. It is no wonder why he was named Chelsea’s Academy Player of the Year 2017/18, Wigan’s Player of the Month 4 times in the same season, and in the EFL Championship Team of the Season 2018/19. Although his defensive positioning could be improved upon, he’s often the most creative player on the pitch with his magnificent passing and unrivalled crossing ability. He’s always an outlet on the right-hand side with his pace and intelligent forward runs, and in addition to his direct dribbling, he possesses a menacing shot, his strength is devastating and he has no trouble getting stuck in and timing tackles to perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James’ competencies allow him to excel in a variety of positions, from his favoured right-back role to centre-back to central midfield. His talent and versatility is so noteworthy that it led Wigan’s manager, Paul Cook, to proclaim that “Reece James could play in goal, he’s that outstanding!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England have a flurry of top-class right backs at the moment, and Reece James is making a case for himself to be the most complete. Jermaine Jenas on Match Of The Day described him as a hybrid between Trent Alexander-Arnold, Kyle Walker, Kieran Trippier and Aaron Wan-Bissaka because of the way in which James possesses the best qualities of them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jack Grealish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grealish was still a boy with unleashed potential when his side were relegated from the top-flight 4 years ago, however, this time round he is a fully fledged man and has been a shining light for a team who are among the dark depths of possible relegation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to effectively break the lines with marvellous dribbling and an eye for a pass, he also tracks back and works hard defensively, while also being a first-class finisher who’s adept with both feet. The talisman of his boyhood club has been one of the standout players in the league and his presence significantly increases Villa’s chances of staying in the division. It beggars belief as to how he’s not yet been called up for England, with seemingly everyone but Southgate praising his remarkable ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 24, he has all the necessary qualities to succeed wherever he goes, and a big money move is surely on the cards this summer. Tottenham will be rueing the fact that they came close to securing his signature in the summer of 2018 for a fee that would’ve been paltry compared to his value now as he would’ve gone a long way towards replacing Christian Eriksen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.premierleague.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.premierleague.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ali Abdi</name></author><category term="sports" /><category term="football" /><category term="headline" /><summary type="html">Gabriel Martinelli</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Durga Puja: Cultural or Religious Festival?</title><link href="/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Durga Puja: Cultural or Religious Festival?" /><published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival">&lt;p&gt;Being a Bengali girl who has lived her entire life up to the age of 18 in the Eastern state of West Bengal in India, visiting any other Indian state inevitably results in a major culture shock for me. Much of what we do and how we live our lives is vastly different from the rest of India. These divergences are more apparent to me now that I live in the state of Goa, and yet they always prove to be surprising. To give an example: when one of my friends asked me why I did not abstain from non-vegetarian food during Durga Puja, the most important festival for Bengalis, I was taken aback. I love non-vegetarian food and so do most of my people. Stepping away from enjoying a specific kind of food during a festival when we are expected to enjoy ourselves to the fullest did not make any sense to me. It seems, however, that that is certainly not how the rest of India looks at Hindu festivals. The way we celebrate our holy days is poles apart from what other Hindu cultures envision a festival to be. Not only that, the way we look at our own methods of celebration changes from age to age, to suit the trends of the era we live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu festivals in general are very colourful and often involve various rites and rituals. However, Hinduism in itself is perceived very differently by people of varying backgrounds. The first of these distinctions is the caste system which, very broadly, categorises Hindus into Brahmins (the highest caste), Kshatriyas, Vaishyas and Shudras (the lowest caste). Over the years, these castes have also faced segregation into multiple sub-castes. The kind of rituals that are performed, or more accurately, allowed to be performed depends on one’s caste. While many claim that the divisions have eroded over time, countless continue to be very strict with the customs and traditions and uphold the caste system as an integral part of their religion. There are also restrictions based on gender and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, the aforementioned customs and traditions have developed very differently in the multitude of diverse Hindu communities that reside in India and abroad. The same festival celebrated by different communities may involve the employment of varying mechanisms for similar rites and rituals. Very often, different communities celebrate different festivals and it is not unlikely to find an individual hailing from one community to have absolutely no clue about a festival that is very important to another community. Hindus, as a collective, believe in 330 million different deities and the various festivals are primarily celebrated to worship one of these gods or goddesses. Each community celebrates multiple festivals but one of them is almost like an identifying feature of the same; just as Christmas is for Christians and Eid is for Muslims. For Bengali Hindus, &lt;em&gt;Durga Puja *or *Pujo&lt;/em&gt; is the most important festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Durga Puja is celebrated every year by primarily the people of Bengal, Assam, Tripura and Odisha in autumn. The phrase “Durga Puja” literally translates to “the worship of Goddess Durga” and it marks the mythological event of Mother Goddess Durga’s win over the malicious shape-shifting demon, Mahisasura. The goddess is a symbol of “Good” for many and is worshipped by Hindus across the world in her different forms or avatars. In my home province, it is certainly more of a cultural event than a religious one. Bengalis from across the world drive, ride and fly in to celebrate this auspicious occasion with their families. The crowds at the railway stations and airports across the state of West Bengal are unimaginably large around this time. For Bengalis, Maa Durga is a member of their own family and they need to be there to greet her when she arrives. The word “Maa” translates to “mother”, but Bengalis often use the word as a term of endearment for the female members of their families. The story goes that Durga is a daughter of our mortal family who married Shiva, another Hindu god and thus, now resides in her heavenly abode in the Himalayas. She visits her parents’ family (us) once a year and this visitation is what Bengalis celebrate as Durga Puja.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festival is primarily celebrated over five days, although traditionally, it was meant to be a ten day event. The last five days of the aforementioned ten days is what is celebrated with the craze and passion often associated with the festivity. These five days are referred to as Sashti, Saptami, Ashtami, Navami and Dashami which literally translates to six to ten, respectively, in Sanskrit. These names are generally used to mark the corresponding days of any Hindu lunar month. The festival is a big tourist magnet and the celebrations often start much before Sashti. Several months leading up to the festival is spent in preparations. Idols of Goddess Durga and her four children: Saraswati, Laxmi, Kartik and Ganesh are placed inside beautifully decorated pandals (a kind of a religious marquee). Various kinds of rites and rituals are performed over the days of pujo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why I choose to call it a cultural festival rather than a religious one has its roots in the manner in which the festival is celebrated. While many Hindus across India abstain from non-vegetarian food and indulge in rigorous rituals and worship during auspicious times such as these, many Bengalis choose to go about it all differently. It is an occasion of happiness for Bengalis as Durga is returning to meet them with her children and they hardly see a reason to refrain from things that make them happy - good non-vegetarian food and fancy clothing, among other things. Besides, Bengalis spend the months leading up to the festival in rigorous preparation for Durga’s arrival. They go shopping for new “fashion-forward” clothes, get their hair and nails done and, of course, invest a considerable amount of their time planning whom to hang out with, where to eat and what pandals to visit during the days of pujo itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born and brought up in Kolkata, the capital of West Bengal, and every year I witness my city light up in colourful lights for the festival. It is genuinely impossible to express the feeling that comes with it in words. “Parar bondhura” (friends who live in the same neighbourhood) come together to decorate the pandals keeping a theme in mind. Several events are organised and they cater to a seemingly endless number of interests. There are dance competitions, drawing contests, cooking tournaments, fashion shows and so on and so forth. There are also competitions meant to felicitate the best decorated pandals across the state. These pandals are often artistic masterpieces and assume themes from the most abstract to the most obvious. The masses spend the nights giving these pandals a visit and conveying their intellectual interpretation of the theme and their assessment of how well the artists have brought the theme to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing about it is the fact that it is not a festival for the Bengali Hindus alone. All are welcome, and many Muslims, Christians, Parsis, Sikhs and people of other religious backgrounds who reside in Bengal get themselves involved in the festivities alongside the Hindus. For instance, some of the idol artists are Muslims, who form the majority of the population apart from the Hindus. Numerous members of the Islamic community in Bargachia, about 30 km from Kolkata, have devoted their lives to the subtle art of making Maa Durga’s lustrous hair. This has been in practice for at least five decades. Besides, people of all religions can be seen spending their nights pandal hopping, helping Hindus in their preparation for the rituals and sometimes even taking part in them. People of other faiths are no less important than Bengali Hindus themselves when it comes to organising and celebrating the festival that is so close to their hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navratri is celebrated majorly in Northern India on the days Bengalis celebrate Durga Pujo. It is the celebration of the nine forms of Goddess Durga and comprises 9 days of rigorous rites and rituals and living under restrictions like abstaining from non-vegetarian food, fasting and so on. These rituals are often limited only to the Hindus and sometimes restricted to just a single caste among them - the Brahmins. The people do indulge in activities like dancing and feasting, mostly at the end of the festival. Although Navratri has a grandeur of its own, nothing can really match the intensity, colour and craze of Durga Pujo in Bengal and thus, spending Pujo away from home is undoubtedly among the most difficult things Bengalis can be expected to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have established that Durga Pujo is indeed celebrated very differently by Bengalis, as compared to the people of the other states, let’s talk about how the manner of celebration changes among Bengalis themselves every year. As I have previously mentioned in one of my own articles, Bengalis are very fond of political and societal revolutions and reforms. They love change and they try to do everything they can to bring about or, at the very least, support a change for the betterment of their lives, the lives of those around them and their state. This attitude finds reflection in Bengali art and literature. Bengali Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore’s poems and novels are heavily influenced by his critical attitude towards the western concept of nationalism and celebrated pre-independence era Bengali poet Kazi Nazrul Islam’s poems, which led many to overcome their fear of the British and to take a strong stance against them during the colonial rule. This trend exists today too. Artforms like poetry, novels, songs and, of course, pandal decorations bring to light the various issues that has infected Indian society. Themes highlighting the crisis due to the implementation of the National Register for Citizens, the Pulwama Attack and other political issues were major crowd pullers last year. Themes based on social issues are no less in number and are equally appreciated. They have one motive: to inspire change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Hinduism often fails to address issues surrounding LGBTQIA+ community. In fact, the transgender community is often looked down upon and gay relationships are shunned by the majority of Indian society. The fact that gay sex was legalised only in 2018 doesn’t help the case for them either. The Dum Dum Park Tarul Dal Durga Pujo committee, a group of pujo organisers  in Kolkata, believed that Hinduism at heart supports and loves all kinds of genders. To spread their message, they had a LGBTQIA+ themed pujo last year. They stated their theme as “Tumi dekho nari purush, ami dekhi shudui manush” (you see women and men, I see only humans). Not only did they have an idol which was half female (Durga) and half male (Krishna), they decorated the pandal to showcase the pain of being in a closet or being discriminated against for not being cis-gendered or straight. Hundreds flocked to this pandal to appreciate the artwork and the emotion around the idea behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While global warming skeptics around the world continue to win elections and lead nations, the poor but highly talented artists in Bengal decorated the pandal of Dum Dum Park with artwork showcasing what the world would be like in the years to come: commoners carrying oxygen cylinders around all the time, government rations including oxygen supply and scientists desperately trying to keep the last plant on earth alive. They topped it off with sculptures of the goddess wearing oxygen masks. These extremely graphic depiction of the possible consequences of our ways sent a very strong message to the huge crowd that flooded the pandal at all times: our planet is dying and we need to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the pujo of 2019, artwork wasn’t the only way the Bengalis decided to get people thinking about their ways and the society. Their beliefs found a place in the rituals too. Proposals to change the wording of the various religious chants are fairly regular these days and not out of the ordinary. For example, it is fairly common for the traditional invocation requesting a son to be replaced by a more modern one merely seeking a child, regardless of sex. However, this year what shocked everyone was when the Beleghata 33 Pally Durga Puja committee, another pujo organiser, decided to play the &lt;em&gt;Azan&lt;/em&gt; (a form of a Muslim call for ritual prayer) in their pandal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the rituals during Durga Pujo involves praying to a young woman or “kumari”. Traditionally, she is expected to belong to the Brahmin caste (the highest caste). While this rule lost its relevance a long time back, she is still, at least popularly, expected to be Hindu in the very least. However, to join the fight for communal harmony, Bidhannagar Ramkrishna Vivekananda Kendra, Salt Lake, another pujo organiser in Kolkata decided to have a Muslim “kumari”. Having Muslim “kumaris” is not an absolutely unheard of concept though, despite what one might assume, given Bengal’s history of communal violence and post-Independence partitioning of the state on primarily religious lines. Bengali Hindu spiritual leader Ramkrishna Paramahamsa converted to Islam but continued to preach “Joto mot, toto poth” (the doctrine that all paths lead to God) to the people of 19th century Bengal. His disciple, famous freedom fighter Swami Vivekananda worshipped a young Muslim girl as “kumari” in pre-Independence India. Besides, Belur Math, which serves as the headquarters for Ramkrishna Mission (a Hindu spiritual organisation founded by Vivekananda himself), houses a Mazhar within its perimeters. This inclusivity is magnified by certain groups of Muslims from Kolkata and other Muslim majority districts in Bengal when they come together to celebrate Durga Pujo themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This practice is not just limited to the state of West Bengal. The “Blood Drop” club of the Sipahijala district of Tripura was in the news in 2015 when they elected a Muslim president for themselves to organise their annual Durga Pujo. Hasem Ali, a devout Muslim and an artist from Darrang district of Assam became famous in 2018 because of his unusual practices in terms of art: he made Hindu idols including those of Goddess Durga for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often use Durga Pujo as a platform to speak out against regressive religious ideas and taboos and pave the way for change. While for the longest time sex workers were exempted from the celebrations, the last couple of years brought drastic changes in favour of them. Sonagachi, India’s largest red-light district, organised a theme Pujo for the first time in 2019. Although, all the celebrations are centred on worshipping a goddess, various taboos restrict many women’s access to the festivities. The hard crusts of these orthodox Hindu rules have, however, eroded over the years and barely exist today among most Bengali communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivities of Durga Pujo end with “shidur khela” on Dashami, which literally translates to “vermillion game”. Married women, draped in (usually, but not always) beautiful white sarees with red borders smear vermillion on each other’s faces. This part of the celebration is traditionally limited to married women. Sex workers, transgenders, divorcees and widows are not given a place. This taboo exists even today. &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Times of India&lt;/em&gt; launched a “No conditions apply” campaign in Kolkata with an aim to bring about a change in 2019. As a result, marginalised women from the LGBTQIA+ community, single women and so on and so forth were invited to participate in “shidur khela”. Hundreds supported the cause to change this 400 year-old custom to be more inclusive and with the great strength in participation, the movement was a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most atheists believe that religion is useless and, in its true form, rather harmful to human society, the people of Bengal continue to use religious ceremonies to raise political and social issues and attempt to usher in change. The marriage of religion with the Bengali culture and society allows the promotion of unorthodox ideologies like communal harmony and inclusivity not just among the privileged and educated, but also among the downtrodden. While the world continues to think that religious traditions either shouldn’t be changed or simply cannot be changed, Bengalis beg to differ. They use religion as a medium to influence change while changing religious practices themselves to suit the millennium. They bear testimony to the fact that change in all realms of human life is indeed within the grasps of possibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oindrila Ghosh</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Being a Bengali girl who has lived her entire life up to the age of 18 in the Eastern state of West Bengal in India, visiting any other Indian state inevitably results in a major culture shock for me. Much of what we do and how we live our lives is vastly different from the rest of India. These divergences are more apparent to me now that I live in the state of Goa, and yet they always prove to be surprising. To give an example: when one of my friends asked me why I did not abstain from non-vegetarian food during Durga Puja, the most important festival for Bengalis, I was taken aback. I love non-vegetarian food and so do most of my people. Stepping away from enjoying a specific kind of food during a festival when we are expected to enjoy ourselves to the fullest did not make any sense to me. It seems, however, that that is certainly not how the rest of India looks at Hindu festivals. The way we celebrate our holy days is poles apart from what other Hindu cultures envision a festival to be. Not only that, the way we look at our own methods of celebration changes from age to age, to suit the trends of the era we live in.</summary></entry></feed>