<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-02T22:50:27+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Arrival of the New Wave Generational Quarterbacks: What Will They Possibly Bring?</title><link href="/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Arrival of the New Wave Generational Quarterbacks: What Will They Possibly Bring?" /><published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks">&lt;p&gt;The centerpiece of any NFL team is the quarterback and a new wave of quarterbacks is on the verge of taking over. Over the next few years or so, the NFL is going to undergo a transition phase that, some purists say, has been long-awaited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hall of Fame shoe-ins like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/tom-brady-surprisingly-hints-that-retirement-could-come-as-soon-as-next-year/&quot;&gt;Tom Brady&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/drew-brees-hints-that-his-retirement-could-be-coming-sooner-than-anyone-thinks/&quot;&gt;Drew Brees&lt;/a&gt; only have a couple years left in the tank at most. Other legendary quarterbacks like Aaron Rodgers and Ben Roethlisberger are also very soon expected to bring down curtains on their illustrious careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these Super Bowl winning quarterbacks have always been the focal points in the media year after year after year. With age and injury combining forcefully to put an ultimate end date on all of their careers, the NFL needs new quarterbacks to fill the spotlight and it needs them soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we going to see a new wave of elite quarterbacks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is quite possibly. New, explosive offenses are being led by young quarterbacks and they have taken the league by storm. Collegiate, pass-heavy offenses are quickly being adopted by NFL offensive coordinators because of the sense of familiarity they present to rookie quarterbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the breathtaking 2018-2019 season Drew Brees had, Patrick Mahomes stole the show during his second year in the league and first year as a starter for the Kansas City Chiefs. Mahomes threw over &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001005879/article/patrick-mahomes-tosses-50th-touchdown-pass-of-2018&quot;&gt;50 touchdown passes&lt;/a&gt; which has only ever been done twice, by Peyton Manning and Tom Brady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with Patrick Mahomes, Jared Goff has found his home in Los Angeles with the Rams. Goff led the Rams to back to back NFC West division championships and will be the solidified quarterback for the Rams when they finally move into their new multi-billion dollar stadium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2018-2019 NFL season the Rams and Chiefs stole the show because of their explosive, pass-heavy offense and it led them to division championships. After 16 games, both Mahomes and Goff showcased their tremendous talents, but it also proved that there is a new formula to winning in the National Football League. And what the heart of that formula comprises of is, to say the least, simple. A new, young quarterback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the league be out of Hall of Fame Quarterbacks’ soon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the greats in the league today retire in a few short years, Mahomes, Mayfield, and even Jared Goff will most likely be referred to as the best in the game. In their young careers, these three quarterbacks have broken records that nobody in their sane mind saw coming. Mahomes is the youngest quarterback to throw for 50 touchdowns and 5,000 passing yards in a single season. Baker Mayfield has resurrected the dysfunctional Browns franchise by breaking the record for most passing touchdowns as a rookie. And if they stick to what has provided them with initial success, they can only get better along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the newcomers surpass the veterans?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cam Newton and Matt Ryan have solidified starting jobs with their respected teams, and they both have had similar success. Both quarterbacks won an MVP award and each made a trip to a Super Bowl, and they both came up short. Now, a couple years removed from their prime, injury and other internal issues have crippled the success of both quarterbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other notable quarterbacks who have a lot of experience in the league but do not qualify as championship-caliber players include Matt Stafford, Ryan Tannehill and Andy Dalton. They have combined for seven playoff appearances and still have yet to win one. With young quarterbacks embracing leadership and implementing new fast paced offenses, veteran quarterbacks like these three are becoming irrelevant faster than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all said and happening, it’s a very, very exciting time for the National Football League and the fans only hope they get to witness some high-quality skills out there. Onward and upward.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tyler Pesavento</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">The centerpiece of any NFL team is the quarterback and a new wave of quarterbacks is on the verge of taking over. Over the next few years or so, the NFL is going to undergo a transition phase that, some purists say, has been long-awaited.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Editorial: On The Importance of Sex</title><link href="/Importance-of-sex" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Editorial: On The Importance of Sex" /><published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Importance-of-sex</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Importance-of-sex">&lt;p&gt;It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: &lt;em&gt;“WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!”&lt;/em&gt; That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book &lt;i&gt;Portnoy’s Complaint&lt;/i&gt; (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s &lt;i&gt;120 Days of Sodom&lt;/i&gt;) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a brilliant place to find a conversation about sex that is stimulating (in the right way) is the comments section of any porn video (it’s also a good way of ensuring the video is a good one!). The things people say (and don’t say) about sex in these comments is so profoundly revealing (never thought I’d use the word profound when writing about sex!). These comments tell us that people don’t just watch porn to simply &lt;em&gt;“bust a nut or yaw yaw the sisterhood”&lt;/em&gt;. Masturbation is a very sensuous thing in our lives: It relieves boredom, which is perennially the human mind’s most wicked enemy and it gives us the opportunity to enjoy the feelings (and hormones) that sex brings with the most important person in our erotic lives: ourselves. Therefore, it is no wonder that people have such strikingly specific criticisms of the acting in the video, or the stilettos of the female porn star, or the absolutely unrealistic time for which the male porn star lasts. People put up comments stating all sorts of things, from the things they found funny like the orgasm face of the actors or the scenes they felt where outright bizarre like one where they felt the porn star’s screaming was extremely unappealing as it sounded like a &lt;em&gt;“donkey braying”&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porn is about the deep voyeurism that inhabits the human mind, it is about finding release (literally) and for that one needs a good experience. Put it this way: when we want to release our bowels we want a clean toilet that smells good, when we want to fulfil our hunger we want food that tastes good, and when we want to avoid the cold we want a jumper that looks good. If we want quality in all other things, should it surprise anyone that we want porn to be more than just people “doing it” with each other? Good pornography is important for the same reason that anything is important to human beings, we are not just Plato’s “featherless birds” and we don’t just have sex in caves (HA!). Unlike the plots and scripts of most porn movies, human beings are interesting in nature, and their erotic lives reflect that via their desires from pornography. There’s a reason why &lt;i&gt;Playboy&lt;/i&gt; Magazine, instead of just having any other nudes, had Marilyn Monroe’s nudes. And there is a reason why Pornhub has reported a phenomenal rise in the consumption of incest porn by…(drum-roll)…millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex as an activity is about satisfying the human imagination—otherwise, a few grunts and no foreplay would have kept everyone happy. On the issue of ‘grunts’, we all know that men can have very few problems when it ‘comes’ to (pardon the pun) reaching climax, whereas there is a whole body of feminist literature on how women don’t really climax at all most of the time. The common form that the female orgasm takes is due to clitoral stimulation, and the reason why women do not really come due to vaginal stimulation is because, well, men don’t usually last long enough. This creates an obviously skewered power dynamic in sex, where men are able to “unload” ever so easily and women are left feeling constantly under-appreciated. I don’t mean to say that this means men are near-constantly aroused pigs who pay no heed to the needs of their female partners, although there is truth in that contention. My point here is simply that without a good amount of foreplay and some good oral sex, our sexual activities with all their imaginative passion can simply end up being a dull series of painful thrusts for one whole half of the human population—and sex must be far more than that if in these feminist times we men are to redeem ourselves for having treated women as objects of sex for thousands of years. Ancient India, being a culture at a stupendous height of civilisation, was acutely aware of the consequences of denying women the beauty of an orgasm. As Wendy Doniger, a controversial yet revered Indologist, points out, even the legendary &lt;i&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/i&gt; is clear on the fact that women must orgasm first, given how easy it is for men to do so. The message is clear and has been clear for more than a thousand years: boys, at least try to find the fabled G-spot once in a while instead of just seeking blowjobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power dynamics of sex bring up a very curious issue with specific regard to sex between homosexual men. It is difficult to accurately describe how significantly being either a ‘top’ or a ‘bottom’ has an effect on the masculinity of gay men (MEN!!). The power politics in that part of human sexuality has assumed new proportions with the world’s gay community bidding adieu to the stereotype of the “camp” gay man and welcoming a more traditionally masculine homosexual male as more desirable. As Kevin Troughton &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/nov/30/the-end-of-camp-straight-acting-gay&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“very few find [camp] sexually attractive. That limp-wristed, bitchy queen might be hilarious, but you wouldn’t want him as a boyfriend, or even as a one-night stand.”&lt;/em&gt; The fact is “bottoming” gay men have always been stereotyped into the camp category, facing potentially even internalised homophobia due to their perceived passivity in the gay community. And now with the rise in the desirability of the straight-acting gay alpha male, it would appear that all men who wish to receive anal sex will potentially have greater issues relating to dominance and estimations of their own masculinity. Funny enough, all of this simply reinforces the words of Oscar Wilde: &lt;em&gt;“Everything in the world is about sex except sex. Sex is about power”&lt;/em&gt;. It is slightly hilarious but definitely unsurprising that men having sex with other men is where power dynamics take centre stage, after all, the ‘male ego’ manifests itself most strongly in front of other men!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between love and sex is complicated (well, of course). And if you have read a bit of Freud (he has to be mentioned in a discussion on sex, you know, #respect), sex and love are both about your mum. Obviously, his Oedipus Complex and theories on the development of libido are a bit bogus, but his underlying assertion that we learn how to have relationships primarily from our parents makes a lot of intuitive sense. Parents give their children a reality, they define what human interaction means for them and they do so simply because that’s how it is, for good or for bad. This means people’s relationships are (to a degree) shaped by the experiences given to them by their childhood and their parents. The problem is that people fall in love with the people they have sex with quite often and vice versa! And people falling in love leads to all sorts of problems like marriage, infidelity, drama and the responsibility to take care of children. The very point of sex leads to relationships that are determined on factors outside your control (your mum!), and lead to a sexual rut (your children) with added responsibilities of bringing up another human being—so that the cycle can continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is definitely weird talking about sex and extremely difficult to treat it with the sensitivity and respect it deserves. But it certainly is fun to think about and research on something that is so goddamn brilliant. I mean, my research showed me that orgasms could be had by brain dead people if the right nerves are stimulated! And it was facts and observations like this that made my task ever so out-of-control. Yes, sex is important, I could see that, but what is the common thread that makes it all ever so important? And why? I think I have chanced upon a simple answer to these questions: sex is humanity’s deepest desires manifested in the most physical of acts, and for that very reason it’s going to be more than just a simple act. Adieu!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The Oxy Moron</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: “WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!” That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book Portnoy’s Complaint (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s 120 Days of Sodom) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trump’s ‘New African Policy’: Can US weave diplomatic tapestries using Chinese threads?</title><link href="/trumps-new-african-policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trump’s ‘New African Policy’: Can US weave diplomatic tapestries using Chinese threads?" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/trumps-new-african-policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/trumps-new-african-policy">&lt;p&gt;On December 14, 2018, the US National Security Adviser, John Bolton revealed Trump’s ‘New African Strategy’, which aims to advance U.S. trade and investment, suppress terrorism and conflict, and ensure that US aid in the continent is well spent. This policy, entitled &lt;i&gt;Prosper Africa&lt;/i&gt;, is perhaps the Trump’s administration’s biggest policy decision vis-à-vis the African continent. Yet, many critics detected the familiar rhetoric of the Cold War return in subtle hues with this policy. This is because, rather than focusing on developing Africa, this policy has taken the narrative of simply countering China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his speech at the Heritage Foundation, Bolton spoke of the “predatory” policies of China in Africa, which are led by opaque terms of loans and have given China unfair leverage over the national governments in Africa. Over the last two years, American foreign policy had turned into a listless farce, with no meaning or purpose, as far as Africa was concerned. Contrary to previous administrations, Trump’s inward-looking politics left no space for new initiatives to be launched and left existing partnerships lurching in confusion, disarray, and disregard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Chinese Threat&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no question about the fact that a renewed and rigorous policy towards Africa was long overdue. According to the African Development Bank, African states need to invest $68 billion to $108 billion more each year in infrastructure to boost growth and create enough jobs for their booming populations. Thus, when China came knocking on Africa’s doors, with ambitions of infrastructural development, large-scale investments, cultural exchange, trade and prosperity, Africa didn’t go over the terms and conditions as well as one would hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being orphaned by the US and adopted by China simultaneously, Africa witnessed an immense growth in Chinese capital. According to the consulting firm McKinsey, more than 10,000 Chinese companies now do business on the continent, earning approximately $180 billion each year. Although the United States still has more foreign direct investment stock in Africa, Chinese investment in the region is growing fast. In 2009, China overtook the United States to become Africa’s biggest trading partner. It has also taken over the Western superpower as the largest creditor of the continent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) underway, the Chinese global trading zones are bound to increase many-fold. With even greater lending to developing countries and promises of trade, exports and economic growth, China is fulfilling its destiny of being a superpower of the East. And, to reclaim Africa, the US’s strategy has finally been kick-started. Even Bolton’s words at the conference were foreboding and warned of foreign threats, instead of being optimistic and growth-driven.  Particularly, he said that “Great power competitors, namely China and Russia, are rapidly expanding their financial and political influence across Africa. They are deliberately and aggressively targeting their investments in the region to gain a competitive advantage over the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Flight to dominance via Africa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump’s policy has the following three major objectives:
Advancing U.S. trade and commercial ties with nations across the region to the benefit of both the United States and Africa;
Countering the threat from Radical Islamic Terrorism and violent conflict.
Ensuring that U.S. taxpayer dollars for aid are used efficiently and effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This announcement has followed the signing of the BUILD Act by President Trump. The Act provides new authorities to the Overseas Private Investment Corporation (OPIC), including doubling its lending cap to 60 billion USD. ‘Prosper Africa’ will lead to over 1 billion USD in new investments and greater private-public partnerships in the region to flourish growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the policy is well suited to the situation, it is still being viewed as ‘poorly targeted’. This is because Bolton’s speech missed all the usual cries of human rights, democracy and freedom. Instead of posing as the harbinger of liberty and peace, as US policy has done since the end of Cold War, this one blatantly stands against the advances of Russia and China. Throughout his speech, Bolton mentioned the evils of China and Russia, which are making enormous investments by fooling African nations with opaque credit terms, bribes and strategic use of debt. He also criticised several UN peacekeeping missions, which have received enormous American funds, but to no fruition. His speech, thus, disregarded the commercial, economic, political and military advances of China and Russia and admitted that the US’s efforts in the region have yielded no substantial political or economic results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Trump administration views this policy as the best way to secure American interests in the region while ensuring sustained development, previous governments have used multilateral approaches instead. This means that in order to achieve peace and economic growth, previous governments saw China as a partner, instead of a global adversary. Obama, in particular, saw China’s interest in the region, even via American initiatives, as a medium to further bolster growth. Many experts feel that a triangular approach to the African question, wherein both U.S and China could invest in partnership, rather than in competition, would have been more desirable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one cannot ignore that there has been a significant shift in the positions of both, the US and China, on the global stage. China indeed has been aggressively advancing its economic and military interests in Africa and Asia and perhaps, a strong political move like this was what the US needed to reiterate its own position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America has finally built a concrete structure for its African policy. Although there are still many blanks that need to be filled, there are several desirable changes that are coming about, especially, reduction in expenditure on UN projects that have not led to any tangible results and increase in investment-driven projects, led by economic and commercial interests. With the trade war first and the African policy now, it seems that U.S. and China are diverging on their paths to achieve global growth and prosperity. Globalisation and planetary collaboration are increasingly taking a back seat and national superiority is coming to the forefront again. Whether or not this works out for Africa, China and the US is yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ashima Makhija</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">On December 14, 2018, the US National Security Adviser, John Bolton revealed Trump’s ‘New African Strategy’, which aims to advance U.S. trade and investment, suppress terrorism and conflict, and ensure that US aid in the continent is well spent. This policy, entitled Prosper Africa, is perhaps the Trump’s administration’s biggest policy decision vis-à-vis the African continent. Yet, many critics detected the familiar rhetoric of the Cold War return in subtle hues with this policy. This is because, rather than focusing on developing Africa, this policy has taken the narrative of simply countering China.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Siddis: The Black Rulers of India</title><link href="/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Siddis: The Black Rulers of India" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India">&lt;p&gt;Deep in the annals of Indian history, there lies a long-forgotten tale of daring heroes, who, although foreign to the land, quickly got assimilated into her blood and added to her magnificence. This is the story of the first African rulers of India, the Siddis. India has long been acting as a magnet, drawing to her shores communities from lands afar which have flourished and prospered in her. Amongst these communities were the Africans who although arrived as slaves, still emerged as the mightiest of rulers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journeying all the way from Abyssinia, their motherland, through the treacherous waters, the ‘habshis’ (another term used for addressing the Siddis, descendants of the Bantu people) arrived at the Deccan as a part of the ongoing lucrative slave trade by the Arab merchants. The very distinguished Moroccan scholar, Ibn Batutta recounts how the habshis were reputed for being formidable, such that the presence of even a single habshi in a ship would make the pirates turn away from it. While most of the habshis arrived as slaves and soldiers for the armies of the Delhi Sultanate, not all remained so, and some even climbed the social ladder to become dignified nobles. One of such nobles was Jamal-ud-din Yakut, a close confidant of Razia Sultan (the first female monarch to assume the ascendancy over the Delhi Sultanate), who enjoyed a privileged position as the Amir al-Umara (Amir of Amirs), under her patronage. His growing proximity with the Sultana, along with his racial humbleness, earned him great spite from the Turkish clerics, especially Malik Ikhtiar-ud-din Altunia, who led a violent rebellion against the two, ultimately culminating in his tragic end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also other Abyssinian men like the governor general Malik Sarwar who even went to the extent of laying down the foundation of a sovereign state called Jaunpur, which survived for nearly a century as a symbol of cultural amity and unity. Furthermore, some even established themselves in the eastern part of the subcontinent by dethroning the Sultans of Bengal. The very impressive Siddi Sayed mosque in Ahmedabad was also sanctioned for construction by a Habshi in 1572. Other noteworthy cases of Abyssinians entering the political limelight include Suhail Khan, saviour of the beleaguered Queen of Ahmadnagar, Chand Bibi, who was at war with the Mughals, and Yakut Khan, a navy admiral commissioned by the great Mughal emperor, Aurangzeb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these achievements are indeed great, nowhere had the habshis thrived as much as they did in the Deccan region. Many soared up sky-high, attaining extraordinary heights in the administration and military, because of their physical competency and fidelity. They no longer remained subdued, and with social ascendency, came greater power and privilege at their disposal. Such is the story of another Habshi, Malik Ambar, who held the post of the prime minister of the Ahmadnagar Sultanate. Born in the Oromo tribe, he was sold out at a very young age to an Arab merchant and passed through the hands of several owners to ultimately arrive at India and write his own destiny, where he converted to Islam and was renamed Ambar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 1571 that Ambar arrived at the Deccan where he served under a new master, the Peshwa of Ahmadnagar, who was himself a black man. This must have presented to Ambar a tempting prospect of rising above slavery to cease power and wealth. After the death of his master, he established an independent army (with the help of other habshi lords) and provided his valuable services to Adil Shah for which he was even conferred the title of Malik. But his most impressive accomplishment by far was during the invasions of the 1590’s, where he led a pluralistic force of several thousands under his command against the Mughals. His animosity towards the Mughals was especially long drawn, against whom he fought bravely to establish Nizam Shah on the throne of Ahmadnagar as the lawful monarch. Apart from being an able administrator, Malik Ambar is also accredited with engineering the military tactic of guerrilla warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donning Indian clothes and speaking the language of the land, the Siddis over time have coalesced into the culture and tradition of the subcontinent. However, contrary to the honour and fame attained as a part of history, the Siddis of present-day India remain a secluded community. Maintaining their distance from the mainstream culture and society, they live in tiny clusters scattered around the states of Karnataka, Maharashtra, and Gujarat. Having been reduced to mere outsiders in a country of their own, the Siddis have to continuously battle against the evils of racism and poverty. The only positive step taken by the government towards their upliftment was the establishment of the Special Area Games Project, in the hope of nurturing the raw talent for athletics which runs in their blood. This initiative, however, could not sustain for long and the dream of having Indo-African athletes run for the country in the Olympics was lost. Sports being the only way out of their deplorable condition, the Siddi community now dwells in the hope of the revival of SAG project and creation of many such opportunities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With xenophobia and racial attacks on the rise all over the country, there is a dire need to spread greater awareness about this community. The government, especially, needs to shoulder some responsibility and formulate comprehensive policies to harness the enormous potential lying in the Siddi community. This can come in the form of better employment, education, and opportunities in sports, and most importantly, acceptance from the rest of the countrymen. The time has come for us to uproot this deep-seated feeling of prejudice against the Indo-African community and truly embrace them to the core in an attempt to learn from the glorious past and shape a bright future based on mutual recognition and brotherhood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Namya Tewari</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">Deep in the annals of Indian history, there lies a long-forgotten tale of daring heroes, who, although foreign to the land, quickly got assimilated into her blood and added to her magnificence. This is the story of the first African rulers of India, the Siddis. India has long been acting as a magnet, drawing to her shores communities from lands afar which have flourished and prospered in her. Amongst these communities were the Africans who although arrived as slaves, still emerged as the mightiest of rulers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Only Turkey can save the European dream, but not in the way you think.</title><link href="/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only Turkey can save the European dream, but not in the way you think." /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To unite the EU needs a common enemy and only the wanker from Ankara is ready to play the role.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Europe, where are its borders, who are its people, and why should I die for it? These are the questions the European Union has desperately grappled with since the 2008 crash. National governments derive power from the willingness of their citizens to make sacrifices. Whether its paying an extra 2.9 cents for a litre of petrol, or traveling across the seas to get shot for Uncle Sam, a government’s power comes from the support of its people. But while the idea of the EU remains popular amongst the European people, with over 60% support across the block in 2017 Eurobarometer surveys, few are willing to make sacrifices for the EU. Northern Europeans don’t want to pay for the ‘greedy’ Southerners. Meanwhile, the Western Europeans don’t see the need to defend Eastern Europe against the Russians. It seems as though the EU has millions of supporters, but very few citizens ready to make the sacrifice necessary for a truly united Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So will Europe ever unite? Can the European Union potentially become a single federalised state, or a superpower capable of challenging China or America? Such a force could defeat the Russians over a long weekend and potentially upset the balance of global politics like no event since the unification of Germany or the French revolution. But the EU needs a threat to give the extra push needed for federalisation. Once that would’ve been Russia, but with an aging population and a declining economy, Russia is today truly only a threat to the Baltic republics: Belarus and the Ukraine. From the beaches of Barcelona or Palermo, the idea of Russia as a serious threat is due to Europe’s ‘special relationship’. Even so is the idea of sending their young lads to fight for Estonian sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily an Armenian phrase tells us who could provide the necessary threat to Europe: “when dealing with the Turk, don’t let go of the stick”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only power capable of convincing European nations to unify is the threat of a rising Turkey with an expansionist government. It has two key advantages over Russia: Firstly, by a matter of its geography it is able to threaten far more of the European continent than Russia can. Secondly, because in a conflict between Turkey and Europe, the United States would likely remain neutral (as it did in the Falklands War), Turkey would force the EU to take the leadership position during the conflict. This would be a cold conflict only though, likely to result in direct confrontation only through proxies in hotspots such as Cyprus or North Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the boom years, European integration seemed both logical and inevitable. The EU expanded its influence both geographically and politically, incorporating the A8 nations of eastern Europe in 2004 and increasing the authority of the Commission with the Treaties of Nice (2007) and Lisbon (2007). Then the bad times came. In 2008, the Great Recession began, since then the EU has lumbered from crisis to crisis. The Greek debt crisis, the migrant crisis and Brexit have all rocked the continent. Through it all, the EU Commision has struggled to act decisively and has lost the support of people across the continent, resulting in the surge of populist and eurosceptic parties. In Poland, Italy and Austria, pro-EU governments have been replaced with eurosceptic regemes unafraid of challenging the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new hope appeared in 2017 in the form of Emmanuel Macron, who sweeped to power, defeated Le Penn and promised to reform Europe and save the Union from irrelevance. At first it seemed to work, Macron faced down protestors in France with a neo-liberal zeal, and Merkel made statements to support Macron’s vision. However, following severe losses for the ruling coalition in the 2017 German election and the populist AFD entering the Bundestag, Merkel’s political capital dried-up. Meanwhile, resentment grew in France at the so called “president of the rich”, culminating in the recent Gilets Jaunes protests which may have permanently crippled Macron’s Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade on from the 2008 crash, it’s now perfectly clear that in a vacuum European states will continue to squabble likely forever. But Europe does not exist in a vacuum. The Republic of Turkey has a population of over 80 million of which over half are under 25, it has the largest army in Europe and will soon be home to the world’s largest airport. Also, it has done a good job of challenging Europe in the past, the Ottoman Empire once touched Vienna, Malta and the Moroccan coast opposite southern Spain. As it became clear that the EU could never allow Turkey to join, the nation has become increasingly hostile to Europe. In 2012, French diplomats were expelled following France’s formal recognition of the Armenian Genocide. In 2016, German Parliamentarians were banned from visiting their own pilots at a NATO airbase in Turkey. And in 2017, President Erdogan called the Dutch government “fascist”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Turkish Navy and Airforce can pose a direct threat to Southern and Eastern Europe, the Turkish also have the capability to threaten violence on the streets of Western Europe. Most of Western Europe’s great cities (Berlin, Rotterdam, Brussels) have large impoverished Turkish minorities which the Europeans have utterly failed to integrate or provide economic opportunity to. Amongst the Turkish diaspora, support for President Erdogan is strong, giving Ankara the capability to ignite social unrest on the streets of European capitals. Moreover, Turkey has a strong relationship with the United States, which hopes to use Turkey to check Russian and Iranian influence, and is willing to sidestep allies in order to do so (as we all saw last week when America abandoned the Syria Kurds). While the USA supporting Turkey against Europe remains unthinkable, if the Turks were able to make a confrontation appear to be at least partly the fault of the Europeans, America could be convinced to take a neutral position as it did during the Cyprus Crisis in 1964. In this scenario, Turkey becomes a threat capable of scaring the Europeans like none other, perhaps even enough to form a federation in resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern definition of Europe comes from the time of the Carolingian Renaissance when the word was used to refer to the union of Latin and Germanic Catholic peoples. This was in contrast to the Islamic Al Andalus in the south and the Orthodox Byzantine Empire in the east. From the beginning Europe was about uniting different peoples to face an enemy from outside. This Union formed under Charlemagne was not to last long after his demise, but the idea of a common people without a shared language, but owing a shared civilisation continues. Globalisation has given Europe a common language, even post Brexit over 51% percent of EU citizens can hold a conversation in English and that number will only grow. A United States of Europe is today more possible than ever before, but it will require a rival to give it shape and purpose. And Europe’s old enemy Turkey is going to be that rival.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reuben Scholtz</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">To unite the EU needs a common enemy and only the wanker from Ankara is ready to play the role.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Market and Politics: The New Separation</title><link href="/Market-and-politics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Market and Politics: The New Separation" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Market-and-politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Market-and-politics">&lt;p&gt;The system of production established in the 1920’s, Fordism, entailed mass standardization of goods for societies that were increasingly headed towards urbanization. The demand was for consumer durables that were cheap and reliable, such as televisions and refrigerators. The market, therefore, was run by a few oligopolistic firms and consumers were used to waiting for a long time before getting the goods they had ordered. This period involved the initiation of assembly lines in production. Factories employed unskilled workers who were regarded as a cog in the machine within the capitalist mode of production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time the 70’s rolled around, many workers in industrialized economies refused to subject themselves to alienation under the Taylorist factory regime, demanding shorter working hours and a higher pay. Another setback to capitalist accumulation was posed by the changing products market. In the West, basic needs had largely been covered by this time and the market for standardized consumer durables was undergoing a secular saturation. What resulted was a restructuring of the production process, and the product lines. Capital responded by re-engineering its products and making them less standardized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Products had become differentiated and customized to cater to the preferences of the smallest groups of potential customers. Like never before, markets allowed customers to pay attention to their individual wants, thereby boosting the move towards customization. The two decades of 1980’s and 1990’s ushered in a period of new consumerism. As products got closer to satisfying idiosyncratic preferences, customers became more willing to work harder or borrow to attain the purchasing power required to acquire them. The growth of the industry for luxury goods, which included perfumes, watches and fashion, followed an identical pattern. Global food chains like McDonald’s incorporated aspects of local cuisines in their menus for different countries. Marketing, on one hand, discovered the commercially untapped wants, and on the other hand, it developed consumer wants. When consumer desires exceeded income, upscale emulation resulted in increasing levels of indebtedness and decreased savings. This marked a transition of markets from those that satisfied needs to those that satisfied wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By developing market niches, commercialized diversification allowed the individual to differentiate himself from some social groups and at the same time associate with others, conveying a desire for upward social mobility. The act of shopping is a way of socializing with others. Moreover, specific kinds of clothing and brands can be used to create a sense of group membership. In fact, rejecting consumer brands in itself establishes quasi-group identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What differentiates this from traditional social integration is that this is voluntary. In well-developed post-Fordist markets, collective identities can be formed through a purchase and abandoned without much ado. In one sense, this signifies liberation from the identity associated with one’s family, community and nation, which the individual is born into and does not have much choice in. It also means that social ties have become much more fragile and weaker as individuals shift identities and desert them as per their convenience. Market forces in this sense writhed their way deeper into social life under a capitalist mode of production. Social media acts as another mode to form these voluntary ties. Twitter, Facebook, Instagram and the likes allow for the formation of a community of followers who interact with each other. Companies use this to further their individualized marketing. Celebrities use it to promote their works and stay relevant. Politicians use it to prevent the increasing weakening of traditional party organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets that seek to cater to the idiosyncrasies of consumers have resulted in the development of a political system best described as “politainment”. Since purchasing power in affluent societies allow the average citizens to get what they want, their interest in the political process begins to fade as there is no vested interest. Participation in traditional politics no longer seems worthwhile. Although people continue to follow the news and pay emphasis on being informed, politics is gradually turning into a form of entertainment, and the citizen is made a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move forward, we find ourselves diverting from a vision for social and economic progress to an overemphasis on individual political decisions. Politics, in effect is becoming de-contextualized. Political participation becomes like an act of consumption, something that can be abandoned or replaced if it ceases to be exciting, much like the T-shirt you bought a few months ago. A consequence is that the public begins to perceive politics as a cumulation of antics resulting from a game of power grabbing. What becomes the focus are the scandals, the petty statements made by opposing sides against each other and representatives focus on managing their appearances rather than serving the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;An argument for a separation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what has been discussed, it is evident that goods aren’t merely for consumption, but also a status symbol. Underlying consumer behaviour is a desire for emulation and differentiation. In advanced industrial societies, consumption of a good serves a dual purpose: It should allow the consumer to distinguish himself or herself from other social groups and classes, while simultaneously allowing for the retention of a sense of individuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This affects the allocation of resources between the public and private sphere. Government goods, those produced by government authorities, are designed to be standardized to ensure a sense of equality among those who consume them. In doing so, they fail to serve the purpose of status differentiation. Their inability to allow the consumer to derive a personal status benefit causes government goods to suffer in cases where the consumer is the decision maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it became well accepted that only private firms could satisfy expectations of the consumer for more customized products, the private sector began to be seen as inherently more superior to the public sector. The public sector reforms of the 90’s followed suit. They involved privatisation of government industries that produced consumer goods, decentralisation of government activities, the use of private producers to sell government produced goods and, a change in the mix of government activities, with a greater focus towards education and healthcare. Formerly public functions moved to the private sphere and even in mixed governments, the balance shifted in favour of the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of politics, regardless of how romanticised it may seem in today’s day and age, is the maintenance of social order and parity. Political communities are built on the idea of accepting a collective identity rather than focusing on one’s individuality. They do not allow for the flexibility of choice as in the markets of highly industrialized economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The employment of a democratic procedure entails that one must accept decisions that they don’t personally prefer, even if they aren’t optimal from an individual’s perspective. In its essence, Politics cannot cater to hedonistic individual desires. Rather, it assesses them to form a general idea that supersedes an individual’s wants. Similarly, social goods cannot be diversified at the rate of customization in the consumer market. As a result they will always seem unfavourable in comparison to private goods. Eventually, the incentive to contribute to the provision of public goods and civil services will dry up. Moreover, paying taxes for financing government activities without having prior knowledge of how they are to be used is in contrast to any other market purchase. This decline in interest in collective projects by people with sufficient purchasing power will ensue an increase in tax resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a shift from public to private consumption, those who continue to depend on public provisions will also get affected. In commercial markets that effectively oust the poorer segments, the only effective means to promote their requirements is their power to affect the electoral outcome. When the political system is starved of legitimacy and financial resources, the lower classes will refrain from voting and even symbolically participating in the political process; Consequently, the state’s ability to ensure public order will slowly evaporate. The reorganization of social life under capitalism, culminates today in a dual crisis of the global financial system and the creation of a ‘minimalist’ democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reema Singh</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The system of production established in the 1920’s, Fordism, entailed mass standardization of goods for societies that were increasingly headed towards urbanization. The demand was for consumer durables that were cheap and reliable, such as televisions and refrigerators. The market, therefore, was run by a few oligopolistic firms and consumers were used to waiting for a long time before getting the goods they had ordered. This period involved the initiation of assembly lines in production. Factories employed unskilled workers who were regarded as a cog in the machine within the capitalist mode of production.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MOURINHO OUT (or not?) - What it Means for the Devils Going Forward and Again, Mourinho.</title><link href="/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MOURINHO OUT (or not?) - What it Means for the Devils Going Forward and Again, Mourinho." /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho</id><content type="html" xml:base="/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho">&lt;p&gt;It was their worst start to any championship season in as many as 28 years. For a team considered to be a giant in world club football, only 10 wins out of 20 games is, to say the least, terrible. Anti-positional, even. It had the potential to be a major surprise initially. But nevertheless, it was always on the cards. Jose Mourinho, much-celebrated manager, was fired. The management had finally taken the leap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news, which came out early December 18th following an almost-devastating 3-1 loss to Jurgen Klopp’s Liverpool at Anfield, was christened by a not-so-coincidental Instagram post by Paul Pogba, whose feud with Mourinho over the last season has been no secret to a sane person. Not to say, this garnered huge reactions across all social media, but that’s another story. For another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most United fans cannot stop smiling ear-to-ear with the news, some feel it’s all a bit too late with the Red Devils &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2812956-epl-results-saturdays-week-20-scores-updated-2019-premier-league-table&quot;&gt;currently placed 6th&lt;/a&gt; in the Premier League, six points behind 5th-placed Arsenal and a gargantuan nineteen points behind table-toppers Liverpool, all combining to make a Champions League spot for next year seem very, very unlikely. However things aren’t all gloomy for Manchester United as they did manage to qualify for the knockout stage of this year’s Champions League. What’s more, they have a long two-month break (holiday?) before their game against French rivals Paris Saint Germain. This affords the interim manager Ole Gunnar Solskjaer a fighting chance to get the boys back and running before the all-important clash. It however will be no easy task, as post Sir Alex Ferguson, United have had as many as four managers (including Jose Mourinho), every single one of whom have failed to deliver the bounties or even as much as have any real impact on the club. Norwegian Ole ‘Gunnar’ Solskjaer is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2812956-epl-results-saturdays-week-20-scores-updated-2019-premier-league-table&quot;&gt;former United forward&lt;/a&gt;, netting 126 goals in 366 appearances for the club. His exploits also earned him the rather scary nickname of ‘baby-faced-Assassin’. In retrospect, it is also an oxymoron, so you never know. He is expected to run the show at Old Trafford for now, until the board can appoint a successor to Mourinho’s three year ‘reign-of-terror’. The current favorites’ to replace him would be Spurs’ manager Mauricio Pochettino and former Madrid superstar Zinedine Zidane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to United’s actual players, we saw a flickering shade of the Reds of yore in their first game post the Mourinho ‘era’ with their resounding 5-1 win over Cardiff this weekend immediately followed by 3–1 and 4-1 wins over Huddersfield and Bournemouth respectively just a few days later. With Mourinho ousted and gone, it’s a massive opportunity for United’s big signings Sanchez, Pogba and the effervescent Lukaku to step up and regain some lost pride for the club. Moreover, they would always have the services of the younger guns like Rashford, Lingard and Martial. In a recent interview, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.football365.com/news/lingard-explains-what-ole-has-done-for-pogba&quot;&gt;Lingard talked&lt;/a&gt; about Pogba and Solskjaer. He said, “I can definitely, definitely see the Paul I used to know. Ole has given him the license to be free and play his game and do what all of us know he can.” So, if we go by what Lingard has to say, the future bodes well for the Devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as José Mourinho goes, the hope of another Premier League managerial job seems slim given his consecutive failures at United and a poor last season at Chelsea which saw them spiraling to lose nine out of their last sixteen League games. There are a few Madrid rumors in the air but it all seems pretty bleak as one of ESPN’s pundits puts it, going on to say, “At this point, Mourinho is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.espn.in/video/clip?id=25564591&quot;&gt;damaged brand&lt;/a&gt;.” However, with all due respect to Mourinho, he is still one of the greatest managers the world has ever seen, with as many as a whopping twenty-five major honors. So maybe, just maybe, his story doesn’t end here. Who knows, perhaps international management is on the cards as well as he could very likely be the potential successor to Portugal’s Fernando Santos. Only time will tell, whatever that is. As for now his 22.5 million pound payout should keep him fed for a while.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrew Mark</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">It was their worst start to any championship season in as many as 28 years. For a team considered to be a giant in world club football, only 10 wins out of 20 games is, to say the least, terrible. Anti-positional, even. It had the potential to be a major surprise initially. But nevertheless, it was always on the cards. Jose Mourinho, much-celebrated manager, was fired. The management had finally taken the leap.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Hollywood the Perfect Fit for Superstar Bryce Harper?</title><link href="/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Hollywood the Perfect Fit for Superstar Bryce Harper?" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper">&lt;p&gt;The end of baseball season is the time when all diehard fans settle on watching football for a few months. A long 152 days until baseball rolls back around. But that time in the offseason is one of the most important for a franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offseason is when general managers, scouts, and other team personnel come together to talk about the future of their organization. Trades and new contracts are the most important part of the offseason for a general manager. And with every MLB team having one or more superstars, it has been a wild offseason for trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest buzz that has been circling around MLB is where Bryce Harper is going to be cleating up to start the 2019 season. As one of the star names in professional baseball, and arguably the biggest free agent this offseason, everyone is hoping that their general manager is keeping an eye out for the 26-year-old phenom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Can the Dodgers make the best case for Harper?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harper, who is now a free agent after an 8-year contract with the Washington Nationals, is looking for a new city to call home. Being a 7-time All-Star with only 8 seasons under his belt makes it obvious that he will have an immediate impact on any team that he joins. Many teams in the MLB are making trades and moves to adjust their lineup for someone like Harper, but none have made a splash like the Los Angeles Dodgers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With back to back World Series appearances, the Dodgers have been making their mark on the MLB in recent years. But in mid-December, the Dodgers traded two powerhouse outfields to the Cincinnati Reds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3-time All-Star, 2-time Gold Glover, and 2-time Silver Slugger, Matt Kemp is a known face for Los Angeles. He played his first 9 seasons with the Dodgers and made it to the All-Star Game last season with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yasiel Puig is another big name for Los Angeles as he has geared up for the Dodgers in all 6 of his professional seasons. In that time he has had an All-Star selection and was runner up for the Rookie of the Year award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Puig and Kemp are outfielders, so it is obvious that the Dodgers’ staff  are trying to open the outfield up. Whether they are doing so for Harper or not is not clear yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dodgers are desperately looking for an opportunity to get that World Series Ring in October, and maybe Harper is the man they need leading the charge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Tanberg</name></author><category term="sports" /><summary type="html">The end of baseball season is the time when all diehard fans settle on watching football for a few months. A long 152 days until baseball rolls back around. But that time in the offseason is one of the most important for a franchise.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chasing Inflation</title><link href="/Chasing-Inflation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chasing Inflation" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Chasing-Inflation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Chasing-Inflation">&lt;p&gt;To someone not from an economics background, the idea of ‘chasing inflation’ might seem counter-intuitive. Why pursue inflation―a general increase in the price level of commodities-which wipes off your purchasing power? We, however, are well aware of how increasing inflation (rather bringing back the ‘lost inflation’) which reached near zero levels during the financial crisis, has become an obsession of central banks. Few developed countries will mind additional doses of inflation today. Bank of Japan is still in the trajectory of negative interest rates in the hope of countering the deflation that has plagued the country since the 1990’s. The Fed, at least till last year, was wondering why inflation hadn’t picked up despite the economy nearing full employment. Germany’s inflation rate is not going much beyond the 2% line, which 30 years ago, with the same level of unemployment, would be 5%. This has contributed to Germany’s current account surplus because of increased savings; it is also making it harder for peripheral countries to improve their competitive position vis-à-vis Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ‘missing inflation’ could mean two things. One, there is a force which is holding inflation back inside many countries. Two, there lies some problem with the way inflation is tracked in these countries. Surprisingly, the answer to both these problems lies in the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not guessed already, the culprit is Amazon. Largely called the ‘Amazon Effect’, retail prices in the USA have been withheld primarily because of the e-commerce giant’s discounting policies. This is not the first time this has happened. Since the 1990’s, Walmart and cheap Chinese imports have held prices back. This pressure seemed to be easing after the financial crisis, until the advent of e-commerce on the big stage. Online sales account for more than 10% of retail sales in the US. From 2000 to 2009, the online price index rose from a little above 90 to 100, implying an inflation rate of about 1% per year. But since 2009, the price index for goods purchased via e-commerce has actually been declining by about 1% per year. This implies a deflationary pressure of 10% on all retail sales. If this is not enough, add to it the slashing of prices by brick and mortar competitors to keep Amazon and other e-tailers in check. Goldman Sachs’ chief US economist Jan Hatzius has said that this effect is reducing core goods’ inflation by 0.25% and reducing overall core personal consumption expenditure (PCE) inflation by 0.1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Amazon effect isn’t going to die down soon. Amazon is one of the most valuable companies in the world, and with its billionaire founder, Jeff Bezos, it is looking to expand its horizons. Its acquisition of Whole Foods Market, a supermarket chain, could do to the $800 billion grocery market what it did to the retail market. According to Bloomberg, prices were cut as high as 43% on a range of items at Whole Foods on the first day under Amazon. Food makes up about 14.6% of the consumer price index. Very significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon might not stop at the grocery. Amazon Web Services has disrupted the IT industry. Its impact has been called ‘deflationary’ by Citigroup. This triggers a chain reaction of other competitors cutting their prices, and their profits (if not their employees’ wages). As Amazon increases in efficiency, helped by automation, one has to be very optimistic to predict a rise in prices in this war with e-commerce on one side, and all the rest on the other. Nomura had declared ‘Amazonification of Inflation’ one of its 10 grey swans of 2018. As of now, the Amazon effect has had only half the influence of the Walmart effect on inflation. But I would not bet my money against the former outshining the latter very soon. ‘Amazon effect’, in fact, is more of a misnomer. It is not Amazon specific. It is true for all e-tailers in all countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With it established how online players can disrupt inflation targeting by central banks, it is imperative that policymakers take into account the effect of online transactions on inflation. The Billion Prices Project (BPP) aims to do just that. BPP gathers data from online retailers in over 70 countries, allowing for real-time inflation updates. It tracks the price level of 5 million goods sold online. Data is published daily, rather than monthly, and with a lag of three days, rather than several weeks. It offers an immediate measure of inflation. A brainchild of 2 MIT economists, BPP also prevents data twisting by governments. It was set up in 2008 in Buenos Aires and it found that the inflation rate in Argentina was three times the official government estimates; 4 years later, The Economist rejected official Argentine numbers. It has more benefits. It costs less and the frequency of measurement is high. It solves many problems of data collection which exist in the status quo. A basket of goods is updated on a real-time basis as new products enter the market and old ones are discontinued. Currently, data gatherers assume people shy away from expensive products. For example, if beef’s price increases, it is assumed people switch to chicken. It ignores how people also consider quality and personal preferences while purchasing. Online purchase data collection solves this as well. It, however, does not give a good enough indication of the price level of services, as they (usually) aren’t sold online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central Banks are already adapting to this shift in consumer-producer interaction. Bank of England uses data from Google searches to gauge economic sentiment (searching “estate agent” is a good indicator of housing transactions, for example). Google is itself working on a price index based on online shopping. Asia is already one step ahead of the West. Policymakers throughout all budding Asian economies, from India to South Korea are looking over the internet to gauge inflation. Japan has set up a team to improve its data collection which takes into account online spending. There are strong chances that online purchases will be an important part of Japan’s upcoming Consumption Trend Index, which would measure personal spending. ASEAN members Malaysia, Thailand, Singapore, and the Philippines are not behind as well. “This ‘Amazon effect’ is well documented in the US, but we think they also play a substantial role in keeping inflation low in Thailand as well,” a Bank of Thailand statement adds. China, already a potential leader of the world in the age of big data, is not only monitoring e-commerce activity but also engaging with executives to study the impact in detail. Brace yourselves; leftists predicting the collapse of all social order because of government supervision over our online activity are coming.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidyarthi</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">To someone not from an economics background, the idea of ‘chasing inflation’ might seem counter-intuitive. Why pursue inflation―a general increase in the price level of commodities-which wipes off your purchasing power? We, however, are well aware of how increasing inflation (rather bringing back the ‘lost inflation’) which reached near zero levels during the financial crisis, has become an obsession of central banks. Few developed countries will mind additional doses of inflation today. Bank of Japan is still in the trajectory of negative interest rates in the hope of countering the deflation that has plagued the country since the 1990’s. The Fed, at least till last year, was wondering why inflation hadn’t picked up despite the economy nearing full employment. Germany’s inflation rate is not going much beyond the 2% line, which 30 years ago, with the same level of unemployment, would be 5%. This has contributed to Germany’s current account surplus because of increased savings; it is also making it harder for peripheral countries to improve their competitive position vis-à-vis Germany.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beauty and the Beast</title><link href="/Beauty-and-the-Beast" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty and the Beast" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Beauty-and-the-Beast</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-and-the-Beast">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift given randomly, stupidly.”&lt;/em&gt; – K. Hosseini&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stealthily and openly, invisibly and brazenly, beauty snakes through conversations, decisions and opinions. The discussion of beauty is not just the domain of subjects like narcissism or nature’s trickery to perpetuate a species. Beauty is a matter to be discussed sociologically, for beauty is far more than just how we perceive ourselves, it is also how we perceive each other. In a world that paints less with words and more with filters, it becomes important to examine the intrusion of physical appearances into how one thinks, and leads life. No longer just a measure of what one finds visually or aesthetically soothing, beauty has now become a socially approved metric for the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; we place on people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Indian matrimonial advertisements that yearn for ‘fair’ and ‘slim’ brides and show business boosting looks over talent; right from the start it is ingrained and embedded into us that society fosters a reward mechanism that favours the handsome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift but is it really given &lt;em&gt;randomly&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What truly needs to be pondered upon is, how is it that there is a set of bodily and facial attributes that have been magically fixed as attractive and thereby high value? Why is light skin preferred to dark skin in most cultures? Why are perky breasts seen as more attractive as compared to breasts that sag? Why is it easier for one to find a woman with straight blonde hair aesthetically pleasing but not a woman with frizzy black hair?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fraud in beauty is that we have been made to believe that there is something &lt;em&gt;inherently beautiful&lt;/em&gt; about certain attributes, such as having fair skin. We do not find fair skin beautiful because it is embedded into our genetic constitution to find it so, it is not an innate characteristic of our species to find fair skin beautiful. We find it beautiful because society has deemed it to be beautiful. We find it beautiful because society tells us to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“She had perfect features, with her eye, nose, lips, and ears the right size and in right places. That is all it takes to make people beautiful, normal body parts – yet why does nature mess it up so many times?”&lt;/em&gt; – an un-ironic quote from a Chetan Bhagat novel. Society manufactures and dictates the way we feel about beauty while making us believe that those feelings and judgements arise organically from within. Beauty, is a social construct and this construct too rests upon a farce, which revolves around Eurocentricity and gendered expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Yeh chaand sa roshan chehra, zulfon ka rang sunehra, yeh jheel si neeli aakhein, koi raaz hai inmein gehra, tareef karun kya uski, jisne tumhe banaya?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song, from a 1964 film in India, casting Indian actors to be watched largely by people living in India, glorifies white skin, blonde hair and blue eyes and people actually &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;related&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to this song to the extent that today it is considered to be a classic. How does this make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European standards of beauty are living proof that colonialism once prevailed. When European countries colonised African and Asian nations they did not just see the people they subjugated as &lt;em&gt;‘different’&lt;/em&gt; from themselves but also as inferior, as subhuman. Colonialists glorified everything European as a superior, more civilised and refined way of leading life. They attached ‘disgust’ to everything native and indigenous. Idealisation of European beauty was a by-product of colonisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skewed power dynamics of the world allowed white people to narrate the norms for beauty. Colourism today, grips cultures across the world. From black women who look at their skin and wonder how much black is too black, to a nation of brown people being marketed skin lightening creams under the brand of ‘Fair &amp;amp; Lovely’. Colourism grips us both by the bane of society and the bane of our selfhood. And while beauty standards affect everyone, they affect people of colour way more. Because it has made us forget what we actually look like. Through the alchemy of Eurocentric standards of beauty, the untamed wavy black hair on the heads of Indian goddesses look mythical to Indians, yet somehow Cameron Diaz’s blonde hair looks more &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt; and more &lt;em&gt;attainable&lt;/em&gt;. The conventional archetypes of beauty do not even coincide with traditional looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The normativity extends to gendered expectations too, as society and media continue to be obsessed with narrow waisted women and tall, brawny men. Once again, the sham lies in the fact that these expectations are &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;assumed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;intrinsic&lt;/em&gt; to any gender. In a day and age when media is ever present and more dominant than anything else, when one does not see a single woman having body hair on screen, it’s almost as if society wants us to pretend that women do not have body hair. This promotes a form of normativity that borders on delusion! Media latches on a sense of disgust to chest hair, and sells us the lie that it is ‘gross’ and ‘repulsive’ for men to have it. Media strips away what is natural, and in its place synthesises a new ‘normal’. This new ordinary makes the state of nature seem abnormal, if it didn’t it would be easier to picture Chris Evans with chest hair. Ah! Never mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These imposed standards are so deeply entrenched in us that even when one is aware of the sham surrounding beauty, they visit one in private moments. Like the inward rejoice of having hair straightened because it feels as if frizz was something to be corrected, and straight just looks more ‘normal’. Or stopping a porn video midway because the woman having a tuft of pubic hair made it ‘uncomfortable’ to watch, or because watching people of colour have sex ‘feels wrong’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even when faced with these inner hypocrisies, one must remember that these dilemmas too are imposed and injected into the people by a media that rests upon the commoditization of beauty and reinforces the same toxic ideas. But ah! To hell with norms! It is the era for shaking up normativity and outraging beauty ideals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty, in all its failing and its glory, is subjective. “Beauty is subjective” is not a lie meant to console people who do not fall within conventional archetypes of beauty. On the contrary, &lt;em&gt;‘subjective beauty’&lt;/em&gt; is the only truth, for beauty cannot and should not be standardised. Beauty does not conform, why then should its ideals do the same?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Stuti Gupta</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">“Beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift given randomly, stupidly.” – K. Hosseini</summary></entry></feed>