<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-11T16:39:26+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Legislators in Crime</title><link href="/Legislators-in-Crime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Legislators in Crime" /><published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Legislators-in-Crime</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Legislators-in-Crime">&lt;p&gt;Taking a step into Indian politics is infinitely easier for a criminal than for an ordinary citizen. As paradoxical as this notion is, it has proven itself true each time an election has passed by. The Association for Democratic Reform (ADR) found that in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Indian Parliament, the percentage of legislators with a criminal record or awaiting trial has almost doubled in the past two decades. In the 2004 Lok Sabha, this number was 24%, while in 2019, it went up to 43%. What is more concerning is that a significant number of these legislators have been accused of serious crimes such as murder and rape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law of the land prohibits convicts from contesting elections, but not individuals with a charge sheet against them. This gap was intentional in order to prevent state machinery from being utilised for political vendetta, however, it has been grossly exploited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nexus between crime and politics has held strong for decades because of its perceived benefit to three important stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criminals are the first and the most direct beneficiaries. In fact, booth capture and suppression or mobilisation of voters in favour of political parties were one of the main sources of income for criminals between 1940’s and the 1970’s. Their support makes the legislators indebted to them and consequently, the law enforcement system is forced to be complicit in the process. Eventually, their role shifted from henchmen to legislators themselves. The presence of such an astonishingly large number of criminals in Parliament is an ode to the ailing criminal justice system as well. A criminal could complete two terms in office before they are brought to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, political parties have been gaining from their alliance with criminals since the birth of democracy in India. As Milan Vaishnav explains in his book &lt;em&gt;When Crime Pays: Money and Muscle in Indian Politics&lt;/em&gt;,  there were two factors in India’s political history that solidified this nexus. First, as regional parties were on the rise, political competition has increased the demand for criminals. This created a need and a market for criminals to generate security around electoral results for the parties. This often took place through threats and fear to secure votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, in 1969, Indira Gandhi put a ban on corporate funding for elections. This pushed a significant source of campaign finance underground. Parties preferred candidates who could secure large sums of cash and finance their campaigns. Criminals fit this bracket as many of them had managed to amass large quantities of wealth. Money plays a large role in this nexus, which is why there is great advocacy for a transparent electoral finance system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voters of India play a part in the preservation of this system as well. In fact, we see that a candidate with a criminal background is three times more likely to win a seat than a clean one. Struggling to access basic services such as law enforcement, healthcare, and welfare schemes, voters prefer candidates “who can get things done”, instead of one restrained by red tapism and morality. This nexus of crime and politics is actively supported by inefficient state services and poor access to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous N N Vohra Committee in 1993, set up to unearth crime and political nexus, had documented the rise of a criminal empire with the active support of top politicians and bureaucrats, eroding the rule of law and the legitimacy of democratic governance. In its report, the committee highlighted that many criminals were running a parallel government and blamed the existing criminal justice system for failing to effectively prosecute them. It suggested several measures to break the nexus. However, the “very explosive” report was never tabled in the Parliament and has since been kept as a top-secret by the Ministry of Home Affairs. All the Right to Informations (RTIs) filed have been skillfully evaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All major initiatives against the crime-politics nexus have been led by the judiciary and civil society. In the case of &lt;em&gt;Union of India v Association for Democratic Reforms and Another&lt;/em&gt;, the Supreme Court, in 2002, directed compulsory disclosure of the candidates’ financial, educational and criminal background while contesting elections. Expectedly, the court verdict was bitterly opposed by most political parties and the Union Government promulgated an ordinance, using its temporary law-making powers, to nullify the judgment. However, the court rose to the occasion by striking down the ordinance as unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court (SC) made another valiant attempt to curb criminalisation in December 2017. It asked for the setting up of special courts to fast-track the long-pending trials of elected members. In another judgment in 2018, the Supreme Court mandated the political parties and candidates to declare in print and electronic media in the locality about the antecedents of each candidate. However, these judgments did not yield any visible positive outcome as is evident from the rising number of criminal politicians in the Lok Sabha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2020, expressing concern over the growing intersection of crime and politics, the Supreme Court had ordered political parties to publish the details of their candidates with criminal charges on their websites and social media platforms, and in newspapers. The parties are required to also clearly outline the nature of the charges and explain why these candidates had been given tickets. This information was made public, and a compliance report was sent to the Election Commission (EC) within a specified period of time. The failure to do so was to be read as contempt. Upcoming Bihar elections in October 2020 will be the first election in which the Supreme Court’s decision will be implemented. The effects remain to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often said that the people of India need to undergo a ‘behavioural change’ in order to eradicate criminals from politics. As long as voters keep voting for criminals, there will be no solution. However, this requires a high level of trust in a better and rule-abiding alternative. It is the duty of the state and the political parties to instil this trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process can be started by creating a transparent electoral funding system. This can be done through state funding of elections as recommended by various committees such as the Dinesh Goswami Committee and the Indrajit Gupta Committee on electoral reforms. This is a step towards curbing the use of black money to a large extent and limiting criminalisation of politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another profusely opposed way forward is bringing political parties under the ambit of the Right to Information Act, 2005. Except for their political strategy, other matters relating to finance and administration should be made available to the public. The current system of electoral bonds does not promote transparency in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a need for increasing the powers of the Election Commission. The Election Commission can register a political party but cannot deregister it. As a neutral body, it is essential that the EC is allowed to regulate the affairs of a political party for a cleaner electoral process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of suggestions and reforms, what the Indian political system lacks is any sort of incentive to push these forward. The implementation of the February 2020 judgment guidelines will show whether seeing the true and bare face of the criminal-political nexus at an official level awakens the dormant morality of the Indian electorate or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Taking a step into Indian politics is infinitely easier for a criminal than for an ordinary citizen. As paradoxical as this notion is, it has proven itself true each time an election has passed by. The Association for Democratic Reform (ADR) found that in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Indian Parliament, the percentage of legislators with a criminal record or awaiting trial has almost doubled in the past two decades. In the 2004 Lok Sabha, this number was 24%, while in 2019, it went up to 43%. What is more concerning is that a significant number of these legislators have been accused of serious crimes such as murder and rape.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inauguration of the Ram Mandir: A Change to Indian Secularism for Eternity?</title><link href="/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inauguration of the Ram Mandir: A Change to Indian Secularism for Eternity?" /><published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir">&lt;p&gt;Man has known religion more than he has known himself. When Adam ate an apple which was forbidden for him to eat, it was the verses in religious books that told mankind that he wronged himself; but when an apple supposedly fell on Newton’s head, the world cheered for his triumph. As time progressed, religion slowly began to recede in its control and its influence. The Church lost its political power, and politics pushed religion out of its domain, slowly yet meticulously. The West gifted the world the idea of ‘secularism’ and envisioned a world where men would keep the cross and prayer mat at home; not to imply that secularism would be misjudged as apathy towards religion or would imply the absence of spirituality, but because politics and religion, if brewed together, would be a stain to the national fabric irrespective of place, time and ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert G Ingersoll, an American writer contemplated upon the reasons for this and stated, &lt;em&gt;“They knew that to put God in the constitution was to put man out. They knew that the recognition of a Deity would be seized upon by fanatics and zealots as a pretext for destroying the liberty of thought. They knew the terrible history of the church too well to place in her keeping or in the keeping of her God the sacred rights of man. They intended that all should have the right to worship or not to worship that our laws should make no distinction on account of creed.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of what exists in principles and theories, secular states have changed their means of functioning with politics and religion. This game in which one of the two tries to monopolise the other, keeps the equilibrium of secular powers ever shaken. The ‘secular’ state of Turkey had its President taking part in Hagia Sophia’s first prayer in 86 years, and the ‘secular’ state of India witnessed its Prime Minister inaugurate the construction of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt; on August 5, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as criticism over Indian PM Modi’s move to attend this ceremony starts to abound, one must realise that maybe the faultiness of the action is backed by an idea which itself is faulty and illusionary. For a political scientist like Christopher Jaffrelot, India’s secularism has always been screwed. Not because it wasn’t ‘western’ in its approach, but because its outlook and affinities with pluralism and multiculturalism were much more than it could handle. How can a newly born independent nation that rose fiercely at Gandhi’s idea of &lt;em&gt;Ram Rajya&lt;/em&gt; (The rule of Rama) forget its inclinations towards a ‘Hindu civilisation’ in a matter of a decade? How could a nation that was compelled to fight the colonial rulers instigated by the idea that India’s lands were always attacked by outsiders, colonisers, intruders, and Muslims be forgotten once India became independent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question remains: how does a nation that endured a national struggle with several secular symbols and undoubtedly persistent Hinduistic virtues, try and push itself away and remain ‘equidistant’ from all religious communities including Hinduism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PM Modi in his victory speech in 2019 had said that for the last 30 years, political parties in power had practised &lt;em&gt;nakli&lt;/em&gt; (fake) secularism, and true secularism was embedded in the idea of &lt;em&gt;sabka saath sabka vikas&lt;/em&gt;, which is translated by his party as “justice to all, appeasement to none”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rajeev Bhargava in his article ‘How to rescue genuine secularism?’ claimed, &lt;em&gt;“It is communal to believe or act in a way that presupposes that one can’t be a Hindu without being anti-Muslim, or vice-versa. Communalism is communitarianism gone sour. It is to see each other as enemies locked in a permanent war with one another.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this light, if one explores the idea of the Supreme Leader of a modern secular India inaugurating a temple and the allegations that such a deed negates the oath that he took as a Prime Minister, one must come to terms with the fact that the Indian PM is an outright Hindu. In 2019, when the PM made a visit to Kedarnath, his actions weren’t criticised because Kedarnath receives respect in the Hindu faith. The picture of him meditating in a cave was not being called ‘un-secular’ or ‘fallacious’ because the leader of the country is a follower of the Hindu faith and, hence, it would be mere hypocrisy to expect him to bow down his head in a mosque on a Friday afternoon or sing melodies in a Church on a bright Sunday morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does the problem exactly lie when it’s about inaugurating the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt;? The trouble lies in the fact that the inauguration, specifically of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt;, symbolises a celebration; a new beginning of a place of worship of Lord Ram, and also communicates the end of another place of worship - the Babri Masjid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amartya Sen, the Indian Nobel Laureate, when discussing the ideals of secularism claimed that &lt;em&gt;“The state must be equidistant from all religions – refusing to take sides and having a neutral attitude towards them, and the state must not have any relation at all with any religion”&lt;/em&gt;. In matters of these, the inauguration of the Mandir not only denies every atom of being secular, it moreover rejoices the construction as a predestined merriment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If August 5 marked the construction of the Mandir and the imprisonment of every violator that pulled the Masjid to dust, would the criticisms against the PM be the same? Or would that be an element within the orbit of secularism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when justice seems to exist nowhere and celebration remains at the peak?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answers remain unknown and unheard, and it boils down to one query; which is more flawed: is the ‘Indian ideal of secularism’ deeply flawed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Muslims haven’t forgotten the demolition of the Babri Masjid, maybe they haven’t forgotten the Godhra Riots, maybe wishing them ‘Eid Mubarak’ via a tweet from the PM feels like mere hypocrisy, maybe they cannot choose to forget the faces of young Muslim boys who were lynched, and maybe every wound remains so wide open that they haven’t moved an inch towards recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticisms that surround the inauguration of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt; by the PM, that are deemed as mere ‘insecurities’ of a minority community, maybe aren’t just insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sheer panic to witness and accept a blow to the nation’s secular fabric which in hindsight seems rather largely inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The systematic push for political power by the Hindu right-wing would not have advanced without the ground prepared by the Ayodhya movement. It has contributed to India’s foundational shift from a pluralist democracy to majoritarian rule,”&lt;/em&gt; said Zoya Hasan, a political scientist and professor emeritus at Jawaharlal Nehru University in New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The message is a clear one: here is a day which should be celebrated as the day BJP fulfilled two of its core promises. The fact that no opposition leaders have raised their voice against this event being held in the middle of a pandemic shows how powerful the BJP has become,”&lt;/em&gt; said Sanjay Kumar, Director of New Delhi based think-tank Center for the Study of Developing Societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Rajeev Khanna in his article in &lt;em&gt;The Citizen&lt;/em&gt; had said, &lt;em&gt;“This Babri Masjid = Ram Janmabhoomi campaign has had a devastating impact on people like myself, who have spent most of their lives under its shadow…. The poet Kaifi Azmi was not wrong to describe the Babri demolition as Ram’s ‘Doosra Banwas’ (second forest exile) in one of his iconic poems under the title. But those who have never subscribed to the plurality of Indian ethos are once again busy bombarding us with calls to celebrate Diwali this August 5th”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s secular mechanism is just like a vehicle with a failed break. And what happens to such a vehicle which is moving too fast, beyond bounds and red lights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It crashes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aniba Junaid</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Man has known religion more than he has known himself. When Adam ate an apple which was forbidden for him to eat, it was the verses in religious books that told mankind that he wronged himself; but when an apple supposedly fell on Newton’s head, the world cheered for his triumph. As time progressed, religion slowly began to recede in its control and its influence. The Church lost its political power, and politics pushed religion out of its domain, slowly yet meticulously. The West gifted the world the idea of ‘secularism’ and envisioned a world where men would keep the cross and prayer mat at home; not to imply that secularism would be misjudged as apathy towards religion or would imply the absence of spirituality, but because politics and religion, if brewed together, would be a stain to the national fabric irrespective of place, time and ideology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vision 20/20</title><link href="/Vision-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vision 20/20" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Vision-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Vision-2020">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Info Edge, it seems, has mastered the maths of running online classifieds in India. Industry observers attribute this success to the fact that customers don’t pay anything to use these platforms, except for Jeevansathi. From listings of jobs, real estate, and education, the company earns most of its revenue from businesses, advertisements, listing fees, and subscription products. This is in sharp contrast to the likes of OLX and Quikr, where a customer has the option to buy a paid listing, but the vast majority of users don’t pay to have their products listed; consequently, they have also burnt through millions of dollars to acquire new customers. However, Info Edge founders do not believe in this philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country’s largest employment website, Naukri, boasts about 67 million résumés and currently has 500,000 job listings on its platform. More than 60% of its revenue comes from the fees it charges from employers for access to its huge résumé database. 99acres, another successful venture of the Info Edge brand was founded in 2005 and is also a leader in its category. As of December 31, 2019, the site had total listings of 1,004,378 properties. It competes with Magicbricks, Commonfloor, and Housing. However, between 2013 and 2016, VC funding was abundantly available, triggering a mushrooming of players in the real estate sector. Backed by the likes of NewsCorp, SoftBank, and Tiger Global Management, startups such as Proptiger, Commonfloor, Housing, Quikr, OLX, Indiahomes, and Indiaproperty started giving 99Acres a tough fight. However, 99acres has held its ground. Jeevansathi is the third-largest matrimonial site in India, after Bharat Matrimony and Shaadi. Online spending on the business is likely to grow to ₹11-12 billion by 2023-24 from ₹7-8 billion in 2020-21. This is expected to give a huge boost to Info Edge’s matrimonial website. Shiksha, the portal providing information on careers, examinations, colleges, and courses is facing stiff competition as there are a lot many major players in the EdTech sector. With the likes of Byju’s, it has become tough for Shiksha to make a strong presence in the Indian EdTech sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bikhchandani had seen potential in classifieds websites when there were just around 14,000 internet accounts in the country and a few thousand users comparing that to the around 500 million users in India now, second only to China’s more than 800 million. It became the early mover in the internet economy, taking many essentials online as India’s population started discovering the joys of a virtually connected world. But as an early mover, Bikhchandani knows the downside of the treadmill. He is aware of the need to continuously make innovations in the fast-changing technological world. For that, Info Edge will leverage its advantage of two decades’ worth of data, using artificial intelligence, data analytics, and machine learning to drive informed change through improved user experiences and new products. Also, Info Edge will continue its 12-year-long practice of investing in ‘ideas’ with the ₹1 billion ‘Info Edge Venture Fund’, launched in January, to fund early-stage startups across categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the first fund by Info Edge, but the company has already invested ₹1.03 billion in 16 startups, including the likes of Zomato and PolicyBazaar. Overall the company has 21 active investments worth ₹1.108 billion at the end of 2020-21. In fact, one of its most successful bets has been restaurant aggregator and food delivery platform Zomato. Bikhchandani, a foodie, had been using Foodiebay (rebranded as Zomato only in 2010). A subsequent conversation with founder Deepinder Goyal set the tone for a business association, and Bikhchandani made an initial investment of ₹40.5 million. Its investment till date is ₹1.52 billion with about 22.7% stake. Zomato has already successfully acquired Uber’s food delivery business in India, Uber Eats. Moreover, PolicyBazaar is expected to receive investment from Google in its bid to expand its digital presence in India. Additionally, the insurance aggregator is also expected to raise $500 million from its Initial Public Offering (IPO) sometime next year. So the prospects of Info Edge cashing out big are right around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While making investments, Bikhchandani not only focuses on the business model but also takes into consideration the commitment, capability, and integrity of founders, and good governance. The importance of these qualities can be understood when fiascos like WeWork and Wirecard occur. Of course, some of the newer business models ask for cash burn to gain market share which is not how Bikhchandani runs his companies. He has always advised startups to get ‘customer money’ before ‘investor money’. Maybe some of the larger funds can learn from this strategy instead of blindly burning cash.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JioMart: The Disruptor?</title><link href="/JioMart" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JioMart: The Disruptor?" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/JioMart</id><content type="html" xml:base="/JioMart">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Don’t find customers for your products, find products for your customers”&lt;/em&gt;, they say, and truly, those who have always thought about their consumers, are the ones whose products have been the most successful. I would not be wrong in saying that the economic development of any country starts and ends with the consumers of that country. Any consumer-related business can rise to great heights if the creators of that business model cater to the needs of the consumers and provide them with efficient services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving along these lines, Mukesh Ambani has now become the fourth richest in the Forbes Global Rich List 2020 as Reliance Industries’ market capitalisation, including the partly paid shares, topped the ₹13 trillion mark. With the recent rise in the e-commerce sector, Reliance Industries has aimed to extend its reach here, which is in contrast with its previous approach wherein they limited themselves to the oil refinery and petroleum sector. To put this in context, we have to take a look at the facts to see why Reliance Industries is where it is today. In the last few years, the launch of Reliance Jio Infocomm Ltd has been able to attract customers even from other rivals such as Vodafone-Idea, Airtel and other telecom operators in India, with its cheap data plans, free calls, and other exciting features. Due to this, it now has the largest user base in India. The launch of Jio was game-changing for India because it redefined the limits of internet usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its e-commerce platform JioMart, Reliance plans to cause a similar disruption that Jio caused in the telecom sector. The aim is to “completely transform”  India’s unorganised retail market of mostly mom-and-pop stores, which account for nearly 90% of the nation’s retail industry. Through this online-offline model, JioMart won’t sell products to the customers directly but instead, it would link the online buyers with offline retailers in their locality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reliance estimates that through this platform it would be able to link 30 million offline retailers with 200 million households. The digital platform, unlike other foreign competitors, would link producers, traders, small merchants, consumer brands, and consumers under a common shed. Hence, JioMart is a strategically planned holistic model that aims to usher in opportunities not only to Reliance Industries but also to other people directly linked to the same industry. Moreover, at a time when other ventures of Reliance in the grocery segment such as Reliance Retail and Reliance Fresh, which have a strong offline presence over the country, are doing quite well, we can expect this online platform to be a ‘cash cow’ for the giant. To make them completely digitised, JioMart claims to integrate local &lt;em&gt;kirana&lt;/em&gt; (corner) stores and provide them with Points of Sale (PoS) terminals, educate them about inventory management skills, supply chain management, and Goods and Service Tax (GST) compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysts and experts are of the view that Facebook’s recent investment in Jio could help JioMart grow. The deal is expected to bear fruits for both the giants. On one side, Jio would gain from the technological expertise that Facebook brings to the table. At the same time, the payments made on the platform through WhatsApp Pay would help the messaging app to overcome the regulatory issues it has been facing. Moreover, Reliance being an already established brand in India would increase the customer base of the Facebook-owned company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to market the online retail platform, Jio has been sending invites to all its users to avail the preliminary discounts. Furthermore, it claims that all its listed products are sold at 5% below the Maximum Retail Price (MRP), this feature is quite similar to DMart’s model that made it quite successful overnight. Additionally, it is still offering the cash-on-delivery option that a lot of existing competitors have stopped. Claims have also been made that JioMart delivers 400,000 orders in a single day which is significantly higher than other grocery home delivery companies. Hence, if JioMart continues working in the same direction, it is bound to give a tough competition to its counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the launch of JioMart, rivals such as Amazon, have started taking steps to maintain their foothold. Amazon has signed a deal with Kishore Biyani’s Future Group to deliver its products. It has also started to broaden the options it provides and has resorted to selective discounting. Amazon has also launched ‘Local Shops’ which has enabled 5,000 offline retailers to set up shop online and has established 10 new warehouses to expand their storage capacity. Additionally, Flipkart said that it would reapply for a food retail license in India. Most importantly, Flipkart has bought Walmart India’s wholesale business in July and is expected to launch a digital marketplace, Flipkart Wholesale in August. So, these already established online platforms have identified the threat being posed by JioMart, and have buckled themselves up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At present, all that we can expect is that with the launch of JioMart, competitive intensity is likely to increase and nothing can be said about who will win the race. Everything is completely dependent upon who would be able to gain the eyes of more consumers and attract them easily with their lucrative offers, but it also seems to be a stiff competition since both JioMart and other established e-commerce websites are leaving no stone unturned. So, whether established e-commerce platforms retain their place or JioMart takes over is what remains to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cherry Sharma</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“Don’t find customers for your products, find products for your customers”, they say, and truly, those who have always thought about their consumers, are the ones whose products have been the most successful. I would not be wrong in saying that the economic development of any country starts and ends with the consumers of that country. Any consumer-related business can rise to great heights if the creators of that business model cater to the needs of the consumers and provide them with efficient services.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Elyments: A Step Towards ‘Atma Nirbhar’ Tech</title><link href="/Elyments" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elyments: A Step Towards ‘Atma Nirbhar’ Tech" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Elyments</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Elyments">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Friends, we have been hearing since the last century that the 21st century belongs to India. This is not our dream, rather a responsibility for all of us.”&lt;/em&gt;  These were the words of the Indian Prime Minister when the ‘Atma Nirbhar’ COVID-19 stimulus package was introduced. The PM seems to be determined to make this dream a reality and has successfully commenced India’s venture in the tech world. Indian Vice President Venkaiah Naidu launched India’s first social media app &lt;em&gt;Elyments&lt;/em&gt; on July 5, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After implementing a ban on Chinese apps, the Indian government decided to set its foot in the tech market and secure a powerful position. The app offers various features of video/voice call, instant messaging as well as social networking. It has encouraged the ‘Make in India’ initiative as it employed 1000 Information Technology (IT) professionals who created the app in a very short period. The aim was to boost confidence and faith in the campaign among fellow citizens. It has been downloaded more than 5 million times since its launch which is huge, considering it’s only been a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the app is being known as the “super app” because of the numerous features it has to offer, it does leave us with a few questions to ponder upon. The success is still undetermined and data security is a big concern among the users. Questions were frequently raised regarding data security in the case of Aadhaar and thus, it makes it difficult for us to trust this app as well. The developers have guaranteed safety and assurance that all data will be stored with the Indian servers itself. No data will be transferred to any third party without the user’s consent. A considerable amount of effort has been made just to ensure data safety and that no lapses are being experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition in this field is tough, with tech giants like Facebook and WhatsApp being the rivals. It becomes more important for the government to offer something new to the consumers. It won’t be a cakewalk for Elyments to secure its position as a strong player. The moment it fails to do so, the investments will boil down to zero making it difficult for the government to establish India in the tech space. The success of an app is determined by its active user base, which isn’t much in the case of Elyments. Developers should prioritise maximum sign-ups in the coming days. I feel the government is seriously lacking in the aspect of marketing the product that they have created. Strategising their moves and giving adequate attention to the required areas will definitely help it grow at a steady and smooth pace. Amid the Indo-Sino standoff, Elyments suffered a cyberattack and successfully recovered from it, which shows that it is capable of competing at a global level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these times of COVID-19 pandemic, when the economy is paying a heavy cost due to it, a failed attempt will be faced with major backlash, and people would not hesitate to highlight it as a waste of the taxpayer’s money. Further, this one failure will allow the rivals to regain control, thus making it even more difficult to enter the circle again. On the bright side, if it turns out to be a success, it will boost the economy and open up the gateway to ‘Made in India’ tech. This beginning will ensure a promising future for our young minds and a strong foothold of India in this domain. The vision of Atma Nirbhar Bharat will become a reality and the faith will be restored. Furthermore, there have never been any doubts regarding the brainpower that India possesses in terms of IT. Being the manufacturer of CEOs for tech companies around the world, it is time for India to focus on a homegrown giant and take over the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ananya Singh</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">“Friends, we have been hearing since the last century that the 21st century belongs to India. This is not our dream, rather a responsibility for all of us.” These were the words of the Indian Prime Minister when the ‘Atma Nirbhar’ COVID-19 stimulus package was introduced. The PM seems to be determined to make this dream a reality and has successfully commenced India’s venture in the tech world. Indian Vice President Venkaiah Naidu launched India’s first social media app Elyments on July 5, 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Businesses are Flying!</title><link href="/Businesses-are-Flying" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Businesses are Flying!" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Businesses-are-Flying</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Businesses-are-Flying">&lt;p&gt;Airports are incredibly complex and challenging businesses but, in many cases, they are businesses that make money. Many airports are owned by the government but still, they are often operated as businesses – just businesses that are publicly owned. The majority of airports make their money through what they earn from passenger-carrying commercial flights using their facilities. Some airports are cargo focused and fund their operation through cargo flights but airports such as Paris’s Charles De Gaulle Airport and London’s Heathrow Airport rely almost entirely on passenger flights. While the amount of cargo going through these airports is significant, the number of dedicated cargo flights is low in proportion to the airport’s daily flights. The question is: how do they generate profits and what goes on behind the scenes that enable them to run their operations effectively and, at the same time, efficiently? For this study, I am going to be looking at the most famous airport in the world – the London Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heathrow makes its money off of the 78 million passengers flying through each year. Heathrow is the busiest airport in the world that is fully privately owned - the UK government owns no stake in it and so it is perhaps the best example of an airport built to turn a profit. It costs $1,485,650,000 per year to run Heathrow airport. This includes costs like $494,000,000, which Heathrow pays in salaries to its 6,500 employees. Almost 76,000 people actually work at Heathrow but only those 6,500 actually work for Heathrow. The company that runs Heathrow, Heathrow Airport Holdings, is only responsible for the oversight and administration of the airport, within Heathrow’s walls though, there are hundreds of other companies operating. Those 70,000 other people work for the airlines, the baggage handling companies, the air traffic control company, the restaurants, the rental car companies, the bus company, and all the other different employers at the airport. There are, of course, plenty of other costs involved in running the airport from the $232 million dollars per year in maintenance to the $113 million yearly utility bill for water, electricity, internet, gas, and more. But overall that number of $1.5 billion is what it costs to run the sixth busiest airport in the world. That’s more than it costs to run the entire 1.3 million people country of Swaziland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a per passenger basis, it costs approximately $19 to run the Heathrow. Essentially that means Heathrow needs to make $19 from each passenger that passes through its doors in order to break even. Obviously, some passengers are more profitable than others. Arriving passengers generally just get off the plane, go through customs, and leave immediately without making any purchases. Whereas, connecting and departing passengers generally have more time to shop at the airport. Retail is incredibly important to the profitability of any airport. This is part of the reason why it’s in the airport’s best interest to make the security and check-in procedure as quickly as possible so the passengers have more time to shop. Heathrow makes money through retail by taking a cut out of every sale made. On average, through restaurants the airport earns 95 cents per passenger, retail stores earn them $5.15 per passenger, the parking lots add to another $2.03, then all the other smaller sources of retail revenue such as rental car companies and VIP lounges account for another $3.04. Rather uniquely, Heathrow also operates the express train from the airport to Paddington Station which makes them another $2.15 per passenger. All in all, the airport makes $13.32 from passengers through purchases on top of their actual airplane ticket, and it’s worth pointing out that this doesn’t mean that passengers spend $13.32 - this means that Heathrow makes $13.32 per passenger. This is their cut, the actual spending at the airport per passenger is much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may think that this amount of retail revenue per passenger is high and you would be right, it is. In fact, it’s one of the highest retail revenues per passenger of any airport worldwide. In comparison, Washington Dulles Airport makes $5.68 per passenger, Auckland Airport makes $7.71, and Paris’ Charles De Gaulle Airport makes $10.92 per passenger from retail. Heathrow is an expert in making passengers spend. They use all sorts of tricks and tactics to increase passenger spending. For example, in Terminal 3, to get from security and to all the gates, all passengers have to walk through duty-free which increases sales enormously. Heathrow also doesn’t display the gate for flights until 45-90 minutes before departure. Because of this, passengers wait in a central area where all the shops and restaurants are located. Being one of the very few airports with non-stop service to all six continents, Heathrow also has the advantage of being an airport focused on long-haul service. These flights tend to carry the wealthiest passengers and while, worldwide, passengers arrive at an average of 2 hours and 17 minutes before their flight, Heathrow passengers arrive 2 hours and 51 minutes before. This means they have more time to shop at the airport. As mentioned, though the airport needs to make $19 per passenger but retail only earns them just over $13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of it comes from flights. Each plane that lands at Heathrow pays the airport an average of $9,500. That goes to paying for things like gate space, a check-in area, and the runway time itself. On departure, airlines are charged again, this time per passenger. For each passenger flying to a destination outside of Europe, the airline is charged a base of $58 but this charge is reduced to $44 if a passenger connects through Heathrow rather than originating or to $39 if the aircraft is parked at a remote stand rather than a gate. It’s worth noting that these are the published prices. In reality, many airlines with a significant number of flights at Heathrow have an agreement with the airport that reduces their costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking it down, what those numbers mean is that Heathrow gets, on average, $29 of the cost of every passenger’s ticket. As you can see that means that Heathrow makes a fair bit more than it costs to run the airport. The company mostly uses this operating profit to pay off debt from prior projects and to pay taxes so, in the end, they are only truly making about $8.20 off of each of their passengers, but what these numbers also mean is that, by design, Heathrow is incentivised to attract long-haul flights. The airport is currently at capacity. Their maximum number of flights per day is 657, and they currently have 650. They really have no more capacity which means one of the only ways for them to grow financially is to bring in larger planes. This is no doubt that part of the reason why Heathrow is so poorly connected to the country is that it is in the UK. The airport only has flights to eight airports in the UK which means the airport has exactly the same number of destinations in the UK as it has in China. The reality is that Heathrow is a commercial company while most UK residents would likely want to see domestic flights to their largest airport, it just doesn’t make commercial sense to operate short and cheap flights. It’s not only less lucrative for the airport, but it’s also more costly for the passenger than flying to other smaller airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not every airport is like Heathrow. Not every airport is a commercial company, and that’s just because, in many cases, running an airport the way the public wants it to be run is bad business. About two-thirds of all airports worldwide lose money. In many cases that’s because they are government-run and just not that focused on making money. However, the entire focus of the authorities should not be on making the airports profitable. Because of the fact that ultimately, it’s the passengers who would be paying more for their travel and this would cause less travel and mobility, thus, hindering opportunities for people and lesser growth opportunity for the airport itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Manav Gupta</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Airports are incredibly complex and challenging businesses but, in many cases, they are businesses that make money. Many airports are owned by the government but still, they are often operated as businesses – just businesses that are publicly owned. The majority of airports make their money through what they earn from passenger-carrying commercial flights using their facilities. Some airports are cargo focused and fund their operation through cargo flights but airports such as Paris’s Charles De Gaulle Airport and London’s Heathrow Airport rely almost entirely on passenger flights. While the amount of cargo going through these airports is significant, the number of dedicated cargo flights is low in proportion to the airport’s daily flights. The question is: how do they generate profits and what goes on behind the scenes that enable them to run their operations effectively and, at the same time, efficiently? For this study, I am going to be looking at the most famous airport in the world – the London Heathrow.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accountability: An Illusion in Reality</title><link href="/An-Illusion-in-Reality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accountability: An Illusion in Reality" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/An-Illusion-in-Reality</id><content type="html" xml:base="/An-Illusion-in-Reality">&lt;p&gt;India is grappling with a spike in COVID-19 cases—even by the current earliest estimates, the peak is anywhere but close. Amidst the escalating tensions with neighbours Nepal and China, it has set the ball rolling for what is the most difficult test of governance for the incumbent Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what still remains obscure amidst this pandemonium is India’s interminable tryst with sustainable development—maintaining an equipoise of biodiversity and urbanisation. As the country went through phases of lockdowns, the Indian Environment Ministry, led by Prakash Javedkar, uploaded the reformed version of the EIA, which was last amended in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new legislation has led to a huge outcry among environmentalists, for it dilutes the ‘green law’­­—which compelled infrastructure projects to clear the scrutiny of its impact on the environment, and also involved the public. This update was approved by Javedkar and his predecessor, Dr Harsh Vardhan, after being drafted and updated within two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister, who spoke parables and platitudes pertaining to self-reliance, exhorted people to support indigenous brands and products. The growing Sinophobia has culminated with multinational brands such as Apple announcing shift of its manufacturing facilities to India, much to the delight of the average Indian, thumping to celebrate it as an embellishment to the nationalistic pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, what most Indians fail to notice, or passively take cognizance of, is the toll such ambitious manufacturing would take on the environment. This sets a dangerous premise, especially when India’s track record in sustainable development has been mediocre, to be modest, it dates back to the Nehru days. Jawaharlal Nehru famously said to the villagers displaced by the Hirakud Dam in 1948, &lt;em&gt;“If you must suffer, you should suffer in the interest of the country”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s obsession with building dams, despite most studies highlighting their futility, continues to haunt the tribal people living in the hinterlands. The Sardar Sarovar Dam is the country’s prime example of the environmental racism that continues to elude the front pages of the newspapers. Harrowing tales narrated by Man Booker Prize-winning author Arundhati Roy exposes the deepest trenches of social and economic oppression that the tribal landowners are subjected to after being deprived of the very land that is paramount to their survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unaware of how money works in urban dwellings, the displaced people are often stuffed into slum-like residences, sardonically quoted as urban ghettos. Not only are the displaced people forced to work as labourers, the conditions in which they live, far away from their homeland, raise concerns, especially with the country neck-deep in the contagion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To salvage themselves from the perils of a recession looming large at the economy, the government also decided to auction off 41 of its coal mines, many of which are located in the Hasdeo Arand region of Chhattisgarh—which is home to many tribal communities, for it is one of the largest contiguous dense forest areas in India. Privatisation would definitely place them under the threat of being displaced as well as the perils of pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arunachal Pradesh, which is one of the most diverse regions in the country with 26 tribal groups and 100 sub-tribal groups, is home to a 3,097-megawatt Etalin Dam. It is expected to submerge over 300,000 trees and affect Idu Mishmi, an indigenous tribe with a population of over 13,000. Additionally, the 2,880-megawatt Dibang Multipurpose Project, one of the largest planned projects in India, is set to displace nearly 2,000 Mishmi people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the dilution of the EIA, new biodiversity hotspots like Arunachal Pradesh would be set up, especially after the aforementioned projects having been approved without a dialogue with the major stakeholders - the displaced tribal groups. With only 3 Members of Parliament from Arunachal Pradesh, this minuscule representation has also been attributed to environmental racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EIA is essential for India, especially when the country has projects operational without proper environmental clearance. It was found out that the LG Polymer Plant in Vishakapatnam, from which styrene gas was leaked on May 7, was functional for over 20 years without any clearance. A similar incident was reported in Assam where the natural gas of Oil India Limited in the Tinsukia district was incinerated, causing severe damage to local biodiversity. The local environmental authority later released a statement accusing that the plant was running without their approval for the past 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conflagrating a movement for the environment with a law meant for seditious and extremism activities is alarming. A shallow EIA favouring builders with easy environmental clearances can increase incidents in Assam and Andhra Pradesh. It would further push a hitherto obscure yet an important section of the population residing for generations into oblivion. Meanwhile, an EIA report has recently stated that an estimated 33,000 trees would be cut to make way for the proposed Peripheral Ring Road in Bengaluru, from the proposed 200 trees in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unchecked environmental legislation could not only be the final blow to an already bludgeoning biodiversity but can also fan the flames of a humanitarian crisis, for fulfilling the fetishes of the rich.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Kant</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">India is grappling with a spike in COVID-19 cases—even by the current earliest estimates, the peak is anywhere but close. Amidst the escalating tensions with neighbours Nepal and China, it has set the ball rolling for what is the most difficult test of governance for the incumbent Prime Minister.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Icarus Paradox: Why Successful Ventures Fail?</title><link href="/Icarus-Paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Icarus Paradox: Why Successful Ventures Fail?" /><published>2020-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Icarus-Paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Icarus-Paradox">&lt;p&gt;Though most people deem pride as transgression, some appraise it as a trait that can be capitalised upon. Research teams at the University of Montreal and UC Santa Barbara’s Center for Evolutionary Psychology (CEP) suggest that pride is an evolutionary by-product of the trait of self-preservation. Because of the frequent lethal reversals that our ancestors faced, they needed their fellow band members to value them enough during hardships to pull them through. Therefore, in making choices, humans had to weigh their self-interest over the approval of others, so that when they needed help, others would value them enough to give it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though we have come a long way, &lt;em&gt;hubris&lt;/em&gt; is still not hard to come across. Irrespective of the peculiarity of its radix, pride is not limited to individuals - organisations also emanate it. The anomaly, however, is that organisational hubris is just a compendium of the egos of individuals who comprise it, but people in an organisation struggle to keep their individual pride in parity with the organisational one. Therefore, in theory, there is no comprehensible line distinguishing individual pride from organisational pride, as one is a concoction of the other. The practical aspect, however, differentiates between the magnitude and gravity of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanity is believed to be the root of all sin by cultures across the globe. While the widely followed Abrahamic religions talk about the spiritual descent of Lucifer into Satan as a result of his pride, the Greeks present the tale of Icarus. Icarus was the son of Daedalus - a famous Greek inventor. While in captivity, Daedalus crafted two pairs of wings which would enable him and his son to escape certain execution. Before taking off, Daedalus specifically instructed his son not to fly too high. Ignoring the words of his father, Icarus soared too near to the clouds, which ultimately led to his wings failing him. The boy plummeted to his death in the sea because his pride clouded his judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Danny Miller coined the term ‘Icarus Paradox’ in 1990. The term, alluding to the Greek tale, refers to the phenomenon of businesses suddenly failing after a period of success, where this failure is brought about by the very elements that led to their initial uprise. Miller noted that it’s the victories of the past that conceit a successful organisation, lulling them into complacency. The very values that usher companies upwards in the pecking order - such as tried-and-true business strategies, dauntless and self-assured management, and the overall combination of all these elements - may be rendered blunt and platitudinous, ultimately leading to business catastrophes. Managers tend to make injudicious decisions, as they cling onto the past success of their manoeuvres and fail to factor in the revamp in the external business environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most successful firms owe their fortune to a unique competitive algorithm which guides the formulation and execution of their policies. It helps it gain momentum and reach a higher pedestal, but cloaks its dynamism and its ability to acclimatise because the management’s confidence in this winning formula is bolstered. Eventually, the firm ends up focusing only on refining and extending these strategies, products and values. Activities/policies that do not conform to the paradigm are neglected or even discouraged. This may be profitable in the short run as companies continue to specialise and improve in a certain product or strategy, leading to higher efficiency, sales and growth as they develop a competitive advantage in a particular area. However, its viability is leached away in the long run, as the stereotypical aspect ingrained in their corporate culture barres them from keeping up with the threats of new competitors, changing consumer demands, newly developed business models and changes in the external environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standard economic theory explains the high rate of failures as an inevitable result of companies taking rational risks in the face of peaky situations. The rewards of a few successes outweigh losses incurred from many failures in the long run. Executives know this and accept the risk. Anyhow, this theory absolves them from blame as they simply obey rationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lovallo and Kahneman from the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/em&gt;, however, argue that most failures are actually the results of flawed decision making. While predicting the outcomes of potentially risky projects, executives easily fall victim to what psychologists call the ‘planning fallacy’. They make decisions based on delusional optimism instead of rational computation of gains, losses, and probabilities, dwelling in situations of hypothetical success while overlooking potential problems. Consequently, they are overly optimistic and pursue opportunities that are unlikely to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prime example of the paradox at work would be Tesco’s experimental venture into the US market – Fresh &amp;amp; Easy. Tesco opened the chain in 2007- right before the economic recession which took a severe toll on consumer spending. Tesco also did not anticipate the upshot in the popularity of online grocery shopping. Additionally, Tesco’s research segment misconstrued the spending habits of their consumer base. While their Metro stores in the UK were popular, there was not enough demand in the US as the population was not accustomed to grab-and-go meals. Most of the Americans would usually order take out or cook their own meals - as purchasing such meals would be comparatively costlier than grocery shopping. Lastly, an elementary point of distinction was the statistics indicating that most people in the US buy their groceries once a week, with bulk and diversity of purchase being the key takeaways. Conversely, Europeans tend to make more frequent, but smaller trips to the grocery stores. After they took a hit of approximately £1.2bn ($1.8bn), Tesco’s net profit slithered down by 96%, compelling them to abandon the US market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, Tesco’s confidence in bringing its successful concept of ready meals to the US market contributed heavily to its failure. The intensive marketing required to change people’s daily consumption proclivities takes time and money, neither of which Tesco invested enough of. Tesco was also confident enough to continue to hang on for over 5 years despite indications of possible failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above example highlights &lt;em&gt;hubris&lt;/em&gt; in its raw essence, which can be used as a base for conceptual bifurcation, creating multiple subdivisions rooted in the same basic concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Humans have a natural tendency to amplify their own talents, which leads a lot of executives to believe that they transcend the rest in ability and output. This is further reinforced by the tendency to misperceive causes of certain events and attribute success to their abilities when it might have been out of pure luck.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People also display keenness to take credit for positive outcomes and ascribe undesirable ones to external factors. A study of letters to shareholders in annual reports, for example, found that managers tend to attribute favourable outcomes to variables under their control, like corporate strategy or R&amp;amp;D (research and development) programs, while inimical ones were more likely to be attributed to uncontrollable external factors like the weather or inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A company’s values unify its people. Strong, meaningful credos can help inculcate employee loyalty, strengthen the bonds between a company and its customers, attract like-minded partners, and hold together a company’s far-flung operations. However, as companies mature, these values may morph into commandments- which contribute more towards suppressing novelty and flexibility, rather than inspiring moral conduct.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A peculiar observation made in business process analysis is that, as more investment is made in information technology, worker productivity may go down instead of going up. This observation has been firmly supported by empirical evidence from the 1970’s to the early 1990’s. Prior to the upward jolt in IT investment, the expected return on investment in terms of productivity was 3-4%. The aberration, however, was that with IT, the normal return on investment was only 1% from the 1970’s to the early 1990’s. Thus, the investment in IT - done for performance enhancement - led to contradictory outcomes that threatened to pick the organisation apart. This is known as the ‘paradox of information technology’- a concept encapsulated by the Icarus paradox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it may seem easy to deal with, the paradox is a trap that is too hard to escape, with companies like Lehman Brothers, Xerox, Atari, Digital Equipment, Tupperware and Revlon on the victim list. Also, a lot of unforeseen complications arise upon the initial implementation of solutions. The key is an optimum blend of flexibility, innovation, and diversification, which needs to be instilled in the bedrock of the organisational structure of business entities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aryaman Dhiman</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Though most people deem pride as transgression, some appraise it as a trait that can be capitalised upon. Research teams at the University of Montreal and UC Santa Barbara’s Center for Evolutionary Psychology (CEP) suggest that pride is an evolutionary by-product of the trait of self-preservation. Because of the frequent lethal reversals that our ancestors faced, they needed their fellow band members to value them enough during hardships to pull them through. Therefore, in making choices, humans had to weigh their self-interest over the approval of others, so that when they needed help, others would value them enough to give it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shutting Our Doors?</title><link href="/Shutting-Our-Doors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shutting Our Doors?" /><published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Shutting-Our-Doors</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Shutting-Our-Doors">&lt;p&gt;Observation has reached its peak for me as I find my eyes looking for details behind each jar of Nutella or on the side of our microwave. All thanks to the lockdown that has dragged me back home from college and given me enough free time to look around the house with a magnifying glass, which I wouldn’t have done otherwise on my busy school days as a child. And observation, mixed with a little bit of research, has led me to the understanding that my house, which in fact buys everything from local stores, actually reeks of products from China. From the water geyser to the processor in the ceiling fan, from the dinner crockery to the food processor, from parts of our mobile phones to our daily t-shirts, nothing is spared from the clenching claws of China. The fact that all these products were available to us in the local stores at prices comfortable enough for our pockets, speaks volumes about the kind of consumerism China has created in each and every household, office, company, factory, industry and restaurant in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calls to boycott Chinese goods had started gaining momentum when the martyrdom of twenty Indian soldiers in the Ladakh stand-off against China aroused public sentiment, and they took to their hands to avenge the soldiers’ deaths by publicly breaking TV sets of Chinese brands. These calls couldn’t have gone unnoticed by the government which then had to take a step to show India’s hostility towards China. A violent uprising, that had cost us our soldiers’ lives, very recently, was discarded as a move from our end, also taking into account that China had retreated from the Indian borders. Now the question was :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Can India afford to boycott China?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feasibilities of numbers of steps like - import reduction, import-substitution, self-reliance, and lastly, a blanket ban - were pondered upon. While the other options were on the table, considering the sentimental charge of the public, the possible implications of a blanket ban were considered. A blanket ban is a complete prohibition, which in this case would mean banning not just imports from China but also trade and investment. A superpower like the US has openly made hate speeches on China and has also taken moves such as shutting down a Chinese consulate in Texas. But considering the Indian economy’s huge dependence on China, can India really impose a blanket ban on China and move to self-reliance as quickly as we think? A step-by-step analysis will help us understand the implications of this move better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade:&lt;/strong&gt; The Indian economy is heavily dependent on Chinese imports that include intermediate and finished goods. Intermediate goods from China, such as chemicals, pharmaceuticals, electronic components, have long helped industries in India sustain. But if India wishes to take a few steps back in its trading chain with China, India will have to adopt medium to long-term policy moves. These include, but are not restricted to, financial support or subsidising micro, small and medium businesses that can actually manufacture the products that we import from China. The informal sector in the production chain in India, with the right kind of policy support, can eventually lead us to self-reliance in a matter of a few years. However, a step backwards in the import chain from China could also mean opening doors to imports from other countries. For India to become a favourable import destination, certain financial supports like import duty exemption and cash subsidy on imports from other countries are necessary to match the cost of Chinese imports. In the short-term, expediting Free Trade Agreements (FTAs) to lure imports and investments from other countries is one of the most viable options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investment:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian start-ups, with the right kind of investment boost, have a tendency of growing big in this ever-evolving capitalistic world of ours. But a lot of local start-ups fail to garner the kind of investment from major Indian ventures, which is what China has taken advantage of for close to a decade now. Alibaba, invested in an Indian start-up Paytm, back in 2015 when the future of Paytm itself was bleak, but China slyly took advantage of the gap in investment that existed. Moreover, China has not blinked an eye before investing in a lot of local start-ups, knowing very well that like most other start-ups, these too may be loss-making. The reason behind this is that China is ready to make a trade-off of investing in a loss-making start-up to be able to get a footing in the market share of the Indian market. Eventually, when the local start-ups grow enough to have a valuation of over $1 billion and come under the category of ‘Unicorns’, is when it finally comes to our eyes that the major Indian start-ups, like Snapdeal, Ola, Swiggy, Paytm, Flipkart and so many more, have a Chinese investor. To combat the issue of Chinese investors, like Alibaba, monopolising in the Indian market by investing in most Indian unicorns and creating an obvious outsized impact, the Indian government decided to amend the Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) rules to cap off the number of companies an investor can invest in, so as to prevent any hostile takeovers of the Indian market by any foreign investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology:&lt;/strong&gt; We’re no aliens to the fact that China practically holds the lion’s share in the smartphone market of India, while India has little to no alternatives in the smartphone arena. It would require huge amounts of investment in research and technology to be able to reduce dependence on China for smartphone technology and components. In addition, Chinese tech firms, like Alibaba, and apps like TikTok, reach the Indian consumers as much as applications like Google, Amazon, Facebook, and Instagram. The Indian government has recently made a move to ban the likes of these Chinese applications that actually have local alternatives, and this as a strategic move has a lasting impact on the kind of hostility India wants to opt for. In fact, a restriction in the telecommunications sector, such as banning Huawei, is also a feasible move considering that Indian alternatives, such as Jio and BSNL, are easily available to the Indian consumers. To top it off, Huawei could also be banned from India’s 5G rollout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, answering the bigger question: &lt;em&gt;Can India really shut its doors by imposing a blanket ban on China&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, a blanket ban on China will result in a very quick supply disruption leaving the Indian consumers exposed to only a minimal amount of not-so-pocket friendly alternatives. Furthermore, the economy will have to bear high input costs and therefore, this move will prove to be a costly one for India. Instead, the viable solution would be to allow steady withdrawal of Chinese products by allowing import substitution as well as funding the budding industries in the unorganised sector. India will have to take slow steps forward, keeping in mind cost-effectiveness and affordability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Observation has reached its peak for me as I find my eyes looking for details behind each jar of Nutella or on the side of our microwave. All thanks to the lockdown that has dragged me back home from college and given me enough free time to look around the house with a magnifying glass, which I wouldn’t have done otherwise on my busy school days as a child. And observation, mixed with a little bit of research, has led me to the understanding that my house, which in fact buys everything from local stores, actually reeks of products from China. From the water geyser to the processor in the ceiling fan, from the dinner crockery to the food processor, from parts of our mobile phones to our daily t-shirts, nothing is spared from the clenching claws of China. The fact that all these products were available to us in the local stores at prices comfortable enough for our pockets, speaks volumes about the kind of consumerism China has created in each and every household, office, company, factory, industry and restaurant in India.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gandhi, a ‘Mahatma’?</title><link href="/Gandhi-a-Mahatma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gandhi, a 'Mahatma'?" /><published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Gandhi-a-Mahatma</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Gandhi-a-Mahatma">&lt;p&gt;In June 2020, an online petition to remove Mahatma Gandhi’s statue in the British city of Leicester was filed which had garnered 6,052 signatures, as of July 30, 2020. The bronze statue in Leicester, which captures Gandhi in his walking stride, was unveiled in the city in 2009. The petition titled ‘Remove the Gandhi Statue in Leicester’ accuses him of being “a fascist, racist and sexual predator”. It further says, “&lt;em&gt;For years he has been idolised and taught in the school curriculum. For many people in my community, he has brought inconsolable suffering against my people. As a result, I do not wish to see a statue and praise of that kind of character. Therefore, I want to take action to remove it&lt;/em&gt;”. According to the Leicester City Council, the petition hasn’t been submitted to the authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar online petition was filed in the Canadian city of Ottawa in June 2020 calling for the removal of Gandhi’s statue from the Carleton University Campus. As of July 30, 2020, it had garnered 2,563 signatures. Echoing similar sentiments as the Leicester petition, it says, “&lt;em&gt;Why should an institution continue to yield the statue of an individual who was publicly anti-black, referred to Africans as savages, likening them to animals, and slept naked with his grandniece to ‘test his willpower’? It is inexplicable and inexcusable. As an institution, we cannot claim to champion diversity and seek to eradicate institutionalised racism as long as symbols like this are still present on our campus. The time for action is now&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These petitions come after a series of statues of racist people being removed. On May 25, 2020, an African-American man, George Floyd, was murdered in Minneapolis by a white Police officer. His death sparked a series of protests against police brutality and racial inequality all over the world. The Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement of 2020, has put the past to scrutiny by targeting the monuments and statues of people who carry the legacy of slavery and colonialism: the Confederate General Robert E Lee in Virginia, Theodore Roosevelt in New York City, Christopher Columbus in many US cities, the Belgian king Leopold II in Brussels, the slave trader Edward Colston in Bristol, Jean-Baptiste Colbert, Finance Minister for Louis XIV and author of the infamous Code Noir in France, Indro Montanelli, and so on. Their statues are being toppled, defaced, destroyed and vandalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi is known as the renowned Indian lawyer-turned-activist who led India to independence. However, he, too, was an imperfect human being. Rajmohan Gandhi, Gandhi’s biographer, and grandson has previously admitted that his grandfather was “at times ignorant and prejudiced towards South Africa’s blacks”. Several academics have noted reports of Gandhi’s derogatory views towards native Africans while he lived in South Africa in the late 19th century. Gandhi wrote to the Natal Parliament in 1893, “&lt;em&gt;A general belief seems to prevail in the Colony that the Indians are a little better, if at all, than savages or the Natives of Africa&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1904, he wrote to a health officer in Johannesburg that the council “must withdraw Kaffirs” from an unsanitary slum called the “Coolie Location” where a large number of Africans lived alongside Indians. He wrote, “&lt;em&gt;About the mixing of the Kaffirs with the Indians, I must confess I feel most strongly&lt;/em&gt;”. The same year he wrote that unlike the African, the Indian had no “war-dances, nor does he drink Kaffir beer”. During the Durban plague in 1905, Gandhi wrote that the problem would persist as long as Indians and Africans were being herded together indiscriminately at the hospital. The term *&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-34265882&quot;&gt;kaffi*r&lt;/a&gt; is considered a racial slur used to refer to indigenous Black South Africans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book, &lt;em&gt;The South African Gandhi: Stretcher-Bearer of Empire&lt;/em&gt;, Ashwin Desai and Goolam H Vahed wrote that during his stay in Africa, Gandhi kept the Indian struggle separate from Africa’s, despite the fact that the latter was also being denied political rights based on colour. Further, Ashwin Desai, professor of Sociology at the University of Johannesburg, described Gandhi as a man who “supported more taxes on impoverished African people and turned a blind eye to the brutality of the Empire on Africans”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, owing to his work during the Indian independence struggle, many people have come to defend the statue. Leicester East Member of Parliament Claudia Webbe called the petition a “massive distraction” from the BLM movement. Comparing Gandhi to Martin Luther King, the Labour politician said, &lt;em&gt;“Gandhi, too, created a movement the same way Martin Luther King did, which became a force for change&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faisal Devji, a professor of Indian history at Oxford University, described the debate to remove the statue as absurd. He added, “&lt;em&gt;He’s a fallible man as all men are, but to lump him in with slave owners, that’s a bit much&lt;/em&gt;”. Citing the importance of the statue, he calls it a representation of the large refugee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-leicestershire-53025407&quot;&gt;Gujarati community in the city&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This protest is not the first time people have called out Gandhi’s racist beliefs. London had witnessed protests against Gandhi’s statues in 2003 and 2008. Similarly, American states like California, San Francisco, Michigan and Texas have witnessed such protests in 2013, 2011, 2010, and 2014, respectively. Johannesburg too witnessed one in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2016, an online petition started by professors at the University of Ghana called for the removal of Gandhi’s statue from the university’s Legon campus. The statue was erected in June 2016 at the Recreational Quadrangle and is the only statue of a historical personality on campus. Supporting the BLM movement, Dr Obadele Kambon, the creator of the petition, told BBC, “&lt;em&gt;At the end of the day, we need images of ourselves for our psychosocial well-being and not images of those who called us savages. May Gandhi fall that Africa may rise!&lt;/em&gt;” In 2018, this statue was removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2019, students from Manchester called for a similar statue of Gandhi given to the city by Shrimad Rajchandra Mission Dharampur (SRMD) to be removed because of his “well-documented anti-black racism”. In an open letter, the students demanded the Council acknowledge his vile comments and issue an apology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statues of historical figures don’t help people learn about history, but merely place certain figures on pedestals. While the past can no longer be changed, and society evolves to become more cognizant of other identities, we need to take a stand about whom we place on a celebration. The protests against these statues do just that. For instance, in the city of Bristol, England, a statue of Black Lives Matter protester Jen Reid was placed on an empty plinth where a monument to a 17th-century slave trader had stood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, while the statues in Leicester and Ottawa still stand tall, we must also question the actions of those whom we glorify. Additionally, to what extent shall we pedestalise these people? If you focus on only one part of their life, are you ignoring their other work? Does their noble work negate their wrongdoings? Can we hold them accountable for their wrongdoings? And if so, what is the best method?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While discriminating against any section of people is unacceptable, I hold the opinion that we cannot view our ancestor’s actions with a presentist lens - the tendency to interpret past events in terms of modern values and concepts. We all too often colour history with our lens of current prejudices. Fritz Fischer, a German historian, was against presentism as it allowed people to skew history in a way that would validate their own political beliefs. Thus, a 21st-century inclusive society must also take note of the attitudes and cultural values that existed in the past. Gandhi grew up in an orthodox Hindu family. Thus, his actions were a product of his time and a manifestation of the attitudes that existed then. This, however, is not to say that we should let him off the hook. Instead, we shall create a space where all of his actions can equally co-exist, instead of seeing him in the binary of a good or a bad person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our forebears will always fail to measure up to our modern standards, but it is not to say that any of these findings are irrelevant. While bygones will be bygones, we can accept the past and readily evolve ourselves, as a society, to ensure we no longer make similar mistakes. This also encompasses being tolerant of diverging opinions, especially those which stem out of lived experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Devyani Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In June 2020, an online petition to remove Mahatma Gandhi’s statue in the British city of Leicester was filed which had garnered 6,052 signatures, as of July 30, 2020. The bronze statue in Leicester, which captures Gandhi in his walking stride, was unveiled in the city in 2009. The petition titled ‘Remove the Gandhi Statue in Leicester’ accuses him of being “a fascist, racist and sexual predator”. It further says, “For years he has been idolised and taught in the school curriculum. For many people in my community, he has brought inconsolable suffering against my people. As a result, I do not wish to see a statue and praise of that kind of character. Therefore, I want to take action to remove it”. According to the Leicester City Council, the petition hasn’t been submitted to the authority.</summary></entry></feed>