<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-20T09:57:15+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Free Market Conundrum</title><link href="/The-Free-Market-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Free Market Conundrum" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Free-Market-Conundrum</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Free-Market-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;The 1980’s was an important era in the history of economics and the world. With the election of President Ronald Regan in the United States and Baroness Thatcher of Kesteven as Prime in the United Kingdom, economic policies in the West underwent a major overhaul. Subsequently, international institutions made these policies a prerequisite for granting loans to the countries that were on the brink of bankruptcy. The policies that I am talking about are the neo-liberal economic policies, and the framework they are built upon is the fundamental assumption of the efficiency of free markets. Every undergraduate economics student is taught that leaving markets to function without any intervention by the State will accrue benefits to the society as a whole. This article is an attempt to look at why free markets are not so free and why they do not always lead to the best of outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every transaction takes place with an implicit assumption that the other party will uphold their end of the bargain. If that does not happen, they are likely to approach the police or courts for justice. This tells us that to function freely, markets depend on some rules and regulations. The rhetoric around the free markets often fails to appreciate these rules because they are taken for granted. In fact, for the markets to function, property rights need to be clearly defined and enforceable. Therefore, it is absolutely correct to say that government laws, rules and regulations create scope for the markets to function and form the basis that drives competition. Then there are patents. Though there are strong arguments as to the requirement of such laws in place, they themselves act as obstacles to market freedom. Patents can lead to situations where the goods are out of reach of those who value (value here is not in terms of the amount paid but in terms of necessity) them the most. &lt;em&gt;Gleevac&lt;/em&gt;, a leukaemia drug, is a case in point. The cost of this drug in the US is $70,000 since Novartis, the company that manufactures the drug has a patent in the US. Thanks to the refusal of the Supreme Court of India to grant a patent, it is available for $2,500 in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem with free markets is that of ‘asymmetric information’. Asymmetric information arises when one party (typically the seller) possesses more information or knowledge about goods or services being sold. One common example that you will come across is about how the buyers of health insurance have an incentive to conceal their health information to get a better insurance deal. This example portrays how the sellers are at a loss. But today, you see almost every insurance company has a physician only from whom you are allowed to take a medical checkup. For a more general example, consider a clothes shop or a tech gadget shop. Old stock is prominently displayed so as to dispose of the stock and in such situations, the seller has more information than the buyer. Of course, there are resources available today that help bridge the information gap, but still the problem is more commonplace than we all think. The economic theory treats this asymmetry of information as an anomaly — one of the three instances of market failure. What it fails to recognise is that this phenomenon is not an exception, but a ubiquitous conundrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inherent characteristic of the free markets, that has hardly ever been a part of the public discourse, is that they are indifferent to human needs and provide only those goods and services that are profitable. Take, for example, the case of Google. Over the years the search engine giant has altered its webpage to show pre-packaged information when we search for something, rather than sending traffic to other websites. This may not affect you or me directly; but will result in the loss of customers to many businesses, whose business models rely on Google sending traffic to their websites. Another example is the pharmaceutical industry. During the initial stages in the coronavirus outbreak in February 2020, Rolf Hilgenfeld, a structural biologist, told the scientific journal &lt;em&gt;Nature, “The total number of people infected, if you combine SARS, MERS [previous related coronavirus outbreaks] and this new virus, is under 12,500 people. That’s not a market. The number of cases is too small. Pharmaceutical companies are not interested”&lt;/em&gt;. Though the trails for a vaccine are underway, one cannot miss the larger point. One more example is the Indian realty market. Despite the requirement of an additional 20 million houses, there is no sign of falling housing prices. This is partly because the developers prevent a fall in price in anticipation of a boost in demand in the future. Sometimes, by delaying construction, they demand higher amounts from the buyers to complete the construction. The end result is, despite a huge population without their own houses and large inventories held by realtors, the market is unable to satisfy the needs of the end-users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time, you might have come to the conclusion that I am a communist; I am not. What I am trying to get across is that while free markets benefit society in many ways, there are also many faults associated with free markets. Even as free markets provide what most people want, they will deceive, manipulate, and tempt us into buying things that might be harmful to us. Renowned economists George Akerlof and Robert Shiller said, &lt;em&gt;“Markets are not benign forces working for the greater good but instead are filled with businesses that ‘phish’ by exploiting our weaknesses to get us to buy their products”&lt;/em&gt;. From the 1980’s, in many countries across the world, the role of the state was cut down, paving ways for the ‘free markets’ to operate. There has been little debate about the flaws in the free market system and economists fail to acknowledge the problem. The failure in understanding the markets will only result in the formulation of bad policies. The failure to rectify the existing problems will tilt the markets to work in favour of a few and will result in wide sections of society being worse off. The capitalist system works well not just because there are free markets but also because there are a wide range of institutional arrangements that act as checks and balances on these markets. It is important to recognise that the state plays as important a role as the markets to bring the economy to equilibrium. Finally, there is nothing wrong with wanting free markets; but to think that they can’t go wrong is a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">The 1980’s was an important era in the history of economics and the world. With the election of President Ronald Regan in the United States and Baroness Thatcher of Kesteven as Prime in the United Kingdom, economic policies in the West underwent a major overhaul. Subsequently, international institutions made these policies a prerequisite for granting loans to the countries that were on the brink of bankruptcy. The policies that I am talking about are the neo-liberal economic policies, and the framework they are built upon is the fundamental assumption of the efficiency of free markets. Every undergraduate economics student is taught that leaving markets to function without any intervention by the State will accrue benefits to the society as a whole. This article is an attempt to look at why free markets are not so free and why they do not always lead to the best of outcomes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO</title><link href="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”&lt;/em&gt;, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included &lt;em&gt;“And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”&lt;/em&gt;. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NATO was founded in 1949 with a total of 30 members. The members include nations from North America (Canada and the United States) and 28 of the European countries. Its military nature is profoundly indicated by Article 5 of the treaty which states that in the occurrence of an attack against any one of the member states, it shall be understood to have been an attack against all members. This ensures the assistance of all the other member nations against the common adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) formed what was known as the Warsaw Pact in 1955 that included the Eastern Bloc Socialist Republics of Central and Eastern Europe. It was a collective defence treaty created as a reaction to the integration of West Germany into NATO. After the end of the Cold War and consequent nullification of the Warsaw Pact, NATO added 14 more member nations – 10 of them included in the Warsaw Pact and 4 former Yugoslav Republics. Some of the important operations undertaken by NATO include the defence of Denmark and Norway during September 1952, Exercise Longstep in the Mediterranean sea, Exercise Campaign Reforger which was an annual exercise by NATO states during the Cold War, and Exercise Strikeback which was a naval exercise that took place over a ten-day period in September 1957. The Northern Wedding had been another significant naval military exercise aimed at examining NATOs ability to reinforce Europe militarily during the Cold War in 1978. The latest development arrived in the form of DEFENDER-Europe 20 which was a US-led multinational exercise which included NATO’s participation. Notably, it was the largest deployment of US-based forces to Europe in the last quarter of a century. It included the participation of 20,000 soldiers deployed directly from the US to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Aspersions on NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ascent of Donald Trump in US national politics birthed a characteristic nationalistic, isolationist tendency, popularly termed as the ‘America First Policy’. It has been manifested in his scathing takes on multilateral organisations which include the United Nations (UN), and more recently the World Health Organisation (WHO) in the background of the coronavirus pandemic. Thus it comes as no surprise that he had been a stringent opponent to the very fundamental notions that have contributed to the formation of NATO. The &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; had reported that President Trump had on more than one occasion expressed desires to pull the US out of NATO. There are three primary reasons for his efforts to distance the US from this treaty - nearly 70% of the total spending on defence by NATO governments is accounted for by the US. In terms of the US Gross Domestic Product (GDP), the US spent roughly 3.4% on defence in 2019, while the average in European NATO countries and Canada was 1.55%. Naturally, Trump considers NATO to be an extra drain upon the military budget. NATO is funded by a common funding arrangement determined by each country’s national income. NATO had stated that the civilian and military budget for 2019 was $1.84 billion, out of which the US was paying 22%, France and the UK paid around 10.5% and Germany about 14.76%. The other alliance members contributed for the rest. This had caused bilateral relations between the US and Germany to worsen, as Trump, while referring to the burden shouldered by the US criticised the Germans for being “delinquent” in their payment to NATO. Trump further stated that the US shall move 12,000 troops out of the country. Jens Stoltenberg, the NATO Secretary-General had stated, &lt;em&gt;“We have now agreed (on) a new formula for sharing costs. The US will pay less. Germany will pay more”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem lies in the fact that the US, being a global superpower, has military commitments around the world and is not restricted to the geographical area of Europe and North America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the US deploys tens of thousands of active-duty personnel in Europe including in Turkey. The US diplomatic commitments in Europe also include a missile defence system run by NATO members. This is designed to shield against potential long-range ballistic missile attacks from outside the continent. Thus, the active presence of both men and arms is required on the part of the US. For the US President, all these factors are more of a display of magnanimity than a tool of diplomatic leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is important to note that a Chicago Council Survey in 2014 said that 78% of the American public supports NATO, 66% believed that the US commitment to NATO should remain as it is, as opposed to 7% supporting the possibility of a withdrawal. Thus the question of whether it is time to ring the death knell of NATO has its fair share of nay-sayers and aye-sayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Consequences in a World without NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the possible dissolution of the 71-year-old organisation, there will be a risk of Russian aggression. Many diplomats believe that had the post-Soviet Baltic nations which did not join NATO would have already been occupied by Russian expansionist aims. In the absence of NATO, mutual security interests such as combating ISIS and other global defence attempts emanating from coalition operations would be severely jeopardised. NATO’s retirement has the possibility to exacerbate divisions within Europe, especially in a post-Brexit, weakened European Union. The disappearance of NATO might make America’s Asian partners side with a rising China. Moreover, it will greatly strengthen the Russian Federation, which will reclaim the East European states which were formerly a part of the USSR. The clear political gainers would be Russia and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the question remains: To be or not to be? Amer-Exit from NATO and the consequent dissolution of NATO? Or a fundamental rebuilding exercise is that shall salvage the organisation that has maintained relative stability in the trans-Atlantic region?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included “And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Israel-UAE Deal: History Created?</title><link href="/Israel-UAE-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Israel-UAE Deal: History Created?" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Israel-UAE-Deal</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Israel-UAE-Deal">&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump exemplified his love affair with Twitter as he took to the microblogging platform to break the news of a historic truce between Israel and the United Arab Emirates (UAE). This makes Abu Dhabi the third nation in the Arab world and the first among the Gulf nations to recognise Israel as a nation. The move is touted by many as a game-changer in the geopolitics of the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gulf countries have not, for over a century, officially recognised Israel as a nation because of the ongoing Israel-Palestinian crisis. Trump also brokered an agreement where Israel would suspend its plans to annex the Western Bank — a region of conflict between the Jewish Israelis and the Palestinian Muslims, where the latter has also been subjucted to various atrocities violating human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle East is a precarious region, and its geopolitics is largely influenced by a Cold War-like proxy war between two of its behemoths – Saudi Arabia and Iran. The roots of this complex crosshairs can be traced back to the First World War, which culminated with the fall of the Ottoman Empire. The local Al Saud tribe in the Arabian peninsula fought off everyone who staked a claim in the region, and modern-day Saudi Arabia was officially recognised in 1932. Until 1979, Saudi Arabia was regarded as an undisputed bastion of Muslims across the world, for the progeny of the dynasty were also the custodians of the holy mosques in Mecca and Medina — the two holiest shrines in Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Iranian Revolution in 1979 saw the rise of a theocratic rule stemming from the Shia sect of Islam under Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini. Not only did he envisage Iran as a regional power, but he also challenged a Sunni-dominated Saudi Arabia’s claim to lead the Muslim world. This came as a shock to many for Khomeini’s ascent was first welcomed by then-Saudi ruler King Salman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran, rich in oil reserves, changed its foreign policy to undermine America’s influence in the region. This further fanned its animosity with Saudi, which had been a pro-America state. However, unlike Saudi, Iran wasn’t able to pull in money for its oil reserves and was crippled with the sanctions imposed on it by the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has largely supported rebel groups, some of them are extremists and are categorised as ‘terrorist groups’ in the unrest that has prevailed in the region. Before the US invasion in Iraq, the country served as somewhat of a buffer zone between the two nations. Many diplomatic circles jokingly say that America invaded Iraq only to gift it to Iran, and it is for a good reason that the ISIS occupation in Iraq had been largely supported by the Iraqi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khomeini’s new government also turned hostile towards Israel, it withdrew its decision to recognise Israel as a state and severed all ties with it. Iraq’s policy of supporting rebel groups in conflict-laden areas also meant that it supported opposing extremist groups against Israel — Hezbollah in Lebanon, and Hamas and Palestinian Islamic Jihad in Israel, for it considers the state a Zionist regime. (Zionism was the movement which led to the foundation of Israel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE’s peace agreement (albeit the government in Abu Dhabi calls it a roadmap to a peaceful relationship) has offended the Palestinians, who saw an ally in them. They were also taken by surprise by this announcement since they were not informed about any of this. &lt;em&gt;“May you never be sold out by your ‘friends’”&lt;/em&gt;, Hanan Ashrawi, a senior official, angrily tweeted at the Emirati crown prince.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian Authority has been championing for a separate state, and its President Mahmoud Abbas is disillusioned with the Trump administration for its pro-Israel stance. &lt;em&gt;“The Palestinian leadership rejects and denounces the UAE, Israeli and US trilateral, surprising, announcement”&lt;/em&gt;, said a senior adviser to Abbas and called it a &lt;em&gt;“betrayal of Jerusalem, Al-Aqsa, and the Palestinian cause”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to look at this agreement is a reaffirmation of the fact that UAE doesn’t detest Israel as much as its Arab counterparts do. This is diametrically opposed to the Arab and Muslim viewpoint of the official recognition of Israel in 1948 as a ‘pro-Western’ move, analogous to the erstwhile European colonialism that once existed. Many diplomatic commentators see this as the UAE’s plan for a more liberal and open foreign policy which is evident from the immigrants that throng to the country for work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian cause is, irrefutably, hurt by this agreement. Although the UAE made it clear that the “suspension of plans to annex the Western Bank” was their priority, Palestinians would see it as tokenism if the UAE doesn’t raise the question of Palestinian statehood. There is an opinion that the Emiratis are disenchanted with the Palestinian separatist movement, possibly because they don’t want to see its citizens or its government to be supportive of a separatist movement, especially when dissent is hardly tolerated in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both for US President Donald Trump and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, it is an attempt to save some of the public approval that elected them. The two leaders are receiving flak and opprobrium for their management of the coronavirus pandemic. While Trump is also criticised for his failed diplomatic projects and a US economy that has been bludgeoned by the pandemic, Netanyahu faces a trial of corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the decision in Washington is bipartisan — the Democratic Presidential candidate Joe Biden and presumptive Vice-Presidential candidate Kamala Harris have also welcomed this decision. This also indicates that the government in Abu Dhabi is preparing itself for the fact that Trump might not win a second term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Trump is pinning his hopes on other Arab states to follow suit. However, this agreement also undermines any hopes of a permanent settlement between the Israelis and Palestinians. The further implications of this deal are yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishi Kant</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">President Donald Trump exemplified his love affair with Twitter as he took to the microblogging platform to break the news of a historic truce between Israel and the United Arab Emirates (UAE). This makes Abu Dhabi the third nation in the Arab world and the first among the Gulf nations to recognise Israel as a nation. The move is touted by many as a game-changer in the geopolitics of the region.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Injudicious Judiciary</title><link href="/Injudicious-Judiciary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Injudicious Judiciary" /><published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Injudicious-Judiciary</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Injudicious-Judiciary">&lt;p&gt;Marquess Acton of Groppoli famously said, &lt;em&gt;“Power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely”&lt;/em&gt;. In order to prevent absolute power from corrupting absolutely, the founding fathers of free India established the Indian judicial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian judicial system has been hailed as the third pillar of democracy. Its primary duty as bestowed by the Constitution of India was to keep a check on the government and to protect the rights of the citizens. Created as a way to balance the powers of the legislature and the executive, and purposely kept out of reach and influence of the aforementioned, the judiciary enjoys the privilege to interfere and overrule the legislature and/or the executive. Vested with the powers of protecting the democratic institutions and championing the rights of the people of India, the judiciary has managed to create for itself an image as a “paragon of justice”, intervening even in matters of public policy to ensure the end of good governance is served.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in the last 18 months, this carefully built facade has been slowly but surely crumbling. It reveals the image of an institution not strong enough to weather the pressure and demands of the public, and an institution apathetic to the innumerable human rights violations that currently encumber the nation. In order to understand how the judiciary has failed to step up and take charge when it needed to, a recounting of its majorly catastrophic judgments and silence in these past few months is imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We begin by recounting the migrant crisis that underscored the disaster wreaked by the coronavirus pandemic. For months, our phones, televisions and newspapers were brimming with stories of resilient men and women travelling hundreds of kilometres to reach home or to seek medical care when the nation went into lockdown. Amidst those stories were also reports of workers and the underprivileged people of India dying on roads because of hunger and thirst, and being killed in accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the country was put under lockdown with barely a 24-hour warning in advance, ration shops, factories, and markets were closed down. The daily wage workers were forced to leave their premises and travel back to their hometown from the big cities when they could neither continue working nor be able to afford rent or food. No modes of transportation or provisions for basic necessities were forthcoming which left these migrant workers and daily wage workers stranded. In the first week of June, the Chief Labour Commissioner estimated that around 2,600,000 migrants were stranded across India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government of India’s failure to account for the millions of underprivileged people in India while formulating the policy of lockdown was not seized upon by the judiciary. At a time when the courts should have taken charge and forced the government to care for the safety and health of the underprivileged citizens, the judiciary’s silence was jarring. Its neglect of the most vulnerable people in the country highlights its egregious failure to uphold the promise of equality in the Indian Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrible human rights violation in the state of Kashmir following the abrogation of Article 370 is yet another failure of the Indian judicial system. 12,500,000 people had to live without access to the internet and were isolated from the rest of the nation under the most stringent military supervision while we heard snippets of the horrors many Kashmiris faced. It took almost a year for the apex Court of India, the Supreme Court to re-establish the privilege of mobile connections in Kashmir. Yet it does not absolve them of their silence and willingness to ignore the hundreds of petitions and Public Interest Litigations (PILs) against the government’s decision regarding Kashmir. The government did not even receive a slap on the wrist from the courts for their actions, underscoring the judiciary’s failure to uphold and protect the fundamental rights of the citizens of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This failure is only aggravated by the superficial response of the courts on the arrest of students, activists, lawyers and journalists by the government for protesting against the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2019. The right to protest and question the government is the key feature of a democracy, and the authorities blatantly violated that right by putting people in jail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varavara Rao, a 79-year-old poet, teacher, and activist, has been diagnosed with COVID-19, yet he suffers in jail for protesting against the government. Sudha Bharadwaj, Hany Babu, and Natasha Narwal are some of the innumerable students and teachers who have been arrested for dissenting. The judiciary’s fear of displeasing the current authorities and holding them accountable for their offence is blatantly emphasised by their inability to protect the democratic principles that uphold the structures of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neglect and lack of concern for extrajudicial killings is yet another characteristic of the Indian judicial system. While it certainly seems extremely heroic for police to take charge, and kill rapists and gang leaders, it undermines the role of a justice system. The glaring misuse of power by the police is a violation of fundamental rights and does not create the deterrence necessary to desist future perpetrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the judiciary fails to perform the duties it was conferred by the Constitution, they excel in performing a role that they should avidly be avoiding: moral policing. The judiciary has a history of passing moral judgments on rape survivors. In a recent rape case, the courts berated the girl for falling asleep after being raped, saying &lt;em&gt;“It is unbecoming of an Indian woman to fall asleep after being ravished”&lt;/em&gt; while in another case, the Court dismissed a sexual assault case by asking the girl to tie a &lt;em&gt;Rakhi&lt;/em&gt; (an amulet tied by sisters around the wrists of brothers, symbolically protecting them) to the person who assaulted her. The courts questioning the moral character of the rape survivors and instances of victim-blaming and shaming form a major chunk of court proceedings. This behaviour is unbecoming of an institution built to protect the dignity of the citizens of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The failure and decay of the judicial system in India is a precursor to receding public trust in justice, lack of accountability of the government, and misuse of power leading to a very dystopian-like future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is justice? What is right and what is wrong? The question of morality and justice has remained unanswered, making the duty of the judiciary difficult. However, we do not expect our courts to answer this question, neither do we expect perfection from our courts, we only expect competence and determination to not purposely violate our freedom and fundamental rights. The role of the judiciary is crucial for the efficient functioning of the country, but during times of rampant fascism led by the government and civil turmoil, it is the duty of the judiciary to keep the country from spiralling into chaos.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vidhi Arora</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Marquess Acton of Groppoli famously said, “Power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely”. In order to prevent absolute power from corrupting absolutely, the founding fathers of free India established the Indian judicial system.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Microsoft’s Satya Nadella: A Catalyst</title><link href="/Satya-Nadella" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microsoft’s Satya Nadella: A Catalyst" /><published>2020-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Satya-Nadella</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Satya-Nadella">&lt;p&gt;Hailing from the Southern part of India which has given birth to leaders of giant companies around the world, Satya Nadella has made Microsoft the largest company in the world, in terms of market capitalisation since he took over 6 years ago. His leadership style has been completely different from what the company had witnessed under its past leaders. From Steve Ballmer’s flashy and supposedly ‘epic’ speeches, Nadella brought a more calming effect to the table. This has certainly worked for the company. Instead of a sideward movement of the stock prices witnessed under Ballmer’s reign, the share prices have only been going up under Nadella’s leadership. Nadella, a proponent of the growth mindset philosophy, believes in the growth of individuals and the team as a whole. Instead of focussing too much on tradition, he convinced the employees that innovation is the only thing that is respected in their industry. Often under the guidance of Ballmer and Gates, Microsoft had begun living off of its past rather than focussing on providing world-class tech to its users. However, tradition is fleeting and the only constant is change in this ever-changing world. This philosophy has helped Nadella in bringing Microsoft where it is today. When Nadella was given charge of Microsoft’s Cloud services, Ballmer had warned Nadella that he would be fired if he doesn’t make it work, and yet again while taking charge as the CEO, he faced a similar do-or-die situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft, by many accounts, was in dire shape before Nadella took over in 2014. Windows 8 had debuted with poor reception, and it was struggling to navigate the smartphone revolution. Although the Surface tablet is a modest success, Microsoft’s smartphones have flopped despite the firm paying more than €5.4 billion ($6.2bn; £4.7bn) for Nokia’s handset business. Apple’s iPhone, and then Google’s Android left Microsoft in the dust. Additionally, ‘Zune’, the company’s iPod lookalike, was considered one of the worst product flops in tech history. There was no doubt that Microsoft had maintained a longstanding legacy in Silicon Valley, but many agreed that it needed a new strategy to compete against its more nimble counterparts like Apple Inc and Alphabet Inc. The major problem was that Microsoft was not dynamic. It had not been changing with time, and was not adapting to the changes that its competitors were creating in the business environment. Where Bill Gates had taken the wind of personal computing, Steve Ballmer failed to do the same with smartphones. However, Satya had no intention of committing the same mistake. He made a pronouncement on day one, &lt;em&gt;“The world is about cloud-first, mobile-first”&lt;/em&gt;, and made clear the direction in which the company would be going for the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Nadella’s leadership, Microsoft has embarked on a major transition towards becoming a cloud computing giant through its Azure platform. The cloud business, growing at a rate of 47%, continues to be the primary driver of the company’s success in recent years. The company’s current flagship business has a 20% market share in the cloud business. Azure is second only to Amazon’s AWS, with 31%. The coevolution of software and hardware will digitise most of the things that we do and experience in business, life and the world. It will be interesting to see who comes out on the top in the cloud competition in this world that is moving towards more sophisticated tech every day. Microsoft surely seems to be on the right path, being one step ahead of the change and not relying too much on its past successes. Nadella has completely shifted the company’s focus from its core business of Windows in the tenure of his leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has also forayed into the world of cloud gaming with Azure. Cloud gaming is like a subscription for games that you can play on any platform (mobile phone, laptop, gaming consoles, etc.). For Microsoft, getting the first-mover advantage would be key as Google too is planning to capture the market with ‘Stadia’. However, it should be easier for Microsoft to establish a strong foothold in this area as it already has experience with its gaming console business ‘Xbox’. The company has been using gamers’ data and constantly improving itself, to give the customers what they want, according to their preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella opposed the decision to purchase Nokia as he could not see why the world needed a third ecosystem in phones. He focussed on more sensible acquisitions, such as that of the job-search portal, LinkedIn. With this acquisition, Microsoft has become the leader in professional data. The Redmond giant plans to integrate the portal and make it available inside Outlook, Office, Skype, and Windows, thereby creating an ecosystem that is inescapable for the customer. Moreover, plans to integrate Cortana with LinkedIn have also been made. If something like this happens, Cortana would be able to assist the users in a much more complex manner by providing intel on customers’ business relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella has also incorporated lessons from his personal life into his leadership style. Talking about his son’s struggle with cerebral palsy in his book &lt;em&gt;Hit Refresh&lt;/em&gt;, he talks about how that experience instilled in him the feeling of empathy. He believes that it is important for people working in an innovation-centric company to be empathetic. In order to find a solution for a problem that your consumer is facing, you need to first be able to put yourself in his shoes and feel the need for innovation. He has repeatedly pressed on the importance of understanding what others are going through in order for a business to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadella’s managing style, say those who know him, is akin to cricket’s long-form (a sport of which the CEO is very fond of): slow, deliberative and patient. He makes no snap decisions. He focuses on a handful of the most important issues facing the company and takes a deep dive into each, encouraging serious input from others. Listening, probing, questioning. When he’s satisfied that he has enough information, he makes his decision — not a minute sooner. Nadella and his team know exactly what Microsoft is and what they want it to be: an innovative technology company that exists to help other businesses thrive. This vision is what has kept them growing, and will continue doing so in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Hailing from the Southern part of India which has given birth to leaders of giant companies around the world, Satya Nadella has made Microsoft the largest company in the world, in terms of market capitalisation since he took over 6 years ago. His leadership style has been completely different from what the company had witnessed under its past leaders. From Steve Ballmer’s flashy and supposedly ‘epic’ speeches, Nadella brought a more calming effect to the table. This has certainly worked for the company. Instead of a sideward movement of the stock prices witnessed under Ballmer’s reign, the share prices have only been going up under Nadella’s leadership. Nadella, a proponent of the growth mindset philosophy, believes in the growth of individuals and the team as a whole. Instead of focussing too much on tradition, he convinced the employees that innovation is the only thing that is respected in their industry. Often under the guidance of Ballmer and Gates, Microsoft had begun living off of its past rather than focussing on providing world-class tech to its users. However, tradition is fleeting and the only constant is change in this ever-changing world. This philosophy has helped Nadella in bringing Microsoft where it is today. When Nadella was given charge of Microsoft’s Cloud services, Ballmer had warned Nadella that he would be fired if he doesn’t make it work, and yet again while taking charge as the CEO, he faced a similar do-or-die situation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Importance of Human Connections, as Told by the Coronavirus</title><link href="/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Importance of Human Connections, as Told by the Coronavirus" /><published>2020-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections">&lt;p&gt;Every day, we step out of our homes with ambition in our eyes,  aspirations in our heart  and a desire to change the world as we want to see it (until someone ate a bat somewhere?). At the heart of this colossal myriad of &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; lies something that defines our whole existence – the ability to connect with another human being. Human connection is the exchange of positive energy between people.  The potential of feeling understood and united through human connection is one of the most rewarding elements in life. It has the power to deepen the moment and the bond between people, inspire change and build trust. It has proven to lower anxiety &amp;amp; depression, help us regulate our emotions better and lead to higher self-esteem and empathy, which is actually said to change our immune systems for the better. A research study by Harvard, conducted over a period of 80 years, proves that human connections and healthy relationships are the number one &amp;amp; two drivers of longevity, respectively. Though, our inherent need for a human connection doesn’t mean that every introvert must become a social butterfly. Instead, having a human connection can look different for everyone. Irrespective of what it is for each person, it serves a purpose which nothing else can – make someone feel genuinely happy, and at peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Humans have this dire need to connect. Our brains have learned from brutal evolutionary lessons that social isolation is a death sentence”&lt;/em&gt; said James Coan, a Professor of Psychology at the University of Virginia. The power of touch releases oxytocin, the feel-good hormone. Albeit temporarily, the coronavirus has stripped us all of this supposed elixir for the mind. We are a social species and hence it is not easy to NOT touch each other, as so much of our communication is defined by these touches. While technology seems to be connecting us more than ever, the blue-light emitting screens disconnect us from nature, from ourselves, and from other human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as people are struggling with an economic recession, they are struggling with an emotional recession too, due to loneliness. Loneliness is not just a feeling in one’s head; it is a biological instinct to seek out other human beings, just like hunger is a signal that sends a person to seek out food. In a situation where we have to stay at home, all by ourselves, such as the one caused by this pandemic, this feeling of loneliness might escalate for many, with limited ways of assuaging it. Even though in some parts of the world, nations have started to open up, the fear of catching the disease will remain in people’s minds, for a long time to come.  The isolation caused by this is proven by science to exact a physical toll on the brain’s circuitry. The confluence of multiple challenges during the pandemic – to health, education, jobs, access to resources has produced a bizarre assemblage of circumstances that increase the risk of depression and Post-traumatic Stress Disorder. In times of disaster, we seek respite in the fact that there is an ending to it which can be accurately predicted. But with this pandemic, we see no end in sight, which makes it more traumatic and compounds the negatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a situation where loneliness exacerbates the negative effects of the pandemic, how do we ensure that we connect in a way which is good for us and also reduces the risk of spreading the disease? In our current situation, the need to reduce physical distances, boost social or relational connections, and not see a rise in loneliness and related mental health problems poses a big problem for us. We need a connection culture, which is rich in relational connection while maintaining a physical distance between individuals. Technology has been a big boon for man since time immemorial, and it is this technology that comes to our rescue here. Be it a conventional video call with friends, a virtual cocktail party, gaming sites where people can compete virtually, watching movies and shows with your friends, or any other thing, we have seen a lot of new inventions throughout the course of this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how does the coronavirus revolutionise human connection and communication? For the past few decades, humans have focused increasingly on earning money and material belongings, which coupled with rapid technological growth led to the neglect of human relationships, at large. But now that we’re stuck in our homes, the best means of surviving psychologically is to interact with people by whatever means possible. But most importantly, we have begun to understand the value of a human connection, a panacea for all mental health issues, that has no other substitute, in its true essence. &lt;em&gt;‘We realise the true value of anything, only after it is taken away from us’&lt;/em&gt; – asserts a very common saying. Each and every one of us, throughout the course of this pandemic, have felt the importance of a human connection, and it is this realisation in our hearts, which will make us value real connections over materialistic things. And it is this realisation, that finally helps us understand what’s more important: material wealth or mental health?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Every day, we step out of our homes with ambition in our eyes, aspirations in our heart and a desire to change the world as we want to see it (until someone ate a bat somewhere?). At the heart of this colossal myriad of everything lies something that defines our whole existence – the ability to connect with another human being. Human connection is the exchange of positive energy between people. The potential of feeling understood and united through human connection is one of the most rewarding elements in life. It has the power to deepen the moment and the bond between people, inspire change and build trust. It has proven to lower anxiety &amp;amp; depression, help us regulate our emotions better and lead to higher self-esteem and empathy, which is actually said to change our immune systems for the better. A research study by Harvard, conducted over a period of 80 years, proves that human connections and healthy relationships are the number one &amp;amp; two drivers of longevity, respectively. Though, our inherent need for a human connection doesn’t mean that every introvert must become a social butterfly. Instead, having a human connection can look different for everyone. Irrespective of what it is for each person, it serves a purpose which nothing else can – make someone feel genuinely happy, and at peace.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Legislators in Crime</title><link href="/Legislators-in-Crime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Legislators in Crime" /><published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Legislators-in-Crime</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Legislators-in-Crime">&lt;p&gt;Taking a step into Indian politics is infinitely easier for a criminal than for an ordinary citizen. As paradoxical as this notion is, it has proven itself true each time an election has passed by. The Association for Democratic Reform (ADR) found that in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Indian Parliament, the percentage of legislators with a criminal record or awaiting trial has almost doubled in the past two decades. In the 2004 Lok Sabha, this number was 24%, while in 2019, it went up to 43%. What is more concerning is that a significant number of these legislators have been accused of serious crimes such as murder and rape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law of the land prohibits convicts from contesting elections, but not individuals with a charge sheet against them. This gap was intentional in order to prevent state machinery from being utilised for political vendetta, however, it has been grossly exploited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nexus between crime and politics has held strong for decades because of its perceived benefit to three important stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criminals are the first and the most direct beneficiaries. In fact, booth capture and suppression or mobilisation of voters in favour of political parties were one of the main sources of income for criminals between 1940’s and the 1970’s. Their support makes the legislators indebted to them and consequently, the law enforcement system is forced to be complicit in the process. Eventually, their role shifted from henchmen to legislators themselves. The presence of such an astonishingly large number of criminals in Parliament is an ode to the ailing criminal justice system as well. A criminal could complete two terms in office before they are brought to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, political parties have been gaining from their alliance with criminals since the birth of democracy in India. As Milan Vaishnav explains in his book &lt;em&gt;When Crime Pays: Money and Muscle in Indian Politics&lt;/em&gt;,  there were two factors in India’s political history that solidified this nexus. First, as regional parties were on the rise, political competition has increased the demand for criminals. This created a need and a market for criminals to generate security around electoral results for the parties. This often took place through threats and fear to secure votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, in 1969, Indira Gandhi put a ban on corporate funding for elections. This pushed a significant source of campaign finance underground. Parties preferred candidates who could secure large sums of cash and finance their campaigns. Criminals fit this bracket as many of them had managed to amass large quantities of wealth. Money plays a large role in this nexus, which is why there is great advocacy for a transparent electoral finance system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voters of India play a part in the preservation of this system as well. In fact, we see that a candidate with a criminal background is three times more likely to win a seat than a clean one. Struggling to access basic services such as law enforcement, healthcare, and welfare schemes, voters prefer candidates “who can get things done”, instead of one restrained by red tapism and morality. This nexus of crime and politics is actively supported by inefficient state services and poor access to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous N N Vohra Committee in 1993, set up to unearth crime and political nexus, had documented the rise of a criminal empire with the active support of top politicians and bureaucrats, eroding the rule of law and the legitimacy of democratic governance. In its report, the committee highlighted that many criminals were running a parallel government and blamed the existing criminal justice system for failing to effectively prosecute them. It suggested several measures to break the nexus. However, the “very explosive” report was never tabled in the Parliament and has since been kept as a top-secret by the Ministry of Home Affairs. All the Right to Informations (RTIs) filed have been skillfully evaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All major initiatives against the crime-politics nexus have been led by the judiciary and civil society. In the case of &lt;em&gt;Union of India v Association for Democratic Reforms and Another&lt;/em&gt;, the Supreme Court, in 2002, directed compulsory disclosure of the candidates’ financial, educational and criminal background while contesting elections. Expectedly, the court verdict was bitterly opposed by most political parties and the Union Government promulgated an ordinance, using its temporary law-making powers, to nullify the judgment. However, the court rose to the occasion by striking down the ordinance as unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court (SC) made another valiant attempt to curb criminalisation in December 2017. It asked for the setting up of special courts to fast-track the long-pending trials of elected members. In another judgment in 2018, the Supreme Court mandated the political parties and candidates to declare in print and electronic media in the locality about the antecedents of each candidate. However, these judgments did not yield any visible positive outcome as is evident from the rising number of criminal politicians in the Lok Sabha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2020, expressing concern over the growing intersection of crime and politics, the Supreme Court had ordered political parties to publish the details of their candidates with criminal charges on their websites and social media platforms, and in newspapers. The parties are required to also clearly outline the nature of the charges and explain why these candidates had been given tickets. This information was made public, and a compliance report was sent to the Election Commission (EC) within a specified period of time. The failure to do so was to be read as contempt. Upcoming Bihar elections in October 2020 will be the first election in which the Supreme Court’s decision will be implemented. The effects remain to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often said that the people of India need to undergo a ‘behavioural change’ in order to eradicate criminals from politics. As long as voters keep voting for criminals, there will be no solution. However, this requires a high level of trust in a better and rule-abiding alternative. It is the duty of the state and the political parties to instil this trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process can be started by creating a transparent electoral funding system. This can be done through state funding of elections as recommended by various committees such as the Dinesh Goswami Committee and the Indrajit Gupta Committee on electoral reforms. This is a step towards curbing the use of black money to a large extent and limiting criminalisation of politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another profusely opposed way forward is bringing political parties under the ambit of the Right to Information Act, 2005. Except for their political strategy, other matters relating to finance and administration should be made available to the public. The current system of electoral bonds does not promote transparency in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a need for increasing the powers of the Election Commission. The Election Commission can register a political party but cannot deregister it. As a neutral body, it is essential that the EC is allowed to regulate the affairs of a political party for a cleaner electoral process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of suggestions and reforms, what the Indian political system lacks is any sort of incentive to push these forward. The implementation of the February 2020 judgment guidelines will show whether seeing the true and bare face of the criminal-political nexus at an official level awakens the dormant morality of the Indian electorate or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ritisha Gupta</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Taking a step into Indian politics is infinitely easier for a criminal than for an ordinary citizen. As paradoxical as this notion is, it has proven itself true each time an election has passed by. The Association for Democratic Reform (ADR) found that in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Indian Parliament, the percentage of legislators with a criminal record or awaiting trial has almost doubled in the past two decades. In the 2004 Lok Sabha, this number was 24%, while in 2019, it went up to 43%. What is more concerning is that a significant number of these legislators have been accused of serious crimes such as murder and rape.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inauguration of the Ram Mandir: A Change to Indian Secularism for Eternity?</title><link href="/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inauguration of the Ram Mandir: A Change to Indian Secularism for Eternity?" /><published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir">&lt;p&gt;Man has known religion more than he has known himself. When Adam ate an apple which was forbidden for him to eat, it was the verses in religious books that told mankind that he wronged himself; but when an apple supposedly fell on Newton’s head, the world cheered for his triumph. As time progressed, religion slowly began to recede in its control and its influence. The Church lost its political power, and politics pushed religion out of its domain, slowly yet meticulously. The West gifted the world the idea of ‘secularism’ and envisioned a world where men would keep the cross and prayer mat at home; not to imply that secularism would be misjudged as apathy towards religion or would imply the absence of spirituality, but because politics and religion, if brewed together, would be a stain to the national fabric irrespective of place, time and ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert G Ingersoll, an American writer contemplated upon the reasons for this and stated, &lt;em&gt;“They knew that to put God in the constitution was to put man out. They knew that the recognition of a Deity would be seized upon by fanatics and zealots as a pretext for destroying the liberty of thought. They knew the terrible history of the church too well to place in her keeping or in the keeping of her God the sacred rights of man. They intended that all should have the right to worship or not to worship that our laws should make no distinction on account of creed.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of what exists in principles and theories, secular states have changed their means of functioning with politics and religion. This game in which one of the two tries to monopolise the other, keeps the equilibrium of secular powers ever shaken. The ‘secular’ state of Turkey had its President taking part in Hagia Sophia’s first prayer in 86 years, and the ‘secular’ state of India witnessed its Prime Minister inaugurate the construction of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt; on August 5, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as criticism over Indian PM Modi’s move to attend this ceremony starts to abound, one must realise that maybe the faultiness of the action is backed by an idea which itself is faulty and illusionary. For a political scientist like Christopher Jaffrelot, India’s secularism has always been screwed. Not because it wasn’t ‘western’ in its approach, but because its outlook and affinities with pluralism and multiculturalism were much more than it could handle. How can a newly born independent nation that rose fiercely at Gandhi’s idea of &lt;em&gt;Ram Rajya&lt;/em&gt; (The rule of Rama) forget its inclinations towards a ‘Hindu civilisation’ in a matter of a decade? How could a nation that was compelled to fight the colonial rulers instigated by the idea that India’s lands were always attacked by outsiders, colonisers, intruders, and Muslims be forgotten once India became independent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question remains: how does a nation that endured a national struggle with several secular symbols and undoubtedly persistent Hinduistic virtues, try and push itself away and remain ‘equidistant’ from all religious communities including Hinduism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PM Modi in his victory speech in 2019 had said that for the last 30 years, political parties in power had practised &lt;em&gt;nakli&lt;/em&gt; (fake) secularism, and true secularism was embedded in the idea of &lt;em&gt;sabka saath sabka vikas&lt;/em&gt;, which is translated by his party as “justice to all, appeasement to none”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rajeev Bhargava in his article ‘How to rescue genuine secularism?’ claimed, &lt;em&gt;“It is communal to believe or act in a way that presupposes that one can’t be a Hindu without being anti-Muslim, or vice-versa. Communalism is communitarianism gone sour. It is to see each other as enemies locked in a permanent war with one another.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this light, if one explores the idea of the Supreme Leader of a modern secular India inaugurating a temple and the allegations that such a deed negates the oath that he took as a Prime Minister, one must come to terms with the fact that the Indian PM is an outright Hindu. In 2019, when the PM made a visit to Kedarnath, his actions weren’t criticised because Kedarnath receives respect in the Hindu faith. The picture of him meditating in a cave was not being called ‘un-secular’ or ‘fallacious’ because the leader of the country is a follower of the Hindu faith and, hence, it would be mere hypocrisy to expect him to bow down his head in a mosque on a Friday afternoon or sing melodies in a Church on a bright Sunday morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does the problem exactly lie when it’s about inaugurating the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt;? The trouble lies in the fact that the inauguration, specifically of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt;, symbolises a celebration; a new beginning of a place of worship of Lord Ram, and also communicates the end of another place of worship - the Babri Masjid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amartya Sen, the Indian Nobel Laureate, when discussing the ideals of secularism claimed that &lt;em&gt;“The state must be equidistant from all religions – refusing to take sides and having a neutral attitude towards them, and the state must not have any relation at all with any religion”&lt;/em&gt;. In matters of these, the inauguration of the Mandir not only denies every atom of being secular, it moreover rejoices the construction as a predestined merriment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If August 5 marked the construction of the Mandir and the imprisonment of every violator that pulled the Masjid to dust, would the criticisms against the PM be the same? Or would that be an element within the orbit of secularism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when justice seems to exist nowhere and celebration remains at the peak?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answers remain unknown and unheard, and it boils down to one query; which is more flawed: is the ‘Indian ideal of secularism’ deeply flawed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Muslims haven’t forgotten the demolition of the Babri Masjid, maybe they haven’t forgotten the Godhra Riots, maybe wishing them ‘Eid Mubarak’ via a tweet from the PM feels like mere hypocrisy, maybe they cannot choose to forget the faces of young Muslim boys who were lynched, and maybe every wound remains so wide open that they haven’t moved an inch towards recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticisms that surround the inauguration of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt; by the PM, that are deemed as mere ‘insecurities’ of a minority community, maybe aren’t just insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sheer panic to witness and accept a blow to the nation’s secular fabric which in hindsight seems rather largely inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The systematic push for political power by the Hindu right-wing would not have advanced without the ground prepared by the Ayodhya movement. It has contributed to India’s foundational shift from a pluralist democracy to majoritarian rule,”&lt;/em&gt; said Zoya Hasan, a political scientist and professor emeritus at Jawaharlal Nehru University in New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The message is a clear one: here is a day which should be celebrated as the day BJP fulfilled two of its core promises. The fact that no opposition leaders have raised their voice against this event being held in the middle of a pandemic shows how powerful the BJP has become,”&lt;/em&gt; said Sanjay Kumar, Director of New Delhi based think-tank Center for the Study of Developing Societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Rajeev Khanna in his article in &lt;em&gt;The Citizen&lt;/em&gt; had said, &lt;em&gt;“This Babri Masjid = Ram Janmabhoomi campaign has had a devastating impact on people like myself, who have spent most of their lives under its shadow…. The poet Kaifi Azmi was not wrong to describe the Babri demolition as Ram’s ‘Doosra Banwas’ (second forest exile) in one of his iconic poems under the title. But those who have never subscribed to the plurality of Indian ethos are once again busy bombarding us with calls to celebrate Diwali this August 5th”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s secular mechanism is just like a vehicle with a failed break. And what happens to such a vehicle which is moving too fast, beyond bounds and red lights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It crashes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aniba Junaid</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">Man has known religion more than he has known himself. When Adam ate an apple which was forbidden for him to eat, it was the verses in religious books that told mankind that he wronged himself; but when an apple supposedly fell on Newton’s head, the world cheered for his triumph. As time progressed, religion slowly began to recede in its control and its influence. The Church lost its political power, and politics pushed religion out of its domain, slowly yet meticulously. The West gifted the world the idea of ‘secularism’ and envisioned a world where men would keep the cross and prayer mat at home; not to imply that secularism would be misjudged as apathy towards religion or would imply the absence of spirituality, but because politics and religion, if brewed together, would be a stain to the national fabric irrespective of place, time and ideology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">God’s Homophobia will Die and We will Kill It</title><link href="/God-s-Homophobia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="God's Homophobia will Die and We will Kill It" /><published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/God-s-Homophobia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/God-s-Homophobia">&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that most religions of the world are opposed to homosexuality. The Bible clearly states: &lt;em&gt;“If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.”&lt;/em&gt; (Leviticus 18:22). While the Quran does not have such an explicit declaration, traditional Islamic jurisprudence fully proscribes homosexual acts. Hindu jurisprudence has no equivalent bans on homosexual acts, and its law books do contain a recognition of a ‘third gender’, but most Hindus oppose it vigorously in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of these religions are monolithic and all contain various elements that are sympathetic towards homosexuality, whether among general followers or in their institutions. Despite all that, only a fool would say that the religions of the world fully accept homosexuals or their rights. This is epitomised in the most patronising argument religious people put forth, i.e. that while they accept LGBTQ persons like any other human being and believe homosexuality to be natural, their dogma commands that they continue to consider homosexual acts as immoral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: what can one do in such a situation? Can an LGBTQ person agree to disagree with the religious person and still continue to co-exist? Or is peace simply not an option? The religious person obviously insists that they are only proceeding from a vantage point of empathy, that they demand restraint from the gay person not out of prejudice but because all persons have to control their desires under a religious framework, not just homosexuals. So, there is no ground to allege homophobia on their part at all. But all of this is utter hogwash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that this new kind of argument is a clear attempt at dehumanising the homosexual, because it proscribes the very fruition of the gay person’s inner desires, it has more sinister implications: It leads to religious people favouring the maintenance of legal bans on homosexual acts because that is not seen as an impeachment of LGBTQ rights by itself. It also leads to a moral justification for continuing with the torturous practice of gay conversion therapy because that is verily seen as an expression of love which only seeks to prevent sin. And it is the brutality of these points as well as the very sinews of religious beliefs on homosexuality that makes such beliefs worthy of eradication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions, after all, view the very fact of homosexuality as wrong. To them, it is fundamentally unnatural and a deviation from the human normal which God(s) has thought fit to prohibit. The outward empathy they seek to exhibit for LGBTQ rights is informed not by an understanding of the fact that homosexuality is no deviation from the normal, but by their desire to be kind in a way no different to the kindness/forgiveness they may have for the rapist or the murderer. When one takes that into account, one can clearly see that religious people want the LGBTQ community to become dogs on a leash - restraining themselves from a fruition of their sexual desires and a more visible existence in public life - in exchange for little treats of kindness and little beatings of gay conversion therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the question of making peace with the religious person who denies the normalcy of homosexual relations or deems them sinful is moot. The religious person may seek to caustically self-victimise here by saying that their human rights as religious people cannot be restricted by the homosexual agenda. But the fact of the matter is that their argument would likely not find traction in any human rights court save the ones found in America with elected Republican judges. It is well-known in human rights jurisprudence that the right to practice one’s faith may be qualified. The requirement is that such a qualification be for a legitimate aim, that it be the necessary means to achieve such an aim and that it be the least-intrusive means available for achieving that aim. We clearly know that a criminalisation of the espousal of anti-homosexual beliefs is for a very legitimate aim: the securing of fuller rights to LGBTQ person. We also know that such a measure is necessary to achieve that aim. If there is no threat of criminal sanction on the espousal of anti-LGBTQ beliefs, then a threat to the right of LGBTQ persons to lead a dignified existence forever remains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only hurdle would be the question of intrusiveness. But given the nature of the mischief sought to be controlled here, criminalisation is not in the least excessive. The threat of criminal sanction that secures the rights of homosexuals is hardly intrusive upon religious rights: such a measure does not require the religious person to go out of his way to do anything, it merely requires them to forbear from preaching certain values. That may be intrusive due to the fact that proselytisation is an article of some faiths, but again, there’s no ban on proselytisation here - just a ban on bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions will make every attempt to try and hold on to their homophobia, going so far as to to suggest that their moral values are given by a creator and are immutable, regardless of the fact that science and nature condone homosexuality. They will say that their laws are not bendable and that science does not provide an objectively ethical guide to what is permissible among humans. So, a restriction on their right to believe is not objective or valid. But that’s not the point, society is not here to play religion’s game of “my group’s values are objective and right, your group’s values are subjective and wrong”. What society, at this present moment, is required to do is secure complete rights to human beings who have sexual and romantic relations with persons of the same gender. This is the reality of the here and now, and it is non-negotiable, morally or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about time that religion killed God’s homophobia, lest He face the proverbial sulphur of a modern society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anon.anon</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="society" /><summary type="html">It is no secret that most religions of the world are opposed to homosexuality. The Bible clearly states: “If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.” (Leviticus 18:22). While the Quran does not have such an explicit declaration, traditional Islamic jurisprudence fully proscribes homosexual acts. Hindu jurisprudence has no equivalent bans on homosexual acts, and its law books do contain a recognition of a ‘third gender’, but most Hindus oppose it vigorously in practice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vision 20/20</title><link href="/Vision-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vision 20/20" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/Vision-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Vision-2020">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Info Edge, it seems, has mastered the maths of running online classifieds in India. Industry observers attribute this success to the fact that customers don’t pay anything to use these platforms, except for Jeevansathi. From listings of jobs, real estate, and education, the company earns most of its revenue from businesses, advertisements, listing fees, and subscription products. This is in sharp contrast to the likes of OLX and Quikr, where a customer has the option to buy a paid listing, but the vast majority of users don’t pay to have their products listed; consequently, they have also burnt through millions of dollars to acquire new customers. However, Info Edge founders do not believe in this philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country’s largest employment website, Naukri, boasts about 67 million résumés and currently has 500,000 job listings on its platform. More than 60% of its revenue comes from the fees it charges from employers for access to its huge résumé database. 99acres, another successful venture of the Info Edge brand was founded in 2005 and is also a leader in its category. As of December 31, 2019, the site had total listings of 1,004,378 properties. It competes with Magicbricks, Commonfloor, and Housing. However, between 2013 and 2016, VC funding was abundantly available, triggering a mushrooming of players in the real estate sector. Backed by the likes of NewsCorp, SoftBank, and Tiger Global Management, startups such as Proptiger, Commonfloor, Housing, Quikr, OLX, Indiahomes, and Indiaproperty started giving 99Acres a tough fight. However, 99acres has held its ground. Jeevansathi is the third-largest matrimonial site in India, after Bharat Matrimony and Shaadi. Online spending on the business is likely to grow to ₹11-12 billion by 2023-24 from ₹7-8 billion in 2020-21. This is expected to give a huge boost to Info Edge’s matrimonial website. Shiksha, the portal providing information on careers, examinations, colleges, and courses is facing stiff competition as there are a lot many major players in the EdTech sector. With the likes of Byju’s, it has become tough for Shiksha to make a strong presence in the Indian EdTech sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bikhchandani had seen potential in classifieds websites when there were just around 14,000 internet accounts in the country and a few thousand users comparing that to the around 500 million users in India now, second only to China’s more than 800 million. It became the early mover in the internet economy, taking many essentials online as India’s population started discovering the joys of a virtually connected world. But as an early mover, Bikhchandani knows the downside of the treadmill. He is aware of the need to continuously make innovations in the fast-changing technological world. For that, Info Edge will leverage its advantage of two decades’ worth of data, using artificial intelligence, data analytics, and machine learning to drive informed change through improved user experiences and new products. Also, Info Edge will continue its 12-year-long practice of investing in ‘ideas’ with the ₹1 billion ‘Info Edge Venture Fund’, launched in January, to fund early-stage startups across categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the first fund by Info Edge, but the company has already invested ₹1.03 billion in 16 startups, including the likes of Zomato and PolicyBazaar. Overall the company has 21 active investments worth ₹1.108 billion at the end of 2020-21. In fact, one of its most successful bets has been restaurant aggregator and food delivery platform Zomato. Bikhchandani, a foodie, had been using Foodiebay (rebranded as Zomato only in 2010). A subsequent conversation with founder Deepinder Goyal set the tone for a business association, and Bikhchandani made an initial investment of ₹40.5 million. Its investment till date is ₹1.52 billion with about 22.7% stake. Zomato has already successfully acquired Uber’s food delivery business in India, Uber Eats. Moreover, PolicyBazaar is expected to receive investment from Google in its bid to expand its digital presence in India. Additionally, the insurance aggregator is also expected to raise $500 million from its Initial Public Offering (IPO) sometime next year. So the prospects of Info Edge cashing out big are right around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While making investments, Bikhchandani not only focuses on the business model but also takes into consideration the commitment, capability, and integrity of founders, and good governance. The importance of these qualities can be understood when fiascos like WeWork and Wirecard occur. Of course, some of the newer business models ask for cash burn to gain market share which is not how Bikhchandani runs his companies. He has always advised startups to get ‘customer money’ before ‘investor money’. Maybe some of the larger funds can learn from this strategy instead of blindly burning cash.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Amrit Chadha</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?</summary></entry></feed>