<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-13T23:48:29+01:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">The Pangean</title><subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What’s at the End of a Rainbow? A Gold Pot</title><link href="/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What's at the End of a Rainbow? A Gold Pot" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow">&lt;p&gt;The month of June is coloured with colours of solidarity, determination and struggles of the LGBTQ+ community. Pride month is and was, indeed, a month full of people taking &lt;em&gt;pride &lt;/em&gt;in who they are and pride parades are a sight to behold. However, this article is not a fairytale painting a happy picture of the month but rather explores its dark side, i.e. rainbow washing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would scroll through the LinkedIn profiles of a big, or as a matter-of-fact, any company during the month of June, it would not be hard to notice that most of them have rainbows slapped on their logos. Isn't it something to be happy about? After all, this is a sign of increasing acceptance of the LGBTQ+ community by society. If the previous two sentences outlined your thought process, then it reinforces the importance of awareness about rainbow washing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting with rainbow washing, it is important to understand another terminology associated with it that is 'pink money'. Pink money refers to the purchasing power of LGBTQ+ community. The 'pink' here is a reference to the pink triangle which was used as a badge in Nazi concentration camps to identify homosexuals. When the gay rights community became active it took it as a symbol to identify their movement and till date it serves as a strong symbol of their struggles. According to the sources, the LGBT population accounts for 5-10% of the total population. If it were a country, the community could claim to have the fourth-largest GDP in the world, estimated at $4.6 trillion. Now, a lot of corporations can and do go out of their way to monetise this 'pink money'. Here's where rainbow washing comes into the picture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rainbow washing refers to the practice of supporting LGBTQ issues in public to gather an audience while having private policies that are detrimental for them. To put it in simple words, corporations put rainbows on their logos, products and icons to tap the LGBTQ+ markets. Though when it comes to issues such as recruiting and helping them concretely, the companies back out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey found that about 50% of people belonging to this group believed being out at work would end up hurting their careers. During pride month, this year, Lego launched its special series titled 'Everybody is awesome' adorned in rainbow colours and priced it at $30, with it being a limited edition. Most other big brands such as Apple came up with products specifically targeted towards this segment intending to donate the proceeds generated through these sales towards organisations working for the betterment of the community. However, the past records tell a different story. A large part of this revenue is never actually spent on the betterment of the community.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rainbow washing may seem like a pretty marketing tactic or a petty issue but it has a lot of detrimental effects on the existence of pride. The commodification and monetisation of an event like pride end up demeaning the struggles and identity of the community celebrating it. As opposed to being a month of acceptance and love, pride turns into a month of closing business deals and getting traction for your product. A majority of people from the community said that rainbow washing made them feel uncomfortable about their identity. The fact that their coming out or acceptance is being reduced to a marketing tactic makes them feel used.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If business conglomerates actually want to support the cause and fight for the community, they should indeed open up employment opportunities or destigmatize the talk around LGBTQ+ issues. Most of them are just trying to tap into the 'pink money' while the people are left behind. Their economic condition is not robust and at a lot of places, they are not even allowed to enter a shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, looking at the flip side of rainbow washing, the symbolism has helped spread awareness about the issue in the marginalised or backward communities. The advertisements during pride month do provide a lot of opportunities to the people of the community. Although again, the phenomenon is not year-round. Hence, the opportunities end up being more like a company-influencer relationship rather than being a company-employee relationship. As soon as the pride month starts coming to an end, the support and charisma behind these rainbow coloured logos starts fading and so does the love and acceptance bestowed upon the community by the corporates. Life for them returns to normalcy with all its struggles and rocky roads, and the community for them seems long forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Shiksha Mody</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">The month of June is coloured with colours of solidarity, determination and struggles of the LGBTQ+ community. Pride month is and was, indeed, a month full of people taking pride in who they are and pride parades are a sight to behold. However, this article is not a fairytale painting a happy picture of the month but rather explores its dark side, i.e. rainbow washing. If you would scroll through the LinkedIn profiles of a big, or as a matter-of-fact, any company during the month of June, it would not be hard to notice that most of them have rainbows slapped on their logos. Isn't it something to be happy about? After all, this is a sign of increasing acceptance of the LGBTQ+ community by society. If the previous two sentences outlined your thought process, then it reinforces the importance of awareness about rainbow washing. Before starting with rainbow washing, it is important to understand another terminology associated with it that is 'pink money'. Pink money refers to the purchasing power of LGBTQ+ community. The 'pink' here is a reference to the pink triangle which was used as a badge in Nazi concentration camps to identify homosexuals. When the gay rights community became active it took it as a symbol to identify their movement and till date it serves as a strong symbol of their struggles. According to the sources, the LGBT population accounts for 5-10% of the total population. If it were a country, the community could claim to have the fourth-largest GDP in the world, estimated at $4.6 trillion. Now, a lot of corporations can and do go out of their way to monetise this 'pink money'. Here's where rainbow washing comes into the picture.&amp;nbsp; Rainbow washing refers to the practice of supporting LGBTQ issues in public to gather an audience while having private policies that are detrimental for them. To put it in simple words, corporations put rainbows on their logos, products and icons to tap the LGBTQ+ markets. Though when it comes to issues such as recruiting and helping them concretely, the companies back out. A survey found that about 50% of people belonging to this group believed being out at work would end up hurting their careers. During pride month, this year, Lego launched its special series titled 'Everybody is awesome' adorned in rainbow colours and priced it at $30, with it being a limited edition. Most other big brands such as Apple came up with products specifically targeted towards this segment intending to donate the proceeds generated through these sales towards organisations working for the betterment of the community. However, the past records tell a different story. A large part of this revenue is never actually spent on the betterment of the community.&amp;nbsp; Rainbow washing may seem like a pretty marketing tactic or a petty issue but it has a lot of detrimental effects on the existence of pride. The commodification and monetisation of an event like pride end up demeaning the struggles and identity of the community celebrating it. As opposed to being a month of acceptance and love, pride turns into a month of closing business deals and getting traction for your product. A majority of people from the community said that rainbow washing made them feel uncomfortable about their identity. The fact that their coming out or acceptance is being reduced to a marketing tactic makes them feel used.&amp;nbsp; If business conglomerates actually want to support the cause and fight for the community, they should indeed open up employment opportunities or destigmatize the talk around LGBTQ+ issues. Most of them are just trying to tap into the 'pink money' while the people are left behind. Their economic condition is not robust and at a lot of places, they are not even allowed to enter a shop. However, looking at the flip side of rainbow washing, the symbolism has helped spread awareness about the issue in the marginalised or backward communities. The advertisements during pride month do provide a lot of opportunities to the people of the community. Although again, the phenomenon is not year-round. Hence, the opportunities end up being more like a company-influencer relationship rather than being a company-employee relationship. As soon as the pride month starts coming to an end, the support and charisma behind these rainbow coloured logos starts fading and so does the love and acceptance bestowed upon the community by the corporates. Life for them returns to normalcy with all its struggles and rocky roads, and the community for them seems long forgotten.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolutionary Force of K-Pop</title><link href="/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolutionary Force of K-Pop" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop">&lt;p&gt;This year, K-pop accelerated its expansion into all sorts of mediums — &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5892708/jessica-jung-shine-interview/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;novels&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/international/9342105/k-pop-podcasts-coronavirus-quarantine/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;podcasts&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/movies/9446222/netflix-blackpink-documentary&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;documentaries&lt;/a&gt;. And yet, for all the satisfaction these new forms brought with them, the music remained the heart of this global phenomenon. Despite the pandemic’s impact on the worldwide recording industry, releases from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/entertainer-of-the-year-2020-bts/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;South Korea&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;saw no decline in quantity or quality, and a slew of artists produced their best work to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The K-pop songs and albums that defined the year transported us to places we miss most—from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5912807/best-broadway-shows-to-stream/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the theat&lt;/a&gt;re&amp;nbsp;to the jazz bar to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5870462/rick-steves-coronavirus-quarantine/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;island vacation&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;that lives only in our memories or imaginations. Some prompted nostalgia for things we&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5902420/hugging-coronavirus-amy-ephron/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;once took for granted&lt;/a&gt;, while others inspired hope for their return. Through these releases, many of our favorite artists experimented with their sounds, all while building deeper connections with an&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5912998/bts-army/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;audience&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;they could only interact with from a distance. A talented rookie class experimented with retro sounds, while K-pop's most successful women brazenly defied expectations. Disco completely took over, and noise music prevailed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also a year for career breakthroughs and major milestones, as the world's biggest superstars&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.papermag.com/tag/bts&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BTS&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;continued to shatter records left and right and break new ground for Korean artists. They're going into the new year with three number-one singles on the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;Hot 100, a whole quarantine album, and a Grammy nomination. And while the world got smaller, K-pop went bigger and bolder — sonically and aesthetically.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the global coronavirus pandemic put an end to live touring, the K-pop industry brought the spectacle to our screens with&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teenvogue.com/story/k-pop-future-of-live-music-immersive-online-concerts&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;immersive live concert&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;experiences. The music never stopped, not even for a second&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you're a casual listener, a stan, or someone who's just genuinely curious to see what K-pop is all about,&amp;nbsp;here are 10 songs from the heat of KPOP that made the hard 2020 much easier and eventually took the world by storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1)&lt;strong&gt; BTS, 'Black Swan' (&lt;em&gt;Map of the Soul: 7&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTS has connected with a worldwide fanbase in large part thanks to the universal-but-still-personal themes of their music, and 'Black Swan' represents one of their most intimate confessions. Dreamy, gloomy hip-hop soundscapes lay the backdrop for the chart-toppers to open up about their darkest fears: that they may one day fall out of love with music. Using the title as a metaphor – to represent both the one-of-a-kind phenomenon they are and the 2010 movie where a ballerina makes the ultimate sacrifice for her art – the superstar septet investigates their underlying anxieties whilst declaring that they won’t let fear win over passion in the end. It’s a full-fledged motion picture-packed into just over three minutes to tell a rare, real-life story of one of the world’s biggest stars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2)&lt;strong&gt; TXT, 'Can’t You See Me' (&lt;em&gt;The Dream Chapter: ETERNITY&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 'Can’t You See Me' TXT pulls the dark undercurrent of their youthful whimsy out from under the bed. Crunchy electric guitars and a jaunty whistle add a refreshing contrast to the track’s trap underpinnings, but where it best exposes its murkiness is through the quintet's vocal performances. Alternating between distorted tremolo vocals, hushed whisper-raps, and delicate verses wisping like curls of smoke, the members’ voices lurch between dulcet and disorienting as they reveal the cracks in a friendship. Through unsettling sounds and an idyllic music video that devolves into something frightening, TXT lay bare a horror rarely spoken of: watching a friendship fade before your eyes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3)&lt;strong&gt; &amp;nbsp;Twice, “I CAN’T STOP ME” (&lt;em&gt;Eyes Wide Open)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Dua Lipa and Lady Gaga, Twice were hip to electro basslines this year in “I CAN’T STOP ME.” The girl group bask in the elastic, strobing synth that pulses under the glamorous nu-disco track, and it snaps into formation with the chorus. The song calls for a grand celebration, but they’re too distracted trying not to indulge in their own treacherous desires: “I just can’t go back anymore/ Out of control,” Chaeyoung sings before the rest of the group fully surrender to temptation. Twice fight to keep cool, though it’s hard to notice when they nail such a spotless performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) WOODZ, “BUMP BUMP” (&lt;em&gt;WOOPS!&lt;/em&gt;)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great year for soloists in K-pop, and no one was more honest with themselves than WOODZ. The push-and-pull of any romance is often the most enticing yet stressful aspect of it all. Amidst airy promises from his lover is the dreary prospect of being left alone, but he approaches this mixed-messaging with a refreshing candour. In our own whirlpools of flirting and call backs, IG-reels and missed messages, “BUMP BUMP” was comfortingly straightforward – with WOODZ relaying what he wants, exactly how he wants it. It was the wrong year to be young and in love in 2020, but at least we had WOODZ to keep us company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Weki Meki, “COOL” (&lt;em&gt;NEW RULES&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weki Meki revamp their approach in 'Cool' by swapping their preppy dance-pop for steely electro. The group’s demeanor is as spartan as the icy beat, and they amplify their bratty voices to assert their flawlessness. Their cockiness peaks in the chorus, which doubles as a taunt and a mantra: &quot;Be hotter/ Beyond the control,” they sing like a drill instructor. “Get out of all the boring rules.” If “Cool” sounds standoffish, then the song succeeds at what it sets out to do. Weki Meki don’t aspire to be a role model for attainable, girl-crush cool but instead point out the gap between you and them. “Cool” is a conceited celebration of self, though sometimes it just feels satisfying to flaunt what you got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6). GFRIEND, 'MAGO' (&lt;em&gt;回:Walpurgis Night&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'MAGO' distils disco to its very best qualities, shimmering – quite literally – with synths and steady beats, building a heady, atmospheric high. As cohesive as it is musically, its magic lies in how perfectly it fits into the ethos of&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;回:Walpurgis Night.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;The album&amp;nbsp;is built on the idea of modern witches, at the centre of which are women who exercise the same agency and power of the song’s namesake, and GFRIEND has fun while doing it. Interspersed with images of the girls dancing the night away – not what you’d expect from a concept dealing with the occult – are lyrics that brim with confidence and ambition. Instead of believing in fairy tales and waiting for a Prince Charming, their only love is the images of themselves smiling in the mirror. It’s a cheeky way to poke fun at how society perceives self-assured women since the title itself translates to 'wizard.' In celebrating their limitless ambition, 'MAGO' casts a spell that keeps you coming back for more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7) SEVENTEEN, 'Left &amp;amp; Right' (&lt;em&gt;Heng:garæ&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' is so exuberant that every sound – from doorbell chimes to 808 cowbells, organ synth riffs to full-bodied brass&amp;nbsp; –&amp;nbsp; bursts forth like aural confetti. One could readily claim SEVENTEEN have made their own 'Cupid Shuffle' but they’re aiming for something beyond mere dance instructional: this is a song for transforming every moment into a cause for celebration. In a time when in-person parties aren’t possible, 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' converts bedrooms into dancefloors. And with exultant shouts and energized rapping, they tell you to keep your chin up, to run down red carpets, to&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;dance&lt;/em&gt;. SEVENTEEN act as leaders and hype men here, but the role they fill best is that of life coaches: despite their talk of races and finish lines, they exclaim that “not running is an answer too / who cares what we do.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They grant permission to simply be: a reminder that surviving every day is enough right now. And after all, if you’re not moving forward, why not move &quot;LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT,”&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;? They understand something that should be taught in schools around the world: busting your ass should be supplemented with time spent shaking it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8) Apink, 'Dumhdurum' (&lt;em&gt;LOOK&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K-pop tends to be a young person's game – both the industry and its labels regularly shift their priorities to younger artists – but Apink’s 'Dumhdurum' makes an exceptional case for the continuing effort and investment in senior acts. The track opens with a swirling synth-pop hook strong enough to stand as a chorus on its own, before diving into verses and choruses that strike pop gold with just the right amount of catchy repetition and melancholy longing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apink detail the complexity of remaining calm in the presence of a past love, even when one’s heart's still beating&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;dumhdurum&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;for them – a concept that could be difficult for younger groups to believably pull off. This mature message successfully connected with a large audience, and 'Dumhdurum' became a knockout success in both Korea (topping all local music charts) and the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;charts (tying for their longest-running hit on&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/charts/world-digital-song-sales&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Digital Song Sales&lt;/a&gt;).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nine years into their career, Apink are still more than equipped to bring their A-Game, and that deserves larger recognition all in itself for the industry to pay equal attention to both its senior and developing artists. Matured musical magic awaits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9). EVERGLOW, 'LA DI DA' (&lt;em&gt;-77.82x-78.29&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a virtual flattening of borders, musical trends in the States now get reflected in&amp;nbsp;K-pop in real-time. Throughout 2020 – in both the U.S. and South Korea – throwback sounds were ubiquitous. This year’s K-pop magnum opus, EVERGLOW’s 'LA DI DA' mirrored the US’ pop magnum opus, The Weeknd’s 'Blinding Lights' only months after its release. But where The Weeknd’s work is chilling and sinister in its search for love, EVERGLOW’s is a spry kiss-off to all the haters, the bad guys, and the players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A successful pastiche of the 80's that’s crafted by producer Ollipop, 'LA DI DA' blends myriad influences: the&amp;nbsp;layered cheerleader chants of Toni Basil's '&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0aqLwHP4y6Q&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mickey&lt;/a&gt;' the spunky girl power of Cyndi Lauper and the Go-Go's, the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HnYWmgSZdlM&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;na-na-nas&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;of Bananarama, and above all, the shimmering synth-pop sound that permeated the top half of that decade. 'LA DI DA' melds these all together, with K-pop twists: a killing part punctuated by handclaps, a tempo-shifting rap section carried by leader E:U, and an earworm of a melody evocative of early 2010's K-pop – a time when choruses were packed with hooky vocal melodies instead of hollow drops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10) 'Lovesick Girls', BLACKPINK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrival of BLACKPINK’s first&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5896487/blackpink-the-album/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;full-length album&lt;/a&gt; — so highly anticipated at the project was simply titled&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;The Album&lt;/em&gt;—was one of K-pop’s biggest news events in 2020. While the pre-release singles&amp;nbsp;'&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5859277/blackpink-how-you-like-that/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How You Like That&lt;/a&gt;'&amp;nbsp;and 'Ice Cream' with Selena Gomez charted higher on the &lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt; Hot 100, 'Lovesick Girls' is the true gem on the album. The heavy electronic production characteristic of BLACKPINK’s crowd-riling bops remains intact, but it’s stripped back to accentuate sung melodies from the four members. Their voices are layered over an acoustic guitar to create a breezy and mellow ambience, taking a more pensive and melancholic turn from the hard-hitting nature of the group’s 2018 and 2019 title track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 2020 has been far from a banner year for K-pop, with the coronavirus pandemic impacting the industry through disbandments, cancelled tours, and shelved comebacks, there have been enough pleasant surprises to keep fans plugged in. BTS’ success these days can make it hard to recall that they were once considered the underdogs of the K-pop industry. The seven-piece group didn’t come from a big management firm, and at the time of their debut, they stood out for not sounding (or looking) overly packaged or produced. Instead, BTS was built by their fans — the 'Army' — who rallied behind the group. This month, the Army’s influence has extended beyond music and into social justice, when the loyal fanbase helped to match the group’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/bts-black-lives-matter-donation-1011198/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$1 million donation to Black Lives Matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That followed a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/white-lives-matter-k-pop-1009581/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;coordinated campaign&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;by K-pop fans just days earlier, when fans came together to drown out the racist #WhiteLivesMatter hashtag on Twitter by spamming it with irreverent memes and fan cams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who still thought K-pop was a passing fad or a niche subset best left to the 'world music' fringes, the recent rallying of the fandoms (not to mention a host of spirited new releases) has underlined the fact that K-pop is more than just another overseas import — it’s officially a global force.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tejasvi Joshi</name></author><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">This year, K-pop accelerated its expansion into all sorts of mediums — novels,&amp;nbsp;podcasts,&amp;nbsp;documentaries. And yet, for all the satisfaction these new forms brought with them, the music remained the heart of this global phenomenon. Despite the pandemic’s impact on the worldwide recording industry, releases from&amp;nbsp;South Korea&amp;nbsp;saw no decline in quantity or quality, and a slew of artists produced their best work to date. The K-pop songs and albums that defined the year transported us to places we miss most—from&amp;nbsp;the theatre&amp;nbsp;to the jazz bar to the&amp;nbsp;island vacation&amp;nbsp;that lives only in our memories or imaginations. Some prompted nostalgia for things we&amp;nbsp;once took for granted, while others inspired hope for their return. Through these releases, many of our favorite artists experimented with their sounds, all while building deeper connections with an&amp;nbsp;audience&amp;nbsp;they could only interact with from a distance. A talented rookie class experimented with retro sounds, while K-pop's most successful women brazenly defied expectations. Disco completely took over, and noise music prevailed.&amp;nbsp; It was also a year for career breakthroughs and major milestones, as the world's biggest superstars&amp;nbsp;BTS&amp;nbsp;continued to shatter records left and right and break new ground for Korean artists. They're going into the new year with three number-one singles on the&amp;nbsp;Billboard&amp;nbsp;Hot 100, a whole quarantine album, and a Grammy nomination. And while the world got smaller, K-pop went bigger and bolder — sonically and aesthetically.&amp;nbsp; When the global coronavirus pandemic put an end to live touring, the K-pop industry brought the spectacle to our screens with&amp;nbsp;immersive live concert&amp;nbsp;experiences. The music never stopped, not even for a second&amp;nbsp; Whether you're a casual listener, a stan, or someone who's just genuinely curious to see what K-pop is all about,&amp;nbsp;here are 10 songs from the heat of KPOP that made the hard 2020 much easier and eventually took the world by storm. 1) BTS, 'Black Swan' (Map of the Soul: 7) BTS has connected with a worldwide fanbase in large part thanks to the universal-but-still-personal themes of their music, and 'Black Swan' represents one of their most intimate confessions. Dreamy, gloomy hip-hop soundscapes lay the backdrop for the chart-toppers to open up about their darkest fears: that they may one day fall out of love with music. Using the title as a metaphor – to represent both the one-of-a-kind phenomenon they are and the 2010 movie where a ballerina makes the ultimate sacrifice for her art – the superstar septet investigates their underlying anxieties whilst declaring that they won’t let fear win over passion in the end. It’s a full-fledged motion picture-packed into just over three minutes to tell a rare, real-life story of one of the world’s biggest stars 2) TXT, 'Can’t You See Me' (The Dream Chapter: ETERNITY) On 'Can’t You See Me' TXT pulls the dark undercurrent of their youthful whimsy out from under the bed. Crunchy electric guitars and a jaunty whistle add a refreshing contrast to the track’s trap underpinnings, but where it best exposes its murkiness is through the quintet's vocal performances. Alternating between distorted tremolo vocals, hushed whisper-raps, and delicate verses wisping like curls of smoke, the members’ voices lurch between dulcet and disorienting as they reveal the cracks in a friendship. Through unsettling sounds and an idyllic music video that devolves into something frightening, TXT lay bare a horror rarely spoken of: watching a friendship fade before your eyes 3) &amp;nbsp;Twice, “I CAN’T STOP ME” (Eyes Wide Open) Like Dua Lipa and Lady Gaga, Twice were hip to electro basslines this year in “I CAN’T STOP ME.” The girl group bask in the elastic, strobing synth that pulses under the glamorous nu-disco track, and it snaps into formation with the chorus. The song calls for a grand celebration, but they’re too distracted trying not to indulge in their own treacherous desires: “I just can’t go back anymore/ Out of control,” Chaeyoung sings before the rest of the group fully surrender to temptation. Twice fight to keep cool, though it’s hard to notice when they nail such a spotless performance. 4) WOODZ, “BUMP BUMP” (WOOPS!)&amp;nbsp; This was a great year for soloists in K-pop, and no one was more honest with themselves than WOODZ. The push-and-pull of any romance is often the most enticing yet stressful aspect of it all. Amidst airy promises from his lover is the dreary prospect of being left alone, but he approaches this mixed-messaging with a refreshing candour. In our own whirlpools of flirting and call backs, IG-reels and missed messages, “BUMP BUMP” was comfortingly straightforward – with WOODZ relaying what he wants, exactly how he wants it. It was the wrong year to be young and in love in 2020, but at least we had WOODZ to keep us company. 5) Weki Meki, “COOL” (NEW RULES) Weki Meki revamp their approach in 'Cool' by swapping their preppy dance-pop for steely electro. The group’s demeanor is as spartan as the icy beat, and they amplify their bratty voices to assert their flawlessness. Their cockiness peaks in the chorus, which doubles as a taunt and a mantra: &quot;Be hotter/ Beyond the control,” they sing like a drill instructor. “Get out of all the boring rules.” If “Cool” sounds standoffish, then the song succeeds at what it sets out to do. Weki Meki don’t aspire to be a role model for attainable, girl-crush cool but instead point out the gap between you and them. “Cool” is a conceited celebration of self, though sometimes it just feels satisfying to flaunt what you got. 6). GFRIEND, 'MAGO' (回:Walpurgis Night) 'MAGO' distils disco to its very best qualities, shimmering – quite literally – with synths and steady beats, building a heady, atmospheric high. As cohesive as it is musically, its magic lies in how perfectly it fits into the ethos of&amp;nbsp;回:Walpurgis Night.&amp;nbsp;The album&amp;nbsp;is built on the idea of modern witches, at the centre of which are women who exercise the same agency and power of the song’s namesake, and GFRIEND has fun while doing it. Interspersed with images of the girls dancing the night away – not what you’d expect from a concept dealing with the occult – are lyrics that brim with confidence and ambition. Instead of believing in fairy tales and waiting for a Prince Charming, their only love is the images of themselves smiling in the mirror. It’s a cheeky way to poke fun at how society perceives self-assured women since the title itself translates to 'wizard.' In celebrating their limitless ambition, 'MAGO' casts a spell that keeps you coming back for more. 7) SEVENTEEN, 'Left &amp;amp; Right' (Heng:garæ) 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' is so exuberant that every sound – from doorbell chimes to 808 cowbells, organ synth riffs to full-bodied brass&amp;nbsp; –&amp;nbsp; bursts forth like aural confetti. One could readily claim SEVENTEEN have made their own 'Cupid Shuffle' but they’re aiming for something beyond mere dance instructional: this is a song for transforming every moment into a cause for celebration. In a time when in-person parties aren’t possible, 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' converts bedrooms into dancefloors. And with exultant shouts and energized rapping, they tell you to keep your chin up, to run down red carpets, to&amp;nbsp;dance. SEVENTEEN act as leaders and hype men here, but the role they fill best is that of life coaches: despite their talk of races and finish lines, they exclaim that “not running is an answer too / who cares what we do.”&amp;nbsp; They grant permission to simply be: a reminder that surviving every day is enough right now. And after all, if you’re not moving forward, why not move &quot;LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT,”&amp;nbsp;right? They understand something that should be taught in schools around the world: busting your ass should be supplemented with time spent shaking it.&amp;nbsp; 8) Apink, 'Dumhdurum' (LOOK) K-pop tends to be a young person's game – both the industry and its labels regularly shift their priorities to younger artists – but Apink’s 'Dumhdurum' makes an exceptional case for the continuing effort and investment in senior acts. The track opens with a swirling synth-pop hook strong enough to stand as a chorus on its own, before diving into verses and choruses that strike pop gold with just the right amount of catchy repetition and melancholy longing. Apink detail the complexity of remaining calm in the presence of a past love, even when one’s heart's still beating&amp;nbsp;dumhdurum&amp;nbsp;for them – a concept that could be difficult for younger groups to believably pull off. This mature message successfully connected with a large audience, and 'Dumhdurum' became a knockout success in both Korea (topping all local music charts) and the&amp;nbsp;Billboard&amp;nbsp;charts (tying for their longest-running hit on&amp;nbsp;World Digital Song Sales).&amp;nbsp; Nine years into their career, Apink are still more than equipped to bring their A-Game, and that deserves larger recognition all in itself for the industry to pay equal attention to both its senior and developing artists. Matured musical magic awaits. 9). EVERGLOW, 'LA DI DA' (-77.82x-78.29) Thanks to a virtual flattening of borders, musical trends in the States now get reflected in&amp;nbsp;K-pop in real-time. Throughout 2020 – in both the U.S. and South Korea – throwback sounds were ubiquitous. This year’s K-pop magnum opus, EVERGLOW’s 'LA DI DA' mirrored the US’ pop magnum opus, The Weeknd’s 'Blinding Lights' only months after its release. But where The Weeknd’s work is chilling and sinister in its search for love, EVERGLOW’s is a spry kiss-off to all the haters, the bad guys, and the players. A successful pastiche of the 80's that’s crafted by producer Ollipop, 'LA DI DA' blends myriad influences: the&amp;nbsp;layered cheerleader chants of Toni Basil's 'Mickey' the spunky girl power of Cyndi Lauper and the Go-Go's, the&amp;nbsp;na-na-nas&amp;nbsp;of Bananarama, and above all, the shimmering synth-pop sound that permeated the top half of that decade. 'LA DI DA' melds these all together, with K-pop twists: a killing part punctuated by handclaps, a tempo-shifting rap section carried by leader E:U, and an earworm of a melody evocative of early 2010's K-pop – a time when choruses were packed with hooky vocal melodies instead of hollow drops. 10) 'Lovesick Girls', BLACKPINK The arrival of BLACKPINK’s first&amp;nbsp;full-length album — so highly anticipated at the project was simply titled&amp;nbsp;The Album—was one of K-pop’s biggest news events in 2020. While the pre-release singles&amp;nbsp;'How You Like That'&amp;nbsp;and 'Ice Cream' with Selena Gomez charted higher on the Billboard Hot 100, 'Lovesick Girls' is the true gem on the album. The heavy electronic production characteristic of BLACKPINK’s crowd-riling bops remains intact, but it’s stripped back to accentuate sung melodies from the four members. Their voices are layered over an acoustic guitar to create a breezy and mellow ambience, taking a more pensive and melancholic turn from the hard-hitting nature of the group’s 2018 and 2019 title track. While 2020 has been far from a banner year for K-pop, with the coronavirus pandemic impacting the industry through disbandments, cancelled tours, and shelved comebacks, there have been enough pleasant surprises to keep fans plugged in. BTS’ success these days can make it hard to recall that they were once considered the underdogs of the K-pop industry. The seven-piece group didn’t come from a big management firm, and at the time of their debut, they stood out for not sounding (or looking) overly packaged or produced. Instead, BTS was built by their fans — the 'Army' — who rallied behind the group. This month, the Army’s influence has extended beyond music and into social justice, when the loyal fanbase helped to match the group’s&amp;nbsp;$1 million donation to Black Lives Matter. That followed a&amp;nbsp;coordinated campaign&amp;nbsp;by K-pop fans just days earlier, when fans came together to drown out the racist #WhiteLivesMatter hashtag on Twitter by spamming it with irreverent memes and fan cams. For anyone who still thought K-pop was a passing fad or a niche subset best left to the 'world music' fringes, the recent rallying of the fandoms (not to mention a host of spirited new releases) has underlined the fact that K-pop is more than just another overseas import — it’s officially a global force.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Not Tying the Knot in Korea</title><link href="/Not-Tying-the-Knot-in-Korea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not Tying the Knot in Korea" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Not-Tying-the-Knot-in-Korea</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Not-Tying-the-Knot-in-Korea">&lt;p&gt;Korea's value for marriage can be recognised from the popular saying: &quot;&lt;em&gt;A person becomes an adult only after marriage&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; which is broadly used in the country. This reveals that the culture often sees being married as the equivalent of being an adult. Moreover, there is the obvious influence of Confucianism in South Korea which considers marriage to be essential for maintaining bloodlines.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Sampo&amp;nbsp;Generation (&amp;nbsp;삼포세대 ) however, disagrees.&amp;nbsp;Sampo&amp;nbsp;Generation, which literally translates to 'giving up on three, generation' is the younger generation of the country who are giving up on dating, marriage and having children. If we look at the statistics over the last three decades (1981-2011), the average age of marriage for South Korean women has increased by six years (23.0 to 29.1), a year more than it has for men (26.4 to 31.9). Furthermore, there has also been a drastic increase in single households (9% in 1990 to 26% in 2013). What are the factors that have led to such an increase?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Korea, as a society,&amp;nbsp;stereotypically&amp;nbsp;preferred sons to daughters. While daughters were prepared for their future roles as mothers and wives, education for women was not thought to be as important as it was for men. However, there were also social groups like the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Gisaeng&lt;/em&gt;s.&amp;nbsp;The &lt;em&gt;Gisaeng&lt;/em&gt;s first appeared in the&amp;nbsp;Goryeo&amp;nbsp;Dynasty (918-1392) and were often historically misrepresented to be only entertainers for the rich and upper class, but, in actuality, they were intelligent and extraordinarily skilled women, who can be compared to today's professionally-trained and educated women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women, after first democratic Korea was established, got increased opportunities to pursue education and engage in other economic activities. Now women are successful in every field: from business to law, and from science to architecture. But successful careers could also entail increased working hours. According to a report by OECD, on average, a South Korean person works about 38.9 hours a week, ranking the nation third among 37 countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increased working hours lead to disinterest in dating or the inability to maintain existing relationships. A successful position in any industry for a woman comes with the fear of having to abandon it after her marriage. Marriage would mean the addition of another family (her in-laws) and the pressure of having a baby. Even if a working female decides to have a baby after her marriage, she would have to be away from her job for a while, which in turn would be a threat to the position she holds at her workplace. The work culture is very competitive in Korea and you can easily find replacements for any position. For a man to replace a woman is even easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marriage is not a union between two individuals but two families. This is even more appropriate for East Asian cultures, where, from marriage to childbearing, everything is linked. For a society bearing such thinking, it is only natural for a girl's parents to find an ideal groom for their daughter. An ideal son-in-law would be someone who can provide their daughter emotional and financial support.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many women in Korea would not marry the man of their choice if their parents do not approve of him. Even if she decides to marry the guy her parents have chosen for her, she would still have to rely on her parents' financial help as marriages in Korea are very expensive. According to&amp;nbsp;Statista, in 2018 an average Korean wedding cost around 230 million Korean Won which includes&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Yedam&lt;/em&gt;, the gifts given to the groom's family. In a country where marriage comes with such a cost, it is only natural that a 21st-century South Korean woman finds having enough money in her bank account to own an apartment in&amp;nbsp;Gangnam&amp;nbsp;to be more attractive than getting married, even if it means that she has to work a few extra hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, with the growing popularity of Korean dramas which portray getting married to an older woman to be desirable, it is seen that the female population, when it does tie the knot, is also inclining towards getting married to men who are younger by five years and sometimes even ten years. This has led to increased growth in the number of remarriages, even though Korea's culture does not&amp;nbsp;favour&amp;nbsp;remarriage. In fact, given the increasing popularity of marriages with older women, changing trends can be seen with the subtle possibility of a matriarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all of this comes with a cost. Fertility in Korea has become not only an issue that concerns the people of the country but is also often talked about by various international news outlets. South Korea is known to have one of the lowest fertility rates in the world. The World Bank reports that women in South Korea have 1.2 children per capita (global average being 2.5 children). The problem, however, multiplies with the rapidly ageing population. The declining popularity of marriage among women has led to lessening birth rates in the country which indicates that there aren't enough babies being born to replace the older generations. This entails a high possibility of population decline. In fact, the UN reports that, by 2100, South Korea's population would reach as low as 29 million which is the same as the country's population in 1966.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Korea has been one of the flag bearers when it comes to exemplifying ideal romantic relationships to the consumers of television dramas but the reality is a bit different.&amp;nbsp;The&amp;nbsp;government's effort to popularise dating and marriage to defend the country from a possible population decline includes introducing schemes and policies like providing one-off payment for each baby born to cover parental costs to turning off the Ministry of Health and Family Affairs' lights at 7 pm, once a month, with the hope that their employees would not be too tired to date and even have babies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dristi Das is a student at the University of Delhi, who is pursuing her Bachelor's degree in Philosophy. Her field of interest is East Asian culture and she likes reading and researching on the same.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guest</name></author><category term="society" /><summary type="html">Korea's value for marriage can be recognised from the popular saying: &quot;A person becomes an adult only after marriage&quot;, which is broadly used in the country. This reveals that the culture often sees being married as the equivalent of being an adult. Moreover, there is the obvious influence of Confucianism in South Korea which considers marriage to be essential for maintaining bloodlines.&amp;nbsp; The&amp;nbsp;Sampo&amp;nbsp;Generation (&amp;nbsp;삼포세대 ) however, disagrees.&amp;nbsp;Sampo&amp;nbsp;Generation, which literally translates to 'giving up on three, generation' is the younger generation of the country who are giving up on dating, marriage and having children. If we look at the statistics over the last three decades (1981-2011), the average age of marriage for South Korean women has increased by six years (23.0 to 29.1), a year more than it has for men (26.4 to 31.9). Furthermore, there has also been a drastic increase in single households (9% in 1990 to 26% in 2013). What are the factors that have led to such an increase? Korea, as a society,&amp;nbsp;stereotypically&amp;nbsp;preferred sons to daughters. While daughters were prepared for their future roles as mothers and wives, education for women was not thought to be as important as it was for men. However, there were also social groups like the&amp;nbsp;Gisaengs.&amp;nbsp;The Gisaengs first appeared in the&amp;nbsp;Goryeo&amp;nbsp;Dynasty (918-1392) and were often historically misrepresented to be only entertainers for the rich and upper class, but, in actuality, they were intelligent and extraordinarily skilled women, who can be compared to today's professionally-trained and educated women. Women, after first democratic Korea was established, got increased opportunities to pursue education and engage in other economic activities. Now women are successful in every field: from business to law, and from science to architecture. But successful careers could also entail increased working hours. According to a report by OECD, on average, a South Korean person works about 38.9 hours a week, ranking the nation third among 37 countries.&amp;nbsp; Increased working hours lead to disinterest in dating or the inability to maintain existing relationships. A successful position in any industry for a woman comes with the fear of having to abandon it after her marriage. Marriage would mean the addition of another family (her in-laws) and the pressure of having a baby. Even if a working female decides to have a baby after her marriage, she would have to be away from her job for a while, which in turn would be a threat to the position she holds at her workplace. The work culture is very competitive in Korea and you can easily find replacements for any position. For a man to replace a woman is even easier. Marriage is not a union between two individuals but two families. This is even more appropriate for East Asian cultures, where, from marriage to childbearing, everything is linked. For a society bearing such thinking, it is only natural for a girl's parents to find an ideal groom for their daughter. An ideal son-in-law would be someone who can provide their daughter emotional and financial support.&amp;nbsp; Many women in Korea would not marry the man of their choice if their parents do not approve of him. Even if she decides to marry the guy her parents have chosen for her, she would still have to rely on her parents' financial help as marriages in Korea are very expensive. According to&amp;nbsp;Statista, in 2018 an average Korean wedding cost around 230 million Korean Won which includes&amp;nbsp;Yedam, the gifts given to the groom's family. In a country where marriage comes with such a cost, it is only natural that a 21st-century South Korean woman finds having enough money in her bank account to own an apartment in&amp;nbsp;Gangnam&amp;nbsp;to be more attractive than getting married, even if it means that she has to work a few extra hours. Interestingly, with the growing popularity of Korean dramas which portray getting married to an older woman to be desirable, it is seen that the female population, when it does tie the knot, is also inclining towards getting married to men who are younger by five years and sometimes even ten years. This has led to increased growth in the number of remarriages, even though Korea's culture does not&amp;nbsp;favour&amp;nbsp;remarriage. In fact, given the increasing popularity of marriages with older women, changing trends can be seen with the subtle possibility of a matriarchy. But all of this comes with a cost. Fertility in Korea has become not only an issue that concerns the people of the country but is also often talked about by various international news outlets. South Korea is known to have one of the lowest fertility rates in the world. The World Bank reports that women in South Korea have 1.2 children per capita (global average being 2.5 children). The problem, however, multiplies with the rapidly ageing population. The declining popularity of marriage among women has led to lessening birth rates in the country which indicates that there aren't enough babies being born to replace the older generations. This entails a high possibility of population decline. In fact, the UN reports that, by 2100, South Korea's population would reach as low as 29 million which is the same as the country's population in 1966. South Korea has been one of the flag bearers when it comes to exemplifying ideal romantic relationships to the consumers of television dramas but the reality is a bit different.&amp;nbsp;The&amp;nbsp;government's effort to popularise dating and marriage to defend the country from a possible population decline includes introducing schemes and policies like providing one-off payment for each baby born to cover parental costs to turning off the Ministry of Health and Family Affairs' lights at 7 pm, once a month, with the hope that their employees would not be too tired to date and even have babies! Dristi Das is a student at the University of Delhi, who is pursuing her Bachelor's degree in Philosophy. Her field of interest is East Asian culture and she likes reading and researching on the same.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Sense of India’s Steel Prices</title><link href="/Making-Sense-of-India-s-Steel-Prices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Sense of India's Steel Prices" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Making-Sense-of-India-s-Steel-Prices</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Making-Sense-of-India-s-Steel-Prices">&lt;p&gt;Last year in March 2020, when the world became afflicted by the new virus, traders dealing in commodities knew they were in for a difficult time. As these commodities are governed by the supreme forces of demand and supply, demand was close to nil due to the Central Government-imposed lockdown in India, which led the prices of commodities to fall to multi-year lows. Various prominent economists speculated about a slow-recovery, some predicted a short-term V-shaped recovery, but traders were sceptical as to what lay ahead of them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May, 2020, the prices of steel increased but were restricted to a paltry bracket of ₹3000 – ₹ 4000/- per tonne. The main reason for this were the high inventory levels maintained by the stockists as well as industrialists. Suppose, you have a warehouse and let’s suppose you’ve 100 tonnes of finished steel @ ₹35,000 per tonne, which means that unless you’re finished with 80% of your stock, you won’t order more. So essentially the prices won’t increase by a higher level, unless the stock is about to end. This is exactly what happened, and therefore, prices remained low.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the stock started to deplete at a tremendous rate, when India started to open up, owing to the pent-up demand, which led the traders to scramble for iron ore as well as finished steel, hence shooting up the prices. Iron-ore, the primary raw material of finished steel, was scantily available, due to most of the iron ores being closed because of the economic disruptions. Steadily, mines started operating, but it was a phased-opening. On the backdrop of a robust demand domestically, this furthered the upward pressure on the prices.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, even China imported a record-high of 1.9 million tonnes during the first half of 2020-21. In contrast, in the same period of the previous year, China had merely imported 2,500 tonnes from India. This was essential because most of the Chinese steel firms use the blast furnace, which shouldn’t be turned off unless it is being shut down for the good. As the show must go on, China didn’t cease its infrastructure operations, rather it turned into an importer of India’s low grade iron ore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More intriguingly, this is the first time that India has turned into a net exporter of iron ore in a few years. India was literally exporting 69% of semi-finished steel and 28% of finished steel between April and August. Such heavy exporting activity exerted an even greater pressure on demand when the supply side was in shambles, making it another reason for the price growth from June to December 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things started to normalise in terms of easy availability of raw materials and demand scaled down to a normal level, stockists thought that prices would wane in the near future, but let’s wait and read!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned story is a classic case of a robust demand but scanty supply. But the story can’t be so straightforward: China has been the supremist steel player, not only in terms of production but also in terms of consumption. Therefore, any slow-down in the Chinese steel sector is reverberated all across the world. China, for quite some time, has been focusing on curbing pollution, and as steel mills heavily contribute to the pollution, there have been certain limitations to the production done by these ‘zombie enterprises.’&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This campaign was started by China in 2019, and though the emissions control goal wasn’t achieved in that year, the government has become stringent on production curbs since late 2020’s. Now, we can understand why India turned into a net exporter, because when there are production curbs in China, someone had to fulfil the demand, and hence India stepped in.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking about India, demand was really strong and on top of that, major steel producers were also exporting a lion’s share of their produce to China. When an investor thinks about all these macro and micro level developments, one can certainly understand that the steel players are going to be benefitted immensely by these developments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stock prices discount future earnings, they took a similar course of action this time as well. Major beneficiaries like JSW, SAIL, TATA STEEL, JSPL, to name a few have been on a bull run since November, 2020, and share prices have increased by up to 75%. Therefore, we can easily infer that the steel sector has been in for a rosy ride. But after a bright day, we certainly have a short gloomy period, and so did the steel industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steel prices had skyrocketed, and this caused a major impediment for the Chinese government to continue working on a plethora of infrastructure projects, and hence the administration stepped in. In the month of May, the Chinese Government intervened and started imposing heavy fines on people trying to hike up the prices. This made the investors lose confidence in the industry and the Iron Ore Futures fell north of 16% in a span of two weeks. Though this has proved to be a slight hiccup to the Indian steel Industry, with prices falling to about ₹4,000/- per tonne from the peak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But stalwarts of the industry are pretty optimistic about the Indian steel prices, because the current prices are still on discount, if compared with the global prices, and thereby provides some leeway for prices to increase.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What lies ahead of us is certainly hazy, like the current weather, but we can only sip our teas and hobble on our samosas, until China comes up with another development with regards to the steel industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aditya Khandelwal</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Last year in March 2020, when the world became afflicted by the new virus, traders dealing in commodities knew they were in for a difficult time. As these commodities are governed by the supreme forces of demand and supply, demand was close to nil due to the Central Government-imposed lockdown in India, which led the prices of commodities to fall to multi-year lows. Various prominent economists speculated about a slow-recovery, some predicted a short-term V-shaped recovery, but traders were sceptical as to what lay ahead of them.&amp;nbsp; In May, 2020, the prices of steel increased but were restricted to a paltry bracket of ₹3000 – ₹ 4000/- per tonne. The main reason for this were the high inventory levels maintained by the stockists as well as industrialists. Suppose, you have a warehouse and let’s suppose you’ve 100 tonnes of finished steel @ ₹35,000 per tonne, which means that unless you’re finished with 80% of your stock, you won’t order more. So essentially the prices won’t increase by a higher level, unless the stock is about to end. This is exactly what happened, and therefore, prices remained low.&amp;nbsp; However, the stock started to deplete at a tremendous rate, when India started to open up, owing to the pent-up demand, which led the traders to scramble for iron ore as well as finished steel, hence shooting up the prices. Iron-ore, the primary raw material of finished steel, was scantily available, due to most of the iron ores being closed because of the economic disruptions. Steadily, mines started operating, but it was a phased-opening. On the backdrop of a robust demand domestically, this furthered the upward pressure on the prices.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, even China imported a record-high of 1.9 million tonnes during the first half of 2020-21. In contrast, in the same period of the previous year, China had merely imported 2,500 tonnes from India. This was essential because most of the Chinese steel firms use the blast furnace, which shouldn’t be turned off unless it is being shut down for the good. As the show must go on, China didn’t cease its infrastructure operations, rather it turned into an importer of India’s low grade iron ore. More intriguingly, this is the first time that India has turned into a net exporter of iron ore in a few years. India was literally exporting 69% of semi-finished steel and 28% of finished steel between April and August. Such heavy exporting activity exerted an even greater pressure on demand when the supply side was in shambles, making it another reason for the price growth from June to December 2020.&amp;nbsp; When things started to normalise in terms of easy availability of raw materials and demand scaled down to a normal level, stockists thought that prices would wane in the near future, but let’s wait and read!&amp;nbsp; The aforementioned story is a classic case of a robust demand but scanty supply. But the story can’t be so straightforward: China has been the supremist steel player, not only in terms of production but also in terms of consumption. Therefore, any slow-down in the Chinese steel sector is reverberated all across the world. China, for quite some time, has been focusing on curbing pollution, and as steel mills heavily contribute to the pollution, there have been certain limitations to the production done by these ‘zombie enterprises.’&amp;nbsp; This campaign was started by China in 2019, and though the emissions control goal wasn’t achieved in that year, the government has become stringent on production curbs since late 2020’s. Now, we can understand why India turned into a net exporter, because when there are production curbs in China, someone had to fulfil the demand, and hence India stepped in.&amp;nbsp; Talking about India, demand was really strong and on top of that, major steel producers were also exporting a lion’s share of their produce to China. When an investor thinks about all these macro and micro level developments, one can certainly understand that the steel players are going to be benefitted immensely by these developments.&amp;nbsp; As stock prices discount future earnings, they took a similar course of action this time as well. Major beneficiaries like JSW, SAIL, TATA STEEL, JSPL, to name a few have been on a bull run since November, 2020, and share prices have increased by up to 75%. Therefore, we can easily infer that the steel sector has been in for a rosy ride. But after a bright day, we certainly have a short gloomy period, and so did the steel industry. Steel prices had skyrocketed, and this caused a major impediment for the Chinese government to continue working on a plethora of infrastructure projects, and hence the administration stepped in. In the month of May, the Chinese Government intervened and started imposing heavy fines on people trying to hike up the prices. This made the investors lose confidence in the industry and the Iron Ore Futures fell north of 16% in a span of two weeks. Though this has proved to be a slight hiccup to the Indian steel Industry, with prices falling to about ₹4,000/- per tonne from the peak.&amp;nbsp; But stalwarts of the industry are pretty optimistic about the Indian steel prices, because the current prices are still on discount, if compared with the global prices, and thereby provides some leeway for prices to increase.&amp;nbsp; What lies ahead of us is certainly hazy, like the current weather, but we can only sip our teas and hobble on our samosas, until China comes up with another development with regards to the steel industry.&amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Your Ideal Brand Doing for Your ‘Pride’?</title><link href="/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Your Ideal Brand Doing for Your ‘Pride’?" /><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride</id><content type="html" xml:base="/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride">&lt;p&gt;Each year, in the summertime, Pride collections emerge like a swarm of vividly coloured locusts. They envelop every storefront and Instagram feed in June, promising solidarity for LGBTQ+ communities. In 2021, we are yet again observing the second virtual celebration of pride month. Numerous brands have leveraged pride marketing to increase visibility and lend support to others within the LGBTQ+ community who are still exploring their identities. However, brands tend to forget the existence of the community as soon as July rolls on. It makes us question, is this just another marketing gimmick?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is customary for Pride-themed merchandise to spike during June, a practice known as rainbow capitalism, is often criticised and compared to pinkwashing. Nevertheless, there is still tremendous value that can come from rocking rainbows during this time of the year. Like ‘empowerment campaigns’, several brands climb the trend wagon in Pride month, with no concern for the cause. Pride marketing is empathetic, where aiming ‘just for sales’ will misfire and attract more backlash from the audience and hurt the entity's image in the long term. Therefore, brands should not use Pride month to ramp up the sales but instead use their platform to show support and disperse awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Burger King's Pride month initiative was very thoughtful and won many hearts. Their tagline stated, &quot;&lt;em&gt;The pride is on you. The parade is on us&lt;/em&gt;&quot;, along with their delivery vehicles transformed. The campaign persisted till July 5. This year, diverse brands showcased their support to the community beyond rainbow washing and making the most out of pride marketing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Popular brands like Fossil, Apple, Reebok and others often dedicate enormous resources during Pride month to LGBTQ+ non-profit organisations (among them,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thetrevorproject.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Trevor Project&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glsen.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GLSEN&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and different groups), which means you could be helping others gain access to valuable resources, too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To honour Pride month, Fossil launched its all-new limited-edition Pride collection to celebrate the spirit of love, equality and the very essence of individuality. The proceeds from this collection will benefit The Trevor Project — the world’s most significant suicide prevention and crisis intervention organisation for LGBTQ+ young adults.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Apple, it has released two new Apple Watch Pride bands this year and a new Pride watch face for users. The brand also supports many LGBTQ+ advocacy organisations, including&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://encircletogether.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Encircle&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(which offers safe spaces for LGBTQ+ youth, young adults and families), the&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://transequality.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Center for Transgender Equality&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(committed to social justice advocacy for transgender humans), and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add on, Reebok’s newest collection celebrating the LGBTQ+ community features a vibrant assortment of Pride-inspired footwear and apparel. The items were designed by Colorful Soles, the brand’s LGBTQ+ employee community, which also partnered with the legendary House of Ninja (spotlighted in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reviewed.com/streaming/features/black-history-documentaries-stream-now&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iconic documentary&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paris is Burning&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, Reebok is donating $75,000 to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://srlp.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sylvia Rivera Law Project&lt;/a&gt;, which advocates for affirming access to social, health and legal services for persons of all gender identities and expressions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the bargain, loads of fashion and beauty brands create Pride-inspired products that not only help you look great but also feel good as they support organisations that empower and uplift LGBTQ+ communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give some instances, the Gap Collective Pride collection includes T-shirts, hoodies, socks and more for all ages. The brand is donating $50,000 this season to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glaad.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD)&lt;/a&gt;, an LGBTQ media advocacy organization.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levi's is flaunting the Pride collection &quot;All Pronouns. All Love&quot; by emphasising respect for people's pronouns. They have the inscribed phrase &quot;they/them, she/her, he/him, we&quot; on their collections, which is gender-neutral. It will be donating 100% of the profits to OutRight Action International.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NYX's limited-edition collection comprises a wide makeup range that will bring a colourful ultra-metallic sheen. It will also donate $100,000 to Pride efforts globally and contribute towards the LA LGBT Center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other brands are also making their Pride-themed offerings and donations a year-round initiative, including Happy Socks, donating 10% of the sales from its rainbow-coloured socks to InterPride throughout the year, and Pink, which has expanded its offerings with its gender-inclusive Pink for All collection that debuted earlier this year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next door, LEGO has launched a limited-edition&amp;nbsp;LGBTQ themed set. This is the first LGBTQ set with 11 monochromatic figures, each with an assigned colour and 346 pieces creating a rainbow cascade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, TGI Fridays have introduced a decadent, delicious dessert. This dessert is six layers of rainbow-coloured vanilla cake piled high with vanilla icing and sprinkles and is available for home delivery and in-store locations. Part of the profits generated from the sales will be donated to support GLSEN&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many music platforms in India, like music streaming service Jio Saavan and Spotify, and music channel VH1 are also celebrating Pride Month.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other brands, Skittles took a bold move of launching limited-edition&amp;nbsp;Skittles Pride Packs&amp;nbsp;that come in grey packaging rather than rainbow washing. Even the candies inside are grey with delicious strawberries, orange, grape, apple, and lemon. For every pack sold, $1 will be donated to GLAAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shira Kogan, Director of Corporate Development at The Trevor Project, said &lt;em&gt;&quot;We are thrilled to see so many companies and brands stepping up to support Pride this year.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; Well, it is true that brands have the power and platform to influence others. These brands can tell stories to empower the LGBTQ+ community through marketing campaigns or a separate product line. Together they can create a world where the LGBTQ+ community is championed, celebrated and protected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that consumers of Pride gear are becoming more aware and are making an effort to shop where proceeds will make the most significant impact, including shopping at small, queer-owned businesses. For example, consumers are taking note when companies only feature underrepresented groups during their respective history or heritage months, says Ali Fazal, Vice President of Marketing at influencer marketing platform&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://grin.co/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GRIN&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&quot;(If) the only time they see LGBT people represented is during Pride Month, it's clear that what you're doing is not a long-term evolution for your company and your marketing.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; says Fazal.&lt;em&gt;&quot;You're just trying to capitalize upon the seasonality of that month.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's be honest: Most major brands have not maintained a consistent enough relationship with LGBTQ+ communities to survive Pride month without some level of scrutiny. More often than not, ‘rainbow washing’ — that is, the act of deploying Pride-themed versions of their products and marketing it without substantially engaging queer communities — tends to be the minimal-effort route that multiple brands take and majority of consumers recognise these attempts as inauthentic almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's never too late to start developing real bonds with LGBTQ+ consumers. One of the most effective ways to show support is through charitable efforts, and Pride offers brands ample opportunities to turn their specialised products into the support that resonates beyond June.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a recent analysis, queer consumers who tend to maintain higher median household incomes, are more likely than other marginalised groups to actively seek and patronise the companies that engage with their collective community in a sustained fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, some brands understand the lasting power of giving back. It is important to remember the message one leaves out there can help lay the foundation of change. We need to understand that equality is not a once-a-month fight, but year-round support is necessary — not just for Pride month, but all the social causes we rise for. Together we can create a world, which is fairer for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samakshi Garg</name></author><category term="trending" /><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">Each year, in the summertime, Pride collections emerge like a swarm of vividly coloured locusts. They envelop every storefront and Instagram feed in June, promising solidarity for LGBTQ+ communities. In 2021, we are yet again observing the second virtual celebration of pride month. Numerous brands have leveraged pride marketing to increase visibility and lend support to others within the LGBTQ+ community who are still exploring their identities. However, brands tend to forget the existence of the community as soon as July rolls on. It makes us question, is this just another marketing gimmick? While it is customary for Pride-themed merchandise to spike during June, a practice known as rainbow capitalism, is often criticised and compared to pinkwashing. Nevertheless, there is still tremendous value that can come from rocking rainbows during this time of the year. Like ‘empowerment campaigns’, several brands climb the trend wagon in Pride month, with no concern for the cause. Pride marketing is empathetic, where aiming ‘just for sales’ will misfire and attract more backlash from the audience and hurt the entity's image in the long term. Therefore, brands should not use Pride month to ramp up the sales but instead use their platform to show support and disperse awareness. In 2020, Burger King's Pride month initiative was very thoughtful and won many hearts. Their tagline stated, &quot;The pride is on you. The parade is on us&quot;, along with their delivery vehicles transformed. The campaign persisted till July 5. This year, diverse brands showcased their support to the community beyond rainbow washing and making the most out of pride marketing.&amp;nbsp; Popular brands like Fossil, Apple, Reebok and others often dedicate enormous resources during Pride month to LGBTQ+ non-profit organisations (among them,&amp;nbsp;The Trevor Project,&amp;nbsp;GLSEN&amp;nbsp;and different groups), which means you could be helping others gain access to valuable resources, too.&amp;nbsp; To honour Pride month, Fossil launched its all-new limited-edition Pride collection to celebrate the spirit of love, equality and the very essence of individuality. The proceeds from this collection will benefit The Trevor Project — the world’s most significant suicide prevention and crisis intervention organisation for LGBTQ+ young adults.&amp;nbsp; In the case of Apple, it has released two new Apple Watch Pride bands this year and a new Pride watch face for users. The brand also supports many LGBTQ+ advocacy organisations, including&amp;nbsp;Encircle&amp;nbsp;(which offers safe spaces for LGBTQ+ youth, young adults and families), the&amp;nbsp;National Center for Transgender Equality&amp;nbsp;(committed to social justice advocacy for transgender humans), and others. To add on, Reebok’s newest collection celebrating the LGBTQ+ community features a vibrant assortment of Pride-inspired footwear and apparel. The items were designed by Colorful Soles, the brand’s LGBTQ+ employee community, which also partnered with the legendary House of Ninja (spotlighted in the&amp;nbsp;iconic documentary,&amp;nbsp;Paris is Burning). Moreover, Reebok is donating $75,000 to the&amp;nbsp;Sylvia Rivera Law Project, which advocates for affirming access to social, health and legal services for persons of all gender identities and expressions.&amp;nbsp; Into the bargain, loads of fashion and beauty brands create Pride-inspired products that not only help you look great but also feel good as they support organisations that empower and uplift LGBTQ+ communities.&amp;nbsp; To give some instances, the Gap Collective Pride collection includes T-shirts, hoodies, socks and more for all ages. The brand is donating $50,000 this season to the&amp;nbsp;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), an LGBTQ media advocacy organization.&amp;nbsp; Levi's is flaunting the Pride collection &quot;All Pronouns. All Love&quot; by emphasising respect for people's pronouns. They have the inscribed phrase &quot;they/them, she/her, he/him, we&quot; on their collections, which is gender-neutral. It will be donating 100% of the profits to OutRight Action International.&amp;nbsp; NYX's limited-edition collection comprises a wide makeup range that will bring a colourful ultra-metallic sheen. It will also donate $100,000 to Pride efforts globally and contribute towards the LA LGBT Center. Other brands are also making their Pride-themed offerings and donations a year-round initiative, including Happy Socks, donating 10% of the sales from its rainbow-coloured socks to InterPride throughout the year, and Pink, which has expanded its offerings with its gender-inclusive Pink for All collection that debuted earlier this year.&amp;nbsp; Next door, LEGO has launched a limited-edition&amp;nbsp;LGBTQ themed set. This is the first LGBTQ set with 11 monochromatic figures, each with an assigned colour and 346 pieces creating a rainbow cascade.&amp;nbsp; Meanwhile, TGI Fridays have introduced a decadent, delicious dessert. This dessert is six layers of rainbow-coloured vanilla cake piled high with vanilla icing and sprinkles and is available for home delivery and in-store locations. Part of the profits generated from the sales will be donated to support GLSEN.&amp;nbsp; Many music platforms in India, like music streaming service Jio Saavan and Spotify, and music channel VH1 are also celebrating Pride Month.&amp;nbsp; Unlike other brands, Skittles took a bold move of launching limited-edition&amp;nbsp;Skittles Pride Packs&amp;nbsp;that come in grey packaging rather than rainbow washing. Even the candies inside are grey with delicious strawberries, orange, grape, apple, and lemon. For every pack sold, $1 will be donated to GLAAD. Shira Kogan, Director of Corporate Development at The Trevor Project, said &quot;We are thrilled to see so many companies and brands stepping up to support Pride this year.&quot; Well, it is true that brands have the power and platform to influence others. These brands can tell stories to empower the LGBTQ+ community through marketing campaigns or a separate product line. Together they can create a world where the LGBTQ+ community is championed, celebrated and protected.&amp;nbsp; The result is that consumers of Pride gear are becoming more aware and are making an effort to shop where proceeds will make the most significant impact, including shopping at small, queer-owned businesses. For example, consumers are taking note when companies only feature underrepresented groups during their respective history or heritage months, says Ali Fazal, Vice President of Marketing at influencer marketing platform&amp;nbsp;GRIN. &quot;(If) the only time they see LGBT people represented is during Pride Month, it's clear that what you're doing is not a long-term evolution for your company and your marketing.&quot; says Fazal.&quot;You're just trying to capitalize upon the seasonality of that month.&quot; Now let's be honest: Most major brands have not maintained a consistent enough relationship with LGBTQ+ communities to survive Pride month without some level of scrutiny. More often than not, ‘rainbow washing’ — that is, the act of deploying Pride-themed versions of their products and marketing it without substantially engaging queer communities — tends to be the minimal-effort route that multiple brands take and majority of consumers recognise these attempts as inauthentic almost immediately. But it's never too late to start developing real bonds with LGBTQ+ consumers. One of the most effective ways to show support is through charitable efforts, and Pride offers brands ample opportunities to turn their specialised products into the support that resonates beyond June.&amp;nbsp; According to a recent analysis, queer consumers who tend to maintain higher median household incomes, are more likely than other marginalised groups to actively seek and patronise the companies that engage with their collective community in a sustained fashion. Fortunately, some brands understand the lasting power of giving back. It is important to remember the message one leaves out there can help lay the foundation of change. We need to understand that equality is not a once-a-month fight, but year-round support is necessary — not just for Pride month, but all the social causes we rise for. Together we can create a world, which is fairer for everyone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wars: The Hole in a Country’s Pocket</title><link href="/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wars: The Hole in a Country’s Pocket" /><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What gives rise to wars? Well, conflicts are an inevitable part of the survival of the human race; especially when existence is heterogeneous in nature. When conflicts intersect with political ideals and ideologies, land rights, religious dominance, etc they have the potential to churn out a war.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Time and time again, countries around the world have stepped down to avoid war but a few remain unlucky and suffer the aftermath. The cost of war is immeasurable for all the parties involved. No matter who wins the battle, the loss is suffered on all ends; and usually, it is equal in magnitude. Economics is well-stitched into a war, so much so that experts believe every war entails an economic motive irrespective of the reason presented to the public. This is probably why one will never come across two entities fighting for a barren land with no water sources, no mineral wealth and no means of attracting investment in any form. Even if the total area of such land can help the country expand its territorial boundaries, it is not worth a war!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To lay the foundation it is important to understand the ‘war economy’. When a nation is in a state of war, the prioritisation principle witnesses a shift in expenditure. The production of goods and services that support war efforts and strengthen the defence front of the country assume importance. A country at war re-configures its budget and diverts all the taxes towards national security, the nation might also borrow to fund its requirements. One ramification of war is that it encourages innovation. War economies demonstrate more technological, industrial and medical advancements as they are in competition to create cheaper defence products along with the emergency medical units to be well prepared. This is an instance of infrastructural development. However, the focus is not the welfare of its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One might expect wealthy nations to be more violent as they have more to fight over. However, the econometric evidence is divided, most researches show that wealth reduces the probability of a civil war by manifolds. In addition, economic growth acts as a shield against violence, while recession increases the probability. The most common reason for this is that wealthier societies are able to better protect assets, thus making violence less attractive for would-be rebels. Another explanation, given by political scientist Thomas Homer-Dixon argues that poverty causes violence, and points to cases where scarcity leads to migrations that result in conflicts between identity groups over resources. The cost of physical capital destruction and human capital destruction remain inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;Do wars benefit anyone?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It will be paradoxical to state that war will benefit the country. A conflict that results in loss of human lives, destruction of property, trauma, leaving hundreds of people homeless, and the list goes on, cannot do good to anyone. However, economics rises a notch above human sentiments and reflects on the infrastructural developments and a shift in the demand-supply chain. A country that is in a state of war will accommodate its working population in order to work to the brim and achieve the fullest of its capacity, thus aiming at full employment across different sectors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Spike in employment, the surge in working capacity and inclusion of the latest technology to produce efficiently helps in boosting economic growth. The government invests in the latest technology in order to keep pace with the war which in turn boosts innovation in the territory and paves way for research and development (R&amp;amp;D).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another important side effect of war is the change in social outlook and attitudes. History is evidence of the fact that women have stepped out of their houses in order to be a part of the labour force contributing to the battle whenever a war breaks out. Healthcare, a major support system during wars, witnesses women participating in large numbers to save the lives of soldiers. Various industries that work to boost the supplies welcome women in order to elevate the production capacity while the men go out to the battlefield. Women have played an important role in all the wars that humanity has witnessed till now, so much so that they became aware of their rights after World War I and World War II and with a stride of independence they continued to voice their rights and soon the demand for ‘vote’ was raised by women across the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is at stake for Israel-Palestine?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In May 2021, Israel and Pakistan counted 11 days of hostilities that resulted in the loss of life and physical capital on both ends. The housing ministry of Gaza stated that 16,800 housing units have been damaged. The electricity grids across Gaza remain dismantled with barely three-four hours of power supply in a day. The Hamas media office estimated the bombardments had caused $40 million in damage to factories and the strip’s industrial zone and other industrial facilities, in addition to $22 million in damage to the energy sector. In addition, the sanitation facilities have been damaged and the water supply remains disrupted with limited or no access to water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Israeli economy already contracted by 6.5% in the first quarter due to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The Central Bureau of Statistics predicts that the road to revival is likely to stay disrupted owing to the fight between Israel and Palestine. Israel’s manufacturers’ association reported a loss of $166 million as of 13 May 2021 because the south and centre of the country witnessed intense rocket fire from Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The economic relations between Israel and Palestine date back to 1967 when Israel occupied the West Bank and Gaza Strip and integrated their markets with its own. The Israeli economy was about ten times the size of its neighbour’s economy and the manufacturing sector’s GDP share was over four times larger. Thus the difference was between a large, rich and advanced economy and a small, poor and underdeveloped economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Both theoretical analysis and empirical studies suggest that the dynamics of such a relationship always generates two opposing forces that disproportionately affect the smaller economy and shape its development. A favourable repercussion is an increased demand for the products of the small economy, diffusion of technology and knowledge. Unfavourable repercussions arise from the disappearance of many industries in the small economy, its confinement to producing low-skill goods, and the emigration of a sizable segment of its labour force to the neighbouring economy, as well as to other countries. This suppression of a powerful neighbour has resulted in numerous incidents of violence, time and again. The end consequence has been that the region of Palestine has seen practically no development and has remained war torn.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, “who benefits from war?” remains unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vanshika Sighroha</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">What gives rise to wars? Well, conflicts are an inevitable part of the survival of the human race; especially when existence is heterogeneous in nature. When conflicts intersect with political ideals and ideologies, land rights, religious dominance, etc they have the potential to churn out a war.&amp;nbsp; Time and time again, countries around the world have stepped down to avoid war but a few remain unlucky and suffer the aftermath. The cost of war is immeasurable for all the parties involved. No matter who wins the battle, the loss is suffered on all ends; and usually, it is equal in magnitude. Economics is well-stitched into a war, so much so that experts believe every war entails an economic motive irrespective of the reason presented to the public. This is probably why one will never come across two entities fighting for a barren land with no water sources, no mineral wealth and no means of attracting investment in any form. Even if the total area of such land can help the country expand its territorial boundaries, it is not worth a war!&amp;nbsp; To lay the foundation it is important to understand the ‘war economy’. When a nation is in a state of war, the prioritisation principle witnesses a shift in expenditure. The production of goods and services that support war efforts and strengthen the defence front of the country assume importance. A country at war re-configures its budget and diverts all the taxes towards national security, the nation might also borrow to fund its requirements. One ramification of war is that it encourages innovation. War economies demonstrate more technological, industrial and medical advancements as they are in competition to create cheaper defence products along with the emergency medical units to be well prepared. This is an instance of infrastructural development. However, the focus is not the welfare of its citizens. One might expect wealthy nations to be more violent as they have more to fight over. However, the econometric evidence is divided, most researches show that wealth reduces the probability of a civil war by manifolds. In addition, economic growth acts as a shield against violence, while recession increases the probability. The most common reason for this is that wealthier societies are able to better protect assets, thus making violence less attractive for would-be rebels. Another explanation, given by political scientist Thomas Homer-Dixon argues that poverty causes violence, and points to cases where scarcity leads to migrations that result in conflicts between identity groups over resources. The cost of physical capital destruction and human capital destruction remain inevitable. &amp;nbsp;Do wars benefit anyone? It will be paradoxical to state that war will benefit the country. A conflict that results in loss of human lives, destruction of property, trauma, leaving hundreds of people homeless, and the list goes on, cannot do good to anyone. However, economics rises a notch above human sentiments and reflects on the infrastructural developments and a shift in the demand-supply chain. A country that is in a state of war will accommodate its working population in order to work to the brim and achieve the fullest of its capacity, thus aiming at full employment across different sectors.&amp;nbsp; Spike in employment, the surge in working capacity and inclusion of the latest technology to produce efficiently helps in boosting economic growth. The government invests in the latest technology in order to keep pace with the war which in turn boosts innovation in the territory and paves way for research and development (R&amp;amp;D).&amp;nbsp; Another important side effect of war is the change in social outlook and attitudes. History is evidence of the fact that women have stepped out of their houses in order to be a part of the labour force contributing to the battle whenever a war breaks out. Healthcare, a major support system during wars, witnesses women participating in large numbers to save the lives of soldiers. Various industries that work to boost the supplies welcome women in order to elevate the production capacity while the men go out to the battlefield. Women have played an important role in all the wars that humanity has witnessed till now, so much so that they became aware of their rights after World War I and World War II and with a stride of independence they continued to voice their rights and soon the demand for ‘vote’ was raised by women across the world. What is at stake for Israel-Palestine? In May 2021, Israel and Pakistan counted 11 days of hostilities that resulted in the loss of life and physical capital on both ends. The housing ministry of Gaza stated that 16,800 housing units have been damaged. The electricity grids across Gaza remain dismantled with barely three-four hours of power supply in a day. The Hamas media office estimated the bombardments had caused $40 million in damage to factories and the strip’s industrial zone and other industrial facilities, in addition to $22 million in damage to the energy sector. In addition, the sanitation facilities have been damaged and the water supply remains disrupted with limited or no access to water. The Israeli economy already contracted by 6.5% in the first quarter due to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The Central Bureau of Statistics predicts that the road to revival is likely to stay disrupted owing to the fight between Israel and Palestine. Israel’s manufacturers’ association reported a loss of $166 million as of 13 May 2021 because the south and centre of the country witnessed intense rocket fire from Gaza. The economic relations between Israel and Palestine date back to 1967 when Israel occupied the West Bank and Gaza Strip and integrated their markets with its own. The Israeli economy was about ten times the size of its neighbour’s economy and the manufacturing sector’s GDP share was over four times larger. Thus the difference was between a large, rich and advanced economy and a small, poor and underdeveloped economy.&amp;nbsp; Both theoretical analysis and empirical studies suggest that the dynamics of such a relationship always generates two opposing forces that disproportionately affect the smaller economy and shape its development. A favourable repercussion is an increased demand for the products of the small economy, diffusion of technology and knowledge. Unfavourable repercussions arise from the disappearance of many industries in the small economy, its confinement to producing low-skill goods, and the emigration of a sizable segment of its labour force to the neighbouring economy, as well as to other countries. This suppression of a powerful neighbour has resulted in numerous incidents of violence, time and again. The end consequence has been that the region of Palestine has seen practically no development and has remained war torn.&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, “who benefits from war?” remains unanswered.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Black Heart of Suburbia</title><link href="/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Black Heart of Suburbia" /><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia">&lt;p&gt;In April, Representative Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and US Senator Edward Markey &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/green-new-deal-alexandria-ocasio-cortez-ed-markey-reintroduce/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to reintroduce the Green New Deal, intended to enable divestment from fossil fuels, stimulate jobs in renewable industries, and spur the decarbonisation of America’s economy by 2050.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An encouraging development within mainstream environmentalism, the Green New Deal commits to considerable levels of public investment in renewable energy and green infrastructure. However, like many social-democratic solutions to climate change, it is underpinned by a Keynesian assumption that technical fixes, rather than broader structural changes, are the key to solving political problems. Much of modern environmentalism is impeded by a naive technological utopianism that commits to elaborate spending plans on major green infrastructure projects, remaining oblivious to the fact that a broader reorganisation of society is required to reverse the effects of climate change. Spending millions of dollars on the rollout of electric vehicles does little to dissuade the use of cars, create cycle lanes, or to change the fact that vast swathes of America were designed to enable car usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, much of American society, from rampant consumerism to dependency on artificially enhanced food from chemical and agricultural corporations, is based around providing a consumer market for the products of the petroleum industry, which rose to prominence in the aftermath of World War II, securing both domestic and international success. To understand the extent to which American consumer capitalism has become inextricably linked with the power of petroleum, it is necessary to trace the emergence of the fossil fuel industry to the post-War era, in which the United States sought to dominate the world through the exertion of financial and military power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American dominance in the post-war era involved achieving two aims which would safeguard the untrammelled might of the oil industry: firstly, the transition from a world economy based on coal to one based on oil, which would disintegrate organised labour and subjugate European powers to American hegemony via dependency on the dollar for ERP funds; secondly, a culture of consumerism based on constructing identical suburbs whose value was kept high by segregation and redlining, alongside widespread car ownership which necessitated a drastic change in the layout of America’s cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dollar would become the predominant global currency, in which the values of all other currencies were to be expressed, facilitating the construction of a geopolitical settlement based on the flow of Middle Eastern oil into European countries, who would buy the products of American petroleum companies using dollars. Though commonly misconstrued as an example of great power benevolence, in which the United States generously rebuilt the economies of Western Europe to ensure mutual peace and prosperity in the aftermath of history’s bloodiest conflict, the Marshall Plan prostrated European economies to American influence. Tim Mitchell, in his book &lt;em&gt;Carbon Democracy, &lt;/em&gt;described the process whereby the militancy of coal miners was curtailed, and the reorientation of the global economic order took place. He wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The corporatised democracy of postwar Western Europe was to be built on this reorganisation of energy flows. ERP funds helped pay for building oil refineries and installing oil-fired industrial boilers, putting in place the infrastructure needed to convert from coal to oil. The US encouraged the building of roads, gave ERP countries $432.5 million to purchase American vehicles, and subsidised Italian and French car manufacturers.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1948 and 1951, more than half the oil sold to Western European countries by American companies was paid for by funds gained from the Marshall Plan. Companies such as Standard Oil and representatives of the Rockefeller family had lobbied Congress for the Marshall Plan to be approved, with the end goal being not to create prosperity, but to ensure dependency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, the switch from coal to oil had the advantage of changing the relationship between energy and labour. Previously, with coal-dominated economies, labour had been concentrated in certain areas, with economies of scale accruing around coal deposits, largely in Central Europe. But with the advent of oil, the atomisation of organised labour was made possible. Oil, unlike coal, could be extracted from the Earth using a relatively small workforce, supervised at close quarters. Pumping stations and pipelines, unlike railways, did not require overseers to constantly monitor production and transportation processes, meaning that it was far easier to neutralise the power of an otherwise militant labour force. To quote from Mitchell again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“In the case of oil, the capacity to slow down or interrupt the supply of energy on a large scale was much harder to organise. Oil workers found it difficult to carry out a successful sabotage — a difficulty that would impede their efforts to build with oil an enduring mechanism for advancing democratic political claims.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Compared to carrying coal by rail, moving oil by sea eliminated the labour of coal heavers and stokers, and thus the power of organised workers to withdraw their labour from a critical point in the energy system.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of World War II demonstrated the effectiveness of these tactics; not only was labour subordinated to capital by the Taft Hartley Act, which aimed to suppress ‘Communist’ infiltration alongside other draconian provisions, but a clear path to global American hegemony had been established. A wave of strikes had succeeded FDR’s New Deal; in 1945, 3.5 million workers took part in 4,750 strikes across the US, as General Motors, in addition to steel and electrical industries, witnessed a sustained period of labour militancy unrivalled in US history.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the introduction of the Marshall Plan and conversion of the economy from coal to oil can be seen as part of a wider initiative to subdue workers’ autonomy, which also included buying off union leaders by offering pay increases in exchange for uninterrupted production and relative docility. The post-War era, despite being widely regarded as an era of high wage growth and untrammelled prosperity, in fact, according to Michael Yates, created&lt;em&gt; “an ideologically loyal and industrially moderate labour movement, which bargained for concessions without challenging basic dispositions of a business society.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the USA from the War as the world’s preeminent economic force carried with it the untrammelled power of the petroleum industry, in a domestic context, as well as internationally. American oil wells and refineries had supplied six out of every seven barrels of oil used by the Allies during WWII, and between 1948 and 1972, domestic oil consumption tripled from 5.8 to 16.4 million barrels per day. In a 1950 report, Conoco (The Continental Oil Company) told its shareholders that &lt;em&gt;“the main contributing factor to the high level of business activity of the country was the continued high demand for housing and automobiles, two industries which vitally affect the consumption of petroleum products.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1947 until 1960, the motor and petroleum sectors produced one-third of all manufacturing expenditures. The booming automobile industry employed 19% of the total workforce, facilitating a considerable advancement in the material conditions of millions of Americans, but also necessitating a reorientation of the country’s topography; reaping the rewards of consumer capitalism would require the construction of neighbourhoods where car ownership was essential, and where cheap land and lax regulations could allow mass production of homes and goods to satiate the burgeoning appetite of affluent, white suburbia. Nuclear families living in suburbs required lawn mowers, fridges, furniture, and a host of other consumer goods available to the rising class of white, skilled workers, all of which cemented the power of petroleum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structure of the suburbs, located away from cities where redlining prevented ethnic minorities from securing the capital or investment required to move into these areas, ensured the provision of a large-scale market for goods produced by fossil-fuel driven sectors. The domination of the new American suburbs by grotesque McMansions phased out public transport, ensuring that millions of Americans were dependent on cars for travel, and that roads and parking lots replaced rail and pedestrian infrastructure. For example, Lester Brown calculated in 2001 that the US had enough miles of road to encircle the Earth at the equator 157 times. According to author James Kunstler, the automobile boom that drove the construction of highways at the expense of public transportation was: &lt;em&gt;“the greatest misallocation of resources in the history of the world.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates that transformative action on climate change cannot merely involve spending on various projects likely to ameliorate fossil fuel emissions, but must involve a drastic re-thinking of why it is that the American economy and society are structured in the way that they are. Simply spending more on clean energy, while worthwhile in extricating the economy from dependency on fossil fuels, does little to incentivise decarbonisation. Rewilding and urban densification, with their potential to limit excess resource use and curtail mass dependency on cars, ought to be vital aspects of a genuinely transformative environmentalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned at the beginning of this article that handing out vast subsidies to electric cars, which are often expensive and only available to a small number of consumers, will have a negligible impact on the climate in comparison to disincentivising private car ownership in general through the provision of cycle lanes and pedestrianisation. The fact that these alternatives, which include carbon capture and regenerative agriculture are largely sidelined in environmentalist discourse is illustrative of the extent to which consumer dependency on fossil fuels for everyday products, cars and houses has been ingrained into American lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is required is a form of environmentalism which attempts to divest from consumerism and reorient production in a more self-sufficient direction, prioritising family farms over large, agricultural behemoths which, at present, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/2016/09/agriculture-ecology-food-justice-farmworkers-local-climate&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;control&lt;/a&gt; 67% of food supply despite making up less than 4% of all farms across the United States. Family farms currently supply just 26% of food despite making up 90% of all farming operations, due to the huge subsidies accrued by Big Agriculture, in addition to their vast economies of scale. Globally, family farms could double food production in ten years if given an opportunity, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.srfood.org/images/stories/pdf/officialreports/20110308_a-hrc-16-49_agroecology_en.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to a 2011 UN study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the United States from WWII as the predominant world power was catalysed by the rise of the petroleum industry alongside a powerful industrial sector and a neutralised labour force, bereft of militancy. In the decades since, the climate crisis that fossil fuels have been largely responsible for aggravating has necessitated a radical environmentalist agenda. Such a programme would entail challenging the basis of consumerism and the assumption that infinite, endogenous growth is necessarily beneficial for the economy, attempting to divest from the large factory farms that dominate the American economy, and expanding regenerative agriculture and pedestrianisation to eclipse the undifferentiated mass of suburbs which the petroleum industry required to assert its supremacy. This article has attempted to provide an insight into why these changes currently seem inimical to the way in which American society is organised at present, and to outline an alternative vision for the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tom Perrett</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">In April, Representative Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and US Senator Edward Markey pledged to reintroduce the Green New Deal, intended to enable divestment from fossil fuels, stimulate jobs in renewable industries, and spur the decarbonisation of America’s economy by 2050. An encouraging development within mainstream environmentalism, the Green New Deal commits to considerable levels of public investment in renewable energy and green infrastructure. However, like many social-democratic solutions to climate change, it is underpinned by a Keynesian assumption that technical fixes, rather than broader structural changes, are the key to solving political problems. Much of modern environmentalism is impeded by a naive technological utopianism that commits to elaborate spending plans on major green infrastructure projects, remaining oblivious to the fact that a broader reorganisation of society is required to reverse the effects of climate change. Spending millions of dollars on the rollout of electric vehicles does little to dissuade the use of cars, create cycle lanes, or to change the fact that vast swathes of America were designed to enable car usage. In fact, much of American society, from rampant consumerism to dependency on artificially enhanced food from chemical and agricultural corporations, is based around providing a consumer market for the products of the petroleum industry, which rose to prominence in the aftermath of World War II, securing both domestic and international success. To understand the extent to which American consumer capitalism has become inextricably linked with the power of petroleum, it is necessary to trace the emergence of the fossil fuel industry to the post-War era, in which the United States sought to dominate the world through the exertion of financial and military power.&amp;nbsp; American dominance in the post-war era involved achieving two aims which would safeguard the untrammelled might of the oil industry: firstly, the transition from a world economy based on coal to one based on oil, which would disintegrate organised labour and subjugate European powers to American hegemony via dependency on the dollar for ERP funds; secondly, a culture of consumerism based on constructing identical suburbs whose value was kept high by segregation and redlining, alongside widespread car ownership which necessitated a drastic change in the layout of America’s cities. The dollar would become the predominant global currency, in which the values of all other currencies were to be expressed, facilitating the construction of a geopolitical settlement based on the flow of Middle Eastern oil into European countries, who would buy the products of American petroleum companies using dollars. Though commonly misconstrued as an example of great power benevolence, in which the United States generously rebuilt the economies of Western Europe to ensure mutual peace and prosperity in the aftermath of history’s bloodiest conflict, the Marshall Plan prostrated European economies to American influence. Tim Mitchell, in his book Carbon Democracy, described the process whereby the militancy of coal miners was curtailed, and the reorientation of the global economic order took place. He wrote: “The corporatised democracy of postwar Western Europe was to be built on this reorganisation of energy flows. ERP funds helped pay for building oil refineries and installing oil-fired industrial boilers, putting in place the infrastructure needed to convert from coal to oil. The US encouraged the building of roads, gave ERP countries $432.5 million to purchase American vehicles, and subsidised Italian and French car manufacturers.” Between 1948 and 1951, more than half the oil sold to Western European countries by American companies was paid for by funds gained from the Marshall Plan. Companies such as Standard Oil and representatives of the Rockefeller family had lobbied Congress for the Marshall Plan to be approved, with the end goal being not to create prosperity, but to ensure dependency. Crucially, the switch from coal to oil had the advantage of changing the relationship between energy and labour. Previously, with coal-dominated economies, labour had been concentrated in certain areas, with economies of scale accruing around coal deposits, largely in Central Europe. But with the advent of oil, the atomisation of organised labour was made possible. Oil, unlike coal, could be extracted from the Earth using a relatively small workforce, supervised at close quarters. Pumping stations and pipelines, unlike railways, did not require overseers to constantly monitor production and transportation processes, meaning that it was far easier to neutralise the power of an otherwise militant labour force. To quote from Mitchell again: “In the case of oil, the capacity to slow down or interrupt the supply of energy on a large scale was much harder to organise. Oil workers found it difficult to carry out a successful sabotage — a difficulty that would impede their efforts to build with oil an enduring mechanism for advancing democratic political claims.” He also wrote: “Compared to carrying coal by rail, moving oil by sea eliminated the labour of coal heavers and stokers, and thus the power of organised workers to withdraw their labour from a critical point in the energy system.” The aftermath of World War II demonstrated the effectiveness of these tactics; not only was labour subordinated to capital by the Taft Hartley Act, which aimed to suppress ‘Communist’ infiltration alongside other draconian provisions, but a clear path to global American hegemony had been established. A wave of strikes had succeeded FDR’s New Deal; in 1945, 3.5 million workers took part in 4,750 strikes across the US, as General Motors, in addition to steel and electrical industries, witnessed a sustained period of labour militancy unrivalled in US history.&amp;nbsp; Therefore, the introduction of the Marshall Plan and conversion of the economy from coal to oil can be seen as part of a wider initiative to subdue workers’ autonomy, which also included buying off union leaders by offering pay increases in exchange for uninterrupted production and relative docility. The post-War era, despite being widely regarded as an era of high wage growth and untrammelled prosperity, in fact, according to Michael Yates, created “an ideologically loyal and industrially moderate labour movement, which bargained for concessions without challenging basic dispositions of a business society.” The emergence of the USA from the War as the world’s preeminent economic force carried with it the untrammelled power of the petroleum industry, in a domestic context, as well as internationally. American oil wells and refineries had supplied six out of every seven barrels of oil used by the Allies during WWII, and between 1948 and 1972, domestic oil consumption tripled from 5.8 to 16.4 million barrels per day. In a 1950 report, Conoco (The Continental Oil Company) told its shareholders that “the main contributing factor to the high level of business activity of the country was the continued high demand for housing and automobiles, two industries which vitally affect the consumption of petroleum products.” From 1947 until 1960, the motor and petroleum sectors produced one-third of all manufacturing expenditures. The booming automobile industry employed 19% of the total workforce, facilitating a considerable advancement in the material conditions of millions of Americans, but also necessitating a reorientation of the country’s topography; reaping the rewards of consumer capitalism would require the construction of neighbourhoods where car ownership was essential, and where cheap land and lax regulations could allow mass production of homes and goods to satiate the burgeoning appetite of affluent, white suburbia. Nuclear families living in suburbs required lawn mowers, fridges, furniture, and a host of other consumer goods available to the rising class of white, skilled workers, all of which cemented the power of petroleum. The structure of the suburbs, located away from cities where redlining prevented ethnic minorities from securing the capital or investment required to move into these areas, ensured the provision of a large-scale market for goods produced by fossil-fuel driven sectors. The domination of the new American suburbs by grotesque McMansions phased out public transport, ensuring that millions of Americans were dependent on cars for travel, and that roads and parking lots replaced rail and pedestrian infrastructure. For example, Lester Brown calculated in 2001 that the US had enough miles of road to encircle the Earth at the equator 157 times. According to author James Kunstler, the automobile boom that drove the construction of highways at the expense of public transportation was: “the greatest misallocation of resources in the history of the world.” This demonstrates that transformative action on climate change cannot merely involve spending on various projects likely to ameliorate fossil fuel emissions, but must involve a drastic re-thinking of why it is that the American economy and society are structured in the way that they are. Simply spending more on clean energy, while worthwhile in extricating the economy from dependency on fossil fuels, does little to incentivise decarbonisation. Rewilding and urban densification, with their potential to limit excess resource use and curtail mass dependency on cars, ought to be vital aspects of a genuinely transformative environmentalism. I mentioned at the beginning of this article that handing out vast subsidies to electric cars, which are often expensive and only available to a small number of consumers, will have a negligible impact on the climate in comparison to disincentivising private car ownership in general through the provision of cycle lanes and pedestrianisation. The fact that these alternatives, which include carbon capture and regenerative agriculture are largely sidelined in environmentalist discourse is illustrative of the extent to which consumer dependency on fossil fuels for everyday products, cars and houses has been ingrained into American lifestyles. What is required is a form of environmentalism which attempts to divest from consumerism and reorient production in a more self-sufficient direction, prioritising family farms over large, agricultural behemoths which, at present, control 67% of food supply despite making up less than 4% of all farms across the United States. Family farms currently supply just 26% of food despite making up 90% of all farming operations, due to the huge subsidies accrued by Big Agriculture, in addition to their vast economies of scale. Globally, family farms could double food production in ten years if given an opportunity, according to a 2011 UN study. The emergence of the United States from WWII as the predominant world power was catalysed by the rise of the petroleum industry alongside a powerful industrial sector and a neutralised labour force, bereft of militancy. In the decades since, the climate crisis that fossil fuels have been largely responsible for aggravating has necessitated a radical environmentalist agenda. Such a programme would entail challenging the basis of consumerism and the assumption that infinite, endogenous growth is necessarily beneficial for the economy, attempting to divest from the large factory farms that dominate the American economy, and expanding regenerative agriculture and pedestrianisation to eclipse the undifferentiated mass of suburbs which the petroleum industry required to assert its supremacy. This article has attempted to provide an insight into why these changes currently seem inimical to the way in which American society is organised at present, and to outline an alternative vision for the future.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Simple Good?</title><link href="/Is-simple-good" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Simple Good?" /><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Is-simple-good</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Is-simple-good">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When Netﬂix released its adventure interactive series ‘You vs Wild’ it left its viewers in a dilemma of choosing between a muddy swamp full of crocodiles and a turfy route traversed along by wild animals, one of which could be a potential life-saving course for the show’s host Bear Grylls, it saw its viewers’ brains work in wondrous ways to be able to make a decision in the blink of an eye.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As for viewers, they weren’t met with a life altering decision to make, but instead a gripping show that gave them the adrenaline rush with each passing course of action. Their decisions were based on a simpler question - I wonder what happens next. These viewers, in most cases, aren’t individuals who have or will ever go on a full-ﬂedged adventure; therefore, their decisions in the series are based out of whatever incomplete prior knowledge they have or out of sheer instinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The behaviour that our brain adapts to simplify the decision-making process is called heuristics. It is a shortcut that our brain mechanises to reach a reasonable decision under uncertainty and risk and especially when the perfect decision is unknowable or unreachable. It usually devises a method by which our brain substitutes a complex problem at hand with a simpler question, one which is readily answerable by the stakeholder. In our example, the viewers’ brains substituted the complex problem of saving Bear Grylls’ life with the simpler question: I wonder what happens next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Heuristics has multiple types, but narrowing it down to two broad categories gives us heuristics in terms of cognitive biases and intuition-based heuristics. Cognitive biases can be understood as the context in which an individual looks at a problem. The context could be anything: the way a problem was presented to the individual, prior judgement or perception of the individual acting as an anchor to their decision-making, peer inﬂuence, prior beliefs supported by ancillary evidence, or simply the brain retaining and believing the most recent piece of information, ignoring relevant facts and evidences in favour of or against the individual’s claimed decision. Cognitive biases aren’t necessarily ﬂaws because they depict the behavioural process an individual will adopt in incorporating the context and conditioning they come from.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An individual cannot be isolated from their context, and hence rationality should assume subjective cognitive capabilities playing their respective roles in determining an individual’s decision. As for intuition-based heuristics, they are simply the built-in or learned capacities of humans to approach a certain problem. For example, to catch a ball thrown at you, there’s an imminent risk on you and hence you use your sight and reﬂexes to catch or dodge the ball, instead of adopting the more complicated and time-taking method of ﬁnding out the trajectory of the ball mathematically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Post the behavioural economics revolution, which has transformed the way economics looks at how humans approach their own behaviours, it has become imperative for us to understand how this particular human psyche could be used as a problem-solving tactic on a macroeconomic canvas.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Heuristics are tools to reach beyond the shelves of customarily understanding. Using them to make good and reduce bad in our world is our job”&lt;/em&gt;, said Warren Weaver. The application of heuristics by ordinary individuals is well understood, however, practitioners, analysts and policy makers have for long associated with the traditional techniques of research, systems analysis and quantitative modelling for policy recommendations, which are often presumed to be understood by well-educated individuals, thereby making it highly complex and a depoliticised exercise, out of reach for common individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;More often than not, policymaking is embedded in quantitative techniques and formal analysis that sometimes fails to take into account the qualitative and abstract policy concepts which are not included as variables or parameters within a policy analysis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This stringent policy model framework tends to underemphasise certain errors or inadequately deﬁne a problem, therefore analysing the wrong problem or a problem which is analysable using formal methods. Policy analysis requires policymakers to be aware of and to incorporate the conditions and context an issue is arising from. Policy issues are deeply layered and solving them is a step-by-step procedure, one that is backed by data but also abstract concepts like conditioning, decision-making and other socio-economic factors. Such issues are solved by arriving at a consensus, which is the opposite of how traditional policymaking works. It essentially assumes the reactions to when a new policy or law is announced, without actually drawing a link between passing of the law and actual human behaviour, which is not as analytical in its approach to problems like professional policymakers and analysts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The essential goal of policymaking is not just problem solving but of problem ﬁnding and structuring it around the needs of people. Policymaking by professionals can adopt the approach of understanding and comprehending individual decision-making or to view decision-making as problem solving, which is largely determined by heuristics. This approach also poses another relevant question - why should the methods of problem solving and policy analysis be different at all?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The answer lies in a framework, which lies at the intersection of the existing methods and heuristics, an analysis which revises the existing policy making methods in constructive ways that incorporates human behaviour and then constructs a policy. The process of construction must incorporate ﬂexibility in criteria, variables and solutions and must devise alternatives and rank them in order of effectiveness. It must eliminate those alternatives that are unrealistic or unattainable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The policy should be such that it focuses on creating habits among individuals that become an accepted social norm over the course of time. Such accepted habits are constantly reinforced by the public themselves as a demonstrated cognitive behaviour. Certain examinations like Randomised Controlled Trials (RCTs) are a stepping stone towards incorporating behavioural insights into analysis, which ﬁnds itself at the intersection of formal methods and human behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Heuristic analysis has its value in its ability to improve decisions and in dissociating from stringent models and placing emphasis on individual behaviour and informed judgement. Policymaking can become a cognisant process with conscious efforts instead of complex methods becoming a constraint, for it affects the lives of people on a national scale. It addresses some limitations of traditional policy analysis, however it does come with its own set of limitations - lack of subjective knowledge or access to communities or social settings, lack of resources and time to conduct in-depth surveys, errors in judgement by the policy maker, etc. These can be dealt with on a structural level if a conclusive framework is organised.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishi Shrivastava</name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">When Netﬂix released its adventure interactive series ‘You vs Wild’ it left its viewers in a dilemma of choosing between a muddy swamp full of crocodiles and a turfy route traversed along by wild animals, one of which could be a potential life-saving course for the show’s host Bear Grylls, it saw its viewers’ brains work in wondrous ways to be able to make a decision in the blink of an eye.&amp;nbsp; As for viewers, they weren’t met with a life altering decision to make, but instead a gripping show that gave them the adrenaline rush with each passing course of action. Their decisions were based on a simpler question - I wonder what happens next. These viewers, in most cases, aren’t individuals who have or will ever go on a full-ﬂedged adventure; therefore, their decisions in the series are based out of whatever incomplete prior knowledge they have or out of sheer instinct. The behaviour that our brain adapts to simplify the decision-making process is called heuristics. It is a shortcut that our brain mechanises to reach a reasonable decision under uncertainty and risk and especially when the perfect decision is unknowable or unreachable. It usually devises a method by which our brain substitutes a complex problem at hand with a simpler question, one which is readily answerable by the stakeholder. In our example, the viewers’ brains substituted the complex problem of saving Bear Grylls’ life with the simpler question: I wonder what happens next? Heuristics has multiple types, but narrowing it down to two broad categories gives us heuristics in terms of cognitive biases and intuition-based heuristics. Cognitive biases can be understood as the context in which an individual looks at a problem. The context could be anything: the way a problem was presented to the individual, prior judgement or perception of the individual acting as an anchor to their decision-making, peer inﬂuence, prior beliefs supported by ancillary evidence, or simply the brain retaining and believing the most recent piece of information, ignoring relevant facts and evidences in favour of or against the individual’s claimed decision. Cognitive biases aren’t necessarily ﬂaws because they depict the behavioural process an individual will adopt in incorporating the context and conditioning they come from.&amp;nbsp; An individual cannot be isolated from their context, and hence rationality should assume subjective cognitive capabilities playing their respective roles in determining an individual’s decision. As for intuition-based heuristics, they are simply the built-in or learned capacities of humans to approach a certain problem. For example, to catch a ball thrown at you, there’s an imminent risk on you and hence you use your sight and reﬂexes to catch or dodge the ball, instead of adopting the more complicated and time-taking method of ﬁnding out the trajectory of the ball mathematically. Post the behavioural economics revolution, which has transformed the way economics looks at how humans approach their own behaviours, it has become imperative for us to understand how this particular human psyche could be used as a problem-solving tactic on a macroeconomic canvas.&amp;nbsp; “Heuristics are tools to reach beyond the shelves of customarily understanding. Using them to make good and reduce bad in our world is our job”, said Warren Weaver. The application of heuristics by ordinary individuals is well understood, however, practitioners, analysts and policy makers have for long associated with the traditional techniques of research, systems analysis and quantitative modelling for policy recommendations, which are often presumed to be understood by well-educated individuals, thereby making it highly complex and a depoliticised exercise, out of reach for common individuals. More often than not, policymaking is embedded in quantitative techniques and formal analysis that sometimes fails to take into account the qualitative and abstract policy concepts which are not included as variables or parameters within a policy analysis.&amp;nbsp; This stringent policy model framework tends to underemphasise certain errors or inadequately deﬁne a problem, therefore analysing the wrong problem or a problem which is analysable using formal methods. Policy analysis requires policymakers to be aware of and to incorporate the conditions and context an issue is arising from. Policy issues are deeply layered and solving them is a step-by-step procedure, one that is backed by data but also abstract concepts like conditioning, decision-making and other socio-economic factors. Such issues are solved by arriving at a consensus, which is the opposite of how traditional policymaking works. It essentially assumes the reactions to when a new policy or law is announced, without actually drawing a link between passing of the law and actual human behaviour, which is not as analytical in its approach to problems like professional policymakers and analysts. The essential goal of policymaking is not just problem solving but of problem ﬁnding and structuring it around the needs of people. Policymaking by professionals can adopt the approach of understanding and comprehending individual decision-making or to view decision-making as problem solving, which is largely determined by heuristics. This approach also poses another relevant question - why should the methods of problem solving and policy analysis be different at all?&amp;nbsp; The answer lies in a framework, which lies at the intersection of the existing methods and heuristics, an analysis which revises the existing policy making methods in constructive ways that incorporates human behaviour and then constructs a policy. The process of construction must incorporate ﬂexibility in criteria, variables and solutions and must devise alternatives and rank them in order of effectiveness. It must eliminate those alternatives that are unrealistic or unattainable.&amp;nbsp; The policy should be such that it focuses on creating habits among individuals that become an accepted social norm over the course of time. Such accepted habits are constantly reinforced by the public themselves as a demonstrated cognitive behaviour. Certain examinations like Randomised Controlled Trials (RCTs) are a stepping stone towards incorporating behavioural insights into analysis, which ﬁnds itself at the intersection of formal methods and human behaviour. Heuristic analysis has its value in its ability to improve decisions and in dissociating from stringent models and placing emphasis on individual behaviour and informed judgement. Policymaking can become a cognisant process with conscious efforts instead of complex methods becoming a constraint, for it affects the lives of people on a national scale. It addresses some limitations of traditional policy analysis, however it does come with its own set of limitations - lack of subjective knowledge or access to communities or social settings, lack of resources and time to conduct in-depth surveys, errors in judgement by the policy maker, etc. These can be dealt with on a structural level if a conclusive framework is organised.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Game of Musical Chairs at the Nepalese Parliament</title><link href="/A-Game-of-Musical-Chairs-at-the-Nepalese-Parliament" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Game of Musical Chairs at the Nepalese Parliament" /><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/A-Game-of-Musical-Chairs-at-the-Nepalese-Parliament</id><content type="html" xml:base="/A-Game-of-Musical-Chairs-at-the-Nepalese-Parliament">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The President has dissolved the House of Representatives and ordered the first phase of General Elections on November 12 and the second phase on November 19&lt;/em&gt;”, the President of Nepal Bidhya Devi Bhandari announced on May 22, 2021 as neither the caretaker Prime Minister K P Sharma Oli nor the opposition leader Sher Bahadur Deuba were able to demonstrate a majority in the floor of the Nepalese Parliament by the Presidential deadline of May 21.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The month-long political turmoil amidst a raging Covid pandemic reporting more than 8,000 infections on average, each day has further complicated the mandate. Its culmination has brought forth the domestic political upheaval of one of India's geographically and socio-politically relevant neighbours. It is said that the decision is nothing but a result of the cabinet headed by the caretaker Prime Minister K P Oli, whose December 2020 dissolution of the Parliament had ignited demonstrations and was later reversed by the Supreme Court as unconstitutional in February. Further, opposition leaders have questioned the legitimacy of Oli's recommendation as he himself had been unable to garner majority support in the Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Led to the Political Turmoil?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khadga Prasad Sharma Oli's Nepal Communist Party had won the Parliamentary elections in late 2017 and he was nominated by the Parliament to head the government as the Nepalese Prime Minister in early 2018. On May 13, K P Sharma Oli was reappointed as Prime Minister as the leader of the largest block with 121 seats in the House of Representatives after the opposition parties failed to form a government that would have required 136 seats. Oli was given 30 days to win a vote of confidence. The Nepali Congress on the other hand had 63 seats and the Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist Center) led by Oli's opponent Pushpa Kumar Dahal had 54 seats.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roots of the turmoil can be traced back to December 28, 2020, when Oli had, for the first time in his tenure, recommended dissolution of the lower Parliament and it was almost as if a mirror image of the events of May 2021, the President approved it promptly. It ended the left unity that had coalesced to form the Nepal Communist Party.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation was the culmination of a factional feud within the party. In February, Oli himself was expelled from the ruling Communist Party. The Maoist faction of the Nepal Communist Party was led by Prachanda. He had led the Maoist insurgency for a decade between 1996 to 2006 before joining mainstream politics. Oli was one of the primary critics of the Maoist political violence responsible for the death of 17,000 individuals. However, Oli had approached the Maoist faction in 2017 for a merger between their parties, preempting the possibility of an alliance between the Maoists and the Nepali Congress that would have come as a hindrance to Oli's prime ministerial ambitions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oli, who was then leading the Communist Party of Nepal (Unified Marxist Leninist), and Prachanda’ Maoist faction had agreed that they would lead the government by turn, however, the former turned his back upon the promise at the end of two-and-a-half years, thus sowing the seeds of a split. The Election Commission refused to recognise the split in the ruling party between the factions of the Prime Minister and that of Prachanda and Madhav Kumar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Future of the Constitution and the Army&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Nepal is no stranger to a dissolution of the Parliament, it was the first such instance after the adoption of the 2015 Constitution that had placed safeguards against such a dissolution. The guarantee is enshrined in the idea that the new Constitution does not envisage dissolution without exploring the possibility of forming an alternative government. The 1991 Constitution which was scrapped in 2006 contained provisions for dissolution of Parliament at the Prime Minister’s prerogative. It had witnessed three dissolutions during its period of operation. The first Parliament elected in 1991 was dissolved on the recommendation of Prime Minister G P Koirala after he had failed to have a vote of thanks motion by the King passed in the House. The Supreme Court had upheld that dissolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However in 1995, the Nepali Supreme Court had rejected the dissolution by Prime Minister Manmohan Adhikary after a no-trust motion had been tabled against him before the loss of majority was proved. The Court had advanced the argument that the executive did not have the jurisdiction over an issue under the purview of the legislature. In 2002, Prime Minister Sher Bahadur Deuba had dissolved the Parliament and the Supreme Court had upheld the verdict. The role of the army too was believed to be a crucial one in deciding the course of events. It had made it clear that they would remain neutral in the political developments in the Parliaments. This ensured that had Oli tried to rule with the help of security forces to maintain law and order and to curb dissent and the protesters, the army's support would be highly unlikely to be gained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roots of all this political instability and the fact that Nepal has since 1951 not witnessed a single government completing its full term may be attributed to four factors: the first being a fragmented polity as no political party is devoid of internal factions and the leadership is not in full control of its cadres. Secondly, political cronyism, nepotism, fragile political and constitutional institutions suffer from both the lack of democratic experience and guidance. The highly ambitious, intensely power-driven political leadership’s unwillingness to share power and the interfering role of external stakeholders and immediate neighbours including China have all contributed to the current upheaval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of all this on international relations equations is obviously significant. Hou Yanki, the Chinese Ambassador in Nepal made attempts at patching up the differences between Oli and his detractors to maintain the stability of the Communist Party of Nepal. After her failed endeavours, the four-member high powered delegation led by Guo Yezhou, Vice President of the Chinese Communist Party’s internal division visited Nepal last December.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Nepalese politics lie scrambled, many observers believe that the present crisis has opened up political space and given a fresh lease of life to previously redundant forces to reclaim their share in the power structure. Notable among them is the combination of Hindutva and the overthrown monarchy which had been staging massive demonstrations all over Kathmandu since January. Their primary demands include the revival of the monarchy and the creation of a Hindu state. As the current dissolution has been challenged in Court by five political parties including the Nepali Congress, Janata Samajwadi Party and several dissidents from Oli’s own UML Party, another faction of the JSP led by Madhesi leader Mahanta Thakur has extended his support to Oli in return for seven ministerial berths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains to be seen as to who wins the game of musical chairs at the Nepalese Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name></author><category term="policy" /><summary type="html">“The President has dissolved the House of Representatives and ordered the first phase of General Elections on November 12 and the second phase on November 19”, the President of Nepal Bidhya Devi Bhandari announced on May 22, 2021 as neither the caretaker Prime Minister K P Sharma Oli nor the opposition leader Sher Bahadur Deuba were able to demonstrate a majority in the floor of the Nepalese Parliament by the Presidential deadline of May 21.&amp;nbsp; The month-long political turmoil amidst a raging Covid pandemic reporting more than 8,000 infections on average, each day has further complicated the mandate. Its culmination has brought forth the domestic political upheaval of one of India's geographically and socio-politically relevant neighbours. It is said that the decision is nothing but a result of the cabinet headed by the caretaker Prime Minister K P Oli, whose December 2020 dissolution of the Parliament had ignited demonstrations and was later reversed by the Supreme Court as unconstitutional in February. Further, opposition leaders have questioned the legitimacy of Oli's recommendation as he himself had been unable to garner majority support in the Parliament. What Led to the Political Turmoil? Khadga Prasad Sharma Oli's Nepal Communist Party had won the Parliamentary elections in late 2017 and he was nominated by the Parliament to head the government as the Nepalese Prime Minister in early 2018. On May 13, K P Sharma Oli was reappointed as Prime Minister as the leader of the largest block with 121 seats in the House of Representatives after the opposition parties failed to form a government that would have required 136 seats. Oli was given 30 days to win a vote of confidence. The Nepali Congress on the other hand had 63 seats and the Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist Center) led by Oli's opponent Pushpa Kumar Dahal had 54 seats.&amp;nbsp; The roots of the turmoil can be traced back to December 28, 2020, when Oli had, for the first time in his tenure, recommended dissolution of the lower Parliament and it was almost as if a mirror image of the events of May 2021, the President approved it promptly. It ended the left unity that had coalesced to form the Nepal Communist Party.&amp;nbsp; The situation was the culmination of a factional feud within the party. In February, Oli himself was expelled from the ruling Communist Party. The Maoist faction of the Nepal Communist Party was led by Prachanda. He had led the Maoist insurgency for a decade between 1996 to 2006 before joining mainstream politics. Oli was one of the primary critics of the Maoist political violence responsible for the death of 17,000 individuals. However, Oli had approached the Maoist faction in 2017 for a merger between their parties, preempting the possibility of an alliance between the Maoists and the Nepali Congress that would have come as a hindrance to Oli's prime ministerial ambitions.&amp;nbsp; Oli, who was then leading the Communist Party of Nepal (Unified Marxist Leninist), and Prachanda’ Maoist faction had agreed that they would lead the government by turn, however, the former turned his back upon the promise at the end of two-and-a-half years, thus sowing the seeds of a split. The Election Commission refused to recognise the split in the ruling party between the factions of the Prime Minister and that of Prachanda and Madhav Kumar. The Future of the Constitution and the Army While Nepal is no stranger to a dissolution of the Parliament, it was the first such instance after the adoption of the 2015 Constitution that had placed safeguards against such a dissolution. The guarantee is enshrined in the idea that the new Constitution does not envisage dissolution without exploring the possibility of forming an alternative government. The 1991 Constitution which was scrapped in 2006 contained provisions for dissolution of Parliament at the Prime Minister’s prerogative. It had witnessed three dissolutions during its period of operation. The first Parliament elected in 1991 was dissolved on the recommendation of Prime Minister G P Koirala after he had failed to have a vote of thanks motion by the King passed in the House. The Supreme Court had upheld that dissolution. However in 1995, the Nepali Supreme Court had rejected the dissolution by Prime Minister Manmohan Adhikary after a no-trust motion had been tabled against him before the loss of majority was proved. The Court had advanced the argument that the executive did not have the jurisdiction over an issue under the purview of the legislature. In 2002, Prime Minister Sher Bahadur Deuba had dissolved the Parliament and the Supreme Court had upheld the verdict. The role of the army too was believed to be a crucial one in deciding the course of events. It had made it clear that they would remain neutral in the political developments in the Parliaments. This ensured that had Oli tried to rule with the help of security forces to maintain law and order and to curb dissent and the protesters, the army's support would be highly unlikely to be gained. The Way Ahead The roots of all this political instability and the fact that Nepal has since 1951 not witnessed a single government completing its full term may be attributed to four factors: the first being a fragmented polity as no political party is devoid of internal factions and the leadership is not in full control of its cadres. Secondly, political cronyism, nepotism, fragile political and constitutional institutions suffer from both the lack of democratic experience and guidance. The highly ambitious, intensely power-driven political leadership’s unwillingness to share power and the interfering role of external stakeholders and immediate neighbours including China have all contributed to the current upheaval. The impact of all this on international relations equations is obviously significant. Hou Yanki, the Chinese Ambassador in Nepal made attempts at patching up the differences between Oli and his detractors to maintain the stability of the Communist Party of Nepal. After her failed endeavours, the four-member high powered delegation led by Guo Yezhou, Vice President of the Chinese Communist Party’s internal division visited Nepal last December.&amp;nbsp; As Nepalese politics lie scrambled, many observers believe that the present crisis has opened up political space and given a fresh lease of life to previously redundant forces to reclaim their share in the power structure. Notable among them is the combination of Hindutva and the overthrown monarchy which had been staging massive demonstrations all over Kathmandu since January. Their primary demands include the revival of the monarchy and the creation of a Hindu state. As the current dissolution has been challenged in Court by five political parties including the Nepali Congress, Janata Samajwadi Party and several dissidents from Oli’s own UML Party, another faction of the JSP led by Madhesi leader Mahanta Thakur has extended his support to Oli in return for seven ministerial berths. It remains to be seen as to who wins the game of musical chairs at the Nepalese Parliament.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coach - The Success Story</title><link href="/Coach-The-Success-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coach - The Success Story" /><published>2021-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/Coach-The-Success-Story</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Coach-The-Success-Story">&lt;p&gt;'Classic American Style', the style embodied by Coach, has defined its soul and essence for over 80 years now. In these 80 years, the brand transitioned from a small family business based in a New York loft to an international company with worldwide sales of $600 million in 2001. Today, Coach, Inc has carved a niche for itself as one of the leading modern luxury lifestyle brands providing various merchandise characterised by authenticity and distinctiveness that define its consumers' way of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1941, the company started with just six leather workers who produced small leather goods like wallets and billfolds. Five years later, Miles Cahn, a New Yorker and his wife joined the company. He saw that the leather used in baseball gloves became soft and supple with wear and abrasion. So he devised a way of processing the leather, which made it wear-and-tear resistant and long-lasting. At the same time, his wife started producing women's handbags with such innovative techniques that marked the brand's entry into manufacturing, designing and marketing of leather goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From its inception, Coach adopted a business strategy of producing timeless and elegant pieces which would not be affected by the vagaries of fashion. As a result, its goods were identified with artistic craftsmanship and sophisticated designs rather than being fashionable. Despite staying away from fashion fads, what built the brand reputation and set it apart from its competitors was that it offered sturdy and functional handbags of supreme quality that could last for an average of 15 years.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, Coach provided lifetime repairs and replacement services for its products without any additional costs. This helped in its unique positioning in the luxury market as an 'accessible luxury brand'. Coach's products were known for their exquisite quality but were priced lower than other designer products. It attracted people from both the higher and middle end of the wealth spectrum by adopting a mid-premium pricing strategy. This strategy allowed the brand to maintain its exclusivity and, at the same time, kept its door open for further sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things were going well for the brand until the 1990's. Then, it encountered a bottleneck in development that restricted it from building a unique brand image when every brand was adopting aggressive advertising and promotional policies. This was also the era of ushering in new competitor brands like Michael Kors and Kate Spade, which completely transformed the market scene. Michael Kors had a similar brand position as Coach, but it found that affordable luxury was a rage in China. As a result, Kors diversified its product line and customised its products to suit the Chinese demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kate Spade targeted millennials by designing chic and contemporary accessories. However, Coach was not ready to handle such cut-throat competition, due to which it lost almost 30% of its market share. So Coach introduced its first non-leather product, silk scarves, to soften the blow to its earnings. However, this proved disastrous since the equestrian designs on the scarves looked like a cheaper version of the Hermes scarves. This left the company more miserable than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to plummeting sales, Coach had launched discount stores and factory outlet stores, which boosted its performance quickly, but did not address the real product issues that eventually diluted the brand image. This was at the beginning of 2008.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach's 'affordable luxury' position, which elevated the brand from niche to powerhouse, was no longer influential because of the negative influence of the competitors and customers on the market environment. According to a survey taken in 2009, only 30% of the customers had a positive feeling for Coach. Consumers felt that it was no longer fashionable and that there were better alternatives available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the brand had lagged behind its competitors in the 'trendiness' dimension because it targeted older women who prioritise quality over fashion. As a result, the brand became regarded as a brand for the masses attracted to gaudy handbags. Coach was also responsible for the rising phenomenon of 'the death of the designer bags'. Since it kept its prices lower to attract a larger audience, nearly every rich woman had one of its bags which tarnished its exclusive image. For a luxury brand, if a product is not precious and scarce enough, there is no meaning in associating with the brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company carried on its operations in losses for a few years till it could continue no further.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Victor Luis took the reins as CEO and hired the new creative head Stuart Vevers. They carried out a series of successful revolutions to revive the company and rejuvenate its image to rebuild a high-end brand and win customers' favour. He repositioned the brand as a smaller, healthier retailer, putting the onus on quality and not on mass-market quantity and rebranded Coach to be 'Modern Luxury' which meant that the brand was inclusive and more approachable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luis allocated a significant chunk of the brand's budget on opening up new plush flagship stores in various fashion capitals and spruced up their store milieu to provide a better shopping experience. Stuart brought fresh blood to the organisation and revamped the brand's image by infusing traditional designs with his innovative ones which helped attract millennials. In addition, Coach diversified the product lines and started making ready-to-wear collections. Although clothing was a small part of Coach's revenue, its influence on the brand went far beyond the dollar terms, for it helped to develop the 'halo effect', that is, it helped to reshape the brand's aura, which gave a whole new lease of life to the entire product line.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2015, the US had started evolving as a fan economy, and social media had gained tremendous popularity. The new generation of consumers loved to use social media to catch up with trends and follow the celebrities they loved. A survey in 2015 found that 33% of the consumers were lured by social media promotions to splurge on big brands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Coach decided to resuscitate its online presence and hired Selena Gomez, the US pop singer, to represent the brand from 2016. She was the highest-paid celebrity on Instagram, and Coach took advantage of her social media power to appeal to the millennials. For example, when Coach announced the launch of a new handbag in collaboration with Selena, it sold out within a month. In 2017, Coach acquired Kate Spade to tap into a broader millennial-driven customer base and develop into a luxury lifestyle brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This acquisition pushed Coach in a better position to compete with Michael Kors. After four years of efforts, Coach has finally rebranded as a modern luxury brand thanks to the series of radical initiatives launched by Victor Luis and several incomparable products rebuilt by Stuart Vevers. By this time, Coach became the biggest story in the retail sector riding the handbag fascination. It helped propel sales into billions.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Coach represents a unique combination of magic and logic, representing rich cultural heritage and a truly aspirational and distinctive American style. The brand maintains the highest standard for materials and artistry. Its labour is committed to carefully upholding the principles of quality and integrity that defines the company. The strategy of moving beyond tangible products to own a larger share of customers' minds has proved to be an excellent defence against the volatile market and consumers' changing needs. The brand seeks to establish long-term relationships with customers based on loyalty and satisfaction, which also helps in the automatic adoption of new products upon release.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The products are made from genuine leather and undergo strict research checking before being launched in the consumer market. Coach has a strong distribution network and has adopted both direct and indirect channels to distribute products. The company shares fashion runway videos via streaming platforms like YouTube to create a positive buzz.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand believes in celebrity endorsements and advertises its products using Bohemian imagery in magazines and billboards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach has also adopted a promotional pricing strategy wherein it offers incentives, and on the arrival of new stock, the company puts the older stock for a clearance sale. It has an official website that handles sales and caters to customers' queries in more than 20 countries. However, their website does not have visualisation apps and suitable size guides. They need to keep it updated and try to list all their products on their online shop. Besides this, Coach actively engages in corporate social responsibility by supporting organisations that provide women's education.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach should now focus on expansion, especially in emerging prosperous economies like Latin America, Japan and India. It needs to ship to more countries, especially those that do not levy consumer taxes on foreign online shopping. It has become a famous brand among men who are willing to spend liberal amounts on fashion products.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It needs to live up to their expectations and meet their demands. It should also improve the technological content of its products to prevent counterfeiting of its products. Apart from this, the brand should invest more in eye-catching and stimulating commercials and print advertisements. Coach needs to reinvigorate its brand image and keep up with new trends without losing the original touch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abhinav Gupta</name></author><category term="business-finance" /><summary type="html">'Classic American Style', the style embodied by Coach, has defined its soul and essence for over 80 years now. In these 80 years, the brand transitioned from a small family business based in a New York loft to an international company with worldwide sales of $600 million in 2001. Today, Coach, Inc has carved a niche for itself as one of the leading modern luxury lifestyle brands providing various merchandise characterised by authenticity and distinctiveness that define its consumers' way of life. In 1941, the company started with just six leather workers who produced small leather goods like wallets and billfolds. Five years later, Miles Cahn, a New Yorker and his wife joined the company. He saw that the leather used in baseball gloves became soft and supple with wear and abrasion. So he devised a way of processing the leather, which made it wear-and-tear resistant and long-lasting. At the same time, his wife started producing women's handbags with such innovative techniques that marked the brand's entry into manufacturing, designing and marketing of leather goods. From its inception, Coach adopted a business strategy of producing timeless and elegant pieces which would not be affected by the vagaries of fashion. As a result, its goods were identified with artistic craftsmanship and sophisticated designs rather than being fashionable. Despite staying away from fashion fads, what built the brand reputation and set it apart from its competitors was that it offered sturdy and functional handbags of supreme quality that could last for an average of 15 years.&amp;nbsp; In addition, Coach provided lifetime repairs and replacement services for its products without any additional costs. This helped in its unique positioning in the luxury market as an 'accessible luxury brand'. Coach's products were known for their exquisite quality but were priced lower than other designer products. It attracted people from both the higher and middle end of the wealth spectrum by adopting a mid-premium pricing strategy. This strategy allowed the brand to maintain its exclusivity and, at the same time, kept its door open for further sales.&amp;nbsp; Things were going well for the brand until the 1990's. Then, it encountered a bottleneck in development that restricted it from building a unique brand image when every brand was adopting aggressive advertising and promotional policies. This was also the era of ushering in new competitor brands like Michael Kors and Kate Spade, which completely transformed the market scene. Michael Kors had a similar brand position as Coach, but it found that affordable luxury was a rage in China. As a result, Kors diversified its product line and customised its products to suit the Chinese demand. Kate Spade targeted millennials by designing chic and contemporary accessories. However, Coach was not ready to handle such cut-throat competition, due to which it lost almost 30% of its market share. So Coach introduced its first non-leather product, silk scarves, to soften the blow to its earnings. However, this proved disastrous since the equestrian designs on the scarves looked like a cheaper version of the Hermes scarves. This left the company more miserable than ever. Due to plummeting sales, Coach had launched discount stores and factory outlet stores, which boosted its performance quickly, but did not address the real product issues that eventually diluted the brand image. This was at the beginning of 2008.&amp;nbsp; Coach's 'affordable luxury' position, which elevated the brand from niche to powerhouse, was no longer influential because of the negative influence of the competitors and customers on the market environment. According to a survey taken in 2009, only 30% of the customers had a positive feeling for Coach. Consumers felt that it was no longer fashionable and that there were better alternatives available. Furthermore, the brand had lagged behind its competitors in the 'trendiness' dimension because it targeted older women who prioritise quality over fashion. As a result, the brand became regarded as a brand for the masses attracted to gaudy handbags. Coach was also responsible for the rising phenomenon of 'the death of the designer bags'. Since it kept its prices lower to attract a larger audience, nearly every rich woman had one of its bags which tarnished its exclusive image. For a luxury brand, if a product is not precious and scarce enough, there is no meaning in associating with the brand.&amp;nbsp; The company carried on its operations in losses for a few years till it could continue no further.&amp;nbsp; In 2014, Victor Luis took the reins as CEO and hired the new creative head Stuart Vevers. They carried out a series of successful revolutions to revive the company and rejuvenate its image to rebuild a high-end brand and win customers' favour. He repositioned the brand as a smaller, healthier retailer, putting the onus on quality and not on mass-market quantity and rebranded Coach to be 'Modern Luxury' which meant that the brand was inclusive and more approachable.&amp;nbsp; Luis allocated a significant chunk of the brand's budget on opening up new plush flagship stores in various fashion capitals and spruced up their store milieu to provide a better shopping experience. Stuart brought fresh blood to the organisation and revamped the brand's image by infusing traditional designs with his innovative ones which helped attract millennials. In addition, Coach diversified the product lines and started making ready-to-wear collections. Although clothing was a small part of Coach's revenue, its influence on the brand went far beyond the dollar terms, for it helped to develop the 'halo effect', that is, it helped to reshape the brand's aura, which gave a whole new lease of life to the entire product line.&amp;nbsp; By 2015, the US had started evolving as a fan economy, and social media had gained tremendous popularity. The new generation of consumers loved to use social media to catch up with trends and follow the celebrities they loved. A survey in 2015 found that 33% of the consumers were lured by social media promotions to splurge on big brands.&amp;nbsp; So Coach decided to resuscitate its online presence and hired Selena Gomez, the US pop singer, to represent the brand from 2016. She was the highest-paid celebrity on Instagram, and Coach took advantage of her social media power to appeal to the millennials. For example, when Coach announced the launch of a new handbag in collaboration with Selena, it sold out within a month. In 2017, Coach acquired Kate Spade to tap into a broader millennial-driven customer base and develop into a luxury lifestyle brand.&amp;nbsp; This acquisition pushed Coach in a better position to compete with Michael Kors. After four years of efforts, Coach has finally rebranded as a modern luxury brand thanks to the series of radical initiatives launched by Victor Luis and several incomparable products rebuilt by Stuart Vevers. By this time, Coach became the biggest story in the retail sector riding the handbag fascination. It helped propel sales into billions.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Today, Coach represents a unique combination of magic and logic, representing rich cultural heritage and a truly aspirational and distinctive American style. The brand maintains the highest standard for materials and artistry. Its labour is committed to carefully upholding the principles of quality and integrity that defines the company. The strategy of moving beyond tangible products to own a larger share of customers' minds has proved to be an excellent defence against the volatile market and consumers' changing needs. The brand seeks to establish long-term relationships with customers based on loyalty and satisfaction, which also helps in the automatic adoption of new products upon release.&amp;nbsp; The products are made from genuine leather and undergo strict research checking before being launched in the consumer market. Coach has a strong distribution network and has adopted both direct and indirect channels to distribute products. The company shares fashion runway videos via streaming platforms like YouTube to create a positive buzz.&amp;nbsp; The brand believes in celebrity endorsements and advertises its products using Bohemian imagery in magazines and billboards.&amp;nbsp; Coach has also adopted a promotional pricing strategy wherein it offers incentives, and on the arrival of new stock, the company puts the older stock for a clearance sale. It has an official website that handles sales and caters to customers' queries in more than 20 countries. However, their website does not have visualisation apps and suitable size guides. They need to keep it updated and try to list all their products on their online shop. Besides this, Coach actively engages in corporate social responsibility by supporting organisations that provide women's education.&amp;nbsp; Coach should now focus on expansion, especially in emerging prosperous economies like Latin America, Japan and India. It needs to ship to more countries, especially those that do not levy consumer taxes on foreign online shopping. It has become a famous brand among men who are willing to spend liberal amounts on fashion products.&amp;nbsp; It needs to live up to their expectations and meet their demands. It should also improve the technological content of its products to prevent counterfeiting of its products. Apart from this, the brand should invest more in eye-catching and stimulating commercials and print advertisements. Coach needs to reinvigorate its brand image and keep up with new trends without losing the original touch.</summary></entry></feed>