<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/samakshi.garg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-10-28T17:29:17+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/samakshi.garg/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What is Your Ideal Brand Doing for Your ‘Pride’?</title>
      <link href="/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Your Ideal Brand Doing for Your ‘Pride’?" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride">&lt;p&gt;Each year, in the summertime, Pride collections emerge like a swarm of vividly coloured locusts. They envelop every storefront and Instagram feed in June, promising solidarity for LGBTQ+ communities. In 2021, we are yet again observing the second virtual celebration of pride month. Numerous brands have leveraged pride marketing to increase visibility and lend support to others within the LGBTQ+ community who are still exploring their identities. However, brands tend to forget the existence of the community as soon as July rolls on. It makes us question, is this just another marketing gimmick?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is customary for Pride-themed merchandise to spike during June, a practice known as rainbow capitalism, is often criticised and compared to pinkwashing. Nevertheless, there is still tremendous value that can come from rocking rainbows during this time of the year. Like ‘empowerment campaigns’, several brands climb the trend wagon in Pride month, with no concern for the cause. Pride marketing is empathetic, where aiming ‘just for sales’ will misfire and attract more backlash from the audience and hurt the entity's image in the long term. Therefore, brands should not use Pride month to ramp up the sales but instead use their platform to show support and disperse awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Burger King's Pride month initiative was very thoughtful and won many hearts. Their tagline stated, &quot;&lt;em&gt;The pride is on you. The parade is on us&lt;/em&gt;&quot;, along with their delivery vehicles transformed. The campaign persisted till July 5. This year, diverse brands showcased their support to the community beyond rainbow washing and making the most out of pride marketing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Popular brands like Fossil, Apple, Reebok and others often dedicate enormous resources during Pride month to LGBTQ+ non-profit organisations (among them,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thetrevorproject.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Trevor Project&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glsen.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GLSEN&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and different groups), which means you could be helping others gain access to valuable resources, too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To honour Pride month, Fossil launched its all-new limited-edition Pride collection to celebrate the spirit of love, equality and the very essence of individuality. The proceeds from this collection will benefit The Trevor Project — the world’s most significant suicide prevention and crisis intervention organisation for LGBTQ+ young adults.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Apple, it has released two new Apple Watch Pride bands this year and a new Pride watch face for users. The brand also supports many LGBTQ+ advocacy organisations, including&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://encircletogether.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Encircle&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(which offers safe spaces for LGBTQ+ youth, young adults and families), the&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://transequality.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Center for Transgender Equality&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(committed to social justice advocacy for transgender humans), and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add on, Reebok’s newest collection celebrating the LGBTQ+ community features a vibrant assortment of Pride-inspired footwear and apparel. The items were designed by Colorful Soles, the brand’s LGBTQ+ employee community, which also partnered with the legendary House of Ninja (spotlighted in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reviewed.com/streaming/features/black-history-documentaries-stream-now&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iconic documentary&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paris is Burning&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, Reebok is donating $75,000 to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://srlp.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sylvia Rivera Law Project&lt;/a&gt;, which advocates for affirming access to social, health and legal services for persons of all gender identities and expressions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the bargain, loads of fashion and beauty brands create Pride-inspired products that not only help you look great but also feel good as they support organisations that empower and uplift LGBTQ+ communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give some instances, the Gap Collective Pride collection includes T-shirts, hoodies, socks and more for all ages. The brand is donating $50,000 this season to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glaad.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD)&lt;/a&gt;, an LGBTQ media advocacy organization.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levi's is flaunting the Pride collection &quot;All Pronouns. All Love&quot; by emphasising respect for people's pronouns. They have the inscribed phrase &quot;they/them, she/her, he/him, we&quot; on their collections, which is gender-neutral. It will be donating 100% of the profits to OutRight Action International.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NYX's limited-edition collection comprises a wide makeup range that will bring a colourful ultra-metallic sheen. It will also donate $100,000 to Pride efforts globally and contribute towards the LA LGBT Center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other brands are also making their Pride-themed offerings and donations a year-round initiative, including Happy Socks, donating 10% of the sales from its rainbow-coloured socks to InterPride throughout the year, and Pink, which has expanded its offerings with its gender-inclusive Pink for All collection that debuted earlier this year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next door, LEGO has launched a limited-edition&amp;nbsp;LGBTQ themed set. This is the first LGBTQ set with 11 monochromatic figures, each with an assigned colour and 346 pieces creating a rainbow cascade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, TGI Fridays have introduced a decadent, delicious dessert. This dessert is six layers of rainbow-coloured vanilla cake piled high with vanilla icing and sprinkles and is available for home delivery and in-store locations. Part of the profits generated from the sales will be donated to support GLSEN&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many music platforms in India, like music streaming service Jio Saavan and Spotify, and music channel VH1 are also celebrating Pride Month.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other brands, Skittles took a bold move of launching limited-edition&amp;nbsp;Skittles Pride Packs&amp;nbsp;that come in grey packaging rather than rainbow washing. Even the candies inside are grey with delicious strawberries, orange, grape, apple, and lemon. For every pack sold, $1 will be donated to GLAAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shira Kogan, Director of Corporate Development at The Trevor Project, said &lt;em&gt;&quot;We are thrilled to see so many companies and brands stepping up to support Pride this year.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; Well, it is true that brands have the power and platform to influence others. These brands can tell stories to empower the LGBTQ+ community through marketing campaigns or a separate product line. Together they can create a world where the LGBTQ+ community is championed, celebrated and protected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that consumers of Pride gear are becoming more aware and are making an effort to shop where proceeds will make the most significant impact, including shopping at small, queer-owned businesses. For example, consumers are taking note when companies only feature underrepresented groups during their respective history or heritage months, says Ali Fazal, Vice President of Marketing at influencer marketing platform&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://grin.co/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GRIN&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&quot;(If) the only time they see LGBT people represented is during Pride Month, it's clear that what you're doing is not a long-term evolution for your company and your marketing.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; says Fazal.&lt;em&gt;&quot;You're just trying to capitalize upon the seasonality of that month.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's be honest: Most major brands have not maintained a consistent enough relationship with LGBTQ+ communities to survive Pride month without some level of scrutiny. More often than not, ‘rainbow washing’ — that is, the act of deploying Pride-themed versions of their products and marketing it without substantially engaging queer communities — tends to be the minimal-effort route that multiple brands take and majority of consumers recognise these attempts as inauthentic almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's never too late to start developing real bonds with LGBTQ+ consumers. One of the most effective ways to show support is through charitable efforts, and Pride offers brands ample opportunities to turn their specialised products into the support that resonates beyond June.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a recent analysis, queer consumers who tend to maintain higher median household incomes, are more likely than other marginalised groups to actively seek and patronise the companies that engage with their collective community in a sustained fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, some brands understand the lasting power of giving back. It is important to remember the message one leaves out there can help lay the foundation of change. We need to understand that equality is not a once-a-month fight, but year-round support is necessary — not just for Pride month, but all the social causes we rise for. Together we can create a world, which is fairer for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Each year, in the summertime, Pride collections emerge like a swarm of vividly coloured locusts. They envelop every storefront and Instagram feed in June, promising solidarity for LGBTQ+ communities. In 2021, we are yet again observing the second virtual celebration of pride month. Numerous brands have leveraged pride marketing to increase visibility and lend support to others within the LGBTQ+ community who are still exploring their identities. However, brands tend to forget the existence of the community as soon as July rolls on. It makes us question, is this just another marketing gimmick? While it is customary for Pride-themed merchandise to spike during June, a practice known as rainbow capitalism, is often criticised and compared to pinkwashing. Nevertheless, there is still tremendous value that can come from rocking rainbows during this time of the year. Like ‘empowerment campaigns’, several brands climb the trend wagon in Pride month, with no concern for the cause. Pride marketing is empathetic, where aiming ‘just for sales’ will misfire and attract more backlash from the audience and hurt the entity's image in the long term. Therefore, brands should not use Pride month to ramp up the sales but instead use their platform to show support and disperse awareness. In 2020, Burger King's Pride month initiative was very thoughtful and won many hearts. Their tagline stated, &quot;The pride is on you. The parade is on us&quot;, along with their delivery vehicles transformed. The campaign persisted till July 5. This year, diverse brands showcased their support to the community beyond rainbow washing and making the most out of pride marketing.&amp;nbsp; Popular brands like Fossil, Apple, Reebok and others often dedicate enormous resources during Pride month to LGBTQ+ non-profit organisations (among them,&amp;nbsp;The Trevor Project,&amp;nbsp;GLSEN&amp;nbsp;and different groups), which means you could be helping others gain access to valuable resources, too.&amp;nbsp; To honour Pride month, Fossil launched its all-new limited-edition Pride collection to celebrate the spirit of love, equality and the very essence of individuality. The proceeds from this collection will benefit The Trevor Project — the world’s most significant suicide prevention and crisis intervention organisation for LGBTQ+ young adults.&amp;nbsp; In the case of Apple, it has released two new Apple Watch Pride bands this year and a new Pride watch face for users. The brand also supports many LGBTQ+ advocacy organisations, including&amp;nbsp;Encircle&amp;nbsp;(which offers safe spaces for LGBTQ+ youth, young adults and families), the&amp;nbsp;National Center for Transgender Equality&amp;nbsp;(committed to social justice advocacy for transgender humans), and others. To add on, Reebok’s newest collection celebrating the LGBTQ+ community features a vibrant assortment of Pride-inspired footwear and apparel. The items were designed by Colorful Soles, the brand’s LGBTQ+ employee community, which also partnered with the legendary House of Ninja (spotlighted in the&amp;nbsp;iconic documentary,&amp;nbsp;Paris is Burning). Moreover, Reebok is donating $75,000 to the&amp;nbsp;Sylvia Rivera Law Project, which advocates for affirming access to social, health and legal services for persons of all gender identities and expressions.&amp;nbsp; Into the bargain, loads of fashion and beauty brands create Pride-inspired products that not only help you look great but also feel good as they support organisations that empower and uplift LGBTQ+ communities.&amp;nbsp; To give some instances, the Gap Collective Pride collection includes T-shirts, hoodies, socks and more for all ages. The brand is donating $50,000 this season to the&amp;nbsp;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), an LGBTQ media advocacy organization.&amp;nbsp; Levi's is flaunting the Pride collection &quot;All Pronouns. All Love&quot; by emphasising respect for people's pronouns. They have the inscribed phrase &quot;they/them, she/her, he/him, we&quot; on their collections, which is gender-neutral. It will be donating 100% of the profits to OutRight Action International.&amp;nbsp; NYX's limited-edition collection comprises a wide makeup range that will bring a colourful ultra-metallic sheen. It will also donate $100,000 to Pride efforts globally and contribute towards the LA LGBT Center. Other brands are also making their Pride-themed offerings and donations a year-round initiative, including Happy Socks, donating 10% of the sales from its rainbow-coloured socks to InterPride throughout the year, and Pink, which has expanded its offerings with its gender-inclusive Pink for All collection that debuted earlier this year.&amp;nbsp; Next door, LEGO has launched a limited-edition&amp;nbsp;LGBTQ themed set. This is the first LGBTQ set with 11 monochromatic figures, each with an assigned colour and 346 pieces creating a rainbow cascade.&amp;nbsp; Meanwhile, TGI Fridays have introduced a decadent, delicious dessert. This dessert is six layers of rainbow-coloured vanilla cake piled high with vanilla icing and sprinkles and is available for home delivery and in-store locations. Part of the profits generated from the sales will be donated to support GLSEN.&amp;nbsp; Many music platforms in India, like music streaming service Jio Saavan and Spotify, and music channel VH1 are also celebrating Pride Month.&amp;nbsp; Unlike other brands, Skittles took a bold move of launching limited-edition&amp;nbsp;Skittles Pride Packs&amp;nbsp;that come in grey packaging rather than rainbow washing. Even the candies inside are grey with delicious strawberries, orange, grape, apple, and lemon. For every pack sold, $1 will be donated to GLAAD. Shira Kogan, Director of Corporate Development at The Trevor Project, said &quot;We are thrilled to see so many companies and brands stepping up to support Pride this year.&quot; Well, it is true that brands have the power and platform to influence others. These brands can tell stories to empower the LGBTQ+ community through marketing campaigns or a separate product line. Together they can create a world where the LGBTQ+ community is championed, celebrated and protected.&amp;nbsp; The result is that consumers of Pride gear are becoming more aware and are making an effort to shop where proceeds will make the most significant impact, including shopping at small, queer-owned businesses. For example, consumers are taking note when companies only feature underrepresented groups during their respective history or heritage months, says Ali Fazal, Vice President of Marketing at influencer marketing platform&amp;nbsp;GRIN. &quot;(If) the only time they see LGBT people represented is during Pride Month, it's clear that what you're doing is not a long-term evolution for your company and your marketing.&quot; says Fazal.&quot;You're just trying to capitalize upon the seasonality of that month.&quot; Now let's be honest: Most major brands have not maintained a consistent enough relationship with LGBTQ+ communities to survive Pride month without some level of scrutiny. More often than not, ‘rainbow washing’ — that is, the act of deploying Pride-themed versions of their products and marketing it without substantially engaging queer communities — tends to be the minimal-effort route that multiple brands take and majority of consumers recognise these attempts as inauthentic almost immediately. But it's never too late to start developing real bonds with LGBTQ+ consumers. One of the most effective ways to show support is through charitable efforts, and Pride offers brands ample opportunities to turn their specialised products into the support that resonates beyond June.&amp;nbsp; According to a recent analysis, queer consumers who tend to maintain higher median household incomes, are more likely than other marginalised groups to actively seek and patronise the companies that engage with their collective community in a sustained fashion. Fortunately, some brands understand the lasting power of giving back. It is important to remember the message one leaves out there can help lay the foundation of change. We need to understand that equality is not a once-a-month fight, but year-round support is necessary — not just for Pride month, but all the social causes we rise for. Together we can create a world, which is fairer for everyone.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Political Drama Worthy of Shakespeare: The Case of Malaysia</title>
      <link href="/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Political Drama Worthy of Shakespeare: The Case of Malaysia" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare">&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Najib Razzak, who had become Prime Minister with the campaign promise of liberal politics, lost a general election to his former mentor, Mahathir Mohamad. The Barisan Nasional (BN) coalition, which had governed the country since its independence in 1957, was voted out of power. Following the downfall, Najib's properties were raided. Both he and his wife were charged with a string of offences and since then been found guilty on seven charges of corruption linked to the multibillion-dollar state investment fund 1MDB.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Najib’s history with corruption allegations is a long one. He has consistently denied the allegations and had been cleared by the country's authorities while still in office. During his tenure, he reformed strict laws on public gatherings and reinstated the controversial Internal Security Act in 2011 allowing detention without trial. The following year, he also went back on a pledge to repeal a controversial sedition law and instead strengthened it. Critics say the laws were a way for Najib to silence his political opponents and pander to the ethnic Malay-Muslim majority who formed his political party's most significant support base. In 2015, opposition leader and former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim was convicted of sodomy for the second time. In 2016, a security act aimed at combating terrorism was used to detain electoral reform activists. Ahead of the 2018 election, Najib's government set up a law against spreading &quot;fake news”, inadvertently used to silence campaigns by his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a string of numerous allegations, the real blight of Najib's political career has been his mismanagement of the state investment fund, 1Malaysia Development Berhad. The 1MDB fund was set up in 2009 to turn Kuala Lumpur into a financial hub and boost the economy through strategic investments. It began to draw negative attention in early 2015 after it missed payments due for some of the $11 billion it owed to banks and bondholders. The fund was then indicted for money laundering and sending hundreds of millions of dollars into private pockets to acquire assets globally, including yachts, paintings, jewellery and real estate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Department of Justice began investigating 1MDB, finding a diversion of $4.5 billion. Najib Razak was accused of pocketing nearly $700 million from the fund he set up. Ahead of the 2018 election, mass protests in Kuala Lumpur called on him to resign. The claims of corruption at 1MDB were a significant cause of Najib's election loss to Mahathir Mohamad, the world's oldest elected leader. Shortly after his victory, Malaysia's new Prime Minister reopened the 1MDB investigations and swore that Najib &quot;would face the consequences&quot; if he was guilty. Najib was forbidden from leaving the country, and properties linked to him were raided. Policemen state they recovered $273 million in luxury goods and cash, calling the seizure of valuables the biggest in Malaysian history.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US prosecutors had hinted that an anonymous individual dubbed &quot;Malaysian Official 1&quot; had received more than $1 billion from 1MDB, and that person is broadly believed to be Najib. Another target of the investigation is Malaysian businessman Low Taek Jho, who helped set up the fund, and is accused of diverting money to himself and his associates. He, too, has consistently rebuffed any wrongdoing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, Najib was arrested by anti-corruption authorities. He faces 21 counts of money laundering and 4 for abuse of power and negates all wrongdoing. The 12-year jail term for Malaysia's ex-Prime Minister serves as a warning that no matter how powerful one becomes, the sceptre of democracy hangs low over the heads of all public officials.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2018, Najib Razzak, who had become Prime Minister with the campaign promise of liberal politics, lost a general election to his former mentor, Mahathir Mohamad. The Barisan Nasional (BN) coalition, which had governed the country since its independence in 1957, was voted out of power. Following the downfall, Najib's properties were raided. Both he and his wife were charged with a string of offences and since then been found guilty on seven charges of corruption linked to the multibillion-dollar state investment fund 1MDB.&amp;nbsp; Najib’s history with corruption allegations is a long one. He has consistently denied the allegations and had been cleared by the country's authorities while still in office. During his tenure, he reformed strict laws on public gatherings and reinstated the controversial Internal Security Act in 2011 allowing detention without trial. The following year, he also went back on a pledge to repeal a controversial sedition law and instead strengthened it. Critics say the laws were a way for Najib to silence his political opponents and pander to the ethnic Malay-Muslim majority who formed his political party's most significant support base. In 2015, opposition leader and former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim was convicted of sodomy for the second time. In 2016, a security act aimed at combating terrorism was used to detain electoral reform activists. Ahead of the 2018 election, Najib's government set up a law against spreading &quot;fake news”, inadvertently used to silence campaigns by his opponents. Despite a string of numerous allegations, the real blight of Najib's political career has been his mismanagement of the state investment fund, 1Malaysia Development Berhad. The 1MDB fund was set up in 2009 to turn Kuala Lumpur into a financial hub and boost the economy through strategic investments. It began to draw negative attention in early 2015 after it missed payments due for some of the $11 billion it owed to banks and bondholders. The fund was then indicted for money laundering and sending hundreds of millions of dollars into private pockets to acquire assets globally, including yachts, paintings, jewellery and real estate.&amp;nbsp; The US Department of Justice began investigating 1MDB, finding a diversion of $4.5 billion. Najib Razak was accused of pocketing nearly $700 million from the fund he set up. Ahead of the 2018 election, mass protests in Kuala Lumpur called on him to resign. The claims of corruption at 1MDB were a significant cause of Najib's election loss to Mahathir Mohamad, the world's oldest elected leader. Shortly after his victory, Malaysia's new Prime Minister reopened the 1MDB investigations and swore that Najib &quot;would face the consequences&quot; if he was guilty. Najib was forbidden from leaving the country, and properties linked to him were raided. Policemen state they recovered $273 million in luxury goods and cash, calling the seizure of valuables the biggest in Malaysian history.&amp;nbsp; US prosecutors had hinted that an anonymous individual dubbed &quot;Malaysian Official 1&quot; had received more than $1 billion from 1MDB, and that person is broadly believed to be Najib. Another target of the investigation is Malaysian businessman Low Taek Jho, who helped set up the fund, and is accused of diverting money to himself and his associates. He, too, has consistently rebuffed any wrongdoing.&amp;nbsp; Eventually, Najib was arrested by anti-corruption authorities. He faces 21 counts of money laundering and 4 for abuse of power and negates all wrongdoing. The 12-year jail term for Malaysia's ex-Prime Minister serves as a warning that no matter how powerful one becomes, the sceptre of democracy hangs low over the heads of all public officials.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper</title>
      <link href="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 5: Connecting the Dots&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “&lt;em&gt;it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge&lt;/em&gt;.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp; Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp; Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp; With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp; Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people. The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes. Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp; Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp; Part 5: Connecting the Dots Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp; Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive. Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">11.11 - The Singles’ Date</title>
      <link href="/11-11-The-Singles-Date" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="11.11 - The Singles’ Date" />
      <published>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/11-11-The-Singles-Date</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/11-11-The-Singles-Date">&lt;p&gt;China is one of the world’s biggest powerhouses in innovation and technology. While the country has its own set of laws, it has a holiday that not many people around the globe know about- the &lt;em&gt;Singles’ Day&lt;/em&gt;! It might sound peculiar, but it is a huge part of modern Chinese culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Singles’ Day&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Double 11&lt;/em&gt;, originally called&lt;em&gt; Bachelors’ Day&lt;/em&gt;, is celebrated on November 11. It is a Chinese commercial holiday to celebrate being romantically unattached and paradoxically, turns out to be the largest physical retail and online shopping day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative behind the Singles’ Day is pretty nice. It originated at Nanjing University in 1993. A group of lonely, yet positive students decided that instead of lamenting their lack of a significant other, they would celebrate being single. The reasoning? 11.11 looks like four, single sticks, strung together trying to make the most out of their time. The anti-Valentine’s Day celebration of singledom caught on and spread across universities throughout China, generally characterised by fun and harmless events. With the widespread use of social media, the day has become increasingly popular within contemporary Chinese culture and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alibaba’s Blockbuster Growth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alibaba’s co-founder Jack Ma instituted the first Singles’ Day sale in 2009, laying the foundation for the highest-grossing shopping day of the year in the world. In 2012, the e-commerce company officially trademarked ‘Double 11’. Next in 2017, Alibaba’s mobile wallet app Alipay broke the record for the greatest number of transactions per second, whoa!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not be Singles’ Day without Alibaba having some great deals available. This year, the company’s annual sales frenzy broke records again by raking in roughly $75 billion. The total includes an earlier three-day period that was added to boost post-pandemic sales. The company claimed that, compared to the same timeframe as last year, this year’s haul represents an increase of 26%. Chinese consumers, who already buy about 30% of the nation’s retail purchase online, have become more reliant on e-commerce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, Alibaba also held a ‘Go Global 11.11 Pitch Fest’ aimed at small and medium-sized US brands, offering them a chance to be spotlighted during the event. Besides that, the company has been trying to involve more foreign brands globally. In 2019, Americans commanded the second-highest sales among importers, behind Japan but ahead of South Korea, Australia, and Germany.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, Alibaba makes stupendous efforts to hype up Double 11 with its extravagant, rather over-the-top countdown gala. It featured appearances from celebrities such as Nicole Kidman, Kobe Bryant, Scarlett Johansson, Mariah Carey, Pharrell Williams, Miranda Kerr, Jessie J, Lionel Messi, and Taylor Swift in the preceding years. Pop star Katy Perry, who has performed at the event before, made an appearance at the company’s gala this season, albeit via a live stream, as travel restrictions on outside visitors remain in place in China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though many other online platforms and stores take part in Singles’ Day, it is still closely tied to Alibaba.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crazy Sale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For brands and retailers scrambling to recover from months of shuttered shops and consumers hunkered down indoors, the profitable Chinese shopper is a much-needed bright spot. It is estimated that the participation of luxury brands has doubled on Singles’ Day, as millions of Chinese who have been unable to travel overseas on shopping trips go online for what experts are dubbing ‘revenge spending’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the buzz of Singles’ Day led the retailers worldwide to opt for special promotions to boost sales. &lt;em&gt;Uniqlo&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Foot Locker&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Best Buy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Steam&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Target&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Expedia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Topman&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Brooklinen&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Levi’s&lt;/em&gt;, and numerous other companies offered massive deals and discounts, orbiting the holiday. Three million workers, aided by 4,000 planes and ships got ready for the world’s biggest online sale in the current year- with ‘revenge spending’ tipping to be one of this year’s biggest trends.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey by market research firm &lt;em&gt;Oliver Wyman&lt;/em&gt; found out that 86% of Chinese consumers were willing to spend the same as or more than what they did during last year’s Singles’ Day. The remaining 14% of survey respondents said that they had spent less on Singles’ Day, because of the unprecedented times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On The Outside&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singles’ Day has become the most lucrative shopping holiday in several places outside China as well. The holiday has particularly grown in Southeast Asia, with customers in Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam, who are the recipient of the huge discounts offered by Alibaba’s subsidiary Lazada. In the United Kingdom, Singles’ Day is marked on March 11. It was initiated by a group of internationally recognised dating experts to help singles embrace themselves. Furthermore, Swedish Electronic retailer &lt;em&gt;Elgiganten&lt;/em&gt; promoted a Singles’ Day campaign in Norway before implementing it in the other Nordic countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MediaMarkt&lt;/em&gt;, a German Company, also promotes this day in its stores. Conversely, Belgian &lt;em&gt;MediaMarkt&lt;/em&gt; also participates but the reactions have been negative. It is because November 11 is the anniversary of the Armistice of 1918 that ended the First World War.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, awareness of Singles’ Day in New Zealand is still relatively low. According to a survey by &lt;em&gt;PriceSpy&lt;/em&gt;, around 73% of Kiwis have never heard of this day, with just 12% of Kiwis reporting to have brought something during the world’s biggest shopping bonanza.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singles’ Day will continue to grow in importance for retailers outside of China, particularly in the United Kingdom, which last year grew their discounting assortment to mirror the United States. In the light of the pandemic and feel of 2020, upbeat marketing angles that touch on celebrating and treating yourself are drawing attention globally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Antidote to Valentine’s Day&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally on Singles’ Day, people buy things, take themselves out for dinner, watch movies, sheepishly ruin dates, hang out with their other single friends and delve into the gratifying embrace of self-love. This phenomenon of retail therapy has resulted in oodles of sales, easily surpassing Black Friday and Cyber Monday combined.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, it is fun getting gifts on your birthday, Christmas and on other occasions- but how can people know what you actually want? On this day, you get to shop for yourself. I’m not just talking about buying yourself flowers or a decent meal. It is the day to show yourself some real love and appreciation. Go on, indulge. Splurge on those jeans you have been eying, or fancy wine club membership- you have earned it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retailers all over the world are instigating exclusive, singles-oriented deals in Alibaba’s footsteps. Grab the benefit of special promotions- ticket for 1 to Fiji? Yes, please.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">China is one of the world’s biggest powerhouses in innovation and technology. While the country has its own set of laws, it has a holiday that not many people around the globe know about- the Singles’ Day! It might sound peculiar, but it is a huge part of modern Chinese culture.&amp;nbsp; The Singles’ Day or Double 11, originally called Bachelors’ Day, is celebrated on November 11. It is a Chinese commercial holiday to celebrate being romantically unattached and paradoxically, turns out to be the largest physical retail and online shopping day of the year. Genesis The narrative behind the Singles’ Day is pretty nice. It originated at Nanjing University in 1993. A group of lonely, yet positive students decided that instead of lamenting their lack of a significant other, they would celebrate being single. The reasoning? 11.11 looks like four, single sticks, strung together trying to make the most out of their time. The anti-Valentine’s Day celebration of singledom caught on and spread across universities throughout China, generally characterised by fun and harmless events. With the widespread use of social media, the day has become increasingly popular within contemporary Chinese culture and society.&amp;nbsp; Alibaba’s Blockbuster Growth Alibaba’s co-founder Jack Ma instituted the first Singles’ Day sale in 2009, laying the foundation for the highest-grossing shopping day of the year in the world. In 2012, the e-commerce company officially trademarked ‘Double 11’. Next in 2017, Alibaba’s mobile wallet app Alipay broke the record for the greatest number of transactions per second, whoa!&amp;nbsp; It would not be Singles’ Day without Alibaba having some great deals available. This year, the company’s annual sales frenzy broke records again by raking in roughly $75 billion. The total includes an earlier three-day period that was added to boost post-pandemic sales. The company claimed that, compared to the same timeframe as last year, this year’s haul represents an increase of 26%. Chinese consumers, who already buy about 30% of the nation’s retail purchase online, have become more reliant on e-commerce.&amp;nbsp; This year, Alibaba also held a ‘Go Global 11.11 Pitch Fest’ aimed at small and medium-sized US brands, offering them a chance to be spotlighted during the event. Besides that, the company has been trying to involve more foreign brands globally. In 2019, Americans commanded the second-highest sales among importers, behind Japan but ahead of South Korea, Australia, and Germany.&amp;nbsp; Undoubtedly, Alibaba makes stupendous efforts to hype up Double 11 with its extravagant, rather over-the-top countdown gala. It featured appearances from celebrities such as Nicole Kidman, Kobe Bryant, Scarlett Johansson, Mariah Carey, Pharrell Williams, Miranda Kerr, Jessie J, Lionel Messi, and Taylor Swift in the preceding years. Pop star Katy Perry, who has performed at the event before, made an appearance at the company’s gala this season, albeit via a live stream, as travel restrictions on outside visitors remain in place in China.&amp;nbsp; Even though many other online platforms and stores take part in Singles’ Day, it is still closely tied to Alibaba.&amp;nbsp; Crazy Sale For brands and retailers scrambling to recover from months of shuttered shops and consumers hunkered down indoors, the profitable Chinese shopper is a much-needed bright spot. It is estimated that the participation of luxury brands has doubled on Singles’ Day, as millions of Chinese who have been unable to travel overseas on shopping trips go online for what experts are dubbing ‘revenge spending’.&amp;nbsp; Unsurprisingly, the buzz of Singles’ Day led the retailers worldwide to opt for special promotions to boost sales. Uniqlo, Foot Locker, Best Buy, Steam, Target, Alibaba, Expedia, Topman, Brooklinen, Levi’s, and numerous other companies offered massive deals and discounts, orbiting the holiday. Three million workers, aided by 4,000 planes and ships got ready for the world’s biggest online sale in the current year- with ‘revenge spending’ tipping to be one of this year’s biggest trends.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A survey by market research firm Oliver Wyman found out that 86% of Chinese consumers were willing to spend the same as or more than what they did during last year’s Singles’ Day. The remaining 14% of survey respondents said that they had spent less on Singles’ Day, because of the unprecedented times.&amp;nbsp; On The Outside Singles’ Day has become the most lucrative shopping holiday in several places outside China as well. The holiday has particularly grown in Southeast Asia, with customers in Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam, who are the recipient of the huge discounts offered by Alibaba’s subsidiary Lazada. In the United Kingdom, Singles’ Day is marked on March 11. It was initiated by a group of internationally recognised dating experts to help singles embrace themselves. Furthermore, Swedish Electronic retailer Elgiganten promoted a Singles’ Day campaign in Norway before implementing it in the other Nordic countries.&amp;nbsp; MediaMarkt, a German Company, also promotes this day in its stores. Conversely, Belgian MediaMarkt also participates but the reactions have been negative. It is because November 11 is the anniversary of the Armistice of 1918 that ended the First World War.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, awareness of Singles’ Day in New Zealand is still relatively low. According to a survey by PriceSpy, around 73% of Kiwis have never heard of this day, with just 12% of Kiwis reporting to have brought something during the world’s biggest shopping bonanza.&amp;nbsp; Singles’ Day will continue to grow in importance for retailers outside of China, particularly in the United Kingdom, which last year grew their discounting assortment to mirror the United States. In the light of the pandemic and feel of 2020, upbeat marketing angles that touch on celebrating and treating yourself are drawing attention globally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; An Antidote to Valentine’s Day&amp;nbsp; Traditionally on Singles’ Day, people buy things, take themselves out for dinner, watch movies, sheepishly ruin dates, hang out with their other single friends and delve into the gratifying embrace of self-love. This phenomenon of retail therapy has resulted in oodles of sales, easily surpassing Black Friday and Cyber Monday combined.&amp;nbsp; Certainly, it is fun getting gifts on your birthday, Christmas and on other occasions- but how can people know what you actually want? On this day, you get to shop for yourself. I’m not just talking about buying yourself flowers or a decent meal. It is the day to show yourself some real love and appreciation. Go on, indulge. Splurge on those jeans you have been eying, or fancy wine club membership- you have earned it.&amp;nbsp; Retailers all over the world are instigating exclusive, singles-oriented deals in Alibaba’s footsteps. Grab the benefit of special promotions- ticket for 1 to Fiji? Yes, please.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Bootstrapping vs Funding: The Dilemma</title>
      <link href="/Bootstrapping-vs-Funding-The-Dilemma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bootstrapping vs Funding: The Dilemma" />
      <published>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bootstrapping-vs-Funding-The-Dilemma</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bootstrapping-vs-Funding-The-Dilemma">&lt;p&gt;Here is the toughest question for an entrepreneur: Should I bootstrap my business, or make an effort and raise capital through a venture fund? While the choice rests on a myriad of divergent factors, it is important to understand these financing methods and how they can influence the future of a business.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In layman’s terms, bootstrapping refers to the act of starting a company with an individual’s personal finances and without external funding. If people are building up a company with whatever money they have in hand and from the profits they are earning, that is ‘Bootstrapping’. In contrast, ‘Venture Capital’ funding is when funding is put into a new business by venture capitalists as an investment in exchange for equity in the business. It allows a startup to move and scale quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More entrepreneurs are showing up to shoot for the stars and go for the gold to fuel their startup by either adopting the guerilla-style bootstrapping path or by trying to raise funds. In determining whether entrepreneurs should bootstrap or seek external funding for their company, it is necessary to weigh up the pros and cons associated with a plethora of significant factors and decide which is the better fit.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several external factors that the company must keep in mind while making a funding decision. Suppose a company is functioning in a highly competitive market, like Uber or Slack, this means that they have to scale as fast as possible and become or remain a dominant player. It most likely implies that investment is required to afford growth in the near future, which makes it suitable for the company to opt for venture capital funding. In juxtaposition to the above market structure, a fragmented market where many mid-sized firms coexist, like Snappa and Buffer, funding may not be necessary. Under these circumstances, entrepreneurs can choose to bootstrap their company and grow it by themselves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s walk through the internal factors that help in deciding between bootstrapping versus funding. The goal that the company strives to achieve affects their decision to bootstrap or seek external funding. For bootstrapped companies, the goal is generally to become more profitable whereas funded companies aim to maximise revenue growth and become the market leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, if the company has the ambition to continue growing forever and founders want to stay with the firm, then bootstrapping is a viable option. On the other hand, if they are planning to exit in a couple of years, then raising venture capital money to scale faster may be the right choice. This is because venture capitalists typically invest with a target to exit in about 3-10 years. Since a bootstrapped company works with limited resources, its growth rate is slower in comparison to the funded companies that gain traction quickly. Bootstrapping becomes successful when a startup can sustain itself over a period of time. After initial hiccups, like investment arranged by the founder, the company starts making profits out of its products and services that carry the business forward. Needless to say, both can achieve good growth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now most importantly, when it comes to the freedom and the control of the owners, there is a lot more flexibility in a bootstrapped company. It allows gung-ho entrepreneurs to experiment with what they can do. They can focus on partnering with someone who brings in the required skill set and industry-specific expertise. The focus is directed towards a clear goal and there is no interference from investors who might have conflicting visions. However, the downside is that this form of financing might also place the entrepreneur under unnecessary financial risk.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, the funded company’s ability to pivot is constrained. This essentially means that the companies have to consult with their venture capitalists in all the decision-making processes. In addition to this, it brings more people into the business with different ideas, expertise and varied backgrounds. Experienced investors can also act as mentors for young entrepreneurs, and guide them through tricky situations. But instead of owning a business, the founders usually end up owning just a smaller portion of a much bigger pie after going through multiple rounds of fundraising that continuously dilute their ownership.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the realm of email newsletters, Atlanta-based MailChimp is a successful giant. Co-founders Ben Chestnut and Dan Kurzius &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/10/06/technology/mailchimp-and-the-un-silicon-valley-way-to-make-it-as-a-start-up.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;started the company in 2000&lt;/a&gt; from a bootstrapped dream and it became one of the biggest companies in its space with due course of time. The company was named &lt;em&gt;Inc.’s&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/magazine/201802/mailchimp-company-of-the-year-2017.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Company of the Year in 2017&lt;/a&gt; and till today it is still 100% founder-owned. Thriving startups like Mailchimp, Spanx, GoPro, Craigslist and so many more have bootstrapped their way to success and have gained mainstream attention that began to attract investors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, RUSSSH started its journey in 2012 as GetMyPeon and was the only errand-running and delivery service in Mumbai, India. The seven-year-old bootstrapped company lacked the capital to fight competition. It could not offer great discounts like other emergent players, and to achieve success in a developing service market proved unnerving. Like RUSSSH, numerous bootstrapped startups such as LoanMeet, Woolpr and Koinex among many others could not survive in the market for long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, giving prominence to the best-funded startups like One97 Communications (Paytm), Ola Cabs, OYO, Snapdeal, Swiggy, BYJU’s, Big Basket and so many more that have funding totalling billions of dollars are flourishing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlikely, Anki Inc, founded in 2010 by three Carnegie Mellon Robotics Institute graduates, focused on creating unique consumer products. The company’s total funding amount was $182 million. According to its long-term roadmap, it could no longer continue as a hardware and software business even after selling 1.5 million robot units due to insufficient funds. Similarly,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Call9, Aria Insights, Stimwave Technologies, Oryx Vision, and many other companies sustained in the market for a very short period of time. Not to mention the world-famous case of Theranos!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, bootstrapping and funding both have their own benefits and drawbacks. There is no one option that is inherently better or worse off than the other. From a finance outlook, funding gives the startup more power to scale, but it also comes with high stakes. When it comes to bootstrapping, it makes it harder for entrepreneurs to scale their company, but while it might grow at a slower pace, there still remains the advantage of owning and controlling the whole pie.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Here is the toughest question for an entrepreneur: Should I bootstrap my business, or make an effort and raise capital through a venture fund? While the choice rests on a myriad of divergent factors, it is important to understand these financing methods and how they can influence the future of a business.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In layman’s terms, bootstrapping refers to the act of starting a company with an individual’s personal finances and without external funding. If people are building up a company with whatever money they have in hand and from the profits they are earning, that is ‘Bootstrapping’. In contrast, ‘Venture Capital’ funding is when funding is put into a new business by venture capitalists as an investment in exchange for equity in the business. It allows a startup to move and scale quickly. More entrepreneurs are showing up to shoot for the stars and go for the gold to fuel their startup by either adopting the guerilla-style bootstrapping path or by trying to raise funds. In determining whether entrepreneurs should bootstrap or seek external funding for their company, it is necessary to weigh up the pros and cons associated with a plethora of significant factors and decide which is the better fit.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; There are several external factors that the company must keep in mind while making a funding decision. Suppose a company is functioning in a highly competitive market, like Uber or Slack, this means that they have to scale as fast as possible and become or remain a dominant player. It most likely implies that investment is required to afford growth in the near future, which makes it suitable for the company to opt for venture capital funding. In juxtaposition to the above market structure, a fragmented market where many mid-sized firms coexist, like Snappa and Buffer, funding may not be necessary. Under these circumstances, entrepreneurs can choose to bootstrap their company and grow it by themselves.&amp;nbsp; Let’s walk through the internal factors that help in deciding between bootstrapping versus funding. The goal that the company strives to achieve affects their decision to bootstrap or seek external funding. For bootstrapped companies, the goal is generally to become more profitable whereas funded companies aim to maximise revenue growth and become the market leaders.&amp;nbsp; Next, if the company has the ambition to continue growing forever and founders want to stay with the firm, then bootstrapping is a viable option. On the other hand, if they are planning to exit in a couple of years, then raising venture capital money to scale faster may be the right choice. This is because venture capitalists typically invest with a target to exit in about 3-10 years. Since a bootstrapped company works with limited resources, its growth rate is slower in comparison to the funded companies that gain traction quickly. Bootstrapping becomes successful when a startup can sustain itself over a period of time. After initial hiccups, like investment arranged by the founder, the company starts making profits out of its products and services that carry the business forward. Needless to say, both can achieve good growth.&amp;nbsp; Now most importantly, when it comes to the freedom and the control of the owners, there is a lot more flexibility in a bootstrapped company. It allows gung-ho entrepreneurs to experiment with what they can do. They can focus on partnering with someone who brings in the required skill set and industry-specific expertise. The focus is directed towards a clear goal and there is no interference from investors who might have conflicting visions. However, the downside is that this form of financing might also place the entrepreneur under unnecessary financial risk.&amp;nbsp; On a similar note, the funded company’s ability to pivot is constrained. This essentially means that the companies have to consult with their venture capitalists in all the decision-making processes. In addition to this, it brings more people into the business with different ideas, expertise and varied backgrounds. Experienced investors can also act as mentors for young entrepreneurs, and guide them through tricky situations. But instead of owning a business, the founders usually end up owning just a smaller portion of a much bigger pie after going through multiple rounds of fundraising that continuously dilute their ownership.&amp;nbsp; In the realm of email newsletters, Atlanta-based MailChimp is a successful giant. Co-founders Ben Chestnut and Dan Kurzius started the company in 2000 from a bootstrapped dream and it became one of the biggest companies in its space with due course of time. The company was named Inc.’s Company of the Year in 2017 and till today it is still 100% founder-owned. Thriving startups like Mailchimp, Spanx, GoPro, Craigslist and so many more have bootstrapped their way to success and have gained mainstream attention that began to attract investors.&amp;nbsp; Conversely, RUSSSH started its journey in 2012 as GetMyPeon and was the only errand-running and delivery service in Mumbai, India. The seven-year-old bootstrapped company lacked the capital to fight competition. It could not offer great discounts like other emergent players, and to achieve success in a developing service market proved unnerving. Like RUSSSH, numerous bootstrapped startups such as LoanMeet, Woolpr and Koinex among many others could not survive in the market for long. Furthermore, giving prominence to the best-funded startups like One97 Communications (Paytm), Ola Cabs, OYO, Snapdeal, Swiggy, BYJU’s, Big Basket and so many more that have funding totalling billions of dollars are flourishing. Unlikely, Anki Inc, founded in 2010 by three Carnegie Mellon Robotics Institute graduates, focused on creating unique consumer products. The company’s total funding amount was $182 million. According to its long-term roadmap, it could no longer continue as a hardware and software business even after selling 1.5 million robot units due to insufficient funds. Similarly, Call9, Aria Insights, Stimwave Technologies, Oryx Vision, and many other companies sustained in the market for a very short period of time. Not to mention the world-famous case of Theranos! At the end of the day, bootstrapping and funding both have their own benefits and drawbacks. There is no one option that is inherently better or worse off than the other. From a finance outlook, funding gives the startup more power to scale, but it also comes with high stakes. When it comes to bootstrapping, it makes it harder for entrepreneurs to scale their company, but while it might grow at a slower pace, there still remains the advantage of owning and controlling the whole pie.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
