<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/shohan.mukherjee/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-26T23:16:55+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/shohan.mukherjee/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The State of the Millennial in 2019</title>
      <link href="/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The State of the Millennial in 2019" />
      <published>2019-07-07T01:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-07T01:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Millennials (smh). Pampered and nurtured by parents, trying to avoid the
mistakes of a previous generation. You are late to graduate, late to marry and
late to have children. You’re even late to find a job (IF you find a job). To
this ever-determined and ambitious generation, we dedicate the series, ‘for’ and
‘by’ the Millennials, who are most likely still living with their parents. It’s
time we spoke about our host of issues, Gen-Y style.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Millennial, you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be angry. Also, if you’re a Millennial
who’s about to hit the job market, I’ve got disappointing news for you. The
Millennial unemployment rate now stands at an &lt;a href=&quot;https://americansforprosperity.org/?utm_source=GO&amp;amp;utm_medium=banner&amp;amp;utm_campaign=redirect&amp;amp;utm_content=main&quot;&gt;astounding
12.8%&lt;/a&gt;,
dwarfing the US national average. Furthermore, if you are a Millennial who has
gone through the past decade unemployed or not, you have also had to endure the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic&quot;&gt;biggest financial
disaster&lt;/a&gt; of the past
half-century, so kudos to you for sticking around and having a firsthand account
of the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were robbed, I tell you. The Millennials were supposed to be the ‘greatest
generation’ yet, the most technologically advanced and by far the most educated
generation ever. We were expected to come in and revolutionise the industry, do
away with the old-fashioned and bear the torch of progress. Well, so much for
trying. We have still not cracked into the industry as smoothly as we would have
wanted. Employers are unsatisfied with our over-expectant attitudes (Note: most
of them being baby-boomers, the slackers of Generation X never made it).
Overall, it has been a struggle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, we are hard to please, overconfident and maybe a tad bit narcissistic.
We dream too much about having it all, without taking our daily dose of reality.
Flashy cars, jewellery, big condos, champagne and caviar. Well, that’s what was
sold to us ever since we got on to &lt;em&gt;MTV&lt;/em&gt; or were young enough to watch
television. We also focus too much on ourselves, often losing track of the &lt;em&gt;‘Big
Picture’.&lt;/em&gt; But we never had to answer the call of the GI generation or the
rallying cry of growth and economic development in the 80’s and 90’s. How often
were you taught to think as a generation, and not as individuals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what, one thing is for sure. The Millennial Generation or Gen-Y as it
is called, is the most highly educated generation to date, and we are definitely
proud of it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/03/16/how-millennials-compare-with-their-grandparents/ft_millennials-education_031715/&quot;&gt;Pew Research
Center&lt;/a&gt;
recently conducted a study showing that 21% and 27% of men and women (aged
18-33) had a college degree, as compared to the Baby Boomers (17% and 14%) and
Generation X (18% and 20%). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Oh, what do I hear? We aren’t learning interpersonal and communication skills?
Really?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True adulthood only hits us when we realize that these numbers do not mean
anything to the people hiring out there. They say we lack team building and the
ability to communicate effectively, and are more adept at theoretical knowledge
than actual applicable skills. Which in essence is saying that our school and
college education did not really help us at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, that just rubs us off the wrong way, especially with how
increasingly expensive university education has become, with ballooning student
debt plaguing much of the Western world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If the employer is just having a problem with me and my ways, then guess what,
I quit!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/504bc9dab4a70c6c69a5696be0456568/tumblr_n22rf1CVMY1tq4of6o1_500.gif&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//lalalala.gif&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there lies another innate flaw deep within us. Maybe, it is
because a lot of us are still young and haven’t grown out of the habit of
denial. But for many, it is very hard for us to come to terms with our
shortcomings. Much too often we will just dismiss them, or much worse, put the
blame on the employer. But as we all know, that’s just a quicker way to get the
boot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to make up ground, and reach our expectations (sky high!), we will
have to adjust to the ways of the world and not be so adamant as we strive to
perfection. But why ‘perfection’? Why are we so obsessed with getting it right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/shohan.mukherjee/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//millennials1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies with the world that has been built by the last generation to
earn the ‘greatest’ title before us: the baby boomers. As baby boomers emerged
from childhood, they soon had a very jolting experience into the foray of the
professional worker. Their journey into adulthood was not as long and smoothed
out as ours. Most of them emerged from the growing middle class, at a time when
countries all across the world were engaged in a GDP scoring competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, most of this generation were thrust directly into the workforce and found
a way to sustain themselves, thanks to their resilient nature. They ended up
earning far more than their parents, a trend which had been continuing since the
1900’s. Later on in life, most of them ended up giving birth to Generation X as
well as the Millennials. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it seems like the buck stops here, as the Millennials are suited to be the
first generation to earn &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; than their parents. It is not a surprise that
rising difficulties to secure a job coupling with employment opportunities
bottoming out post the Great Recession have led to employment protests
throughout Europe, the USA and Asia. And although Millennials are believed to be
far more open-minded and tolerant, the dire circumstances have led to growing
support for right-wing politics in many European and South Asian nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The super-saturated job market has lead to increasingly weird paradoxes. Here’s
one story from &lt;em&gt;The Huffington Post&lt;/em&gt;, which could be one of many:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“I was literally paying to work,” says Elena, a 29-year-old dietician in Texas.
As part of her master’s degree, she was required to do a yearlong “internship”
in a hospital. It was supposed to be training, but she says she worked the same
hours and did the same tasks as paid staffers. “I took out an extra \$20,000 in
student loans to pay tuition for the year I was working for free,” she says.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse yet, with the increase of contractor companies which deal especially in
security, storage and inventory management, or housekeeping activities, the
future of low-income workers is further at risk. Take the example of Mr Joe, the
security guard at the mall, who is actually signed to a contractor that has
inked a deal with the mall. In this way, the mall just has to pay the contractor
and not the individual person who is doing the job. This cuts out a lot of costs
including any form of pension or benefits. Of course, that goes out of Mr Joe’s
pocket. And out goes any form of career advancement either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Princeton-LSE grad Michael Lewis made a fortune and a legacy out of his book,
&lt;em&gt;Liar’s Poker&lt;/em&gt;, which details the rise of Lewie Ranieri and his team of traders
who made big money at Salomon Brothers back in the late-80’s. In the book he
often spoke of back office workers, including people who worked the fax and
xerox machines, later trying their hand at trading for the company after slowly
rising through the ranks over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, thanks to him for documenting another list of practices that went out the
window during the Financial Crisis. You can wave goodbye to that sort of career
mobility in the 21st century. After all, the Great Crash of 2008 was all about
under-skilled people working over-skilled jobs. Look at where we have arrived
now with the current wave of Millennial underemployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because of things like these that we fear a slip up so much, even a little
one, that could send us hurtling down the tunnel of underemployment,
unemployment, and at last, poverty. No, no, don’t laugh, this is serious. You
might not have gotten out of your post-sack funk by the time you realise that
you have fallen below the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sanford.duke.edu/people/faculty/krishna-anirudh&quot;&gt;Anirudh Krishna&lt;/a&gt;, a
professor at Duke University, has documented over 1,000 cases of people who fell
into poverty, and only some of whom managed to escape it. He conducted his
search throughout India and Kenya, and revealed that poverty arises from a
series of mishaps. One broken leg, one lost job, one sick family member and you
find yourself below the line. And it is this chance of slipping (literally),
coupled with humongous college and healthcare costs, that force us Millennials
to hope against hope to strive for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inverse.com/article/53091-millennials-largest-ever-perfectionism-study&quot;&gt;perfection at every living
moment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, here we stand at the brink of a period of flux and change. Our
generation’s defining moment has come and gone in 2008, we are just afraid
another one might &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2019/06/04/next-recession-2020-predictions/&quot;&gt;come along too
soon&lt;/a&gt;. We might
well be the first generation in decades to earn less than our parents. We will
delay our marriages as well as moving out of home. Yes, buying a home now is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://globalnews.ca/news/3230146/numbers-show-its-harder-for-millennials-to-buy-a-home-than-it-was-for-their-parents/&quot;&gt;exponentially
tougher&lt;/a&gt;
than 30 years ago. Deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/jan/05/perfectionism-mental-health-millennial-social-media&quot;&gt;a
problem&lt;/a&gt;
with that? We don’t, we have no choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the future (FML).&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Millennials (smh). Pampered and nurtured by parents, trying to avoid the mistakes of a previous generation. You are late to graduate, late to marry and late to have children. You’re even late to find a job (IF you find a job). To this ever-determined and ambitious generation, we dedicate the series, ‘for’ and ‘by’ the Millennials, who are most likely still living with their parents. It’s time we spoke about our host of issues, Gen-Y style. If you are a Millennial, you should be angry. Also, if you’re a Millennial who’s about to hit the job market, I’ve got disappointing news for you. The Millennial unemployment rate now stands at an astounding 12.8%, dwarfing the US national average. Furthermore, if you are a Millennial who has gone through the past decade unemployed or not, you have also had to endure the biggest financial disaster of the past half-century, so kudos to you for sticking around and having a firsthand account of the experience. We were robbed, I tell you. The Millennials were supposed to be the ‘greatest generation’ yet, the most technologically advanced and by far the most educated generation ever. We were expected to come in and revolutionise the industry, do away with the old-fashioned and bear the torch of progress. Well, so much for trying. We have still not cracked into the industry as smoothly as we would have wanted. Employers are unsatisfied with our over-expectant attitudes (Note: most of them being baby-boomers, the slackers of Generation X never made it). Overall, it has been a struggle.  Alright, we are hard to please, overconfident and maybe a tad bit narcissistic. We dream too much about having it all, without taking our daily dose of reality. Flashy cars, jewellery, big condos, champagne and caviar. Well, that’s what was sold to us ever since we got on to MTV or were young enough to watch television. We also focus too much on ourselves, often losing track of the ‘Big Picture’. But we never had to answer the call of the GI generation or the rallying cry of growth and economic development in the 80’s and 90’s. How often were you taught to think as a generation, and not as individuals? No matter what, one thing is for sure. The Millennial Generation or Gen-Y as it is called, is the most highly educated generation to date, and we are definitely proud of it. The Pew Research Center recently conducted a study showing that 21% and 27% of men and women (aged 18-33) had a college degree, as compared to the Baby Boomers (17% and 14%) and Generation X (18% and 20%).  “Oh, what do I hear? We aren’t learning interpersonal and communication skills? Really?” True adulthood only hits us when we realize that these numbers do not mean anything to the people hiring out there. They say we lack team building and the ability to communicate effectively, and are more adept at theoretical knowledge than actual applicable skills. Which in essence is saying that our school and college education did not really help us at all. To be honest, that just rubs us off the wrong way, especially with how increasingly expensive university education has become, with ballooning student debt plaguing much of the Western world.  “If the employer is just having a problem with me and my ways, then guess what, I quit!” Unfortunately, there lies another innate flaw deep within us. Maybe, it is because a lot of us are still young and haven’t grown out of the habit of denial. But for many, it is very hard for us to come to terms with our shortcomings. Much too often we will just dismiss them, or much worse, put the blame on the employer. But as we all know, that’s just a quicker way to get the boot! If we are to make up ground, and reach our expectations (sky high!), we will have to adjust to the ways of the world and not be so adamant as we strive to perfection. But why ‘perfection’? Why are we so obsessed with getting it right? The answer lies with the world that has been built by the last generation to earn the ‘greatest’ title before us: the baby boomers. As baby boomers emerged from childhood, they soon had a very jolting experience into the foray of the professional worker. Their journey into adulthood was not as long and smoothed out as ours. Most of them emerged from the growing middle class, at a time when countries all across the world were engaged in a GDP scoring competition.  Thus, most of this generation were thrust directly into the workforce and found a way to sustain themselves, thanks to their resilient nature. They ended up earning far more than their parents, a trend which had been continuing since the 1900’s. Later on in life, most of them ended up giving birth to Generation X as well as the Millennials.  But it seems like the buck stops here, as the Millennials are suited to be the first generation to earn less than their parents. It is not a surprise that rising difficulties to secure a job coupling with employment opportunities bottoming out post the Great Recession have led to employment protests throughout Europe, the USA and Asia. And although Millennials are believed to be far more open-minded and tolerant, the dire circumstances have led to growing support for right-wing politics in many European and South Asian nations. The super-saturated job market has lead to increasingly weird paradoxes. Here’s one story from The Huffington Post, which could be one of many: “I was literally paying to work,” says Elena, a 29-year-old dietician in Texas. As part of her master’s degree, she was required to do a yearlong “internship” in a hospital. It was supposed to be training, but she says she worked the same hours and did the same tasks as paid staffers. “I took out an extra \$20,000 in student loans to pay tuition for the year I was working for free,” she says. Worse yet, with the increase of contractor companies which deal especially in security, storage and inventory management, or housekeeping activities, the future of low-income workers is further at risk. Take the example of Mr Joe, the security guard at the mall, who is actually signed to a contractor that has inked a deal with the mall. In this way, the mall just has to pay the contractor and not the individual person who is doing the job. This cuts out a lot of costs including any form of pension or benefits. Of course, that goes out of Mr Joe’s pocket. And out goes any form of career advancement either. Princeton-LSE grad Michael Lewis made a fortune and a legacy out of his book, Liar’s Poker, which details the rise of Lewie Ranieri and his team of traders who made big money at Salomon Brothers back in the late-80’s. In the book he often spoke of back office workers, including people who worked the fax and xerox machines, later trying their hand at trading for the company after slowly rising through the ranks over the years.  Well, thanks to him for documenting another list of practices that went out the window during the Financial Crisis. You can wave goodbye to that sort of career mobility in the 21st century. After all, the Great Crash of 2008 was all about under-skilled people working over-skilled jobs. Look at where we have arrived now with the current wave of Millennial underemployment. It is because of things like these that we fear a slip up so much, even a little one, that could send us hurtling down the tunnel of underemployment, unemployment, and at last, poverty. No, no, don’t laugh, this is serious. You might not have gotten out of your post-sack funk by the time you realise that you have fallen below the line. Anirudh Krishna, a professor at Duke University, has documented over 1,000 cases of people who fell into poverty, and only some of whom managed to escape it. He conducted his search throughout India and Kenya, and revealed that poverty arises from a series of mishaps. One broken leg, one lost job, one sick family member and you find yourself below the line. And it is this chance of slipping (literally), coupled with humongous college and healthcare costs, that force us Millennials to hope against hope to strive for perfection at every living moment. Thus, here we stand at the brink of a period of flux and change. Our generation’s defining moment has come and gone in 2008, we are just afraid another one might come along too soon. We might well be the first generation in decades to earn less than our parents. We will delay our marriages as well as moving out of home. Yes, buying a home now is exponentially tougher than 30 years ago. Deal with it. And you have a problem with that? We don’t, we have no choice.  Welcome to the future (FML).</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">United in Pay, Divided in Dues</title>
      <link href="/United-in-pay" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="United in Pay, Divided in Dues" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:14:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:14:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/United-in-pay</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/United-in-pay">&lt;p&gt;India’s Jet Airways may have shut down all operations, but they are not the only
ones with their international business up in flames due to a financial crisis.
The United Nations has been jostling with its latest set of money problems as
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not been living under a rock for the past couple of weeks, you must
have already come across numerous articles like these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//united-in-pay-1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost every publication on the Internet that you could think of has been
reeling from this news and successfully copy-pasting news from one another.
Whichever side you look at, whatever your source is, it does not make a
difference. There have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=moYojoQsedU&quot;&gt;YouTube
videos&lt;/a&gt;, Facebook posts, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5hJzKSJCtn8&quot;&gt;TV
monologues&lt;/a&gt; and private rants about
it. The same thing, boxed up and packaged differently, again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ok! The United Nations owes India money, lots of money. Now get over it”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the discussion is that it is pointed in the wrong direction and
the whole narrative is messed up. To be honest, the United Nations is not really
at fault here. When you have a situation like this, news consumers tend to
simplify the news in their terms and react to it in the most primitive way
possible: by losing their minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//united-in-pay-2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, let’s get down to business. The United Nations is under a financial
crisis of unusual proportions. It is facing severe shortages in its Regular
Budget compensation, as well as its Peacekeeping Budget, which is the main
reason why they are finding it tough to repay their dues to the
Police-Contributing Countries (PCCs) and Troop-Contributing Countries (TCCs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of the beginning of April 2019, the United Nations is yet to complete $256
million in total payments, with the likes of India, Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan
and Rwanda each being &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/defence/un-owes-india-usd-38-million-for-peacekeeping-operations-unsg-report/articleshow/68904063.cms&quot;&gt;owed $23-38
million&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation has a direct link with the state of the United Nations’ cash
balance, which has fallen by $735 million since the beginning of the decade. It
currently stands at an abysmal -$323 million (yes, the minus sign is a negative
balance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could such a dangerous cash crunch bite the UN at this point of time? To
understand things, we have to get a better understanding of the way the UN gets
its money to function. It is a bit complex, but if you know basic maths and
possess an above-average attention span, then you will definitely get a grip of
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it works like this. The United Nations decides the amount that each country
should pay to the Regular Budget, based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/ny.gnp.mktp.cd&quot;&gt;Gross National Income
(GNI)&lt;/a&gt; of the respective
country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It then makes a series of adjustments based on the amount of external debt of
the country, whether the country has a very low per-capita GNI and if it belongs
to the list of Least Developed Countries or not. If so, the contributions by the
country will be capped at 0.01% of the total budget. Also, every country must
pay at least 0.001% of the budget, called the minimum pay adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and lastly, if a country’s share exceeds 22%, it will be brought down to and
capped at 22% of the total budget amount. The United States whose estimated
share is 23.069% is the only country that is getting a discount, in having to
pay only 22%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a great infographic from &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/author/ashendrukqz/&quot;&gt;Amanda
Shendruk&lt;/a&gt; of Quartz.com, who sums it up
perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India’s Jet Airways may have shut down all operations, but they are not the only ones with their international business up in flames due to a financial crisis. The United Nations has been jostling with its latest set of money problems as well. If you have not been living under a rock for the past couple of weeks, you must have already come across numerous articles like these. Almost every publication on the Internet that you could think of has been reeling from this news and successfully copy-pasting news from one another. Whichever side you look at, whatever your source is, it does not make a difference. There have been YouTube videos, Facebook posts, TV monologues and private rants about it. The same thing, boxed up and packaged differently, again and again. “Ok! The United Nations owes India money, lots of money. Now get over it” The problem with the discussion is that it is pointed in the wrong direction and the whole narrative is messed up. To be honest, the United Nations is not really at fault here. When you have a situation like this, news consumers tend to simplify the news in their terms and react to it in the most primitive way possible: by losing their minds. Alright, let’s get down to business. The United Nations is under a financial crisis of unusual proportions. It is facing severe shortages in its Regular Budget compensation, as well as its Peacekeeping Budget, which is the main reason why they are finding it tough to repay their dues to the Police-Contributing Countries (PCCs) and Troop-Contributing Countries (TCCs). As of the beginning of April 2019, the United Nations is yet to complete $256 million in total payments, with the likes of India, Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan and Rwanda each being owed $23-38 million. This situation has a direct link with the state of the United Nations’ cash balance, which has fallen by $735 million since the beginning of the decade. It currently stands at an abysmal -$323 million (yes, the minus sign is a negative balance). How could such a dangerous cash crunch bite the UN at this point of time? To understand things, we have to get a better understanding of the way the UN gets its money to function. It is a bit complex, but if you know basic maths and possess an above-average attention span, then you will definitely get a grip of it. So, it works like this. The United Nations decides the amount that each country should pay to the Regular Budget, based on the Gross National Income (GNI) of the respective country. It then makes a series of adjustments based on the amount of external debt of the country, whether the country has a very low per-capita GNI and if it belongs to the list of Least Developed Countries or not. If so, the contributions by the country will be capped at 0.01% of the total budget. Also, every country must pay at least 0.001% of the budget, called the minimum pay adjustment. Oh, and lastly, if a country’s share exceeds 22%, it will be brought down to and capped at 22% of the total budget amount. The United States whose estimated share is 23.069% is the only country that is getting a discount, in having to pay only 22%. Here is a great infographic from Amanda Shendruk of Quartz.com, who sums it up perfectly.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Exposing the Irrational Voter, Mathematically!</title>
      <link href="/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exposing the Irrational Voter, Mathematically!" />
      <published>2019-04-26T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-26T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter">&lt;p&gt;The Indian elections are right around the corner and the mood is currently in
full swing. Check the papers and you’ll barely find any real estate left for
anything else (but you can always check back with &lt;a href=&quot;http://thepangean.com&quot;&gt;The
Pangean&lt;/a&gt; for more). The juries are out and so are the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloombergquint.com/bq-blue-exclusive/elections-2019-a-manifesto-for-political-manifestos&quot;&gt;manifestos&lt;/a&gt;.
The line between celebrities and candidates gets blurrier by the day and
election campaigns are &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/kolkata/for-mimi-chakraborty-its-all-work-and-no-sleep-before-poll-drill-starts/articleshow/68434360.cms&quot;&gt;quickly turning into promotional
tours&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to feel sorry for the manifestos, which the &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; of voters will
probably have only a glance of at most. Studies at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002205310800080X?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;frontiers of decision
theory&lt;/a&gt;
have shown that when people do not pay attention to candidate policy choices,
uninformed voters end up making decisions based on personalities. This seems to
explain most of the name-calling and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MkqIEWY2-aY&quot;&gt;on-stage
singing&lt;/a&gt; that candidates have
resorted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of all this, three main talking points have emerged: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiainfoline.com/article/general-blog/rising-unemployment-and-the-future-of-indian-youth-118112200298_1.html&quot;&gt;youth
unemployment&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fairobserver.com/region/central_south_asia/indian-farmer-suicides-india-south-asian-world-news-latest-32349/&quot;&gt;farmer’s
perils&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2018/06/27/india-ranked-worlds-most-dangerous-place-for-women-reigniting-debate-about-womens-safety/?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.933d533d9a10&quot;&gt;safety of
women&lt;/a&gt;.
It is no doubt that these topics will be sticking out as the major drivers of
the 2019 Indian election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at some data that will give us some insight into the State of the
Nation. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=2019-01-08%2009:28:37&amp;amp;msec=666&quot;&gt;Centre for Monitoring Indian
Economy&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=2019-01-08%2009:28:37&amp;amp;msec=666&quot;&gt;CMIE&lt;/a&gt;)
estimated that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/opinion/lead/surveying-indias-unemployment-numbers/article26218615.ece&quot;&gt;11 million
jobs&lt;/a&gt;
were lost in 2018 – pushing the unemployment rate to 7.38%. A leaked NSSO report
pegged the unemployment rate at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/unemployment-rate-at-four-decade-high-nsso-survey-compared-past-figures-119020100042_1.html&quot;&gt;6.1%&lt;/a&gt;,
the highest in over four decades. Things do not look so good for our youth at
work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the farmers, the bedrock of our society? Well, this is where
things go further downhill. According to Wholesale Price Index
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://tradingeconomics.com/india/producer-prices-change&quot;&gt;WPI&lt;/a&gt;) data for the
month of December released by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry, the WPI
sub-component for primary food articles has been negative for six consecutive
months beginning July 2018. This is a direct indication of the sliding prices
that farmers have been facing for their produce, which has led to innumerable
suicides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women’s safety is also experiencing issues that India cannot seem to get away
from that have been lingering for far too long and are only getting worse.
According to a recent poll of 548 experts by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://poll2018.trust.org/country/?id=india&quot;&gt;Thomson Reuters
Foundation&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“India ranked 1st among the world’s most dangerous countries for women.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No progress here, ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is dire and the immediate need for change is crystal clear. It is
also understood that this summer the onus is on the people to effect change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can we &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt; the voters? How rational are they when it comes to making
decisions? How rational are &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where our rant comes to an end and the &lt;em&gt;dissection&lt;/em&gt; begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us play a little game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections are only about promises and promises do not hold up most of the time,
so we reduce them to a matter of &lt;em&gt;probability&lt;/em&gt;. Now, let’s see how you and your
choices fare in our mock election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let there be two political parties, A and B, standing in the elections. Party A
promises to reduce unemployment by 20%, with a 100% chance of fulfilling his
promise. Whereas, Party B promises to reduce unemployment by 35%, with a 15 out
of 16 chance of fulfilling his promise. To put it neatly,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;20% unemployment drop, with certainty (100% Guarantee).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;35% unemployment reduction, with 15/16 chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go on. Take your pick. Is it party A or party B? Who would you bank on for the
country’s sake?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, here’s a second case to choose from.  Party A promises a 20% reduction in
unemployment, only now with a 16% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas,
Party B promises 35% fall, with a 15% chance. Restating it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;20% unemployment drop, with a 16% chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;35% unemployment reduction, with a 15% chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, whom did you pick? If you happened to pick Party A in Case 1, then you are
like the majority, who prefer certainty over chance. For those who chose Party B
in the first case, you were ready to take the risk for the greater reward. But
there is nothing wrong with either choice, the real game starts with Case 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what about Case 2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, here’s the bombshell. Case 2 is equal to Case 1 with a one-sixth chance.
That is, Case 2 is the same situation as Case 1, only with a 16% probability.
The change between the party’s probability of fulfilling promises in both cases
was proportional and thus, renders both cases to be the absolute same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if the problem never changed, did your choice of candidates change? From B to
A, or A to B?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you did not, then congratulations, you have
rational preferences. If you did, then there are more than a few things at work
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us try another problem of this sort. Whether or not the government promised
to deposit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businesstoday.in/current/economy-politics/bjp-never-promised-to-deposit-rs-15-lakh-in-people-bank-accounts-rajnath-singh/story/335629.html&quot;&gt;Rs. 15
Lakh&lt;/a&gt;
in everyone’s accounts, it is always possible another party will make a similar
promise in the run-up to the elections. Farmers are definitely in need of severe
financial help, so take Party A and Party B who make the respective
&lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/economy/agriculture/budget-2019-income-support-for-farmers-a-progressive-step-but-not-enough-to-mitigate-stress/articleshow/67802322.cms&quot;&gt;income-support&lt;/a&gt;
promises:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 11,000 a year, with an 11% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 11,000 a year, &lt;b&gt;guaranteed&lt;/b&gt; (100% chance).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance, and Rs 11,000 a year, with an 89%
chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who gets the vote, in each case, this time around? Did you choose the same party
both times, or different parties? Choosing different parties is a sign of
incoherent decision-making. This is because Case 1 is once again of a similar
form as Case 2. There has been no significant change in the factors that should
influence your decision-making. Yet there will be more than a few instances of
people making unidentical choices for Cases 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to do a bit of explaining. Consider these cases as lotteries. Both Party A
and Party B have an 89% chance of not fulfilling any promise in Case 1. But
wait? Didn’t Party B promise a 10% chance? So it gives us (100% -10%=) 90%
chance of empty-handed farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, there is the existence of a lottery within a lottery; a &lt;strong&gt;compound&lt;/strong&gt;
lottery, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lottery within is actually a 10 out of 11 chance of receiving Rs 15000 and 1
out of 11 chance of getting Rs 0. So when it is nested inside the outer lottery
of Party B, we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 0&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is essentially,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance and Rs 0, with a 90% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, things are getting discombobulated in your head, but stay with me.
Eventually, what we are left with is a much detailed way to re-write and
represent Cases 1 and 2 as &lt;em&gt;nested&lt;/em&gt; probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: 11% x &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt; +   &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;11% x [&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)&lt;/span&gt;]   +  &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: 11% x &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt; +   &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;11% x [&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)&lt;/span&gt;]   + &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parts marked in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Red&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are the actual &lt;em&gt;determinants&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; factors
when it comes to decision-making between the two parties. The segments marked in
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;Blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are offered by &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; parties and thus, should not be a determining
factor in rational choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you ended up choosing A in Case 1 and B in Case 2 (or vice versa), you
have just chosen two different answers for the same problem. Do you see it now?
That is where rational preferences are violated and we can now find our
&lt;em&gt;irrational voter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this, we come to the origins of the problem. The lack of coherence
empirically observed above is called the &lt;strong&gt;Allais Paradox&lt;/strong&gt;, and has been the
talk of game theorists and psychologists for years. First published in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wolfweb.unr.edu/homepage/pingle/Teaching/BADM%20791/Week%206%20Decision%20Making%20Under%20Uncertainty/Allais%20Paradox%201953.pdf&quot;&gt;1953&lt;/a&gt;,
in the &lt;em&gt;Econometrica&lt;/em&gt; journal by French economist Maurice Allais, the Allais
Paradox was observed among subjects who, when presented with choices such as the
ones above, made snap decisions that were proven to be incoherent upon further
study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not everyone got it wrong, a significant number of people made the
error which prompted him to wonder whether there was more than just rationality
behind human choices. So the Allais Paradox started off as more of a standout
against conventional rationality theory, than as the rationality test that it
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/zJZvoiwydJ5zvzTHK/the-allais-paradox&quot;&gt;has evolved to
today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maurice Allais did end up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/1988/summary/&quot;&gt;winning the 1988 Nobel Prize in
Economics&lt;/a&gt;
but it was not until 20 years after it was first published, that the Allais
Paradox was brought back to the mainstream by Daniel Kahneman. In a way, the
Allais Paradox was what got Nobel laureate Daniel Kahneman (2002 Nobel laureate)
into economics. He along with Amos Tversky, were two young psychologists back in
the 1970s who came across this paradox and were so intrigued by the study of
human approach towards uncertainty that they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1207/S15427579JPFM0402_01&quot;&gt;opened up new
dimensions&lt;/a&gt; in
the world of economics and &lt;a href=&quot;http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/economics/laureates/2002/&quot;&gt;decision-making under
uncertainty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maurice Allais had made one of the foremost and yet perplexing dives into human
rationality and for that, today, the world is in a better position to understand
human behaviour and decision-making. And while we are on the topic of making
decisions, we get back to the decision of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This election may be driven by 3 &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; issues: unemployment, farmers and
women’s protection. But at the end of the day, it is the people who &lt;em&gt;drive&lt;/em&gt;
elections. Yet what we often overlook is what drives the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; and their
&lt;em&gt;choices&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we as smart as we think we are? Does being &lt;em&gt;irrational&lt;/em&gt; only mean being
‘unreasonable’ or ‘baseless’ as the Dictionary says? Or is there more to this
than meets the eye &lt;em&gt;or brain&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that note, we ask you to think twice before calling someone else irrational.
Oh, and yes, don’t forget to think twice before voting. Happy elections!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*31st May, 2019 marks the 108th Birth Anniversary of French physicist and
economist Maurice Allais, best known for his contributions to the neoclassical
synthesis and the Allais Paradox.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian elections are right around the corner and the mood is currently in full swing. Check the papers and you’ll barely find any real estate left for anything else (but you can always check back with The Pangean for more). The juries are out and so are the manifestos. The line between celebrities and candidates gets blurrier by the day and election campaigns are quickly turning into promotional tours. One has to feel sorry for the manifestos, which the majority of voters will probably have only a glance of at most. Studies at the frontiers of decision theory have shown that when people do not pay attention to candidate policy choices, uninformed voters end up making decisions based on personalities. This seems to explain most of the name-calling and on-stage singing that candidates have resorted to. In the midst of all this, three main talking points have emerged: youth unemployment, farmer’s perils and the safety of women. It is no doubt that these topics will be sticking out as the major drivers of the 2019 Indian election. Here’s a look at some data that will give us some insight into the State of the Nation. The Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE) estimated that 11 million jobs were lost in 2018 – pushing the unemployment rate to 7.38%. A leaked NSSO report pegged the unemployment rate at 6.1%, the highest in over four decades. Things do not look so good for our youth at work. But what about the farmers, the bedrock of our society? Well, this is where things go further downhill. According to Wholesale Price Index (WPI) data for the month of December released by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry, the WPI sub-component for primary food articles has been negative for six consecutive months beginning July 2018. This is a direct indication of the sliding prices that farmers have been facing for their produce, which has led to innumerable suicides. Women’s safety is also experiencing issues that India cannot seem to get away from that have been lingering for far too long and are only getting worse. According to a recent poll of 548 experts by the Thomson Reuters Foundation, “India ranked 1st among the world’s most dangerous countries for women.” No progress here, ladies and gentlemen. The situation is dire and the immediate need for change is crystal clear. It is also understood that this summer the onus is on the people to effect change. But can we trust the voters? How rational are they when it comes to making decisions? How rational are you? This is where our rant comes to an end and the dissection begins. Let us play a little game. Elections are only about promises and promises do not hold up most of the time, so we reduce them to a matter of probability. Now, let’s see how you and your choices fare in our mock election. Let there be two political parties, A and B, standing in the elections. Party A promises to reduce unemployment by 20%, with a 100% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas, Party B promises to reduce unemployment by 35%, with a 15 out of 16 chance of fulfilling his promise. To put it neatly, Case 1 A: 20% unemployment drop, with certainty (100% Guarantee). B: 35% unemployment reduction, with 15/16 chance. Go on. Take your pick. Is it party A or party B? Who would you bank on for the country’s sake? Ok, here’s a second case to choose from.  Party A promises a 20% reduction in unemployment, only now with a 16% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas, Party B promises 35% fall, with a 15% chance. Restating it, Case 2 A: 20% unemployment drop, with a 16% chance. B: 35% unemployment reduction, with a 15% chance. So, whom did you pick? If you happened to pick Party A in Case 1, then you are like the majority, who prefer certainty over chance. For those who chose Party B in the first case, you were ready to take the risk for the greater reward. But there is nothing wrong with either choice, the real game starts with Case 2. Now, what about Case 2? Well, here’s the bombshell. Case 2 is equal to Case 1 with a one-sixth chance. That is, Case 2 is the same situation as Case 1, only with a 16% probability. The change between the party’s probability of fulfilling promises in both cases was proportional and thus, renders both cases to be the absolute same. So if the problem never changed, did your choice of candidates change? From B to A, or A to B? If you did not, then congratulations, you have rational preferences. If you did, then there are more than a few things at work here. Let us try another problem of this sort. Whether or not the government promised to deposit Rs. 15 Lakh in everyone’s accounts, it is always possible another party will make a similar promise in the run-up to the elections. Farmers are definitely in need of severe financial help, so take Party A and Party B who make the respective income-support promises: Case 1 A: Rs 11,000 a year, with an 11% chance B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance Case 2 A: Rs 11,000 a year, guaranteed (100% chance). B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance, and Rs 11,000 a year, with an 89% chance Who gets the vote, in each case, this time around? Did you choose the same party both times, or different parties? Choosing different parties is a sign of incoherent decision-making. This is because Case 1 is once again of a similar form as Case 2. There has been no significant change in the factors that should influence your decision-making. Yet there will be more than a few instances of people making unidentical choices for Cases 1 and 2. Time to do a bit of explaining. Consider these cases as lotteries. Both Party A and Party B have an 89% chance of not fulfilling any promise in Case 1. But wait? Didn’t Party B promise a 10% chance? So it gives us (100% -10%=) 90% chance of empty-handed farmers. Here, there is the existence of a lottery within a lottery; a compound lottery, so to speak. The lottery within is actually a 10 out of 11 chance of receiving Rs 15000 and 1 out of 11 chance of getting Rs 0. So when it is nested inside the outer lottery of Party B, we get B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 0 Which is essentially, B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance and Rs 0, with a 90% chance I know, things are getting discombobulated in your head, but stay with me. Eventually, what we are left with is a much detailed way to re-write and represent Cases 1 and 2 as nested probabilities. Case 1 A: 11% x Rs 11,000 +   89% x Rs 0 B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   +  89% x Rs 0 Case 2 A: 11% x Rs 11,000 +   89% x Rs 11,000 B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 11,000 The parts marked in Red are the actual determinants and the only factors when it comes to decision-making between the two parties. The segments marked in Blue are offered by both parties and thus, should not be a determining factor in rational choosing. So if you ended up choosing A in Case 1 and B in Case 2 (or vice versa), you have just chosen two different answers for the same problem. Do you see it now? That is where rational preferences are violated and we can now find our irrational voter. After all this, we come to the origins of the problem. The lack of coherence empirically observed above is called the Allais Paradox, and has been the talk of game theorists and psychologists for years. First published in 1953, in the Econometrica journal by French economist Maurice Allais, the Allais Paradox was observed among subjects who, when presented with choices such as the ones above, made snap decisions that were proven to be incoherent upon further study. Although not everyone got it wrong, a significant number of people made the error which prompted him to wonder whether there was more than just rationality behind human choices. So the Allais Paradox started off as more of a standout against conventional rationality theory, than as the rationality test that it has evolved to today. Maurice Allais did end up winning the 1988 Nobel Prize in Economics but it was not until 20 years after it was first published, that the Allais Paradox was brought back to the mainstream by Daniel Kahneman. In a way, the Allais Paradox was what got Nobel laureate Daniel Kahneman (2002 Nobel laureate) into economics. He along with Amos Tversky, were two young psychologists back in the 1970s who came across this paradox and were so intrigued by the study of human approach towards uncertainty that they opened up new dimensions in the world of economics and decision-making under uncertainty. Maurice Allais had made one of the foremost and yet perplexing dives into human rationality and for that, today, the world is in a better position to understand human behaviour and decision-making. And while we are on the topic of making decisions, we get back to the decision of the year. This election may be driven by 3 central issues: unemployment, farmers and women’s protection. But at the end of the day, it is the people who drive elections. Yet what we often overlook is what drives the people and their choices. Are we as smart as we think we are? Does being irrational only mean being ‘unreasonable’ or ‘baseless’ as the Dictionary says? Or is there more to this than meets the eye or brain? On that note, we ask you to think twice before calling someone else irrational. Oh, and yes, don’t forget to think twice before voting. Happy elections! *31st May, 2019 marks the 108th Birth Anniversary of French physicist and economist Maurice Allais, best known for his contributions to the neoclassical synthesis and the Allais Paradox.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Apple’s China problems ft. Future Apple and the Coase Conjecture</title>
      <link href="/Apple-China-Problems" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple’s China problems ft. Future Apple and the Coase Conjecture" />
      <published>2019-03-28T02:03:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T02:03:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Apple-China-Problems</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Apple-China-Problems">&lt;p&gt;The Apple craze in China is officially over a decade old. During my days in
China, more often than not, I would take the early bus to Tianjin, along with 20
people glued to the glare of their phone screens. Take a walk across a busy
intersection on a weekday morning and you will find dozens of people marching to
work, busy on their smartphones. Not just any smartphones―the Apple iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/lb38KXlz1F2TllikTfKpV3QKflZ14w92D3AnAwq8xIDHYLYtaELdYAwVWzngy9CZL74x2d-m5T_5E5xvwu8CCnNjQQZdB_1EhYWv6BH0lrHxWevAoriAgQAx-uvdWf0jM9KdcirH&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/1509730264519.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why I did not specify which models are most popular is that the
iPhone craze in China is more about class than tech specs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“The people don’t bother which generation it is, as long as it’s an iPhone”--
Mobile store owner, Tianjin, China
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 4th Generation all the way to the latest models, the Chinese make a big
deal out of the iPhone, even if they are not the ones to show it. Despite this,
Apple’s returns for the holiday quarter have not been good. One may attribute
this to the slowing Chinese economy but there are other factors at play. Things
have turned so bad that Apple has had to scale down its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investors.com/news/apple-chinese-iphones-demand-revenue/&quot;&gt;revenue forecasts by an
estimated $5 billion- $9
billion&lt;/a&gt;.
The announcement (made way back in January) sent its stock
&lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/aapl/&quot;&gt;(AAPL)&lt;/a&gt; tumbling, falling by about 10
percentage points, though it has managed to recover since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The struggle for Apple in the Chinese market was real and people were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apnews.com/e0a2c907669c4821814763035b562c55&quot;&gt;simply
not buying iPhones&lt;/a&gt; as
they found the price tag too demanding. What seemed to be the problem? Was there
a new competitor on the block? If so, who was causing the disruption?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is pretty simple, it was Apple - yes, Apple from the Future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break this down, we have to take a look at the Cupertino smartphone giant and
its position in the Chinese market. Yes, they make smartphones, but not just any
smartphone. They are makers of the most sought-after digital product in China.
No, not the BlackBerry. With an iPhone comes class, finesse, style, elegance,
efficiency, exclusivity and a burning hole in the pocket. This is where Apple
separates itself from the Huaweis and the Xiaomis of the market. To be honest,
Apple is a monopoly, with no competition in the foreseeable future. But wait,
our good friend Ronald Coase, a Nobel-winning economist, has something important
to say…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“[A]s soon as the consumers who are willing to pay the monopoly price make
their purchases, the monopolist has an incentive to lower his price and sell to
some of the remaining consumers. Immediately after the next round of sales, the
monopolist would find it worthwhile to lower his price yet again. This process
would continue until all buyers with reservation prices above marginal cost are
served. But rational consumers would anticipate this rapid fall of prices and
wait until the market price reaches its ultimate level before making any
purchases”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that went over your head, do not panic. What he means to say is that in a
market for a durable good (whose resale is not possible) with only one primary
seller (monopoly), once the first lot of goods is sold at a particular price,
the remaining goods are sold at a lower price. Now of the further remaining
goods, some are sold at an even lower price than before and those still
remaining shall be sold even cheaper and this goes on. If a rational buyer
anticipates this and waits for the price to keep falling, he can nab the good at
a much lower price than before. This is what we call the Coase Conjecture. In
effect, the Coase Conjecture holds that a monopolist faces competition from
future incarnations of himself, even though he is the only producer in the
market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we take an iPhone (any generation) to be a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bgr.com/2018/05/28/iphone-x-vs-iphone-7-case-screen-scratches/&quot;&gt;durable&lt;/a&gt;
good, as most of the Chinese market prefers it to be, and Apple as the
monopolist, there will be competition faced by Apple. From whom one may ask?
From the Apple of tomorrow, its future self. And as a result, Apple will be
forced to drive down prices to encourage purchases. Oh, look, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notebookcheck.net/Apple-cuts-iPhone-8-and-XR-prices-in-China-by-20-percent.394146.0.html&quot;&gt;it’s already
taking
place&lt;/a&gt;.
Time to get yourself an iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/ZTgkOCzIQP3kJpWuDzoY5rOmUl3jCg11OTrIRKWgguK_Qc8JXos7VycoRldaD2_HHOTOFTtfklC5r8vT2j8JDSeOcyM1IPjIfgIDQmCm78DiUmHKLevdmnuwMw2le3Yx_MSrDOTk&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/gettyimages-93081350.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people in China know this well enough and this is why they keep sitting on
the iPhones, waiting for prices to drop. That, ladies and gentlemen, is exactly
how most of the Chinese middle class enjoys an excess of iPhones. Nevermind them
showing off models released six years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that there is little Apple can do to rid themselves of such a
predicament. They could try introducing a new spec of such a high quality that
people simply &lt;em&gt;have to have&lt;/em&gt; the new model. Or, as an alternative, they could
simply refuse to lower the price of new models for such a period of time that
people are practically forced into a purchase. But neither of these seem like
realistic solutions. The former will likely fail due to the notional loyalty to
&lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; iPhone. The latter will fall short also, as long as older models continue
to function. The question is then, what next for Apple in the Chinese market? Is
there an unexploited strategy waiting to lure the Chinese public into parting
with their hard earned cash, or is Apple destined to be a fashion item?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Apple craze in China is officially over a decade old. During my days in China, more often than not, I would take the early bus to Tianjin, along with 20 people glued to the glare of their phone screens. Take a walk across a busy intersection on a weekday morning and you will find dozens of people marching to work, busy on their smartphones. Not just any smartphones―the Apple iPhone. The reason why I did not specify which models are most popular is that the iPhone craze in China is more about class than tech specs. “The people don’t bother which generation it is, as long as it’s an iPhone”-- Mobile store owner, Tianjin, China From 4th Generation all the way to the latest models, the Chinese make a big deal out of the iPhone, even if they are not the ones to show it. Despite this, Apple’s returns for the holiday quarter have not been good. One may attribute this to the slowing Chinese economy but there are other factors at play. Things have turned so bad that Apple has had to scale down its revenue forecasts by an estimated $5 billion- $9 billion. The announcement (made way back in January) sent its stock (AAPL) tumbling, falling by about 10 percentage points, though it has managed to recover since. The struggle for Apple in the Chinese market was real and people were simply not buying iPhones as they found the price tag too demanding. What seemed to be the problem? Was there a new competitor on the block? If so, who was causing the disruption? The answer is pretty simple, it was Apple - yes, Apple from the Future. To break this down, we have to take a look at the Cupertino smartphone giant and its position in the Chinese market. Yes, they make smartphones, but not just any smartphone. They are makers of the most sought-after digital product in China. No, not the BlackBerry. With an iPhone comes class, finesse, style, elegance, efficiency, exclusivity and a burning hole in the pocket. This is where Apple separates itself from the Huaweis and the Xiaomis of the market. To be honest, Apple is a monopoly, with no competition in the foreseeable future. But wait, our good friend Ronald Coase, a Nobel-winning economist, has something important to say… “[A]s soon as the consumers who are willing to pay the monopoly price make their purchases, the monopolist has an incentive to lower his price and sell to some of the remaining consumers. Immediately after the next round of sales, the monopolist would find it worthwhile to lower his price yet again. This process would continue until all buyers with reservation prices above marginal cost are served. But rational consumers would anticipate this rapid fall of prices and wait until the market price reaches its ultimate level before making any purchases” If that went over your head, do not panic. What he means to say is that in a market for a durable good (whose resale is not possible) with only one primary seller (monopoly), once the first lot of goods is sold at a particular price, the remaining goods are sold at a lower price. Now of the further remaining goods, some are sold at an even lower price than before and those still remaining shall be sold even cheaper and this goes on. If a rational buyer anticipates this and waits for the price to keep falling, he can nab the good at a much lower price than before. This is what we call the Coase Conjecture. In effect, the Coase Conjecture holds that a monopolist faces competition from future incarnations of himself, even though he is the only producer in the market. Now, if we take an iPhone (any generation) to be a durable good, as most of the Chinese market prefers it to be, and Apple as the monopolist, there will be competition faced by Apple. From whom one may ask? From the Apple of tomorrow, its future self. And as a result, Apple will be forced to drive down prices to encourage purchases. Oh, look, it’s already taking place. Time to get yourself an iPhone. The people in China know this well enough and this is why they keep sitting on the iPhones, waiting for prices to drop. That, ladies and gentlemen, is exactly how most of the Chinese middle class enjoys an excess of iPhones. Nevermind them showing off models released six years ago. It appears that there is little Apple can do to rid themselves of such a predicament. They could try introducing a new spec of such a high quality that people simply have to have the new model. Or, as an alternative, they could simply refuse to lower the price of new models for such a period of time that people are practically forced into a purchase. But neither of these seem like realistic solutions. The former will likely fail due to the notional loyalty to any iPhone. The latter will fall short also, as long as older models continue to function. The question is then, what next for Apple in the Chinese market? Is there an unexploited strategy waiting to lure the Chinese public into parting with their hard earned cash, or is Apple destined to be a fashion item?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Higher Ups: Appointments and Disappointments</title>
      <link href="/The-Higher-Ups" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Higher Ups: Appointments and Disappointments" />
      <published>2019-02-15T01:50:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-15T01:50:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Higher-Ups</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Higher-Ups">&lt;p&gt;In this article, we take a look at the people in the past decade and more who had exponential burdens placed on their shoulders and examine how they fared. The men and women who moved markets and sentiments; whose names were heard on the internet and in households across the globe, setting examples to follow and learn from, for the generation ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mario-draghi-ecb&quot;&gt;Mario Draghi (ECB)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/55/Mario_Draghi_-_World_Economic_Forum_Annual_Meeting_2012.jpg/1024px-Mario_Draghi_-_World_Economic_Forum_Annual_Meeting_2012.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Mario-Draghi.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; Italy &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; La Sapienza University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mario Draghi has been in and out of &lt;i&gt;Most Influential&lt;/i&gt; around the world for more than a decade, topping out at number 2 on &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/worlds-greatest-leaders/mario-draghi-2/&quot;&gt;Fortune greatest&lt;/a&gt; world leaders. Before taking Jean-Claude Trichet’s place at the top of the European Central Bank, he had served as the Governor of the Bank of Italy and was elected as Chairman of the Financial Stability Forum of 2006. But his biggest achievements came in the form of righting the ship that was the European economy, which was on the brink of collapse with a host of countries running on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=10&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjh6Nj26aPgAhULS48KHV9fDZkQFjAJegQIChAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.telegraph.co.uk%2Fnews%2F0%2Feuropean-debt-crisis-not-just-greece-drowning-debt%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0sq0KE3R4uEWXWRaxmklU1&quot;&gt;failing&lt;/a&gt; economies, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwivr_fr6aPgAhUGSY8KHc-uAcsQFjABegQICBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.thebalance.com%2Fwhat-is-the-greece-debt-crisis-3305525&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1nusWDPX7zHeB3hayomLwC&quot;&gt;huge debts&lt;/a&gt; and crippling deficits. He said he would  do “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pq1V0aPEO3c&quot;&gt;…whatever it takes…&lt;/a&gt;” to preserve the Euro and so he did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only time will tell how this proven leader will stand up to the task of a Britain-less EU economy, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: President of the European Central Bank&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jean-claude-trichet-ecb&quot;&gt;Jean-Claude Trichet (ECB)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/117994717@N06/15890096265&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Jean-Claude-Trichet.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; France &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; University of Paris, Sciences Po&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming off the worst &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/1401696/French-candidate-to-head-Euro-bank-faces-fraud-trial.html&quot;&gt;banking scandal&lt;/a&gt; in French History, Jean-Claude Trichet was able to successfully manoeuvre himself out of the French Treasury and into the leading post at the ECB. It was under his Presidency that Europe plunged into the Great Recession of the 21st Century, and many still believe that he should get most of the blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was 2009 when an IMF report showing telling signs of a Greek default came out, but Mr Trichet was not ready to budge, standing firmly in resistance stating, “no European country could ever be allowed to go bankrupt”. Instead of fixing the problems &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/business/global/europes-two-years-of-denials-trapped-greece.html?_r=1&quot;&gt;he chose to resist any contemplation of a default&lt;/a&gt; until October 2011, when a consensus to devalue Greek bonds was reached. He resigned as President before the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Board of Directors, Airbus Group&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;janet-yellen-federal-reserve&quot;&gt;Janet Yellen (Federal Reserve)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/fordschool/33842410502&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Janet-Yellen.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; United States of America &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Brown University, Yale University&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the huge success stories of the last decade, Janet Yellen has done more than defy expectations and targets set for the economy. Starting her term as Vice-Chair in 2010, and later serving as 14th Chair of the Federal Reserve, she replaced the outgoing Ben Bernanke whose $3 trillion stimulus package she &lt;a href=&quot;http://money.cnn.com/2013/11/14/news/economy/janet-yellen-confirmation-hearing/&quot;&gt;defended throughout&lt;/a&gt; the Senate hearings. She has successfully overseen a gradual return to full employment as well as an increase in real income growth. She has even managed to scale back the stimulus packages to the economy while simultaneously leaving inflation rates stagnant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//higherups-graph.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although considered to be a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20131113032024/http://www.sfgate.com/business/investopedia/article/Janet-Yellen-Background-And-Philosophy-4902126.php&quot;&gt;dove&lt;/a&gt;”, she has gradually raised interest rates in the past few years from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/robertlenzner/2017/12/16/janet-yellen-leaves-us-with-goldilocks-economy/#4067146794b6&quot;&gt;1.5% to 2.25%&lt;/a&gt;. Donald Trump may not approve of her but the people definitely do, as she has left a great inheritance for Trump’s nominee Jay Powell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Distinguished Fellow in Residence at Brookings Institution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;john-stumpf-wells-fargo&quot;&gt;John Stumpf (Wells Fargo)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/hieronymus/3635257139&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//John-Stumpf.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; United States of America &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; St Cloud State University, University of Minnesota&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Stumpf was the commander and captain of a $1.9 trillion empire. Today he has lost it all; well, nearly all of it. Rising steadily through the ranks from 1998 he finally assumed the position of Chairman and CEO of Wells Fargo Bank, the fourth-largest bank in the US by total assets, and it was all going well as Wells Fargo emerged as arguably the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwigwbiEqqTgAhWOT30KHdKfDK8QFjABegQIBxAF&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.fool.com%2Finvesting%2Fgeneral%2F2015%2F11%2F04%2Fwells-fargo-is-the-biggest-bank-in-america-accordi.aspx&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3kFZ7WWDtQhkoh2bN7nYuX&quot;&gt;biggest player&lt;/a&gt; in the American economy. In December 2008, when the world was in the middle of an economic collapse, he led the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20121213150723/https://www.wellsfargo.com/about/corporate/executive_officers/stumpf&quot;&gt;purchase of Wachovia bank&lt;/a&gt;, one of the biggest mergers in the history of banking. However, in September of 2016, the bank was charged with opening &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/oct/12/wells-fargo-ceo-john-stumpf-retires-fake-accounts&quot;&gt;2 million accounts without customers’ permission&lt;/a&gt;, just so that they could meet the sales quotas of the company. Slapped with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/oct/14/john-stumpf-retirement-wells-fargo-ceo-jail-time&quot;&gt;$185 million fine&lt;/a&gt; by US regulators for their fraudulent activities, John Stumpf had to eventually resign in the wake of the disaster. His story is still a matter of public hatred, as he got away with a hefty &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usatoday.com/story/money/markets/2016/10/12/wells-fargo-ceo-retires-under-fire/91964778/&quot;&gt;$134 million paycheck&lt;/a&gt;, although a Wells Fargo spokeswoman had this to say, “Mr.John Stump will not receive any severance payment”. At least when it comes to banking, no severance payment doesn’t mean severance from a payday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Just bought a $3.77M mansion in the Arizona valley&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;christine-lagarde-imf&quot;&gt;Christine Lagarde (IMF)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1e/Women_in_Economic_Decision-making_Christine_Lagarde_%288414041294%29.jpg/1024px-Women_in_Economic_Decision-making_Christine_Lagarde_%288414041294%29.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Christine-Lagarde.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; France &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Paris West University, Institute of Political Studies- Aix&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2011 the IMF made history by electing Christine Lagarde as its first ever woman head. It was also slap-bang in the middle of the European sovereign debt crisis and Europe needed her, to call her strict or strong would be an understatement. She has repeatedly shown her unforgiving nature, especially when it comes to doing what needs to be done, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/financialcrisis/9293602/Irate-Greeks-vilify-IMF-chief-on-Facebook-after-she-brands-them-tax-dodgers.html&quot;&gt;Greece knows it far too well&lt;/a&gt;. If you were to ask her about the way she handles such issues, she &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vogue.com/article/christine-lagarde-changing-of-the-guard&quot;&gt;says that she relates&lt;/a&gt; to “Adam Smith— that is liberal”. Initially hesitant towards writing off Greek debts, she had repeatedly asked for austerity measures to be carried out. But when the people of Greece decided &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/may/25/payback-time-lagarde-greeks&quot;&gt;to just not pay&lt;/a&gt; their taxes, she was forced to take the initiative of creating a rescue package for the debt-ridden country. When she knew that the help arranged was still &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424127887324299104578527202781667088&quot;&gt;not enough&lt;/a&gt; to save the country, she decided to finally write off the debts and was even ready to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2015/jul/17/imf-steps-up-greek-bailout-criticism-debt-relief-package&quot;&gt;call for debt relief on a global scale&lt;/a&gt; on behalf of the IMF. This IMF MD is as close as an “Iron lady” as you can find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Managing Director and Chair of the IMF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;raghuram-rajan-rbi&quot;&gt;Raghuram Rajan (RBI)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d5/Raghuram_Rajan%2C_IMF_69MS040421048l.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Raghuram-Rajan.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; India &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; IIT Delhi, IIM Ahmedabad, MIT Sloan School of Management&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He started out as an assistant professor of finance in 1991 at the Chicago Booth School of Business, but his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiZrrP0t6TgAhXIEHIKHUUpBkgQFjABegQICRAC&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Ffaculty.chicagobooth.edu%2Fluigi.zingales%2Fpapers%2Fresearch%2Fcapintro.pdf&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0fVqHg4mb3p14Lobhs89dX&quot;&gt;Saving Capitalism from the Capitalists&lt;/a&gt; caught the eye of the IMF’s first deputy managing director Anne Krueger, who appointed him as the Chief Economist. This made him the first Indian and the youngest ever at his post. He helped the IMF make huge strides in financial sector analysis and led increasing research into their effects on a macro level. In 2012, he was appointed chief economic adviser of India and even prepared the Economic Survey of India for the year. It was less than a year later that he was appointed Governor of the Reserve Bank of India. It was under his tenure that India experienced a fall of 6 percentage points in its retail inflation rate and a historically low rate of wholesale inflation. With global support on his side, India’s foreign exchange reserves &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiqxbnlt6TgAhWKF3IKHXy1ALEQFjAAegQICRAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fqz.com%2Findia%2F774034%2Fa-comparison-of-indias-economy-when-raghuram-rajan-took-charge-at-rbi-and-now-as-urjit-patel-steps-in%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1c_zvCu7ALa8t76Xctf9lk&quot;&gt;ballooned to $380 million in a matter of only two years&lt;/a&gt; and with the election of the new government, prospects of the Indian economy were as bright as ever, despite the many tussles with the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, his will to return to academia got the better of him and the government wanted to head in a different direction (Note: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwja6vfHt6TgAhVab30KHY1IDuYQFjABegQIBxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Findianexpress.com%2Farticle%2Fbusiness%2Feconomy%2Fdemonetisation-rbi-gst-raghuram-rajan-economic-growth-5440435%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1qs88yKq6IarMKs5iGYswa&quot;&gt;Demonetization&lt;/a&gt;) while he preferred taxation to tackle the issues of black money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Katherine Dusak Miller Distinguished Service Professor of Finance at University of Chicago&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;zhou-xiaochuan-pboc&quot;&gt;Zhou Xiaochuan (PBOC)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/f/fb/Secretary_Geithner_and_People%27s_Bank_of_China_Governor_Zhou_Xiaochuan%2C_following_a_working_lunch_on_May_23%2C_2010_in_Beijing.jpg/1220px-Secretary_Geithner_and_People%27s_Bank_of_China_Governor_Zhou_Xiaochuan%2C_following_a_working_lunch_on_May_23%2C_2010_in_Beijing.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Zhou-Xiaochuan.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; China&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Beijing Institute of Chemical Technology, Tsinghua University&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After serving as president of China Construction Bank and Chairman of the China Securities Regulatory Commission, he was appointed as governor of the People’s Bank of China by Premier Zhu Rongji, a tenure which lasted a whopping 15 years. Unlike its contemporaries from across the globe, the People’s Bank of China is not independent. Almost everything has to go through the State Council whose members prefer to have low interest rates and lots of credit. Yet it is through these confines that Zhou Xiaochuan has managed to manoeuvre policies &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/2013/03/16/china-parliament-zhou-idUSL3N0C7CV920130316&quot;&gt;in and outside of his jurisdiction&lt;/a&gt; that truly set up the Chinese economy as an international investment opportunity. He is responsible for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/0631ab2e-2387-11e8-8138-569c3d7ab0a7&quot;&gt;internationalising the renminbi, encouraging the growth of online banking&lt;/a&gt; throughout the nation and clearing up more than $800 million in bad loans. The man is considered among the most academically capable among the Chinese leadership, has an increasingly friendly openness toward the media and is the only Chinese higher-up who has been published in a Western Journal. Add to that his attitude toward markets,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;If the market can solve the problem, let the market do it. I am just a referee. I am neither a sportsman nor a coach.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you probably have one of the biggest reasons why China has roared into the foray as a global economic powerhouse over the past decade. After opening up the Chinese economy through a legacy of financial reform, he stepped down in 2018, just as the fear of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble&quot;&gt;Chinese slowdown&lt;/a&gt; was materialising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Member of China Investment Corp.’s (CIC) International Advisory Council&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this article, we take a look at the people in the past decade and more who had exponential burdens placed on their shoulders and examine how they fared. The men and women who moved markets and sentiments; whose names were heard on the internet and in households across the globe, setting examples to follow and learn from, for the generation ahead.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Oil Trickled Through the Decade</title>
      <link href="/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Oil Trickled Through the Decade" />
      <published>2019-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; It all started with the oil. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 20, 2010, the &lt;i&gt;Deepwater Horizon&lt;/i&gt;, an oil drilling rig owned by British Petroleum in the Gulf of Mexico, exploded. It was the largest marine oil spill in the history of the petroleum industry; an estimated 4.9 million barrels of crude oil in over 87 days was supposed to have been spilled. At the time, 126 crew members were on board and eleven workers were never found despite multiple US Coast Guard search operations. The &lt;i&gt;Deepwater Horizon&lt;/i&gt; sank two days later. Official reports say the oil spill has likely harmed or killed approximately 82,000 birds of 102 species, and approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20160130231923/http://news.discovery.com/animals/whales-dolphins/record-dolphin-sea-turtle-deaths-since-gulf-spill-130402.htm&quot;&gt;6,165 sea turtles, and up to 25,900 marine mammals.&lt;/a&gt; The entire rescue, response and cleanup operations took 4 months, 4 weeks and 2 days. British Petroleum paid more than $20 billion in fines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Obama Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;i&gt;The consequences of our inaction are now in plain sight. Countries like China are investing in clean energy jobs and industries that should be here in America. Each day, we send nearly $1 billion of our wealth to foreign countries for their oil. We cannot consign our children to this future. The tragedy unfolding on our coast is the most painful and powerful reminder yet. The time to embrace a clean energy future is now.&lt;/i&gt; “– Barack Obama, June 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 44th President of the United States had just been in office for over a year and yet he had already done the unimaginable. Pulling the economy out of The Great Recession, Obama became a symbol of hope to the post-crash America. &lt;i&gt;Hope&lt;/i&gt;. The most important word on his campaign trail; something he hoped to carry on with him into the White House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on this June morning, addressing the Mississippi crowd, he focused on two things: clean energy and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barack Obama’s struggle towards clean energy has been tough and why shouldn’t it be? When you have an unresponsive Congress who won’t budge because of a Republican majority; when the Congress won’t lend an ear to clean energy because their donors are rich oil magnates; when nobody in your government seems to be rooting for you, what do you do? You look outside. It was at the 2009 United Nations Climate Change Conference at Copenhagen, where he championed the cause of alternative sources of energy for a cleaner environment before member nations of the UNFCCC. It was called the COP15 but they called it ‘&lt;i&gt;Hope&lt;/i&gt;nhagen’.  Unfortunately, things were ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://unfccc.int/resource/docs/2009/cop15/eng/l07.pdf&quot;&gt;taken note of&lt;/a&gt;’ and not ‘adopted’. Things would remain the same in coming years. Obama had the intentions, but people questioned his execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chinese Production or Possibilities?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, China’s economy was on the rise. Just look at the number of billionaires shoot up post-2000:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//oilrig1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the turn of the decade, China had a GDP growth rate bordering on 10% with investors high about the potential that the Chinese market had. Even the US markets were looking at the Far East manufacturing powerhouse as a likely rival in the coming future, with experts predicting their economic output to be at par by 2018. China was not only becoming a force to be reckoned with but also a major consumer of oil which was expected to lead a huge boost in global oil demand. But &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/yuwahedrickwong/2018/08/23/the-reality-of-chinas-economic-slowdown/#2c7990464d86&quot;&gt;predictions do not always come true, do they?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring in the Arab Desert&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early years of the decade, just as the world was reeling from the financial disaster that was, the markets were shaken by another catastrophic series of events. A revolution broke out in Tunisia, powered majorly by the newfound abilities of social media. All of a sudden, one country after another started falling to popular uprisings, social violence and major protests with regimes being overthrown in at least five other countries in the Middle East and North Africa region. This time, again, it was the oil markets which faced the brunt of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy and Middle East scholar at Oxford, &lt;a href=&quot;http://rebeleconomy.com/economy/how-the-arab-spring-shook-up-oil-markets/&quot;&gt;Justin Dargin&lt;/a&gt; put it this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Global investors speculated that in the beginning months of the Arab Spring, there could be oil production disruption in the oil-producing Gulf countries. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;

There was the fear that perhaps several important sea-lanes and canals, such as the Strait of Hormuz or the Suez Canal, could be blocked. Furthermore, a bit later on during the Arab Spring, terrorism fears grew and it was thought that the regional power vacuum could encourage militant groups to launch attacks on MENA energy infrastructure.”&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;‘fear premium&lt;/i&gt;’(price rise due to speculations about significant events that will negatively affect markets) caused a surge that the world was definitely not prepared for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//oilrig2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sheikh Vs. Shale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2015, Crude oil prices ended &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=13&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiZrMawhvLfAhUQfSsKHdylDWEQFjAMegQIBBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washingtonpost.com%2Fopinions%2Frobert-samuelson-key-facts-about-the-great-oil-crash-of-2014%2F2014%2F12%2F03%2Fa1e2fd94-7b0f-11e4-b821-503cc7efed9e_story.html&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3vc-XO8xnUKemMPPF_GwR9&quot;&gt;below $40 per barrel&lt;/a&gt;, the lowest level since 2009. Prices were above $100 just a year ago, only to be met by an inconceivable bust to the oil markets. Lower crude oil prices in 2015 reflected the sustained excess of crude oil supply over global demand. There had been a major supply gut which caused global crude oil inventories to increase steadily through the year. With China facing a gradual slowdown in its economy, the hopes for higher crude oil demand looked slim. What had happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most surprising fact of all was the conflict in the Middle East, including the Syrian Crisis, had little to no effect on the oil markets. If these forces did not affect the markets, then who did? OPEC? Saudi Arabia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//oilrig3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, and No. The Saudis were partially to blame. But they were completely responsible for one of the &lt;i&gt;greatest tricks pulled in economic history&lt;/i&gt;. Since 2008, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ihsmarkit.com/press-release/energy-power/tight-oil-test-us-production-growth-remains-resilient-amid-lower-crude-oi&quot;&gt;US had been steadily increasing&lt;/a&gt; their production of ‘shale’ oil, obtained from organic-rich sedimentary rock found primarily in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2018/11/23/669198912/after-struggles-north-dakota-grows-into-its-ongoing-oil-boom&quot;&gt;Texas and North Dakota&lt;/a&gt;. By 2014, they had shaved off 50% of their imports from OPEC while expanding production by a hefty 70 percent. This boost to supply caused oil prices to drop globally and at a frenetic pace, unchecked by the OPEC disagreeing on whether to lower their production. So Saudi Arabia held out, their Oil Minister saying he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwipvYmKjfLfAhWCXSsKHc33CJcQFjAAegQIAxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.businessinsider.com%2Fr-saudis-naimi-says-opec-will-not-cut-output-however-far-oil-falls-mees-2014-12&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2O8qH49yL33uAaNlFrEgoY&quot;&gt;doesn’t care&lt;/a&gt; even if prices fell to $20 a barrel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon the outwitted Americans realised that the oil prices were falling far too low to maintain production at a sustainable (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiE4Z7FjfLfAhUGbo8KHWIgAiEQFjAAegQICBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Foilprice.com%2FEnergy%2FCrude-Oil%2FThe-Struggle-Continues-For-Bankrupt-Shale-Drillers.html&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1L4UlPPBvNj8c_0HHOwo42&quot;&gt;let alone profitable&lt;/a&gt;) pace. Even at $60-$80 a barrel, shale oil was going for a loss, and a toss. The OPEC had won again, this time, thanks to the clever Saudi Arabians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volatile shifts and the Trump Era&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slump had caused economic contractions in oil-producing countries like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/e1c89278-c33c-3fbe-83ae-985497365cf6&quot;&gt;Brazil&lt;/a&gt; and Venezuela, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-venezuela-economy/venezuelas-economy-shrank-16-5-percent-in-2016-government-idUSKBN1EG06V&quot;&gt;whose economy shrunk by 16.5%&lt;/a&gt;. Even Saudi Arabia took on austerity measures, dropping capital spending by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/saudi-arabia-capital-spending-drop-71-per-cent-2016-amid-cheaper-oil-austerity-a7357666.html&quot;&gt;whopping 71 percent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prayers were finally heard in 2016. The OPEC cut its production in November, which hadn’t happened since the global crisis of ‘08. The cut, which was joined by the likes of Russia, helped push oil costs sharply higher. Crude oil jumped at least five per cent when the OPEC decided to limit production to thirty-three million barrels daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As things seem to be moving towards a period of stability by the end of the year, Donald Trump wins the elections and is ushered into the White House, sailing on a campaign of lambasting the Obama administration and in particular the Iran Deal (JCPOA):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;“John Kerry can’t get over the fact that he had his chance and blew it!”&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/993815373190492160&quot;&gt;Trump wrote&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;“Stay away from negotiations John, you are hurting your country!”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Venezuela whose economy was (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2018/12/15/having-wrecked-the-economy-venezuelas-rulers-see-no-reason-to-change&quot;&gt;and still is&lt;/a&gt;) reeling from Nicholas Maduro’s autocracy, had their production declining so much that they could no longer satisfy their domestic needs, let alone foreign customers. Then they went out and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/venezuela-bolivar-cryptocurrency-economy-crisis-collapse-petro-bitcoin-a8499266.html&quot;&gt;pegged their failing currency to their almost failing oil market&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back in the global oil markets, things were looking better. Prices were rising steadily for the latter half of 2017 and most of 2018, which prompted Trump to tweet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;“Oil prices are too high, OPEC is at it again. Not good!”—US President Donald Trump in June 2018&lt;/i&gt;
This prompted the 23rd June meeting of OPEC ministers in Vienna where they decided to boost production by 1 million barrels/day. Unfortunately, it was soon overshadowed by Trump’s announcement of US withdrawal from the JCPOA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/realdonaldtrump/status/1021234525626609666?lang=en&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//oilrig4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action, as the market expected, would result in a greater loss of supply than the initial estimates of 500,000 bl/d. As a result, the market began &lt;a href=&quot;https://oilprice.com/Energy/Crude-Oil/Iran-Claims-Its-Oil-Revenues-Surged-Despite-Sanctions.html&quot;&gt;preparing for the worst&lt;/a&gt;(even overestimating shortages) and sources reveal that OPEC had started to hike its production way before the June 2018 meeting.
Contrary to economic understanding, when November 4th approached, the day the sanctions on Iran would be enforced again, the price of crude oil &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/why-oil-prices-are-plunging-despite-us-sanctions-on-irans-energy-sector-2018-11-01&quot;&gt;dropped like a rock&lt;/a&gt;.Factor in the growing fears of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/chinas-coming-recession-has-pushed-oil-below-60-2018-11-13&quot;&gt;oncoming recession in China&lt;/a&gt; (the world’s largest importer of oil) and the ensuing fall in demand, and we have another spectacular swing again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//oilrig5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Year may bring new sentiments but much remains to be seen. Only Oil can affect geopolitics so greatly. Or is it the other way around? At least for the past century, one thing’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It all started with the oil.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It all started with the oil.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Counting Down the Biggest Economic Policy Announcements since the 2008 Financial Crash</title>
      <link href="/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Counting Down the Biggest Economic Policy Announcements since the 2008 Financial Crash" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic">&lt;p&gt;In economics, recessions and depressions are supposed to have taught us many valuable lessons (Keynes was one of them). What about the last major recession? It’s been a decade since the Global Markets Crash of ’08. As we enter 2019, let’s see how our governments and institutions have used their financial knowledge over the decade. Many of these announcements are a direct cause of the crisis, while the rest were too important to be left out. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is early 2009, the United States, reeling from the 2008 Financial Crisis, has the New Year as the only positive yet (besides the new President). Obama outlined throughout his 2008 campaign plans for an economic stimulus package and this was delivery time. On February 17, 2009, President Obama signed the fiscal stimulus passed by Congress, which would raise overall demand in the economy by an initial $780-billion worth of federal spending and tax cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This indeed was a necessary follow-up to President Bush’s Troubled Asset Recovery Program, which bailed out the big banks of Wall Street still at the point of revival (sorry, Lehman Brothers). It was only later in 2012 that Congress added to the ARRA making it stand at &lt;i&gt;eight-hundred-and-forty-billion-dollars&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act was largely successful, ending the Recession in July 2009, just 5 months after the bill’s passing. Although many people were skeptical whether they received any tax benefits, the program was hailed for its effectiveness and served as a model for a country that appears later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 - North Korea ‘Won’, 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, they did not win 2009. There have not been many cases of currency revaluation or demonetization in the 21st Century; in fact, less than the number of fingers on your hand. Yet for an occurrence this rare, the 2nd entry on our list has not had the fanfare it deserves. We travel far East to the Korea of the daily news cycle. You guessed it, welcome to North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2009, the North Korean government decided to devalue their currency, the Won, for the first time in 50 years. Many speculated this was a move either initiated or approved personally by Supreme Leader Kim Jong-Il, father of Kim Jon-Un. Seen as a move against private market activity, it also wiped out many North Koreans’ savings. To make matters worse, the announcement was made to foreign embassies but not to North Korean State media. The old notes ceased to be legal tender on November 30, with new notes not being delivered until December 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only think of ways to &lt;i&gt;spend&lt;/i&gt; that week without monetary transaction possible. Needless to say, things were chaotic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 - The Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can blame the Housing markets all they want. But the reason why banks went overboard was in large part due to the repealing of the Glass-Steagall Act in 1999. The Glass–Steagall Act was enacted after the Great Depression of 1930. It separated commercial banks and investment banks, to avoid potential conflicts of interest between the lending activities of the former and rating activities of the latter. Economist Joseph Stiglitz said the repeal would mean the risk-taking culture of investment banking dominated the more risk-averse commercial banking culture, leading to increased levels of risk-taking and leverage during the boom period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the Dodd-Frank reforms. Spelled out over roughly 2,300 pages, this piece of financial reform intends to decrease various risks in the U.S. financial system. The Act established a number of new government agencies tasked with overseeing various aspects of the banking system. Apart from monitoring the financial stability of major firms whose failure could have a major negative impact on the economy, it also provides for regulations keeping a check on Wall Street, which is why President Trump looks to repeal it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 - Austerity returns—to Ireland, Greece, the U.K., and, perhaps to the U.S.A., 2011&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, dear, Austerity! The things you promised us, and now look at what you did to the PIGS (and Italy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know who or what I’m talking about, the reduction of &lt;i&gt;government budget deficits&lt;/i&gt; through &lt;i&gt;spending cuts, tax increases,&lt;/i&gt; or a &lt;i&gt;combination of both&lt;/i&gt; is referred to as &lt;em&gt;Austerity&lt;/em&gt;. It is a series of strict measures to deal with governments unable to pay their debts, viz. Greece (which lost 25% of its GDP) and the members of the Eurozone who have spectacularly contributed to its economic failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//irelandbust2010.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the European debt crisis, many countries embarked on austerity programs, reducing their budget deficits relative to GDP from 2010 to 2011. According to the CIA World Factbook, Greece decreased its budget deficit from 10.4% of GDP in 2010 to 9.6% in 2011. Iceland, Italy, Ireland, Portugal, France, and Spain also decreased their budget deficits from 2010 to 2011 relative to GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, the European people found it too tough to cope up with the heavy tax burdens and unemployment went from 10.3% in 2011 to 12.1% in 2013. Even Paul Krugman saw no sign of success, “this also implies that 1 euro of austerity yields only about 0.4 euros of reduced deficit, even in the short run. No wonder, then, that the whole austerity enterprise is spiraling into disaster.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 - Cyprus and the Big Bailout, 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a story with a happy ending―but it starts off just as bad as the Eurozone. Back in 2013, Europe looked on in despair as yet another country appeared on the brink of collapse. Panic spread through the Cyprus financial system as government bonds were downgraded to junk status and long queues formed outside cash machines as the country failed to make ends meet. Cyprus struck a last-minute bailout deal worth 10 billion euro ($11 billion) in the early hours of Monday morning, aimed at preventing the island becoming the first country forced out of the single European currency. Guess where the help came from- Russian Oligarchs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyprus’s second-largest bank, Laiki Bank was closed. Its €4.2bn in deposits over €100,000 were wiped out entirely. All lenders to Laiki saw their investments wiped out, in a first for a Eurozone bailout. Bank of Cyprus survived the axe. Fast forward to March 2016 via a rescue package program, raft of reforms and austerity measures (finally worked!)  and the country is exiting its three-year, 10 billion euro financial aid package as one of the more robust Eurozone economies. Voila!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 - Japan’s Quantitative Easing is like the USA on steroids!,  2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States did quantitative easing the right way; with loads and loads of asset purchases by the government. Under the most recent incarnation of monetary easing - dubbed “QE3” - the central bank has purchased around $1.6 trillion in government bonds and mortgage-backed securities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese then went out and did this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Abenomics6036.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Here’s a graph, showing the BoJ’s asset purchases, source: Haver Analytics)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the Federal Reserve was winding down, the Bank of Japan (BoJ) voted by 5:4 in a hotly-contested decision to boost its asset purchases by a quarter to roughly $700bn a year, covering the fiscal deficit and the lion’s share of Japan’s annual budget. Governor Haruhiko Kuroda said the fresh stimulus was intended to “pre-empt” mounting deflation risks in the world and vowed to do whatever it takes to see through Japan’s &lt;i&gt;“Abenomics”&lt;/i&gt; revolution. “We are at a critical moment in our efforts to break free from the deflationary mindset,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hans Redeker, from Morgan Stanley, believes that Japan’s aggressive measures seem to be putting pressure on the rest of their economic competitors in Asia to raise government spending too. But this is where China finds it tough to compete with a large budget deficit, slowing economy and FDI gradually turning negative. No wonder the Dragon is angry at its eastern neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 - Greece becomes first advanced economy ever to fail in arrears to the IMF, 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2015 was all about Greece”—is an understatement. 2015 saw Greece’s debt crisis, Greece’s referendum, Greece’s bailout, Greece’s election, Greece’s second election. At one point it really seemed that the battered country, which has been through so much, would finally crash out of the eurozone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;No Bailouts&lt;/i&gt; campaign securing 61.31% majority, won the referendum. In a television address, PM Alex Tsipras said the outcome showed that democracy could not be blackmailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a week later, however, he would be forced to accept a bailout of further austerity measures and economic reforms, even more onerous than those the nation had so dramatically rejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//chart6034.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 - India’s Demonetization and the GST Bill, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two polar opposites. One nobody saw coming and the other that had been there all along. No, I’m not referring to the Congress and the BJP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Demonetization Scheme struck like a lightning rod throughout Indian society, affecting both the poor and rich equally (so much for inequality). In a move targeted at debilitating the shadow economy, counterfeit cash and “black money” used to fund illegal activity, Rs. 500 and Rs. 1000 banknotes were demonetized and new Rs. 500 and Rs. 2000 notes were introduced. The GST Bill, on the other hand, was first put forth by the Vajpayee administration almost 20 years ago but only saw the light of day in late 2016. It has successfully eliminated the Cascading effect of taxes (tax on a tax) and taken its place as the Destination tax of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being initially met with protests, litigation, and strikes, it has received support from many eminent bankers and the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 - Venezuela devalues its currency by the crypto, 2018&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have truly reached the advent of technology when Venezuela decides to peg the Bolivar to an oil-backed cryptocurrency called the petro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela under Nicolas Maduro is an economic autocracy at best. Since 2014, they have lied on reports and economic statistics and by 2016, were in an economic collapse, with the IMF estimating a 500% inflation rate and a 10% GDP contraction and as of today, are experiencing Hyperinflation—Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the government decided to slash five zeros off and devalue the currency, and back it by their oil and mineral reserves; the only things not spiraling out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really a sneak peek of the decade to come!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In economics, recessions and depressions are supposed to have taught us many valuable lessons (Keynes was one of them). What about the last major recession? It’s been a decade since the Global Markets Crash of ’08. As we enter 2019, let’s see how our governments and institutions have used their financial knowledge over the decade. Many of these announcements are a direct cause of the crisis, while the rest were too important to be left out. Here you go:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
