<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/shiksha.mody/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-02-22T08:51:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/shiksha.mody/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lights, Camera, Generalise!</title>
      <link href="/Lights-Camera-Generalise" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lights, Camera, Generalise!" />
      <published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lights-Camera-Generalise</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lights-Camera-Generalise">&lt;p&gt;While going through my Google feed one day, I came across this&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/entertainment/bollywood/meenakshi-sundareshwar-inauthentic-stereotypical-take-on-tamil-culture-sanya-malhotra-abhimanyu-dassani-7616835/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;in &lt;em&gt;The Indian Express &lt;/em&gt;about the review of the recent film,&lt;em&gt; Meenakshi Sundareshwar&lt;/em&gt;. Because I hail from Rajasthan, I could relate to what the author was trying to say. Whenever I introduce myself as a Rajasthani, certain visuals pop up in the mind of the listener; vast stretches of sand, men wearing colourful turbans, and women in sarees with ‘&lt;em&gt;matkas&lt;/em&gt;’ on their heads living in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;kutcha&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;houses, and even though a large part of Rajasthan is similar to that, these visuals are not representative of the entire state. I too have played the role of ‘the listener’ in a lot of cases and had my fair share of stereotypes about places, people and cultures, merely based on their depiction in movies or series. If suppose, I mention Tamils; “loud exaggerated accents, dark-skinned villains, gajras, jhumkis, curd, aiyoo, and religiously inclined vegetarian folks without a sense of humour” (as pointed out by the article) is what comes to my mind. Indeed because this is how I have seen Tamils; whether it was Deepika Padukone portraying&amp;nbsp;Meenama&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Chennai Express&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;or Shiv Subramaniam acting as Alia’s father in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Two States&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, what is the big deal about Bollywood stereotyping practically everything? The current value of the film industry is approximately ₹183 billion which explains the number of people who are influenced by the content of Bollywood films. Thus, Hindi cinema shapes the perception of a vast majority of Indians and for a lot of us, what we see in movies ends up being how we think things are. Moreover, the problem is not just limited to forming perceptions about different places; in fact, this is not even the tip of the iceberg. The real problem comes into picture when these perceptions start fuelling stereotypes that already exist in society. For example, women in Bollywood have always been portrayed as ‘damsels in distress’ whose apparent role is to have a love-hate relationship with the protagonist, and all her life problems get solved post their union. The little to no screen time given to female actresses in Hindi cinema except for brief appearances in a song, here and there, is a metaphor of the way women are positioned in the real society. The film&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Ranjhanaa&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;went overboard with the idea of Sonam Kapoor’s character in the film agreeing to meet the protagonist, her stalker, because he was ‘consistent’ in his ways and there was no love involved. The cliché storyline wherein the protagonist does everything to get the attention of the girl while the girl constantly ignores him but eventually gives in (because he is the protagonist) drives home the idea that girls actually want to say 'yes' but due to her &lt;em&gt;sanskari &lt;/em&gt;(traditional) values, she refrains from it. This portrayal absolutely undermines the concept of consent wherein the 'no' is lost in translation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the generalisations don’t stop here. Not just promoting sexist stereotypes, there are multiple instances (even in recent times) where Bollywood has promoted body shaming. The female actresses, with their perfect figure, end up setting unrealistic expectations about looks and body amongst the general population. Further, Bollywood seems to fuel these misconceptions of beauty when they appoint people who look a little different than the idealistic standards of beauty as the ‘side characters’ in films. These characters are seldom portrayed to have any loving relationships. This ends up communicating the idea that if you do not have a perfect body or glowing skin, you would have a hard time finding partners. Even Bollywood songs are heavily inclined towards appreciating the beauty of a ‘gora’ or ‘gori,’ which literally translates to white in English. “&lt;em&gt;Goriya Chura Na Mera Jiya” &lt;/em&gt;(O White Woman&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;don't steal my heart), &lt;em&gt;“Chura Ke Dil Mera Goriya Chali” &lt;/em&gt;(The White Woman has stolen my heart) are just a few cases of such lyrics&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;Such stereotypes transcend onto races and religions as well. Whether it was 2000’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Phir Bhi Dil Hai Hindustani&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;or 2008’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Chandni Chowk To China,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;the weird obsession to make an mainland Indian actor have the ‘East Asian look’ by taping their eyes to slant them is the ugly truth of an industry consumed by over a billion people. Even people belonging to the LGBTQ+ community, especially homosexual men, are portrayed as having feminine features. Most movies stereotypically mock the way they walk and dress which was pretty evident in movies like&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Student Of The Year&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Dostana.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it might not be a big deal for many, it does hurt a community at large, and makes their attempts at fighting stigmas in society prove futile. There is no denying that Bollywood is evolving. The increasing number of heavyweight female characters who come in all sizes, shapes and color, sparks hope for a fairer, aware and more appropriate Bollywood culture in the future. However, Bollywood still has an immense population of stereotypes buried in its backyard, more so because it is the easiest route to singling out a community (generally minorities) or driving home the ideas that the majority in a country identifies with.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before parting ways, here is another&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/trending/trending-in-india/tweeple-are-calling-out-stereotypes-in-movies-and-its-a-must-read-5528242/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; which I found while researching for my piece. It is hilarious but sadly true; and yes, I am still a Rajasthani, but I do not carry&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;‘matkas&lt;/em&gt;!’&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While going through my Google feed one day, I came across this&amp;nbsp;article&amp;nbsp;in The Indian Express about the review of the recent film, Meenakshi Sundareshwar. Because I hail from Rajasthan, I could relate to what the author was trying to say. Whenever I introduce myself as a Rajasthani, certain visuals pop up in the mind of the listener; vast stretches of sand, men wearing colourful turbans, and women in sarees with ‘matkas’ on their heads living in&amp;nbsp;kutcha&amp;nbsp;houses, and even though a large part of Rajasthan is similar to that, these visuals are not representative of the entire state. I too have played the role of ‘the listener’ in a lot of cases and had my fair share of stereotypes about places, people and cultures, merely based on their depiction in movies or series. If suppose, I mention Tamils; “loud exaggerated accents, dark-skinned villains, gajras, jhumkis, curd, aiyoo, and religiously inclined vegetarian folks without a sense of humour” (as pointed out by the article) is what comes to my mind. Indeed because this is how I have seen Tamils; whether it was Deepika Padukone portraying&amp;nbsp;Meenama&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;Chennai Express&amp;nbsp;or Shiv Subramaniam acting as Alia’s father in&amp;nbsp;Two States. However, what is the big deal about Bollywood stereotyping practically everything? The current value of the film industry is approximately ₹183 billion which explains the number of people who are influenced by the content of Bollywood films. Thus, Hindi cinema shapes the perception of a vast majority of Indians and for a lot of us, what we see in movies ends up being how we think things are. Moreover, the problem is not just limited to forming perceptions about different places; in fact, this is not even the tip of the iceberg. The real problem comes into picture when these perceptions start fuelling stereotypes that already exist in society. For example, women in Bollywood have always been portrayed as ‘damsels in distress’ whose apparent role is to have a love-hate relationship with the protagonist, and all her life problems get solved post their union. The little to no screen time given to female actresses in Hindi cinema except for brief appearances in a song, here and there, is a metaphor of the way women are positioned in the real society. The film&amp;nbsp;Ranjhanaa&amp;nbsp;went overboard with the idea of Sonam Kapoor’s character in the film agreeing to meet the protagonist, her stalker, because he was ‘consistent’ in his ways and there was no love involved. The cliché storyline wherein the protagonist does everything to get the attention of the girl while the girl constantly ignores him but eventually gives in (because he is the protagonist) drives home the idea that girls actually want to say 'yes' but due to her sanskari (traditional) values, she refrains from it. This portrayal absolutely undermines the concept of consent wherein the 'no' is lost in translation. Unfortunately, the generalisations don’t stop here. Not just promoting sexist stereotypes, there are multiple instances (even in recent times) where Bollywood has promoted body shaming. The female actresses, with their perfect figure, end up setting unrealistic expectations about looks and body amongst the general population. Further, Bollywood seems to fuel these misconceptions of beauty when they appoint people who look a little different than the idealistic standards of beauty as the ‘side characters’ in films. These characters are seldom portrayed to have any loving relationships. This ends up communicating the idea that if you do not have a perfect body or glowing skin, you would have a hard time finding partners. Even Bollywood songs are heavily inclined towards appreciating the beauty of a ‘gora’ or ‘gori,’ which literally translates to white in English. “Goriya Chura Na Mera Jiya” (O White Woman don't steal my heart), “Chura Ke Dil Mera Goriya Chali” (The White Woman has stolen my heart) are just a few cases of such lyrics. Such stereotypes transcend onto races and religions as well. Whether it was 2000’s&amp;nbsp;Phir Bhi Dil Hai Hindustani&amp;nbsp;or 2008’s&amp;nbsp;Chandni Chowk To China,&amp;nbsp;the weird obsession to make an mainland Indian actor have the ‘East Asian look’ by taping their eyes to slant them is the ugly truth of an industry consumed by over a billion people. Even people belonging to the LGBTQ+ community, especially homosexual men, are portrayed as having feminine features. Most movies stereotypically mock the way they walk and dress which was pretty evident in movies like&amp;nbsp;Student Of The Year&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Dostana.&amp;nbsp; While it might not be a big deal for many, it does hurt a community at large, and makes their attempts at fighting stigmas in society prove futile. There is no denying that Bollywood is evolving. The increasing number of heavyweight female characters who come in all sizes, shapes and color, sparks hope for a fairer, aware and more appropriate Bollywood culture in the future. However, Bollywood still has an immense population of stereotypes buried in its backyard, more so because it is the easiest route to singling out a community (generally minorities) or driving home the ideas that the majority in a country identifies with.&amp;nbsp; Before parting ways, here is another&amp;nbsp;article which I found while researching for my piece. It is hilarious but sadly true; and yes, I am still a Rajasthani, but I do not carry&amp;nbsp;‘matkas!’</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stand Up and Economics</title>
      <link href="/Stand-Up-and-Economics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stand Up and Economics" />
      <published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Stand-Up-and-Economics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stand-Up-and-Economics">&lt;p&gt;Who would be a perfect partner for a tub of Popcorn and a day drowned in gloom? For me, it has always been Kenny Sebastian cracking jokes on coffee or biscuits. Not just Kenny Sebastian, but as a matter of fact, stand-up comedians in general have been my saviour in times of crisis. The giggles and the laughs indeed help one escape from reality and live in the moment. However, there is one not so known fact about stand-ups - they share a close relationship with everybody’s favourite subject, economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This relationship between Economics and Stand Ups is bilateral, and however funny and astonishing it may sound, we have someone with the title of 'Stand-up Economist'. Yoram Bauman is deemed to be the first Stand up Economist in the world. He is a microeconomist and his key focus area is the environment. He once wrote a parody on the 'ten principles of Economics'&amp;nbsp; by N Mankiw which kick-started his side-career in comedy. Now, he regularly performs at colleges, clubs and institutes&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;The difference, of course, being that microeconomists are people who are wrong about specific things and macroeconomists are wrong about things in general&quot; &lt;/em&gt;was one of his lines at a 45- minute comedy show performed at Mission College which made the audience burst into laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving ahead, while we look at the first half of the relationship, we will be looking at stand-ups as economics. A lot of people have drawn similarities between jokes and currency. Some went overboard and termed jokes as a 'Strange Currency'. The value of this currency rests on a shared agreement and it keeps fluctuating, i.e., increases or decreases, over time. Moreover, if we visualise stand-up as a market, the market does have a point of saturation wherein the joke becomes so diffused that it no longer pleases the audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, like everything else, jokes react to the principles of supply and demand. Jokes, in this market, are characterised as investments. Not everyone can wake up one day, go on the stage and become a stand up comedian. There’s a lot of refinement and honing that goes behind a successful joke (or investment) which can be presented to a paid audience and in turn yield money. &lt;a href=&quot;http://marknormandcomedy.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mark Normand&lt;/a&gt;’s line “&lt;em&gt;If I can get a joke to work on [a free] show, that joke is worth money” &lt;/em&gt;sums up the idea pretty well. These jokes have a lasting or terminal value like any other investment. However, when does the value of a joke fade away? The lasting value depends on the person who’s making the joke. For example, stand-up comedians who have been in the business for as long as decades can dig out old jokes and please the audience with the reference. Thus, the jokes still have a lasting value for them even after decades. Generally, it is considered that non-conventional jokes have a longer lasting value than the conventional ones.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we have walked through the streets of the stand-up industry, there’s another visualisation of the joke market which was proposed by Yoram Bauman. Instead of considering jokes as a currency, Bauman considers jokes to be like public goods such as fresh air, water, etc. If one of the members enjoys the joke, it doesn’t take away the right of enjoying it from any other member. However, even estimating the value of a public good is difficult, as no one puts equal value on a nice view or a nice joke. Again like any other goods, jokes face saturation in the market. If a comedy show has the same specific bit of jokes about the same things, the value of the jokes would reduce. Ultimately the audience would refuse to buy these jokes by either not laughing at them or worse by heckling. However, one fundamental question that still remains is how one puts a value on a creative intangible hobby because a lot of stand up comedians don’t really want money in exchange for their “goods” but are satisfied by the giggles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now exploring the second half of the relationship, a lot of stand-ups have economic concepts entwined in them. Stand ups provide a really holistic view of human behavior. Since most of the jokes are centered on everyday life; these comedians analyze our behavior to derive jokes out of them. Hence, economics lovers should definitely watch stand ups apart from reading the usual microeconomics textbook. As was noted in one of the articles by Mint, there are various instances where stand-up comedians have explained complex economics issues through jokes. For example, when in one of his gigs, Abhishek Upmanyu said that, in his childhood, on his grandmother’s death anniversary, his mother used to request him to offer food to poor people. While he agrees that it is a noble deed to do, he also states that it creates an unwanted incentive. If poor people get to know that elderly people dying means food, they’ll start hurting elderly people. This, in economics, is called ‘The Cobra Effect’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it’s stand-up comedy in economics or economics in stand-up comedy, there’s one thing clear that there is a relationship between the two. So, the next time you sit with a tub of popcorn and Kenny Sebastian, you can skip your microeconomics tuition!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Who would be a perfect partner for a tub of Popcorn and a day drowned in gloom? For me, it has always been Kenny Sebastian cracking jokes on coffee or biscuits. Not just Kenny Sebastian, but as a matter of fact, stand-up comedians in general have been my saviour in times of crisis. The giggles and the laughs indeed help one escape from reality and live in the moment. However, there is one not so known fact about stand-ups - they share a close relationship with everybody’s favourite subject, economics. This relationship between Economics and Stand Ups is bilateral, and however funny and astonishing it may sound, we have someone with the title of 'Stand-up Economist'. Yoram Bauman is deemed to be the first Stand up Economist in the world. He is a microeconomist and his key focus area is the environment. He once wrote a parody on the 'ten principles of Economics'&amp;nbsp; by N Mankiw which kick-started his side-career in comedy. Now, he regularly performs at colleges, clubs and institutes. &quot;The difference, of course, being that microeconomists are people who are wrong about specific things and macroeconomists are wrong about things in general&quot; was one of his lines at a 45- minute comedy show performed at Mission College which made the audience burst into laughter. Moving ahead, while we look at the first half of the relationship, we will be looking at stand-ups as economics. A lot of people have drawn similarities between jokes and currency. Some went overboard and termed jokes as a 'Strange Currency'. The value of this currency rests on a shared agreement and it keeps fluctuating, i.e., increases or decreases, over time. Moreover, if we visualise stand-up as a market, the market does have a point of saturation wherein the joke becomes so diffused that it no longer pleases the audience.&amp;nbsp; And again, like everything else, jokes react to the principles of supply and demand. Jokes, in this market, are characterised as investments. Not everyone can wake up one day, go on the stage and become a stand up comedian. There’s a lot of refinement and honing that goes behind a successful joke (or investment) which can be presented to a paid audience and in turn yield money. Mark Normand’s line “If I can get a joke to work on [a free] show, that joke is worth money” sums up the idea pretty well. These jokes have a lasting or terminal value like any other investment. However, when does the value of a joke fade away? The lasting value depends on the person who’s making the joke. For example, stand-up comedians who have been in the business for as long as decades can dig out old jokes and please the audience with the reference. Thus, the jokes still have a lasting value for them even after decades. Generally, it is considered that non-conventional jokes have a longer lasting value than the conventional ones.&amp;nbsp; While we have walked through the streets of the stand-up industry, there’s another visualisation of the joke market which was proposed by Yoram Bauman. Instead of considering jokes as a currency, Bauman considers jokes to be like public goods such as fresh air, water, etc. If one of the members enjoys the joke, it doesn’t take away the right of enjoying it from any other member. However, even estimating the value of a public good is difficult, as no one puts equal value on a nice view or a nice joke. Again like any other goods, jokes face saturation in the market. If a comedy show has the same specific bit of jokes about the same things, the value of the jokes would reduce. Ultimately the audience would refuse to buy these jokes by either not laughing at them or worse by heckling. However, one fundamental question that still remains is how one puts a value on a creative intangible hobby because a lot of stand up comedians don’t really want money in exchange for their “goods” but are satisfied by the giggles. Now exploring the second half of the relationship, a lot of stand-ups have economic concepts entwined in them. Stand ups provide a really holistic view of human behavior. Since most of the jokes are centered on everyday life; these comedians analyze our behavior to derive jokes out of them. Hence, economics lovers should definitely watch stand ups apart from reading the usual microeconomics textbook. As was noted in one of the articles by Mint, there are various instances where stand-up comedians have explained complex economics issues through jokes. For example, when in one of his gigs, Abhishek Upmanyu said that, in his childhood, on his grandmother’s death anniversary, his mother used to request him to offer food to poor people. While he agrees that it is a noble deed to do, he also states that it creates an unwanted incentive. If poor people get to know that elderly people dying means food, they’ll start hurting elderly people. This, in economics, is called ‘The Cobra Effect’.&amp;nbsp; While it’s stand-up comedy in economics or economics in stand-up comedy, there’s one thing clear that there is a relationship between the two. So, the next time you sit with a tub of popcorn and Kenny Sebastian, you can skip your microeconomics tuition!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women in Corporations: Breaking the Glass Ceiling or Standing at the Glass Cliff?</title>
      <link href="/Women-in-Corporations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women in Corporations: Breaking the Glass Ceiling or Standing at the Glass Cliff?" />
      <published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Women-in-Corporations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Women-in-Corporations">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While listening to Ava Max’s song &lt;em&gt;Kings and Queens&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;whenever the line ‘&lt;em&gt;If all of the kings had queens on their throne, we would pop champagne and raise a toast’ &lt;/em&gt;comes,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;a gush of enthusiasm runs through my veins and the thought of women leading everywhere leaves me in awe of the world that they would create. However, as I sit down to write this article today, contemplating upon the lyrics, I am left baffled by the thought of whether the problem of gender discrimination is really solved by passing of thrones or is there more to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Historically, men have been perceived to be natural leaders while women and other minority groups have fought for their way upwards in any organisation. Around only 8.1% of the latest fortune 500 companies are being run by women CEOs. Though it is a milestone in itself that should be celebrated, yet the numbers are not so encouraging.&amp;nbsp; This underrepresentation of women in the higher positions of an organisation is called the ‘glass ceiling effect’. But there’s more to the story. Even if a small portion of determined and strong women break the glass ceiling and demonstrate their innate talent of being a leader, they are faced with yet another patriarchal barrier – the glass cliff effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Recently, Blizzard Company appointed Jen Oneal as its first female lead. Though it would have been an encouraging move under normal circumstances, currently it is a testimony to the prevalence of the glass cliff effect. Why? The promotion of Jen was preceded by a big lawsuit of sexual harassment that the company is tackling. More like a sister to the glass ceiling effect, the glass cliff effect refers to the phenomenon whereby women are promoted to higher positions during a precarious situation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This term was coined by two researchers at the University of Exeter, Michelle Ryan and Alexander Haslam in 2005. Haslam and Ryan looked at the 100 companies that were a part of the FTSE 100 Index listed on the London Stock Exchange to analyse what happened at those firms before and after men and women board members were brought on board. The findings suggested that during periods of stock market decline, firms that brought women on their board were more likely to have experienced constantly bad performance in the preceding five months than those who brought men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The glass cliff effect assumes greater importance as it fuels the traditionally-existing stereotypes about women leaders. When women leaders are unable to perform under precarious situations they are dismissed as being not competent enough to hold positions of power. The effect is closely knit with the saviour effect. When women are not able to deliver results under a glass cliff appointment they are immediately replaced by men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, I believe there’s more to the glass cliff effect than just research backed by statistics. I believe the roots of the glass cliff effect go to the way girls are conditioned from the beginning. Apart from painting the picture of a damsel in distress waiting to be saved by a prince in shining armour, a lot of women are conditioned to believe that they are responsible for cleaning the 'mess' that has so far been created by dominant patriarchal characters in their life. The submissive and complacent attitude that is imbibed in girls during their childhood adds up to become a phenomenon like the glass cliff effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Why do women choose to accept an offer of being promoted to a higher stature if they know that the company is currently in a dangerous situation? Well, women as a group have to face a lot of struggles to climb up the corporate ladder. The offer of a C-suite position is just too lucrative for a lot of women to pass on. So, instead, they take up a chance and try to fight the situation; and if we look at the flip side, there have been a lot many instances where women have vigorously fought against the glass cliff effect, pulled companies out of crisis and proved their acumen. Mary Barra, CEO and Chairman of General Motors is one such example. When she was promoted after a controversial bail-out, the odds of her succeeding&amp;nbsp;were low. However, she defied all the odds and succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Though the saddening part still remains. Imagine that you’ve been trying hard to break through the glass and finally succeed. You let out a sigh of relief. However, as soon as you look around, you find yourself standing at the edge of a cliff. You are disheartened. This is what a glass cliff effect looks like. The glass cliff effect is a lesser-known fact however it impacts the lives of almost millions of women working in the corporate sector. Will women ever break out of these shackles or are there more glass barriers waiting for them?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While listening to Ava Max’s song Kings and Queens, whenever the line ‘If all of the kings had queens on their throne, we would pop champagne and raise a toast’ comes, a gush of enthusiasm runs through my veins and the thought of women leading everywhere leaves me in awe of the world that they would create. However, as I sit down to write this article today, contemplating upon the lyrics, I am left baffled by the thought of whether the problem of gender discrimination is really solved by passing of thrones or is there more to it? Historically, men have been perceived to be natural leaders while women and other minority groups have fought for their way upwards in any organisation. Around only 8.1% of the latest fortune 500 companies are being run by women CEOs. Though it is a milestone in itself that should be celebrated, yet the numbers are not so encouraging.&amp;nbsp; This underrepresentation of women in the higher positions of an organisation is called the ‘glass ceiling effect’. But there’s more to the story. Even if a small portion of determined and strong women break the glass ceiling and demonstrate their innate talent of being a leader, they are faced with yet another patriarchal barrier – the glass cliff effect. Recently, Blizzard Company appointed Jen Oneal as its first female lead. Though it would have been an encouraging move under normal circumstances, currently it is a testimony to the prevalence of the glass cliff effect. Why? The promotion of Jen was preceded by a big lawsuit of sexual harassment that the company is tackling. More like a sister to the glass ceiling effect, the glass cliff effect refers to the phenomenon whereby women are promoted to higher positions during a precarious situation.&amp;nbsp; This term was coined by two researchers at the University of Exeter, Michelle Ryan and Alexander Haslam in 2005. Haslam and Ryan looked at the 100 companies that were a part of the FTSE 100 Index listed on the London Stock Exchange to analyse what happened at those firms before and after men and women board members were brought on board. The findings suggested that during periods of stock market decline, firms that brought women on their board were more likely to have experienced constantly bad performance in the preceding five months than those who brought men. The glass cliff effect assumes greater importance as it fuels the traditionally-existing stereotypes about women leaders. When women leaders are unable to perform under precarious situations they are dismissed as being not competent enough to hold positions of power. The effect is closely knit with the saviour effect. When women are not able to deliver results under a glass cliff appointment they are immediately replaced by men.&amp;nbsp; However, I believe there’s more to the glass cliff effect than just research backed by statistics. I believe the roots of the glass cliff effect go to the way girls are conditioned from the beginning. Apart from painting the picture of a damsel in distress waiting to be saved by a prince in shining armour, a lot of women are conditioned to believe that they are responsible for cleaning the 'mess' that has so far been created by dominant patriarchal characters in their life. The submissive and complacent attitude that is imbibed in girls during their childhood adds up to become a phenomenon like the glass cliff effect. Why do women choose to accept an offer of being promoted to a higher stature if they know that the company is currently in a dangerous situation? Well, women as a group have to face a lot of struggles to climb up the corporate ladder. The offer of a C-suite position is just too lucrative for a lot of women to pass on. So, instead, they take up a chance and try to fight the situation; and if we look at the flip side, there have been a lot many instances where women have vigorously fought against the glass cliff effect, pulled companies out of crisis and proved their acumen. Mary Barra, CEO and Chairman of General Motors is one such example. When she was promoted after a controversial bail-out, the odds of her succeeding&amp;nbsp;were low. However, she defied all the odds and succeeded. Though the saddening part still remains. Imagine that you’ve been trying hard to break through the glass and finally succeed. You let out a sigh of relief. However, as soon as you look around, you find yourself standing at the edge of a cliff. You are disheartened. This is what a glass cliff effect looks like. The glass cliff effect is a lesser-known fact however it impacts the lives of almost millions of women working in the corporate sector. Will women ever break out of these shackles or are there more glass barriers waiting for them?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What’s at the End of a Rainbow? A Gold Pot</title>
      <link href="/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What's at the End of a Rainbow? A Gold Pot" />
      <published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow">&lt;p&gt;The month of June is coloured with colours of solidarity, determination and struggles of the LGBTQ+ community. Pride month is and was, indeed, a month full of people taking &lt;em&gt;pride &lt;/em&gt;in who they are and pride parades are a sight to behold. However, this article is not a fairytale painting a happy picture of the month but rather explores its dark side, i.e. rainbow washing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would scroll through the LinkedIn profiles of a big, or as a matter-of-fact, any company during the month of June, it would not be hard to notice that most of them have rainbows slapped on their logos. Isn't it something to be happy about? After all, this is a sign of increasing acceptance of the LGBTQ+ community by society. If the previous two sentences outlined your thought process, then it reinforces the importance of awareness about rainbow washing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting with rainbow washing, it is important to understand another terminology associated with it that is 'pink money'. Pink money refers to the purchasing power of LGBTQ+ community. The 'pink' here is a reference to the pink triangle which was used as a badge in Nazi concentration camps to identify homosexuals. When the gay rights community became active it took it as a symbol to identify their movement and till date it serves as a strong symbol of their struggles. According to the sources, the LGBT population accounts for 5-10% of the total population. If it were a country, the community could claim to have the fourth-largest GDP in the world, estimated at $4.6 trillion. Now, a lot of corporations can and do go out of their way to monetise this 'pink money'. Here's where rainbow washing comes into the picture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rainbow washing refers to the practice of supporting LGBTQ issues in public to gather an audience while having private policies that are detrimental for them. To put it in simple words, corporations put rainbows on their logos, products and icons to tap the LGBTQ+ markets. Though when it comes to issues such as recruiting and helping them concretely, the companies back out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey found that about 50% of people belonging to this group believed being out at work would end up hurting their careers. During pride month, this year, Lego launched its special series titled 'Everybody is awesome' adorned in rainbow colours and priced it at $30, with it being a limited edition. Most other big brands such as Apple came up with products specifically targeted towards this segment intending to donate the proceeds generated through these sales towards organisations working for the betterment of the community. However, the past records tell a different story. A large part of this revenue is never actually spent on the betterment of the community.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rainbow washing may seem like a pretty marketing tactic or a petty issue but it has a lot of detrimental effects on the existence of pride. The commodification and monetisation of an event like pride end up demeaning the struggles and identity of the community celebrating it. As opposed to being a month of acceptance and love, pride turns into a month of closing business deals and getting traction for your product. A majority of people from the community said that rainbow washing made them feel uncomfortable about their identity. The fact that their coming out or acceptance is being reduced to a marketing tactic makes them feel used.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If business conglomerates actually want to support the cause and fight for the community, they should indeed open up employment opportunities or destigmatize the talk around LGBTQ+ issues. Most of them are just trying to tap into the 'pink money' while the people are left behind. Their economic condition is not robust and at a lot of places, they are not even allowed to enter a shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, looking at the flip side of rainbow washing, the symbolism has helped spread awareness about the issue in the marginalised or backward communities. The advertisements during pride month do provide a lot of opportunities to the people of the community. Although again, the phenomenon is not year-round. Hence, the opportunities end up being more like a company-influencer relationship rather than being a company-employee relationship. As soon as the pride month starts coming to an end, the support and charisma behind these rainbow coloured logos starts fading and so does the love and acceptance bestowed upon the community by the corporates. Life for them returns to normalcy with all its struggles and rocky roads, and the community for them seems long forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The month of June is coloured with colours of solidarity, determination and struggles of the LGBTQ+ community. Pride month is and was, indeed, a month full of people taking pride in who they are and pride parades are a sight to behold. However, this article is not a fairytale painting a happy picture of the month but rather explores its dark side, i.e. rainbow washing. If you would scroll through the LinkedIn profiles of a big, or as a matter-of-fact, any company during the month of June, it would not be hard to notice that most of them have rainbows slapped on their logos. Isn't it something to be happy about? After all, this is a sign of increasing acceptance of the LGBTQ+ community by society. If the previous two sentences outlined your thought process, then it reinforces the importance of awareness about rainbow washing. Before starting with rainbow washing, it is important to understand another terminology associated with it that is 'pink money'. Pink money refers to the purchasing power of LGBTQ+ community. The 'pink' here is a reference to the pink triangle which was used as a badge in Nazi concentration camps to identify homosexuals. When the gay rights community became active it took it as a symbol to identify their movement and till date it serves as a strong symbol of their struggles. According to the sources, the LGBT population accounts for 5-10% of the total population. If it were a country, the community could claim to have the fourth-largest GDP in the world, estimated at $4.6 trillion. Now, a lot of corporations can and do go out of their way to monetise this 'pink money'. Here's where rainbow washing comes into the picture.&amp;nbsp; Rainbow washing refers to the practice of supporting LGBTQ issues in public to gather an audience while having private policies that are detrimental for them. To put it in simple words, corporations put rainbows on their logos, products and icons to tap the LGBTQ+ markets. Though when it comes to issues such as recruiting and helping them concretely, the companies back out. A survey found that about 50% of people belonging to this group believed being out at work would end up hurting their careers. During pride month, this year, Lego launched its special series titled 'Everybody is awesome' adorned in rainbow colours and priced it at $30, with it being a limited edition. Most other big brands such as Apple came up with products specifically targeted towards this segment intending to donate the proceeds generated through these sales towards organisations working for the betterment of the community. However, the past records tell a different story. A large part of this revenue is never actually spent on the betterment of the community.&amp;nbsp; Rainbow washing may seem like a pretty marketing tactic or a petty issue but it has a lot of detrimental effects on the existence of pride. The commodification and monetisation of an event like pride end up demeaning the struggles and identity of the community celebrating it. As opposed to being a month of acceptance and love, pride turns into a month of closing business deals and getting traction for your product. A majority of people from the community said that rainbow washing made them feel uncomfortable about their identity. The fact that their coming out or acceptance is being reduced to a marketing tactic makes them feel used.&amp;nbsp; If business conglomerates actually want to support the cause and fight for the community, they should indeed open up employment opportunities or destigmatize the talk around LGBTQ+ issues. Most of them are just trying to tap into the 'pink money' while the people are left behind. Their economic condition is not robust and at a lot of places, they are not even allowed to enter a shop. However, looking at the flip side of rainbow washing, the symbolism has helped spread awareness about the issue in the marginalised or backward communities. The advertisements during pride month do provide a lot of opportunities to the people of the community. Although again, the phenomenon is not year-round. Hence, the opportunities end up being more like a company-influencer relationship rather than being a company-employee relationship. As soon as the pride month starts coming to an end, the support and charisma behind these rainbow coloured logos starts fading and so does the love and acceptance bestowed upon the community by the corporates. Life for them returns to normalcy with all its struggles and rocky roads, and the community for them seems long forgotten.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Millennial Bermuda Triangle</title>
      <link href="/The-Millennial-Bermuda-Triangle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Millennial Bermuda Triangle" />
      <published>2021-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Millennial-Bermuda-Triangle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Millennial-Bermuda-Triangle">&lt;p&gt;The Bermuda Triangle is an unreal patch of sea in the Atlantic Ocean which is infamous for the disappearance of thousands of ships, cargo and airplanes in its vicinity. While there has been a lot of speculation about the reasons for such disappearances, there has been no consensus on one single theory to explain these mysterious occurrences. People have proposed theories from the triangle being an alleged home of aliens to mysterious creatures residing there and engulfing the ships that go that way.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I will not decipher the fundamental reasons behind these disappearances in this article, I will outline the aspects of another Bermuda Triangle that almost all of us have sailed through. While some of us could cross it successfully, some lost a part of themselves there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man is a social animal. As Darwin said, &lt;em&gt;&quot;Society is something that precedes an individual&quot;&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, the need to belong is intuitive. This fact that ‘belongingness is a need’ means that it is imperative for humans to maintain and establish some relationships. This theory has been explored by various psychologists including Freud and Maslow. Abraham Maslow placed belongingness in the needs hierarchy between physical needs and the need for self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media, the technology-enabled communication systems, have drastically altered the way we perceive ourselves as belonging in society. Social media is more about psychology and community rather than technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a student who has just joined university amidst the COVID scenario, there's one thing I could definitely say- social media has had a lot of effect on my perceptions of myself. With the onset of university, there is one more social media that is added to your list apart from the usual networking sites, i.e. LinkedIn. When you start networking here, all of you would come across profiles that are absolute gold. With this facade that social media and networking sites create, they inadvertently point towards a better and happy life that is being led by people behind these profiles. Competition and comparison is inevitable. However, these personas are also attached to a false sense of belonging. People who are passive consumers on these sites suffer from greater levels of social loneliness and feelings of ostracism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two studies conducted in this domain brought out the effect of social media consumption on the self esteem of the passive users. In the first one, some Facebook users were divided into two groups. One group was asked to post as usual over the study period, while the other group was instructed not to post during the same period. All participants could log in to Facebook and read posts, but only the first group was allowed to make public posts or respond to other people’s posts. After the lapse of the time of study it was found that the second group reported lower levels of “belonging” and “meaningful existence” than those in the first group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the second study were even more astonishing and clearly depicted the role that social validation plays in our life. In the second study by the team, participants were asked to make a status update on a Facebook account set up by these researchers. However, the researchers had conditioned the experiment so that only half of them would receive a response on the update. Participants who received no feedback reported lower levels of belonging, self-esteem, meaningful activity than the ones who did receive feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Existentialism is a philosophical concept which deals with answering major life questions such as &quot;who am I?&quot; and underlining the major purpose behind one's existence. All of us face existential crises at some point of time in our life but social media just seems to have accelerated the process. Whenever something happens, we are more concerned about posting it and seeking others' opinions. We are not concerned about our perceptions but want others to hold a mirror for ourselves and ultimately their ideologies become our perceptions. The 'I' in the &quot;Who am I?&quot; is lost forever.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media presents a very skewed image of a person's life. Instead of portraying what your actual life is, you portray the kind of life you want others to see. This alone can create emptiness and push someone into an existential crisis. But there's more to it. Even your friends are doing the same thing. They’re posting selfies and bits of their life outlining the fabulous things they’re doing with their lives. And when you compare these things to your own relatively bleak existence, the cumulative effects lead to depression, anxiety and existential dread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation has been further aggravated with the advent of COVID-19. With everybody locked inside their homes, there is no other way to stay connected other than on these sites. The biased and tainted information that we receive through these social media handles have been responsible for worsening our mental health and psychological distress during this pandemic. With each passing day, the information makes you ruminate a little more till you have nothing but emptiness. In a study it was found that US college students are on their smartphones around nine hours a day. Further, coincidentally, anxiety in young people is alarmingly high.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As humans we cannot fight the need to fit in or the need for acceptance. Caught in the rising waves of this bermuda triangle and driven by the endless rat race, a lot of us forget what it's like to be ourselves. The mask of social media productivity and LinkedIn badges take away the little joys. Bruises on our bodies are visible but the bruises on someone's self image are never seen. However, there's one thing that makes you sail through these storms and that's faith. The curated world of social media is not even half of the truth. The struggles and downfalls behind those glittering profiles are silent. So, give yourself a daily reminder to take some time off this world. Prepare yourself to walk endlessly and no matter how cliché it may sound, we all should keep faith that it will all make sense one day.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>vanshika.singh shiksha.mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Bermuda Triangle is an unreal patch of sea in the Atlantic Ocean which is infamous for the disappearance of thousands of ships, cargo and airplanes in its vicinity. While there has been a lot of speculation about the reasons for such disappearances, there has been no consensus on one single theory to explain these mysterious occurrences. People have proposed theories from the triangle being an alleged home of aliens to mysterious creatures residing there and engulfing the ships that go that way.&amp;nbsp; Though I will not decipher the fundamental reasons behind these disappearances in this article, I will outline the aspects of another Bermuda Triangle that almost all of us have sailed through. While some of us could cross it successfully, some lost a part of themselves there. Man is a social animal. As Darwin said, &quot;Society is something that precedes an individual&quot;. Thus, the need to belong is intuitive. This fact that ‘belongingness is a need’ means that it is imperative for humans to maintain and establish some relationships. This theory has been explored by various psychologists including Freud and Maslow. Abraham Maslow placed belongingness in the needs hierarchy between physical needs and the need for self-esteem. Social media, the technology-enabled communication systems, have drastically altered the way we perceive ourselves as belonging in society. Social media is more about psychology and community rather than technology.&amp;nbsp; As a student who has just joined university amidst the COVID scenario, there's one thing I could definitely say- social media has had a lot of effect on my perceptions of myself. With the onset of university, there is one more social media that is added to your list apart from the usual networking sites, i.e. LinkedIn. When you start networking here, all of you would come across profiles that are absolute gold. With this facade that social media and networking sites create, they inadvertently point towards a better and happy life that is being led by people behind these profiles. Competition and comparison is inevitable. However, these personas are also attached to a false sense of belonging. People who are passive consumers on these sites suffer from greater levels of social loneliness and feelings of ostracism. Two studies conducted in this domain brought out the effect of social media consumption on the self esteem of the passive users. In the first one, some Facebook users were divided into two groups. One group was asked to post as usual over the study period, while the other group was instructed not to post during the same period. All participants could log in to Facebook and read posts, but only the first group was allowed to make public posts or respond to other people’s posts. After the lapse of the time of study it was found that the second group reported lower levels of “belonging” and “meaningful existence” than those in the first group. The results of the second study were even more astonishing and clearly depicted the role that social validation plays in our life. In the second study by the team, participants were asked to make a status update on a Facebook account set up by these researchers. However, the researchers had conditioned the experiment so that only half of them would receive a response on the update. Participants who received no feedback reported lower levels of belonging, self-esteem, meaningful activity than the ones who did receive feedback. Existentialism is a philosophical concept which deals with answering major life questions such as &quot;who am I?&quot; and underlining the major purpose behind one's existence. All of us face existential crises at some point of time in our life but social media just seems to have accelerated the process. Whenever something happens, we are more concerned about posting it and seeking others' opinions. We are not concerned about our perceptions but want others to hold a mirror for ourselves and ultimately their ideologies become our perceptions. The 'I' in the &quot;Who am I?&quot; is lost forever.&amp;nbsp; Social media presents a very skewed image of a person's life. Instead of portraying what your actual life is, you portray the kind of life you want others to see. This alone can create emptiness and push someone into an existential crisis. But there's more to it. Even your friends are doing the same thing. They’re posting selfies and bits of their life outlining the fabulous things they’re doing with their lives. And when you compare these things to your own relatively bleak existence, the cumulative effects lead to depression, anxiety and existential dread. The situation has been further aggravated with the advent of COVID-19. With everybody locked inside their homes, there is no other way to stay connected other than on these sites. The biased and tainted information that we receive through these social media handles have been responsible for worsening our mental health and psychological distress during this pandemic. With each passing day, the information makes you ruminate a little more till you have nothing but emptiness. In a study it was found that US college students are on their smartphones around nine hours a day. Further, coincidentally, anxiety in young people is alarmingly high.&amp;nbsp; As humans we cannot fight the need to fit in or the need for acceptance. Caught in the rising waves of this bermuda triangle and driven by the endless rat race, a lot of us forget what it's like to be ourselves. The mask of social media productivity and LinkedIn badges take away the little joys. Bruises on our bodies are visible but the bruises on someone's self image are never seen. However, there's one thing that makes you sail through these storms and that's faith. The curated world of social media is not even half of the truth. The struggles and downfalls behind those glittering profiles are silent. So, give yourself a daily reminder to take some time off this world. Prepare yourself to walk endlessly and no matter how cliché it may sound, we all should keep faith that it will all make sense one day.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
