<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/headline/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-05T12:09:57+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/headline/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why Bukayo Saka Should Be In England’s Euro 2020 Squad</title>
      <link href="/Bukayo-Saka-2020-Squad" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Bukayo Saka Should Be In England’s Euro 2020 Squad" />
      <published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bukayo-Saka-2020-Squad</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bukayo-Saka-2020-Squad">&lt;p&gt;During a difficult season for Arsenal, one of the major positives has been the rise of 18-year-old Bukayo Saka. The Hale End graduate started the season off with impressive performances on the left-wing, notably away at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sKrmDr0d6_0&quot;&gt;Eintracht Frankfurt&lt;/a&gt; and Manchester United, but it has been at left-back where Saka has really caught the eye in the last few months. With England’s dearth of talent at left-back, relative to their options on the right, it is worth considering whether Bukayo Saka should be in the Three Lions’ squad for Euro 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering he was only known as a tricky, slight, teenage winger a few months ago, it is difficult to overstate how impressive Saka has been since his move into defence following injuries to Kieran Tierney and Sead Kolasinac. He has held his own in the Premier League against more experienced and physical right-wingers, showing himself to be adept in 1v1 duels. What’s more is that Saka has also rarely been caught out positionally for someone who has such little experience of the position. This ability to learn on the fly bodes well for his progression for England and Arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with his solid defensive play, he has still managed to flourish as an attacking force; the 18-year-old is frequently being used as one of the focal points of Arsenal’s attack. Slick combination play with the likes of Mesut Ozil and Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang results in Saka often finding himself in threatening positions where he can whip in a quality left-footed cross to the Arsenal striker, as he did for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mom_VOTUxmk&quot;&gt;Eddie Nketiah’s equaliser vs Everton&lt;/a&gt;. Should he make the England squad, then the likes of Harry Kane and Tammy Abraham will be licking their lips over the prospect of feasting off of his crosses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned, England’s current crop of left-backs are distinctly average, with there being no one on the level of Kyle Walker, Aaron Wan-Bissaka or Trent Alexander-Arnold. Ben Chilwell is currently manager Gareth Southgate’s first choice and, despite some patchy form this season, seems virtually assured of his place in the Euros squad. Danny Rose has joined Chilwell in the last five England squads, but this season has been a disappointing one for Rose after having been dropped at Tottenham by Jose Mourinho. He is trying to resurrect his career at Newcastle but still looks some way off the player he was a few years ago and he certainly won’t be assured of his place in the Three Lions’ squad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the World Cup in Russia two years ago, it was Ashley Young who was the starter at left-wing-back, however, the veteran hasn’t added to his 39 caps since, despite recently establishing himself in the XI of title-challenging Inter Milan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teenager Brandon Williams has looked solid, if unspectacular, since taking Young’s place in the Manchester United side. However, like Young, his propensity to cut inside onto his prefered right foot isn’t ideal when trying to build fluid attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2014, the thought of Luke Shaw being an afterthought for Euro 2020 would have been laughable, but a rough five and a half year stint at Old Trafford has meant he is currently just that. Shaw has featured just twice for England in the last four years but still represents a solid option for Southgate, especially since having proven himself to be competent in a back-three in recent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Tackles/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Key Passes/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Interceptions/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Passes Completed/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dribbles Completed/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dribbled Past/90&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;England Caps&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Ben Chilwell&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;58.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Danny Rose&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;45.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Bukayo Saka&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:bold&quot;&gt;2.1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;36.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Luke Shaw&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;60.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Brandon Williams&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;49.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Ashley Young&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;49.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Stats from all competitions in the 2019/20 season (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whoscored.com/&quot;&gt;www.whoscored.com/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking someone of Bukayo Saka’s age and inexperience to a major tournament wouldn’t be unprecedented for England with the likes of Michael Owen and Wayne Rooney famously capturing the world’s attention as 18-year-olds in 1998 and 2004 respectively. Whilst it would be outlandish to claim Saka is on par with those two, Marcus Rashford, Theo Walcott and Shaw have also gone to major tournaments as teenagers and even though they didn’t make a significant impact it provided the (then) youngsters with a great experience moving forward. Rashford looks on his way to becoming a key-player for England and this would have likely been the case for Walcott and Shaw had injuries not derailed their progress. Walcott’s hat-trick as a 19-year-old in Zagreb against a tricky Croatia side serves as an example of how getting youngsters integrated into the international set-up can benefit their progress on the big stage in the following years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst he may be deserving of a place in the England squad by the summer, it is important to bear in mind that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football/50886874&quot;&gt;Saka has still not committed his international allegiance to the country of his birth&lt;/a&gt;. Born in East London to Nigerian parents, Saka hasn’t ruled out playing for the Super Eagles and, if they don’t act fast, England could find themselves losing out on a precocious talent in similar circumstances to how they let Wilfried Zaha slip through their grasp and into an Ivory Coast shirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be understandable if Gareth Southgate elects not to take Saka to the Euros in favour of a safer choice, especially considering the England squad is already relatively young and inexperienced. With that being said, Bukayo Saka could be the perfect wildcard addition to fill a problem position and there’s no reason to think he isn’t capable of making the squad should he continue his good form.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">During a difficult season for Arsenal, one of the major positives has been the rise of 18-year-old Bukayo Saka. The Hale End graduate started the season off with impressive performances on the left-wing, notably away at Eintracht Frankfurt and Manchester United, but it has been at left-back where Saka has really caught the eye in the last few months. With England’s dearth of talent at left-back, relative to their options on the right, it is worth considering whether Bukayo Saka should be in the Three Lions’ squad for Euro 2020.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Premier League’s 2019/20 Rising Stars</title>
      <link href="/PL-Rising-Stars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Premier League’s 2019/20 Rising Stars" />
      <published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/PL-Rising-Stars</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/PL-Rising-Stars">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another example of Brazil’s extraordinary footballing talent, Martinelli was playing in the fourth tier of Brazilian football before moving to north London. He’s as tenacious and fearless as a freeclimber and although he may lack height and stature, his quick feet, range of finishes and mature decision-making are evidence of precocious ability. Still only 18, he’s already scored 3 goals in 5 league starts this season. Clearly, Arsenal have unearthed a gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brandon Williams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The departure and decline of Ashley Young and Luke Shaw respectively has enabled this Manchester United academy graduate to break into the first-team. Rather than looking out of place or short of confidence, which would be typical of a teenager appearing in the most watched league in the world, Williams’ excellent showings have caught the eye. Proficient with both feet, quick, good technically and able to hold his own against the very best, he is the epitome of the modern fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams had no trouble counteracting the threat of Adama Traore, one of the most powerful and skillful wingers in the league, so much so that Adama was forced to switch flanks in the repeat 3rd round FA Cup fixture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emiliano Buendia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Argentine’s stats this season are something to behold. He’s completed the 3rd most take-ons (78) and the 2nd most chances created (68) in the division, with only Kevin De Bruyne having created more goal scoring opportunities. He’s also the only player in the league to have completed 50+ tackles, take-ons and chances created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stats are evidence of his tremendous quality; he works as hard as anyone, while also having the close control and passing ability of an elite playmaker. With Norwich almost certain to go down, the 22-year-old should be at the top of many clubs’ shopping lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Todd Cantwell&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The England U21 international has been another bright spark for a side who’ve been bottom for most of the season, having popped up with 6 goals and 2 assists so far. Born and bred in Norfolk, and a product of the Norwich academy, he’s a talented dribbler with clever passing and movement which makes him a real handful for defenders. He is another Norwich player who’s been linked with a move away pending their imminent relegation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tammy Abraham&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After scoring 25 goals in the Championship with Aston Villa last season, the 22-year-old returned to his parent club this season and has donned the number 9 shirt for Chelsea accordingly. Tall, quick and skillful, his quality is undoubted after scoring 13 goals in 23 appearances so far this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His clever movement in addition to fine link-up play means he will always pose a threat, and his performances this season have deservedly led to an England call-up. With Harry Kane facing a long injury layoff, Abraham will relish the opportunity to lead the line for the Three Lions at the upcoming European Championships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Japhet Tanganga&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanganga had to wait patiently to be given his first league start for Tottenham after impressing in pre-season against the likes of Real Madrid and Juventus. After being thrust in for his Premier League debut against Liverpool earlier this month, the 20-year-old followed it up with another outstanding display against Middlesbrough in the FA Cup in which he was named Man of the Match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily a centre-back, he’s so far been deployed at right-back and left-back in addition to his favoured role, and some have even gone so far to suggest that he could be an option in defensive midfield. His positional sense fused with his astute reading of play makes him a top-class centre back, but his speed and comfort on the ball makes him adept in both fullback positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing the elite Belgian centre-back pairing of Vertonghen and Alderweireld will be no easy task but supporters and staff alike are confident that Tanganga can cement himself in the Spurs backline for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dean Henderson&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 22-year-old is a stalwart of Chris Wilder’s Sheffield United team and has been key to their success over the last 2 seasons. With current England ‘keeper Jordan Pickford flattering to deceive, many fans are calling for the in-form Blades goalie to replace Pickford between the sticks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The on-loan Manchester United ‘keeper has conceded just 20 goals in 23 appearances this season, racking up 8 clean sheets. This trumps both Pickford and Nick Pope, who are Henderson’s main rivals for the England number 1 jersey - Pickford has conceded 35 in 24 appearances with 6 clean sheets, while Pope has let in 38 in 23 with 7 clean sheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henderson’s save percentage is superior too. Of the 15 Premier League goalkeepers to have saved 50+ shots this season, Henderson has the highest save percentage (74.68%). Meanwhile, Pickford and Pope’s save percentages are 64% and 60% respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main gripe with Henderson is that his passing stats are not particularly attractive. While Pickford has completed 56.77% of his passes this season, Pope has completed 38.29%, but Henderson’s passing accuracy is just 33.72%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southgate is a keen proponent of playing out from the back and it seems unlikely that he will replace Pickford between the sticks, whom he’s trusted for the last 2 years, but there’s certainly a strong case for Henderson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reece James&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This youngster is a phenomenon; it’s rarely the case that a player is able to combine technical excellence with physical power and strength, but James is a special case. Though he’s just 19, James plays well beyond his years. It is no wonder why he was named Chelsea’s Academy Player of the Year 2017/18, Wigan’s Player of the Month 4 times in the same season, and in the EFL Championship Team of the Season 2018/19. Although his defensive positioning could be improved upon, he’s often the most creative player on the pitch with his magnificent passing and unrivalled crossing ability. He’s always an outlet on the right-hand side with his pace and intelligent forward runs, and in addition to his direct dribbling, he possesses a menacing shot, his strength is devastating and he has no trouble getting stuck in and timing tackles to perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James’ competencies allow him to excel in a variety of positions, from his favoured right-back role to centre-back to central midfield. His talent and versatility is so noteworthy that it led Wigan’s manager, Paul Cook, to proclaim that “Reece James could play in goal, he’s that outstanding!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England have a flurry of top-class right backs at the moment, and Reece James is making a case for himself to be the most complete. Jermaine Jenas on Match Of The Day described him as a hybrid between Trent Alexander-Arnold, Kyle Walker, Kieran Trippier and Aaron Wan-Bissaka because of the way in which James possesses the best qualities of them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jack Grealish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grealish was still a boy with unleashed potential when his side were relegated from the top-flight 4 years ago, however, this time round he is a fully fledged man and has been a shining light for a team who are among the dark depths of possible relegation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Able to effectively break the lines with marvellous dribbling and an eye for a pass, he also tracks back and works hard defensively, while also being a first-class finisher who’s adept with both feet. The talisman of his boyhood club has been one of the standout players in the league and his presence significantly increases Villa’s chances of staying in the division. It beggars belief as to how he’s not yet been called up for England, with seemingly everyone but Southgate praising his remarkable ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 24, he has all the necessary qualities to succeed wherever he goes, and a big money move is surely on the cards this summer. Tottenham will be rueing the fact that they came close to securing his signature in the summer of 2018 for a fee that would’ve been paltry compared to his value now as he would’ve gone a long way towards replacing Christian Eriksen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.premierleague.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.premierleague.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Gabriel Martinelli</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Mauricio Pochettino’s Next Move</title>
      <link href="/Mauricio-Pochettino-Next-Move" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mauricio Pochettino’s Next Move" />
      <published>2020-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Mauricio-Pochettino-Next-Move</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Mauricio-Pochettino-Next-Move">&lt;p&gt;Mauricio Pochettino’s 5 year spell in charge of Tottenham Hotspur came to an end in November after he was sacked by chairman Daniel Levy. As one of Europe’s most highly rated managers, this came as somewhat of a surprise and it’s left the football world waiting to see what his next move will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though his Tottenham tenure ended bitterly, there should be no doubt that Pochettino was a resounding success during his half decade in North London. Pochettino revitalised a club which had been in turmoil the season before his appointment and oversaw several impressive cup runs, including reaching the 2019 Champions League final, as well as four consecutive top 4 finishes during his time at the club. Pochettino put Spurs on the world map as they became able to go toe-to-toe with Europe’s elite, and his achievements didn’t go unnoticed as he was continually linked with some of the biggest clubs in the world. In 2019, the 47-year-old was named as one of the three finalists in the FIFA Men’s Best Coach award, alongside Pep Guardiola and eventual winner Jurgen Klopp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around the Champions League final that some serious cracks in his marriage to Spurs began to appear when he said that he may walk away if they lifted the trophy. Whether this was seen as a lack of commitment by the club’s hierarchy and contributed to his dismissal is pure speculation, but what is known is that he was instantly replaced by Jose Mourinho indicating the board went behind Pochettino’s back to search for his successor while he was still in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A manager that put together the best 5 year run in Tottenham’s modern history, including a staggering 86-point 2016/17 season, deserved a more dignified exit than &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mirror.co.uk/sport/football/news/mauricio-pochettinos-tottenham-sacking-caught-20970112&quot;&gt;being given his marching orders&lt;/a&gt; in front of cameras for a cash-grab for the club. On the plus side for Pochettino, he will now be able to move on from a club that, quite incredibly, decided to go 18 months without a first-team signing, and he will surely attract interest from some world football powerhouses. So, what are the Argentine’s options?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Barcelona&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite claiming that he would never manage Barcelona due to his past affiliation with their rivals Espanyol, he had still been linked with the position as it became clear the writing was on the wall for Ernesto Valverde. After openly pursuing their former legendary midfielder Xavi Hernandez in the hope he would take over, they eventually settled on former Real Betis coach Quique Setien. Setien has been given a contract until 2022 but that likely won’t stop rumours of Xavi or Pochettino replacing him surfacing as soon as his Barca side hit a rough patch. Whilst the Barcelona squad would suit Mauricio Pochettino, it would take a monumental change of heart for him to take charge at the Camp Nou, so this can be considered an unlikely option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real Madrid&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been through 17 managers in the past 16 years, Real Madrid aren’t shy about changing coach if things aren’t going well. Madrid are having a modest season by their standards, 2nd in their Champions League group and on course for 80 points in La Liga under Zinedine Zidane. However, with Eden Hazard unable as of yet to fill a Ronaldo sized hole and key players such as Sergio Ramos, Toni Kroos and Luka Modric not what they once were, Los Blancos’ season could quickly head south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A trophyless season could see Zidane depart again and Mauricio Pochettino has previously been linked with the 13-time European Champions. Unlike with Barcelona, his Espanyol spell won’t stand in the way of him becoming Real Madrid manager and it would be an opportunity to truly show he belongs among Europe’s elite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There would be no shortage of funds to construct a squad in his image and he would already have a great mix of veterans, such as Karim Benzema and Marcelo, and young starlets like Rodrygo, Federico Valverde and Vinícius Júnior. Real are well known for being trigger happy when it comes to changing managers which may be a concern for Pochettino who has just enjoyed a 5 ½ year stint at a club where he became comfortable, but he likely knows this to be an anomaly in modern football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, top clubs rarely retain a manager for more than 3 years and Pochettino may end up having spells at several top European clubs like Pep Guardiola and Carlo Ancelotti have done, for example. If Pochettino believes in his ability as a manager (and the opportunity presents itself) then he should jump at the chance to test himself at the biggest club in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manchester United&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should he decide to stay in the Premier League, then Manchester United would surely be the most likely option, with the Argentine having been continually linked with them since they sacked his eventual successor at Spurs, Jose Mourinho, last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that United have been a mess since Sir Alex Ferguson retired 6 and a half years ago, with Ole Gunnar Solskjaer being the 4th underwhelming manager during this time. Whilst Man United have more financial power than Tottenham, there has been criticism of United’s transfer policy under Ed Woodward due to several big money flops. This criticism was only exacerbated last summer when United failed to replace Romelu Lukaku, leaving themselves with a threadbare squad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite United’s poor recent track record in the transfer market and inadequate squad, the chance to resurrect a sleeping giant must be one that intrigues Pochettino. A young core centred around Marcus Rashford, Aaron Wan Bissaka and Scott McTominay can’t compete with some of Europe’s best, but it provides a solid foundation for Woodward and the United manager (whoever it may end up being) to build around. That is as long as they use their considerable funds in a way that constructs the best team possible rather than making a bunch of ‘statement signings’ like Zlatan Ibrahimovic, Bastian Schweinsteiger, Alexis Sanchez, Radamel Falcao etc. Serious investment would likely have to be promised in order for Pochettino to come to Old Trafford and it may be that he decides it’s too big of a project for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manchester City&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Down the road, United’s ‘noisy neighbours’ have had an underwhelming start to their league campaign as they languish 16 points behind Liverpool. Pep Guardiola has never stayed at one club beyond 4 seasons and if he were to continue that trend and leave this summer then Pochettino would surely represent an ideal replacement. City have an embarrassment of riches to play with, boasting arguably the best squad in Europe, and Pochettino could be the man to continue what Pep started and go toe to toe with Jurgen Klopp’s Reds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bayern Munich&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Mauricio Pochettino wants to return to management imminently, then Bayern Munich certainly represent a presentable option for him. Hans-Dieter Flick is currently in interim charge after Niko Kovac’s departure last month, however it would be difficult for Bayern management to favour him over someone with Pochettino’s reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the Bavarians have done a solid job of moving on from some veteran club stalwarts such as Franck Ribery and Arjen Robben whilst phasing out Thomas Muller and Jerome Boateng to allow the club’s impressive young nucleus to grow and put the club in a position to once again challenge for the Champions League. They have stagnated since Pep Guardiola left in 2016 and Mauricio Pochettino could be the man to restore an identity to Bayern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pochettino experienced great success at White Hart Lane with an attack built around an excellent all-round centre-forward in Harry Kane and, being a similar type of player, Robert Lewandowski would flourish in a Pochettino attack surrounded by the likes of Serge Gnabry and Kingsley Coman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paris Saint-Germain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mauricio Pochettino spent 2 and a half years at PSG in the early 2000s and once said that a return to Paris would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/football/2016/apr/28/tottenham-mauricio-pochettino-psg-dream&quot;&gt;“one of his dreams”&lt;/a&gt;. Despite PSG having a very solid season, Thomas Tuchel’s future depends on their Champions League performance, so, should there be another disappointing European exit, Pochettino’s dream may become a reality this summer and in many ways it would be the perfect job for him. First and foremost, PSG are still progressing as a project and have a squad that puts them firmly in and amongst Europe’s elite. Any team which includes Neymar and Kylian Mbappe has to be considered desirable for an ambitious manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a major criticism of Pochettino is that he hasn’t yet won a managerial trophy. He would almost certainly break that drought at the earliest opportunity at a PSG side that has consistently racked up silverware over the last decade. After overcoming that hurdle, he would then have to set about trying to win the Champions League with a squad brimming with talent and winning experience along with an ambitious owner. The PSG job won’t come with the same scrutiny as some of the other historically great European clubs and that could also appeal to Pochettino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Mauricio Pochettino decides he’s ready to return to management, he won’t be short of suitors and it is up to him to pick the right club to ensure that his reputation as a top manager continues to grow.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Mauricio Pochettino’s 5 year spell in charge of Tottenham Hotspur came to an end in November after he was sacked by chairman Daniel Levy. As one of Europe’s most highly rated managers, this came as somewhat of a surprise and it’s left the football world waiting to see what his next move will be.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Christmas On K2 - Everest’s Tougher Little Brother</title>
      <link href="/K2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christmas On K2 - Everest’s Tougher Little Brother" />
      <published>2020-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/K2</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/K2">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;In height, it may be second to Everest. But in notoriety, well, I shall leave the words unsaid.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a regular Christmas party or for that matter, even at the bar or the library, if you declare you are an Everest summiteer, you’ll undoubtedly be catapulted to instant fame and accorded the title of a hero, much more than the average fifteen-minutes-of-fame the average Joe achieves in a lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you have climbed a mountain which goes by the name of K2 (or Mount Godwin Austen), your jubilant declaration is likely to meet with a horde of confused stares. Maybe, just maybe, you’ll receive a couple of congratulations, although half-hearted ones at that. And only if you are lucky, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people have never heard of K2 or really any mountain other than Everest, of course. In mountaineering parlance, it is the same way a ‘novice’ climber who is ‘escorted’ up Everest thanks his lead guide profusely but utterly overlooks the contribution of the Sherpas, without whose help any ascent would be impossible. In cricketing parlance, it would be akin to people having heard of a certain Andre Russell, but not a Ryan Harris. However, it wouldn’t be right to blame them since they hardly know better. After all, all of us in school only learnt that the highest (mind you, not the tallest - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/trevornace/2015/11/25/tallest-mountain-in-the-world-debatable/#322bb80c221c&quot;&gt;the tallest is Mauna Kea, Hawaii&lt;/a&gt;) mountain in the world is Mount Everest, and that was it. Consider this - we learnt the highest mountain was Mount Everest, however what we never learnt is why or what makes it the highest et cetera, which probably would have been the more important question. But that is another story, for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;K2, situated in the Karakoram range of Northern Pakistan, is the second highest mountain in the world, rising a staggering 8,611 metres above sea level. To put that into perspective, imagine going vertically upwards for more than eight kilometres. Daunting, eh? Well for all it’s height, it still falls short of Everest’s by the length of a couple of football fields, something which, I daresay, has haunted it since eternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said that, The Himalayas, The Karakoram and The Hindu Kush Mountains boast some of the highest mountains in the world, with all of the fourteen ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eight-thousander&quot;&gt;eight-thousanders&lt;/a&gt;’ (mountains reaching a height of 8000 m) situated in one of the former two ranges and the latter boasting the highest number of ‘seven-thousanders’. Most of these mountains are located in either Nepal, Tibet, Pakistan or Afghanistan. However, even India and China find themselves taking a slice of the cake, with a number of mountains sitting on the borders of these countries, most notably Kanchenjunga (India-Nepal) and K2 (Pakistan-China).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, the human body simply lacks the ability to survive, let alone function, at the kind of heights we are talking about here. And at a point in time that happens, even attempting to climb a structure which covers one’s entire vision of the horizon from even as much as 100 miles afar, becomes an intrinsically irrational act. Regardless, despite the obvious fallacy of the thought, the 1900’s saw the birth of the belief that these mountains could be climbed, with more than a few tragic cases of going to the extent of believing that nature could be overpowered. However, until 1950, none of the eight-thousanders were climbed, with the more prominent ones to have failed including &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Mallory&quot;&gt;George Leigh Mallory and Andrew Irvine&lt;/a&gt;. After Maurice Herzog climbed the mountain with the highest ascent-to-fatality ratio, Annapurna, in 1950, the belief saw a mighty resurgence, with expeditions one after the other. And when the hallowed Everest was finally conquered by a certain Edmund Hillary and the affable Tenzing Norgay, the floodgates well and truly opened. The last eight-thousander to be climbed for the first time was Shishapangma Peak, in 1964.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter part of the 1900’s saw a number of successful ascents on the world’s highest peaks, owing to greater technology, advanced fitness regimes and established routes to the summits. However, for all the technology, these mighty peaks, in winter, withstood the onslaught of the human race. Slowly and steadily, humans found themselves on the top before February 26 (the designated date marking the end of the winter season) on 13 of the 14 eight-thousanders, with the most recent one being the successful summit of Pakistan’s infamous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/adventure/adventure-blog/2016/02/27/absolute-misery-climbers-complete-the-historic-first-winter-ascent-of-nanga-parbat-the-killer-mountain/&quot;&gt;Nanga Parbat (Naked Peak)&lt;/a&gt; in 2016. There are no prizes for guessing which is the last peak to remain. A number of mountaineers, including the legendary Reinhold Messner, deem the task “as close to impossible as it gets”. While the first summit of Mount Everest in winter was in as far back as 1980, an age where equipment could be considered archaic in comparison to today’s standards, K2 still remains unclimbed in winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why K2 is a much more difficult climb than Mount Everest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might argue that if K2 was commercialised as heavily as Everest is today, we would see the mountain being conquered much more easily. However, this argument would fall flat in the face of the 26% fatality ratio of K2. One only has to look at the list of the people who have died on the mountain, and would easily notice that the list contains a number of accomplished and all the more celebrated climbers. What is more is that, the statistic of 1 in 4 deaths only includes those climbers who have summited K2 and does not include people who died on the mountain’s perilous slopes without summiting. If that was added, the statistic would look much more ominous, if it does not already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, let’s come to the topography of the respective mountains in discussion, K2 and Everest. For starters, Everest Base Camp is relatively easier to get to, requiring only a few days trek from Kathmandu, Nepal’s capital. In comparison, one has to trek over 100 kilometres on dangerously steep country from the nearest village (Askole) to reach K2’s base camp, making it one of the most physically demanding hikes planet Earth has to offer. To provide further perspective and well, allure, the mountain is so remote that Pakistani locals never even bothered to name the mountain. It’s counterparts K1 (Masherbrum), K4 (Gasherbrum), K5 (Gasherbrum-II) and Broad Peak (Faichan Kangri) all had local names before the venture of the British, but not the then-unnamed Mount Godwin-Austen, owing to its unparalleled remoteness. Furthermore, K2 and the Karakoram house a much more unpredictable climate and harsher winds than the Himalayas. The easterlies that blow in from the Central Asian highlands are hindered in their journey by the Karakoram, which is located north-west of Nepal, thus significantly reducing their speeds before they reach the Himalayas. Owing to the same dangerously fickle weather, the Karakoram is more prone to avalanches, a sure sign of doom for any mountaineer, however experienced he or she might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the routes, Everest is usually climbed through either the North Face route or the South Col Route. The trails are so well established that many a climber has commented that he/she simply ‘walked upto the top’. Of course, there is the infamous Hillary Step and the Khumbu Icefall lower down, whose might is not to be underestimated, but these obstacles can be overcome with precise application of basic technicalities. However, K2 does not have as many twists and turns, which increases its ‘steepness’ by a considerable margin. As a result, an ascent of K2 requires skilful manoeuvring, something that cannot be expected of the fifty-year-old average Joe who eats chips and drinks cola thrice a day. In addition, if one is skilled, or rather lucky enough, to cross the lower areas of the mountain and successfully evades the ubiquitous avalanches along the way, one is confronted by the mighty ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bottleneck_(K2)&quot;&gt;Bottleneck&lt;/a&gt;’, an outrageous couloir of overhanging ice seracs, which x-ray the climbers underneath and could topple at the slightest misstep. One can only hope and pray that one is not underneath a serac which surely will come hurtling down, sooner or later. Upon crossing the Bottleneck, one still has to climb a long distance as the summit still stands far away. This has given the mountain the reputation of having the ‘longest (summit) day’, despite the distance to be covered being roughly equal to the distance one has to cover on Everest’s summit day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, the fact that the mountain hasn’t been summitted yet in winter should come as no surprise. Mountaineers, both established and (informed) amateurs, regard K2 as the Holy Grail of Mountaineering, and the toughest assignment a climber could ever face in his lifetime. Therefore, if one were to complete this unlikely feat, they would have claimed one of the last remaining great prizes in mountaineering - the first winter ascent of the world’s second-highest mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece could come off as slightly disrespectful, towards Mount Everest in particular. However, that is not the case. It’s immense altitude still fazes many climbers, with more than 200 bodies on the mountain’s slopes being a testament to this fact. Despite the development and usage of brutal technology on Everest, the mountain still remains an incredibly difficult one to climb, particularly along the Eastern (Kangshung) face. The tragedy of 1996, an event narrated in ‘Into Thin Air’ by Jon Karakeur and adapted multiple times into the cultural arena, and the more recent 2015 earthquake in Nepal which took 18 lives, is justification of Sagarmatha’s eternal might. However, what is merely being contested through this write-up is that K2 receives the respect it deserves. And perhaps, on an arguably more aesthetic level, this article deals with how human nature is obsessed with only the best and the biggest whilst blatantly ignoring both the runners-up and the dark horse, be it whatever field. Needless to say, in this case, the best refers to Everest, with K2 donning the mantle of the classic ‘so-near-yet-so-far’ trope, in popular human perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, as I write this, two simultaneous cross-cultural expeditions attempting to climb K2 in the 2019 winter have failed, with disputed reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end with a little trivia, Annapurna, Nanga Parbat and potentially the isolated Kanchenjunga boast a higher ‘deadly’ rate, with Annapurna leading at 34% and also having seen the least number of ascents to date. However, the difficulty of attempting K2, much less summiting, is not up for debate at the ‘Elite Mountaineers’ Club’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even if your mate at the library does not fully appreciate the enormity of your achievement, you have managed to huff and puff your way into the Elite Mountaineers’ Club, er, I mean, the summit of K2.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="extreme-sports" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“In height, it may be second to Everest. But in notoriety, well, I shall leave the words unsaid.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The End of the Wildcard Era</title>
      <link href="/The-End-Of-The-Wildcard-Era" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of the Wildcard Era" />
      <published>2020-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-End-Of-The-Wildcard-Era</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-End-Of-The-Wildcard-Era">&lt;p&gt;It’s obvious to even the casual viewer that wildcard weekend has some of the dullest storylines of the year. Another weekend where a powerhouse divisional champion hosts an underdog wildcard winner. On paper, this is exciting. The NFL playoffs are on a single-game format, so any team could end up making a historic run to the Super Bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen it twice in recent history, the New York Giants were an underdog team and ended up dethroning the great Tom Brady. This is the type of storyline fans want to see every year. Unfortunately, this is not what we’ve come to expect from the wildcard weekend. Too many times we’ve seen a completely boring matchup between a team we expect to win, and a team we expect to lose, badly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One matchup indicates the time of the wildcard is over, or at least on the path to being adjusted. The Philadelphia Eagles will be hosting the Seattle Seahawks on wildcard Sunday. You might be wondering why this matchup is so special. The powerhouse Seahawks are 11-5 on the season, while the Eagles are only 9-7. Why does a lesser team have the right to home-field advantage in the first round of the playoffs? The answer is simple; divisional winners will always host a wildcard team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes total sense considering the divisional winner usually has a better record than the team they are hosting, but this isn’t the case for two teams this season. The Minnesota Vikings are 10-6 and the Seahawks are 11-5. Why should either of these teams be punished because of a terrible NFC East division? If either the Seahawks or the Vikings were in the NFC East, they would be hosting a wildcard team this weekend. While ‘fairness’ should be a factor in changing the rules, excitement is a better reason to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good football team like the Seahawks shouldn’t have to prove they can win on the road to a Philadelphia Eagles squad that barely snuck into the playoffs. It should be the other way around, as it has been in many of the NFL’s great underdog stories, with the unexpected team having to prove themselves. Watching the Eagles escape with a victory on CenturyLink Field in Seattle would create a much more exciting divisional matchup next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most people do not expect the Eagles to hold off the Seahawks, a string of injuries for both teams will make this game closer than originally expected. Going forward, the NFL should consider changing the seeding to reflect the standings rather than division winners. It is already a rare occurrence for a divisional winner to have a worse record than a wildcard so why not reward the better team?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday night’s matchup between the Seahawks and 49ers was exciting and meant the winner would go on to have a first-round bye and home-field advantage throughout the playoffs. And the loser? The loser (the Seahawks) plays wildcard weekend on the road in Philadelphia. How does this make any sense? Why should the Seahawks end up playing on the road throughout the entire playoffs due to the lack of success in the NFC East? There isn’t really a good answer to either of these questions but there is a solution going forward; to eliminate divisional seeding all together and to have divisional records impact seeding based on the teams in each division. This would mean that two teams with identical records would be seeded based on their divisional records or games played between the two teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Sunday night game between the (at the time) 11-4 Seahawks and 12-3 49ers shouldn’t indicate who escapes the wildcard spot but rather who will have the home-field advantage. Yes, this would make season matchups less exciting, especially when so much was on the line in Sunday night’s game. However, this would alleviate the problem of lackluster conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is highly unlikely that a division has two Super Bowl contenders in the first place, but when it does happen, you better believe one of the teams will get screwed and end up on the road during the wildcard weekend. It’s time to stop rewarding poor divisions and teams with a free home game in the playoffs and start making them work even harder. While the season matchups could be affected by this rule change, the playoffs would be a lot more exciting, just like when Eli Manning led the lowly New York Giants on the road to a spectacular Super Bowl victory in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the 2011 Giants Super Bowl run had a similar storyline to 2019. The Giants played at home against a 10-6 Falcons team who were pushed into the wildcard by a better New Orleans Saints team in their division. Had the format been changed back then, Eli Manning might only have 1 Super Bowl championship but if he had ended up winning on the road again, it would have made for an even better story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the main reason the NFL would have for changing the playoff seeding. It is a sport and league rich with history and unbelievable stories, which shouldn’t allow an underachieving team to sneak into home-field advantage and ride that momentum to the Super Bowl. If the NFL ever does change this format, we could have many amazing underdog stories. Teams like the Seahawks wouldn’t be on the road for the first round of the playoffs while fans remain in disbelief that a 9-7 Eagles team is hosting wildcard weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NFL Standings on FOX Sports: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foxsports.com/nfl/standings&quot;&gt;https://www.foxsports.com/nfl/standings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aric Kirsten</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="american-football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s obvious to even the casual viewer that wildcard weekend has some of the dullest storylines of the year. Another weekend where a powerhouse divisional champion hosts an underdog wildcard winner. On paper, this is exciting. The NFL playoffs are on a single-game format, so any team could end up making a historic run to the Super Bowl.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Ole ‘Goner’ Solskjaer?</title>
      <link href="/Ole-Goner" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ole ‘Goner’ Solskjaer?" />
      <published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ole-Goner</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ole-Goner">&lt;p&gt;Since being appointed as permanent Manchester United manager, Ole Gunnar Solskjær’s win rate in the Premier League is just 32%, a figure meagre enough for any manager to get sacked, let alone one of a club who are so accustomed to glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do the problems begin and end at Manchester United?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to appoint Ole Gunnar Solskjær on a full-time basis in March 2019, after a 3 month period in which he was greatly successful, epitomised the naivety and ineptitude of the United board. For whatever reason, the United board could not wait until the end of the season to take a more balanced, level-headed decision on the managerial appointment. The fans could be forgiven for believing that the initial honeymoon period which saw a huge upturn in results made Ole the right man for the job, but for the board to buy into this delirium exhibits an utter lack of prudence and shrewdness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their haste to appoint the legendary former striker as manager, they took a risk which has backfired and the decision becomes ever more questionable and costly as each day passes by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last season, when Jose Mourinho was relieved of his duties by Ed Woodward, he had accumulated 26 points from 17 games in the league. This campaign, Ole has managed 25 points in the same number of games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester United have seemingly settled for mediocrity under Solskjær. In recent weeks, Arsenal, Tottenham and Everton have all fired their underperforming managers and replaced them. While United have dithered and dallied, Everton have been able to allure one of the most decorated managers in the world in Carlo Ancelotti, a man who surely would have been of interest to United.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If United were to sack Solskjær soon, Max Allegri and Mauricio Pochettino would be among the favourites to succeed the Norwegian. Ed Woodward and co. have long been admirers of former Spurs boss Pochettino, but they will have to act quickly if they wish to acquire his services. The Argentine has become one of the most sought after coaches in world football during the last few years and he will have no shortage of job offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hit and Miss Signings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signings have also been a sticking point of United’s in recent years. The £80m expended to obtain Harry Maguire was exorbitant, excessive and another example of United overpaying for a player. He’s undoubtedly one of the best centre-halves in the league, but his quality still fails to justify such an inflated fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexis Sanchez was another extortionate mistake, and while Fred has improved in recent weeks, the Brazilian is yet another player who has failed to vindicate such a large price tag. Meanwhile, defenders Diogo Dalot and Eric Bailly have failed to flourish and have subsequently fallen out of favour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youngsters Daniel James and Aaron Wan-Bissaka have been better signings, but both are still raw and will take time to develop into the class of player that United were previously famed for. They would also both benefit from competition for their places; ironically, they are more nailed on to start for Manchester United than they were at their respective previous clubs, Swansea City and Crystal Palace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back even further, the acquisitions of Wilfried Zaha and Memphis Depay perhaps came too early in their careers. Both have gone on to forge formidable reputations for themselves and proven that the Red Devils should have remained patient with them when they didn’t immediately thrive at such young ages. The star quality they possess certainly wouldn’t go amiss at United at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lacking a Playmaker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot has been made of the fact that the Red Devils struggle to break down opposition teams who sit deep. United are bereft of ideas when facing low blocks; they are crying out for a playmaker who can control the tempo of games and break teams down with line-breaking passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In games which tend to be more open, typically against higher quality opposition, United have enjoyed more success. They have the benefit of being able to utilise the lightning quick pace of Rashford, Martial and James, enabling them to be menacing on the break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one damning statistic which proves this notion. United currently lie in 6th place, and they have amassed 13 points from the 5 teams that sit above them, but just 12 points from the teams below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With recent victories over Spurs and rivals City, Ole has bought himself more time to prove to the Old Trafford faithful that he’s got what it takes to be successful in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a positive note, Solskjær is bringing the best out of Marcus Rashford this year. The 22-year-old is in sumptuous form, enjoying his best goal scoring season to date. This is perhaps one reason that the United hierarchy have no plans to sack their manager anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason for sticking with the Norweigian is stability. Stability is vital for any football club and group of players, and a club who had the same manager for 26 years prior to 2013 know that better than anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the reasons outlined above, United’s decay is not entirely the fault of the former Molde manager. He is struggling with an incompetent board and an imbalanced squad, but questions remain over whether Ole has the managerial experience and tactical acumen needed to prevail at the biggest club in England. With long-term managerial target Mauricio Pochettino currently out of a job, it would make sense for Ed Woodward to try to entice Pochettino towards Carrington.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since being appointed as permanent Manchester United manager, Ole Gunnar Solskjær’s win rate in the Premier League is just 32%, a figure meagre enough for any manager to get sacked, let alone one of a club who are so accustomed to glory.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why PSG Should be Champions League Favourites</title>
      <link href="/Why-PSG-Should-be-Champoins-League-Favourites" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why PSG Should be Champions League Favourites" />
      <published>2019-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-PSG-Should-be-Champoins-League-Favourites</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-PSG-Should-be-Champoins-League-Favourites">&lt;p&gt;After a summer that was dominated by transfer rumours focused around wantaway Brazillian star Neymar, it’s been easy to overlook Paris Saint-Germain when it comes to considering Champions League contenders. Coupled with perennial European underachievement since their 2011 Qatar takeover, the Parisians still aren’t seen as a major Champions League contender by many and that won’t change until they advance past the Champions League quarter-finals, but could this be their year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Squad&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst history isn’t on their side, they undoubtedly have one of the very best squads in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve arguably never had an elite goalkeeper since the takeover, with Salvatore Sirigu, Kevin Trapp, Alphonse Areola and 41-year-old Gianluigi Buffon all having stints in goal. Last season Buffon was directly at fault for a goal in their 3-1 knockout round loss to Manchester United and to solve this issue they made the astute acquisition of 3 times Champions League winner Keylor Navas from Real Madrid. Despite riding the bench last season, the Costa Rican has established himself as one of Europe’s elite shot-stoppers over the last 5 seasons and represents a marked improvement from their previous options, and at just 32 years old, should still have a few top seasons left in the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the back, their squad remains largely the same, with the exception of Dani Alves’ departure and the arrival of Abdou Diallo from Borussia Dortmund, but it’s difficult to improve upon the excellent central defensive trio of Marquinhos, Thiago Silva and Presnel Kimpembe. Full-back is arguably the Parisians’ weakest area, although Juan Bernat and Thomas Meunier are both very capable going forward, especially when used as wing-backs alongside a back three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outfield signing, which will likely have the biggest impact on their defensive solidity, is 30-year-old midfielder Idrissa Gana Gueye. The tenacious Senegal international arrived from Everton with little fanfare compared to some of PSG’s previous star signings but could be just as important. Since the decline and subsequent departure of Blaise Matuidi in 2017, PSG have been lacking some athleticism in the middle of the park which Gueye will no doubt provide. He has already hit the ground running with a man-of-the-match performance in a 3-0 win over Real Madrid and he has been joined by another industrious, tough-tackling midfielder in the shape of Ander Herrera. Herrera and Gueye, along with Marco Verratti, are exactly the type of midfielders that top teams need to succeed in Europe; energetic, hardworking and defensively solid. Verratti has become one of Europe’s premier central midfielders over the past half decade and PSG’s success will depend on him remaining disciplined and avoiding a repeat of his costly red card against Real Madrid in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top, PSG’s attacking firepower speaks for itself: Neymar, Kylian Mbappe, Edinson Cavani, Angel Di Maria and Mauro Icardi ensure that PSG will never be lacking in firepower. Nevertheless, it is essential that PSG have a fit and available Neymar for the knockout stages if they want to go all the way. The Brazil star is one of the best players in the world, yet he has only managed to play one Champions League knockout match since arriving in Paris due to injury and is once again sidelined, this time by a hamstring problem, after three serious ankle injuries in the previous 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst PSG have improved their already impressive attacking depth with the signings of Icardi and Pablo Sarabia from Inter and Sevilla respectively, Neymar’s deadly combination of goal-scoring, dribbling and creativity can only be matched by Lionel Messi and he has the ability to completely alter the outcome of a Champions League knockout match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PSG’s attacking depth should allow for a lot of rotation and rest for Neymar in order to keep him fresh. And when the Brazilian superstar lines up alongside Mbappe and Cavani, they create an attacking trio that would fancy their chances against any opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//parissaintgermain-1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:40%&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//parissaintgermain-2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; margin-left:10%; text-align: left; width:40%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newly formed superclubs such as PSG, Roman Abramovich’s Chelsea and Manchester City under the Abu Dhabi United Group have all historically tended to underperform in the Champions League in the first years of their projects, relative to financial investment and expectations. This may be partly attributed to a lack of European pedigree and winning culture, where lots of players and staff involved with the club haven’t experienced much in the way of major continental success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PSG, however, now have a wealth of Champions League experience in their squad with Silva, Marquinhos, Verratti, Cavani, Draxler, Neymar, Di Maria and Navas all having over forty Champions League appearances to their name, with the latter three winning the competition during their spells at Barcelona and Real Madrid respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even at his young age, Kylian Mbappe already has eight Champions League knockout goals and the young World Champion and his teammates should be able to avoid mental issues which have crippled them in the past, most notably in the humiliating 6-1 defeat to Barcelona in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Contenders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Real Madrid’s European domination came to an end last year, there hasn’t been an obvious favourite in a wide-open competition that featured several improbable comebacks last year (including one at PSG’s expense), and it’s looking like a similar story this year. Liverpool are naturally one of the favourites after last season’s triumph and whilst they have an excellent starting XI, injuries to key players could damage their hopes due to a lack of squad depth in certain areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fellow Premier League juggernauts Manchester City may be the favourites this year, but they have failed to get past the quarter-finals in the past three years under Pep Guardiola largely due to poor results in away legs and are also suffering from a lack of depth in defensive positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spanish teams are the most successful of any nation in European cup competitions, and Barcelona, Real Madrid and Atletico Madrid have been 3 of Europe’s top teams this decade, however all 3 have issues which could prevent them from going all the way. After failing to re-sign Neymar, Barcelona’s over-reliance on Lionel Messi will once again be evident this season due to Luis Suarez’s decline and the misuse of Antoine Griezmann, who has often found himself stuck out on the left-wing. Meanwhile Ernesto Valverde is a manager under pressure due to embarrassing collapses in Rome and Liverpool in the last two UCL campaigns as well as an unconvincing start to this season. So, there are understandable doubts about this very talented side’s ability to go all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over in Madrid, Real have gotten off to a shocker in the Champions League, losing to PSG and drawing to Club Brugge with the absence of Cristiano Ronaldo still felt despite Eden Hazard’s arrival. When you look at the likes of Marcelo, Sergio Ramos, Luka Modric, Gareth Bale and Toni Kroos all seemingly in a state of decline and the comprehensive manner in which Ajax ended their 3-season reign as European champions last season, it certainly appears as though this edition of Real Madrid’s team is coming to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Down the road from the Bernabeu, Diego Simeone’s Atletico will always be a well-drilled unit but have struggled for goals so far this season, netting only 10 in 10 league games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the likes of Juventus and Bayern can never be written off. Juventus under Sarri have a well-rounded team but neither them nor Bayern look as strong as they did in previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most prestigious club competition in the world is wide open this year. With a tactically astute manager and top squad featuring some of the best attackers in the world, don’t bet against PSG finally going all the way this year.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">After a summer that was dominated by transfer rumours focused around wantaway Brazillian star Neymar, it’s been easy to overlook Paris Saint-Germain when it comes to considering Champions League contenders. Coupled with perennial European underachievement since their 2011 Qatar takeover, the Parisians still aren’t seen as a major Champions League contender by many and that won’t change until they advance past the Champions League quarter-finals, but could this be their year? Squad Whilst history isn’t on their side, they undoubtedly have one of the very best squads in Europe. They’ve arguably never had an elite goalkeeper since the takeover, with Salvatore Sirigu, Kevin Trapp, Alphonse Areola and 41-year-old Gianluigi Buffon all having stints in goal. Last season Buffon was directly at fault for a goal in their 3-1 knockout round loss to Manchester United and to solve this issue they made the astute acquisition of 3 times Champions League winner Keylor Navas from Real Madrid. Despite riding the bench last season, the Costa Rican has established himself as one of Europe’s elite shot-stoppers over the last 5 seasons and represents a marked improvement from their previous options, and at just 32 years old, should still have a few top seasons left in the tank. At the back, their squad remains largely the same, with the exception of Dani Alves’ departure and the arrival of Abdou Diallo from Borussia Dortmund, but it’s difficult to improve upon the excellent central defensive trio of Marquinhos, Thiago Silva and Presnel Kimpembe. Full-back is arguably the Parisians’ weakest area, although Juan Bernat and Thomas Meunier are both very capable going forward, especially when used as wing-backs alongside a back three. The outfield signing, which will likely have the biggest impact on their defensive solidity, is 30-year-old midfielder Idrissa Gana Gueye. The tenacious Senegal international arrived from Everton with little fanfare compared to some of PSG’s previous star signings but could be just as important. Since the decline and subsequent departure of Blaise Matuidi in 2017, PSG have been lacking some athleticism in the middle of the park which Gueye will no doubt provide. He has already hit the ground running with a man-of-the-match performance in a 3-0 win over Real Madrid and he has been joined by another industrious, tough-tackling midfielder in the shape of Ander Herrera. Herrera and Gueye, along with Marco Verratti, are exactly the type of midfielders that top teams need to succeed in Europe; energetic, hardworking and defensively solid. Verratti has become one of Europe’s premier central midfielders over the past half decade and PSG’s success will depend on him remaining disciplined and avoiding a repeat of his costly red card against Real Madrid in 2018. Up top, PSG’s attacking firepower speaks for itself: Neymar, Kylian Mbappe, Edinson Cavani, Angel Di Maria and Mauro Icardi ensure that PSG will never be lacking in firepower. Nevertheless, it is essential that PSG have a fit and available Neymar for the knockout stages if they want to go all the way. The Brazil star is one of the best players in the world, yet he has only managed to play one Champions League knockout match since arriving in Paris due to injury and is once again sidelined, this time by a hamstring problem, after three serious ankle injuries in the previous 18 months. Whilst PSG have improved their already impressive attacking depth with the signings of Icardi and Pablo Sarabia from Inter and Sevilla respectively, Neymar’s deadly combination of goal-scoring, dribbling and creativity can only be matched by Lionel Messi and he has the ability to completely alter the outcome of a Champions League knockout match. PSG’s attacking depth should allow for a lot of rotation and rest for Neymar in order to keep him fresh. And when the Brazilian superstar lines up alongside Mbappe and Cavani, they create an attacking trio that would fancy their chances against any opposition. &amp;lt; Experience Newly formed superclubs such as PSG, Roman Abramovich’s Chelsea and Manchester City under the Abu Dhabi United Group have all historically tended to underperform in the Champions League in the first years of their projects, relative to financial investment and expectations. This may be partly attributed to a lack of European pedigree and winning culture, where lots of players and staff involved with the club haven’t experienced much in the way of major continental success. PSG, however, now have a wealth of Champions League experience in their squad with Silva, Marquinhos, Verratti, Cavani, Draxler, Neymar, Di Maria and Navas all having over forty Champions League appearances to their name, with the latter three winning the competition during their spells at Barcelona and Real Madrid respectively. Even at his young age, Kylian Mbappe already has eight Champions League knockout goals and the young World Champion and his teammates should be able to avoid mental issues which have crippled them in the past, most notably in the humiliating 6-1 defeat to Barcelona in 2017. The Contenders After Real Madrid’s European domination came to an end last year, there hasn’t been an obvious favourite in a wide-open competition that featured several improbable comebacks last year (including one at PSG’s expense), and it’s looking like a similar story this year. Liverpool are naturally one of the favourites after last season’s triumph and whilst they have an excellent starting XI, injuries to key players could damage their hopes due to a lack of squad depth in certain areas. Fellow Premier League juggernauts Manchester City may be the favourites this year, but they have failed to get past the quarter-finals in the past three years under Pep Guardiola largely due to poor results in away legs and are also suffering from a lack of depth in defensive positions. Spanish teams are the most successful of any nation in European cup competitions, and Barcelona, Real Madrid and Atletico Madrid have been 3 of Europe’s top teams this decade, however all 3 have issues which could prevent them from going all the way. After failing to re-sign Neymar, Barcelona’s over-reliance on Lionel Messi will once again be evident this season due to Luis Suarez’s decline and the misuse of Antoine Griezmann, who has often found himself stuck out on the left-wing. Meanwhile Ernesto Valverde is a manager under pressure due to embarrassing collapses in Rome and Liverpool in the last two UCL campaigns as well as an unconvincing start to this season. So, there are understandable doubts about this very talented side’s ability to go all the way. Over in Madrid, Real have gotten off to a shocker in the Champions League, losing to PSG and drawing to Club Brugge with the absence of Cristiano Ronaldo still felt despite Eden Hazard’s arrival. When you look at the likes of Marcelo, Sergio Ramos, Luka Modric, Gareth Bale and Toni Kroos all seemingly in a state of decline and the comprehensive manner in which Ajax ended their 3-season reign as European champions last season, it certainly appears as though this edition of Real Madrid’s team is coming to an end. Down the road from the Bernabeu, Diego Simeone’s Atletico will always be a well-drilled unit but have struggled for goals so far this season, netting only 10 in 10 league games. Additionally, the likes of Juventus and Bayern can never be written off. Juventus under Sarri have a well-rounded team but neither them nor Bayern look as strong as they did in previous years. The most prestigious club competition in the world is wide open this year. With a tactically astute manager and top squad featuring some of the best attackers in the world, don’t bet against PSG finally going all the way this year.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Can England Make the Most of Their Upcoming Golden Generation?</title>
      <link href="/England-Golden-Generation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Can England Make the Most of Their Upcoming Golden Generation?" />
      <published>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/England-Golden-Generation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/England-Golden-Generation">&lt;p&gt;English football has been going through a resurgence in recent years. Along with the likes of Liverpool flying the flag high for England, the national team has excelled at various levels as the World Champion U20 and U17 teams were followed by the senior side achieving their best finish at a World Cup for 28 years. It’s evident that the raw talent coming through the ranks is something special, but now the attention turns to whether the England national team can harness this potential and produce a side good enough to compete for major honours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;English Excellence - Young Players on the Rise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Goalkeepers&lt;/em&gt;: Mark Travers, Dean Henderson, Aaron Ramsdale&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Centre-backs&lt;/em&gt;: Joe Gomez, Fikayo Tomori, Axel Tuanzebe, Rob Holding, Ben Godfrey, Marc Guehi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fullbacks&lt;/em&gt;: Aaron Wan-Bissaka, Trent Alexander-Arnold, Ben Chillwell, Ryan Sessegnon, Reece James, Jamal Lewis, Max Aarons, James Justin, Ainsley Maitland-Niles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Central midfielders&lt;/em&gt;: Declan Rice, Morgan Gibbs-White, Ruben Loftus-Cheek, Hamza Choudhury, Joe Willock, Lewis Cook, Oliver Skipp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Attacking midfielders&lt;/em&gt;: Phil Foden, Mason Mount, James Maddison, Angel Gomes, Emile Smith-Rowe, Todd Cantwell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wingers&lt;/em&gt;: Ademola Lookman, Jadon Sancho, Reiss Nelson, Callum Hudson-Odoi, Harvey Barnes, Dwight McNeil, Bukayo Saka&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strikers&lt;/em&gt;: Eddie Nketiah, Tammy Abraham, Rhian Brewster, Mason Greenwood&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As these players’ abilities is not in doubt, continued hunger to be the best and staving off injuries while maximising gametime for their clubs will be the pivotal factors as to whether these young players are able to sustain long-term success. Complacency in major tournaments has been an issue for England teams in the past, and it was also manifest during the recent U21 European Championships in which many of the players mentioned above were involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England can look at how recent World Cup winners were able to make the most of their talented generations and try and replicate certain aspects of their successes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spain (Euro 2008 &amp;amp; 2012, World Cup 2010 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain were widely considered perennial underachievers on the international stage before their triumph in 2008, as they had produced talented players, such as Raúl, Fernando Hierro and Emiliano Butragueño, but hadn’t won a major honour since 1964.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think of the all-conquering Spain team, technically outstanding players such as Xavi, Andrés Iniesta and Cesc Fàbregas immediately spring to mind. It was no coincidence that Spain produced such an array of small, talented midfielders that Santi Cazorla and Juan Mata could barely get any game time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain worked from the ground up to establish a footballing culture centred around players that were comfortable on the ball and could dominate possession. This philosophy set them apart from other contenders at the time as they suffocated possession, making their opponents have to drastically change their gameplans. Such was this team’s influence that there has been a rise in ‘Spanish style’ English midfielders, such as Phil Foden, who differ from the stereotypical English midfielder. The use of St. George’s Park National Football Centre in 2012 would have hopefully got some of the current youngsters to grow together following a similar footballing philosophy which may now be applied to the senior team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Germany (World Cup 2014 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it’s hard to argue that a nation with 4 World Cups and 3 European Championships has one single golden generation, the group that propelled Germany to 2014 glory are certainly a good example of a close-knit group of players that all progressed lineally. Key players like Mats Hummels, Mesut Özil, Sami Khedira, Manuel Neuer, Jerome Boateng, Toni Kroos and Thomas Müller were all born between 1986 and 1989 and had grown up playing together from a young age for both club and country. Five of the aforementioned players started the U21s Euro 2009 final where they got a taste of victory as they trounced England 4-0. All were subsequently involved in the 2010 World Cup where the youngsters impressed on their way to the semi-finals, putting 4 past both England and Argentina in the knockout stages before succumbing to eventual winners Spain. Although they fell short, this was a resounding success for this young team as Thomas Müller won the Golden Boot and Mesut Özil and Sami Khedira both earned moves to Real Madrid off the back of the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did this generation’s experience hold them in good stead for their 2014 World Cup win, but a group of players born from 1983-1985 had preceded the 2010 class by reaching the semis of the 2006 World Cup. Phillip Lahm, Per Mertesacker, Lukas Podolski and Bastian Schweinsteiger were all 22 years or younger during this tournament and played starring roles which they used to build on their international careers. Lahm and Mertesacker retired from international football immediately after their 2014 World Cup triumph in Brazil whilst Podolski and Schweinsteiger did so a few years later with the quartet accumulating 468 caps between them. That level of experience is invaluable when trying to win major honours and England can try and emulate this template to some degree. Jordan Henderson, Raheem Sterling, Dele Alli, John Stones, Harry Kane et al. have already experienced tournament football with England and can use their experiences, both positive and negative, to try and guide the new crop of U23 talent in the same way the Germans did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;France (World Cup 2018 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that England can take away from France’s World Cup 2018 winning side is how manager Didier Deschamps didn’t just cram all the most talented players into the starting XI, but rather opted for the most balanced team. After starting mercurial winger Ousmane Dembele in their World Cup opener against Australia, Deschamps eventually settled on a team with target man Olivier Giroud favoured over a more prolific striker like Alexandre Lacazette whilst box-to-box midfielder Blaise Matuidi started on the left side of midfield over more creative players like Dembele, Thomas Lemar and Nabil Fekir. This new lineup was very well balanced, complimenting star players Paul Pogba, Antoine Griezmann and Kylian Mbappe. Deschamps was famously called “the water carrier” during his playing days by Eric Cantona, and just as he allowed the likes of Zinedine Zidane to flourish, he found the winning formula for France as manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, after France’s disastrous, mutinous 2010 World Cup campaign, the French Football Federation prioritised good squad harmony. Despite mediocre showing in the subsequent 2 tournaments, the FFF were happy with the job Deschamps had done having replaced Laurent Blanc. It should be noted that neither Franck Ribery (retired) nor Karim Benzema played for France after 2015 and despite being arguably the nation’s two most talented players, the team thrived. Benzema was still an elite centre-forward but after his blackmail scandal involving French teammate Mathieu Valbuena, the Real Madrid striker wasn’t considered for selection again. Both him and Ribery had careers riddled with controversy and could have disrupted the excellent squad chemistry and morale in the French dressing room. Due to their triumph in Russia, no one involved in French football will have any regrets over their omissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;England 2000-2010&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England’s previous ‘golden generation’ were notorious underachievers. Despite boasting players who were world-class for their clubs such as Rio Ferdinand, David Beckham and Wayne Rooney to name but a few, they consistently flattered to deceive on the international stage, never advancing past the quarter-finals of a major tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, this side provides an excellent example of how not to maximise the potential of a golden generation and what Southgate and co. should look to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the obvious downfalls was Sven-Göran Eriksson putting out an XI of all the most ‘talented’ players and the team that looks the best on paper, but not the best team in reality. Steven Gerrard and Frank Lampard infamously struggled to play together in midfield in a 4-4-2 formation with neither player’s quality being fully utilised. Lampard and Gerrard often played alongside the likes of Javier Mascherano and Claude Makelele at club level, allowing the English duo more freedom but English holding midfielders such as Gareth Barry, Michael Carrick and Owen Hargreaves started intermittently so there was no real chemistry that could be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shoehorning players out of position was also a theme for this England team with Paul Scholes and Steven Gerrard often deployed wide left, and whilst this worked for France when they moved Matuidi wide, Matuidi is naturally left-footed and France played a 4-2-3-1 / 4-3-3 hybrid, an entirely different system than the 4-4-2 used by Sven-Göran Eriksson. When you add in Frank Lampard, England had 3 elite centre-midfielders yet their midfield never seemed to really stand out as a collective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue was that, due to fierce club rivalries, there was some tension between England’s stars. Rio Ferdinand stated that once he and then close friend Lampard went their separate ways after leaving West Ham, they stopped speaking to each other due to the ferocity of the Chelsea-Manchester United rivalry with both clubs regularly vying for titles. Whilst selecting players who play for rival clubs isn’t a barrier to international success, as Spain showed with a team largely comprised of Barcelona and Real Madrid players, it’s essential that Southgate’s England don’t let petty rivalries bring down their morale and derail their potential success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current England (2018 - present)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably the most significant feature of Southgate’s reign is that he has harmonised the England setup so that club rivalries do not infringe on the national team’s unity. It is no longer the case that England players only spend time with their clubmates on national duty and, as many English pundits, fans and players have noted since the 2018 World Cup, there is a real sense of togetherness now with England’s senior team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although man-for-man the current England XI can’t compete with Eriksson’s 2000’s team, it does seem as though the current England set up will help England’s talented next generation to succeed in a way that Eriksson’s didn’t. The FA should now be aware of what to avoid and what to do when assembling a team for contention. England have the talent, now it’s time to use it correctly.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">English football has been going through a resurgence in recent years. Along with the likes of Liverpool flying the flag high for England, the national team has excelled at various levels as the World Champion U20 and U17 teams were followed by the senior side achieving their best finish at a World Cup for 28 years. It’s evident that the raw talent coming through the ranks is something special, but now the attention turns to whether the England national team can harness this potential and produce a side good enough to compete for major honours.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Toronto Got Its One Dance, Is There More?</title>
      <link href="/Raptors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toronto Got Its One Dance, Is There More?" />
      <published>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Raptors</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Raptors">&lt;p&gt;Drake references aside, Toronto finally got over the hump by completing the impossible (defeating the juggernaut team from the Bay), made possible by a preseason acquisition and the emergence of a reliable forward: Pascal Siakam. Despite the success of last season and playing in a weak/top-heavy conference, the Raptors will need to survive the trade deadline without losing any major pieces and receive strong playoff performances from Siakam, Van Fleet and Lowry to have a shot at repeating a championship run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest offseason move for Toronto was a subtraction, rather than an addition - the loss of Kawahi Leonard in free agency. Upper management of the Raptors front office knew that this huge off-season transaction to receive Leonard, preceding the 2018-2019 season, could be a one-year rental, as Leonard has openly expressed his desire to play close to Los Angeles for the past three seasons. Despite this, the Raptors pulled the trigger and were willing to come to terms with the large possibility that this would be a one-year lease. The lease worked, reeling in the franchise’s first Larry O’Brien Trophy; however, they must now move forward without a perennial superstar. A core consisting of Gasol, Van Fleet, Siakam, Lowry, and Ibaka has the power to make the playoffs in a weak Eastern Conference, but with expiring contracts and the aforementioned lack of a star, Toronto will need a lot of external help to repeat last year’s success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see how the team looks come the trade deadline because of these expiring contracts and the strong internal urge from several front office officials to push the reset button and begin the rebuilding process. Doing so will allow the Raptors to gain a little compensation back from players, such as Gasol or Ibaka, who no longer fill the void of being roster centerpieces, but rather are being seen and used as role players. These players could reel in sizeable amounts of young talent from teams in contention who are looking for one more piece from a mid-season pick-up to push them over the hump. Although this could set Toronto up for seasons to come, doing so would effectively end their chances of being a real contender for the championship this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young bucks Siakam and Van Fleet took tremendous strides last season and are now pivotal pieces to the future of Toronto’s franchise. Siakam reeled in the NBA’s Most Improved Player of the year, while Van Fleet put on a complete show during the Finals. A large portion of Toronto’s future success and direction depends directly on the play and development of these two young players. If they continue to build on last season’s performance, the future of Toronto’s core looks extremely bright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Toronto’s chances of repeating as NBA Champions seem to be relatively thin, anything can happen in a league that has undergone so many physical and emotional changes this offseason. As long as player development continues within Toronto’s young core, and the front office refrains from hitting the reset button at the trade deadline, Toronto will be in the picture to come out of the Eastern Conference next summer.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gavin Olson</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Drake references aside, Toronto finally got over the hump by completing the impossible (defeating the juggernaut team from the Bay), made possible by a preseason acquisition and the emergence of a reliable forward: Pascal Siakam. Despite the success of last season and playing in a weak/top-heavy conference, the Raptors will need to survive the trade deadline without losing any major pieces and receive strong playoff performances from Siakam, Van Fleet and Lowry to have a shot at repeating a championship run.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Houston, Are We Finally Clear for Takeoff?</title>
      <link href="/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Houston, Are We Finally Clear for Takeoff?" />
      <published>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff">&lt;p&gt;Houston has, perhaps, been one of the most perplexing franchises over the past three seasons because of their seemingly non-existent presence come playoff time. This second installment of breaking down the path to the Larry O’Brien Trophy will discuss the steps the Houston Rockets will need to take in order to finally get over the hump of their recent string of postseason woes, as well as why the Rockets have a strong chance of coming out on top of the 10-team gauntlet that is the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s turn the clock back to the 2016/17 season in which the Rockets went 55-27. Up to this point, James Harden had put up strong performances, however this was the season in which the Rockets finally found their identity: give Harden the ball and allow him to go to work against opposing defenses.With Harden averaging a strong stat line of 29.1/11.2/8.1 (points/assists/rebounds per game), the Rockets were able to secure the third seed in a historic season in which the Golden State Warriors went 67-15. Despite otherworldly offensive talent, Harden was only able to propel the Rockets to the second round of the playoffs, losing a series against the San Antonio Spurs 4-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the second round exit, GM Darly Morey actively pursued several top talents across the NBA that he could pair up with Harden to help carry the load. Out of this search came the (at the time) huge acquisition of Chris Paul. On paper this seemed like a match made in heaven, as Chris Paul is easily one of the top-five passing point guards to have ever played in the association. Having a player of this caliber to accompany Harden causes defenses to draw up on a different defensive scheme, which would, hypothetically, leave players (Eric Gordon, Trevor Ariza, Clint Capela, etc.) open for easier looks, as teams would now have to hone in the Harden/Paul duo out of the backcourt. This trade reaped instant benefits, as the Rockets easily claimed the first seed in the Western Conference, with the Golden State Warriors claiming the second seed 7 games behind the leading Rockets. The year also saw James Harden, once again, astonish the world with his mesmerizing offensive prowess and earn the honor of being crowned the NBA MVP for the 2017/18 regular season. While the Rockets obtained, what was in their eyes, the best possible outcome in the regular season, they again came up short losing to the Golden State Warriors in the Western Conference Finals after being 3-2 up in the series and having the home-court advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This frustration carried over into the 2018/19 season, as the Rockets were unable to consistently stay above the 500 mark into mid-December, largely due to the injury of Chris Paul which sidelined him for roughly half of the season. Despite the slow start, the Rockets saw themselves in the 4th seed, due to the play of James Harden, who seems to have elevated his offensive arsenal to the point that holding him to under 25 points is considered a defensive victory. The Rockets, once again, fell to their foe (the Golden State Warriors) in 6 games in the Western Conference Semifinals, marking yet another early exit. Emotions ran extremely high following the devastating loss, as the Warriors were without Kevin Durant and were expected to lose the series to the Rockets. Soon thereafter, strong disgruntled feelings were reported between James Harden and Chris Paul. Despite the constant dismissal of these reports, this ultimately lead to another blockbuster acquisition by the Rockets this past season, as Harden was reunited with fellow MVP Russell Westbrook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reunification of a backcourt duo of Westbrook and Harden is extremely intriguing given their past playing experience with each other, as well as how their individual playing styles line up very similarly. It is difficult, and misleading, to look at the stats from the three seasons that they were teammates in Oklahoma City because Harden was more of a role-player, and neither had fully reached their offensive potentials that make them top-20 talent players in the current NBA. We, as fans, have learned from the Chris Paul experiment that the success of this acquisition will largely depend on the willingness of James Harden to share the ball. The purpose of the Paul trade in the 2017 offseason was to help take the pressure off of Harden, however, due to injury and ego, Harden put up 1909 field goal attempts, which is nearly 300 more shot attempts than the next highest season, which spans back to times when James Harden was the only offensive power helping the Rockets stay afloat. Harden’s game thrives off of his ability to handle the ball from the second it is inbounded, so the acquisition of another player (especially one that plays the point guard position by nature) that thrives off of holding the ball and making something happen slightly resembles the trade for Paul in the 2017 season, which never came to full fruition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the skepticism, Harden and Westbrook have a different relationship than that of Harden and Paul. Westbrook has the potential to thrive playing off the ball, something that Paul widely struggled with. If Harden and Westbrook are able to create a system in which neither are suffering from not being able to get their shots up, then the Rockets have the potential to bring the Larry O’Brien Trophy back to Houston for the first time since the back-to-back championships in 1994 and 1995. Eric Gordon, PJ Tucker and Clint Capela will most likely round out the rest of the starting five and place their respective starting rotation among the likes of every other top team in the league (Lakers, Clippers, Bucks, 76ers, etc.). With potential contributions off the bench from Tyson Chandler, Austin Rivers, Danuel House and Gerald Green, the Rockets are set-up well to ride the wave when Westbrook and Harden are getting breathers. The talent is definitely present in Houston, as it has been for several seasons. The large looming question is whether the acquisition of Russell Westbrook is more of the same, or if it is the start of a new Warrior-esque dynasty in the West. If good health and cohesion are present in the Rockets locker room, then so will be the Larry O’Brien Trophy come June 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gavin Olson</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Houston has, perhaps, been one of the most perplexing franchises over the past three seasons because of their seemingly non-existent presence come playoff time. This second installment of breaking down the path to the Larry O’Brien Trophy will discuss the steps the Houston Rockets will need to take in order to finally get over the hump of their recent string of postseason woes, as well as why the Rockets have a strong chance of coming out on top of the 10-team gauntlet that is the Western Conference.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
