<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/headline/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-08-21T16:58:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/headline/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The NBA Runs Through L.A. - Lakers Team to Beat</title>
      <link href="/Lakers-Team-to-Beat" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The NBA Runs Through L.A. - Lakers Team to Beat" />
      <published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lakers-Team-to-Beat</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lakers-Team-to-Beat">&lt;p&gt;The NBA offseason has definitely been one for the books, with foreseeable trades and signings, as well as history-altering pick-ups. Although the Eastern Conference has seemingly stolen the best player in the league (at least up until the Finals - Kevin Durant) and has teams with potentially perennial talents (Giannis Antetokounmpo or the Joel Embiid/Ben Simmons tandem), the power of the NBA will still mostly reside in the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the departure of Kevin Durant and the dreadful injury to Klay Thompson, the Golden State Warriors have seemingly opened the door to the rest of the Western Conference, despite bolstering their roster in the short-term with the sign-and-trade deal with the Brooklyn Nets for D’Angelo Russell. An argument can be made for several teams in the west to pick up the torch (which can be read in my breakdown articles of each team), however this article will focus on the path the Los Angeles Lakers can follow in order to retake the reins of the NBA, which seems to be more open than it has been for the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the 2018/19 season, the Lakers were able to reel in the talents of Lebron James on a four-year deal, with the hopes of luring in another superstar, such as Kawahi Leonard or Paul George, during the offseason. In the short-term, James was tasked with taking an ill-advised, yet somewhat promising, mix of old and new players to the playoffs for the first time since the 2012/13 season. However, early promise shown by youngsters Lonzo Ball, Kyle Kuzma and Brandon Ingram was not enough to prevent the Lakers from their inevitable doom of not reaching the playoffs yet again, as they were frustrated by key injuries and inconsistent contributions from role players across the rotation, with a groin injury to Lebron James on Christmas night being the heaviest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading into this offseason and free agency, the Lakers were drawing a tremendous amount of attention around the NBA circuit, however none of it was pertaining to their plans to sign another big name. The Lakers were bogged down by issues within the front office and ownership, as well as speculation that James wanted out of Los Angeles. This was all silenced when the trade of Anthony Davis, who was previously written off as a potential trade option given the strong opposition from key members within the New Orleans’ front office, was announced. Shortly afterwards, the Lakers were then in the running for the addition of Kawahi Leonard, which would have arguably assembled the most potent big three the league has ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lakers sacrificed the possible signings of several other role players, such as Josh Reddick, so that they would have the financial capability to sign Leonard while still having wiggle room for next season when Anthony Davis will officially become a free agent. In holding out for Leonard, who they ultimately were unable to sign, several players that would have provided much needed shooting support were signed to other teams. Despite the loss of several potential role pieces, the Lakers were still able to benefit by having several contracts with potential bench pieces in place in case their pursuit of Leonard came up short. The same night that Leonard broke the news that he was heading to the other LA-based organization, the Lakers proceeded with this Plan B, and inked deals with Demarcus Cousins, Danny Green, Quinn Cook, Avery Bradley and Jason Dudley. They also resigned Rajon Rondo, JaVale McGee and Kentavious Caldwell-Pope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a potential starting-five of James and Green at the guards, Kuzma and Davis as forwards, and a rotation of Cousins/McGee at the center, the Lakers could replicate the formidable offensive capabilities that the Warriors have been known for with their various starting five line-ups over the past two seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Hamptons Five Lineup was the most dynamic line-up the league has ever seen, the Lakers have set their team up for better success due to the surrounding support of their bench. This past NBA Finals we saw that despite having a star-studded starting rotation, it is still possible to come up short when it matters (although gruesome season-ending injuries to Thompson and Durant did not help the Warriors’ case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James and Davis are proven entities within the NBA, so the Lakers should be in every game that both players are able to suit up and play in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kuzma is the only bright young spot that was not shipped off to New Orleans during the acquisition of Davis, and he has the potential to become a strong third contributor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green is a proven three-point specialist and will have an instant impact on a Lakers team that struggled to shoot from deep last season (33.3%), despite throwing up an average of 31 3-pointers a night. Green will also provide strong defensive support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGee had a strong first season with the Lakers last season. He averaged 12 points and 7.5 rebounds in 22.3 minutes, appearing in 75 games. With the signing of Demarcus Cousins it is probable that McGee will see less minutes, however it will depend largely on the health and conditioning of Cousins. Cousins was unable to land the large, long-term deal that he had anticipated following a cheap one-year deal with the Warriors this past season, largely due to heavy criticism of his lack of conditioning in the back half of the season, as well as the Finals. If Cousins comes to opening night in good shape, he should receive the bulk of minutes at the center position, as he has the potential for a huge bounce-back season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acquisitions of Dudley and Bradley are extremely intriguing, as both have proven their worth in the NBA but neither are more than bodies off the bench. Cook is an interesting back-up guard that has played many minutes as a back-up to Stephen Curry, and Rondo has been a proven dimer since his time in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the NBA Finals it would have been crazy to think that the Lakers would be in the position they are in now. The long-term success of the Lakers is dependent on the health status of James, Davis and Cousins, as well as getting consistent contributions from the bench. If both boxes are checked come the end of the season, and the Lakers head into the playoffs at full health, they will be the toughest team to beat, and should come out of the West on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gavin Olson</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The NBA offseason has definitely been one for the books, with foreseeable trades and signings, as well as history-altering pick-ups. Although the Eastern Conference has seemingly stolen the best player in the league (at least up until the Finals - Kevin Durant) and has teams with potentially perennial talents (Giannis Antetokounmpo or the Joel Embiid/Ben Simmons tandem), the power of the NBA will still mostly reside in the Western Conference.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Legitimate a Contender is Ben Askren and What Does the Future Hold for the Former Champion?</title>
      <link href="/Ben-Askren" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Legitimate a Contender is Ben Askren and What Does the Future Hold for the Former Champion?" />
      <published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ben-Askren</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ben-Askren">&lt;p&gt;For many, the news of a deal between One Championship and the UFC to bring one of the hottest welterweight names in MMA in the form of Ben Askren to Dana White’s organisation set pulses racing. The previously undefeated Askren had become widely regarded as one of the welterweight GOATs, amassing an undefeated 18-0 record during his time in both Bellator and One Championship before his move to the UFC. Whilst throughout his career Askren’s stand-up game had been called into question, his incessant grappling and collegiate wrestling background allowed him to dominate almost all of his opponents including big names such as Douglas Lima and Shinya Aoki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, recently the tune has changed for Askren. His unconvincing victory over Robbie Lawler in his UFC debut at UFC 235 drew more questions about the legitimacy of Askren’s talents, after having almost been knocked out in the opening minute of the bout. After he engaged the clinch immediately versus Lawler, Askren was brutally sent into the canvas by a piledriver, from where on Askren absorbed heavy ground and pound from the ex-champion. Once Askren successfully regained the clinch, he was able to take Lawler down and secure a bulldog choke. Referee Herb Dean stepped in to ensure Lawler was still conscious after his arm appeared to go limp. After shaking his arm, Herb Dean assumed Lawler was out, not seeing the thumbs up from Lawler indicating that he was still conscious. Dean promptly ended the bout, which incurred strong protest from Lawler who had clearly been conscious the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his post-fight interview Askren made it clear that he would not entertain the idea of a rematch between himself and Lawler, creating yet more controversy around the manner of his victory, leading many to question whether or not Askren was out of his depth. It appeared as if Askren was simply afraid of losing his undefeated record, which had been extended to 19-0, hence his reluctance to book another fight with Lawler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it can be argued that Askren’s objection to rematching Lawler is because he does not have youth on his side. A title shot did not seem far off for Askren upon his arrival and it would appear a necessity for Askren to get his shot quickly in order to defend and secure his legacy, rather than risk his undefeated record in a rematch that may not better his chances of a title shot. Furthermore, given that Askren talks such a strong game, to almost be denied victory in such an ignominious fashion would potentially spell trouble for Askren, as to falter in such a talent stacked division can severely inhibit a fighter of Askren’s age’s chances of getting back to the top of the division. However, given that Askren is considered a big draw for any fighter at welterweight and the promotion as a whole, it was inevitable he would be given multiple opportunities to prove himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his victory over Lawler, Askren expressed his interest in the winner of Jorge Masvidal and Darren Till at UFC Fight Night London. Till had long made his desire to fight Askren clear, with the two going back and forth on social media. However, the upset of Masvidal viciously knocking Till out cold paved the way for one of, if not the greatest knockout in UFC history at UFC 239 in Las Vegas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an interview on The Joe Rogan Experience Podcast, Masvidal made it evident that his dislike of Askren was personal, detailing how he wanted to ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GQ5075ZFilo&quot;&gt;break his face&lt;/a&gt;’ due to the corny and irritating style in which Askren promotes his fights. When we consider the legitimacy of these threats from Masvidal, it would be easy to see this as just business promotion. In addition, it appeared as if Askren had successfully got under Masvidal’s skin and was apparently living inside his head free of rent. I initially thought Masvidal’s anger would get the better of him in the fight but how wrong I proved to be. Masvidal got his start as a street fighter during the Kimbo Slice days and rapidly shot to notoriety. The ferocity of this form of MMA would force Masvidal to channel his anger into his performances, keeping his composure in the build-up but having the ability to become one of the most formidable fighters to enter the octagon in modern times. During the build-up to the fight Askren appeared relaxed, cracking jokes and frequently questioning Masvidal’s anger, to which I thought Masvidal had no response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masvidal shocked the world on July 6th by knocking Askren out in 5 seconds via a flying knee, silencing his doubters and leaving viewers speechless. To knock out the undefeated Askren in such spectacular fashion makes Masvidal the hottest item in the welterweight division right now, with the hype building around him attracting more and more fans to his camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where does Askren go from here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a 19-0 former champion, to the victim of the fastest KO in history with a 1-1 record in the UFC (with a highly controversial victory), his career has really begun to be questioned by critics and fans alike. Whilst the loss to Masvidal has derailed his title hopes for now, it has also called into question the legitimacy of his fighting abilities, which appear to have been overstated by MMA fans due to his undefeated record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it should not be forgotten that Askren was undefeated for a reason; he still remains a highly regarded fighter and to re-enter the octagon in the premier promotion after a year out of the sport takes a lot of bravery, so hats off to Askren. Fans far and wide believe that this loss will serve as a learning curve for Askren which he will certainly benefit from. Despite this, Askren will still run his mouth as much as he did in the build-up to UFC 239, as he is a smart fighter who understands the necessity of self-promotion, similar to the style of promotion from the likes of Chael Sonnen and Conor McGregor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it is clear that Askren himself believes he can bounce back from this, it is difficult to predict what will happen in such a stacked weight class that contains some of the deadliest strikers in the entire organisation. It is clear that Askren needs a bounce back victory, and with rumours of a fight with Darren Till circulating, I am beginning to question the motivations of the UFC as an organisation, however this is a discussion for another time. Although Till has legitimate one punch knockout power which he has shown in his fights with the likes of Cowboy Cerrone, he has shown a deficiency on the ground which will play into Askren’s hands. Till’s shortcomings on the ground were particularly visible when he fought Tyron Woodley and was submitted via a D’arce choke. As Askren and Woodley are training partners it will be advantageous to Askren to learn from Woodley’s fight with Till and discover the flaws in the British fighter’s game in order to better his chances of a victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst this represents an opportunity for Askren to finally showcase his abilities, it does hold a greater risk than, for example, a match up with a journeyman such as Neil Magny or another lower ranked opponent. News has surfaced over the past couple of days of a match-up between Askren and veteran grappler Demian Maia. Maia has long been regarded as one of the most dangerous grapplers and submission experts in the organisation, so this is a highly desirable match-up. Not only does it allow Askren to prove himself against a highly regarded opponent and put his name back into contention, but it also has the potential to showcase Askren being outclassed at his preferred fighting style. It would certainly be intriguing to see Askren take on another high-level grappler in what is a make-or-break fight for the welterweight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the adversity he has faced, Ben Askren does have a future in the UFC. Whilst it would not be strange for a hype train as large as Askren’s to be derailed, due to the calibre of the competition at welterweight, it would be a shame considering the talent Askren showed in other organisations. Whilst Askren is at risk of fading into the periphery, he remains a big draw for a lot of fighters, so we can only hope that his UFC career picks up from here and he has the chance to showcase his abilities as he has done in One Championship and Bellator.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For many, the news of a deal between One Championship and the UFC to bring one of the hottest welterweight names in MMA in the form of Ben Askren to Dana White’s organisation set pulses racing. The previously undefeated Askren had become widely regarded as one of the welterweight GOATs, amassing an undefeated 18-0 record during his time in both Bellator and One Championship before his move to the UFC. Whilst throughout his career Askren’s stand-up game had been called into question, his incessant grappling and collegiate wrestling background allowed him to dominate almost all of his opponents including big names such as Douglas Lima and Shinya Aoki.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime</title>
      <link href="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime" />
      <published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime">&lt;p&gt;When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When determining what is preventing Arsenal from progressing as a club, it is now clear that there can no longer be a single scapegoat and accountability must be shared across different departments of the club. Wenger had an almost autocratic reign for 2 decades and it was going to take more than 1 man to replace him. Have Arsenal hired the right men?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural place to start is with Wenger’s direct successor, Unai Emery. When Arsenal announced the appointment of the Spaniard, the press release described his role as ‘head coach’, perhaps indicating that he wouldn’t have the same influence on matters such as transfers as his predecessor did and his role would be more focused towards on-pitch matters. From a results point of view, Emery improved Arsenal’s points total and league position by 7 points and 1 place respectively, although it wasn’t hard to improve on a season in which Arsenal lost a staggering 11 away league games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 2 difficult games to open the season, Arsenal had a strong first few months in terms of results, although the performances weren’t on par and stars Aaron Ramsey and Mesut Özil were noticeably less influential than they were during the Wenger years. As of yet, Emery has failed to maximise Özil’s ability. Since he moved to north London in 2013, the German world champion has regularly topped the stats for assists and chances created as he operated as the fulcrum of Wenger’s side, however there was a sharp decline in his output last season. Whilst Özil himself must shoulder most of the blame, he was sometimes bypassed by Emery’s system which saw a more direct way of chance creation. This was often through long passes to Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang and Alexandre Lacazette up front or through Bosnian wing-back Sead Kolašinac getting in behind the back-line, though his end product was often found wanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the reliance on Kolašinac as an attacking outlet caused problems at the back as Arsenal’s left side of the defence was often left exposed by his attacking charges. This contributed to a season where Arsenal conceded just as many league goals as they had the season prior, ending up with a worse defensive record than the likes of Newcastle and Everton despite Emery’s reputation as a pragmatic, defensive minded coach. After years of attractive attacking football under Wenger, it did seem as though a lot of the Arsenal fanbase were more than prepared to trade that off for a more conservative style if it yielded better results. Diego Simeone and Massimiliano Allegri were often (optimistically) touted as possible Wenger replacements, both men having league titles from the top 5 European leagues and multiple Champions League finals under their belts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was Unai Emery who eventually filled Wenger’s boots. The Spaniard came with a reputation as a Europa League specialist and as impressive as his 3 successive tournament victories with Sevilla were, they themselves are a sign of what an uninspiring appointment he was. Sevilla only had the chance to participate in the Europa League by virtue of not being good enough to get into the last 16 of the Champions League. Emery’s Sevilla won the Europa League in 2014 but finished 5th in La Liga, missing out on Champions League qualification and allowing them to win the Europa League the following year. That 2015 triumph guaranteed them qualification for the following season’s Champions League due to a new rule whereby the Europa League winners automatically qualified for Europe’s premier club competition the next season. However, Sevilla could only scrape 3rd in Group D, dropping down back into the EL and winning the competition again, beating Liverpool in the final. Emery was firmly established as a quality second tier manager, cemented further by a mediocre spell with a star-studded Paris Saint Germain team, making him a questionable choice. He was a known quantity; he wouldn’t be a disaster, but neither would he get more out of the squad than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a transfer policy that doesn’t seem to be prioritising youth, the club have signed experienced players such as Aubameyang, Sokratis, Henrikh Mkhitaryan and Stefan Lichsteiner in recent years. Arsenal are currently stagnating with little sign of improvement unless drastic changes are made. Having said all of that, the outlook on Arsenal as a whole would be vastly different if the club had managed to secure a top 4 place over a heavily criticised Maurizio Sarri-led Chelsea or Tottenham, who were distracted by their European run but still managed to stumble over the finishing line. In the end, Arsenal finished just 1 point behind Chelsea and 2 behind Tottenham. Arsenal’s failure to win any of their 4 games against Brighton, Leicester, Wolves and Crystal Palace in the final run-in proved to be the sticking point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seemingly prioritised the Europa League, Emery’s chance at salvaging the season went up in smoke as he was outclassed by Sarri and Chelsea in a humiliating defeat to the London rivals in Baku. With Unai Emery at the helm Arsenal are seemingly treading water and for that reason serious questions have to be asked about whether he is the man to take the club forward or whether a change is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of Emery’s faults, the majority of the blame has to lie within the higher echelons of the club. If we rewind a year (give or take), back to when it was announced Arsène Wenger’s tenure in north London would be coming to an end, Chief Executive Ivan Gazidis and Head of Recruitment Sven Mislintat were primed to be the figureheads of Arsenal’s rebuilding process. Gazidis made himself vocal around this time and spearheaded the search for a new manager, reportedly considering former Arsenal captain Mikel Arteta before settling on Emery. However, he departed for A.C Milan in September 2018, a puzzling decision that was soon followed by Mislintat leaving after barely 12 months in his role, having recruited the likes of Aubameyang, Matteo Guendouzi, Lucas Torreira and Bernd Leno.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal felt Gazidis was so influential that he couldn’t be replaced by one man, thus Vinai Venkatesham and Raul Sanllehi were brought in. The pair featured in a lengthy interview conducted on Arsenal’s social media platforms, a PR exercise in which they looked to assert their positions as the key directors at the club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mislintat, meanwhile, has been replaced by former Arsenal midfielder, Edu. The invincible left his role as general coordinator of the Brazilian national team following their Copa America triumph, being brought in as Arsenal’s first ever technical director with less than a month of the transfer window left. Arsenal’s window, so far, has been disappointing; pursuits of the likes of Kieran Tierney, William Saliba and Wilfried Zaha have been unsuccessful as of now. Once news broke that Arsenal reportedly had a transfer budget of just £45 million, expectations were lowered. With the season fast approaching, Edu will have to quickly re-accustom himself to his old surroundings and set off bargain hunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal owner Stan Kroenke has been extensively criticised for his frugality which, along with Arsenal’s high wage bill and their inability to maximise their assets, has led to this paltry budget. In recent years, the club has let key players such as Mesut Özil, Alexis Sanchez, Aaron Ramsey, Danny Welbeck, Jack Wilshere and Santi Cazorla run their contracts down to the final 6 months, with the latter four having left for free meaning Arsenal did not receive any money to help with finding replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite those inconveniences, the most crippling examples of poor asset management came with Arsenal’s 2 star players as they swapped Alexis Sanchez for (then 29 year old) Manchester United flop Henrikh Mkhitaryan in an attempt to extract some kind of value for the Chilean, reportedly giving Mkhitaryan a 4 year, £180,000 a week contract. Meanwhile, Arsenal retained the services of Özil for the small price of £350,000 a week over 4 years, with the club desperately trying to dump him just 18 months later. Furthermore, with big contract extensions reportedly being lined up for 30-year old Aubameyang and 28-year-old Lacazette, the club must decide whether they want to risk a situation where they again overpay players as they exit their prime. Conversely, the alternative could be to have a repeat of the Sanchez and Ramsey situations if they choose to let the attackers run down the remainder of their contracts, which expire in 2021 and 2022 respectively. It is a somewhat unenviable position for Arsenal management to be in as it must also be considered that any decision to sell either of these two fan favourites will be widely lambasted by the Arsenal faithful, not to mention the impact selling a star player would have on the team’s success. Signings such as 18-year-old forward Gabriel Martinelli represent the player profile that Arsenal should be targeting; young players with potential to improve and be sold for profit. This was the approach Arsenal took following their move to the Emirates Stadium when funds were restricted. Players such as Cesc Fabregas, Emmanuel Adebayor, Robin Van Persie and Alex Song put in years of good service before recouping high transfer fees. Arsenal are currently not in a position to contend for the Premier League or Champions League but could be in 5-8 years if they are patient and have a long-term plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a club has undergone such drastic change in such a short period of time, it is important that it has a clear vision about how to achieve its goals. When a club’s Chief Executive and Head of Recruitment leave in the same season, it makes said club look like an aimless mess. Arsenal’s transfer plans look to be uncreative to say the least. When former Borussia Dortmund scout Sven Mislintat was at the club, Arsenal signed 3 former players that he knew from his time at the German club in Aubameyang, Mkhitaryan and Sokratis. Interestingly, despite this, he was reportedly ‘dismayed’ when Unai Emery requested the signing of one of his former players, Denis Suarez, with the German leaving shortly after. There seems to be a worrying pattern here with several former Emery players such as Ever Banega, Christopher Nkunku and Thomas Meunier also being linked with a move to the Emirates. Furthermore, widely reported targets Kieran Tierney and Wilfried Zaha come with a premium added to their price due to their home grown statuses which isn’t optimal for a club with limited funds. The future looks bleak and will continue to look so until the club commits to a full scale rebuild where they prioritise the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal should be hiring a young manager that has a clear footballing philosophy with the potential to win major honours; Julian Nagelsmann and Mikel Arteta are possible options. The club must come to terms with the fact that the current squad is not close to being good enough to challenge for the league title and youngsters like Reiss Nelson, Hector Bellerin, Ainsley Maitland-Niles, Alex Iwobi, Guendouzi and Torreira should be considered the key to future success, along with any signings that have potential to grow into quality players. This is likely to be a slow process, but, due to the mess the club has gotten itself into, it is a necessary one.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up</title>
      <link href="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up" />
      <published>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up">&lt;p&gt;Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 237&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated UFC 237 saw a Brazilian takeover in the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, with the Fight of the Night being awarded to the epic war between then Strawweight Champion Rose Namajunas and ‘Bate Estaca’ (Pile Driver) Jessica Andrade, who demonstrated her superb strength with a vicious slam knockout to claim the Strawweight belt much to the delight of the Brazilian fans, who all together had enjoyed a torrid evening full of disappointment, with Andrade being one of only four Brazilians to taste victory on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil has always been notorious for showcasing undoubtedly the most hostile fans in MMA. Their unwelcoming spirit to any competitor from outside Brazil was exemplified best in Jared Cannonier’s victory over Anderson Silva in the frustrating co-main event. A leg kick from Cannonier to the knee of Silva ended the fight in unfortunate fashion in the first round, much to the displeasure of the Brazilian fans, who proceeded to boo Cannonier throughout his post-fight interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the match-up between Australia’s Alexander ‘The Great’ Volkanovski and the hometown hero José Aldo did not disappoint. With the crowd expecting the -145 betting favourite José Aldo to pull off a victory that would put him back in title contention, Volkanovski came into the cage relaxed and confident. ‘The Great’ Volkanovski quickly demonstrated why he is considered the Number 1 contender, dominating Aldo for all three rounds with leg kicks and strikes, earning himself a unanimous decision victory, extending his fight win streak to sixteen, and his record in MMA to 19-1-0. This leaves Volkanovski waiting to face the winner of Max Holloway versus Frankie Edgar at UFC 240, whilst José Aldo drops down the rankings to Number 3 in the division, potentially opening up a window for a fight with Number 2 ranked Brian Ortega.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event of UFC 237 saw ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas take on Jessica ‘Bate Estaca’ Andrade in a title showdown for the Women’s Strawweight Title. With Namajunas returning to the Octagon for the first time in over a year after recovering from neck surgery, many expected her not to perform to the same level as her incredible two previous victories over former Strawweight champion Joanna Jedrzejczyk. However, it appeared that Rose was as sharp as ever in the first round, completely out-striking and dominating Andrade for the first five minutes. An attempted but unsuccessful arm-bar submission from Namajunas exemplified the narrative of the first round, with the victory appearing to be merely a formality and an inevitability for the American. Nevertheless, with the backing of her hometown fans, Andrade showed her endurance and determination coming out in the second round pressing Namajunas up to the fence and working for the clinch in order to utilise her far superior strength. Once Andrade secured the clinch, she was able to perform a High Crotch Slam, living up to her nickname ‘Pile Driver’, dumping Namajunas onto the canvas and gaining the KO victory. Andrade’s knockout of Namajunas was only the fourth ever slam KO performed in a UFC title fight, and the first slam KO since Matt Hughes defeated Carlos Newton at UFC 34 in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fight, Namajunas cast doubt over her future in the organisation, hinting at a potential retirement due to the strain it was placing on her life and relationship with husband and coach Pat Barry. All MMA fans hope that this won’t be the end of ‘Thug’ Rose’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Andrade, she will now wait to see whether a rematch with Namajunas is the next step or whether she will face the likes of undefeated contender Tatiana Suarez, who holds massive potential and has been likened to current Men’s Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov due to her superior wrestling ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 238&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prelims saw wins for rising stars such as Tatiana Suarez, Aljamain Sterling and Calvin Kattar. Sterling, who is currently ranked third in the bantamweight division, defeated Pedro Munhoz via unanimous decision, with Munhoz riding high after his KO win over former champion Cody Garbrandt. Sterling controlled the fight with ease, utilising his striking and unique style to win the fight 30-27 on all score cards. This should set Sterling up for a shot at the title, unless Moraes is granted a rematch with Cejudo, in which case it is likely Sterling will face Number 2 ranked Raphael Assuncao.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calvin Kattar showcased exactly why MMA fans are so excited about him with a beautiful first round knockout of Ricardo Lamas. A clean lead left hook followed by a precise and brutal straight right hand ended the fight and catapulted Kattar within touching distance of the top ten of the division. There is certainly a lot on the horizon for the 31 year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tatiana Suarez displayed her talent despite a late rally from opponent Nina Ansaroff to earn a unanimous decision victory and set herself up for a potential title shot against champion Jessica Andrade. Suarez showed persistence and perseverance to secure a takedown early in the first, and proceeded to demonstrate superb top control during the 15 minutes to secure the victory, despite Ansaroff showing great heart in the third round with a great striking game on the feet, winning her the round albeit in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main card began with a heavyweight slugfest between Australia’s Tai Tuivasa and Bulgaria’s Blagoy Ivanov. Ivanov took the fight via unanimous decision. The Bulgarian dropped ‘Bam Bam’ Tuivasa in the first with a fantastic combination and would have won the fight via guillotine choke in the second had the bell not sounded. Despite huge shots from ‘Bam Bam’ threatening throughout the third round, Ivanov saw off Tuivasa to earn the victory with a confident performance that could see him potentially enter the top ten in the Heavyweight division.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petr Yan continued to show why he should be taken seriously at Bantamweight as he defeated Jimmie Rivera, dropping him twice, once in the first and then again in the second round. Rivera rallied to muster the performance he needed in the third round, however the knockdowns gifted Yan two 10-8 rounds, so only a stoppage would have given Rivera the victory. Despite landing shots on Yan in the final round, it was ineffectual as Yan claimed the unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aptly titled People’s Main Event saw two savages in Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson and Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone go to war at Lightweight. The opening round saw the two men stand and trade shots in the centre of the octagon, with Ferguson edging the round by outlanding Cowboy with significant strikes to the head and body. Ferguson’s endurance and pressure fighting style began to pay dividends in the second round, with Cerrone appearing to be slowly broken down by the accuracy of Ferguson’s punches and kicks. The end of the fight came shortly after the bell to end round 2, after Ferguson landed a late blow on Cowboy. Cerrone’s right eye was swollen shut. In an effort to clear the swelling he blew his nose, however, this only worsened the swelling and caused the doctor to call off the fight, awarding Ferguson the TKO victory. Whilst the fight did not end the way many had wished, it was in my opinion a correct decision for the bout to be ended despite protests from Cerrone. Ferguson was visibly upset by the way the fight ended, evidently disappointed in himself for landing the late strike. However, in his post-fight interview with Joe Rogan, Cerrone insisted that his injury was not a result of the strike. An anticlimactic ending but without a doubt one of the most entertaining fights of the night. ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson proved that he deserves a shot against the Lightweight champion Khabib Nurmagomedov by defeating Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone to confirm his position as the man to take on the winner of Khabib versus Dustin Poirier at UFC 242.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The co-main and main event did not hold such disappointment. Here we saw Valentina ‘Bullet’ Shevchenko cement her status as one of the most terrifying female competitors in MMA after defending her Flyweight title in style. Number 1 contender Jessica ‘Evil’ Eye was Shevchenko’s opponent in the Kyrgyzstani’s first defence of the title. Shevchenko showed exactly why she is one of the most devastating and feared fighters in women’s MMA, finishing the fight with a right head-kick that left Eye unconscious and twitching on the canvas for several minutes. In my opinion, Shevchenko has truly reached her peak, and produced one of the scariest KO’s in all of MMA history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Cejudo has arguably experienced the most meteoric rise in success in recent times. This success was furthered by his performance in the main event of UFC 238 at the United Centre in Chicago against Marlon Moraes. Cejudo looked to make history by becoming the first fighter to win an Olympic gold medal and be a 2 division UFC champion. In his way was Brazilian Marlon Moraes, who had been on a 4 fight win streak, finishing the likes of Jimmie Rivera and Raphael Assuncao prior to his title shot. With the vacant bantamweight title up for grabs, both men were plenty fired up in the build up, trading trash talk since the bout was announced. Having beaten TJ Dillashaw in his last fight, Cejudo leapt at the opportunity to become Champ Champ once Dillashaw vacated the title due to him testing positive for EPO in his fight with Cejudo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round saw Moraes take the early initiative, peppering Cejudo with hard leg kicks and strikes, easily winning the round. Moraes was on track to make the fight a one-sided contest, however Cejudo had other plans. ‘The Messenger’ came out in round 2 throwing hard right hands that effectively halted Moraes’ progress and Cejudo was also able to land some hard knees in the clinch, awarding him the second round. The third round showed just how determined and driven Cejudo was to become a double champion. Gaining top position on the ground, Cejudo landed devastating elbows and hammer fists on the visibly broken Moraes, which led to the referee stepping in and ending the fight as Cejudo became the 4th UFC fighter to hold belts in multiple divisions, following in the footsteps of the likes of Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Amanda Nunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This victory undoubtedly puts Cejudo in the conversation for the pound for pound best fighter at this moment in time. Certainly, the likes of Jon Jones and Khabib Nurmagomedov cannot be discounted due to the number of title defences from Jones and Khabib’s phenomenal 27-0 record. However, as Cejudo is the only athlete to have an Olympic gold medal on his resume, he has to, in my opinion, be included within the top 3 or at least the top 5 pound for pound greats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up on the calendar is perhaps the most anticipated card of the year. On July 6th in Las Vegas, UFC 239 sees Jon Jones look to defend his Light Heavyweight title against Thiago Santos, on a card that contains the likes of Amanda Nunes, Ben Askren, Jorge Masvidal, Luke Rockhold and many more. This card promises to be explosive and I believe it will be one of the best events of 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up</title>
      <link href="/CL-QF" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up" />
      <published>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-QF</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-QF">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City were narrowly defeated against a defiant Tottenham side in an enthralling Champions League quarter-final match that will live long in the memory of the competition’s illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first leg finished 1-0 to Spurs after Heung-Min Son’s late strike gave the home side the advantage heading into the second leg at the Etihad stadium; some will argue that the South Korean’s sole goal should have been saved by Ederson as it was close to his body but the sheer power off Son’s left boot managed to dumbfound the Brazilian goalkeeper. Perhaps the biggest turning point of the tie was Lloris’ early penalty save from Aguero, as from then on City’s opportunities were limited by a formidable Spurs defence who were successfully able to deny the Citizens from scoring a vital away goal. The first leg of the tie was a highly entertaining clash between two sides at the peak of their powers, but nobody expected the second leg to be as engrossing as it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Citizens needed to win by more than one goal at their home stadium to ensure going through to the semi-finals and despite the first leg defeat, City were still favourites to proceed to the next round, largely based on their impressive domestic successes and superior squad. Therefore, when Raheem Sterling scored in the 4th minute of the second leg to equal the aggregate score, many thought it would be a routine win for City, but these postulations were withdrawn after Heung-Min Son scored twice in quick succession to give Spurs the advantage. Astonishingly, Bernardo Silva’s deflected shot made it 2-2 within 11 minutes, and City, via Raheem Sterling again, added another before the interval to make it 3-2 on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expectedly, City began the second half putting immense pressure on the away side and their efforts eventually came to fruition after Sergio Aguero’s powerful near-post finish put City 4-2 up on 59 minutes. Spurs replied through Fernando Llorente, who became the unexpected hero after the ball bounced off his body into the net from a corner kick. In the end, the mesmerising game finished 4-3 to the Premier League champions, but it wasn’t enough as Spurs went through on away goals. The final few minutes of the tie saw Raheem Sterling score only for it to be ruled out for offside after VAR was consulted and City celebrations had already taken place in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After losing their talisman, Harry Kane, through a recurrent ankle injury in the first leg, few people expected Tottenham to beat Pep Guardiola’s prestigious team but Heung-Min Son stepped up to the plate in Kane’s absence, as he has numerous times this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result brings into question whether Pochettino is the better overall manager than Pep. Their rivalry stems from their time in Spain, as Espanyol and Barcelona managers respectively. Although Pep’s achievements in the game are unrivalled and has the superior record over the Argentine, Pochettino has had the lesser squad and defeated Pep in a quarter final despite not having made a signing since January 2018 and missing key players such as Harry Kane and Harry Winks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Messi shines again as Barcelona are into the semi-finals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona were 4-0 aggregate winners against a hopeless Manchester United side as the Catalan giants made light work of the Red Devils. After a 1-0 first leg defeat in which the Mancunians failed to provide any serious threat, United were made to pay for costly mistakes in the second leg as Leo Messi capitalised twice to give Barcelona a 3-0 aggregate advantage within 20 minutes of the second leg, all but ending the tie and sending Barcelona through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result marks Manchester United’s largest ever aggregate defeat in a two-legged European tie, while Barcelona will go on to face Liverpool in the last four of the competition, who will surely provide a sterner test than their English counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, it has become clear that Manchester United’s initial upsurge in form after Ole Gunnar Solskjaer’s appointment in December was only a short term reaction to the mood being lifted around the club. Since the unlikely comeback at the Parc des Princes in the competition’s round of sixteen stage, United have lost 6 of their last 8 matches in all competitions. The two games they did win (2-1 victories vs Watford and West Ham respectively) were unmerited by way of being the lesser side on both occasions. It still remains to be seen whether Solskjaer has the tactical know-how to match the enormity of the task being asked of him, which begs the question: why were United so hasty to appoint him as permanent manager, and why did they offer a three year contract, rather than a one-year rolling contract?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astounding Ajax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in Turin, Juventus were humbled by defeat against Dutch champions Ajax in a game in which the Italian heavyweights were strong favourites. Ajax stunned football fans with their accomplished displays against Real Madrid in the last round, and they continued to silence doubters by producing another set of proficient performances against Juventus. Ajax played Juventus off the park in both legs of the tie and if there is a stat that exemplifies the Dutch team’s dominance it is that Ajax scored three goals over the two legs, while Juventus only managed a measly three shots on target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ajax’s 3-2 aggregate win does not begin to tell the story of just how commanding they were over the Italian champions. However, if there can be any criticism pointed towards Ajax, it is that they are often wasteful in front of goal despite creating numerous chances. This may be partly due to not playing a recognised striker, as their front three is a combination of attacking midfielders and wingers, who are typically more involved in the build-up of goals rather than the finishing of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juventus were wholly uninspiring and lacklustre for a team that was tipped as a potential winner of the competition and Max Allegri’s job has now been called into question as reputable Italian newspapers report that his time at the club could be up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liverpool ease past Porto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porto were thumped 6-1 on aggregate by Liverpool as the Scousers comfortably swept aside the Portuguese champions to go on to the semi-finals. In truth, the scoreline does not truly reflect the nature of the game, in which Liverpool were made to defend for large parts to hang onto their lead. However, the result does reassert Liverpool’s defensive solidity and attacking prowess; the team is exceptional at both ends of the pitch. Liverpool defeated Porto by the same margin last season in the 16 round of the competition on their way to reaching the final and they will hope to do the same this year, although their next opponents will be Barcelona in a mouth-watering tie that promises to captivate audiences across the world as two European heavyweights go head-to-head for a place in this year’s final in Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jurgen Klopp has not yet lost a two-legged European tie during his stint at Liverpool and his side are now faced with a tough task of keeping this record intact against a Barcelona side who have only lost three games in all competitions this season. Luis Suarez and Philippé Coutinho will return to meet their former employers for the first time since leaving Anfield, which will host the second leg of the tie on 7th May at 20:00 BST.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament</title>
      <link href="/March-Madness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament" />
      <published>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/March-Madness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/March-Madness">&lt;p&gt;The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past season the Duke Blue Devils were on center stage due to their three phenomenal freshmen: Zion Williamson, RJ Barrett, and Cam Reddish; all three are projected to be drafted among the top ten players this upcoming June. When the ACC tournament was played, all media attention was put on Duke basketball and Zion Williamson, and the  Duke Blue Devils were heavily favored coming into the NCAA tournament as the number one overall seed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Zion Williamson and company were in the spotlight for the first and second rounds, a few breakout stars carried their teams and shocked the world. Ja Morant, a sophomore guard from Murray State, is now being regarded as the second best player in the upcoming draft, right behind Williamson. Morant opened up round one with a victory over Marquette with an impressive triple-double where he had 16 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the regular college season, the only programs that receive coverage from the media are the universities with large national followings such as Duke and Kentucky. However, the upside of  The March Madness tournament is that it allows for athletes at smaller Division 1 schools to make an impact. A good example of this is Warriors point guard Steph Curry, who was severely under recruited due to his small size. The eventual three-time NBA champion’s introduction to the national media happened back in 2008 when he scored 40 points and led the Davidson Wildcats in upsetting the number 7 seed, Gonzaga. Curry ended up leading his team to the elite eight where they were knocked out by number 1 seed Kansas. As a result, Curry was later drafted in 2009 by the Golden State Warriors as the 7th overall pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides such a large platform for college players to make their mark and be noticed, and the benefits can be enormous. Kemba Walker, for example, was not a highly regarded point guard when he led his UConn Huskies to the National Championship in 2011. Walker and the Huskies entered as a 3 seed where they ultimately beat Butler and claimed their third national championship. During their championship run, Walker played sensationally and was awarded the tournament’s Most Outstanding Player Award. Walker was later drafted 9th overall by the Charlotte Hornets and has been on three all-star teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides opportunities for players in smaller programs to showcase their talent on a national level. The media will always follow the athletes and programs that dominate in the regular season, and this is why March Madness is so special. Players like Steph Curry, Kemba Walker, and Ja Morant all have a place in NCAA history where their names were made.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Is Hollywood the Perfect Fit for Superstar Bryce Harper?</title>
      <link href="/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Hollywood the Perfect Fit for Superstar Bryce Harper?" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper">&lt;p&gt;The end of baseball season is the time when all diehard fans settle on watching football for a few months. A long 152 days until baseball rolls back around. But that time in the offseason is one of the most important for a franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offseason is when general managers, scouts, and other team personnel come together to talk about the future of their organization. Trades and new contracts are the most important part of the offseason for a general manager. And with every MLB team having one or more superstars, it has been a wild offseason for trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest buzz that has been circling around MLB is where Bryce Harper is going to be cleating up to start the 2019 season. As one of the star names in professional baseball, and arguably the biggest free agent this offseason, everyone is hoping that their general manager is keeping an eye out for the 26-year-old phenom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Can the Dodgers make the best case for Harper?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harper, who is now a free agent after an 8-year contract with the Washington Nationals, is looking for a new city to call home. Being a 7-time All-Star with only 8 seasons under his belt makes it obvious that he will have an immediate impact on any team that he joins. Many teams in the MLB are making trades and moves to adjust their lineup for someone like Harper, but none have made a splash like the Los Angeles Dodgers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With back to back World Series appearances, the Dodgers have been making their mark on the MLB in recent years. But in mid-December, the Dodgers traded two powerhouse outfields to the Cincinnati Reds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3-time All-Star, 2-time Gold Glover, and 2-time Silver Slugger, Matt Kemp is a known face for Los Angeles. He played his first 9 seasons with the Dodgers and made it to the All-Star Game last season with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yasiel Puig is another big name for Los Angeles as he has geared up for the Dodgers in all 6 of his professional seasons. In that time he has had an All-Star selection and was runner up for the Rookie of the Year award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Puig and Kemp are outfielders, so it is obvious that the Dodgers’ staff  are trying to open the outfield up. Whether they are doing so for Harper or not is not clear yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dodgers are desperately looking for an opportunity to get that World Series Ring in October, and maybe Harper is the man they need leading the charge.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sam Tanberg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="test" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="baseball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The end of baseball season is the time when all diehard fans settle on watching football for a few months. A long 152 days until baseball rolls back around. But that time in the offseason is one of the most important for a franchise.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
