<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/saachi.ghosh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-10T07:01:29+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/saachi.ghosh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Japan’s Political Paradigm</title>
      <link href="/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Japan’s Political Paradigm" />
      <published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm">&lt;p&gt;Shinzo Abe announced that he was resigning from his post on August 28, 2020. He stated that he was doing so in light of extreme health issues, and apologised to the people of Japan for failing to complete his term in the office and for leaving the nation in a period of political uncertainty. At the age of 65 years, Abe suffers from a chronic condition called ‘ulcerative colitis’, which he was diagnosed with when he was a teenager. It is an inflammatory bowel disease that has accentuated recently, prompting him to take this drastic precaution for his health. He had resigned even earlier in 2007 due to this condition. After this, his new period in the office started in 2012, and he has been loved by his people ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Abenomics’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A member of the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP), his reputation is that of a strong nationalist and conservative. His right tilted political front with the Liberal Democratic Party has boosted its popularity. Abe has led it in both the houses of Japanese Parliament. He has developed a stronghold in economic policy on a self-named programme known as ‘Abenomics’, which he introduced in 2012. An output plan to jumpstart Japan’s economy, it has been focussed on the stagnant growth of monetary policy, fiscal stimulus and structural reforms. The success of Abenomics has resulted in a double-edged sword with him aggressively focusing on the first two promises, yet sorely lacking in structural reform. Although his win in the consecutive elections has not been entirely because of this policy, it has played a crucial role. Mr Shinzo Abe has mostly been lauded for his representation as a modicum of stability in Japanese political history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abe’s Political Bandwidth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing a rare close personal relationship with Trump, demands erupted for him to pay more to support around 55,000 American troops on bases across the country. He has maintained a coalition of 11 countries around the Pacific Rim in a trade agreement called the Trans-Pacific Partnership. He had a firmer stance on North Korea in his foreign policy plans. In 2014, he developed Japan’s relationship with the Association of South-East Asian Nations and Australia. He became the first Japanese Prime Minister to attend India’s Republic Day parade as a Chief Guest. He had also maintained good relations with Xi Jinping, the supreme leader of China, before the pandemic and the Hong Kong protests. As stated by an Assistant Professor of Asian Studies at the University of Hawaii at Manoa, “&lt;em&gt;He managed to really elevate Japan’s profile on the international stage and make substantial changes in policy across a number of issue areas, and in Japan that is something we have not seen very often&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But right before his resignation, analysts have noticed that the majority were discontented with Abe. The way he handled the coronavirus outbreak in Japan, and in particular its effects on the economy, undid the fame of what Abenomics achieved. A holistic assessment of his tenure has revealed that he prioritised stability over high-handed risks of huge transformations, which is what helped him rise to power and assured him an important position in Japanese history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yoshihide Suga&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Yoshihide Suga has a central role as the Chief Cabinet Secretary in the current administration. The LDP announced on September 14, 2020, that he will be the direct successor of Shinzo Abe as Prime Minister of Japan. This comes as a surprising announcement because there are many leading Japanese lawmakers who are direct descendants of elite political families, but Mr Suga isn’t one of them. Part of his charisma is that he has worked his way up from his middle-class upbringing to such a position. He held his position alongside Shinzo Abe for a long time, signifying his role in continuing Abe’s legacy. Years of gaining shadow power will result in his abilities to handle the top position, as his victory in the LDP has illuminated his formidable political skills. However, there have been glimpses of his politics that have concerned some critics. He is said to have been behind some of Abe’s most authoritative decisions, including consolidating power over Japan’s bureaucracy, and tactics to silence criticism in the media. But despite apprehension from certain voices, more than half the nation supports his takeover as the subsequent Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he has already epitomised a status quo, Mr Suga has been a major catalyst for national change. He has pushed through some contentious security laws that have allowed for Japan’s military power to join overseas combat missions alongside its allies. His vision for Japan will muster fresh outlooks on the country’s deepest problems and challenges. He has proclaimed to pursue some of Abe’s cherished goals that he couldn’t complete. This includes the completion of a revision of Japan’s pacifist Constitution and a promise for the return of Japanese citizens that North Korea had kidnapped. With the global turbulence from the pandemic and the gradually increasing geopolitical threats in Asia, Japan needs a successor such as Mr Suga to run its course by re-establishing a stable political backdrop. Best described by his high school classmate Hiroshi Kawai in Mr Suga’s hometown Yuzawa City, “&lt;em&gt;We have such proverbs as ‘great talents are slow to mature’ and ‘a wise falcon hides its talons’, now I realised that those words were created for Mr Suga&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Shinzo Abe announced that he was resigning from his post on August 28, 2020. He stated that he was doing so in light of extreme health issues, and apologised to the people of Japan for failing to complete his term in the office and for leaving the nation in a period of political uncertainty. At the age of 65 years, Abe suffers from a chronic condition called ‘ulcerative colitis’, which he was diagnosed with when he was a teenager. It is an inflammatory bowel disease that has accentuated recently, prompting him to take this drastic precaution for his health. He had resigned even earlier in 2007 due to this condition. After this, his new period in the office started in 2012, and he has been loved by his people ever since.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Western Media Texts</title>
      <link href="/Western-Media-Texts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Western Media Texts" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Western-Media-Texts</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Western-Media-Texts">&lt;p&gt;The digital revolution of old media into new media has taken shape very rapidly. Old media has seldom been given its due recognition. Traditional sources of information like newspapers and radio have sustained their quality in truth telling for ages. Its comparison is unparalleled when it comes to new media, which is why it still has a wide market and is almost irreplaceable. On the other hand, new media rose to power because of its instantaneous quality to connect and communicate. News became easy to deliver as new media defined its timeliness. It has definitely changed the dynamics of public consumption of news, heralding a phase in humanity where everything can be reported, by anyone, and at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this has caused a severe decline in the ethics and philosophies of news providers. The power of creating news and gathering information is privy to distortion. Popularising preconceived notions as news is an emerging norm. This leads to misrepresentation and unfortunate consequences. The multiplicity of perspectives, opinions, and beliefs, entailing even factual wrongdoings, mixed with propaganda, has corrupted what was once considered an industry full of good samaritans. It is now a blotch on the entire concept of truth, information and news. Even traditional media faced this deterioration. The downward spiral of media credibility first footed at the advent of selling sensational news. The entire concept of ‘tabloidisation’ in garnering an audience, for the sake of business growth by corporations, led to a complete dilution in the way the public’s sensibilities allowed them to evaluate news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the media’s very history has dictated cultural behaviour throughout the course of time, it has become a core part of our lives. From newspapers to television networks to the abundance of information disseminated on social media, different types of media have both evolved and learnt to coexist. Thus, understanding the people and corporations behind these media networks, and the faces that decide news value, will further provide transparency in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Television is a writer’s playground, and online platforms only widen this space. The artistic freedom and the creative liberty that comes with it, was hitherto unheard of. So what would earlier be written for network audience traction is now developing into its own qualitative entity. All shows based on varied walks of life, using diverse plots, and being highly representative, have a loyal audience. Film and television also influence us in the most impactful ways. Therefore, the story and the way of storytelling employed is imperative to the niche audience it targets. When we talk about journalism and media, it is easy to assume how its machine functions. However, we hardly know the works behind the scenes. That is news nobody can tell us. We are oblivious to what goes into reporting a two minute segment, or a five page article. It always varies depending on the story, the source, the journalist, the editor, and the thousand inbetweeners that it takes to put a story out there. There have been innumerable assumptions around what a media workplace should be or how a journalistic practice must work, usually tied around speculation and hearsay. There’s seldom any representation within media texts portraying the media itself. Let us analyse two stand out accomplishments that tried to do it right, and well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Newsroom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Aaron Sorkin original, HBO’s &lt;em&gt;The Newsroom&lt;/em&gt; revolves around the dramatisation of a fictional news broadcast media network - Atlantis Cable Network. The name itself suggests that it is a fictional, idealistic world of the media elite. It is essentially a newsroom drama, a tale only seen panned out in movies before. Therefore, the scope for incorporating real time journalistic stories is high. And Sorkin knows how to merge that plethora of opportunity through witty dialogue and righteous ethical commentary. The plot revolves around some passionate workaholic journalists who only live by their virtues of delivering the unfiltered truth, without being bothered about the network ratings or audience commands. It is representative of what every journalist wants to be - equally intellectual and ethical - despite being held back by outside forces. The show reiterates that the value of journalistic integrity is above all else. It is a stark contrast to broadcast networks in real life, which are constantly required to entertain rather than provide information. In this day and age, ratings and viewership is highly important for a network to sustain itself. Thus, this show posits itself as an ideal of how every journalist wants to work and does not delve into a practical solution for how broadcast may allow its journalists to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The show tends to remain positive even during the darkest stories that have plagued the United States of America, by the up and coming celebration of democracy that the nation prevails to be. Its coverage of real time political events and serious stories, is not only well written but amazingly performed by the ensemble cast. While the show does not accurately portray broadcast networks in the West (and is especially inaccurate in doing that), it sure lives up to the narrative it is trying to convey - that which every network must strive to achieve. The show also satires and ridicules networks that have different ideologies and functions. Its constant snarky digs at &lt;em&gt;Thirty Mile Zone (TMZ)&lt;/em&gt; for exploitation, and &lt;em&gt;Cable News Network (CNN)&lt;/em&gt; for false reporting, is well-handled and brave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorkin’s masterful writing aids him in articulating some narratives within the media industry that need to be heard. For networks not just in the US, but even worldwide. Even if it’s not an accurate representation, the technical representation and the chaotic nuance of a newsroom workplace is on point. With some admirable takeaways from beloved performances of some truly heroic characters, the show does its job and does it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Morning Show&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Apple TV+ venture, &lt;em&gt;The Morning Show&lt;/em&gt; represents a morning broadcast media show and what the happy rosy environment actually masks. Its script originally dealt with a common plot threading various stories in between, but it ended up changing to accentuate the overarching common storyline due to its relevance. Entailing the #MeToo movement, the show focuses on the alleged sexual harassment cases that women at the media house workplace suffered at the hands of a powerful lead anchor. The anchor is fired and denies the claims. While fictionalised, this premise is taken from what happened to Matt Lauer at the &lt;em&gt;Today Show&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows the complicity of the workplace environment in perpetuating the harassment. This is representative of not just media organisations but of any working environment. Through its complex characters, and dramatic plot twists, the first season does justice in representing the consequences of such unfortunate workplace incidents. It humanises every character involved and doesn’t judge through its writing. It’s everything that is expected from a gripping drama. The story explores the nuanced details of the #MeToo movement, but leaves the audience in suspense about the actual truth until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its course, the show is riddled with characters that are dayside journalists, so the media premise is naturally different. Everything from the type of stories covered, to the positivity that it propagates, it is accurately representative of that broadcast niche. The lead anchors are shown being vain and self absorbed. But the entrance of a righteous journalist who enters this feel-good world, shakes the flow of the show. She has doubts about the kind of journalism this media group stands for. She has constant outbursts of journalistic integrity (much like she’s plucked out of the Sorkin universe), is absolutely apprehended by the overly narcissistic environment, and continually calls out the hypocrisies of the organisation. She acts as a conscience trope for journalism as a virtue. The news producer, and the owner have their own tensions and roles at the backdrop of the story. They show is well-balanced in its media representation that way and does for the media industry, what was long overdue. Gearing up for its second season, the show can further elevate or deteriorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were some of the representations of new broadcast media in the West, and of the West, that were worth analysing due to their brilliant execution. The developing countries of the East, like India, are still short of well-made media representations. Recent releases like &lt;em&gt;Paatal Lok&lt;/em&gt; have stirred this conversation in a much-needed direction, by accurately representing the dichotomies and hypocrisies of Indian journalism and media. Being a fourth pillar to democracy, we mustn’t infuriatingly bash our media sources. A way of portraying gratitude is through such media texts, and encouraging that is reinstating our belief in journalism and truth-telling.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The digital revolution of old media into new media has taken shape very rapidly. Old media has seldom been given its due recognition. Traditional sources of information like newspapers and radio have sustained their quality in truth telling for ages. Its comparison is unparalleled when it comes to new media, which is why it still has a wide market and is almost irreplaceable. On the other hand, new media rose to power because of its instantaneous quality to connect and communicate. News became easy to deliver as new media defined its timeliness. It has definitely changed the dynamics of public consumption of news, heralding a phase in humanity where everything can be reported, by anyone, and at any time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Hagia Sophia: A Tale of Heritance Indignation by Erdogan</title>
      <link href="/Hagia-Sophia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hagia Sophia: A Tale of Heritance Indignation by Erdogan" />
      <published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Hagia-Sophia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Hagia-Sophia">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of the Heritage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructed by Justinian I, the ruler of the Byzantine Empire, in 532 AD when Istanbul was still Constantinople, the Hagia Sophia (Ayasofya in Turkish) was a 65,000 square feet stone-structured church-cathedral. Throughout the course of its ruling history, the church was turned into a mosque which was then converted to a museum. Its original construction was meant to seat the Patriarch of the Eastern Orthodox Church, and it remained the same for approximately 900 years! In 1453, when the Ottoman forces of the Turk ruler Sultan Mehmet II claimed Constantinople as their land, they ransacked the cathedral that was Hagia Sophia and turned it into a mosque in no time. The monument was changed heavily, as key Orthodox features were re-interiorised, removed, even plastered upon, minarets were added to the exterior of the structure, and ornate Christian mosaics were covered with panels of religious Arabic calligraphy, giving it an essence of architectural, cultural, and of course, religious rebirth. For the longest time, it was Istanbul’s most important mosque until the Atatürk revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listed as a UNESCO (The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation) World Heritage site, a 1500-year-old structure, on the backdrop of a religiously unprecedented heritage, and a history panning not just the entirety of the Ottoman Empire but the Byzantine Empire, the Hagia Sophia has a rich story not only in its cultural sense but in a historically and religiously profound way, one that only former Turkish President Mustafa Kemal Atatürk was wise enough to have appreciated in the course of his modernisation of the nation. After the First World War, the Ottoman Sultans fell apart and Turkey was made into a secular nation by Atatürk. In the 1930’s, Atatürk shut down the mosque and created a museum out of it to preserve its culturally rich heritage, and highlight its historic significance. Interestingly, this shifted the honour of the greatest mosque in the Ummah (the Muslim community) to Masjid-al-Haram, the one in Mecca. It was now when Arab and Turkish tensions rose and gave birth to the debate relating to the state of the Hagia Sophia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erdogan’s Political Intent and Long-Term Desire for the Islamic Centralisation of Turkey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was last year when the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan claimed that turning the Hagia Sophia into a museum was a “very big mistake” and considered reverting it back to a mosque just days before the local elections were supposed to be held. Initially, when Erdogan entered politics three decades ago in Turkey, anything even remotely related to Hagia Sophia was never on his agenda. In fact, he was even reported to have opposed the reconversion of the Hagia Sophia to a mosque maybe in an attempt to seem politically correct, still an objection nonetheless. His rhetoric on the same grew the other way in 2019 when he ended up losing the municipal elections in Istanbul. It was later when the US President Donald Trump recognised Jerusalem as the capital of Israel, that Erdogan brought the same agenda up, attempting to maybe score political recognition that he had been losing since last year by supporting such a big decision, hoping to gain radical followership. And it seemed to have worked as he is currently the Turkish President, and is defending his final decision to exercise the country’s sovereign right in converting the museum back to a mosque, as the highest court annulled the site’s status as a museum. Official reports state that some Christian emblems, including mosaics of the Virgin Mary adorning its soaring golden dome, are still intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erdogan’s changes to the Hagia Sophia are majorly to gain political publicity, but this indicates his desires for the nation from a larger standpoint. This agenda is a disguised symbolic ruse to dismantle Ataturk’s secular legacy by remoulding Turkey according to his own vision. He mounds himself as a modern-day Turkish conqueror who will “save” the nation’s sovereignty, and that any outsider that condemns the same is attacking Turkey directly. This decision is also reflective of his intention to shift the Islamic centre of gravity away from Mecca to Turkey. It is a pronounced declaration to the entirety of the Ummah across nations by reclaiming the honour of reinstating what was once the greatest mosque in hopes of going back to its history. The problem with which is that its legacy has proved why the decision is not only disrespectful to the monument’s history but demeans a great leader that democratised Turkey into what it is today (or &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; before Erdogan). Although, this reclamation sits well with his bases, such as religious conservatives and Turkish nationalists, incentivising further radical support. Imposing ultranationalism and non-democratic sentiments, he is becoming an era-defining strongman and threat of caution to democratised ideals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics have argued that Erdogan is using this as a distraction from the economic damage caused in Turkey due to the COVID-19 pandemic, which is highly plausible. Unfortunately, none of the backlashes affected Erdogan’s decision and shortly after the court’s announcement, the first call to prayer at Hagia Sophia was broadcasted on all of Turkey’s main news channels, subsequently after which the cultural site’s social media handles were taken down. The first Muslim prayers were held after 86 years inside the converted building on July 24 (also the anniversary of Turkey’s established borders due to the 1923 treaty), attended by around a thousand people in the mosque and a lot more others outside with their mats. Four muezzins recited the call to prayer from each of the four minarets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Reactions to the Reconversion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UNESCO stated that it deeply regretted the decision and appealed to the Turkish authorities to “open a dialogue without delay”. It urged Turkey not to finalise anything without discussion, yet was cold-shouldered. Greece has condemned the move gravely, being home to many Eastern Orthodox Church followers. Greek archaeologist and Cultural Minister Lina Mendoni stated that the entire tactic was an “open provocation to the civilised world” and was only raising religious tensions in the region. She claimed the court ruling confirmed the absence of an independent justice system in Turkey. Turkey’s Council of State, its top administrative court, ruled on July 10 stating, &lt;em&gt;“It was concluded that the settlement deed allocated it as a mosque and its use outside this character is not possible legally. The cabinet decision in 1934 that ended its use as a mosque and defined it as a museum did not comply with laws”&lt;/em&gt;. The Russian Church, home to the world’s largest Orthodox Christian community, immediately voiced apprehensions that the Turkish court would not take its community’s concerns into account while ruling on the status of Hagia Sophia. This has led to greater divisions between the communities, as the Pope has expressed “profound sadness”. Popular Turkish author Orhan Pamuk voiced the folly of the move while describing its backward motives of assigning an asterisk on its secular identity as a state which Kemal Ataturk helped restore. &lt;em&gt;“There are millions of secular Turks like me who are crying against this but their voices are not heard”&lt;/em&gt;, he stated in an interview with BBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an adamant historical change, despite severe criticism from the international community, to a monument that must belong to humanity at large and not to Turkey exclusively considering its history. It should remain a museum for bearing the brunt of being a bridge between the two faiths, and a worldwide symbol of coexistence with pride instead of battling a long drawn religious wrath that this decision imbibes. How long will regimens such as Erdogan’s allow for secularly-grey decisions to hold pedestals, being ignorant of histories and heritages, furthering matters of religious intolerance, and torturing secular fabrics?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The History of the Heritage</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Historiographic Remembrance of Asian-African Solidarity</title>
      <link href="/Asian-African-Solidarity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Historiographic Remembrance of Asian-African Solidarity" />
      <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Asian-African-Solidarity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Asian-African-Solidarity">&lt;p&gt;Anti-racism protests breaking out across the United States post a gruesome broad-day crime resulting in George Floyd’s death gave rise to a lot of ethnic and racial communities coming together under an umbrella of solidarity to question bigger problems that should have been eradicated decades ago. Western European countries, that have a complicated history of colonial conquest, echo massively of racially discriminatory policing. Imperial colonisers have forever tried to invade what seemed opportunistically resourceful foreign lands to them, to in turn replace its original populations with their own. As surfaced by Mahmood Mamdani in a thought, known as the settler colonialism strategy, this was victorious in countries like Australia and New Zealand, although in countries like Africa this strategy was defeated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us recognise an age-old partnership, that of the Asian-African community supporting each other unconditionally, in retrospect against neo-imperialism and colonialism, united today yet again in a fight against the centuries-old institutionalised systemic racism that haunts majoritarian societies. The political palpability of solidarity in a shared understanding of racial injustice is amply demonstrative. As the identities of the officers who were involved in the George Floyd case were revealed, one of them - Tou Thao, belonging to the Asian-American community, led to a comprehensive narrative around the toxic anti-Black thoughts encircling within Asian communities. The long myth that has been perpetuated within the United States alongside the matter is that Asians occupy most space amongst all the American minority groups. This has escalated obvious differences between the two communities reclaiming their identities by trying to endow their own distinctiveness as part of a subculture. However, a refreshing front is projected in one of the Washington protests by Viet Hoai Tran, “Yellow Peril Supports Black Power” (‘yellow peril’ being a racial slur articulating a Western fear of East Asians takeover of ‘their’ land). It is reflective of a sense of repurposing within Asian-American solidarity with the African community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This alliance of two widely intertwined communities dates back to the Bandung Conference (&lt;em&gt;Konferensi Asia Afrika&lt;/em&gt;) established in 1955. The Bandung spirit was absorbed into the Pan-African movement that reinforced opportunities for national interest pursuits, affirmed colonial geographies and economies, and amplified the intensification of inter-community solidarity. The tone for the Conference was actually set by the then Indian Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru almost a decade earlier, as he mentioned a responsibility on the Indian shoulders for the people of Africa in a speech given at the Asian Relations Organisation in 1947. Indonesian President Sukarno was equally interested in building a third segue of solidarity amidst the massive polarisation in the Cold War. The subsequent formation of the Non-Aligned Movement was a symbol of postcolonial states’ independence from Western imperialism and anti-colonialism. It was a celebration of unlearning Western oppression and embracing native identities. This was a spectacle within the global institutional space not just for decolonisation, but also for paving a way for comprehensively irrefutable foreign policy strategies. Thus, marking a historic path of journey propagating a sense of shared transnational solidarity with respect to overcoming feats as shared experiences amidst minority groups. Nothing could deliver justice to the alliance better than the words of Rachel Leow, who said that Bandung became, &lt;em&gt;“Easy metonymy: Bandung the place, Bandung the spirit—Bandung the moment, Bandung the history. Anti-colonialism and transnational solidarity were all theatrical parts: Bandung was the diplomatic debut of newly decolonized peoples on a bipolar world stage, full of agency and vigour.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a landmark meeting held in Cairo in 1958 celebrating the first Afro-Asian Peoples’ Solidarity Conference (AAPSO) dubbed as the ‘Peoples’ Bandung’. Cairo had started developing into a ‘Third World capital’ due to its transcontinental geopolitical disposition and hosted this politically productive translocal solidarity generating space with representatives from forty-six countries. The Association’s establishment challenged the conventional wisdom on mutually exclusive African and Asian nationalist loyalties. The Association’s community grew suddenly post Egyptian President Gamal Abdel Nasser’s nationalisation of the Suez Canal Company in July 1956. It supremely fulfilled further functions, enabled effective communications, allowed the exchanging of skills and moral support, escaped colonial authorities’ restrictions on the movement, and broadened networks. It afforded African activists the valuable space they needed amidst Egyptian media, disseminating multiculturalism. Furthermore, the Association’s political sentiments were expressed through newer manifestations. An important connection with Cairo Radio resulted in nascent broadcasts in Amharic, Sudanese dialects and Swahili by July 1954. These forged networks proved to be influential in propagating Afro-Asian agendas simultaneously. Nasser emphasised on liberation for the Arab Maghreb and Palestine in Bandung and had been echoed by Tunisian, Algerian, and Moroccan delegates who were being hosted as political exiles in Cairo. This influence was enhanced at the 1957 Afro-Asian Conference by the African delegates who were also now residents in Cairo. From 1973 to 1980, the Association was transformed into a cultural and intellectual hub renamed as the African Society engaging majorly with the African Association of Political Science in Dar Es-Salam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theorised by Indian historian Vijay Prashad, in &lt;em&gt;Afro-Dalits of the Earth, Unite!&lt;/em&gt;, the polycultural identity seeking approach to collate and devolve oppressive experiences is called “epidermal determinism”, entrenching solidarity relations on the basis of skin colour. There was a time when Black slaves were emancipated in the Caribbean, North America, and South Africa, and Asian labour was brought to work replacing the shell of the former slaves perpetuating the racial strata of labour as mirrored in Trinidad and Guayana. Taking note of these historical linkages is important to track the unrelenting struggle against universal racism. Runoko Rashidi and V T Rajshekar are two scholars who provide alternate approaches to African-Indian interconnections and allyship, instigating a bond true enough to stir calls for Dalit discrimination in India. This is a power-packed supplemented activism inspired by the Black Lives Matter movement that has voiced concerns of racial differences, class discriminations, oppressive communities, and has meant unforeseen strength for minority groups across the globe. Such is the powerful impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately because of the growing Cold War tensions around the globe, the unprecedented new world order of African-Asian solidarity and other sociopolitical internationalist breakthroughs that wavered into a world full of decolonial possibilities were never given their due credit for overcoming unfathomable adversities. Nevertheless, the outbreak of the Coronavirus pandemic saw an outburst in the hate spree against Asians, and exposed the structurally engraved African discrimination, reminding us that this long-drawn battle is an exacerbation of deeply rooted systemic racism that we need to combat together as communities for as long as it takes. The fight is being grappled with since generations of humanity, and we need to strive for a world that only gets better with every passing day.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Anti-racism protests breaking out across the United States post a gruesome broad-day crime resulting in George Floyd’s death gave rise to a lot of ethnic and racial communities coming together under an umbrella of solidarity to question bigger problems that should have been eradicated decades ago. Western European countries, that have a complicated history of colonial conquest, echo massively of racially discriminatory policing. Imperial colonisers have forever tried to invade what seemed opportunistically resourceful foreign lands to them, to in turn replace its original populations with their own. As surfaced by Mahmood Mamdani in a thought, known as the settler colonialism strategy, this was victorious in countries like Australia and New Zealand, although in countries like Africa this strategy was defeated.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Saudi Arabia’s Wreckage in Perpetuating the Yemen Crisis</title>
      <link href="/Saudi-Arabias-Wreckage" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saudi Arabia's Wreckage in Perpetuating the Yemen Crisis" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Saudi-Arabias-Wreckage</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Saudi-Arabias-Wreckage">&lt;p&gt;Over 13 million Yemeni civilians are facing the worst famine humanity has witnessed in the last hundred years, due to a conflict that dates back to the Arab Spring of 2011. A people’s uprising was held across Yemen against the country’s long time ruling President Ali Abdullah Saleh, to end his 33-year long rule, for his lack of leadership and authoritative grip on power. The uprising was successful and handed the presidential power over to Saleh’s deputy, Abdrabbuh Mansour Hadi, in a transition that felt necessary to inject stability into one of the poorest countries in the Middle East. Unfortunately, thanks to many military officers’ continuing loyalty to Saleh, President Hadi brought the state to its knees, throwing Yemen into a maddening tussle amidst continual militant attacks, excessive corruption and lack of food security&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the context of the current crisis began a decade ago, it took the shape of a vile regime in 2014, when the Houthi Shia Muslim rebel movement seized control of the northern Saada province and its neighbouring areas. The Houthis belong to a small branch of Shia Muslims known as Zaydis and were formerly known as  Ansar Allah. The rebel group progressed into taking over Sana’a, the capital city of Yemen. This led to a forceful exile of Abdrabbuh Mansour Hadi abroad, while the rebel group took over Yemen leading the country into religious and political turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A largely Sunni Muslim-dominated state being taken hostage by a Houthi Shia Muslim rebel group meant conflict was bound to occur. Moreover, Yemen and Saudi Arabia’s geographical landscape benefits the two nations majorly as they lie on one side of the coastline to the Suez Canal that is the quickest shipping route from Asia to Europe, making it a key geographical location for the purposes of the world’s shipping trade. This clearly meant that Yemen was bound to become a hotbed of proxy wars between regional and world powers. And this is exactly what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a dramatic escalation in the conflict in March 2015 when, backed by the US, UK, and France, Saudi Arabia and eight other Sunni Arab dominated states ordered airstrikes against the Houthis, declaring their aim to restore Hadi’s government. This politically driven Saudi-led military coalition was paranoid of the Houthis’ subsequent success in deterring the strike by getting the support of Saudi’s everlasting regional rival and Shia-majority state, Iran. Being a geographical neighbour, Iran already had a foothold in Yemen but denied the claims made by Saudi Arabia alleging Iran’s backing of the Houthis with logistical support and weaponry. Since then, clashes from both sides have resulted in warfare that has been elongated for years. Ali Abdullah Saleh was killed by Houthi fighters in December 2017, and subsequent anti-Houthi sentiments even led to secessionist movements being stirred in southern Yemen seeking independence for the factions who oppose the rebel group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2018, Saudi-backed government forces attacked a key rebel port named Al-Hudaydah, which was incidentally an entry point for a vast majority of aid reaching Yemen. This aid was a lifeline for two-thirds of the entire population. Their mandate for the continuous interjections was always directed at pushing ‘Iranian influence’ out of Yemen and reinstating Hadi’s government for obvious religious differences. The claims were to stop after a few weeks, but the brokered civil war backed by major state players is still going on after all these testing years. The offensive only made Yemen’s humanitarian catastrophe much worse. In September 2019, Saudi Arabia’s eastern oil fields in the regions of Abqaiq and Khurais were attacked by air, disrupting nearly half the regime’s oil production (representing about 5% of the global output). The Houthis claimed full responsibility for the attack but Saudi and the US were adamant that Iran had a role in carrying out the attacks. Hadi’s government even accused Hezbollah (Iran’s Lebanese ally) of aiding Houthis with arms. The Saudi Arabian perception that it is an Iranian proxy war and not an indigenous movement for democracy has effectively driven its continual intervention in Yemen, verily making it a Saudi proxy war if nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is playing a dicey role in the Yemen crisis. They are acting as pen holders on the Yemen file at the United Nations Security Council (UNSC), and simultaneously providing military advice to the Saudi-led coalition in Riyadh. British diplomats and Saudi sceptics have praised the UK’s role in limiting an all-out assault on Yemen, but it might as well be a diplomatic ruse to protect their position in the UNSC. Moreover, however far the UK went to defend its arms’ sales to Saudi Arabia, it was all for naught, as the UK’s actions were deemed unlawful by the English Court of Appeal. The Court’s judgment was critical of the ministers’ ignorance of whether the airstrikes that killed Yemeni civilians broke humanitarian law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the years of draining war and turmoil weren’t enough, two horrendous health crises have crippled the Yemeni people and impacted their economy negatively - the infamous cholera breakout and the coronavirus disease pandemic. The healthcare system of the country has collapsed, and Yemen is at its lowest. About 24 million people are in dire need of humanitarian assistance, aid, and protection including food, drinking water and healthcare. Around 20 million people need basic healthcare, and 18 million people are in need of water and sanitation facilities. An estimated 85,000 children have perished of acute malnutrition between 2015-2018, and 2 million children who are under the age of five are at risk. The coronavirus disease pandemic has led to an additional 5 million children losing their education. 3 million people have been displaced by the conflict. Since the beginning of the civil war, Yemen’s economy has contracted by 50% due to the economic inflation and devaluation of the Rial. People are being rendered hungry due to poverty and unemployment, amidst the already tough war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the external forces in Yemen are only hell-bent on attacking each other, involving, unfortunately, the Yemeni civilians as victims of their national vendettas. It goes without saying that many interested sides have always had the reinforcements to financially benefit from the status quo of this region. But the harsh conditions that have led Yemen to see humanity’s worst situation have dictated its state today. It’s difficult to imagine what so many millions are going through in the country, and the least we can do is learn, spread awareness, and lend a helping hand. Every small act counts in building it back up. Here is a list of authentic organisations dedicated to solving the humanitarian crisis that Yemen is being subjected to, especially in the midst of a global pandemic. Donating is the way we can effectively help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unicef.org.uk/donate/yemen/&quot;&gt;https://www.unicef.org.uk/donate/yemen/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://donate.unhcr.org/in/yemen/~my-donation&quot;&gt;https://donate.unhcr.org/in/yemen/~my-donation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.islamic-relief.org.uk/yemen-emergency-appeal/&quot;&gt;https://www.islamic-relief.org.uk/yemen-emergency-appeal/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.savethechildren.org.uk/how-you-can-help/emergencies/yemen-crisis&quot;&gt;https://www.savethechildren.org.uk/how-you-can-help/emergencies/yemen-crisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.savethechildren.org/us/what-we-do/where-we-work/greater-middle-east-eurasia/yemen&quot;&gt;https://www.savethechildren.org/us/what-we-do/where-we-work/greater-middle-east-eurasia/yemen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.projecthope.org/crisis-in-yemen/09/2019/&quot;&gt;https://www.projecthope.org/crisis-in-yemen/09/2019/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Over 13 million Yemeni civilians are facing the worst famine humanity has witnessed in the last hundred years, due to a conflict that dates back to the Arab Spring of 2011. A people’s uprising was held across Yemen against the country’s long time ruling President Ali Abdullah Saleh, to end his 33-year long rule, for his lack of leadership and authoritative grip on power. The uprising was successful and handed the presidential power over to Saleh’s deputy, Abdrabbuh Mansour Hadi, in a transition that felt necessary to inject stability into one of the poorest countries in the Middle East. Unfortunately, thanks to many military officers’ continuing loyalty to Saleh, President Hadi brought the state to its knees, throwing Yemen into a maddening tussle amidst continual militant attacks, excessive corruption and lack of food security</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Minimalist Manifesto</title>
      <link href="/A-Minimalist-Manifesto" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Minimalist Manifesto" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Minimalist-Manifesto</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Minimalist-Manifesto">&lt;p&gt;It is irrefutably substantial to propose that the lockdown has generally made us a little less obsessive about how we look all the time, the outfits we wear every day, and has led to a daily decrease in the shopaholic nature of our rapid consumption. It is all seeming a lot simpler because we are at home not having to conform to our social constructs. We all struggle with the daily clutter of having to manage an nth number of things, which can get to the most sorted people’s heads. The pandemic has, in a way, somehow tidied our minds with respect to the number of things we own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimalist movement started out as an art movement emphasising on and advocating simplistic living, that a lot of people mistook only for aesthetics. As the unruly laws of humans always tend to find a way to corrupt anything, a floating zen ideal is already stigmatised. It is not impractical, privileged thinking that undermines the consequences of capitalism. Consumerism is an important aspect that the world functions on today. It becomes devilish when it is used to play with people’s minds in a way that forces them to buy things they don’t necessarily need. Minimising the number of things one assigns ownership to declutters our minds, and leads one to a freer lifestyle. For instance, after a person’s death, one can notice how many of that person’s memories are attached to his/her things. It’s intriguing how we let things play such a central role in a person’s being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jean-Paul Sartre’s interesting and famous existentialist theories were based on the inevitability of the mantra “being precedes essence”. Being is important, and essence is only secondary to that. There is peace and freedom in living that virtue. The daily chase after the things we want to buy and/or want to ‘own’ is taking over the real purposes of life. We are all involved in the rat race of earning the most amount of money, which translates in our head as buying the best, most expensive commodity, thinking of happiness or purpose in quantifiable and tangible terms. The measurable quality of ‘success’ these days is hooked onto this opaque idea of ownership. Not to devalue the importance of this success, but we achieve it in a way that we never prioritise our well being again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimalism focuses on the uncontroversial preaching that one should think critically about what is necessary and what is not. In practice, therefore, it translates into, as Chayka and other have noted, a form of conspicuously inconspicuous consumption. Minimalism, however, is today characterised as the glamourisation of a simplistic lifestyle. So the original intention has now taken a back seat, and the aesthetic it happens to represent has blinded some of its followers. But this psychological impact, fortunately, or unfortunately, could add to the legacy of the notion. It’s morally a slightly grey perspective to approach the growth of the phenomena, nonetheless welcomed if it helps increase the awareness around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of minimalism is described by critics and analysts to be highly curative, hyper-reluctant, over meticulous, stringently restrictive and arrogantly ignorant. These might just be mere consequences of some personally enhanced interpretations of the minimalist philosophy. There is no denying its mantra being overworked upon by highly organised individuals, but that’s a different representation that needn’t be projected upon the ethical commands of what the movement truly advocates. All the movement is about is cutting down consumption, monitoring usage, reducing arbitrary decisions, avoiding having to manage futility, lowering chances of redundancy, leading a reclusive path, and so on to create a lifestyle that can focus more upon the meaningful aspects of life. If we spend most of our lives worrying about things and the more superficially-aligned aspects of living, that’s all our way of thinking will stay limited to. The ascetic undertones it propagates, are crafted in relation to the lesser focused-upon connotations of simplicity that have forever fascinated its followers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sick to think that minimalism romanticises poverty or the unprivileged sects. This critique is oblivious to such a highly principled phenomenon and what it aims to achieve. It is ignorant of its depths and it misunderstands the underlying spiritual faith. A capitalist-critical argument that is essential to consider argues that minimalism is highly imperative to achieve a more equitable society in terms of people’s consumption being proportionate to their needs. This will create a socio-economic environment that protects and celebrates inclusivity and actively preaches egalitarian principles. What must be criticised, if at all, should be the over-fetishisation of the curated ‘simplicity’ that the ultra-rich like to benefit from by pretending it is their ‘style of aesthetic’. The movement has been curdled into more of its ostentatious implications by such classes as ‘show off’ and ‘superficiality’. However, this is exactly what the movement proposes to combat today, added to destructuring the capitalist overindulgence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine a few artistic derivations of minimalism, where the expression authentically originates from. At the School of the Art Institute, Chicago, a contemporary art professor David Raskin states, “&lt;em&gt;Minimalism can return you to this basic state where you’re perceiving purely. Less is more because you strip away the familiar&lt;/em&gt;”. A plain, monochromatic painting or object might seem mundane and dull on the surface, but actually engender a stark sensory experience the mind has never been exposed to before. It inculcates an opportunity to view the world without any preconceptions a mind is previously latched onto. Its existence is simply representative of a clean slate for one to reflect onto. The art radically imbibes the actuality of infinite possibilities and makes one not only think, but delve into introspection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that, as human beings, we must not just preach minimalism in our daily lives but constantly remind ourselves why such spiritual, socio-economic change is required in this rather belittled world of everlasting consumerist societies continually propagating capitalist ideologies, and demanding the grind and hustle to exploit our passions by rapidly creating commodities and products out of it that appeal only to the competitive politics of capitalist regimes, thereby, ultimately crumbling our innate need to stop, absorb and think.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is irrefutably substantial to propose that the lockdown has generally made us a little less obsessive about how we look all the time, the outfits we wear every day, and has led to a daily decrease in the shopaholic nature of our rapid consumption. It is all seeming a lot simpler because we are at home not having to conform to our social constructs. We all struggle with the daily clutter of having to manage an nth number of things, which can get to the most sorted people’s heads. The pandemic has, in a way, somehow tidied our minds with respect to the number of things we own.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Landmark Political Speeches and Rhetorics that Incited Historical Change</title>
      <link href="/Landmark-Political-Speeches" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Landmark Political Speeches and Rhetorics that Incited Historical Change" />
      <published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Landmark-Political-Speeches</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Landmark-Political-Speeches">&lt;p&gt;One of the most earnest driving forces in the political landscape of human history has been the influence of revolutionary and powerful speeches. Some of the most well-written public speeches which attempt to influence audiences are a masterful combination of strong political emotions, the art of language and writing, efficient public speaking, clarity of stance, tensile communicative gestures and a tethered grip of the listeners’ attention. Such speeches combine a gravitative sense of the right pauses, accurate emphasis on event-centric phrases, truthful and emotional connection with the audience, and a perfect translation of thoughts into words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the most impactful speeches are delivered post remarkable events in history. All groundbreaking spectacles of human history are followed by a prideful example of magnificent public speaking. The speeches elaborated upon here have held hearts in dark times, provided hope in despondency, inspired the characters of men, ignited some brave feats, given courage to the downtrodden, kept the dead’s honour and changed the course of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Third Philippic&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Demosthenes, Athens, Greece, 342 BC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most ancient speeches should receive their due in setting historical standards. Demosthenes was a statesman and orator of Athens, his city-state, which he cherished with his life. He was born with a speech impediment—a very unbelievable fact. He would go to any lengths against anyone who might attempt to infringe on the privileges of life and freedom people enjoyed in his state. Unfortunately, this passion was seldom shared by his fellow Athenians. When Philip II of Macedon made unstoppable, bolder incursions into the Greek peninsula, the Athenians fell into a coursing dilemma. Demosthenes kept engaging with his powerful oratorical skills to awaken his fellow citizens from the rousing danger Philip posed. Philip slowly advanced on Thrace, and Demosthenes was sick of how his kinfolk were taking liberty for granted. He called a speech to induce action, at the end of which the assembly cried out, “To arms! To arms!” This speech has always been a classic example of a passionate leader guiding his people by calling out the follies they were succumbing to and rescuing them from subjugation under evil counsels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ain’t I A Woman?&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Sojourner Truth, Ohio, USA, May 29, 1851&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sojourner Truth was an escaped slave, an evangelist, an activist of feminism, and a preacher of abolitionism, who dared to deliver this iconic speech at the Women’s Rights Convention in Akron. This speech was a passionate response and an accusatory call out of male ministers who had protested the Convention believing that women were weaker and intellectually inferior to men. The men protested with citations trying to prove their horrid stance. They said that Jesus had been a man and that the original woman, Eve, had sinned — as documented proof to feed their egotistical male chauvinism. Sojourner Truth herself was a devoted Christain, and she used her own interpretation of the Bible to put the men in their place and become an inspiration to women for centuries to come. &lt;em&gt;“If the first woman God ever made was strong enough to turn the world upside down all alone, these women together ought to be able to turn it back, and get it right side up again! And now they [are] asking to do it, the men better let them.”&lt;/em&gt; She ignited many human rights crusaders through her empowering wisdom and instilled ideals of gender equality amongst the youngest of girls not just in her time, but for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Gettysburg Address&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Abraham Lincoln, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, November 19, 1863&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;272 words of perfectionist rhetoric, The Gettysburg Address is like a founding pillar of American freedom. The Battle of Gettysburg left eight thousand men dead, the land reeking murky of death, violence and absolute horror. It was meant to be solemnised by Edward Everett’s speech and Abraham Lincoln was meant to only add a few remarks to it. He did in two minutes what Everett couldn’t, even in his own ways, in two hours. Lincoln created the speech to be something far larger than merely memorialising the fallen. He invented a discourse and questioned, most importantly, whether the government can maintain the proposition of equality. It was at Gettysburg where the Constitution was etched with its forever embedded ideals of equality and liberty as the Civil War saw the same ideals crumbling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We Shall Fight on the Beaches&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Winston Churchill, House of Commons, London, June 4, 1940&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill was one of the greatest orators to be born out of the 20th century. Like many great orators before him, he was born with a speech impediment. It is tough to grasp that fact considering the massive tensile strength of his voice, one that riled up Britain during some of its darkest hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Battle of France, Allied Forces lost connection with their troops deployed south of the German penetration. These troops were precariously trapped at the Dunkirk bridgehead. On May 26, 1940, a rampant evacuation of these troops under the name ‘Operation Dynamo’ began. The Royal Air Force made an unimaginably successful effort (even for aerial warfare) at keeping the Luftwaffe at bay while thousands of ships, from military destroyers to small fishing boats, were used to safely rescue and ferry French and British troops. Churchill spoke before the House of Commons on June 4, delivering a speech celebrating the ‘miraculous deliverance’ at Dunkirk. He stood and spoke as he gave one of the most momentous speeches in the House of Commons as he defended Britain and France and it created history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Have A Dream&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Martin Luther King Jr., Washington D.C., USA, August 28, 1963&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This legendary speech of Martin Luther King Jr is unarguably one of the greatest, if not the greatest, piece of oratory in world history. King creates a league of his own with his personality and charisma, skills in rhetoric and passionate precision. A century after African-Americans were promised full equality, black people were being run down in the streets, looked down upon, turned away from public places and denied treatment as human beings. Amidst this horrendous track record of being discriminated against, Dr King embodied a humanity-driven, compelling message of hope. He talked about a dream he had, where egalitarianism thrived and discrimination was forgotten. The emotional quotient of this speech truly touched the most human parts of anybody listening. It is a masterpiece with the expression of a once in a lifetime kind of deliverance, yet with the layered ideals of humanity which we should all ethically thrive for as any society. This speech is, in its entirety, just as exhilarating and moving today as it was in 1963.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the aforementioned speeches have some gripping takeaways that will impact generations to come, so they can trace their ancestral passions and encapsulate an understanding of what preceded them. There have been innumerable speeches from the remotest of places that have ingrained the purposes of humanity and politics within the most different communities. It will take a lifetime to reflect on it all. Take this as a proposition to do so. One might find a leader in the most local roads trying to build oneness.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most earnest driving forces in the political landscape of human history has been the influence of revolutionary and powerful speeches. Some of the most well-written public speeches which attempt to influence audiences are a masterful combination of strong political emotions, the art of language and writing, efficient public speaking, clarity of stance, tensile communicative gestures and a tethered grip of the listeners’ attention. Such speeches combine a gravitative sense of the right pauses, accurate emphasis on event-centric phrases, truthful and emotional connection with the audience, and a perfect translation of thoughts into words.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
