<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/saachi.ghosh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-27T22:59:16+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/saachi.ghosh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Minimalist Manifesto</title>
      <link href="/A-Minimalist-Manifesto" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Minimalist Manifesto" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Minimalist-Manifesto</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Minimalist-Manifesto">&lt;p&gt;It is irrefutably substantial to propose that the lockdown has generally made us a little less obsessive about how we look all the time, the outfits we wear every day, and has led to a daily decrease in the shopaholic nature of our rapid consumption. It is all seeming a lot simpler because we are at home not having to conform to our social constructs. We all struggle with the daily clutter of having to manage an nth number of things, which can get to the most sorted people’s heads. The pandemic has, in a way, somehow tidied our minds with respect to the number of things we own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimalist movement started out as an art movement emphasising on and advocating simplistic living, that a lot of people mistook only for aesthetics. As the unruly laws of humans always tend to find a way to corrupt anything, a floating zen ideal is already stigmatised. It is not impractical, privileged thinking that undermines the consequences of capitalism. Consumerism is an important aspect that the world functions on today. It becomes devilish when it is used to play with people’s minds in a way that forces them to buy things they don’t necessarily need. Minimising the number of things one assigns ownership to declutters our minds, and leads one to a freer lifestyle. For instance, after a person’s death, one can notice how many of that person’s memories are attached to his/her things. It’s intriguing how we let things play such a central role in a person’s being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jean-Paul Sartre’s interesting and famous existentialist theories were based on the inevitability of the mantra “being precedes essence”. Being is important, and essence is only secondary to that. There is peace and freedom in living that virtue. The daily chase after the things we want to buy and/or want to ‘own’ is taking over the real purposes of life. We are all involved in the rat race of earning the most amount of money, which translates in our head as buying the best, most expensive commodity, thinking of happiness or purpose in quantifiable and tangible terms. The measurable quality of ‘success’ these days is hooked onto this opaque idea of ownership. Not to devalue the importance of this success, but we achieve it in a way that we never prioritise our well being again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minimalism focuses on the uncontroversial preaching that one should think critically about what is necessary and what is not. In practice, therefore, it translates into, as Chayka and other have noted, a form of conspicuously inconspicuous consumption. Minimalism, however, is today characterised as the glamourisation of a simplistic lifestyle. So the original intention has now taken a back seat, and the aesthetic it happens to represent has blinded some of its followers. But this psychological impact, fortunately, or unfortunately, could add to the legacy of the notion. It’s morally a slightly grey perspective to approach the growth of the phenomena, nonetheless welcomed if it helps increase the awareness around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of minimalism is described by critics and analysts to be highly curative, hyper-reluctant, over meticulous, stringently restrictive and arrogantly ignorant. These might just be mere consequences of some personally enhanced interpretations of the minimalist philosophy. There is no denying its mantra being overworked upon by highly organised individuals, but that’s a different representation that needn’t be projected upon the ethical commands of what the movement truly advocates. All the movement is about is cutting down consumption, monitoring usage, reducing arbitrary decisions, avoiding having to manage futility, lowering chances of redundancy, leading a reclusive path, and so on to create a lifestyle that can focus more upon the meaningful aspects of life. If we spend most of our lives worrying about things and the more superficially-aligned aspects of living, that’s all our way of thinking will stay limited to. The ascetic undertones it propagates, are crafted in relation to the lesser focused-upon connotations of simplicity that have forever fascinated its followers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sick to think that minimalism romanticises poverty or the unprivileged sects. This critique is oblivious to such a highly principled phenomenon and what it aims to achieve. It is ignorant of its depths and it misunderstands the underlying spiritual faith. A capitalist-critical argument that is essential to consider argues that minimalism is highly imperative to achieve a more equitable society in terms of people’s consumption being proportionate to their needs. This will create a socio-economic environment that protects and celebrates inclusivity and actively preaches egalitarian principles. What must be criticised, if at all, should be the over-fetishisation of the curated ‘simplicity’ that the ultra-rich like to benefit from by pretending it is their ‘style of aesthetic’. The movement has been curdled into more of its ostentatious implications by such classes as ‘show off’ and ‘superficiality’. However, this is exactly what the movement proposes to combat today, added to destructuring the capitalist overindulgence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine a few artistic derivations of minimalism, where the expression authentically originates from. At the School of the Art Institute, Chicago, a contemporary art professor David Raskin states, “&lt;em&gt;Minimalism can return you to this basic state where you’re perceiving purely. Less is more because you strip away the familiar&lt;/em&gt;”. A plain, monochromatic painting or object might seem mundane and dull on the surface, but actually engender a stark sensory experience the mind has never been exposed to before. It inculcates an opportunity to view the world without any preconceptions a mind is previously latched onto. Its existence is simply representative of a clean slate for one to reflect onto. The art radically imbibes the actuality of infinite possibilities and makes one not only think, but delve into introspection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that, as human beings, we must not just preach minimalism in our daily lives but constantly remind ourselves why such spiritual, socio-economic change is required in this rather belittled world of everlasting consumerist societies continually propagating capitalist ideologies, and demanding the grind and hustle to exploit our passions by rapidly creating commodities and products out of it that appeal only to the competitive politics of capitalist regimes, thereby, ultimately crumbling our innate need to stop, absorb and think.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is irrefutably substantial to propose that the lockdown has generally made us a little less obsessive about how we look all the time, the outfits we wear every day, and has led to a daily decrease in the shopaholic nature of our rapid consumption. It is all seeming a lot simpler because we are at home not having to conform to our social constructs. We all struggle with the daily clutter of having to manage an nth number of things, which can get to the most sorted people’s heads. The pandemic has, in a way, somehow tidied our minds with respect to the number of things we own.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Landmark Political Speeches and Rhetorics that Incited Historical Change</title>
      <link href="/Landmark-Political-Speeches" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Landmark Political Speeches and Rhetorics that Incited Historical Change" />
      <published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Landmark-Political-Speeches</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Landmark-Political-Speeches">&lt;p&gt;One of the most earnest driving forces in the political landscape of human history has been the influence of revolutionary and powerful speeches. Some of the most well-written public speeches which attempt to influence audiences are a masterful combination of strong political emotions, the art of language and writing, efficient public speaking, clarity of stance, tensile communicative gestures and a tethered grip of the listeners’ attention. Such speeches combine a gravitative sense of the right pauses, accurate emphasis on event-centric phrases, truthful and emotional connection with the audience, and a perfect translation of thoughts into words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the most impactful speeches are delivered post remarkable events in history. All groundbreaking spectacles of human history are followed by a prideful example of magnificent public speaking. The speeches elaborated upon here have held hearts in dark times, provided hope in despondency, inspired the characters of men, ignited some brave feats, given courage to the downtrodden, kept the dead’s honour and changed the course of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Third Philippic&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Demosthenes, Athens, Greece, 342 BC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most ancient speeches should receive their due in setting historical standards. Demosthenes was a statesman and orator of Athens, his city-state, which he cherished with his life. He was born with a speech impediment—a very unbelievable fact. He would go to any lengths against anyone who might attempt to infringe on the privileges of life and freedom people enjoyed in his state. Unfortunately, this passion was seldom shared by his fellow Athenians. When Philip II of Macedon made unstoppable, bolder incursions into the Greek peninsula, the Athenians fell into a coursing dilemma. Demosthenes kept engaging with his powerful oratorical skills to awaken his fellow citizens from the rousing danger Philip posed. Philip slowly advanced on Thrace, and Demosthenes was sick of how his kinfolk were taking liberty for granted. He called a speech to induce action, at the end of which the assembly cried out, “To arms! To arms!” This speech has always been a classic example of a passionate leader guiding his people by calling out the follies they were succumbing to and rescuing them from subjugation under evil counsels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ain’t I A Woman?&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Sojourner Truth, Ohio, USA, May 29, 1851&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sojourner Truth was an escaped slave, an evangelist, an activist of feminism, and a preacher of abolitionism, who dared to deliver this iconic speech at the Women’s Rights Convention in Akron. This speech was a passionate response and an accusatory call out of male ministers who had protested the Convention believing that women were weaker and intellectually inferior to men. The men protested with citations trying to prove their horrid stance. They said that Jesus had been a man and that the original woman, Eve, had sinned — as documented proof to feed their egotistical male chauvinism. Sojourner Truth herself was a devoted Christain, and she used her own interpretation of the Bible to put the men in their place and become an inspiration to women for centuries to come. &lt;em&gt;“If the first woman God ever made was strong enough to turn the world upside down all alone, these women together ought to be able to turn it back, and get it right side up again! And now they [are] asking to do it, the men better let them.”&lt;/em&gt; She ignited many human rights crusaders through her empowering wisdom and instilled ideals of gender equality amongst the youngest of girls not just in her time, but for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Gettysburg Address&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Abraham Lincoln, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, November 19, 1863&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;272 words of perfectionist rhetoric, The Gettysburg Address is like a founding pillar of American freedom. The Battle of Gettysburg left eight thousand men dead, the land reeking murky of death, violence and absolute horror. It was meant to be solemnised by Edward Everett’s speech and Abraham Lincoln was meant to only add a few remarks to it. He did in two minutes what Everett couldn’t, even in his own ways, in two hours. Lincoln created the speech to be something far larger than merely memorialising the fallen. He invented a discourse and questioned, most importantly, whether the government can maintain the proposition of equality. It was at Gettysburg where the Constitution was etched with its forever embedded ideals of equality and liberty as the Civil War saw the same ideals crumbling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We Shall Fight on the Beaches&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Winston Churchill, House of Commons, London, June 4, 1940&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill was one of the greatest orators to be born out of the 20th century. Like many great orators before him, he was born with a speech impediment. It is tough to grasp that fact considering the massive tensile strength of his voice, one that riled up Britain during some of its darkest hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Battle of France, Allied Forces lost connection with their troops deployed south of the German penetration. These troops were precariously trapped at the Dunkirk bridgehead. On May 26, 1940, a rampant evacuation of these troops under the name ‘Operation Dynamo’ began. The Royal Air Force made an unimaginably successful effort (even for aerial warfare) at keeping the Luftwaffe at bay while thousands of ships, from military destroyers to small fishing boats, were used to safely rescue and ferry French and British troops. Churchill spoke before the House of Commons on June 4, delivering a speech celebrating the ‘miraculous deliverance’ at Dunkirk. He stood and spoke as he gave one of the most momentous speeches in the House of Commons as he defended Britain and France and it created history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Have A Dream&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Martin Luther King Jr., Washington D.C., USA, August 28, 1963&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This legendary speech of Martin Luther King Jr is unarguably one of the greatest, if not the greatest, piece of oratory in world history. King creates a league of his own with his personality and charisma, skills in rhetoric and passionate precision. A century after African-Americans were promised full equality, black people were being run down in the streets, looked down upon, turned away from public places and denied treatment as human beings. Amidst this horrendous track record of being discriminated against, Dr King embodied a humanity-driven, compelling message of hope. He talked about a dream he had, where egalitarianism thrived and discrimination was forgotten. The emotional quotient of this speech truly touched the most human parts of anybody listening. It is a masterpiece with the expression of a once in a lifetime kind of deliverance, yet with the layered ideals of humanity which we should all ethically thrive for as any society. This speech is, in its entirety, just as exhilarating and moving today as it was in 1963.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the aforementioned speeches have some gripping takeaways that will impact generations to come, so they can trace their ancestral passions and encapsulate an understanding of what preceded them. There have been innumerable speeches from the remotest of places that have ingrained the purposes of humanity and politics within the most different communities. It will take a lifetime to reflect on it all. Take this as a proposition to do so. One might find a leader in the most local roads trying to build oneness.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most earnest driving forces in the political landscape of human history has been the influence of revolutionary and powerful speeches. Some of the most well-written public speeches which attempt to influence audiences are a masterful combination of strong political emotions, the art of language and writing, efficient public speaking, clarity of stance, tensile communicative gestures and a tethered grip of the listeners’ attention. Such speeches combine a gravitative sense of the right pauses, accurate emphasis on event-centric phrases, truthful and emotional connection with the audience, and a perfect translation of thoughts into words.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
