<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/oyeshi.ganguly/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-03-23T21:47:55+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/oyeshi.ganguly/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘D word’ is missing, Sir</title>
      <link href="/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘D word’ is missing, Sir" />
      <published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The world is watching&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These four words, employed in the joint statement issued by the embassies of the European Union, the United Kingdom and Canada along with 11 other nations to condemn the 2021 military coup in Myanmar, truly reflect the political reality of the nation. The February coup shouldn't come as a surprise to anyone remotely acquainted with contemporary Burmese politics. Free elections had been allowed by the military &lt;em&gt;junta &lt;/em&gt;in 1990 with the presumption that it enjoyed popular support. However, much to the dismay of the generals, Aung San Suu Kyi’s National League for Democracy (NLD) won by a large margin. The narrative henceforth followed a trajectory jarringly similar to the one we see today. The military, steadfast in its refusal to part with power, placed Suu Kyi under house arrest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military, known as Tatmadaw, enjoyed power for 22 years till 2011. As part of the ‘7-Step Roadmap’, the third constitution of Myanmar was drafted in 2008 and the nation took its first steps towards achieving democracy. The 2015 elections general elections resulted in a victory for the National League for Democracy. Yet the achievement could not be appreciated in all its due regards, as the military continued to exert significant influence. It enjoyed the right to appoint one-fourth of the members of the parliament.&amp;nbsp; History repeated itself when the results of the 2020 November elections witnessed the NLD's victory, with the party winning 396 out of 476 parliamentary seats. It had surpassed its previous margins achieved in the 2015 elections. On the other hand, the Union Solidarity and Development Party representing the military junta could win only 33 seats. This electoral result has been attributed as the spark which ignited the coup d’etat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Chronology of the Coup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At about 3 AM on February 1, 2021, Suu Kyi and Han Thi Myint,&amp;nbsp; who is the party spokesperson of the NLD were placed under detention, and communication channels were severely disrupted. The army's TV station declared that power had been handed over to commander-in-chief Min Aung Hlaing and that an emergency was being imposed for the next year. Such kill switch tactics, usually reserved for the Rakhine State, were replicated all over the nation. The roads to the Burmese capital Naypyidaw were blocked by soldiers. 400 elected members of parliament representing the NLD were placed under house arrest. Social media users called for holding a parliament within the same government guest house where they were forced to reside. This was a convincing argument as the number of MPs present in the guest house was meeting the quorum.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two sides have locked horns even though the military clearly has an upper hand when it comes to hard power. Defying military dictates, 70 NLD MPs took the oath of office on February 4. The military also announced on February 4, 2021 that 24 ministers and deputies had been removed from office and 11 replacements had been appointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coup also received a religious tint with the soldiers detaining several Buddhist monks who had led the 2007 Saffron Revolution. The Assistance Association for Political Prisoners has identified 133 officials, 14 civil society activists who had been detained by the military since the coup's inception. Min Aung Hlaing, head of the Tatmadaw, has established the State Administration Council to establish direct control of state affairs and has also imposed a curfew from 8 PM to 4 AM in all major cities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 13, a shocking violation of the freedom of the press was noticed as the military administered Ministry of Information (MoI) exerted pressure upon the press to delete the phrases “junta” and “regime” to describe the coup. The recent military order involves facing 20 years of prison if an individual is found encroaching on the work of the security forces. This order also bestows the power to make arrests, carry out searches and even detain individuals for a period of more than 24 hours without trial or right to proper judicial recourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Deeper&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military had carried out their first coup d'etat against a civilian government in 1962. But the present action may be studied in the context of the time in which it has occurred. This week was to witness the first session of the parliament in which the new democratically elected government would have been officially anointed to power. It is noteworthy that more than 70% of the voters had challenged the pandemic scenario to vote and elect Suu Kyi. This is particularly noteworthy considering the flak that she had been receiving for the genocide against the Rohingyas. Public resentment against the military government is thus inevitable. The primary opposition levelled by the military is that the election was marked by fraud, blaming the UEC (Union Election commission) for voter list irregularities.&amp;nbsp; Sounds familiar? Trumpian? Gotcha.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, there's no evidence to support the claim.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business and financial interests of Min Aung Hlaing's family too have been a cause of contention. He oversees the twin military conglomerates: Myanmar Economic Corporation (MEC) and Myanma Economic Holdings Limited (MEHL) with his daughter, son and daughter-in-law holding substantial business interests in each. Moreover, a few days prior to the coup, the International Monetary Fund had released $350 million in cash to the Central Bank of Myanmar as a COVID-19 relief package. It didn't contain any clause for refund. The misuse of this fund seems to be a likelihood in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way ahead&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manufactured emergency holds little ground legally. The president can declare an emergency only after due consultation with the National Defence and Security Council. The military has proven itself to be enjoying a stature above that of the constitution. The military states that it would rule only for a year and then hold a fresh election. It doesn't require too much political clairvoyance to predict that such an election would be completely orchestrated by the military. The public perception regarding the military has indeed undergone a setback. Burmese Twitter account holders used #RespectOurVotes, #HearTheVoiceofMyanmar among others. Myo Ko Ko, a Burmese student activist articulates the anxiety as he says “We strongly believe in democracy and human rights. We know that it's risky.” The coup has elicited mixed reactions from the nation's diverse ethnic groups. While the Restoration Council of Shan State has strongly condemned the coup, the Kachin Independence Organisation with a large population has remained silent about it. The coup has attracted international reactions, including Jacinda Ardern severing New Zealand's diplomatic ties with Myanmar. The UN Security Council held an emergency meeting upholding the resolution of restoring democracy in Myanmar. The statement however couldn't garner the support of all the members, with permanent members China and Russia refusing to back it. The regional implications in South Asia are, however, muted, with nations including India resorting to soft tactics and not being vocal about the situation. The ASEAN nations continue to stick to their non-interference tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the uncertainty persists amidst the three-finger salute in Myanmar. The gesture of defiance against the spectre that has returned back to haunt the nation, yet again. Democracy, the elusive D-word rests in agitation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The world is watching.” These four words, employed in the joint statement issued by the embassies of the European Union, the United Kingdom and Canada along with 11 other nations to condemn the 2021 military coup in Myanmar, truly reflect the political reality of the nation. The February coup shouldn't come as a surprise to anyone remotely acquainted with contemporary Burmese politics. Free elections had been allowed by the military junta in 1990 with the presumption that it enjoyed popular support. However, much to the dismay of the generals, Aung San Suu Kyi’s National League for Democracy (NLD) won by a large margin. The narrative henceforth followed a trajectory jarringly similar to the one we see today. The military, steadfast in its refusal to part with power, placed Suu Kyi under house arrest.&amp;nbsp; The military, known as Tatmadaw, enjoyed power for 22 years till 2011. As part of the ‘7-Step Roadmap’, the third constitution of Myanmar was drafted in 2008 and the nation took its first steps towards achieving democracy. The 2015 elections general elections resulted in a victory for the National League for Democracy. Yet the achievement could not be appreciated in all its due regards, as the military continued to exert significant influence. It enjoyed the right to appoint one-fourth of the members of the parliament.&amp;nbsp; History repeated itself when the results of the 2020 November elections witnessed the NLD's victory, with the party winning 396 out of 476 parliamentary seats. It had surpassed its previous margins achieved in the 2015 elections. On the other hand, the Union Solidarity and Development Party representing the military junta could win only 33 seats. This electoral result has been attributed as the spark which ignited the coup d’etat.&amp;nbsp; A Chronology of the Coup At about 3 AM on February 1, 2021, Suu Kyi and Han Thi Myint,&amp;nbsp; who is the party spokesperson of the NLD were placed under detention, and communication channels were severely disrupted. The army's TV station declared that power had been handed over to commander-in-chief Min Aung Hlaing and that an emergency was being imposed for the next year. Such kill switch tactics, usually reserved for the Rakhine State, were replicated all over the nation. The roads to the Burmese capital Naypyidaw were blocked by soldiers. 400 elected members of parliament representing the NLD were placed under house arrest. Social media users called for holding a parliament within the same government guest house where they were forced to reside. This was a convincing argument as the number of MPs present in the guest house was meeting the quorum.&amp;nbsp; The two sides have locked horns even though the military clearly has an upper hand when it comes to hard power. Defying military dictates, 70 NLD MPs took the oath of office on February 4. The military also announced on February 4, 2021 that 24 ministers and deputies had been removed from office and 11 replacements had been appointed. The coup also received a religious tint with the soldiers detaining several Buddhist monks who had led the 2007 Saffron Revolution. The Assistance Association for Political Prisoners has identified 133 officials, 14 civil society activists who had been detained by the military since the coup's inception. Min Aung Hlaing, head of the Tatmadaw, has established the State Administration Council to establish direct control of state affairs and has also imposed a curfew from 8 PM to 4 AM in all major cities.&amp;nbsp; On February 13, a shocking violation of the freedom of the press was noticed as the military administered Ministry of Information (MoI) exerted pressure upon the press to delete the phrases “junta” and “regime” to describe the coup. The recent military order involves facing 20 years of prison if an individual is found encroaching on the work of the security forces. This order also bestows the power to make arrests, carry out searches and even detain individuals for a period of more than 24 hours without trial or right to proper judicial recourse. Looking Deeper&amp;nbsp; The military had carried out their first coup d'etat against a civilian government in 1962. But the present action may be studied in the context of the time in which it has occurred. This week was to witness the first session of the parliament in which the new democratically elected government would have been officially anointed to power. It is noteworthy that more than 70% of the voters had challenged the pandemic scenario to vote and elect Suu Kyi. This is particularly noteworthy considering the flak that she had been receiving for the genocide against the Rohingyas. Public resentment against the military government is thus inevitable. The primary opposition levelled by the military is that the election was marked by fraud, blaming the UEC (Union Election commission) for voter list irregularities.&amp;nbsp; Sounds familiar? Trumpian? Gotcha.&amp;nbsp; And yes, there's no evidence to support the claim.&amp;nbsp; The business and financial interests of Min Aung Hlaing's family too have been a cause of contention. He oversees the twin military conglomerates: Myanmar Economic Corporation (MEC) and Myanma Economic Holdings Limited (MEHL) with his daughter, son and daughter-in-law holding substantial business interests in each. Moreover, a few days prior to the coup, the International Monetary Fund had released $350 million in cash to the Central Bank of Myanmar as a COVID-19 relief package. It didn't contain any clause for refund. The misuse of this fund seems to be a likelihood in the near future. The way ahead&amp;nbsp; The manufactured emergency holds little ground legally. The president can declare an emergency only after due consultation with the National Defence and Security Council. The military has proven itself to be enjoying a stature above that of the constitution. The military states that it would rule only for a year and then hold a fresh election. It doesn't require too much political clairvoyance to predict that such an election would be completely orchestrated by the military. The public perception regarding the military has indeed undergone a setback. Burmese Twitter account holders used #RespectOurVotes, #HearTheVoiceofMyanmar among others. Myo Ko Ko, a Burmese student activist articulates the anxiety as he says “We strongly believe in democracy and human rights. We know that it's risky.” The coup has elicited mixed reactions from the nation's diverse ethnic groups. While the Restoration Council of Shan State has strongly condemned the coup, the Kachin Independence Organisation with a large population has remained silent about it. The coup has attracted international reactions, including Jacinda Ardern severing New Zealand's diplomatic ties with Myanmar. The UN Security Council held an emergency meeting upholding the resolution of restoring democracy in Myanmar. The statement however couldn't garner the support of all the members, with permanent members China and Russia refusing to back it. The regional implications in South Asia are, however, muted, with nations including India resorting to soft tactics and not being vocal about the situation. The ASEAN nations continue to stick to their non-interference tactics. Meanwhile, the uncertainty persists amidst the three-finger salute in Myanmar. The gesture of defiance against the spectre that has returned back to haunt the nation, yet again. Democracy, the elusive D-word rests in agitation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Yemen: A Pawn in the Game of Middle Eastern Checkers?</title>
      <link href="/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yemen: A Pawn in the Game of Middle Eastern Checkers?" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers">&lt;p&gt;On December 31, 22 people were killed and 50 others injured in an attack at the Aden airport in South Yemen. The attack was directed at the Saudi-backed cabinet of the new Unity Government which had landed in the same airport at that time. A second explosion was reported from Aden's Maasheq presidential palace which housed the cabinet members including the Yemeni Prime Minister Maeen Abdulmalik and the Saudi ambassador to Yemen. The Yemeni government had been sworn in on December 26, 2020, days prior to the incident, comprising 24 ministers representing the major political powers of the nation including the Southern Transitional Council. The government placed the responsibility of the attack upon the Houthis. This even should not be interpreted in isolation but in the context of a diplomatic and military crisis that goes back years into the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yemen's Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roots of the long-drawn conflict can be traced back to the multi-sided war between the Abrabbuh Mansur Hadi led Yemeni government in the South and the Houthi rebels who have seized control of Northern Yemen including the capital city of Sana'a, adjoining the Saudi border. The civil war started in 2014 and is largely attributed to the religious angle. The Zaidis, a sect of Shias, faced discrimination during the rule of Muhammad al-Shawkani, who propounded Sunnification as the means to consolidate a unified Yemen. This was in defiance to Zaidi Shi'ism. The Houthis trace their ancestry from a Zaidi group located at the Sa'dah governorate on the Northern borders of Yemen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of the Houthi rebellion was seen in 2004, when Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi, a former member of the Yemeni Parliament was killed by government military forces following his protests against governmental regulations. The political situation escalated following the 2011 Yemeni Revolution of Dignity, an offshoot of the broader Arab Spring revolution. Abdul- Malik al-Houthi supported the rebel organisations' demand for the resignation of the Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh and its siege of the Salafi village of Dammaj in Northern Yemen, boycotting the 2012 single-candidate elections aimed at making Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi the President of Yemen (a post which he still holds).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2014, the Sunni-Houthi conflict engulfed the rest of Yemen including the Sana'a Governorate by August 2014. The civil war was marked by several military milestones including the Battle of Taiz, at Yemen's third-largest city. The Houthis employed a Tochka missile (ballistic) against the Saudi-led coalition. At the battle of Aden in 2015, Hadi escaped to Riyadh, seeking assistance from Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman Al Saud, the Saudi heir apparent. The war no longer remained confined within Yemeni borders and was immediately internationalised. A Saudi-led coalition including UAE attempted at restoring the previous Yemeni Government. Sudanese and Egyptian troops had also cooperated against the Houthi advances. Amidst a geopolitical crisis, the ISIS too had been actively involved, conducting a series of suicide bombings that resulted in the death of 15 soldiers affiliated with the Saudi coalition. They, however, didn't side with the Houthi rebels either - exhorting their followers to kill the Zaidis as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the Saudi led coalition launched a major offensive mission to regain control of the city of Hudaydah, adjoining the Red Sea, in spite of warnings by the UN that the port's destruction would serve as a “crossing of Rubicon” moment. Basically, it was a point of no return as it would be impossible to avert massive loss of life due to the famine conditions that would ensue due to the disastrous effects on the shipping of food supplies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;In August 2019, there was a rift in Southern Yemen between the government forces backed by the Saudi government and the Southern Transitional Council (STC) which enjoyed UAE support. Following the failure of the Kuwait initiative seeking a political solution, the 2019 Riyadh agreement was brokered as a power-sharing deal between the Yemeni government and the Southern separatists aimed at transcending this difference between the friends turned foes. However, the conflict resumed on January 7, 2020, when the Houthi rebels shot down a Saudi coalition drone at Jawf.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the COVID-19 outbreak, an air raid ceasefire had been declared while 10,000 people had been displaced, and 13 million civilians denied access to clean and safe drinking water. Yemen had previously faced a cholera epidemic in 2017 affecting 20 out of the 22 Yemeni provinces. As of July 2020, the UNHCR estimated that 3.6 million people had been displaced and 24 million await urgent aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geopolitical ramifications&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The civil war has been at the heart of a much larger international political equation. Despite the fact that United States spokesperson Bernadette Meehan has openly stated: “&lt;em&gt;It remains our assessment that Iran does not exert command and control over the Houthis in Yemen”,&lt;/em&gt; many have viewed this as a larger Iranian proxy war. Iran and Yemen are composed of Shia Islamist, albeit with minor differences - the Iranians are followers of the Twelve Imam Shias while the Houthis are Zaidi Shias. This is in contrast to the Saudi Arabia-led coalition that largely comprises Sunni-majority nations. Ali Khamenei has even explicitly stated that he shall provide “spiritual support&quot; to the movement of the Houthis in 2019. Eritrea too has been accused of providing Iranian ammunition to the Houthis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni government on the other hand has received military as well as financial aid from the United States, which conducted drone strikes in Sana’a aiming to neutralise Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP). Reports published by Amnesty International in 2019 also indicate logistical assistance from the UK in the form of laser-guided bombs and other weaponry. Interestingly, the US Arms Export Control Act was believed to have been violated by the United States Department while ratifying arms sales to the Gulf states of Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates in August 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The launch of the ballistic missile by Houthis aimed at Saudi Arabia in 2017 led to a further strengthening of the Yemen blockade by the Saudi coalition under the pretext of preventing weapon smuggling by Iranian rebels, an accusation Tehran vehemently denies. In hindsight, this led to a hike in the price of food and fuel, adding a food security dimension to the military conflict.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yemen continues to suffer from the world's worst humanitarian crisis. The crisis is not only a concern to the Middle Eastern neighbours of Yemen but fuels the threat perception pertaining to that of the West's War on Terror against terrorism at large, particularly Al-Qaeda and ISIS. Yemen enjoys superior strategic significance, located as it is geographically on the strait linking the Red Sea with the Gulf of Aden which constitutes the zone from which most of the world's oil cargo travels. Many had blamed Saudi Arabia for its lack of security provisions on the day of the Aden airport blast, yet this might be considered as the tip of the iceberg of a deep-seated problem concerning the 'unity government.' What needs to be understood is that in more ways than one, Yemen has become a pawn in the clutches of the broader strategic dynamics of the Arab world and Uncle Sam’s War on Terror.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On December 31, 22 people were killed and 50 others injured in an attack at the Aden airport in South Yemen. The attack was directed at the Saudi-backed cabinet of the new Unity Government which had landed in the same airport at that time. A second explosion was reported from Aden's Maasheq presidential palace which housed the cabinet members including the Yemeni Prime Minister Maeen Abdulmalik and the Saudi ambassador to Yemen. The Yemeni government had been sworn in on December 26, 2020, days prior to the incident, comprising 24 ministers representing the major political powers of the nation including the Southern Transitional Council. The government placed the responsibility of the attack upon the Houthis. This even should not be interpreted in isolation but in the context of a diplomatic and military crisis that goes back years into the past. Yemen's Civil War The roots of the long-drawn conflict can be traced back to the multi-sided war between the Abrabbuh Mansur Hadi led Yemeni government in the South and the Houthi rebels who have seized control of Northern Yemen including the capital city of Sana'a, adjoining the Saudi border. The civil war started in 2014 and is largely attributed to the religious angle. The Zaidis, a sect of Shias, faced discrimination during the rule of Muhammad al-Shawkani, who propounded Sunnification as the means to consolidate a unified Yemen. This was in defiance to Zaidi Shi'ism. The Houthis trace their ancestry from a Zaidi group located at the Sa'dah governorate on the Northern borders of Yemen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The first of the Houthi rebellion was seen in 2004, when Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi, a former member of the Yemeni Parliament was killed by government military forces following his protests against governmental regulations. The political situation escalated following the 2011 Yemeni Revolution of Dignity, an offshoot of the broader Arab Spring revolution. Abdul- Malik al-Houthi supported the rebel organisations' demand for the resignation of the Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh and its siege of the Salafi village of Dammaj in Northern Yemen, boycotting the 2012 single-candidate elections aimed at making Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi the President of Yemen (a post which he still holds). By 2014, the Sunni-Houthi conflict engulfed the rest of Yemen including the Sana'a Governorate by August 2014. The civil war was marked by several military milestones including the Battle of Taiz, at Yemen's third-largest city. The Houthis employed a Tochka missile (ballistic) against the Saudi-led coalition. At the battle of Aden in 2015, Hadi escaped to Riyadh, seeking assistance from Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman Al Saud, the Saudi heir apparent. The war no longer remained confined within Yemeni borders and was immediately internationalised. A Saudi-led coalition including UAE attempted at restoring the previous Yemeni Government. Sudanese and Egyptian troops had also cooperated against the Houthi advances. Amidst a geopolitical crisis, the ISIS too had been actively involved, conducting a series of suicide bombings that resulted in the death of 15 soldiers affiliated with the Saudi coalition. They, however, didn't side with the Houthi rebels either - exhorting their followers to kill the Zaidis as well.&amp;nbsp; In 2018, the Saudi led coalition launched a major offensive mission to regain control of the city of Hudaydah, adjoining the Red Sea, in spite of warnings by the UN that the port's destruction would serve as a “crossing of Rubicon” moment. Basically, it was a point of no return as it would be impossible to avert massive loss of life due to the famine conditions that would ensue due to the disastrous effects on the shipping of food supplies.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;In August 2019, there was a rift in Southern Yemen between the government forces backed by the Saudi government and the Southern Transitional Council (STC) which enjoyed UAE support. Following the failure of the Kuwait initiative seeking a political solution, the 2019 Riyadh agreement was brokered as a power-sharing deal between the Yemeni government and the Southern separatists aimed at transcending this difference between the friends turned foes. However, the conflict resumed on January 7, 2020, when the Houthi rebels shot down a Saudi coalition drone at Jawf.&amp;nbsp; Following the COVID-19 outbreak, an air raid ceasefire had been declared while 10,000 people had been displaced, and 13 million civilians denied access to clean and safe drinking water. Yemen had previously faced a cholera epidemic in 2017 affecting 20 out of the 22 Yemeni provinces. As of July 2020, the UNHCR estimated that 3.6 million people had been displaced and 24 million await urgent aid. Geopolitical ramifications&amp;nbsp; The civil war has been at the heart of a much larger international political equation. Despite the fact that United States spokesperson Bernadette Meehan has openly stated: “It remains our assessment that Iran does not exert command and control over the Houthis in Yemen”, many have viewed this as a larger Iranian proxy war. Iran and Yemen are composed of Shia Islamist, albeit with minor differences - the Iranians are followers of the Twelve Imam Shias while the Houthis are Zaidi Shias. This is in contrast to the Saudi Arabia-led coalition that largely comprises Sunni-majority nations. Ali Khamenei has even explicitly stated that he shall provide “spiritual support&quot; to the movement of the Houthis in 2019. Eritrea too has been accused of providing Iranian ammunition to the Houthis.&amp;nbsp; The Yemeni government on the other hand has received military as well as financial aid from the United States, which conducted drone strikes in Sana’a aiming to neutralise Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP). Reports published by Amnesty International in 2019 also indicate logistical assistance from the UK in the form of laser-guided bombs and other weaponry. Interestingly, the US Arms Export Control Act was believed to have been violated by the United States Department while ratifying arms sales to the Gulf states of Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates in August 2020.&amp;nbsp; The launch of the ballistic missile by Houthis aimed at Saudi Arabia in 2017 led to a further strengthening of the Yemen blockade by the Saudi coalition under the pretext of preventing weapon smuggling by Iranian rebels, an accusation Tehran vehemently denies. In hindsight, this led to a hike in the price of food and fuel, adding a food security dimension to the military conflict.&amp;nbsp; The way forward Yemen continues to suffer from the world's worst humanitarian crisis. The crisis is not only a concern to the Middle Eastern neighbours of Yemen but fuels the threat perception pertaining to that of the West's War on Terror against terrorism at large, particularly Al-Qaeda and ISIS. Yemen enjoys superior strategic significance, located as it is geographically on the strait linking the Red Sea with the Gulf of Aden which constitutes the zone from which most of the world's oil cargo travels. Many had blamed Saudi Arabia for its lack of security provisions on the day of the Aden airport blast, yet this might be considered as the tip of the iceberg of a deep-seated problem concerning the 'unity government.' What needs to be understood is that in more ways than one, Yemen has become a pawn in the clutches of the broader strategic dynamics of the Arab world and Uncle Sam’s War on Terror.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Portrait of a Nation at War with Itself</title>
      <link href="/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portrait of a Nation at War with Itself" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;It has been like watching a train crash in slow motion.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Dino Mahtani, International Crisis Group, commenting upon the Ethiopian crisis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethiopia’s Federal Army is waging a war against the Tigray forces or more specifically the Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF). The grounds for this war lie in the accusation that the Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed &lt;em&gt;“has been trying to sideline.... and even criminalise”&lt;/em&gt; the TPLF. At the core of this predicament lies the nation of Eritrea, Ethiopia's northern neighbour sharing its border with the Tigray region. The Ethiopian Federal government has declared this unexpected war upon its Northern state which puts the stability of one of the world's most strategically important regions, Horn of Africa. This confrontation has prompted thousands of Ethiopians, who are no strangers to humanitarian disasters, to flee to Sudan in thousands. Axel Bisschop, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) representative in Sudan has estimated the figure to be at over 20,000 people, more than half of them constitute children. This might result in resource wars between the already existing refugees in Sudan and the newcomers. The ethnic groups are caught in the midst of a crossfire between the federal government aiming to secure a united Ethiopia and the Tigray rebels guarding their individual sovereignty. However, the culmination of the issues which has reached a tipping point is the outcome of a process and not a knee jerk reaction by the two ends of the spectrum. The roots of the present fragility are important to understand the reasons for the severity of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long Story Short&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The national governments of Ethiopia and Eritrea have been at loggerheads for decades. The fallouts included the Eritrean and Ethiopian War which began in May 1998 and ended in June 2000. The current Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad won the 2019 Nobel Peace Prize for successfully implementing the peace treaty between the two nations. The cause for the war may be understood as Eritrea breaking the international law and invading Eritrea and holding all the disputed territory and advancing into Eritrea. At the end of the war, the Eritrea-Ethiopia Boundary Commission, a UN body declared Badme, the disputed territory to Eritrean land. The internal dispute between the Federal government and the Tigrays which has pushed Africa's second most populous nation into the brink of a civil war too has its origins in the 1970’s. Tigray is located in the northernmost region of Ethiopia. Their total population is estimated to be at 110 million, constituting 6% of the Ethiopian population. They have been at the forefront of the struggle against the military dictatorship that ruled Ethiopia in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. The TPLF established itself as the leader of the coalition named as the Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) grasped power in the nation in 1991. A Tigrayan, Meles Zenawi, led Ethiopia in the years between 1991 and 2012. This period was marked by economic stability and regional prosperity in Northern Africa, albeit with a generous dose of repressing all political opposition. Abiy Ahmad, of the Oromo ethnicity, came to power riding on the tide of anti-government protests in 2018. Worst was yet to befall upon this community. Scores of Tigray’s were arrested in connection to corruption and security related crackdowns, removed from the positions of political authority. One of them was Getachew Asefa, who had evaded arrest and fled to Tigray, he continues to be a fugitive. This widened the gulf between the inhabitants of the Tigray region governed by TPLF and the federal government. This came after Abiy's proclamation that he aims at uniting the country by reducing the autonomy of the regional governments. It didn't sit well with the Tigray’s and invited resistance to this centralisation scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Current Military Offensive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abiy Ahmad dissolved the ruling coalition to form his new political party and has postponed the national elections which had been scheduled for August 2020 under the pretext of the coronavirus pandemic. However, in violation of the orders from Addis Ababa, Tigray held elections. This led to rapid deterioration of the status quo. Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad announced a military offensive after accusing the Tigrayan forces of attacking and seizing a military base in the regional capital of Mekelle on November 4, 2020. The Tigrayans have completely denied the accusation. Both governments now perceive each other as “illegitimate and unconstitutional”. In the first week of October, the Ethiopian federal government decided to sever ties with the Tigray region. The Upper house of Parliament voted to suspend budget aid to this region. The TPLF returned the “favour” by citing an article in the federal constitution that ensured “unconditional right to self-determination, including the right to secession”. The TPLF also resented the Prime Minister's “unprincipled” friendship with the Eritrean President Isais Afwerki as well as the 2018 peace agreement. It is no longer a domestic turmoil within the confines of Ethiopia as the current status of Badme remains unresolved, which is an improbability without the Ethiopian government’s cooperation in Tigray. The telecommunication network in Tigray has been cut, and airstrikes and ground offensives precede the involvement of constituencies of the neighbouring Amhara region. This raging battle involves the TPLF, who are often regarded as one of the best-armed forces led by experienced generals and hold the capacity to deflect equipment from the grip of the Northern Command. The paramilitary and a local militia are estimated to consist of about 250,000 troops. Abiy had plainly accused the Tigrayan leaders of committing “criminal hubris and intransigence”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is There a Civil War in Sight?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest update to spill out of the borders is that Abiy Ahmed had proclaimed on November 15, 2020, that his federal forces had captured another town in the northern Tigray region. This comes after two weeks of fighting. Alberta lies in the control of the federal government. The end of this bloody civil war, many observers predict, may result in the secession of a united Ethiopia. Considering that both sides are evenly matched, the increase in the involvement of&amp;nbsp; Ethiopia’s neighbours, regional partners, and international actors- an escalation would not be a surprise. Though the Eritrean Foreign Minister, Osman Saleh Mohammed had rejected claims of Eritrean involvement, terming the issue as an internal conflict. Concerns remain about the refugee influx into Sudan. The humanitarian concern can be justified when one studies the impact of the war upon the regional capital Mekelle, which houses half a million people. Power and water have been cut. 150,000 soldiers have been forcefully taken over or defected to the Tigrayan side. War crimes include the gruesome killing of hundreds of citizens- slashed by machetes in the town of Mai-Kendra on November 9, 2020. Sudan too has its own skeletons in the cupboard. The Sudanese government was responsible for the Darfur genocide in 2003, which in turn led to a forced displacement of 2.4 million Sudanese. Sudan too can be a perilous nation for the refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic hardships are on the rise, furthered by COVID-19. Banking services have halted thereby resulting in a lack of cash. A refugee from war-torn Ethiopia, with an uncertain future, has perhaps best articulated the tale of a nation at war with itself- “&lt;em&gt;We are in need of everything- food, fresh water, masks. Everything.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize a year before now stands at the risk of being remembered as a man who slashed civilians in his ardour to relinquish the ethnic dissenters. Irony much?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“It has been like watching a train crash in slow motion.&quot; -Dino Mahtani, International Crisis Group, commenting upon the Ethiopian crisis Ethiopia’s Federal Army is waging a war against the Tigray forces or more specifically the Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF). The grounds for this war lie in the accusation that the Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed “has been trying to sideline.... and even criminalise” the TPLF. At the core of this predicament lies the nation of Eritrea, Ethiopia's northern neighbour sharing its border with the Tigray region. The Ethiopian Federal government has declared this unexpected war upon its Northern state which puts the stability of one of the world's most strategically important regions, Horn of Africa. This confrontation has prompted thousands of Ethiopians, who are no strangers to humanitarian disasters, to flee to Sudan in thousands. Axel Bisschop, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) representative in Sudan has estimated the figure to be at over 20,000 people, more than half of them constitute children. This might result in resource wars between the already existing refugees in Sudan and the newcomers. The ethnic groups are caught in the midst of a crossfire between the federal government aiming to secure a united Ethiopia and the Tigray rebels guarding their individual sovereignty. However, the culmination of the issues which has reached a tipping point is the outcome of a process and not a knee jerk reaction by the two ends of the spectrum. The roots of the present fragility are important to understand the reasons for the severity of the crisis. Long Story Short The national governments of Ethiopia and Eritrea have been at loggerheads for decades. The fallouts included the Eritrean and Ethiopian War which began in May 1998 and ended in June 2000. The current Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad won the 2019 Nobel Peace Prize for successfully implementing the peace treaty between the two nations. The cause for the war may be understood as Eritrea breaking the international law and invading Eritrea and holding all the disputed territory and advancing into Eritrea. At the end of the war, the Eritrea-Ethiopia Boundary Commission, a UN body declared Badme, the disputed territory to Eritrean land. The internal dispute between the Federal government and the Tigrays which has pushed Africa's second most populous nation into the brink of a civil war too has its origins in the 1970’s. Tigray is located in the northernmost region of Ethiopia. Their total population is estimated to be at 110 million, constituting 6% of the Ethiopian population. They have been at the forefront of the struggle against the military dictatorship that ruled Ethiopia in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. The TPLF established itself as the leader of the coalition named as the Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) grasped power in the nation in 1991. A Tigrayan, Meles Zenawi, led Ethiopia in the years between 1991 and 2012. This period was marked by economic stability and regional prosperity in Northern Africa, albeit with a generous dose of repressing all political opposition. Abiy Ahmad, of the Oromo ethnicity, came to power riding on the tide of anti-government protests in 2018. Worst was yet to befall upon this community. Scores of Tigray’s were arrested in connection to corruption and security related crackdowns, removed from the positions of political authority. One of them was Getachew Asefa, who had evaded arrest and fled to Tigray, he continues to be a fugitive. This widened the gulf between the inhabitants of the Tigray region governed by TPLF and the federal government. This came after Abiy's proclamation that he aims at uniting the country by reducing the autonomy of the regional governments. It didn't sit well with the Tigray’s and invited resistance to this centralisation scheme. The Current Military Offensive Abiy Ahmad dissolved the ruling coalition to form his new political party and has postponed the national elections which had been scheduled for August 2020 under the pretext of the coronavirus pandemic. However, in violation of the orders from Addis Ababa, Tigray held elections. This led to rapid deterioration of the status quo. Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad announced a military offensive after accusing the Tigrayan forces of attacking and seizing a military base in the regional capital of Mekelle on November 4, 2020. The Tigrayans have completely denied the accusation. Both governments now perceive each other as “illegitimate and unconstitutional”. In the first week of October, the Ethiopian federal government decided to sever ties with the Tigray region. The Upper house of Parliament voted to suspend budget aid to this region. The TPLF returned the “favour” by citing an article in the federal constitution that ensured “unconditional right to self-determination, including the right to secession”. The TPLF also resented the Prime Minister's “unprincipled” friendship with the Eritrean President Isais Afwerki as well as the 2018 peace agreement. It is no longer a domestic turmoil within the confines of Ethiopia as the current status of Badme remains unresolved, which is an improbability without the Ethiopian government’s cooperation in Tigray. The telecommunication network in Tigray has been cut, and airstrikes and ground offensives precede the involvement of constituencies of the neighbouring Amhara region. This raging battle involves the TPLF, who are often regarded as one of the best-armed forces led by experienced generals and hold the capacity to deflect equipment from the grip of the Northern Command. The paramilitary and a local militia are estimated to consist of about 250,000 troops. Abiy had plainly accused the Tigrayan leaders of committing “criminal hubris and intransigence”. Is There a Civil War in Sight? The latest update to spill out of the borders is that Abiy Ahmed had proclaimed on November 15, 2020, that his federal forces had captured another town in the northern Tigray region. This comes after two weeks of fighting. Alberta lies in the control of the federal government. The end of this bloody civil war, many observers predict, may result in the secession of a united Ethiopia. Considering that both sides are evenly matched, the increase in the involvement of&amp;nbsp; Ethiopia’s neighbours, regional partners, and international actors- an escalation would not be a surprise. Though the Eritrean Foreign Minister, Osman Saleh Mohammed had rejected claims of Eritrean involvement, terming the issue as an internal conflict. Concerns remain about the refugee influx into Sudan. The humanitarian concern can be justified when one studies the impact of the war upon the regional capital Mekelle, which houses half a million people. Power and water have been cut. 150,000 soldiers have been forcefully taken over or defected to the Tigrayan side. War crimes include the gruesome killing of hundreds of citizens- slashed by machetes in the town of Mai-Kendra on November 9, 2020. Sudan too has its own skeletons in the cupboard. The Sudanese government was responsible for the Darfur genocide in 2003, which in turn led to a forced displacement of 2.4 million Sudanese. Sudan too can be a perilous nation for the refugees. Economic hardships are on the rise, furthered by COVID-19. Banking services have halted thereby resulting in a lack of cash. A refugee from war-torn Ethiopia, with an uncertain future, has perhaps best articulated the tale of a nation at war with itself- “We are in need of everything- food, fresh water, masks. Everything.” The man who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize a year before now stands at the risk of being remembered as a man who slashed civilians in his ardour to relinquish the ethnic dissenters. Irony much?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">US-Qatar F-35A Deal: A Bed of Diplomatic Nails</title>
      <link href="/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="US-Qatar F-35A Deal: A Bed of Diplomatic Nails" />
      <published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We are going to move ahead, we hope, with designating Qatar a major non-NATO ally&lt;/em&gt;.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Announced Timothy Lenderking, US Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Gulf Affairs, in a conference call on September 17, 2020. The US Secretary of State Mike Pompeo and the Qatar Foreign Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman Al Thani met at Washington DC bestowing the status of a non-NATO ally on Qatar. This means that Qatar will gain preferential access to US military equipment and technology, free surplus material, prioritised cooperation on training and expedited export processing. The other Arab Gulf states including Kuwait and Bahrain are among the 17 states which enjoy Major non-NATO ally (MNNA) status, besides hosting the US Navy's Fifth fleet. However, the US recognition of Qatar has sparked off a series of rows in the aftermath of Qatar's bitter relations with nations like Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Bahrain and Egypt since 2017. The US, which enjoys strong diplomatic relations with all the powerful Middle Eastern states has been viewing the rift as an attempt to thwart the Trump administration’s efforts to contain Iran. A new united Middle East led by the United States seems to be the game plan to rain on Iran's parade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Quartet Blockade against Qatar&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Qatar-Saudi Arabia diplomatic tensions, often referred to as the Second Arab Cold War, had been the result of a fallout between Qatar and Saudi Arabia who shared a severely antagonistic relationship since the beginning of the Arab Spring Revolution, which had created a power vacuum in the region. David S Cohen, the then Deputy Director of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), had famously called Qatar a safe haven for “&lt;em&gt;terrorist financiers to operate with impunity&lt;/em&gt;.” Qatar had been supportive of the revolutionary wave,&amp;nbsp; while Saudi Arabia had opposed it tooth and nail. The fight on grounds of soft power has also escalated between the two nations - Qatar's broadcaster Al Jazeera supported the Arab Spring, which was construed by Saudi Arabia as attempts to topple its monarchy. The Saudis had also been wary of Qatar's stable relationship with Iran, thus, framing the conflict with Qatar as a ramification of the Iran-Saudi proxy conflict - all stemming from Saudi Arabia’s trouble with the infiltration by Iran and Iran-backed militant groups into the Arab Spring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates and Egypt have been steadfastly opposing any action by Qatar and Turkey and their support of democratic, Islamist and Salafi extremist groups during the Syrian Civil War. Post the Saudi execution of Nimr al Nimr in 2016, which drew worldwide condemnation from human rights groups and international organisations, Qatar severed all diplomatic ties with Iran. During the Yemeni Civil War in 2011-12, both Qatar and Saudi Arabia fought side-by-side against the alleged Iran-backed Houthi militants. It is important to note that the undercurrents of this fight may be traced to an ambition to gain regional hegemony, thus, in spite of being members of the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) the animosities continue to exist, resurfacing now and then. All hell broke loose in June 2017, when Saudi Arabia, the UAE, Bahrain, Egypt, Maldives, Mauritania, Senegal, Djibouti, Comoros, Jordan, the Tobruk based Libyan government severed diplomatic relations with Qatar and blocked Qatar's sea routes and airspace. Saudi Arabia went a step further blocking the only land route Qatar shared with Iran. The reaction came as a prompt response to Al Jazeera allegedly airing negative information pertaining to it's fellow GCC nations and its policy of “going soft&quot; on Islamist terror groups by allowing terror financiers to operate freely within its borders. Ron Prosor, an Israeli diplomat went so far to regard it as “the Club Med for Terrorists.” Thus, is it no surprise that close proximity between Qatar and the US has been a cause of concern for the other GCC members which includes UAE and Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;US-Qatar ties down the Age&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Qatar and US deal of 2020 shouldn't be treated as a case in isolation, rather a culmination of mutually beneficial ties handed over from decades ago. Since 1992, Qatar has been instrumental in building military ties and currently plays host to the US Central Command's Forward Headquarters and the Combined Air Operations Centre. It also has the Al Udeid Air Base and the As Sayliyah Army Base, among which the former is the largest American airbase in the Middle East. In 2014, the US sold $11 billion worth of arms to Qatar which also included the AH 64 Apache attack helicopters, Javelin and Patriot defence systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signing of the $12 billion deal regarding the purchase of 36F-15 QA strike aircraft imported from the USA in 2017 may also be treated as a milestone in the bilateral relationship of the two nations. The governments of the United States and the State of Qatar held their third Strategic Dialogue on September 14 and 15, 2020. The United States and Qatar signed a Memorandum of Understanding on education, culture and sports in addition to a Statement of Intent (SoI) designating 2021 as the US-Qatar Year of Culture and an Announcement of Intent for Qatar to host an investment forum in the United States in 2021. Furthermore, the United States also recognised Qatar’s effective leadership to establish peace and reconciliation among contending factions in Somalia and Sudan. The two nations noted an increase in bilateral trade where US exports to Qatar increased by 39% between 2018 and 2019. The United States remains Qatar’s largest foreign direct investor and largest trading partner. The two nations had also discussed the $26 billion Foreign Military Sales program which continued to increase the capability and capacity of the Qatar Armed Forces. The progress in these areas will be reviewed at the Policy Working Group meeting in Washington DC in the first quarter of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2020 Deal: A Bed of Nails&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US intervention in this area was evident in September 2020, when David Schenker, the State Department’s top diplomat for the Middle East stated that the three-year-old blockade might be lifted within a span of “weeks”. Thus, Kuwait and the United States have made an attempt to mediate a rift which was acting as a stumbling block in Washington's aim of uniting the Middle East against Iran. Schenker said, “&lt;em&gt;These are two sides that are dug in... and yet there is a recognition that this is a distraction from Iran&lt;/em&gt;.” However achieving diplomatic victory is a far cry as the boycotting nations set 13 demands which include the closing of Al Jazeera Media Network, downgrading ties with Iran and cutting links with Turkish Brotherhood. However, the Israel factor plays an important cameo. The United States is considering selling F-35s to Qatar as a side deal to the US-brokered agreement between Israel and UAE dubbed as the Abraham Accord. Israel, which had previously signalled stiff opposition to a UAE-US deal, is bound to express similar sentiments towards the deal with Qatar. The Qatari and UAE F-35 deals have to take into consideration the decade-old US-Israel deal that states any US weapons sold to the region must not impair Israel's “qualitative military edge”, thereby ensuring that US weapons furnished to Israel are “superior in quality” in comparison to the ones sold to its neighbours. However, the fifth-generation fighter jet F-35A which is estimated to cost around $80 million has its fate hanging in the air, influenced by the potential havoc it could wreck and alter diplomatic relations in the oil-rich Middle East. Thus it remains imperative for the US to take into consideration the geopolitics in this area lest it becomes a diplomatic graveyard of its ambitions in this region.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We are going to move ahead, we hope, with designating Qatar a major non-NATO ally.”&amp;nbsp; Announced Timothy Lenderking, US Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Gulf Affairs, in a conference call on September 17, 2020. The US Secretary of State Mike Pompeo and the Qatar Foreign Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman Al Thani met at Washington DC bestowing the status of a non-NATO ally on Qatar. This means that Qatar will gain preferential access to US military equipment and technology, free surplus material, prioritised cooperation on training and expedited export processing. The other Arab Gulf states including Kuwait and Bahrain are among the 17 states which enjoy Major non-NATO ally (MNNA) status, besides hosting the US Navy's Fifth fleet. However, the US recognition of Qatar has sparked off a series of rows in the aftermath of Qatar's bitter relations with nations like Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Bahrain and Egypt since 2017. The US, which enjoys strong diplomatic relations with all the powerful Middle Eastern states has been viewing the rift as an attempt to thwart the Trump administration’s efforts to contain Iran. A new united Middle East led by the United States seems to be the game plan to rain on Iran's parade. The Quartet Blockade against Qatar&amp;nbsp; The Qatar-Saudi Arabia diplomatic tensions, often referred to as the Second Arab Cold War, had been the result of a fallout between Qatar and Saudi Arabia who shared a severely antagonistic relationship since the beginning of the Arab Spring Revolution, which had created a power vacuum in the region. David S Cohen, the then Deputy Director of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), had famously called Qatar a safe haven for “terrorist financiers to operate with impunity.” Qatar had been supportive of the revolutionary wave,&amp;nbsp; while Saudi Arabia had opposed it tooth and nail. The fight on grounds of soft power has also escalated between the two nations - Qatar's broadcaster Al Jazeera supported the Arab Spring, which was construed by Saudi Arabia as attempts to topple its monarchy. The Saudis had also been wary of Qatar's stable relationship with Iran, thus, framing the conflict with Qatar as a ramification of the Iran-Saudi proxy conflict - all stemming from Saudi Arabia’s trouble with the infiltration by Iran and Iran-backed militant groups into the Arab Spring.&amp;nbsp; Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates and Egypt have been steadfastly opposing any action by Qatar and Turkey and their support of democratic, Islamist and Salafi extremist groups during the Syrian Civil War. Post the Saudi execution of Nimr al Nimr in 2016, which drew worldwide condemnation from human rights groups and international organisations, Qatar severed all diplomatic ties with Iran. During the Yemeni Civil War in 2011-12, both Qatar and Saudi Arabia fought side-by-side against the alleged Iran-backed Houthi militants. It is important to note that the undercurrents of this fight may be traced to an ambition to gain regional hegemony, thus, in spite of being members of the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) the animosities continue to exist, resurfacing now and then. All hell broke loose in June 2017, when Saudi Arabia, the UAE, Bahrain, Egypt, Maldives, Mauritania, Senegal, Djibouti, Comoros, Jordan, the Tobruk based Libyan government severed diplomatic relations with Qatar and blocked Qatar's sea routes and airspace. Saudi Arabia went a step further blocking the only land route Qatar shared with Iran. The reaction came as a prompt response to Al Jazeera allegedly airing negative information pertaining to it's fellow GCC nations and its policy of “going soft&quot; on Islamist terror groups by allowing terror financiers to operate freely within its borders. Ron Prosor, an Israeli diplomat went so far to regard it as “the Club Med for Terrorists.” Thus, is it no surprise that close proximity between Qatar and the US has been a cause of concern for the other GCC members which includes UAE and Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp; US-Qatar ties down the Age The Qatar and US deal of 2020 shouldn't be treated as a case in isolation, rather a culmination of mutually beneficial ties handed over from decades ago. Since 1992, Qatar has been instrumental in building military ties and currently plays host to the US Central Command's Forward Headquarters and the Combined Air Operations Centre. It also has the Al Udeid Air Base and the As Sayliyah Army Base, among which the former is the largest American airbase in the Middle East. In 2014, the US sold $11 billion worth of arms to Qatar which also included the AH 64 Apache attack helicopters, Javelin and Patriot defence systems.&amp;nbsp; The signing of the $12 billion deal regarding the purchase of 36F-15 QA strike aircraft imported from the USA in 2017 may also be treated as a milestone in the bilateral relationship of the two nations. The governments of the United States and the State of Qatar held their third Strategic Dialogue on September 14 and 15, 2020. The United States and Qatar signed a Memorandum of Understanding on education, culture and sports in addition to a Statement of Intent (SoI) designating 2021 as the US-Qatar Year of Culture and an Announcement of Intent for Qatar to host an investment forum in the United States in 2021. Furthermore, the United States also recognised Qatar’s effective leadership to establish peace and reconciliation among contending factions in Somalia and Sudan. The two nations noted an increase in bilateral trade where US exports to Qatar increased by 39% between 2018 and 2019. The United States remains Qatar’s largest foreign direct investor and largest trading partner. The two nations had also discussed the $26 billion Foreign Military Sales program which continued to increase the capability and capacity of the Qatar Armed Forces. The progress in these areas will be reviewed at the Policy Working Group meeting in Washington DC in the first quarter of 2021. The 2020 Deal: A Bed of Nails The US intervention in this area was evident in September 2020, when David Schenker, the State Department’s top diplomat for the Middle East stated that the three-year-old blockade might be lifted within a span of “weeks”. Thus, Kuwait and the United States have made an attempt to mediate a rift which was acting as a stumbling block in Washington's aim of uniting the Middle East against Iran. Schenker said, “These are two sides that are dug in... and yet there is a recognition that this is a distraction from Iran.” However achieving diplomatic victory is a far cry as the boycotting nations set 13 demands which include the closing of Al Jazeera Media Network, downgrading ties with Iran and cutting links with Turkish Brotherhood. However, the Israel factor plays an important cameo. The United States is considering selling F-35s to Qatar as a side deal to the US-brokered agreement between Israel and UAE dubbed as the Abraham Accord. Israel, which had previously signalled stiff opposition to a UAE-US deal, is bound to express similar sentiments towards the deal with Qatar. The Qatari and UAE F-35 deals have to take into consideration the decade-old US-Israel deal that states any US weapons sold to the region must not impair Israel's “qualitative military edge”, thereby ensuring that US weapons furnished to Israel are “superior in quality” in comparison to the ones sold to its neighbours. However, the fifth-generation fighter jet F-35A which is estimated to cost around $80 million has its fate hanging in the air, influenced by the potential havoc it could wreck and alter diplomatic relations in the oil-rich Middle East. Thus it remains imperative for the US to take into consideration the geopolitics in this area lest it becomes a diplomatic graveyard of its ambitions in this region.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Treat for the Corporate Sharks or Autonomy in Indian Agriculture?</title>
      <link href="/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Treat for the Corporate Sharks or Autonomy in Indian Agriculture?" />
      <published>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Farmer’s bills will create a vacuum that may result in utter chaos.”&lt;/em&gt; - P Sainath, Founder of People’s Archive of Rural India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest source of livelihood in India is agriculture. A whopping 70% of the rural households consider agriculture to be the primary source of their subsistence. Among them, 82% of farmers are engaged as small or marginal agriculturists. An economy which is majorly dependent on farmlands has witnessed unprecedented upheaval in the wake of the passing of the Farmers Bill 2020. Perhaps even more surprising is the polarised public opinion pertaining to it. While it has been welcomed by certain sections of the public, others have expressed stiff opposition to it. The displeasure wasn’t just restricted to the contents of the bill but also to the manner in which it was passed. Many regard it as a move towards a unitarian bias of the Indian State and a blow to federalism. The Minister of Food Processing Industries in the Narendra Modi Government, Harsimrat Kaur Badal, resigned from the Union Cabinet as a mark of protest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the Farmers Bill 2020?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It refers to a collection of three bills dealing with agriculture market reforms that have been passed in mid-September 2020. These draft laws aim to change the existing procedures laid down for the sale, marketing and storage of agricultural produce across the nation. They were passed by voice vote in both the houses of the Indian Parliament - Lok Sabha (the lower house) and the Rajya Sabha (the upper house), during the monsoon session, much to the chagrin of the opposition. The first bill termed as ‘The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill 2020’ allows the farmer to sell his or her produce outside the allotted Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; (marketplace) without having to pay any State taxes. The second bill ‘Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement on Price Assurance and Farm Services Ordinance 2020’ assists in the method of contract farming and empowers the farmer to pursue direct marketing. The final bill ‘The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Ordinance 2020’ ensures the deregulation of the production, storage, movement and the sale of essential food crops such as cereals, pulses, edible oils and onion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Ayes v/s the Nays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones supporting this measure argue that it ensures a greater autonomy of the farmers in terms of the sellers dismantling the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; system (agricultural market system). The government believes that this will invite private sector investments and help in the building of infrastructure and supply chains for agricultural harvest in both national and global markets. Further, it might assist small farmers who may not be in a position to negotiate a bargain or invest in superior technology to improve the quality of their harvest. Moreover, farmers are expected to sell their produce at a better price than the fixed price they have to sell at an APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt;. Market competition and cost-cutting on transportation may facilitate greater profits. The private investments are likely to help in fetching better technological support that a marginal farmer may not have been able to afford prior to the process of privatisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones opposing the bill including regional/national opposition parties such as Indian National Congress and All India Trinamool Congress (TMC) have highlighted the cons and believe it has the power to reverse the benefits bestowed by the Indian Green Revolution of the 1960’s. They have been interestingly opposing the bill on the same ground that the government seeks to promote it - “the interests of small and marginal farmers”. They believe that the farmer may not be able to choose his seller due to the lack of knowledge of negotiation if &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; were rendered redundant, the lack of bargaining power of the farmer when compared with corporate giants might force him to sell his harvest at a far lesser price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their biggest concern stems from the farmers being deprived of the minimum support price (MSP). MSP is a pre-set rate at which the Central Government purchases certain crops such as paddy, wheat and select pulses from the farmers, irrespective of the market rate. These predetermined rates are usually declared at the beginning of each sowing season for the 23 crops which fall under this list. The fact that the Anti-Farmers Bill Protests have been most fervent in Punjab and Haryana may be due to the fact that most government procurement centres are located within the notified APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. Farmers are wary of the fact that encouraging tax-free private trade will lead to a slow and natural demise of the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; thereby leading to a reduction of government procurement. Instead, the farmers demand a universalisation of the minimum support price which will compel the government as well as private players to incorporate these rates as a floor price. There has also been a general concern about the fate of the middlemen as their role in the chain has been rendered obsolete under the new laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The APMC structure consists of two parts - a strong market network where farmers have been selling their produce for decades and have established a familiarity among themselves, a connection between commission agents (known as &lt;em&gt;arthiyas&lt;/em&gt;) who further the cause of procurements. These two antagonistic structures are connected by roads which run from the villages to the notified APMC markets. Most of the private buyers are small traders at local &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; - they face an uncertain financial future as farmers will be directly selling their produce to corporates and industrialists, and the small traders might financially not be in a position to compete with the bigwigs. This is furthered by the provisions of the Essential Commodities Act which removes the ceiling on stock limits thereby allowing bulk purchase and storage - a treat for the corporate players. Thus, the idea of the corporatisation of the agricultural sector has been a major point of hue and cry across the nation. Monopolisation of agriculture where the business houses may attempt to minimise costs would vitiate the farmers’ interests. There has been a concern about growing input costs which the farmers had to bear - trampled between rising expenditure that cultivation demands and the sluggish prices on the other hand. Moreover, the hoarding of the harvest can prompt the industrialists to create artificial shortages and sell the produce later at an exorbitant price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Political Angle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a greater political angle to this debate centering around the question of a gradual smothering of federalism. Out of the three lists in the Seventh Schedule of the Indian Constitution - Union, State and Concurrent lists, agriculture falls under the State list. The State Governments’ believe that it doesn’t lie within the ambit of the Central Government’s authority to legislate upon a subject beyond its jurisdiction. As per this case of &lt;em&gt;Union of India v HS Dhillon&lt;/em&gt; (1972), the constitutionality of parliamentary laws may be challenged on two grounds - first, the subject is in the State list and second, it violates fundamental rights. The state’s loss of revenue from &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; taxes which used to enter the state treasury ranged from being as high as 8.5% in Punjab to being as low as 1% in some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the bill was passed by the Chair in Rajya Sabha, where states are represented, on the basis of a voice vote, refusing to consider repeated demands by the members for a division vote on the statutory resolution. Motions moved by certain left-wing parties to refer the bills to the select standing committees were also rejected. Thus, a violation of the federal principle upon which the very idea of Indian polity is established seemed to have received a jolt. The State Governments of Kerala and Punjab have declared that they shall challenge the bill in the Indian Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission Agent’s market fee and rural development fee are 3% and 2% in Punjab and Haryana respectively. For these states, which are the epicentre of these protests, the biggest sources of state revenue are these additional fees. Thus, financial subordination of the state governments seems like a bitter compromise on their part. These two states estimate a loss of ₹35 billion and ₹16 billion annually, respectively. However, similar to the concept of separation of powers and constitutionalism, the word federalism is not explicitly mentioned in the Indian Constitution. But it is a convention enmeshed in the essence of our constitutional scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is probably wise to look into the prevalent frameworks in some other nations all across the globe. The French dairy producers and the dairy farmers co-operatives in the United States have gained power over the years. A number of buyer cartels fix the price and this has forced the European Union and the US to introspect at the existing mechanisms of their own supply chains and to reduce their consolidative powers. Many believe that corporations may target the grain market as there are more than 90 million tons of food grain in Indian stocks and this might be a lucrative option for big money players. Under the Second Bill which permits contract farming, farmers will produce crops as per contracts with corporate investors for a mutually agreed remuneration. Farmers remain extremely sceptical, with very justifiable reasons, about the Farmers Bill 2020 which has received the assent of Indian President Ram Nath Kovind in late September. This has been largely dubbed as a ‘death warrant’ for poor farmers against the Prime Minister’s declaration of the bills as a ‘watershed moment’ for the Indian Agricultural Community. It remains to be seen whether the trio of bills is a boon or a bane, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Farmer’s bills will create a vacuum that may result in utter chaos.” - P Sainath, Founder of People’s Archive of Rural India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution</title>
      <link href="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important debates raging in American society and polity for decades has been the issue of Gun Control. The nature of the resultant deaths has varied from 21,175 suicides, 11,208 homicides, and 505 deaths due to accidental or negligent discharge of a firearm used with “undetermined intent”. These statistics signify a deep-rooted problem plaguing the question of ownership and control of a gun. A genuine question may arise as to whether this problem is individually only affecting the United States. Seems like it is indeed a cause of concern as compared to 22 other high-income nations, the US Gun-related homicide rate is 25 times higher. Among them, the phenomenon of ‘school shootings’, leading to students preparing for active shooter drills, is huddling in silence as if hiding from an imaginary gunman is a regular phenomenon. This has also been responsible for eleven assassination attempts on the US Presidents, with four “successful” encounters. These heinous incidents have a racist undertone also as research indicates that African Americans, who were only 13% of the US population, were 55% of the victims of gun homicide. Surprisingly, the roots of this problem can be located in the US Constitution itself. The arguments gain a fresh lease of life before every Presidential election with the Democrats demanding stricter gun laws and the Republicans pointing to the Second Amendment and self-defence shooting. President Donald Trump had said that he favoured background checks in the days immediately following shootings in El Paso and Dayton, however, Republican majority opinion regards gun control as a dangerous infringement of personal liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Locating the Origin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the root of this controversy, one needs to travel back in time to the ratification of the Second Amendment to the US Constitution ratified on December 15, 1791. It states “&lt;em&gt;A well-regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep or bear arms, shall not be infringed&lt;/em&gt;.” It is the wording of this very statement from which most of the controversy has been generated. While a section of Americans believes that the phrase “the right of the people to keep and bear Arms” aligns with the individualist notion, they think that any legislative body prohibiting firearm possession is unconstitutional. On the other hand, the opposition believes in the “Collective Rights Theory” which states that citizens do not have an individual right to possess guns and that local, state, and federal legislative bodies possess the authority to regulate firearms without the infringement of a constitutional right. Most US Courts had until the early 21st century understood it to guarantee the right of states to maintain militias or the right of individuals to keep or bear arms. However, this was to be strictly in connection with their service in a state militia, an interpretation that was consistent with a wide variety of existing restrictions on individual gun ownership and use. The 1939 judgment in the case of &lt;em&gt;United States v Miller&lt;/em&gt; too spoke in the same tune. The US Supreme Court held that the Second Amendment didn’t prohibit laws requiring the registration of sawed-off guns under the clause “reasonable relationship to the preservation or efficiency of a well-regulated militia”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2008 &lt;em&gt;District of Columbia v Heller&lt;/em&gt; judgment is considered to be a landmark. The plaintiff in &lt;em&gt;Heller&lt;/em&gt; had challenged the constitutionality of the Washington DC handgun ban. In a turn of events that shook global consciousness, the court delivered a 5-4 decision reiterating the history of the Second Amendment establishing an individual right for US Citizens to possess firearms and struck down the DC handgun ban as a violation of that right. It additionally stated that the Court would not disallow regulations prohibiting criminals and the mentally ill from firearm possession. In the 2010 decision of &lt;em&gt;McDonald v The City of Chicago&lt;/em&gt;, the plaintiff challenged the constitutionality of the Chicago Handgun ban which prohibited handgun possessions by almost all private citizens. The Court held that this interpretation of the Amendment was applicable against state and local gun control laws as well as against federal statutes. Thus, one can trace how over the course of time, gun control laws have undergone a complete transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Current American Scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common argument in favour of the unregulated possession of firearms includes the idea that law-abiding citizens can defend themselves against armed criminals. After the mass shootings at a Walmart Store in El Paso, Texas which left 20 individuals dead, there was a marked change in the attitude of young Americans towards Gun Control. A study conducted by Pew Research Centre in 2019, after the Parkland School Shooting in 2018, said that support for gun control was the highest among 18 to 29-year-olds. These findings further suggest that one-third of over 50s admitted to owning a gun. The rate of gun ownership was lower for younger adults at 28%. The Las Vegas attack in 2017 is regarded as one of the deadliest in American history marked by the death of 58 individuals. One of the reasons for these mass shootings can be attributed to the cheap prices at which firearms are available all over the US. The handguns used by Stephen Paddock, the Las Vegas shooter, were priced at $200 while assault rifles come at a price of $1500. Some states have taken measures to lessen this social menace. One such example is California which has banned around 75 types and models of assault weapons. There is a divide among the Republicans and the Democrats on the issue of “concealed carry policy”. This refers to the idea of whether allowing ordinary citizens increased rights to carry concealed weapons. One of the most stringent oppositions to gun control comes from the National Rifle Association (NRA), a very powerful interest group in the US. Interestingly, these groups also possess a substantial budget to influence members of Congress on gun policy. A significant Republican section in the United States is reported to be members of the NRA. This corroborates with NRA’s spending going uphill- from $3 million per year to more than $5 million in 2017. The NRA also supports the election campaigns of political candidates who oppose gun controls. They propagate against all forms of gun control arguing that more guns make the country safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gun Control laws are expected to reduce the societal costs associated with gun violence. More than 100,000 people are shot in the United States every year, and they generate emergency room and hospital charges of nearly $3 billion. Barack Obama in response to the January 2013 Sandy Hook Elementary School Shooting had announced a 4-parter for reducing gun violence: closing background check loopholes, banning assault weapons and large-capacity magazines, increasing access to mental services, and making schools safer. One of the important ideas behind gun safety laws include conducting a thorough background check-up of the person to whom the gun is being sold. Individuals with mental health problems or criminal backgrounds shouldn’t be allowed to possess weapons. Only a dozen of the US’ 50 states require purchase permits (Federal Firearms License - FFL) for handguns. Of those states, only California, Connecticut and Hawaii require permits for the purchase of rifles and shotguns. However, there is a major loophole in the entire body of Gun Control law. According to the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (ATF), anyone can sell a gun without an FFL from their home, online, or even at a flea market or at a gun show as long as he or she is not conducting the sale as part of regular business activity. Thus, selling a firearm from his or her personal collection or gifting a gun is beyond the reach of the law. The baseline being, only those individuals whose “principal motive” is to obtain a profit via the sale will be bound to obtain an FFL. Thus children under the age of 18, a person with felony charges, and mentally ill individuals may also possess guns that were given to them by their parents as gifts. This corroborates with a 2017 survey conducted by Harvard University which estimates that one in every five transactions occurs without a proper background check. It is the need of the hour to amend the constitution with regard to the Second Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the US awaits its Presidential elections in 2020, the Biden-Trump clashes rise again on the issue of Gun Control, dividing opinions and voices for and against a gun-free America. It gains relevance as a burning issue as on September 2, 2020, two seventeen-year-olds were killed in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. This has become a malady with its tentacles spread across America.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO</title>
      <link href="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO" />
      <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”&lt;/em&gt;, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included &lt;em&gt;“And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”&lt;/em&gt;. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NATO was founded in 1949 with a total of 30 members. The members include nations from North America (Canada and the United States) and 28 of the European countries. Its military nature is profoundly indicated by Article 5 of the treaty which states that in the occurrence of an attack against any one of the member states, it shall be understood to have been an attack against all members. This ensures the assistance of all the other member nations against the common adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) formed what was known as the Warsaw Pact in 1955 that included the Eastern Bloc Socialist Republics of Central and Eastern Europe. It was a collective defence treaty created as a reaction to the integration of West Germany into NATO. After the end of the Cold War and consequent nullification of the Warsaw Pact, NATO added 14 more member nations – 10 of them included in the Warsaw Pact and 4 former Yugoslav Republics. Some of the important operations undertaken by NATO include the defence of Denmark and Norway during September 1952, Exercise Longstep in the Mediterranean sea, Exercise Campaign Reforger which was an annual exercise by NATO states during the Cold War, and Exercise Strikeback which was a naval exercise that took place over a ten-day period in September 1957. The Northern Wedding had been another significant naval military exercise aimed at examining NATOs ability to reinforce Europe militarily during the Cold War in 1978. The latest development arrived in the form of DEFENDER-Europe 20 which was a US-led multinational exercise which included NATO’s participation. Notably, it was the largest deployment of US-based forces to Europe in the last quarter of a century. It included the participation of 20,000 soldiers deployed directly from the US to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Aspersions on NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ascent of Donald Trump in US national politics birthed a characteristic nationalistic, isolationist tendency, popularly termed as the ‘America First Policy’. It has been manifested in his scathing takes on multilateral organisations which include the United Nations (UN), and more recently the World Health Organisation (WHO) in the background of the coronavirus pandemic. Thus it comes as no surprise that he had been a stringent opponent to the very fundamental notions that have contributed to the formation of NATO. The &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; had reported that President Trump had on more than one occasion expressed desires to pull the US out of NATO. There are three primary reasons for his efforts to distance the US from this treaty - nearly 70% of the total spending on defence by NATO governments is accounted for by the US. In terms of the US Gross Domestic Product (GDP), the US spent roughly 3.4% on defence in 2019, while the average in European NATO countries and Canada was 1.55%. Naturally, Trump considers NATO to be an extra drain upon the military budget. NATO is funded by a common funding arrangement determined by each country’s national income. NATO had stated that the civilian and military budget for 2019 was $1.84 billion, out of which the US was paying 22%, France and the UK paid around 10.5% and Germany about 14.76%. The other alliance members contributed for the rest. This had caused bilateral relations between the US and Germany to worsen, as Trump, while referring to the burden shouldered by the US criticised the Germans for being “delinquent” in their payment to NATO. Trump further stated that the US shall move 12,000 troops out of the country. Jens Stoltenberg, the NATO Secretary-General had stated, &lt;em&gt;“We have now agreed (on) a new formula for sharing costs. The US will pay less. Germany will pay more”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem lies in the fact that the US, being a global superpower, has military commitments around the world and is not restricted to the geographical area of Europe and North America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the US deploys tens of thousands of active-duty personnel in Europe including in Turkey. The US diplomatic commitments in Europe also include a missile defence system run by NATO members. This is designed to shield against potential long-range ballistic missile attacks from outside the continent. Thus, the active presence of both men and arms is required on the part of the US. For the US President, all these factors are more of a display of magnanimity than a tool of diplomatic leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is important to note that a Chicago Council Survey in 2014 said that 78% of the American public supports NATO, 66% believed that the US commitment to NATO should remain as it is, as opposed to 7% supporting the possibility of a withdrawal. Thus the question of whether it is time to ring the death knell of NATO has its fair share of nay-sayers and aye-sayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Consequences in a World without NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the possible dissolution of the 71-year-old organisation, there will be a risk of Russian aggression. Many diplomats believe that had the post-Soviet Baltic nations which did not join NATO would have already been occupied by Russian expansionist aims. In the absence of NATO, mutual security interests such as combating ISIS and other global defence attempts emanating from coalition operations would be severely jeopardised. NATO’s retirement has the possibility to exacerbate divisions within Europe, especially in a post-Brexit, weakened European Union. The disappearance of NATO might make America’s Asian partners side with a rising China. Moreover, it will greatly strengthen the Russian Federation, which will reclaim the East European states which were formerly a part of the USSR. The clear political gainers would be Russia and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the question remains: To be or not to be? Amer-Exit from NATO and the consequent dissolution of NATO? Or a fundamental rebuilding exercise is that shall salvage the organisation that has maintained relative stability in the trans-Atlantic region?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included “And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Whose Land Is It Anyway?: Charting The Kalapani Dispute and its Implications on Indo-Nepal Relations</title>
      <link href="/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Whose Land Is It Anyway?: Charting The Kalapani Dispute and its Implications on Indo-Nepal Relations" />
      <published>2020-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We are working to ensure territorial integrity, national sovereignty, and freedom of our people. The kings of Nepal lost our territory, but today we republicans are restoring it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announced by Pushpa Kamal Dahal Prachanda, the co-Chair of the Nepal Communist Party on June 13, 2020, amid loud applauses at the Pratinidhi Sabha (the Lower House of the Nepalese Parliament), the declaration comes at the occasion marking the passage of the Second Constitution Amendment Bill which ensures legitimacy to the updated political map of Nepal. It had been at the eye of a diplomatic storm for including Indian territory within the periphery of Nepalese borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian territory of Limpyadhura, Kalapani, the strategically vital Lipulekh pass, all located in the Pithoragarh district of the Indian state of Uttarakhand have been shown as parts of Nepalese territory. The Indian Ministry of External Affairs has regarded the bill as an encroachment into the sovereignty of the Indian territory as they refer to it as an “artificial enlargement” in an official statement. The bill, which was passed by the approval of 258 members present and voting, out of the total strength of 275 members, has strained the otherwise good bilateral ties between India and Nepal. The upper house of the Nepalese Parliament, the National Assembly had been unanimous in its support for the bill, with all 57 members present voting in its favour on June 18, 2020. The die had been cast when the bill providing for the inclusion of Nepal’s new political map had been approved in its national emblem. The final move has sparked fierce criticism on a “sensitive issue”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The origins of the row&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that this diplomatic uncertainty was birthed through a 200-year-old treaty, the Treaty of Sugauli, that had formally established the boundaries of Nepal. The treaty had been signed on December 2, 1815, between the East India Company and Rajguru Gararaj Mishra with Chandra Sekhar Upadhyaya in the aftermath of the Anglo-Nepalese War of 1814-16. The interpretation of the treaty has been one of the primary causes of the present conflict. According to the treaty, the Eastern side of the river Kali falls within Nepal’s territory while the Western bank lies in India. The trouble brews from a common misinterpretation as Nepal considers Limpiyadhura as the origin of river Kali, thereby forwarding the claim that Limpyadhura, Lipulekh and Kalapani belong to their dominion. The advocates of the Indian cause, on the other hand, state that the origin of river Kali is Kalapani, which is an area located within Indian borders. The two regions of Susta and Kalapani cover 40 km of the Indo-Nepal border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assets-api.kathmandupost.com/thumb.php?src=https://assets-cdn.kathmandupost.com/uploads/source/news/2020/opinion/Kali-map-for-Naresh.jpg&amp;amp;w=900&amp;amp;height=601&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/indianepalmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cartographic dispute had earlier raised its ugly head, when on November 2, 2019, the Indian government had put up a new political map of the nation, depicting the reorganisation of Jammu and Kashmir, with a vivid depiction of the disputed Kalapani region exactly as it had been before. There had been allegations by the Nepalese government that in spite of twin reminders for restarting a foreign secretary-level dialogue mechanism between the two nations, India had not agreed to fix a date for the bilateral talks. Many quarters have regarded it as a fallout of the Nepalese Prime Minister KP Sharma Oli’s proximity to China. The Nepal government had expressed demands to publish their own new map which aimed at incorporating the disputed sites in their own fold. Oli had dismissed such claims on November 16 in the face of contrary claims put forward by Padma Aryal, the Nepalese cabinet minister for land and poverty alleviation who asserted that Nepal would soon come out with a new map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to a shift in priorities of both governments in the face of health security challenges imposed by COVID-19, the matter had been erased from public memory. But it resurfaced with a May 8 tweet by the Indian Defence Minister Rajnath Singh. Singh had laid emphasis on his inauguration of the blacktop road to Lipulekh pass, which had been under construction for 8 years. The Nepalese government in Kathmandu claimed that 19 km of the said road extended to Lipulekh, which according to their claims had been a part of Nepalese territory. It was seen as an attempt on the part of India to make an illegitimate claim on a nation’s territory, a violation of its absolute sovereignty. Populist rhetoric amplified the notion. The Chief of the Indian Army staff, M M Naravane (who is also the honorary General of the Nepal Army) went on to say that the Nepalese protests were being conducted under the behest of “another country” primarily indicating China. Nepalese Defence Minister Ishwor Pokhrel replied to this saying that the comments had been an “insulting statement”, resulting out of ignorance of Nepal’s history, freedom and social characteristics. He further made an allusion to the sentiments of Nepali Gurkha army personnel, a majority of whom are engaged in the Indian Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Diplomatic Ramifications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Nepali Parliament, Oli had reiterated the intention to reclaim the Indian territory, referring to it as being under the ‘occupation’ of the latter. However, his derogatory jibes at the Indian national emblem, manifesting in his controversial remark wondering if India subscribed to the physical aspect of the emblem - the Lion Capital of Ashoka - &lt;em&gt;“simhaev jayate’’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;“satyamev jayate”&lt;/em&gt; (truth alone prevails), led to a deepening of the diplomatic rife between the two otherwise conciliatory foreign policies pursued by the two nations. The issue had been in the priority list of the Nepalese Government ever since Oli’s second term in power began in 2018. New Delhi in spite of its repeated emphasis on the ‘Neighbourhood First’ policy had turned a blind eye. A dent in the mutual relationship between the two had begun to deepen since 2015 when Oli’s government had promulgated Nepal’s new Constitution, widely dubbed by India as flawed since it didn’t include the political aspirations of individuals from the Terai region - Madhesis and Tharus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The border blockade by the Madhesis that followed had allegedly received “Indian support”, according to Oli’s government. It is believed in diplomatic circles that although no evidence of Chinese connection or support has been found in the formulation of the border dispute, Oli is confident of Chinese support in further provoking India. Many believe this stance of his is a result of the turmoil in Nepal’s domestic policy. Oli may be trying to outdo his friend-turned-foe, Pushpa Kumar Dahal Prachanda, creating a scenario that might jeopardise a smooth diplomatic exchange with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need of the hour is to revive diplomatic channels between the two nations. Kalapani continues to be an important area of dispute due to the presence of an Indian military post present there. Kalapani has massive strategic importance to India as it shares a border on the North with the Tibet Autonomous Region of China, and Nepal in the East and South. It falls on the route to Mansarovar, a pilgrimage site in Tibet. It helps India in tracking Chinese movements in the region. The Lipulekh pass, on the other hand, had been an ancient route of trade and pilgrimage but had been temporarily closed following the Indo-China War of 1962. Options to ensure joint sovereignty can be taken as a way out, in times of such a major cartographic dispute. The idea of negotiation had been echoed in 1999, when the then Indian Prime Minister, I K Gujral had said &lt;em&gt;“If Nepal can prove Kalapani belongs to it, we will give it up”&lt;/em&gt;. However, the task of locating the source of a boundary river, coupled with a watershed, remains a Herculean task.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We are working to ensure territorial integrity, national sovereignty, and freedom of our people. The kings of Nepal lost our territory, but today we republicans are restoring it.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair: Afghanistan’s War Within</title>
      <link href="/Fair-is-Foul" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair: Afghanistan's War Within" />
      <published>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Fair-is-Foul</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fair-is-Foul">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When Daesh came to our area, they killed a lot of people because they said we would have helped the Taliban. But now the Taliban have returned and they are saying we helped the Daesh.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Masooma, resident of the Aqsa Area of Darzab (as stated in a &lt;em&gt;Reuters&lt;/em&gt; report)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masooma’s desperate predicament is a perfect one-liner to highlight the political chaos of present-day Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 12, 2020, a crowd of gunmen stormed the Doctors Without Borders (Médecins Sans Frontières) administered maternity clinic at Dashti Barchi, in the western part of the capital of Afghanistan, Kabul, leaving 24 people dead including two new-born babies. The attack drew condemnation from nations across the globe, with the Amnesty International South Asia, regarding them as “The unconscionable war crimes in Afghanistan targeting a maternity hospital and a funeral, must awaken the world to the horrors civilians continue to face.” ISIL (the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant) had claimed responsibility for the barbaric attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About two months prior to the attack on the hospital, on March 25, 2020, assassins raided the Gurdwara Har Rai Saheb in Kabul, Afghanistan killing 25 Sikh worshippers. ISIL subsequently stated its explicit support for the bloodbath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two subsequent events can be said to have been a part of the broader picture in the spectrum of Afghanistan’s war within its frontiers. These attacks are examples from the series of ongoing battles for supremacy between ISIL and the Taliban in their bid to exercise supremacy and dominance over the nation. Its significance is further highlighted as they come within months of the US-Taliban peace deal in February at Doha ending their 18-year long conflict, the roots of which can be traced back to the immediate aftermath of 9/11 and the global war on terror. However, the deal came with a resounding foreboding by the US President Donald Trump, who announced that “If bad things happen, we will go back with a force like no one’s ever seen”. Mike Pompeo, US Secretary of State had made it clear to the militant group to “keep your [their] promises to cut ties with al-Qaeda”. It is interesting to note, a UN Assistance Mission in Afghanistan report (May 2020) had said that since the signing of the peace deal, civil casualties caused by the Afghan government and the Taliban-ISIL conflicts have escalated by more than a quarter when compared with the same month in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Background&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Taliban-ISIL conflict is a phrase used to denote an ongoing armed conflict between the factions of ISIL in Afghanistan, besides counting those within its ambit, groups affiliated with ISIL, and splintered factions of the Taliban, generally opposed to the primary power loci in the central Taliban organisational hierarchy. The conflict may have been said to have begun on November 11, 2015, when fighting began between assailants who were loyal to Akhtar Mansoor, the new Taliban leader, and Mullah Mansoor Dadullah, who exhibited a tilt in favour of the pro-ISIL faction. This fragment received enormous aid from ISIL, including arms and men from Chechnya and Uzbekistan. The turf war ended with the triumph of Mansoor’s faction over that of Dadullah. More than 100 lives on both sides were lost in Southern Afghanistan, as reported by the provincial director of security in Kabul’s Arghandab district. The next year was marked by Muhammad Rasul leading the ISIL faction against the Mansoor loyalists. However, the war escalated from the month of April in 2017 onwards and gained international attention, with the ISIL capturing drug dealers who had been reportedly selling opium in the Jowzjan province. The drug pedlars had alleged Taliban connections. The connections came to light, with the clashes erupting between groups of the Taliban and the ISIL faction to ensure the forcible release of the three drug dealers, who were paying 10 million Afghanis to the Taliban to clinch a deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May 24 marked the largest clash between the two hostile entities near the border shared between Afghanistan and Iran. It had been sparked off by an attack on the ISIL camp by the Taliban, who had agreed not to enter into armed struggle prior to mutual dialogue. An ISIL commander had reportedly told NBC News that the Taliban was entering into a coordinated alliance with the Iranian Military and receiving generous support from them. Fidai Mahaz, also known as the Sacrifice Front, led by Mullah Najibullah, a Taliban splinter group had been strongly opposed to the Taliban-Iran nexus, claiming that the Taliban had received $3 million in cash, 3,000 arms and 40 trucks and ammunition from the Iran government to wage a war against ISIL. The Iranian government implied that they were concerned about the steady gain of territory by ISIL and their increasing status in Afghanistan affected the regional security of Iran; 2018 marked by the Battle of Darzab, in which the Taliban and the Islamic State, in the Khorasan province, engaged in conflict for hegemony over the Darzab district in the Jowzjan province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the June talks between the Russian government and the Taliban, the US criticised the Russian position of extending support to the Taliban to defeat ISIL as they believed it granted legitimacy to the Taliban, discrediting the recognised Afghan government. The resultant fighting left 3,500-7,000 civilians homeless and thousands dead on either side. However, by early August, ISIL’s hold was reduced to two villages, with most ISIL fighters pleading for clemency and protection from the Afghan government against the Taliban. The US-Taliban negotiation in 2018 echoed the Taliban’s plea to end US airstrikes as well as to provide support to combat splinter groups and ISIL. Last year marked heavy clashes at Kunar, with ISIL circulating photos of weapons captured from the Taliban, followed by a video of the fighters renewing their oath to Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi criticising the prospect of US-Taliban peace talks. Further, on October 1, ISIL claimed to have killed 20 Taliban soldiers in Tora Bora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What lies ahead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deeper dig into the causes of conflict between ISIL and the Taliban go beyond the primary causes for the fight to secure more land in accordance with Dabiq, the Islamic State manifesto, since ideology and long term objectives between the two differ strongly. ISIL (or ISIS in the broader spectrum) aims at establishing an Islamic Caliphate worldwide, while the Taliban aims to secure an Islamic State, ruled by Quranic law or their own interpretation of the Shariat. Hence, there can be increasing speculation about the future of Afghanistan, post the US-Afghan peace talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US-Afghan peace deal may result in ironical consequences which might include an increase in the membership of ISIL, as a major chunk of the Taliban foot soldiers who would be dissatisfied with the peace negotiations might join ISIL. It might have a significant impact on the Southeast Asian nations too, with many nations including India eyeing the Taliban with suspicion as a terrorist group and refusing to engage in bilateral or multilateral talks with obvious specifics towards its stand on the Kashmir issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question lingers whether a civil war is imminent in Afghan soil in the decades to come if ISIL strengthens itself or if it is an improbability, or whether a war with obvious outcomes is going to ensue, now that US assistance may help the Taliban in their war against ISIL. The world meanwhile grapples with the timeless words of the three witches in &lt;em&gt;Macbeth&lt;/em&gt;, “Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair”, as US special envoy Zalmay Khalilzad defends the Taliban and their efforts to achieve “peace”, the same Taliban with whom they waged an 18-year long battle. So in diplomacy, fair or foul whichever you choose, (that is if you don’t consider them to be the two sides of the same coin), the great gamble for Afghanistan proceeds between ISIL, Taliban, and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“When Daesh came to our area, they killed a lot of people because they said we would have helped the Taliban. But now the Taliban have returned and they are saying we helped the Daesh.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India’s Tryst with Autocracy</title>
      <link href="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India's Tryst with Autocracy" />
      <published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence">&lt;p&gt;It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the declaration of a national emergency in mid-1975, in accordance with Article 352 of the Indian Constitution, Mrs Gandhi instigated the nation’s total suspension of fundamental rights and every outlet of democratic expression. The Indian Emergency refers to the 21-month period that continues to be recounted as one of the darkest chapters in the modern political historiography of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What led to the imposition of the Indian Emergency?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency shouldn’t be considered an overnight development, but rather a culmination of a significant number of factors. Throughout the end of the 1960’s and the early 1970’s, there had been a gradual rise in the predominance of Parliamentary Sovereignty in India over the judiciary. Besides this, the early 1970’s had been characterised by widespread political unrest. The Naxalbari movement in West Bengal had met with severe state oppression through ‘The Operation Steeplechase’ among other government measures, the Nav Nirman movement in Gujarat (December 1973 - March 1974) led to the imposition of Central Government-rule on the state under Article 356 of the Indian Constitution. Amidst the prevailing political turmoil, there had been widespread dissatisfaction against the agents of the ruling order, particularly the Union Ministers, who are in many ways the most direct representatives of the ruling regime. Lalit Narayan Mishra, the Union Rail Minister was killed by a bomb on January 3, 1975.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most significant political mobilisation took place in April 1974, when a student agitation by the Chatra Sangharsh Samiti (Student Agitation Organisation) led by the Gandhian Socialist Jayaprakash Narayan and his call for “total revolution” to sweep away corruption, gained mass popularity. A significant ramification of the JP movement had been the nationwide strike organised by the railway employees union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raj Narain verdict had been the final nail in the coffin of the Indira Gandhi government which had been in power since 1966, almost 10 years. Mrs Gandhi had defeated Raj Narain in the 1971 Parliamentary elections from the constituency of Rae Bareily. He had filed cases accusing the Prime Minister of election fraud and malpractice along with the use of state machinery for election purposes in the Allahabad High Court. On June 12, 1975, Mr Justice Jagmohan Lal Sinha found Mrs Gandhi guilty of the said charges. The Supreme Court upheld the verdict and ordered a steady withdrawal of all privileges that Mrs Gandhi had received as a member of the Indian Parliament whilst depriving her of the right to vote in the lower house. The following day Narain had organised a rally in Delhi where he had reportedly proclaimed that the instruments of the state machinery, particularly the police, must reject the orders of a government which were immoral, corrupt and unethical. Widely interpreted as an instigation to spark a rebellion, it led to Mrs Gandhi declaring the Emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency was marked by an absolute suspension of the Fundamental Rights mentioned in Part III of the Indian Constitution. Mrs Gandhi had devised a ‘25-point economic programme’ which aimed at, inter alia, poverty eradication, restructuring of the public services, boosting agricultural and industrial production. Mrs Gandhi’s heir apparent and a leader of the Indian National Congress, Sanjay Gandhi, had contributed to it with his own programme of literacy, family planning, planting of trees, literacy promotion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Emergency, the opposition leaders were placed under preventive detention including Jayaprakash Narayan, Charan Singh and Atal Vihari Vajpayee (later Indian Prime Minister in 1997), Lal Krishna Advani, Arun Jaitley, Gayatri Devi, Queen Mother of the erstwhile princely state of Jaipur, Morarji Desai (later 4th Prime Minister of India in 1977-1979). Some prominent leaders of the Indian National Congress including Chandra Sekhar, who had resigned from Mrs Gandhi’s cabinet, were arrested and placed under detention as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, the 42nd Amendment Act which had rewritten the Indian Constitution was also passed. The amendments so introduced sought to reduce the power of the Supreme Court and the High Courts all over the nation, and inserted the words ‘Socialist’ and ‘Secular’ to the preamble of the Constitution. Under this amendment act, the Indian Parliament was bestowed with unlimited, unrestrained power to amend each and every section of the Constitution without judicial review. Thus, the doctrine of separation of powers and the Indian federal structure was negated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forced sterilisation program, undertaken under the leadership of Sanjay Gandhi with the aim of family planning, led to 8.3 million sterilisations within the time frame of 1976-1977 according to &lt;em&gt;India’s Population Reality: Reconciling Change and Tradition&lt;/em&gt;. The primary accounts of the brutality are evident in The Sanjay Story by an eminent Indian political journalist when he recounts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hawa Singh, a widower from the village of Pipli had been taken from a bus against his will and sterilised. The infection that emanated from the vasectomy took his life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government used Doordarshan, the government-owned television network, for its own political propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Turkman Gate demolition and firing which took place on April 18, 1976, a fallout of the drive to clear slum areas in Delhi, resulted in indiscriminate firing and police brutalities, which the popular media wasn’t permitted to report. Unofficial accounts put the figure at 9 deaths from among the ones who resisted the usurpation and bulldozing of their settlements. Later, the Shah Commission report stated that 20 individuals had been killed. The censorship of the press had begun from the night of the declaration of the Emergency itself with the electric supply of Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg being cut off, within 3 hours of the announcement. Most of the publishing houses of newspapers and national magazines were located on the same street. A number of newspapers had published a blank page or a black space in its editorials as an attempt to convey that the news had been tampered with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 18, 1977, Mrs Gandhi called for fresh elections followed by the release of all political prisoners. The Indian Emergency ended on March 23, 1977. The Congress was routed in the General Elections with Janta Dal assuming power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is that one thing about Indira’s India of 1975, inhabited by my grandfather’s generation that resonates with a world so different from ours, 45 years later, in a post-privatisation, liberal democracy? Surprisingly the answer doesn’t take a minute longer to appear so clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amnesty International in 2015 had stated that there was a “total blackout of information” in the state of Chattisgarh. And today, a complete shutting down of information transmission from Kashmir has continued for more than 5 months with major leaders of the state being placed under preventive detention. The idea of placing government loyalists to moot out majority opposition parties from power in the states finds uncanny parallels: Gandhi dismissed the Ajoy Mukherjee-led government in West Bengal in 1969 while Modi used Governors as loyalists to deny the single-largest party to come to power in Manipur, Nagaland and Meghalaya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Gandhi’s Emergency declaration was approved by her Cabinet only after its imposition. Similarly, Modi’s implementation of the demonetisation was known only to a handful in the Cabinet prior to its formal declaration. Additionally, Modi’s appointment of Army Chief Bipin Rawat, superseding two senior officers is reminiscent of Gandhi’s appointment of Mr Justice A N Ray as Chief Justice of India by superseding three others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signs are clear and “those who do not learn from history are doomed to repeat it”. The Indian Emergency only grows in importance during our times to educate us on how a state can go from mere political upheaval to an authoritarian regime.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
