<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/oyeshi.ganguly/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-06T14:06:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/oyeshi.ganguly/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India’s Tryst with Autocracy</title>
      <link href="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India's Tryst with Autocracy" />
      <published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence">&lt;p&gt;It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the declaration of a national emergency in mid-1975, in accordance with Article 352 of the Indian Constitution, Mrs Gandhi instigated the nation’s total suspension of fundamental rights and every outlet of democratic expression. The Indian Emergency refers to the 21-month period that continues to be recounted as one of the darkest chapters in the modern political historiography of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What led to the imposition of the Indian Emergency?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency shouldn’t be considered an overnight development, but rather a culmination of a significant number of factors. Throughout the end of the 1960’s and the early 1970’s, there had been a gradual rise in the predominance of Parliamentary Sovereignty in India over the judiciary. Besides this, the early 1970’s had been characterised by widespread political unrest. The Naxalbari movement in West Bengal had met with severe state oppression through ‘The Operation Steeplechase’ among other government measures, the Nav Nirman movement in Gujarat (December 1973 - March 1974) led to the imposition of Central Government-rule on the state under Article 356 of the Indian Constitution. Amidst the prevailing political turmoil, there had been widespread dissatisfaction against the agents of the ruling order, particularly the Union Ministers, who are in many ways the most direct representatives of the ruling regime. Lalit Narayan Mishra, the Union Rail Minister was killed by a bomb on January 3, 1975.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most significant political mobilisation took place in April 1974, when a student agitation by the Chatra Sangharsh Samiti (Student Agitation Organisation) led by the Gandhian Socialist Jayaprakash Narayan and his call for “total revolution” to sweep away corruption, gained mass popularity. A significant ramification of the JP movement had been the nationwide strike organised by the railway employees union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raj Narain verdict had been the final nail in the coffin of the Indira Gandhi government which had been in power since 1966, almost 10 years. Mrs Gandhi had defeated Raj Narain in the 1971 Parliamentary elections from the constituency of Rae Bareily. He had filed cases accusing the Prime Minister of election fraud and malpractice along with the use of state machinery for election purposes in the Allahabad High Court. On June 12, 1975, Mr Justice Jagmohan Lal Sinha found Mrs Gandhi guilty of the said charges. The Supreme Court upheld the verdict and ordered a steady withdrawal of all privileges that Mrs Gandhi had received as a member of the Indian Parliament whilst depriving her of the right to vote in the lower house. The following day Narain had organised a rally in Delhi where he had reportedly proclaimed that the instruments of the state machinery, particularly the police, must reject the orders of a government which were immoral, corrupt and unethical. Widely interpreted as an instigation to spark a rebellion, it led to Mrs Gandhi declaring the Emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency was marked by an absolute suspension of the Fundamental Rights mentioned in Part III of the Indian Constitution. Mrs Gandhi had devised a ‘25-point economic programme’ which aimed at, inter alia, poverty eradication, restructuring of the public services, boosting agricultural and industrial production. Mrs Gandhi’s heir apparent and a leader of the Indian National Congress, Sanjay Gandhi, had contributed to it with his own programme of literacy, family planning, planting of trees, literacy promotion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Emergency, the opposition leaders were placed under preventive detention including Jayaprakash Narayan, Charan Singh and Atal Vihari Vajpayee (later Indian Prime Minister in 1997), Lal Krishna Advani, Arun Jaitley, Gayatri Devi, Queen Mother of the erstwhile princely state of Jaipur, Morarji Desai (later 4th Prime Minister of India in 1977-1979). Some prominent leaders of the Indian National Congress including Chandra Sekhar, who had resigned from Mrs Gandhi’s cabinet, were arrested and placed under detention as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, the 42nd Amendment Act which had rewritten the Indian Constitution was also passed. The amendments so introduced sought to reduce the power of the Supreme Court and the High Courts all over the nation, and inserted the words ‘Socialist’ and ‘Secular’ to the preamble of the Constitution. Under this amendment act, the Indian Parliament was bestowed with unlimited, unrestrained power to amend each and every section of the Constitution without judicial review. Thus, the doctrine of separation of powers and the Indian federal structure was negated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forced sterilisation program, undertaken under the leadership of Sanjay Gandhi with the aim of family planning, led to 8.3 million sterilisations within the time frame of 1976-1977 according to &lt;em&gt;India’s Population Reality: Reconciling Change and Tradition&lt;/em&gt;. The primary accounts of the brutality are evident in The Sanjay Story by an eminent Indian political journalist when he recounts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hawa Singh, a widower from the village of Pipli had been taken from a bus against his will and sterilised. The infection that emanated from the vasectomy took his life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government used Doordarshan, the government-owned television network, for its own political propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Turkman Gate demolition and firing which took place on April 18, 1976, a fallout of the drive to clear slum areas in Delhi, resulted in indiscriminate firing and police brutalities, which the popular media wasn’t permitted to report. Unofficial accounts put the figure at 9 deaths from among the ones who resisted the usurpation and bulldozing of their settlements. Later, the Shah Commission report stated that 20 individuals had been killed. The censorship of the press had begun from the night of the declaration of the Emergency itself with the electric supply of Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg being cut off, within 3 hours of the announcement. Most of the publishing houses of newspapers and national magazines were located on the same street. A number of newspapers had published a blank page or a black space in its editorials as an attempt to convey that the news had been tampered with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 18, 1977, Mrs Gandhi called for fresh elections followed by the release of all political prisoners. The Indian Emergency ended on March 23, 1977. The Congress was routed in the General Elections with Janta Dal assuming power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is that one thing about Indira’s India of 1975, inhabited by my grandfather’s generation that resonates with a world so different from ours, 45 years later, in a post-privatisation, liberal democracy? Surprisingly the answer doesn’t take a minute longer to appear so clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amnesty International in 2015 had stated that there was a “total blackout of information” in the state of Chattisgarh. And today, a complete shutting down of information transmission from Kashmir has continued for more than 5 months with major leaders of the state being placed under preventive detention. The idea of placing government loyalists to moot out majority opposition parties from power in the states finds uncanny parallels: Gandhi dismissed the Ajoy Mukherjee-led government in West Bengal in 1969 while Modi used Governors as loyalists to deny the single-largest party to come to power in Manipur, Nagaland and Meghalaya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Gandhi’s Emergency declaration was approved by her Cabinet only after its imposition. Similarly, Modi’s implementation of the demonetisation was known only to a handful in the Cabinet prior to its formal declaration. Additionally, Modi’s appointment of Army Chief Bipin Rawat, superseding two senior officers is reminiscent of Gandhi’s appointment of Mr Justice A N Ray as Chief Justice of India by superseding three others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signs are clear and “those who do not learn from history are doomed to repeat it”. The Indian Emergency only grows in importance during our times to educate us on how a state can go from mere political upheaval to an authoritarian regime.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indo-US Relations in the Second Decade of the 21st Century: The Way Ahead</title>
      <link href="/Indo-US-Relations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indo-US Relations in the Second Decade of the 21st Century: The Way Ahead" />
      <published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indo-US-Relations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indo-US-Relations">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump, the President of the United States undertook his first official trip to India since he assumed the Presidency in 2016. His 36-hour trip was marked by activities which ranged from travelling across Ahmedabad to Agra, to culminate his trip to Delhi. In the words of Trump himself, “Nobody else got the reception that I got yesterday. We had thousands of people. That was an incredible scene.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His trip, which took place in the last week of February, may be considered to be an extremely significant political gesture ahead of the United States presidential election due for November this year. This had been the fifth meeting between the two global leaders in the last eight months, indicating a maturity of the two nations’ diplomatic ties. The reception accorded to Trump may be reminiscent of the crowd gathered to welcome Dwight D Eisenhower, the United States President in 1959.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indo-US Ties Down the Ages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indo-US relations can be traced from the time prior to the independence of India in 1947. Prominent leaders of the national movement including M N Roy (one of the leaders of the Indo-German conspiracy), had settled in the US. However, in the initial decades of the Cold War, when the US had made Pakistan a CENTO ally (Central Treaty Organization), India had developed a strategic alliance with the Soviet Union. Yet, with the crystallisation of the Non-Aligned Movement in 1961 at the Bandung Conference, India embarked on an attempt to distance itself from the prevalent Cold War power politics. And there was a gradual deterioration in the relationship between India and the US, with Richard Nixon’s administration extending its support to Pakistan during the Bangladesh Liberation War of 1971 (in which India was an ally of Bangladesh). Moreover, India signed a 20-year Treaty of Friendship with the Soviet Union in 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indo-US ties soured further in 1974 when India detonated its first nuclear device. This strategic move ensured two decades of estrangement between the two nations. However, in 1982, the then US president Ronald Reagan did meet with the then Indian Prime Minister Indira Gandhi where the latter proclaimed, “We should find a common area, however so small.” The thaw in relations was prevalent till 1991, the year which marked the dissolution of the Soviet Union. With the adoption of India’s new economic policy in 1991, under Prime Minister Narasimha Rao and with Manmohan Singh as the Finance Minister, Indian foreign policy adapted itself to the unipolar world with the US as the champion of capitalist global domination. The adoption of the policies of Liberalisation, Privatisation and Globalisation cemented the economic ties of the two nations. Bilateral trade and investments increased, and one saw the strengthening of India’s decision-making powers in global governance via its introduction of India into multilateral export control regimes such as the Australia Group, The Missile Technology Control Regime (2016), the Wassenaar Arrangement and so on. In fact, the US offered assistance to India in joining the Nuclear Suppliers Group and in July 2006, the US Congress had amended the US law to accommodate civilian nuclear trade with India. Indo-US relations reached a zenith when India was declared a major defence partner of the US in 2016, under the Presidency of Barack Obama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Matters of Military and Economic Development Post The 1990’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 11, 1998, the Indian government had declared the successful completion of a series of underground nuclear tests at Pokhran, Rajasthan- close to the North-Western border shared by the two nations. The act drew widespread international criticism with Bill Clinton, the then US President, recalling the US ambassador to India and further imposing economic sanctions, leading to severe diplomatic tensions escalating between the two nations. However, in an amazing turn of events, in March 2000, Clinton became the first US President to visit India since 1978. With a fledgeling global economy, Clinton’s visit signalled a US foreign policy shifting its priorities from its Cold War ally Pakistan to India. In the areas of energy security, the 2005 visit of Condoleezza Rice, the United States Secretary of State initiated a dialogue on this primary core economic sector. This step had gained international significance as there had been mounting tensions over the US sale of fighter jets to Pakistan. Further, the signing of the Civil Nuclear Deal ensured a clear demarcation between India’s civil and military nuclear facilities, leading to India’s civil resources being placed under International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of economic developments, out of India’s largest direct investors, the US ranks number 1. India’s major exports are in the manufacturing sector, closely followed by non-financial services, which predominantly includes the software development industry. The US Department of State mentions that the major American items that have been imported by India include aircraft, fertilisers, computer hardware, scrap metal and medical equipment. The US accounts for a direct investment of $10 billion to India annually. Yet, the hindrance posed by tariff and non-tariff barriers includes agreement on the insecticides manufactured by US companies that may be sold throughout India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Donald Trump’s Presidential Visit and its Diplomatic Repercussions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The population of the Indian diaspora living in the US accounts to 4 million, which constitute slightly over 1% of the US population. Considering the US election due for November 2020, many international observers have regarded this visit as an attempt to secure the vote bank of the Indo-Americans. India and the US have issued a joint statement by proclaiming the US-India ties to the level of “comprehensive global strategic partnership.” An attempt to make defence manufacturers part of each other’s supply chains and an assurance to strengthen homeland security to resist global terrorism was made. A twin arms deal amounting to $3.5 billion for 6 Apache attack helicopters and 24 Seahawk anti-submarine warfare helicopters have been inked. Further, a $1.9 billion for missile defence system awaits in the pipeline. There have been talks to revitalise the Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (US, India, Australia and Japan) initiative on areas such as counter-terrorism and maritime security. Moreover, a collaboration for the Blue Dot Network and escalating tensions over China’s Belt and Road initiative has strengthened collaboration on regional infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Affairs Survey conducted by Gallup (US Analytics and Advisory company) in 2015 states that “Americans perceive India as their 6th favourite nation in the world.” 74% of Americans viewed India favourably in 2017 and 72% in 2019. While all aspects of the economic relations between the two countries are improving, the people-to-people relationship is also getting better. In the words of the Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi, “Relations between India and US aren’t just between two governments, but are people-centric and people-driven.” The bonhomie between the two nations may become stronger if besides military and energy, other areas of cooperation are explored. Much may depend upon the US election results.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Donald Trump, the President of the United States undertook his first official trip to India since he assumed the Presidency in 2016. His 36-hour trip was marked by activities which ranged from travelling across Ahmedabad to Agra, to culminate his trip to Delhi. In the words of Trump himself, “Nobody else got the reception that I got yesterday. We had thousands of people. That was an incredible scene.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Russia Heralds a New Dawn: Power to the People or the Lurking Shadow of a Dictatorial Regime?</title>
      <link href="/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russia Heralds a New Dawn: Power to the People or the Lurking Shadow of a Dictatorial Regime?" />
      <published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&quot;I truly believe that it is time to introduce certain changes to our country's main law.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; 
-Vladimir Putin, January 2020
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 15, 2020, the Russian Government headed by Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev resigned en masse, immediately after the State of the Union address. Within six hours of Medvedev’s resignation, Putin offered the post to Mikhail Mishutshin who had formerly been the head of the Russian Tax Service. It is of significance that the governmental revamp has been preceded by a proposed nationwide referendum on constitutional changes which will ensure the shift of the balance of power from Putin’s successor (the future Russian President) to the Parliament and the newly-appointed Prime Minister, even though Putin has limited the term of the Russian President to two terms. All 432 legislators in the Duma, the lower house of the Russian Parliament, have approved of the amendments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the amendments, 14 articles of the Constitution are to be changed. The State Duma will possess the right to approve a Prime Minister’s candidacy, followed by that of the Deputy Prime Ministers and Federal Ministers. A prospective Presidential candidate has to be an inhabitant of Russia for a minimum of 25 years (earlier it was 10 years). The upper house of the Russian Parliament, the Federation Council, will be able to send a proposal to the President to dismiss Federal Judges. This is an elevation of the Council’s importance, whose significance was previously restricted to being an advisory body. The President will appoint the superior officers of the law enforcement agencies only in consultation with the Federal Council. The individuals who hold important positions for ensuring the country’s security (President, Ministers, Heads of Regions) are forbidden from holding foreign citizenship or residence permits of other nations during their term in office. The Constitutional Court has the competence to ensure the constitutionality of laws which the Parliament of the Russian Federation adopts, by the request of the President, before him signing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That apart, one of the important parts of the amendment includes a clear statement of the priority of the Russian Constitution over international law and the global human rights regime, which many believe is a reflection of Kremlin’s annoyance with the European Court of Human Rights’ declarations that Russia is responsible for gross human rights violations, including the Chechnya disappearances, and the Court’s rulings against Russia’s Federal Security Services in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The otherwise innocuous amendments tend to have latent implications for Russia, in particular, and international politics in general. A cursory analysis reveals that there shall be a surge in the importance of the country’s Parliament: both the upper and lower house. The President’s candidature for the post of Prime Minister would require a formal confirmation from the Duma. The actual centre of power shall shift to the State Council which is being vested with a heightened legal authority. Many believe that it is the future landing gateway for Putin, post-2024, as it will ensure that he retains ultimate power post-retirement from the Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amendments will bestow the Security Council (headed by Putin, it includes the heads of the lower and upper house of parliament, the President’s envoys in Federal Districts and regional Governors) with the status of an official state organ that shall chart the domestic and foreign policies of the Russian Federation. There is an opportunity of the Security Council receiving executive authority that it previously hasn’t possessed. Putin may continue to manipulate foreign and domestic affairs through his pivotal role in this Security Council, in spite of not retaining his presidential post within 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The present amendments may be compared to that of the Kazakhstan President Nursultan Nazarvaev, who formally stepped down from the post of the President last March but continued to enjoy hegemony over the decision-making hierarchy of the nation by capturing important positions in the Security Council whose authority had been strategically heightened before Nazarnaev’s ascendancy. Hints of such parallels find resonance in the words of Pavel Krasheninnikov, Chairman of a Duma committee telling the official Government newspaper &lt;em&gt;Rossiiskaya Gazeta&lt;/em&gt;, “Scores of proposals have been received including one to create an official post of Supreme Leader.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of February, 2020, one may state that the unanimous support of the Duma to the constitutional amendments bill is reminiscent of the Soviet vote on Stalin’s adoption of the December, 1936 Constitution or Brezhnev’s 1977 Doctrine. A national plebiscite on the amendments is due in April and planning for it has already been initiated by the Central Election Commission. However, the opposition aims at converting the plebiscite into a no-confidence vote of the ruling regime. More than 40,000 people have signed a manuscript urging the Russian public to blatantly reject the “constitutional &lt;em&gt;coup&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;d’etat&lt;/em&gt;”. Meanwhile, the fate of Russia swerves in the uncertainty of major constitutional upheaval.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;I truly believe that it is time to introduce certain changes to our country's main law.&quot; -Vladimir Putin, January 2020</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Encounter Killings’- Delivering Justice or Instances of Culpable Homicide?</title>
      <link href="/Encounter-Killings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Encounter  Killings'- Delivering  Justice  or  Instances  of  Culpable  Homicide?" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Encounter-Killings</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Encounter-Killings">&lt;p&gt;Montesquieu, the French philosopher, known worldwide for his articulation of the ‘Theory of Separation of Powers’ had famously stated, “There is no greater tyranny than that which is perpetrated under the shield of the law and in the name of justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of the debate revolving around the idea of ‘extrajudicial killings’, known in popular culture as &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; lies in the timeless relevance of Montesquieu’s words. India, the world’s largest democracy with its constitution bearing testimony to the ideals of “Liberty, Equality, Justice, Fraternity” ranks high on the global index promotion of such a dehumanising practice. Uttar Pradesh, the largest state of the Indian union by population, has recorded 59 instances of such extra judicial killings in the past two years. However, the trend of extra judicial killings in India is not a contemporary phenomenon, it has been an indispensable element of securing obedience at the hands of armed forces, police and similar repressive machineries of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Encounter killing&lt;/em&gt; is a term used to refer to extrajudicial executions (beyond the limits of the judiciary’s scope) of individuals in police custody, which has been staged in such a manner so as to portray their occurrence as instances of death by gun battle, or in supposed self defence carried out by the police or armed forces in self defence on encountering gangsters or terrorists or alleged criminals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major criticism of this idea is that it takes a person’s life without minimal guarantee of due process of law. It can be analysed from diverse viewpoints - one cannot overlook that they are often political assassinations. Edy Kauffman in the &lt;em&gt;Human Rights Quarterly&lt;/em&gt; had defined it as “assassinations that are part of a rational scheme to transfer political power from one group to another or to achieve a specific policy objective.” Its exercise is not limited to transfer of power, but also to retain power. It can be explained through the example of 5,000 murders and 30,000 arrests that took place in Chile following the 1973 military coup, which thereby resulted in Salvador Allende being overthrown by the armed forces. Such &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; have also been widely prevalent in western European nations including, United Kingdom. Operation Kratos which was conducted by London’s Metropolitan Police Service to exterminate suspected suicide bombers included firing on the head without warning. This practice had been exposed after the mistaken shooting of Jean Charles de Menezes (a case of misidentification post the 2005 London Bombings) - leading to several human rights organisations calling out against similar practices. Similarly, the Rio de Janeiro police killed 322 people unlawfully in between January and May of 2016, in accordance to its reports released in July of the same year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A brief history of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; in India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-1947 and transfer of power, there have been innumerable instances of encounter killings in the history of the nation, some supported by historical records while others whose only substantial evidence is in the form of ‘missing person’ documents. The alarming rate of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; had sparked an inquiry by United Nations panel comprising 4 independent human rights experts. This panel had ‘expressed alarm’ in its January 2019 statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“individuals allegedly being abducted or arrested before their killing, and their bodies bearing indicative of torture.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have been the go-to alternative in a variety of contexts - during the Naxalbari insurgency in the state of Bengal during the late 1960’s and early 1970’s. The CPI (M-L) led insurrection across the state included regular instances of the state police shooting down alleged naxalite student activists, which includes the murder of the poet, communist intellectual Saroj Dutta, whose name still appears as ‘missing person’ almost 45 years after his disappearance, followed by repeated petitions for investigation of his death being rejected by the West Bengal State government. The Barasat killings of 1970’s refer to the murder of 11 young men on the night of November 19, 1970 with suspected links to Naxal terror. Operation Steeplechase, commissioned by the Indira Gandhi government has often been accused of perpetrating ‘fake encounters.’ With Rahul Pandita’s &lt;em&gt;Hello Bastar: The Untold Story of India’s Maoist Movement&lt;/em&gt; stating that Govind Narain, the then Home Secretary of India proclaimed “There should be no publicity and no records.” Further instances of extra judicial killings have also been noted during the Punjab insurgency of the 1980’s. Counter-terrorism measures by the state often manifests itself in the form of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; in terrorist infested zones. The North-Eastern state of Manipur, which had for years been reeling under the draconian AFSPA (Armed forces Special Powers Act), has witnessed several such cases. A case filed before the Indian Supreme Court in 2012, recounted the horrors of a staggering 1528 extra judicial killings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jammu and Kashmir has been a hotbed of state sponsored terrorism disguised as counter terror measures, with security forces indulging in gross violations of human rights- with the riveting instance of of soldiers shooting and killing six persons in Shopian district on March 5, 2018. The government spokesman claimed that the ‘miscreants’ had failed to stop at a checkpoint and the soldiers had opened fire in self-defence. In November 2018, the National Human Rights Commission issued a notice to Uttar Pradesh’s Chief Minister, Yogi Adityanath post his “criminals will be jailed or killed in encounters” remark. It highlights the callous and often denigrating reflection of human security measures in the subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reforms as the Need of the Hour&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many argue that instead of resources being utilised for security sector reforms, there must be greater attention devoted to the idea of rights sensitisation, i.e. educating the state machineries of the rights guaranteed to each citizen. Promoting accountability of the security forces, strict criminalisation in cases of fake encounters should be a necessity. Impartial investigations in case of alleged reports of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; should be a necessity. We have often seen such instances are greater if the miscreant belongs to weaker sections of the society, which may include religious minorities or members of financially unstable families. Moreover, the cases of misidentification and death of an innocent citizen doesn’t appear far-fetched, as the role of judiciary is almost null in such cases. However, political pressures from the upper echelons of the government isn’t an exception- Veerapan, the notorious sandalwood forest bridgend was allegedly killed by the Special Task Force in an encounter on October 18, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court has issued a landmark decision in 2016, in which it stated the illegality of such encounters and the lack of ‘absolute impunity’ in such cases. The Court has even ordered the setting up of a Special Investigation Team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate surrounding the concepts of fake encounters has gained a fresh lease of life with the extra judicial killing of the four rapists responsible for the brutal rape and murder of a Hyderabad veterinarian in December 2019. What is particularly alarming about such instances is the public adulation the police officers involved in such instances receive. The encounter specialists in popular media are widely celebrated as heroes. Such a psychological reaction can be attributed to the slow judicial procedures that characterise the Indian judicial system. However, important questions regarding the prisoner’s right to a free and fair trial, right to life (until proven guilty) and the larger moral responsibility of the society must continue to haunt the collective conscience.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Montesquieu, the French philosopher, known worldwide for his articulation of the ‘Theory of Separation of Powers’ had famously stated, “There is no greater tyranny than that which is perpetrated under the shield of the law and in the name of justice.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?</title>
      <link href="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?" />
      <published>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donald Trump on the eve of the 18th anniversary of the 9/11 commemorations on September 11, 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This will lead to more losses to the US. Its credibility will be affected, its anti-peace stance will be exposed to the world, losses to lives and assets will increase.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zabihullah Mujahid, a Talib spokesman criticising the US President for calling off the dialogue between the US and the Taliban.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest concerns pervading global geopolitics in the second decade of the 21st century is the solution to what may be referred to as the “Afghanistan policy of the United States.” The peace process, a mediation attempt in what is regarded as one of the greatest standoffs of our times, has met a dead-end. Peace negotiations between the two sides were stalled off unexpectedly, with the US pulling from the expected accord using a proverbial reason too flimsy for most observers of global politics. Trump has pushed the reason that there has been an uptick in Taliban-inflicted violence all across Afghanistan as well the death of an American soldier along with 11 other people in a suicide bombing which shook the national capital of Kabul in the month of September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To receive a better understanding of this more recent development, it is imperative to cast a glance at the intricacies that have led to the stalemate today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term Taliban can be literally translated as ‘students.’ It can be referred to as an attempt to construct an Islamic Empire in Afghanistan. The Sunni Islamic organisation rose to prominence in 1994, as part of an attempt to end the power vacuum that had exerted itself in the nation as an immediate after-effect of the Afghan Civil War. The Afghan Civil War had resulted in the drop of Kabul’s population from 2 million to 500,000 within a span of a year. It began when Hezb-e-Islami led by Gulbuddin Hekmatyar with the support of neighbouring Pakistan’s Inter-Services Intelligence (ISI) had refused to be a part of the coalition government along with other Mujahideen Groups, establishing their sole authority over Kabul. It was only a year later in 1995-1996 that the militia of the Talibans, having secured sufficient support from Pakistan and ISI, established its supremacy and invaded Kandahar, followed by Herat, with their authority receiving a formal seal of suzerainty with the successful invasion of Kabul in 1996. Al-Qaeda had been granted sanction to operate by the Taliban on the condition that it would not indulge in any activity that could incur the wrath of the US. But the subsequent actions of its leader, Osama Bin Laden’s attack on the American embassies of East Africa, caused a rift between the Taliban and the Al-Qaeda. Many may sight that Al-Qaeda harboured a greater ambition - that of global jihad while Talibans had a restrictive operational base called Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post 9/11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Powell had famously remarked, “You can be sure that the American Spirit will prevail over this tragedy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest turning points of the new millennium had been the four coordinated terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001 at three prime locations in the heart of the United States that killed 2,977 people, injuring 25,000 more. Truly, American foreign policy never remained the same with Islamic nations across the globe, and with Afghanistan, quite obviously, having to bear the brunt. The US demanded that the Taliban hand over Osama Bin Laden, the mastermind behind the tragedy, which was rejected by the Taliban as they demanded greater evidence of his involvement in the terror attack. In response, the US-NATO alliance launched Operation Enduring Freedom. George W Bush, the then President of the US had declared a “War on Terror,” as reported by the New York Times on September 20, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the operation was clearly evident, with the Taliban being driven out of power by the Christmas of 2001. The United Nations Security Council later formed the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF) with the aim of providing multidimensional training to Afghan Security forces, which would rebuild the social and political institutions which had been demolished by the Taliban regime. These institutions also included the establishment of the Afghan Transitional Administration with Hamid Karzai as the President. ISAF spread through four stages all over the Taliban-inflicted ruins of the nation. The Operation Enduring Freedom ended after 13 years in 2014, with Bush’s successor Barack Obama declaring its end with these words of significance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For more than 13 years, ever since nearly 3,000 innocent lives were taken from us on 9/11 our nation has been at war with Afghanistan……our combat mission in Afghanistan is ending, and the longest war in American history is coming to a responsible end.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, he also stressed that in order to preserve the gains made by the US military (as also by the invitation of the Afghan government), a limited military presence would remain in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely stated that negotiations with the Taliban had always been in the pipeline, having been strongly endorsed by the former Afghan president, Hamid Karzai (2004-2014), but American efforts had never been either eager or decisive in the matter. Karzai, on returning from a foreign trip, had offered peace negotiations in 2007, but the Taliban insurgents citing the proliferation of foreign troops had squarely rejected the offer. The precondition that there be a withdrawal of 50,000 NATO troops and US military couldn’t be fulfilled. Karzai had offered to allocate government posts to the Taliban with Hekmatyar even being allowed to contest elections in 2009, but to no avail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2009 Afghan Presidential elections had been widely contested on the issue of whether the war should come to an end or not. In one of his Presidential campaigns, Karzai offered “Loya Jirga” (a traditional Afghan Pashtun ceremony organised for choosing a new head of state). However, the elections, which were widely blood-splattered with the death of 59 Americans, resulted in the increase of the presence of American troops in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2010 marked a significant turn of events, with Karzai stating that “the peace process will be with the Talibans and other militants who are not part of the Al Qaeda or other terrorist networks or ideologically against us.” The then US Secretary of State Hillary Clinton supported the contention. The second-in-command of the Taliban, Abdul Ghani Baradar favoured talks with both the US and the Afghan government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change of political strategy of the US government took place in 2010, with the Taliban Quetta Shura (Taliban Leadership Commanders) leaving Pakistan and being escorted to Kabul by NATO aircraft for discussions, according to Reuters, only to be revealed that one of the leaders Akhtar Mansour was an imposter disguised as senior Taliban commander. A round of talks stood cancelled in 2012 and another stood cancelled in 2013 as a direct consequence of a dispute between the Taliban and Karzai, where the latter felt that the former were portraying themselves as a “government in exile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 2018 marked an abrupt increase in violence, with Ashraf Ghani, the Afghan President offering the Taliban a full recognition as a legal political party and a release of Taliban political prisoners. The Los Angeles Times referred to this as “the most significant peace overture.” Surprisingly, in July 2018, American officials had reportedly met a few members of the Taliban at their political office in Qatar. Zalmay Khalilzad joined the US State Department as Trump’s Special Advisor on Afghanistan, with the sole aim of initiating an intra-Afghan peace process. Fuelling diplomatic speculation, Russia successfully held talks with the Taliban and officials of the Afghanistan High Peace Council. After the February 2019 talks, Khalilzad reported “this round of talk was more productive than they have ever been in the past.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 12, 2019, the US and the Taliban completed the 8th round of negotiations, and US media had been abuzz with the news that the US had been close to reaching a peace deal with Afghanistan which would include the withdrawal of 5,000 troops from Afghanistan. The ‘agreement-in-principle’ was awaiting final approval by the President, which it fortunately or unfortunately did not get. Its cancellation, however, prompted the Talibans to remark that the “doors were open” for further discussions with Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conjectures are afloat that a peace agreement with the Talibans could result in their rise to power, replicating the defeat of the US-backed South Vietnamese government after the 1973 Paris peace accords. US Defence Secretary Mark Esper had visited Afghanistan in late October 2019. He stated that the US could reduce its force in Afghanistan to 8,600 without damaging its counter-terrorism capabilities. On a world diplomacy stage, war with Afghanistan is largely recognised as an unwinnable war. For a concrete conclusion of the war, it is imperative that the US gets rid of its mirage of a perfect deal and allure foŕ hard power. Otherwise, like the North Korean nuclear standoff, there seems no end in sight. Every month this stalemate claims thousands of Afghan lives and almost $4 billion from the US government.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Carnage, with its Fangs Upon History</title>
      <link href="/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Carnage, with its Fangs Upon History" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A retrospection on the eve of the 35th anniversary of the Anti-Sikh riots:
Tale of tribulation and tragedy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“History is only the register of crimes and misfortunes.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Voltaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may disagree with this widely quoted statement, but the following anecdote
may suffice and surprise with its uncanny semblance to Voltaire’s clairvoyance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We were on our way to Mumbai from Punjab. At a station right outside Delhi, a
mob gathered around the train, screaming, ‘Sikhs have killed the nation’s
mother.’ They hit my husband on the head with an iron rod and dragged him out of
the train. I screamed as I watched them burn him alive.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Mohinder Kaur, who lost her family in the 1984 riots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaur is not an exception. Rows of widow colonies scream similar tales. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we embark into October 2019, we, Indians await the 35th death anniversary of
India’s own prototype of an Iron Lady, Mrs. Indira Gandhi, on October 31, 1984.
What remains shrouded in oblivion is the aftermath of the tragedy, which ravaged
parts of the world’s largest democracy with an estimated death toll of 3,350
deaths (in official figures). After the partition in 1947, the anti-Sikh riots
in India witnessed the largest massacre of members of a single religious order
within a span of 3 days. With a public security mechanism, including police and
armed forces turning a blind eye, what transpired has been a portrayal of loss,
political apathy to it’s extreme and gross violation of fundamental human rights
of an unprecedented nature. The last nail on the coffin has perhaps been the
rhetoric delivered by the successor of Mrs Gandhi, as also her son, the then
Prime Minister, Rajiv Gandhi. On being asked about the reported carnage that
shook the Indian capital from October 31-November 3, he went on record stating,
“When a big tree falls, the earth shakes.” The metaphor has been too obvious to
overlook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1984 anti-Sikh riots can be regarded more as a culmination of a flame that
has its roots in a persistent series of events spanning almost over a decade in
the North Indian state of Punjab, prior to 1984. The seeds lay in the Sikh
demand for an independent state for their community, to be formerly termed as
‘Khalistan’, or the land of the Khalsa. Sikhism is the 4th largest religion in
India, with a following of 20.8 million in India. One of it’s militant religious
leaders, Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale had been invited by the Sikh political party
Akali Dal’s then-president, Harchand Singh Longowal to take up residence inside
the Golden Temple Complex in Amritsar, Punjab. The Golden Temple or the
Harminder Sahib, is widely regarded as the holiest shrine of the Sikh community.
One of the reasons to provide shelter to Bhindranwale within the Golden Temple
complex had been to guarantee immunity against his arrest by the Indian
Government. Bhindranwale had made the hallowed sanctuary a garrison of weapons
and subsequently a headquarters of Khalistani militants. One of his principal
aims had been to initiate a battle for the creation of the separate state of
Khalistan. The location of the Temple added credibility to claims of a  ‘holy
war’, adding a religious tinge to the ongoing insurgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An encounter that changed the course of history&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated action, initiated by the Indian Government arrived on June
8, 1984, in the guise of the Indian military action carried out between June
1-8, to eliminate the militant religious leader, Bhindranwale and his band of
insurgents from the Harmandir Sahib Complex in Amritsar. This operation had been
formally codenamed as ‘Operation Blue Star’. The sanction to execute the order
had stemmed from the decision of Mrs Indira Gandhi. An international angle to
the raging political situation in Punjab had heightened its impact on global
geopolitics of the time. Indian intelligence agencies had widely reported that a
trio of the Khalistani militants, Shahbeg Singh, Amrik Singh and Balber Singh
had undertaken 6 trips to Pakistan between the time frame of 1981-1983. The
Indian Intelligence Bureau had reported about the weapons training imparted at
gurudwaras (Sikh centres of worship). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There had been widely circulated international reports pertaining to the Russian
intelligence agencies, including the KGB, tipping off the Indian Agency RAW,
about the CIA and ISI collaborating on an agenda directed at Punjab. Kiessling
in his publication, &lt;em&gt;Faith, Unity, Discipline : The Inter Service Intelligence
(ISI) of Pakistan&lt;/em&gt; had described with vivid detail how during the course of
interrogating a Pakistani Army Officer, RAW had received credible news that over
a thousand trained Special Service Group commandos of the Pakistani Army had
been voluntarily dispatched to extend support to Bhindranwale’s anti India
Insurgency. The Sikh Diaspora in Canada had also explicitly extended their
support to the movement. On the final failure of negotiations and arbitration,
the Indian army launched a full-scale offensive against the contingent of
heavily armed insurgents. The scale of ammunition possessed by the insurgents
included, inter alia, anti-tank heavy artillery, China-made rocket-propelled
grenade launchers. The official estimate of militants nabbed can be numbered at
1,592. Bhindranwale had been one among the dead. However, the operation had
caused severe damage to the Golden Temple, inflaming the religious sentiments of
Sikhs all across the world. The operation attracted widespread criticism from
eminent members of the community all across the globe. Khuswant Singh, the
renowned Indian journalist/novelist returned the Padma Bhushan, the 3rd highest
civilian award by the Republic of India, as a mark of protest. Operation
Woodrose swept through Punjab following Operation Bluestar which marked
indiscriminate arrests across the Punjabi countryside, the banning of the All
India Sikh Student’s Federation and total suspension of civil liberties by the
Indian government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Of an assassination and a pogrom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four months later, as a consequence of the military activity in June, on October
31, 1984, Indira Gandhi had been shot dead by her Sikh Bodyguards, Satwant Singh
and Beant Singh, in vengeance. What followed is often regarded as one of the
darkest chapters in the history of Indian polity. Perhaps the worst hit was the
national capital. The prominent local leaders of the Indian National Congress
including Jagdish Tytler, Sajjan Kumar, Lalit Maken and HKL Bhagat, had been
prominent among the frenzied mob. The riots left hundreds dead, burnt,
butchered, raped, widowed and homeless. What is perhaps the most disturbing
segment of the massacre is that, it wasn’t a natural outburst of anger and
helpless expression emerging from the loss of a much revered Prime Minister but
a well designed, carefully crafted execution of anti-Sikh violence. It was a
result of a series of meetings concluded throughout the night of October 31 and
the dawn of November 1, including senior police officers and sitting members of
the Parliament. The Indian government’s refusal to administer the army
immediately in riot-affected areas, its confiscation of licensed firearms by
legitimate holders of the Sikh religion, and its distribution of lists of homes
which served as residences of Sikh families by making use of government records
ensured precision in the massacres. Most people were scalped and burnt by being
set alight with kerosene or doused in phosphorus, which ensured the charring of
its victim to the bone. On November 1, Sajjan Kumar was seen by eyewitnesses,
handing out iron rods from a parked truck to a group of 120 and ordering them to
“attack Sikhs, kill them, and loot and burn their properties.” The organised
nature and large-scale coordination prevalent in the riot is evident from the
testimony of an eyewitness, Aseem Srivastava in his report to Misra Commission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There were also some young men on motorcycles, who were instructing the mobs
and supplying them with kerosene oil from time to time. [On] one more than a few
occasion[s] we saw auto rickshaw[s] arriving with several tins of kerosene oil
and other inflammable material such as jute sacks.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only in the late evening of November 3 that the army and law enforcement
mechanisms intervened to reduce the riot’s intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten commissions had been set up to investigate the riots. Out of the 10
commissions, the Nanavati Commission (2000) found sufficient evidence against
both Tytler and Kumar. However, it absolved Rajiv Gandhi and other high-ranking
officials of the INC of any possible involvement in the riots. Further
acknowledging that the passive indifference of Delhi Police and its failure to
provide protection to the riot-affected individuals. On December 17, 2018,
Sajjan Kumar’s acquittal in the 1984 riots had been reversed by the Delhi High
Court and he had been sentenced to life imprisonment. The latest development has
been the Indian Home Ministry ordering the reopening of a 1984 anti-Sikh riot
case against veteran Congress leader Kamal Nath (current Chief Minister of the
state of Madhya Pradesh). The Special Investigation Team will look into alleged
accusations of inciting a crowd against Sikhs outside a gurudwara at Rakabganj
in Delhi on the fateful day of Indira Gandhi’s assassination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 35 years since the murderous mob riots ravaging through the nation, debates
continue unabated on whether the term ‘anti-Sikh riots’, should be replaced by
the term ‘Sikh genocide’. The riots bring out the heinous toxicity promoted by
populism, leaving democracy in disarray, paralysing notions of human rights as
mindlessness gains precedence above all. It is ironical that in the demise of
Indira Gandhi, who harboured a legacy of commitment to secularism throughout her
mortal life left a predicament of one of the worst communal killings in India.
The law may take its course, but to the families maimed and destroyed by the
riots, many of whom had been Indira Gandhi loyalists prior to 1984, 35 years on,
closure still remains a far cry.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A retrospection on the eve of the 35th anniversary of the Anti-Sikh riots: Tale of tribulation and tragedy “History is only the register of crimes and misfortunes.”  -Voltaire. One may disagree with this widely quoted statement, but the following anecdote may suffice and surprise with its uncanny semblance to Voltaire’s clairvoyance. “We were on our way to Mumbai from Punjab. At a station right outside Delhi, a mob gathered around the train, screaming, ‘Sikhs have killed the nation’s mother.’ They hit my husband on the head with an iron rod and dragged him out of the train. I screamed as I watched them burn him alive.” -Mohinder Kaur, who lost her family in the 1984 riots. Kaur is not an exception. Rows of widow colonies scream similar tales.  As we embark into October 2019, we, Indians await the 35th death anniversary of India’s own prototype of an Iron Lady, Mrs. Indira Gandhi, on October 31, 1984. What remains shrouded in oblivion is the aftermath of the tragedy, which ravaged parts of the world’s largest democracy with an estimated death toll of 3,350 deaths (in official figures). After the partition in 1947, the anti-Sikh riots in India witnessed the largest massacre of members of a single religious order within a span of 3 days. With a public security mechanism, including police and armed forces turning a blind eye, what transpired has been a portrayal of loss, political apathy to it’s extreme and gross violation of fundamental human rights of an unprecedented nature. The last nail on the coffin has perhaps been the rhetoric delivered by the successor of Mrs Gandhi, as also her son, the then Prime Minister, Rajiv Gandhi. On being asked about the reported carnage that shook the Indian capital from October 31-November 3, he went on record stating, “When a big tree falls, the earth shakes.” The metaphor has been too obvious to overlook. The 1984 anti-Sikh riots can be regarded more as a culmination of a flame that has its roots in a persistent series of events spanning almost over a decade in the North Indian state of Punjab, prior to 1984. The seeds lay in the Sikh demand for an independent state for their community, to be formerly termed as ‘Khalistan’, or the land of the Khalsa. Sikhism is the 4th largest religion in India, with a following of 20.8 million in India. One of it’s militant religious leaders, Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale had been invited by the Sikh political party Akali Dal’s then-president, Harchand Singh Longowal to take up residence inside the Golden Temple Complex in Amritsar, Punjab. The Golden Temple or the Harminder Sahib, is widely regarded as the holiest shrine of the Sikh community. One of the reasons to provide shelter to Bhindranwale within the Golden Temple complex had been to guarantee immunity against his arrest by the Indian Government. Bhindranwale had made the hallowed sanctuary a garrison of weapons and subsequently a headquarters of Khalistani militants. One of his principal aims had been to initiate a battle for the creation of the separate state of Khalistan. The location of the Temple added credibility to claims of a  ‘holy war’, adding a religious tinge to the ongoing insurgency. An encounter that changed the course of history The much anticipated action, initiated by the Indian Government arrived on June 8, 1984, in the guise of the Indian military action carried out between June 1-8, to eliminate the militant religious leader, Bhindranwale and his band of insurgents from the Harmandir Sahib Complex in Amritsar. This operation had been formally codenamed as ‘Operation Blue Star’. The sanction to execute the order had stemmed from the decision of Mrs Indira Gandhi. An international angle to the raging political situation in Punjab had heightened its impact on global geopolitics of the time. Indian intelligence agencies had widely reported that a trio of the Khalistani militants, Shahbeg Singh, Amrik Singh and Balber Singh had undertaken 6 trips to Pakistan between the time frame of 1981-1983. The Indian Intelligence Bureau had reported about the weapons training imparted at gurudwaras (Sikh centres of worship).  There had been widely circulated international reports pertaining to the Russian intelligence agencies, including the KGB, tipping off the Indian Agency RAW, about the CIA and ISI collaborating on an agenda directed at Punjab. Kiessling in his publication, Faith, Unity, Discipline : The Inter Service Intelligence (ISI) of Pakistan had described with vivid detail how during the course of interrogating a Pakistani Army Officer, RAW had received credible news that over a thousand trained Special Service Group commandos of the Pakistani Army had been voluntarily dispatched to extend support to Bhindranwale’s anti India Insurgency. The Sikh Diaspora in Canada had also explicitly extended their support to the movement. On the final failure of negotiations and arbitration, the Indian army launched a full-scale offensive against the contingent of heavily armed insurgents. The scale of ammunition possessed by the insurgents included, inter alia, anti-tank heavy artillery, China-made rocket-propelled grenade launchers. The official estimate of militants nabbed can be numbered at 1,592. Bhindranwale had been one among the dead. However, the operation had caused severe damage to the Golden Temple, inflaming the religious sentiments of Sikhs all across the world. The operation attracted widespread criticism from eminent members of the community all across the globe. Khuswant Singh, the renowned Indian journalist/novelist returned the Padma Bhushan, the 3rd highest civilian award by the Republic of India, as a mark of protest. Operation Woodrose swept through Punjab following Operation Bluestar which marked indiscriminate arrests across the Punjabi countryside, the banning of the All India Sikh Student’s Federation and total suspension of civil liberties by the Indian government. Of an assassination and a pogrom Four months later, as a consequence of the military activity in June, on October 31, 1984, Indira Gandhi had been shot dead by her Sikh Bodyguards, Satwant Singh and Beant Singh, in vengeance. What followed is often regarded as one of the darkest chapters in the history of Indian polity. Perhaps the worst hit was the national capital. The prominent local leaders of the Indian National Congress including Jagdish Tytler, Sajjan Kumar, Lalit Maken and HKL Bhagat, had been prominent among the frenzied mob. The riots left hundreds dead, burnt, butchered, raped, widowed and homeless. What is perhaps the most disturbing segment of the massacre is that, it wasn’t a natural outburst of anger and helpless expression emerging from the loss of a much revered Prime Minister but a well designed, carefully crafted execution of anti-Sikh violence. It was a result of a series of meetings concluded throughout the night of October 31 and the dawn of November 1, including senior police officers and sitting members of the Parliament. The Indian government’s refusal to administer the army immediately in riot-affected areas, its confiscation of licensed firearms by legitimate holders of the Sikh religion, and its distribution of lists of homes which served as residences of Sikh families by making use of government records ensured precision in the massacres. Most people were scalped and burnt by being set alight with kerosene or doused in phosphorus, which ensured the charring of its victim to the bone. On November 1, Sajjan Kumar was seen by eyewitnesses, handing out iron rods from a parked truck to a group of 120 and ordering them to “attack Sikhs, kill them, and loot and burn their properties.” The organised nature and large-scale coordination prevalent in the riot is evident from the testimony of an eyewitness, Aseem Srivastava in his report to Misra Commission: “There were also some young men on motorcycles, who were instructing the mobs and supplying them with kerosene oil from time to time. [On] one more than a few occasion[s] we saw auto rickshaw[s] arriving with several tins of kerosene oil and other inflammable material such as jute sacks.” It was only in the late evening of November 3 that the army and law enforcement mechanisms intervened to reduce the riot’s intensity. Ten commissions had been set up to investigate the riots. Out of the 10 commissions, the Nanavati Commission (2000) found sufficient evidence against both Tytler and Kumar. However, it absolved Rajiv Gandhi and other high-ranking officials of the INC of any possible involvement in the riots. Further acknowledging that the passive indifference of Delhi Police and its failure to provide protection to the riot-affected individuals. On December 17, 2018, Sajjan Kumar’s acquittal in the 1984 riots had been reversed by the Delhi High Court and he had been sentenced to life imprisonment. The latest development has been the Indian Home Ministry ordering the reopening of a 1984 anti-Sikh riot case against veteran Congress leader Kamal Nath (current Chief Minister of the state of Madhya Pradesh). The Special Investigation Team will look into alleged accusations of inciting a crowd against Sikhs outside a gurudwara at Rakabganj in Delhi on the fateful day of Indira Gandhi’s assassination. The 35 years since the murderous mob riots ravaging through the nation, debates continue unabated on whether the term ‘anti-Sikh riots’, should be replaced by the term ‘Sikh genocide’. The riots bring out the heinous toxicity promoted by populism, leaving democracy in disarray, paralysing notions of human rights as mindlessness gains precedence above all. It is ironical that in the demise of Indira Gandhi, who harboured a legacy of commitment to secularism throughout her mortal life left a predicament of one of the worst communal killings in India. The law may take its course, but to the families maimed and destroyed by the riots, many of whom had been Indira Gandhi loyalists prior to 1984, 35 years on, closure still remains a far cry.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Death Penalty: A Contentious Predicament</title>
      <link href="/A-Contentious-Predicament" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Death Penalty: A Contentious Predicament" />
      <published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Contentious-Predicament</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Contentious-Predicament">&lt;p&gt;In the 1889 short story, &lt;em&gt;The Bet&lt;/em&gt;, Anton Chekhov, a Russian writer, subtly raised one of those deeply divisive questions that has been plaguing humankind since the dawn of civilisation. Through the depiction of an altercation between a young lawyer and a banker, who engage in a fierce battle of wits, he brought forward the motion - whether a lifetime in prison is more befitting than the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both, the nature of criminal activities and the very foundational values of human society, have undergone a significant evolution since Chekhov’s time. It would be myopic to confine the debate to which form of punishment is better or worse. It is only appropriate to subject the variables underlying the statement- which criminal activities deserve the highest of all culpable punishment? The age old debate gained a fresh lease of life with the U.S. Attorney General, William P Barr, clearing way for the federal government of the United States to resume executions of death row convicts after a lapse of nearly two decades. .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Debate raging Worldwide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Oxford English dictionary defines &lt;em&gt;death penalty&lt;/em&gt; as ‘the punishment of being killed that is used in some countries for very serious crimes’. Much to democrat Kamla Harris’s dismay, who regards death penalty as ‘immoral and deeply flawed’, the U.S. President Donald Trump had openly declared his support for capital punishment in 2018, at a rally in New Hampshire by stating that, “Drug dealers should be executed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might perhaps recall what Clive Stafford Smith, author of &lt;em&gt;The Injustice System&lt;/em&gt;,  had portrayed, with conviction, of an American lawyer who spent 28 years of his legal career in a futile attempt to save Kris Maharaj from the gallows. Maharaj, a British national, was subjected to an unfair trial for the death row, in Florida. Smith, through this case, successfully portrayed how often the judicial hierarchy, beginning from law enforcement agencies, often determines the final fate of many cases. He drew upon his own experiences, when he stated that a lawyer representing a private corporation harboured the potential of charging $1000 for an hour while for a death penalty often some of the best criminal lawyers would be payed $1000 for the whole case. The wage disparity invariably tantamounts to the difference in outcomes when it comes to a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the globe, 56 countries retain capital punishment and 106 countries have completely abolished it ‘de jure’. Article 2 of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union prohibits capital punishment. Incidentally (or rather ironically), 60% of the world’s population lives in countries where capital punishment still enjoys a legal stature. Most of the countries of the global south such as Saudi Arabia, Iran, Pakistan, Egypt, Sri Lanka and India fall under this category. With the exception of Belarus, all European countries have abolished the death penalty along with most of the Oceanian states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does death penalty really deter criminal instincts?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely accepted that awarding a death penalty for the commission of a crime sets a precedence for criminal acts of similar nature. In other words, it will serve as a warning for to-be criminals. An idea that can be precipitated is that, in earlier times, public executions were the norm of the day. The complete essence of fear would trickle down to the last man in the crowd, and have a direct psychological impact upon anyone harbouring such criminal instincts. However, with closed-door executions being the norm of the day such impact is no longer exercised. Justice Marshall with regard to the &lt;em&gt;Furman v. Georgia&lt;/em&gt;, in 1972, had clearly pronounced, “Capital punishment cannot be justified on the basis of its deterrent effect.” This was in direct contradiction to then US President Richard Nixon’s perception of capital punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As statistical and hard core factual evidence are necessary for informed policy making, a survey conducted by Thornsten Sellin regarding death penalty in 1959, and later in the data from Ruth Peterson and William Bailey’s paper entitled &lt;em&gt;Murder and Capital Punishment in the Evolving Context of the Post Furman Era&lt;/em&gt;, it was concluded that murder had been more common in states with capital punishment than in those where it’s not used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can death penalty be used solely as a tool of retribution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general notion harboured is “As you sow, so shall you reap.” The guilty deserve to be punished. The question that then arises is with respect to the severity of the punishment. It is absolutely in sync and coherent with our innate sense of morality and conscientious call for justice. However, the delay associated with the period of judicial trial leads to being kept in a condemned cell for a long span of time. This induces severe psychological trauma and stress, known as anticipatory suffering. Many argue life imprisonment truly succeeds in punishing an offender as death often comes as a welcome relief. The closure aspect to the victim’s kith and kin can’t be overlooked either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can the social security mechanism of law and police force be termed as infallible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most widely debated aspect remains whether the one who has extinguished another life deserves the right to live. And here comes the irreversible nature of death penalty. It was noted by former US Vice President, Joseph R Biden Jr, that since 1973, around 160 people who were sentenced to death were later exonerated. In India, a similar predicament was noted in September 2012 when 14 former judges of eminence had written to the then-Indian President Pranab Mukherjee. They had stated that seven of the judgements passed by the Supreme Court were rendered &lt;em&gt;in curium&lt;/em&gt;. Back in 1996 and 1997, as a consequence of flawed judgement, two prisoners- Ravji Rao and Surja Ramhad, were exonerated. These can be termed as nothing less than the most severe of miscarriages of justice- where men who ought to live were ‘killed’. Such is the power of capital punishment, which proves that no human rationale lies beyond human fallibility, and there’s no space for repentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is the verdict upon death penalty selective when it comes to final execution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another widely accepted argument remains that the death penalty is often biased towards individuals belonging to minority segments of the society. The racial, ethnic and geographical prejudice often plays the role of a triggering factor when it comes to ascertaining the final verdict. It usually comes down harsher upon the working class and marginalised groups, perhaps due to lack of resources, or rather to pander to majoritarian populism. In January 2008, the University of Maryland concluded in a study, commissioned by the Governor of Maryland, that defendants were at a greater risk to be sentenced to death if they had killed a white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hugely controversial case revolving around &lt;em&gt;Dhananjay Chatterjee V. The State of West Bengal&lt;/em&gt; (1994) widely spruced up a similar notion in India when the plaintiff himself reportedly stated “Since I’m poor, I’m being falsely accused.” Chatterjee had allegedly raped and murdered a teenager in Calcutta, in 1990. In October 2013, Patna High Court in Bihar, India acquitted 26 accused for the murder of 58 dalits (who in the Indian caste hierarchy are regarded as ‘lower castes’) in the Jehanabad district of Bihar in December, 2007. Thus the question of selective justice arises naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, post the &lt;em&gt;Bachan Singh v. State of Punjab&lt;/em&gt; (1980), the Supreme court clarified that the death penalty is to be awarded only in cases which could be termed as ‘rarest of rare’. Taking appropriate steps, like ensuring the death penalty clause is not used for political gains, death warrants are executed within a stipulated time limit and provision of equal legal aid to the accused regardless of socio-economic stature are some of the measures that will help ensure equity and justice to the charged persons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the title of Earnest Raymonds 1930’s seminal work, &lt;em&gt;We, the Accused&lt;/em&gt;, surprises everyone with its underlying irony where the social political system is the real accused, which breeds a criminal. An Amnesty International report sums it up, “Since Canada stopped executing, the murder rate has dropped by 44%.” However, the geopolitical and socio-economic factors of specific countries too demand significant consideration before taking a radical step such as abolishing capital punishment all together.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the 1889 short story, The Bet, Anton Chekhov, a Russian writer, subtly raised one of those deeply divisive questions that has been plaguing humankind since the dawn of civilisation. Through the depiction of an altercation between a young lawyer and a banker, who engage in a fierce battle of wits, he brought forward the motion - whether a lifetime in prison is more befitting than the death penalty.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
