<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/oyeshi.ganguly/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-10T07:05:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/oyeshi.ganguly/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Treat for the Corporate Sharks or Autonomy in Indian Agriculture?</title>
      <link href="/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Treat for the Corporate Sharks or Autonomy in Indian Agriculture?" />
      <published>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Farmer’s bills will create a vacuum that may result in utter chaos.”&lt;/em&gt; - P Sainath, Founder of People’s Archive of Rural India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest source of livelihood in India is agriculture. A whopping 70% of the rural households consider agriculture to be the primary source of their subsistence. Among them, 82% of farmers are engaged as small or marginal agriculturists. An economy which is majorly dependent on farmlands has witnessed unprecedented upheaval in the wake of the passing of the Farmers Bill 2020. Perhaps even more surprising is the polarised public opinion pertaining to it. While it has been welcomed by certain sections of the public, others have expressed stiff opposition to it. The displeasure wasn’t just restricted to the contents of the bill but also to the manner in which it was passed. Many regard it as a move towards a unitarian bias of the Indian State and a blow to federalism. The Minister of Food Processing Industries in the Narendra Modi Government, Harsimrat Kaur Badal, resigned from the Union Cabinet as a mark of protest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the Farmers Bill 2020?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It refers to a collection of three bills dealing with agriculture market reforms that have been passed in mid-September 2020. These draft laws aim to change the existing procedures laid down for the sale, marketing and storage of agricultural produce across the nation. They were passed by voice vote in both the houses of the Indian Parliament - Lok Sabha (the lower house) and the Rajya Sabha (the upper house), during the monsoon session, much to the chagrin of the opposition. The first bill termed as ‘The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill 2020’ allows the farmer to sell his or her produce outside the allotted Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; (marketplace) without having to pay any State taxes. The second bill ‘Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement on Price Assurance and Farm Services Ordinance 2020’ assists in the method of contract farming and empowers the farmer to pursue direct marketing. The final bill ‘The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Ordinance 2020’ ensures the deregulation of the production, storage, movement and the sale of essential food crops such as cereals, pulses, edible oils and onion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Ayes v/s the Nays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones supporting this measure argue that it ensures a greater autonomy of the farmers in terms of the sellers dismantling the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; system (agricultural market system). The government believes that this will invite private sector investments and help in the building of infrastructure and supply chains for agricultural harvest in both national and global markets. Further, it might assist small farmers who may not be in a position to negotiate a bargain or invest in superior technology to improve the quality of their harvest. Moreover, farmers are expected to sell their produce at a better price than the fixed price they have to sell at an APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt;. Market competition and cost-cutting on transportation may facilitate greater profits. The private investments are likely to help in fetching better technological support that a marginal farmer may not have been able to afford prior to the process of privatisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones opposing the bill including regional/national opposition parties such as Indian National Congress and All India Trinamool Congress (TMC) have highlighted the cons and believe it has the power to reverse the benefits bestowed by the Indian Green Revolution of the 1960’s. They have been interestingly opposing the bill on the same ground that the government seeks to promote it - “the interests of small and marginal farmers”. They believe that the farmer may not be able to choose his seller due to the lack of knowledge of negotiation if &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; were rendered redundant, the lack of bargaining power of the farmer when compared with corporate giants might force him to sell his harvest at a far lesser price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their biggest concern stems from the farmers being deprived of the minimum support price (MSP). MSP is a pre-set rate at which the Central Government purchases certain crops such as paddy, wheat and select pulses from the farmers, irrespective of the market rate. These predetermined rates are usually declared at the beginning of each sowing season for the 23 crops which fall under this list. The fact that the Anti-Farmers Bill Protests have been most fervent in Punjab and Haryana may be due to the fact that most government procurement centres are located within the notified APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. Farmers are wary of the fact that encouraging tax-free private trade will lead to a slow and natural demise of the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; thereby leading to a reduction of government procurement. Instead, the farmers demand a universalisation of the minimum support price which will compel the government as well as private players to incorporate these rates as a floor price. There has also been a general concern about the fate of the middlemen as their role in the chain has been rendered obsolete under the new laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The APMC structure consists of two parts - a strong market network where farmers have been selling their produce for decades and have established a familiarity among themselves, a connection between commission agents (known as &lt;em&gt;arthiyas&lt;/em&gt;) who further the cause of procurements. These two antagonistic structures are connected by roads which run from the villages to the notified APMC markets. Most of the private buyers are small traders at local &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; - they face an uncertain financial future as farmers will be directly selling their produce to corporates and industrialists, and the small traders might financially not be in a position to compete with the bigwigs. This is furthered by the provisions of the Essential Commodities Act which removes the ceiling on stock limits thereby allowing bulk purchase and storage - a treat for the corporate players. Thus, the idea of the corporatisation of the agricultural sector has been a major point of hue and cry across the nation. Monopolisation of agriculture where the business houses may attempt to minimise costs would vitiate the farmers’ interests. There has been a concern about growing input costs which the farmers had to bear - trampled between rising expenditure that cultivation demands and the sluggish prices on the other hand. Moreover, the hoarding of the harvest can prompt the industrialists to create artificial shortages and sell the produce later at an exorbitant price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Political Angle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a greater political angle to this debate centering around the question of a gradual smothering of federalism. Out of the three lists in the Seventh Schedule of the Indian Constitution - Union, State and Concurrent lists, agriculture falls under the State list. The State Governments’ believe that it doesn’t lie within the ambit of the Central Government’s authority to legislate upon a subject beyond its jurisdiction. As per this case of &lt;em&gt;Union of India v HS Dhillon&lt;/em&gt; (1972), the constitutionality of parliamentary laws may be challenged on two grounds - first, the subject is in the State list and second, it violates fundamental rights. The state’s loss of revenue from &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; taxes which used to enter the state treasury ranged from being as high as 8.5% in Punjab to being as low as 1% in some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the bill was passed by the Chair in Rajya Sabha, where states are represented, on the basis of a voice vote, refusing to consider repeated demands by the members for a division vote on the statutory resolution. Motions moved by certain left-wing parties to refer the bills to the select standing committees were also rejected. Thus, a violation of the federal principle upon which the very idea of Indian polity is established seemed to have received a jolt. The State Governments of Kerala and Punjab have declared that they shall challenge the bill in the Indian Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission Agent’s market fee and rural development fee are 3% and 2% in Punjab and Haryana respectively. For these states, which are the epicentre of these protests, the biggest sources of state revenue are these additional fees. Thus, financial subordination of the state governments seems like a bitter compromise on their part. These two states estimate a loss of ₹35 billion and ₹16 billion annually, respectively. However, similar to the concept of separation of powers and constitutionalism, the word federalism is not explicitly mentioned in the Indian Constitution. But it is a convention enmeshed in the essence of our constitutional scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is probably wise to look into the prevalent frameworks in some other nations all across the globe. The French dairy producers and the dairy farmers co-operatives in the United States have gained power over the years. A number of buyer cartels fix the price and this has forced the European Union and the US to introspect at the existing mechanisms of their own supply chains and to reduce their consolidative powers. Many believe that corporations may target the grain market as there are more than 90 million tons of food grain in Indian stocks and this might be a lucrative option for big money players. Under the Second Bill which permits contract farming, farmers will produce crops as per contracts with corporate investors for a mutually agreed remuneration. Farmers remain extremely sceptical, with very justifiable reasons, about the Farmers Bill 2020 which has received the assent of Indian President Ram Nath Kovind in late September. This has been largely dubbed as a ‘death warrant’ for poor farmers against the Prime Minister’s declaration of the bills as a ‘watershed moment’ for the Indian Agricultural Community. It remains to be seen whether the trio of bills is a boon or a bane, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Farmer’s bills will create a vacuum that may result in utter chaos.” - P Sainath, Founder of People’s Archive of Rural India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution</title>
      <link href="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important debates raging in American society and polity for decades has been the issue of Gun Control. The nature of the resultant deaths has varied from 21,175 suicides, 11,208 homicides, and 505 deaths due to accidental or negligent discharge of a firearm used with “undetermined intent”. These statistics signify a deep-rooted problem plaguing the question of ownership and control of a gun. A genuine question may arise as to whether this problem is individually only affecting the United States. Seems like it is indeed a cause of concern as compared to 22 other high-income nations, the US Gun-related homicide rate is 25 times higher. Among them, the phenomenon of ‘school shootings’, leading to students preparing for active shooter drills, is huddling in silence as if hiding from an imaginary gunman is a regular phenomenon. This has also been responsible for eleven assassination attempts on the US Presidents, with four “successful” encounters. These heinous incidents have a racist undertone also as research indicates that African Americans, who were only 13% of the US population, were 55% of the victims of gun homicide. Surprisingly, the roots of this problem can be located in the US Constitution itself. The arguments gain a fresh lease of life before every Presidential election with the Democrats demanding stricter gun laws and the Republicans pointing to the Second Amendment and self-defence shooting. President Donald Trump had said that he favoured background checks in the days immediately following shootings in El Paso and Dayton, however, Republican majority opinion regards gun control as a dangerous infringement of personal liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Locating the Origin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the root of this controversy, one needs to travel back in time to the ratification of the Second Amendment to the US Constitution ratified on December 15, 1791. It states “&lt;em&gt;A well-regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep or bear arms, shall not be infringed&lt;/em&gt;.” It is the wording of this very statement from which most of the controversy has been generated. While a section of Americans believes that the phrase “the right of the people to keep and bear Arms” aligns with the individualist notion, they think that any legislative body prohibiting firearm possession is unconstitutional. On the other hand, the opposition believes in the “Collective Rights Theory” which states that citizens do not have an individual right to possess guns and that local, state, and federal legislative bodies possess the authority to regulate firearms without the infringement of a constitutional right. Most US Courts had until the early 21st century understood it to guarantee the right of states to maintain militias or the right of individuals to keep or bear arms. However, this was to be strictly in connection with their service in a state militia, an interpretation that was consistent with a wide variety of existing restrictions on individual gun ownership and use. The 1939 judgment in the case of &lt;em&gt;United States v Miller&lt;/em&gt; too spoke in the same tune. The US Supreme Court held that the Second Amendment didn’t prohibit laws requiring the registration of sawed-off guns under the clause “reasonable relationship to the preservation or efficiency of a well-regulated militia”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2008 &lt;em&gt;District of Columbia v Heller&lt;/em&gt; judgment is considered to be a landmark. The plaintiff in &lt;em&gt;Heller&lt;/em&gt; had challenged the constitutionality of the Washington DC handgun ban. In a turn of events that shook global consciousness, the court delivered a 5-4 decision reiterating the history of the Second Amendment establishing an individual right for US Citizens to possess firearms and struck down the DC handgun ban as a violation of that right. It additionally stated that the Court would not disallow regulations prohibiting criminals and the mentally ill from firearm possession. In the 2010 decision of &lt;em&gt;McDonald v The City of Chicago&lt;/em&gt;, the plaintiff challenged the constitutionality of the Chicago Handgun ban which prohibited handgun possessions by almost all private citizens. The Court held that this interpretation of the Amendment was applicable against state and local gun control laws as well as against federal statutes. Thus, one can trace how over the course of time, gun control laws have undergone a complete transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Current American Scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common argument in favour of the unregulated possession of firearms includes the idea that law-abiding citizens can defend themselves against armed criminals. After the mass shootings at a Walmart Store in El Paso, Texas which left 20 individuals dead, there was a marked change in the attitude of young Americans towards Gun Control. A study conducted by Pew Research Centre in 2019, after the Parkland School Shooting in 2018, said that support for gun control was the highest among 18 to 29-year-olds. These findings further suggest that one-third of over 50s admitted to owning a gun. The rate of gun ownership was lower for younger adults at 28%. The Las Vegas attack in 2017 is regarded as one of the deadliest in American history marked by the death of 58 individuals. One of the reasons for these mass shootings can be attributed to the cheap prices at which firearms are available all over the US. The handguns used by Stephen Paddock, the Las Vegas shooter, were priced at $200 while assault rifles come at a price of $1500. Some states have taken measures to lessen this social menace. One such example is California which has banned around 75 types and models of assault weapons. There is a divide among the Republicans and the Democrats on the issue of “concealed carry policy”. This refers to the idea of whether allowing ordinary citizens increased rights to carry concealed weapons. One of the most stringent oppositions to gun control comes from the National Rifle Association (NRA), a very powerful interest group in the US. Interestingly, these groups also possess a substantial budget to influence members of Congress on gun policy. A significant Republican section in the United States is reported to be members of the NRA. This corroborates with NRA’s spending going uphill- from $3 million per year to more than $5 million in 2017. The NRA also supports the election campaigns of political candidates who oppose gun controls. They propagate against all forms of gun control arguing that more guns make the country safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gun Control laws are expected to reduce the societal costs associated with gun violence. More than 100,000 people are shot in the United States every year, and they generate emergency room and hospital charges of nearly $3 billion. Barack Obama in response to the January 2013 Sandy Hook Elementary School Shooting had announced a 4-parter for reducing gun violence: closing background check loopholes, banning assault weapons and large-capacity magazines, increasing access to mental services, and making schools safer. One of the important ideas behind gun safety laws include conducting a thorough background check-up of the person to whom the gun is being sold. Individuals with mental health problems or criminal backgrounds shouldn’t be allowed to possess weapons. Only a dozen of the US’ 50 states require purchase permits (Federal Firearms License - FFL) for handguns. Of those states, only California, Connecticut and Hawaii require permits for the purchase of rifles and shotguns. However, there is a major loophole in the entire body of Gun Control law. According to the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (ATF), anyone can sell a gun without an FFL from their home, online, or even at a flea market or at a gun show as long as he or she is not conducting the sale as part of regular business activity. Thus, selling a firearm from his or her personal collection or gifting a gun is beyond the reach of the law. The baseline being, only those individuals whose “principal motive” is to obtain a profit via the sale will be bound to obtain an FFL. Thus children under the age of 18, a person with felony charges, and mentally ill individuals may also possess guns that were given to them by their parents as gifts. This corroborates with a 2017 survey conducted by Harvard University which estimates that one in every five transactions occurs without a proper background check. It is the need of the hour to amend the constitution with regard to the Second Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the US awaits its Presidential elections in 2020, the Biden-Trump clashes rise again on the issue of Gun Control, dividing opinions and voices for and against a gun-free America. It gains relevance as a burning issue as on September 2, 2020, two seventeen-year-olds were killed in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. This has become a malady with its tentacles spread across America.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO</title>
      <link href="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO" />
      <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”&lt;/em&gt;, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included &lt;em&gt;“And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”&lt;/em&gt;. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NATO was founded in 1949 with a total of 30 members. The members include nations from North America (Canada and the United States) and 28 of the European countries. Its military nature is profoundly indicated by Article 5 of the treaty which states that in the occurrence of an attack against any one of the member states, it shall be understood to have been an attack against all members. This ensures the assistance of all the other member nations against the common adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) formed what was known as the Warsaw Pact in 1955 that included the Eastern Bloc Socialist Republics of Central and Eastern Europe. It was a collective defence treaty created as a reaction to the integration of West Germany into NATO. After the end of the Cold War and consequent nullification of the Warsaw Pact, NATO added 14 more member nations – 10 of them included in the Warsaw Pact and 4 former Yugoslav Republics. Some of the important operations undertaken by NATO include the defence of Denmark and Norway during September 1952, Exercise Longstep in the Mediterranean sea, Exercise Campaign Reforger which was an annual exercise by NATO states during the Cold War, and Exercise Strikeback which was a naval exercise that took place over a ten-day period in September 1957. The Northern Wedding had been another significant naval military exercise aimed at examining NATOs ability to reinforce Europe militarily during the Cold War in 1978. The latest development arrived in the form of DEFENDER-Europe 20 which was a US-led multinational exercise which included NATO’s participation. Notably, it was the largest deployment of US-based forces to Europe in the last quarter of a century. It included the participation of 20,000 soldiers deployed directly from the US to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Aspersions on NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ascent of Donald Trump in US national politics birthed a characteristic nationalistic, isolationist tendency, popularly termed as the ‘America First Policy’. It has been manifested in his scathing takes on multilateral organisations which include the United Nations (UN), and more recently the World Health Organisation (WHO) in the background of the coronavirus pandemic. Thus it comes as no surprise that he had been a stringent opponent to the very fundamental notions that have contributed to the formation of NATO. The &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; had reported that President Trump had on more than one occasion expressed desires to pull the US out of NATO. There are three primary reasons for his efforts to distance the US from this treaty - nearly 70% of the total spending on defence by NATO governments is accounted for by the US. In terms of the US Gross Domestic Product (GDP), the US spent roughly 3.4% on defence in 2019, while the average in European NATO countries and Canada was 1.55%. Naturally, Trump considers NATO to be an extra drain upon the military budget. NATO is funded by a common funding arrangement determined by each country’s national income. NATO had stated that the civilian and military budget for 2019 was $1.84 billion, out of which the US was paying 22%, France and the UK paid around 10.5% and Germany about 14.76%. The other alliance members contributed for the rest. This had caused bilateral relations between the US and Germany to worsen, as Trump, while referring to the burden shouldered by the US criticised the Germans for being “delinquent” in their payment to NATO. Trump further stated that the US shall move 12,000 troops out of the country. Jens Stoltenberg, the NATO Secretary-General had stated, &lt;em&gt;“We have now agreed (on) a new formula for sharing costs. The US will pay less. Germany will pay more”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem lies in the fact that the US, being a global superpower, has military commitments around the world and is not restricted to the geographical area of Europe and North America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the US deploys tens of thousands of active-duty personnel in Europe including in Turkey. The US diplomatic commitments in Europe also include a missile defence system run by NATO members. This is designed to shield against potential long-range ballistic missile attacks from outside the continent. Thus, the active presence of both men and arms is required on the part of the US. For the US President, all these factors are more of a display of magnanimity than a tool of diplomatic leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is important to note that a Chicago Council Survey in 2014 said that 78% of the American public supports NATO, 66% believed that the US commitment to NATO should remain as it is, as opposed to 7% supporting the possibility of a withdrawal. Thus the question of whether it is time to ring the death knell of NATO has its fair share of nay-sayers and aye-sayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Consequences in a World without NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the possible dissolution of the 71-year-old organisation, there will be a risk of Russian aggression. Many diplomats believe that had the post-Soviet Baltic nations which did not join NATO would have already been occupied by Russian expansionist aims. In the absence of NATO, mutual security interests such as combating ISIS and other global defence attempts emanating from coalition operations would be severely jeopardised. NATO’s retirement has the possibility to exacerbate divisions within Europe, especially in a post-Brexit, weakened European Union. The disappearance of NATO might make America’s Asian partners side with a rising China. Moreover, it will greatly strengthen the Russian Federation, which will reclaim the East European states which were formerly a part of the USSR. The clear political gainers would be Russia and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the question remains: To be or not to be? Amer-Exit from NATO and the consequent dissolution of NATO? Or a fundamental rebuilding exercise is that shall salvage the organisation that has maintained relative stability in the trans-Atlantic region?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included “And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Whose Land Is It Anyway?: Charting The Kalapani Dispute and its Implications on Indo-Nepal Relations</title>
      <link href="/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Whose Land Is It Anyway?: Charting The Kalapani Dispute and its Implications on Indo-Nepal Relations" />
      <published>2020-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We are working to ensure territorial integrity, national sovereignty, and freedom of our people. The kings of Nepal lost our territory, but today we republicans are restoring it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announced by Pushpa Kamal Dahal Prachanda, the co-Chair of the Nepal Communist Party on June 13, 2020, amid loud applauses at the Pratinidhi Sabha (the Lower House of the Nepalese Parliament), the declaration comes at the occasion marking the passage of the Second Constitution Amendment Bill which ensures legitimacy to the updated political map of Nepal. It had been at the eye of a diplomatic storm for including Indian territory within the periphery of Nepalese borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian territory of Limpyadhura, Kalapani, the strategically vital Lipulekh pass, all located in the Pithoragarh district of the Indian state of Uttarakhand have been shown as parts of Nepalese territory. The Indian Ministry of External Affairs has regarded the bill as an encroachment into the sovereignty of the Indian territory as they refer to it as an “artificial enlargement” in an official statement. The bill, which was passed by the approval of 258 members present and voting, out of the total strength of 275 members, has strained the otherwise good bilateral ties between India and Nepal. The upper house of the Nepalese Parliament, the National Assembly had been unanimous in its support for the bill, with all 57 members present voting in its favour on June 18, 2020. The die had been cast when the bill providing for the inclusion of Nepal’s new political map had been approved in its national emblem. The final move has sparked fierce criticism on a “sensitive issue”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The origins of the row&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that this diplomatic uncertainty was birthed through a 200-year-old treaty, the Treaty of Sugauli, that had formally established the boundaries of Nepal. The treaty had been signed on December 2, 1815, between the East India Company and Rajguru Gararaj Mishra with Chandra Sekhar Upadhyaya in the aftermath of the Anglo-Nepalese War of 1814-16. The interpretation of the treaty has been one of the primary causes of the present conflict. According to the treaty, the Eastern side of the river Kali falls within Nepal’s territory while the Western bank lies in India. The trouble brews from a common misinterpretation as Nepal considers Limpiyadhura as the origin of river Kali, thereby forwarding the claim that Limpyadhura, Lipulekh and Kalapani belong to their dominion. The advocates of the Indian cause, on the other hand, state that the origin of river Kali is Kalapani, which is an area located within Indian borders. The two regions of Susta and Kalapani cover 40 km of the Indo-Nepal border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assets-api.kathmandupost.com/thumb.php?src=https://assets-cdn.kathmandupost.com/uploads/source/news/2020/opinion/Kali-map-for-Naresh.jpg&amp;amp;w=900&amp;amp;height=601&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/indianepalmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cartographic dispute had earlier raised its ugly head, when on November 2, 2019, the Indian government had put up a new political map of the nation, depicting the reorganisation of Jammu and Kashmir, with a vivid depiction of the disputed Kalapani region exactly as it had been before. There had been allegations by the Nepalese government that in spite of twin reminders for restarting a foreign secretary-level dialogue mechanism between the two nations, India had not agreed to fix a date for the bilateral talks. Many quarters have regarded it as a fallout of the Nepalese Prime Minister KP Sharma Oli’s proximity to China. The Nepal government had expressed demands to publish their own new map which aimed at incorporating the disputed sites in their own fold. Oli had dismissed such claims on November 16 in the face of contrary claims put forward by Padma Aryal, the Nepalese cabinet minister for land and poverty alleviation who asserted that Nepal would soon come out with a new map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to a shift in priorities of both governments in the face of health security challenges imposed by COVID-19, the matter had been erased from public memory. But it resurfaced with a May 8 tweet by the Indian Defence Minister Rajnath Singh. Singh had laid emphasis on his inauguration of the blacktop road to Lipulekh pass, which had been under construction for 8 years. The Nepalese government in Kathmandu claimed that 19 km of the said road extended to Lipulekh, which according to their claims had been a part of Nepalese territory. It was seen as an attempt on the part of India to make an illegitimate claim on a nation’s territory, a violation of its absolute sovereignty. Populist rhetoric amplified the notion. The Chief of the Indian Army staff, M M Naravane (who is also the honorary General of the Nepal Army) went on to say that the Nepalese protests were being conducted under the behest of “another country” primarily indicating China. Nepalese Defence Minister Ishwor Pokhrel replied to this saying that the comments had been an “insulting statement”, resulting out of ignorance of Nepal’s history, freedom and social characteristics. He further made an allusion to the sentiments of Nepali Gurkha army personnel, a majority of whom are engaged in the Indian Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Diplomatic Ramifications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Nepali Parliament, Oli had reiterated the intention to reclaim the Indian territory, referring to it as being under the ‘occupation’ of the latter. However, his derogatory jibes at the Indian national emblem, manifesting in his controversial remark wondering if India subscribed to the physical aspect of the emblem - the Lion Capital of Ashoka - &lt;em&gt;“simhaev jayate’’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;“satyamev jayate”&lt;/em&gt; (truth alone prevails), led to a deepening of the diplomatic rife between the two otherwise conciliatory foreign policies pursued by the two nations. The issue had been in the priority list of the Nepalese Government ever since Oli’s second term in power began in 2018. New Delhi in spite of its repeated emphasis on the ‘Neighbourhood First’ policy had turned a blind eye. A dent in the mutual relationship between the two had begun to deepen since 2015 when Oli’s government had promulgated Nepal’s new Constitution, widely dubbed by India as flawed since it didn’t include the political aspirations of individuals from the Terai region - Madhesis and Tharus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The border blockade by the Madhesis that followed had allegedly received “Indian support”, according to Oli’s government. It is believed in diplomatic circles that although no evidence of Chinese connection or support has been found in the formulation of the border dispute, Oli is confident of Chinese support in further provoking India. Many believe this stance of his is a result of the turmoil in Nepal’s domestic policy. Oli may be trying to outdo his friend-turned-foe, Pushpa Kumar Dahal Prachanda, creating a scenario that might jeopardise a smooth diplomatic exchange with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need of the hour is to revive diplomatic channels between the two nations. Kalapani continues to be an important area of dispute due to the presence of an Indian military post present there. Kalapani has massive strategic importance to India as it shares a border on the North with the Tibet Autonomous Region of China, and Nepal in the East and South. It falls on the route to Mansarovar, a pilgrimage site in Tibet. It helps India in tracking Chinese movements in the region. The Lipulekh pass, on the other hand, had been an ancient route of trade and pilgrimage but had been temporarily closed following the Indo-China War of 1962. Options to ensure joint sovereignty can be taken as a way out, in times of such a major cartographic dispute. The idea of negotiation had been echoed in 1999, when the then Indian Prime Minister, I K Gujral had said &lt;em&gt;“If Nepal can prove Kalapani belongs to it, we will give it up”&lt;/em&gt;. However, the task of locating the source of a boundary river, coupled with a watershed, remains a Herculean task.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We are working to ensure territorial integrity, national sovereignty, and freedom of our people. The kings of Nepal lost our territory, but today we republicans are restoring it.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair: Afghanistan’s War Within</title>
      <link href="/Fair-is-Foul" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair: Afghanistan's War Within" />
      <published>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Fair-is-Foul</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fair-is-Foul">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When Daesh came to our area, they killed a lot of people because they said we would have helped the Taliban. But now the Taliban have returned and they are saying we helped the Daesh.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Masooma, resident of the Aqsa Area of Darzab (as stated in a &lt;em&gt;Reuters&lt;/em&gt; report)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masooma’s desperate predicament is a perfect one-liner to highlight the political chaos of present-day Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 12, 2020, a crowd of gunmen stormed the Doctors Without Borders (Médecins Sans Frontières) administered maternity clinic at Dashti Barchi, in the western part of the capital of Afghanistan, Kabul, leaving 24 people dead including two new-born babies. The attack drew condemnation from nations across the globe, with the Amnesty International South Asia, regarding them as “The unconscionable war crimes in Afghanistan targeting a maternity hospital and a funeral, must awaken the world to the horrors civilians continue to face.” ISIL (the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant) had claimed responsibility for the barbaric attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About two months prior to the attack on the hospital, on March 25, 2020, assassins raided the Gurdwara Har Rai Saheb in Kabul, Afghanistan killing 25 Sikh worshippers. ISIL subsequently stated its explicit support for the bloodbath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two subsequent events can be said to have been a part of the broader picture in the spectrum of Afghanistan’s war within its frontiers. These attacks are examples from the series of ongoing battles for supremacy between ISIL and the Taliban in their bid to exercise supremacy and dominance over the nation. Its significance is further highlighted as they come within months of the US-Taliban peace deal in February at Doha ending their 18-year long conflict, the roots of which can be traced back to the immediate aftermath of 9/11 and the global war on terror. However, the deal came with a resounding foreboding by the US President Donald Trump, who announced that “If bad things happen, we will go back with a force like no one’s ever seen”. Mike Pompeo, US Secretary of State had made it clear to the militant group to “keep your [their] promises to cut ties with al-Qaeda”. It is interesting to note, a UN Assistance Mission in Afghanistan report (May 2020) had said that since the signing of the peace deal, civil casualties caused by the Afghan government and the Taliban-ISIL conflicts have escalated by more than a quarter when compared with the same month in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Background&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Taliban-ISIL conflict is a phrase used to denote an ongoing armed conflict between the factions of ISIL in Afghanistan, besides counting those within its ambit, groups affiliated with ISIL, and splintered factions of the Taliban, generally opposed to the primary power loci in the central Taliban organisational hierarchy. The conflict may have been said to have begun on November 11, 2015, when fighting began between assailants who were loyal to Akhtar Mansoor, the new Taliban leader, and Mullah Mansoor Dadullah, who exhibited a tilt in favour of the pro-ISIL faction. This fragment received enormous aid from ISIL, including arms and men from Chechnya and Uzbekistan. The turf war ended with the triumph of Mansoor’s faction over that of Dadullah. More than 100 lives on both sides were lost in Southern Afghanistan, as reported by the provincial director of security in Kabul’s Arghandab district. The next year was marked by Muhammad Rasul leading the ISIL faction against the Mansoor loyalists. However, the war escalated from the month of April in 2017 onwards and gained international attention, with the ISIL capturing drug dealers who had been reportedly selling opium in the Jowzjan province. The drug pedlars had alleged Taliban connections. The connections came to light, with the clashes erupting between groups of the Taliban and the ISIL faction to ensure the forcible release of the three drug dealers, who were paying 10 million Afghanis to the Taliban to clinch a deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May 24 marked the largest clash between the two hostile entities near the border shared between Afghanistan and Iran. It had been sparked off by an attack on the ISIL camp by the Taliban, who had agreed not to enter into armed struggle prior to mutual dialogue. An ISIL commander had reportedly told NBC News that the Taliban was entering into a coordinated alliance with the Iranian Military and receiving generous support from them. Fidai Mahaz, also known as the Sacrifice Front, led by Mullah Najibullah, a Taliban splinter group had been strongly opposed to the Taliban-Iran nexus, claiming that the Taliban had received $3 million in cash, 3,000 arms and 40 trucks and ammunition from the Iran government to wage a war against ISIL. The Iranian government implied that they were concerned about the steady gain of territory by ISIL and their increasing status in Afghanistan affected the regional security of Iran; 2018 marked by the Battle of Darzab, in which the Taliban and the Islamic State, in the Khorasan province, engaged in conflict for hegemony over the Darzab district in the Jowzjan province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the June talks between the Russian government and the Taliban, the US criticised the Russian position of extending support to the Taliban to defeat ISIL as they believed it granted legitimacy to the Taliban, discrediting the recognised Afghan government. The resultant fighting left 3,500-7,000 civilians homeless and thousands dead on either side. However, by early August, ISIL’s hold was reduced to two villages, with most ISIL fighters pleading for clemency and protection from the Afghan government against the Taliban. The US-Taliban negotiation in 2018 echoed the Taliban’s plea to end US airstrikes as well as to provide support to combat splinter groups and ISIL. Last year marked heavy clashes at Kunar, with ISIL circulating photos of weapons captured from the Taliban, followed by a video of the fighters renewing their oath to Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi criticising the prospect of US-Taliban peace talks. Further, on October 1, ISIL claimed to have killed 20 Taliban soldiers in Tora Bora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What lies ahead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deeper dig into the causes of conflict between ISIL and the Taliban go beyond the primary causes for the fight to secure more land in accordance with Dabiq, the Islamic State manifesto, since ideology and long term objectives between the two differ strongly. ISIL (or ISIS in the broader spectrum) aims at establishing an Islamic Caliphate worldwide, while the Taliban aims to secure an Islamic State, ruled by Quranic law or their own interpretation of the Shariat. Hence, there can be increasing speculation about the future of Afghanistan, post the US-Afghan peace talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US-Afghan peace deal may result in ironical consequences which might include an increase in the membership of ISIL, as a major chunk of the Taliban foot soldiers who would be dissatisfied with the peace negotiations might join ISIL. It might have a significant impact on the Southeast Asian nations too, with many nations including India eyeing the Taliban with suspicion as a terrorist group and refusing to engage in bilateral or multilateral talks with obvious specifics towards its stand on the Kashmir issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question lingers whether a civil war is imminent in Afghan soil in the decades to come if ISIL strengthens itself or if it is an improbability, or whether a war with obvious outcomes is going to ensue, now that US assistance may help the Taliban in their war against ISIL. The world meanwhile grapples with the timeless words of the three witches in &lt;em&gt;Macbeth&lt;/em&gt;, “Fair is Foul, Foul is Fair”, as US special envoy Zalmay Khalilzad defends the Taliban and their efforts to achieve “peace”, the same Taliban with whom they waged an 18-year long battle. So in diplomacy, fair or foul whichever you choose, (that is if you don’t consider them to be the two sides of the same coin), the great gamble for Afghanistan proceeds between ISIL, Taliban, and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“When Daesh came to our area, they killed a lot of people because they said we would have helped the Taliban. But now the Taliban have returned and they are saying we helped the Daesh.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India’s Tryst with Autocracy</title>
      <link href="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India's Tryst with Autocracy" />
      <published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence">&lt;p&gt;It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the declaration of a national emergency in mid-1975, in accordance with Article 352 of the Indian Constitution, Mrs Gandhi instigated the nation’s total suspension of fundamental rights and every outlet of democratic expression. The Indian Emergency refers to the 21-month period that continues to be recounted as one of the darkest chapters in the modern political historiography of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What led to the imposition of the Indian Emergency?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency shouldn’t be considered an overnight development, but rather a culmination of a significant number of factors. Throughout the end of the 1960’s and the early 1970’s, there had been a gradual rise in the predominance of Parliamentary Sovereignty in India over the judiciary. Besides this, the early 1970’s had been characterised by widespread political unrest. The Naxalbari movement in West Bengal had met with severe state oppression through ‘The Operation Steeplechase’ among other government measures, the Nav Nirman movement in Gujarat (December 1973 - March 1974) led to the imposition of Central Government-rule on the state under Article 356 of the Indian Constitution. Amidst the prevailing political turmoil, there had been widespread dissatisfaction against the agents of the ruling order, particularly the Union Ministers, who are in many ways the most direct representatives of the ruling regime. Lalit Narayan Mishra, the Union Rail Minister was killed by a bomb on January 3, 1975.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most significant political mobilisation took place in April 1974, when a student agitation by the Chatra Sangharsh Samiti (Student Agitation Organisation) led by the Gandhian Socialist Jayaprakash Narayan and his call for “total revolution” to sweep away corruption, gained mass popularity. A significant ramification of the JP movement had been the nationwide strike organised by the railway employees union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raj Narain verdict had been the final nail in the coffin of the Indira Gandhi government which had been in power since 1966, almost 10 years. Mrs Gandhi had defeated Raj Narain in the 1971 Parliamentary elections from the constituency of Rae Bareily. He had filed cases accusing the Prime Minister of election fraud and malpractice along with the use of state machinery for election purposes in the Allahabad High Court. On June 12, 1975, Mr Justice Jagmohan Lal Sinha found Mrs Gandhi guilty of the said charges. The Supreme Court upheld the verdict and ordered a steady withdrawal of all privileges that Mrs Gandhi had received as a member of the Indian Parliament whilst depriving her of the right to vote in the lower house. The following day Narain had organised a rally in Delhi where he had reportedly proclaimed that the instruments of the state machinery, particularly the police, must reject the orders of a government which were immoral, corrupt and unethical. Widely interpreted as an instigation to spark a rebellion, it led to Mrs Gandhi declaring the Emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency was marked by an absolute suspension of the Fundamental Rights mentioned in Part III of the Indian Constitution. Mrs Gandhi had devised a ‘25-point economic programme’ which aimed at, inter alia, poverty eradication, restructuring of the public services, boosting agricultural and industrial production. Mrs Gandhi’s heir apparent and a leader of the Indian National Congress, Sanjay Gandhi, had contributed to it with his own programme of literacy, family planning, planting of trees, literacy promotion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Emergency, the opposition leaders were placed under preventive detention including Jayaprakash Narayan, Charan Singh and Atal Vihari Vajpayee (later Indian Prime Minister in 1997), Lal Krishna Advani, Arun Jaitley, Gayatri Devi, Queen Mother of the erstwhile princely state of Jaipur, Morarji Desai (later 4th Prime Minister of India in 1977-1979). Some prominent leaders of the Indian National Congress including Chandra Sekhar, who had resigned from Mrs Gandhi’s cabinet, were arrested and placed under detention as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, the 42nd Amendment Act which had rewritten the Indian Constitution was also passed. The amendments so introduced sought to reduce the power of the Supreme Court and the High Courts all over the nation, and inserted the words ‘Socialist’ and ‘Secular’ to the preamble of the Constitution. Under this amendment act, the Indian Parliament was bestowed with unlimited, unrestrained power to amend each and every section of the Constitution without judicial review. Thus, the doctrine of separation of powers and the Indian federal structure was negated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forced sterilisation program, undertaken under the leadership of Sanjay Gandhi with the aim of family planning, led to 8.3 million sterilisations within the time frame of 1976-1977 according to &lt;em&gt;India’s Population Reality: Reconciling Change and Tradition&lt;/em&gt;. The primary accounts of the brutality are evident in The Sanjay Story by an eminent Indian political journalist when he recounts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hawa Singh, a widower from the village of Pipli had been taken from a bus against his will and sterilised. The infection that emanated from the vasectomy took his life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government used Doordarshan, the government-owned television network, for its own political propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Turkman Gate demolition and firing which took place on April 18, 1976, a fallout of the drive to clear slum areas in Delhi, resulted in indiscriminate firing and police brutalities, which the popular media wasn’t permitted to report. Unofficial accounts put the figure at 9 deaths from among the ones who resisted the usurpation and bulldozing of their settlements. Later, the Shah Commission report stated that 20 individuals had been killed. The censorship of the press had begun from the night of the declaration of the Emergency itself with the electric supply of Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg being cut off, within 3 hours of the announcement. Most of the publishing houses of newspapers and national magazines were located on the same street. A number of newspapers had published a blank page or a black space in its editorials as an attempt to convey that the news had been tampered with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 18, 1977, Mrs Gandhi called for fresh elections followed by the release of all political prisoners. The Indian Emergency ended on March 23, 1977. The Congress was routed in the General Elections with Janta Dal assuming power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is that one thing about Indira’s India of 1975, inhabited by my grandfather’s generation that resonates with a world so different from ours, 45 years later, in a post-privatisation, liberal democracy? Surprisingly the answer doesn’t take a minute longer to appear so clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amnesty International in 2015 had stated that there was a “total blackout of information” in the state of Chattisgarh. And today, a complete shutting down of information transmission from Kashmir has continued for more than 5 months with major leaders of the state being placed under preventive detention. The idea of placing government loyalists to moot out majority opposition parties from power in the states finds uncanny parallels: Gandhi dismissed the Ajoy Mukherjee-led government in West Bengal in 1969 while Modi used Governors as loyalists to deny the single-largest party to come to power in Manipur, Nagaland and Meghalaya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Gandhi’s Emergency declaration was approved by her Cabinet only after its imposition. Similarly, Modi’s implementation of the demonetisation was known only to a handful in the Cabinet prior to its formal declaration. Additionally, Modi’s appointment of Army Chief Bipin Rawat, superseding two senior officers is reminiscent of Gandhi’s appointment of Mr Justice A N Ray as Chief Justice of India by superseding three others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signs are clear and “those who do not learn from history are doomed to repeat it”. The Indian Emergency only grows in importance during our times to educate us on how a state can go from mere political upheaval to an authoritarian regime.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indo-US Relations in the Second Decade of the 21st Century: The Way Ahead</title>
      <link href="/Indo-US-Relations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indo-US Relations in the Second Decade of the 21st Century: The Way Ahead" />
      <published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indo-US-Relations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indo-US-Relations">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump, the President of the United States undertook his first official trip to India since he assumed the Presidency in 2016. His 36-hour trip was marked by activities which ranged from travelling across Ahmedabad to Agra, to culminate his trip to Delhi. In the words of Trump himself, “Nobody else got the reception that I got yesterday. We had thousands of people. That was an incredible scene.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His trip, which took place in the last week of February, may be considered to be an extremely significant political gesture ahead of the United States presidential election due for November this year. This had been the fifth meeting between the two global leaders in the last eight months, indicating a maturity of the two nations’ diplomatic ties. The reception accorded to Trump may be reminiscent of the crowd gathered to welcome Dwight D Eisenhower, the United States President in 1959.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indo-US Ties Down the Ages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indo-US relations can be traced from the time prior to the independence of India in 1947. Prominent leaders of the national movement including M N Roy (one of the leaders of the Indo-German conspiracy), had settled in the US. However, in the initial decades of the Cold War, when the US had made Pakistan a CENTO ally (Central Treaty Organization), India had developed a strategic alliance with the Soviet Union. Yet, with the crystallisation of the Non-Aligned Movement in 1961 at the Bandung Conference, India embarked on an attempt to distance itself from the prevalent Cold War power politics. And there was a gradual deterioration in the relationship between India and the US, with Richard Nixon’s administration extending its support to Pakistan during the Bangladesh Liberation War of 1971 (in which India was an ally of Bangladesh). Moreover, India signed a 20-year Treaty of Friendship with the Soviet Union in 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indo-US ties soured further in 1974 when India detonated its first nuclear device. This strategic move ensured two decades of estrangement between the two nations. However, in 1982, the then US president Ronald Reagan did meet with the then Indian Prime Minister Indira Gandhi where the latter proclaimed, “We should find a common area, however so small.” The thaw in relations was prevalent till 1991, the year which marked the dissolution of the Soviet Union. With the adoption of India’s new economic policy in 1991, under Prime Minister Narasimha Rao and with Manmohan Singh as the Finance Minister, Indian foreign policy adapted itself to the unipolar world with the US as the champion of capitalist global domination. The adoption of the policies of Liberalisation, Privatisation and Globalisation cemented the economic ties of the two nations. Bilateral trade and investments increased, and one saw the strengthening of India’s decision-making powers in global governance via its introduction of India into multilateral export control regimes such as the Australia Group, The Missile Technology Control Regime (2016), the Wassenaar Arrangement and so on. In fact, the US offered assistance to India in joining the Nuclear Suppliers Group and in July 2006, the US Congress had amended the US law to accommodate civilian nuclear trade with India. Indo-US relations reached a zenith when India was declared a major defence partner of the US in 2016, under the Presidency of Barack Obama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Matters of Military and Economic Development Post The 1990’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 11, 1998, the Indian government had declared the successful completion of a series of underground nuclear tests at Pokhran, Rajasthan- close to the North-Western border shared by the two nations. The act drew widespread international criticism with Bill Clinton, the then US President, recalling the US ambassador to India and further imposing economic sanctions, leading to severe diplomatic tensions escalating between the two nations. However, in an amazing turn of events, in March 2000, Clinton became the first US President to visit India since 1978. With a fledgeling global economy, Clinton’s visit signalled a US foreign policy shifting its priorities from its Cold War ally Pakistan to India. In the areas of energy security, the 2005 visit of Condoleezza Rice, the United States Secretary of State initiated a dialogue on this primary core economic sector. This step had gained international significance as there had been mounting tensions over the US sale of fighter jets to Pakistan. Further, the signing of the Civil Nuclear Deal ensured a clear demarcation between India’s civil and military nuclear facilities, leading to India’s civil resources being placed under International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of economic developments, out of India’s largest direct investors, the US ranks number 1. India’s major exports are in the manufacturing sector, closely followed by non-financial services, which predominantly includes the software development industry. The US Department of State mentions that the major American items that have been imported by India include aircraft, fertilisers, computer hardware, scrap metal and medical equipment. The US accounts for a direct investment of $10 billion to India annually. Yet, the hindrance posed by tariff and non-tariff barriers includes agreement on the insecticides manufactured by US companies that may be sold throughout India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Donald Trump’s Presidential Visit and its Diplomatic Repercussions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The population of the Indian diaspora living in the US accounts to 4 million, which constitute slightly over 1% of the US population. Considering the US election due for November 2020, many international observers have regarded this visit as an attempt to secure the vote bank of the Indo-Americans. India and the US have issued a joint statement by proclaiming the US-India ties to the level of “comprehensive global strategic partnership.” An attempt to make defence manufacturers part of each other’s supply chains and an assurance to strengthen homeland security to resist global terrorism was made. A twin arms deal amounting to $3.5 billion for 6 Apache attack helicopters and 24 Seahawk anti-submarine warfare helicopters have been inked. Further, a $1.9 billion for missile defence system awaits in the pipeline. There have been talks to revitalise the Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (US, India, Australia and Japan) initiative on areas such as counter-terrorism and maritime security. Moreover, a collaboration for the Blue Dot Network and escalating tensions over China’s Belt and Road initiative has strengthened collaboration on regional infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Affairs Survey conducted by Gallup (US Analytics and Advisory company) in 2015 states that “Americans perceive India as their 6th favourite nation in the world.” 74% of Americans viewed India favourably in 2017 and 72% in 2019. While all aspects of the economic relations between the two countries are improving, the people-to-people relationship is also getting better. In the words of the Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi, “Relations between India and US aren’t just between two governments, but are people-centric and people-driven.” The bonhomie between the two nations may become stronger if besides military and energy, other areas of cooperation are explored. Much may depend upon the US election results.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Donald Trump, the President of the United States undertook his first official trip to India since he assumed the Presidency in 2016. His 36-hour trip was marked by activities which ranged from travelling across Ahmedabad to Agra, to culminate his trip to Delhi. In the words of Trump himself, “Nobody else got the reception that I got yesterday. We had thousands of people. That was an incredible scene.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Russia Heralds a New Dawn: Power to the People or the Lurking Shadow of a Dictatorial Regime?</title>
      <link href="/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russia Heralds a New Dawn: Power to the People or the Lurking Shadow of a Dictatorial Regime?" />
      <published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&quot;I truly believe that it is time to introduce certain changes to our country's main law.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; 
-Vladimir Putin, January 2020
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 15, 2020, the Russian Government headed by Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev resigned en masse, immediately after the State of the Union address. Within six hours of Medvedev’s resignation, Putin offered the post to Mikhail Mishutshin who had formerly been the head of the Russian Tax Service. It is of significance that the governmental revamp has been preceded by a proposed nationwide referendum on constitutional changes which will ensure the shift of the balance of power from Putin’s successor (the future Russian President) to the Parliament and the newly-appointed Prime Minister, even though Putin has limited the term of the Russian President to two terms. All 432 legislators in the Duma, the lower house of the Russian Parliament, have approved of the amendments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the amendments, 14 articles of the Constitution are to be changed. The State Duma will possess the right to approve a Prime Minister’s candidacy, followed by that of the Deputy Prime Ministers and Federal Ministers. A prospective Presidential candidate has to be an inhabitant of Russia for a minimum of 25 years (earlier it was 10 years). The upper house of the Russian Parliament, the Federation Council, will be able to send a proposal to the President to dismiss Federal Judges. This is an elevation of the Council’s importance, whose significance was previously restricted to being an advisory body. The President will appoint the superior officers of the law enforcement agencies only in consultation with the Federal Council. The individuals who hold important positions for ensuring the country’s security (President, Ministers, Heads of Regions) are forbidden from holding foreign citizenship or residence permits of other nations during their term in office. The Constitutional Court has the competence to ensure the constitutionality of laws which the Parliament of the Russian Federation adopts, by the request of the President, before him signing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That apart, one of the important parts of the amendment includes a clear statement of the priority of the Russian Constitution over international law and the global human rights regime, which many believe is a reflection of Kremlin’s annoyance with the European Court of Human Rights’ declarations that Russia is responsible for gross human rights violations, including the Chechnya disappearances, and the Court’s rulings against Russia’s Federal Security Services in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The otherwise innocuous amendments tend to have latent implications for Russia, in particular, and international politics in general. A cursory analysis reveals that there shall be a surge in the importance of the country’s Parliament: both the upper and lower house. The President’s candidature for the post of Prime Minister would require a formal confirmation from the Duma. The actual centre of power shall shift to the State Council which is being vested with a heightened legal authority. Many believe that it is the future landing gateway for Putin, post-2024, as it will ensure that he retains ultimate power post-retirement from the Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amendments will bestow the Security Council (headed by Putin, it includes the heads of the lower and upper house of parliament, the President’s envoys in Federal Districts and regional Governors) with the status of an official state organ that shall chart the domestic and foreign policies of the Russian Federation. There is an opportunity of the Security Council receiving executive authority that it previously hasn’t possessed. Putin may continue to manipulate foreign and domestic affairs through his pivotal role in this Security Council, in spite of not retaining his presidential post within 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The present amendments may be compared to that of the Kazakhstan President Nursultan Nazarvaev, who formally stepped down from the post of the President last March but continued to enjoy hegemony over the decision-making hierarchy of the nation by capturing important positions in the Security Council whose authority had been strategically heightened before Nazarnaev’s ascendancy. Hints of such parallels find resonance in the words of Pavel Krasheninnikov, Chairman of a Duma committee telling the official Government newspaper &lt;em&gt;Rossiiskaya Gazeta&lt;/em&gt;, “Scores of proposals have been received including one to create an official post of Supreme Leader.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of February, 2020, one may state that the unanimous support of the Duma to the constitutional amendments bill is reminiscent of the Soviet vote on Stalin’s adoption of the December, 1936 Constitution or Brezhnev’s 1977 Doctrine. A national plebiscite on the amendments is due in April and planning for it has already been initiated by the Central Election Commission. However, the opposition aims at converting the plebiscite into a no-confidence vote of the ruling regime. More than 40,000 people have signed a manuscript urging the Russian public to blatantly reject the “constitutional &lt;em&gt;coup&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;d’etat&lt;/em&gt;”. Meanwhile, the fate of Russia swerves in the uncertainty of major constitutional upheaval.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;I truly believe that it is time to introduce certain changes to our country's main law.&quot; -Vladimir Putin, January 2020</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Encounter Killings’- Delivering Justice or Instances of Culpable Homicide?</title>
      <link href="/Encounter-Killings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Encounter  Killings'- Delivering  Justice  or  Instances  of  Culpable  Homicide?" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Encounter-Killings</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Encounter-Killings">&lt;p&gt;Montesquieu, the French philosopher, known worldwide for his articulation of the ‘Theory of Separation of Powers’ had famously stated, “There is no greater tyranny than that which is perpetrated under the shield of the law and in the name of justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of the debate revolving around the idea of ‘extrajudicial killings’, known in popular culture as &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; lies in the timeless relevance of Montesquieu’s words. India, the world’s largest democracy with its constitution bearing testimony to the ideals of “Liberty, Equality, Justice, Fraternity” ranks high on the global index promotion of such a dehumanising practice. Uttar Pradesh, the largest state of the Indian union by population, has recorded 59 instances of such extra judicial killings in the past two years. However, the trend of extra judicial killings in India is not a contemporary phenomenon, it has been an indispensable element of securing obedience at the hands of armed forces, police and similar repressive machineries of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Encounter killing&lt;/em&gt; is a term used to refer to extrajudicial executions (beyond the limits of the judiciary’s scope) of individuals in police custody, which has been staged in such a manner so as to portray their occurrence as instances of death by gun battle, or in supposed self defence carried out by the police or armed forces in self defence on encountering gangsters or terrorists or alleged criminals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major criticism of this idea is that it takes a person’s life without minimal guarantee of due process of law. It can be analysed from diverse viewpoints - one cannot overlook that they are often political assassinations. Edy Kauffman in the &lt;em&gt;Human Rights Quarterly&lt;/em&gt; had defined it as “assassinations that are part of a rational scheme to transfer political power from one group to another or to achieve a specific policy objective.” Its exercise is not limited to transfer of power, but also to retain power. It can be explained through the example of 5,000 murders and 30,000 arrests that took place in Chile following the 1973 military coup, which thereby resulted in Salvador Allende being overthrown by the armed forces. Such &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; have also been widely prevalent in western European nations including, United Kingdom. Operation Kratos which was conducted by London’s Metropolitan Police Service to exterminate suspected suicide bombers included firing on the head without warning. This practice had been exposed after the mistaken shooting of Jean Charles de Menezes (a case of misidentification post the 2005 London Bombings) - leading to several human rights organisations calling out against similar practices. Similarly, the Rio de Janeiro police killed 322 people unlawfully in between January and May of 2016, in accordance to its reports released in July of the same year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A brief history of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; in India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-1947 and transfer of power, there have been innumerable instances of encounter killings in the history of the nation, some supported by historical records while others whose only substantial evidence is in the form of ‘missing person’ documents. The alarming rate of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; had sparked an inquiry by United Nations panel comprising 4 independent human rights experts. This panel had ‘expressed alarm’ in its January 2019 statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“individuals allegedly being abducted or arrested before their killing, and their bodies bearing indicative of torture.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have been the go-to alternative in a variety of contexts - during the Naxalbari insurgency in the state of Bengal during the late 1960’s and early 1970’s. The CPI (M-L) led insurrection across the state included regular instances of the state police shooting down alleged naxalite student activists, which includes the murder of the poet, communist intellectual Saroj Dutta, whose name still appears as ‘missing person’ almost 45 years after his disappearance, followed by repeated petitions for investigation of his death being rejected by the West Bengal State government. The Barasat killings of 1970’s refer to the murder of 11 young men on the night of November 19, 1970 with suspected links to Naxal terror. Operation Steeplechase, commissioned by the Indira Gandhi government has often been accused of perpetrating ‘fake encounters.’ With Rahul Pandita’s &lt;em&gt;Hello Bastar: The Untold Story of India’s Maoist Movement&lt;/em&gt; stating that Govind Narain, the then Home Secretary of India proclaimed “There should be no publicity and no records.” Further instances of extra judicial killings have also been noted during the Punjab insurgency of the 1980’s. Counter-terrorism measures by the state often manifests itself in the form of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; in terrorist infested zones. The North-Eastern state of Manipur, which had for years been reeling under the draconian AFSPA (Armed forces Special Powers Act), has witnessed several such cases. A case filed before the Indian Supreme Court in 2012, recounted the horrors of a staggering 1528 extra judicial killings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jammu and Kashmir has been a hotbed of state sponsored terrorism disguised as counter terror measures, with security forces indulging in gross violations of human rights- with the riveting instance of of soldiers shooting and killing six persons in Shopian district on March 5, 2018. The government spokesman claimed that the ‘miscreants’ had failed to stop at a checkpoint and the soldiers had opened fire in self-defence. In November 2018, the National Human Rights Commission issued a notice to Uttar Pradesh’s Chief Minister, Yogi Adityanath post his “criminals will be jailed or killed in encounters” remark. It highlights the callous and often denigrating reflection of human security measures in the subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reforms as the Need of the Hour&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many argue that instead of resources being utilised for security sector reforms, there must be greater attention devoted to the idea of rights sensitisation, i.e. educating the state machineries of the rights guaranteed to each citizen. Promoting accountability of the security forces, strict criminalisation in cases of fake encounters should be a necessity. Impartial investigations in case of alleged reports of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; should be a necessity. We have often seen such instances are greater if the miscreant belongs to weaker sections of the society, which may include religious minorities or members of financially unstable families. Moreover, the cases of misidentification and death of an innocent citizen doesn’t appear far-fetched, as the role of judiciary is almost null in such cases. However, political pressures from the upper echelons of the government isn’t an exception- Veerapan, the notorious sandalwood forest bridgend was allegedly killed by the Special Task Force in an encounter on October 18, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court has issued a landmark decision in 2016, in which it stated the illegality of such encounters and the lack of ‘absolute impunity’ in such cases. The Court has even ordered the setting up of a Special Investigation Team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate surrounding the concepts of fake encounters has gained a fresh lease of life with the extra judicial killing of the four rapists responsible for the brutal rape and murder of a Hyderabad veterinarian in December 2019. What is particularly alarming about such instances is the public adulation the police officers involved in such instances receive. The encounter specialists in popular media are widely celebrated as heroes. Such a psychological reaction can be attributed to the slow judicial procedures that characterise the Indian judicial system. However, important questions regarding the prisoner’s right to a free and fair trial, right to life (until proven guilty) and the larger moral responsibility of the society must continue to haunt the collective conscience.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Montesquieu, the French philosopher, known worldwide for his articulation of the ‘Theory of Separation of Powers’ had famously stated, “There is no greater tyranny than that which is perpetrated under the shield of the law and in the name of justice.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?</title>
      <link href="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?" />
      <published>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donald Trump on the eve of the 18th anniversary of the 9/11 commemorations on September 11, 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This will lead to more losses to the US. Its credibility will be affected, its anti-peace stance will be exposed to the world, losses to lives and assets will increase.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zabihullah Mujahid, a Talib spokesman criticising the US President for calling off the dialogue between the US and the Taliban.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest concerns pervading global geopolitics in the second decade of the 21st century is the solution to what may be referred to as the “Afghanistan policy of the United States.” The peace process, a mediation attempt in what is regarded as one of the greatest standoffs of our times, has met a dead-end. Peace negotiations between the two sides were stalled off unexpectedly, with the US pulling from the expected accord using a proverbial reason too flimsy for most observers of global politics. Trump has pushed the reason that there has been an uptick in Taliban-inflicted violence all across Afghanistan as well the death of an American soldier along with 11 other people in a suicide bombing which shook the national capital of Kabul in the month of September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To receive a better understanding of this more recent development, it is imperative to cast a glance at the intricacies that have led to the stalemate today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term Taliban can be literally translated as ‘students.’ It can be referred to as an attempt to construct an Islamic Empire in Afghanistan. The Sunni Islamic organisation rose to prominence in 1994, as part of an attempt to end the power vacuum that had exerted itself in the nation as an immediate after-effect of the Afghan Civil War. The Afghan Civil War had resulted in the drop of Kabul’s population from 2 million to 500,000 within a span of a year. It began when Hezb-e-Islami led by Gulbuddin Hekmatyar with the support of neighbouring Pakistan’s Inter-Services Intelligence (ISI) had refused to be a part of the coalition government along with other Mujahideen Groups, establishing their sole authority over Kabul. It was only a year later in 1995-1996 that the militia of the Talibans, having secured sufficient support from Pakistan and ISI, established its supremacy and invaded Kandahar, followed by Herat, with their authority receiving a formal seal of suzerainty with the successful invasion of Kabul in 1996. Al-Qaeda had been granted sanction to operate by the Taliban on the condition that it would not indulge in any activity that could incur the wrath of the US. But the subsequent actions of its leader, Osama Bin Laden’s attack on the American embassies of East Africa, caused a rift between the Taliban and the Al-Qaeda. Many may sight that Al-Qaeda harboured a greater ambition - that of global jihad while Talibans had a restrictive operational base called Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post 9/11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Powell had famously remarked, “You can be sure that the American Spirit will prevail over this tragedy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest turning points of the new millennium had been the four coordinated terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001 at three prime locations in the heart of the United States that killed 2,977 people, injuring 25,000 more. Truly, American foreign policy never remained the same with Islamic nations across the globe, and with Afghanistan, quite obviously, having to bear the brunt. The US demanded that the Taliban hand over Osama Bin Laden, the mastermind behind the tragedy, which was rejected by the Taliban as they demanded greater evidence of his involvement in the terror attack. In response, the US-NATO alliance launched Operation Enduring Freedom. George W Bush, the then President of the US had declared a “War on Terror,” as reported by the New York Times on September 20, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the operation was clearly evident, with the Taliban being driven out of power by the Christmas of 2001. The United Nations Security Council later formed the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF) with the aim of providing multidimensional training to Afghan Security forces, which would rebuild the social and political institutions which had been demolished by the Taliban regime. These institutions also included the establishment of the Afghan Transitional Administration with Hamid Karzai as the President. ISAF spread through four stages all over the Taliban-inflicted ruins of the nation. The Operation Enduring Freedom ended after 13 years in 2014, with Bush’s successor Barack Obama declaring its end with these words of significance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For more than 13 years, ever since nearly 3,000 innocent lives were taken from us on 9/11 our nation has been at war with Afghanistan……our combat mission in Afghanistan is ending, and the longest war in American history is coming to a responsible end.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, he also stressed that in order to preserve the gains made by the US military (as also by the invitation of the Afghan government), a limited military presence would remain in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely stated that negotiations with the Taliban had always been in the pipeline, having been strongly endorsed by the former Afghan president, Hamid Karzai (2004-2014), but American efforts had never been either eager or decisive in the matter. Karzai, on returning from a foreign trip, had offered peace negotiations in 2007, but the Taliban insurgents citing the proliferation of foreign troops had squarely rejected the offer. The precondition that there be a withdrawal of 50,000 NATO troops and US military couldn’t be fulfilled. Karzai had offered to allocate government posts to the Taliban with Hekmatyar even being allowed to contest elections in 2009, but to no avail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2009 Afghan Presidential elections had been widely contested on the issue of whether the war should come to an end or not. In one of his Presidential campaigns, Karzai offered “Loya Jirga” (a traditional Afghan Pashtun ceremony organised for choosing a new head of state). However, the elections, which were widely blood-splattered with the death of 59 Americans, resulted in the increase of the presence of American troops in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2010 marked a significant turn of events, with Karzai stating that “the peace process will be with the Talibans and other militants who are not part of the Al Qaeda or other terrorist networks or ideologically against us.” The then US Secretary of State Hillary Clinton supported the contention. The second-in-command of the Taliban, Abdul Ghani Baradar favoured talks with both the US and the Afghan government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change of political strategy of the US government took place in 2010, with the Taliban Quetta Shura (Taliban Leadership Commanders) leaving Pakistan and being escorted to Kabul by NATO aircraft for discussions, according to Reuters, only to be revealed that one of the leaders Akhtar Mansour was an imposter disguised as senior Taliban commander. A round of talks stood cancelled in 2012 and another stood cancelled in 2013 as a direct consequence of a dispute between the Taliban and Karzai, where the latter felt that the former were portraying themselves as a “government in exile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 2018 marked an abrupt increase in violence, with Ashraf Ghani, the Afghan President offering the Taliban a full recognition as a legal political party and a release of Taliban political prisoners. The Los Angeles Times referred to this as “the most significant peace overture.” Surprisingly, in July 2018, American officials had reportedly met a few members of the Taliban at their political office in Qatar. Zalmay Khalilzad joined the US State Department as Trump’s Special Advisor on Afghanistan, with the sole aim of initiating an intra-Afghan peace process. Fuelling diplomatic speculation, Russia successfully held talks with the Taliban and officials of the Afghanistan High Peace Council. After the February 2019 talks, Khalilzad reported “this round of talk was more productive than they have ever been in the past.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 12, 2019, the US and the Taliban completed the 8th round of negotiations, and US media had been abuzz with the news that the US had been close to reaching a peace deal with Afghanistan which would include the withdrawal of 5,000 troops from Afghanistan. The ‘agreement-in-principle’ was awaiting final approval by the President, which it fortunately or unfortunately did not get. Its cancellation, however, prompted the Talibans to remark that the “doors were open” for further discussions with Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conjectures are afloat that a peace agreement with the Talibans could result in their rise to power, replicating the defeat of the US-backed South Vietnamese government after the 1973 Paris peace accords. US Defence Secretary Mark Esper had visited Afghanistan in late October 2019. He stated that the US could reduce its force in Afghanistan to 8,600 without damaging its counter-terrorism capabilities. On a world diplomacy stage, war with Afghanistan is largely recognised as an unwinnable war. For a concrete conclusion of the war, it is imperative that the US gets rid of its mirage of a perfect deal and allure foŕ hard power. Otherwise, like the North Korean nuclear standoff, there seems no end in sight. Every month this stalemate claims thousands of Afghan lives and almost $4 billion from the US government.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
