<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/jacob.jones/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-14T18:31:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/jacob.jones/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?</title>
      <link href="/NBA-Midseason-Awards" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?" />
      <published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/NBA-Midseason-Awards</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/NBA-Midseason-Awards">&lt;p&gt;We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable Player: James Harden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many players putting up great numbers for the season so far, but nobody is even close to James Harden. He is putting up 36.7 points, 8.1 assists, 6.7 rebounds, and 2.1 steals per game. He is literally tearing up teams on a nightly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He even went through a five game stretch where he averaged 52.2 points per game. Its beyond impressive how someone can do that against the world’s best basketball players. The Houston Rockets are a much worse team than last year, but they are still contenders because of what Harden is doing this season. If he keeps it up he might just earn back to back MVP awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rookie of the Year: Luka Doncic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into the NBA, Luka was considered the best international prospect ever. So far he has lived up to the hype. He is averaging 19.0 points per game, 6.7 rebounds per game, 5.1 assists per game, and 1.1 steals per game. He is already competing at a high level as a nineteen year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doncic is a wizard with the ball, making shots you can’t believe and constantly coming up with clutch plays for the Mavericks. It’s a great feeling for a team to know that they have their franchise player, and the Mavericks are probably ecstatic knowing that they have their guy. The sky’s the limit for this young star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defensive Player of the Year: Paul George&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far Paul George is having the best offensive season of his career. It’s pretty extraordinary that his defense has been so impressive as well. He leads the NBA in steals and is third in defensive win shares. This award has typically gone to front court players in recent years, which emphasizes how remarkable Paul George’s defensive game has been. Instead of guarding down low, he has the task of locking down the other team’s best perimeter player every night. The Thunder have the best defensive rating in the NBA and a big reason why is because ‘PG’ is leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixth Man of the Year: Domantas Sabonis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabonis has been a key factor to the Pacers success this season. He is nearly averaging a double-double off the bench with 15.0 points and 9.6 rebounds per game. Sabonis is also pulling his weight in defense with one of the better defensive teams in the NBA. The Pacers are at their best when Sabonis is on the court which says a lot since they are currently third in the eastern conference. Why he’s not starting is a matter of logistics but with Victor Oladipo out for the rest of the year look for Domantas to have an even bigger role for the team going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Improved Player: De’Aaron Fox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sacramento Kings have been one of the big surprises this season. They are currently two and a half games out of the playoffs and a big reason for their unpredictable success is the development of De’Aaron Fox. He made a leap from last season going from 11.6 points, 2.8 rebounds, and 4.4 assist per game to 17.6 points, 3.7 rebounds, and 7.2 assist per game. Fox has stepped up as a leader for a team that hasn’t been this close to the playoffs in over a decade. He will be a key factor for the Kings in their late season push for the postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coach of the Year: Mike Budenholzer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Milwaukee Bucks are in the top seed in the East and Budenholzer is a big reason why. The Bucks have made a couple of tweaks this season which have them one of the best teams in the NBA. Offensively the Bucks have made great strides this season as Milwaukee has the second best offensive ranking in the association. With LeBron no longer playing in the East the conference is wide open and the Bucks are the favorites to win it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the second half of the season underway only time will tell if these players and teams can continue to play at the level they have been since the beginning of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;http://basketball-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Basketball-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jacob Jones</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Super Bowl LIII: Old School vs. The New Age</title>
      <link href="/Super-Bowl-LIII" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Super Bowl LIII: Old School vs. The New Age" />
      <published>2019-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Super-Bowl-LIII</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Super-Bowl-LIII">&lt;p&gt;It all comes down to this. 266 games played in the NFL to decide one matchup. It’s the game in which legacies are built, legends are made, and cities are given hope. It’s the Super Bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey to this game could not of been more opposite for these two teams. A team that is trying to build on their incredible dynasty vs. a team that is trying to start one of their own. The best coach in NFL history vs. the best young coach football has ever seen. The best quarterback to ever set foot on a field vs. a young buck that wants to show the world that he’s the next big thing at the quarterback position. The classic David vs. Goliath story. Its experience vs. youth, East Coast vs. West Coast, Belichick vs. McVay, Brady vs. Goff, The New England Patriots vs. The Los Angeles Rams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 3rd these two teams will meet up in Atlanta to battle for the Lombardi Trophy and the right to call themselves World Champions. Playing in Football’s most coveted game isn’t new to the Patriots. This will be Tom Brady’s and Bill Belichick’s ninth Super Bowl together in which they have a previous record of 5-3. For the Rams this will be their first Super Bowl appearance since 2002 when they lost to the Patriots, which actually kick started the Brady and Belichick Patriots dynasty. Like most players on this team this will be the first time Goff and McVay have played on football’s biggest stage. So, the experience factor definitely goes toward the Patriots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about the past, let’s look at the current teams. Both of these teams are stacked on the offensive side of things. The Los Angeles Rams have the third ranked offense in the NFL putting up 32.9 points per game and averaging 421.1 total yards per game. They have dynamic playmakers in running back Todd Gurley (1,251 rushing yards and 17 touchdowns) and wide receiver Brandin Cooks (1,204 receiving yards and 5 touchdowns). At QB they have Jared Goff who is an incredible young quarterback posting a 101.1 QB rating for the season. The man behind the play calling is the best offensive mind football has ever seen, head coach Sean McVay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Patriots aren’t too far behind the Rams offensively. New England has the fourth ranked offense in the NFL racking up 27.2 points per game and a steady 393.4 yards per game. The Patriots have a veteran receiving core lead by future Hall of Famer Rob Gronkowski and the elusive wide receiver Julian Edelman. Both were huge factors in the AFC championship helping Brady convert on many key third downs. The Patriots also have a great running back committee led by Sony Michel who is having a fantastic postseason finding the end zone 5 times already and racking up 242 yards in just two games. And of course, this team is led by arguably the greatest quarterback of all time, Tom Brady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensively these teams aren’t as strong. The Rams have the nineteenth ranked defense in the NFL (358.6 yards per game) and the Patriots have the twenty first (359.1 yards per game). But the difference between the two teams’ defenses are the playmakers that the Rams possess. They got straight dudes on the defensive side. LA has two great interior linemen in Ndamukong Suh and the defensive player of the year Aaron Donald (led the NFL with 20.5 sacks). To complement their front seven, they have Aqib Talib and Marcus Peters, two veteran cornerbacks who have come up big in this postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like every Super Bowl that the Patriots have played in, we are bound to have a very competitive and entertaining game. Looking at the rosters the Rams have by far the best team. But the Patriots aren’t built on having a team full of stars, they never have been. They play brilliantly as a team rather than individuals. They have the richest history in the NFL and the system that Belichick has created makes it impossible not to succeed. They have more experience than anybody in NFL history. That’s why Tom Brady should get his sixth ring. The New England Patriots are the safer bet to repeat history and defeat the Rams in the Super Bowl again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats via &lt;a href=&quot;http://pro-football-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Pro-football-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jacob Jones</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="american-football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It all comes down to this. 266 games played in the NFL to decide one matchup. It’s the game in which legacies are built, legends are made, and cities are given hope. It’s the Super Bowl.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
