<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/alex.omidvar/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-16T20:04:57+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/alex.omidvar/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Story of Easter</title>
      <link href="/The-Story-of-Easter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Easter" />
      <published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Story-of%20Easter</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Story-of-Easter">&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, everyone has a worldview, a lens through which he/she views the world, however implicit this worldview might be. And every worldview is, ultimately, a story. I don’t mean this in a condescending manner – stories can be true! My mother used to tell me stories about my childhood, and I have no doubt concerning the sincerity of her testimony. In fact, it is stories that drive our world. Everyone has their own story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this on the twelfth of April, 2020. It is a Sunday, it is Easter. And what better to write on this occasion than to simply tell the story of Easter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world is a strange, dark and forsaken world. Even in the midst of apparent joy, there is deep and real suffering. Even the ancient Indian prince Siddhartha could not help but realise that the world was filled with pain and anguish. And this realisation was so shocking and heart-wrenching for him that, as the legend goes, he forsook all royalty in search for the enlightenment that he believed would reveal to him the secret of joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things haven’t changed much. In fact, today’s world is filled with Siddharthas, desperate to discover the secret of happiness. Every advertisement you have ever seen, every product you have been keen to buy, every place you have wanted to visit, every prize you have been ambitious to win – in other words, everything you have ever done, you have done it in the hope that what you are about to do will finally bring you the joy and peace that your heart desires – or at the very least, will increase the joy that you already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, here you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I too was a lot like Siddhartha. In fact, my mother wanted to name me Siddhartha, but ultimately decided against it for fear that I would ultimately become a monk. But against all hope, as it turned out, I did have a very ‘monastic’ spirit, even early on. From very early on in my life, I have been searching for answers – answers to the big questions of life. Why am I here? What is my purpose? Why does this world exist? Where am I going?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: what does it all mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thirst to discover these answers eventually became like a madness, like an obsession that had wormed itself deep into my psyche. I’m certain I was the only person in seventh grade who did not know how to play cricket, but who had, in fact, read the entire Bhagavad Gita cover to cover. I was the only kid in high school who was not a Muslim but who wanted to carry the Qur’an with him to read during the tiffin break. I was, in other words, probably exactly the kind of person my mother had initially dreaded I would become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most people, I sought for something that would give purpose to my life: religion, politics, worldly success as a writer or an actor were high on the list. And yet, the questions remained. At one point in my life, I even contemplated raw, naked materialist atheism. I started reading atheist literature and was initially greatly impressed by the force of the rhetoric. Richard Dawkins, in particular, was a crucial influence. There he stood, marshalling all the powers of reason and science in an intellectual assault upon all forms of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, for a while, it seemed the candle had been blown out. There was no god. There was no purpose. There was no meaning to anything. There was no good, there was no evil – there was simply matter, endlessly morphing. As Christopher Hitchens wrote, “To the dumb question, ‘Why me?’ the cosmos barely bothers to return the reply: why not?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atheist ‘enlightenment’ informed me that, at best, I was an accident. I didn’t have to be here, but I was. And I would one day flicker out of existence. I came into being for no reason, and eventually, I would perish for no reason. And all my precious joys, passions, loves, desires, ambitions, fears and sorrows would perish with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the worldview which the atheists presented to me, death was more real than life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was then that I encountered a person who completely changed my life. His name was Dr William Lane Craig. An academic philosopher of religion and a deeply Christian soul, he was a man who had debated leading atheists at universities around the world. He had faced off against big names like Lawrence Krauss, Dan Barker, Sam Harris, Peter Atkins and a whole host of other atheist heavyweights. And with him, for the first time, I saw someone who was able to give a clear and intellectually compelling case in favour of theism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, as I studied more, I came to realise that most militant atheism was more motivated by anger against religion than any careful consideration of the question of whether or not God exists. Many of the arguments atheists had been putting forward, I realised, were extremely poor and shabby, often based upon misunderstandings and caricatures of Christian arguments and theology. And some of the leading atheists like Lawrence Krauss seemed unwilling to even consider the possibility of there being a God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than overthrowing dogmas, at times it seemed that the atheists were championing new dogmas – dogmas based less upon careful intellectual thought and more upon prejudice and hatred for a particular social order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I identify not as an atheist, but as a convinced believer in Jesus Christ. I believe in Jesus – and, even more unthinkably, in the Catholic Church - because I believe Christianity – and Catholicism – are true. And I believe the story of Christianity, which is really the story of Easter, can truly change people’s lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible opens with a very grand and simple line: In the beginning, God created the heavens and earth. In the Biblical worldview, God is the reason why this universe exists. God created us, and we exist because of Him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Bible also tells us that human beings sinned. Though we were originally created holy and good, we turned against God and rebelled against Him. All the evil that exists in the world is merely the outworking of man’s original sin. And the bad news is that none of us is innocent, because we have all participated in this unholy work of sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the good news that Christianity brings is the proclamation that God did not abandon us. On the contrary, He descended from heaven and became one of us. He shared in our misery, our suffering, our loneliness, our pain and our anguish. But He did not share in our sins. He was crucified by men who hated His claims, but as He was dying on the Cross, He offered His life as a sacrifice – to atone for the sins of man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the powers of evil gathered together and climaxed on the Cross of Jesus 2,000 years ago… because there was no sin more grotesque than the murder of God’s only Son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the Christian worldview, death did not have the last word. On the contrary, Jesus Christ rose from the dead, physically, bodily, on the third day, triumphing over the powers of sin and death. Though men murdered Him, death could not hold Him, because He had committed no sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who hold to materialist dogma will scoff at this idea. For countless souls, miracles and resurrections are the stuff of legend. They cannot happen and do not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you doubt the Resurrection, then I highly recommend you to take the time to study it, historically. The Oxford atheist philosopher (and later convert to theism, though not to Christianity) Antony Flew admitted in his debate with the historian Gary Habermas that the Resurrection of Jesus had better evidence than claimed miracles in any other religion. The Gospels, after all, are not myths written centuries after the time of Jesus, but rather are biographical accounts that can, more or less, all be traced back to the first century. Though written by various authors, they all testify that Jesus rose bodily from the dead. It is the same with the letters of Paul of Tarsus, an anti-Christian Jew who was later converted after seeing a vision of the resurrected Jesus. His letter to the Galatians contains a moving testimony of his conversion, and his story is corroborated by the Book of Acts, written by a man named Luke. These documents I speak of are not fabrications, but rather the writings of real people, who lived at specific times in history, and whose biographical and at times autobiographical claims largely corroborate each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my mind, the Resurrection of Jesus is the single most extraordinary event of human history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I invite you – whoever you may be – to consider the claims of Christianity for yourself. You have nothing at all to lose. If Christianity is true, then you have everything to gain from discovering its truthfulness. But if it’s false, then a careful study will only reveal its falsity, because the truth cannot ultimately be hidden. Either way, you will increase your knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What convinced me was the intellectual arguments in favour of God’s existence, the extraordinary testimony of the resurrection of Jesus, the fulfilled prophecies of the Old Testament, the beauty and power of the very words of the Saviour, and, of course, my personal experience of grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you might have questions, and you might want to learn more. If this is so, I rejoice in this, and I encourage you wholeheartedly to follow the truth wherever it leads. A good place to start is the YouTube channel Capturing Christianity, which regularly hosts discussions between Christian and atheist intellectuals and scholars. Bishop Robert Barron’s book &lt;em&gt;Catholicism: A Journey to the Heart of the Faith&lt;/em&gt; is also a great place to start. I also highly recommend the work of Edward Feser, an atheist philosopher whose studies in the philosophy of religion and mind eventually led him to convert to Christianity – I especially commend his book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs of the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;, which, in my mind, is the best intellectual and reasoned defence of classical theism that has been made in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, I urge you to take the time out and read the New Testament, which is a collection of these ancient historical writings that testify to the life and works of Jesus of Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that there are people who will read this article of mine and laugh. Why then do I write? Why then do I spend so much time telling people about a man who lived 2,000 years ago, a man I have never met in person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I believe this man is no mere man, but rather the incarnate Son of God. I write because this Man has changed my life, and He can change yours as well, if only you allow Him. And if you do, you will come to possess a joy that the world cannot give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telling people about the amazing person that is Jesus is worth any sacrifice and any cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the faith that has inspired millions, that has shaken empires, that has changed the course of human history. This is the faith of the martyrs, the confessors and the saints of the Cross. And this is the audacity with which I can stare death in the eye and proclaim that Christ is risen and that He lives forever more.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Explo-Consciousness: The Science, Phenomenology and the Implications of Psychedelic Experience</title>
      <link href="/Explo-Consciousness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explo-Consciousness: The Science, Phenomenology and the Implications of Psychedelic Experience" />
      <published>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Explo-Consciousness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Explo-Consciousness">&lt;p&gt;Since the 1930’s, with the discovery of LSD (Lysergic Acid Diethylamide) by Albert Hoffmann, and much later, with the introduction of Psilocybin mushrooms (magic mushrooms) to the west by Gordon Wasson, there has been much heated debate on the topic from all disciplines. The true history of psychedelics is as old as our evolution, and some like Terrence McKenna have even proposed that human beings developed their unique characteristics, especially that of our deep awareness and self-consciousness as a result of the consumption of varieties of psychedelic plants, especially the psilocybin mushrooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, the advent of many religions is also very likely associated with the experience of psychedelics due to the similar character of religious experiences. This view is further confirmed by the fact that, evolutionary speaking, almost all primates consume mushrooms found in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My purpose here is not to draw attention to the medical benefits of these substances; that is the job of the scientist, but I am mostly here to describe what we call ‘the psychedelic experience’, and to finally go into a theory that I have been deeply thinking about, which is called: ‘Explo-Consciousness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before anything, it is of great importance to explore the science of these substances. Both LSD and Psilocybin are psychedelics, meaning, mind-manifesting or mind-expanding substances. These substances, unlike most recreational drugs, do not increase ‘the pleasure chemicals’ like dopamine, and as such, they do not possess any addictive properties. Instead, they are called serotonergic substances; meaning that they bind with serotonin (the receptor responsible for mood and sleep regulation). When ingested, they alter the user’s perception, and interestingly they bring about hyper-connectivity within the brain as the following diagrams show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//brain-connectivity.png&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two diagrams are the representation of the brain state; (a) is the state of someone who has been given the placebo with few neuro-connectivity, whereas (b) is the brain on psilocybin. This research, carried out by the Imperial College Centre for Psychedelics, is the first time we have understood, using brain scans, that, on psilocybin, the brain becomes hyper-connected. This hyper-connectivity is also understood to suspend the brain’s ‘Default Mode Network’, which is somewhat equivalent to the ‘ego’ or the ‘self’. The DMN is what provides you with a theory of who you are, and it is particularly active when one thinks about the past or plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The over-activity of the DMN is closely correlated with mental illnesses like depression and anxiety, as, roughly stated, the former is in relation to being stuck in the past, and the latter is in relation to worrying about the future. This is, perhaps, what explains the experimental medical use of psychedelic substances to treat anxiety and depression, as for a short while a patient is, simply put, taken out of the prison of the judging and destructive self. As a result, they develop new perspectives about themselves. Such results could also be novel and life-changing for older people, as they too become imprisoned by deeply structured patterns of behaviour and belief. In short, ego dissolution or the suspension of the DMN is not only good for treating mental illnesses but could provide most people with new perspectives in extremely profound life-changing experiences. Such profound experiences were observed in many studies carried out by the John Hopkins Institute, for those of you interested to look further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when describing the psychedelic experience, one must necessarily possess a new language or form of expression, if one is to truly communicate these experiences. And, this is only possible if one enters through ‘the doors of perception’ and arrives in the place, beautifully described by Rudolph Otto, as “the wholly other” with a unique sense of “&lt;em&gt;Mysterium tremendum et fascinans&lt;/em&gt;”. This is a place where all previous beliefs become trivial and one is then struck by a sense of mystery that is infused by feeling of the holy; both imitating love and terror. One feels in union with God, if God means anything! There cannot be anything in the realm of visual and emotional experience that is more spiritual or religious than the psychedelic experience. The experience, for many, takes the turn of a true and meaningful conversation with this energy or cosmic-consciousness. As a result, if the experience is integrated, the profundity of the experience, whether positive or life-changing, can remain with the voyager. And, if negative, it can be managed with integration; hence why it is necessary to have an experienced guide when taking these sacred substances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own experiences with mushrooms have always been profound; especially the second time when I took a huge dose of 6 grams of dried Liberty Caps&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; I probably should have taken less, perhaps 4 grams. As with any psychedelics, ‘&lt;em&gt;set and setting&lt;/em&gt;’ is more important than the substance itself. My ‘set’ (state of mind) was that of a readiness to have a spiritual experience but it also expected to be terrified. And, my setting was a dark quiet room with a comfortable bed that I laid on after ingesting the mushrooms. Indeed, I was alone…and it was in this environment that I experienced the wholly other. This was my fourth time, so I saw no need for a sitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 20 minutes, I felt like my body was warming-up, in a strange spiritual sense. It was as if my body was preparing to travel to another dimension; I felt uneasy and excited at the same time. I was like a snake shedding its old skin, and subsequently after 1 hour, all my recent life-choices came in front of me from a different angle. I saw where I went wrong…. I saw and understood my recent errors or areas in life that I had not paid attention to. All of us know our weaknesses and faults but the DMN or the ego stops us from truly accepting, comprehending and feeling them. We may even admit to other people that we are in the wrong but deep in the foundation of our beliefs, we always manage to convince ourselves that the other is in the wrong. But, this time was different. This time, I gained the power to truly separate myself from my ego, and then from those eyes looked and analysed my mistakes and weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This internal feeling was neither judging nor merciful. It was, rather, like being able to look at all my infirmities with a naked eye that was free from all contaminant lenses, so pure and honest! Imagine looking through the window and seeing the disorderly garden of one’s house. Normally, we are moved by emotions such as disgust, sadness or even perhaps the urgency to clean and organise one’s garden. In my experience, there was only the observable garden and its disorganised state, I was like God just observing… After some time of seeing and understanding all my faults, I was then touched by this divine sensation of love that communicated to me that “it’s ok”. This was the most profound moment in the entire experience where I deeply felt that I didn’t have to be oppressed by my past faults and mistakes. The experience was not only meaningfully self-exploratory but deeply healing and transformative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, the purpose of human beings has transcended survival. It seems that all human cultures have understood the importance of knowledge, whether practical or theoretical. Similarly, all cultures have also understood the importance of experience not only as an activity that is fun and enjoyable but also as something that is deeply related to the human essence. In fact, these two things are not separated, but it is clearly observable that knowledge is also a derivation of either direct experience or reflections of experience. As such, the meaning and purpose of human beings is directly intertwined with experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, the more we have access to different repertoire of experiences and the more we live as humans, the closer we get to completeness of what humanness really means. It is also likely that the process of becoming more human is akin to transcending the current reality of the essence of man. In other words, such an evolution or transformation pushes one to become more than a human. One who has more, has more and is perhaps more prosperous, but one who ‘becomes’ more, he transcends himself, even surpassing God himself. For God supposedly created man…now man can constantly re-create himself and ascend at a place that God himself could never attain. For God’s essence is fixed and his nature unchangeable. All varieties of human experiences offered to us by the world (both positive and negative) is a necessary condition if one were to attain such transformation. It occurs to me after my own study and experience that the ‘psychedelic experience’ is the most profound of all possible human experiences; and yet most modern societies have demonised these sacred substances. The function of the ‘mushroom’ and other sacred plants is teaching and they are the wisest of all teachers as they teach you to think for yourself. Other than this, and many other profound functions that these plants play, they also freely gift you the most challenging and life-changing experiences, and these are not only healing but also what one needs for a true spiritual awakening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;Explo-consciousness&lt;/em&gt; simply means the explosion of consciousness, and this seems to be the essence of the psychedelic experience. In an explosion, there is death and rebirth and hence why we can participate in a constant process of becoming and hence the human being can attains such transformation that even God himself cannot. In every explosion, there is death and destruction but with the explosion of consciousness, death gives way for the resurrection of something new, of something spectacularly novel and beautiful. With the explosion of consciousness, one realises that one is in union with everything and is nothing at the same time; this is the place of the mystic…it is where they live and breathe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the question is, do you prefer a life full of indoctrination and culturally sanctioned values; a life whose contents have been determined by others? Such a life is comfortable as it requires no self-examination and self-exploration of one’s authentic self. When one enters in the psychedelic realm, one realises that the essence of man is so much more than just the ego, which is the construction of society and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, true enlightenment is a lifestyle and not a destination; true enlightenment is the process of constant death and rebirth of the self and what we refer to as the psychedelic experience does just that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Terrence-McKenna.png&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;I want to dedicate this piece to the great Terrence McKenna whose ideas have helped me integrate my psychedelic experiences!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since the 1930’s, with the discovery of LSD (Lysergic Acid Diethylamide) by Albert Hoffmann, and much later, with the introduction of Psilocybin mushrooms (magic mushrooms) to the west by Gordon Wasson, there has been much heated debate on the topic from all disciplines. The true history of psychedelics is as old as our evolution, and some like Terrence McKenna have even proposed that human beings developed their unique characteristics, especially that of our deep awareness and self-consciousness as a result of the consumption of varieties of psychedelic plants, especially the psilocybin mushrooms.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
