<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/alex.omidvar/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-01T19:11:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/alex.omidvar/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Test of the West I</title>
      <link href="/The-Test-of-the-West-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Test of the West I" />
      <published>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Test-of-the-West-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Test-of-the-West-I">&lt;p&gt;This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-I&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-II&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-III&quot;&gt;III&lt;/a&gt;). The first chapter is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter I - the fundamental values of the West&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we first articulate and clearly define the most fundamental principles that the ‘West’ has recently subscribed to? For the sake of this dialogue, we shall speak about trends, as I think culture is a rather complex term made up of various elements. And for this reason, this dialogue I think should focus on major trends and cultural phenomena. So to begin this dialogue, what do you think are those key fundamental principles? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John A Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the ‘West’ has identified freedom as its most essential principle. There are to be few constraints on our individual decisions allowing the individual to choose any set of norms within the law. The philosophical or ethical backdrop for this principle is Utilitarianism, and the implied assumption that no one set of ethical principles is better than any other. There is also the belief that I should be allowed to develop principles out of my own subjectivity because universals do not exist or should be considered “dogma” rather than rationally defensible imperatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, freedom to choose principles around end of life decisions must take precedence over professional principles, which in the past, were seen as important breaks on imbalanced power relationships. A woman may choose to have as many abortions as she desires despite concerns by her physician that harm increases with each procedure. That is, a doctor can lay aside her oath to “do no harm” if a patient requests a procedure that is legal and without restriction. In countries where assisted suicide is legal, medical colleges are tacitly agreeing with the idea that freedom of conscience for professionals cannot override a patient’s reception of a medically assisted death. High court decisions that support such laws base their judgements on three principles : 1) absolute autonomy over self;  2) relativism of personal or professional ethics; 3) the presumed calculus that benefits of such principles and practices outweigh potential harms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with you John that it seems as though individual freedom is the most fundamental principle of the West. And as I see it, individual freedom has many benefits as it keeps the government limited for the advancement of individual sovereignty. However, recently, I also see a negative aspect to freedom. A naive and narcissistic claim that defines freedom as having the ability to do whatever one wants. One need not give examples of this as the current culture screams of such patterns of behaviour such as the so-called sexual freedom that both men and women supposedly enjoy. Similarly, I identify a couple of things as hanging upon our culture. First is the claim for group and individual rights, and second is an overload of postmodern ideas that are simply about ‘deconstruction’ that are taken so dramatically as though we are to take them, ironically, as ‘truths’. And the third fundamental principle is freedom as you identified. However, there seems to be a serious clash between individual freedom (the positive aspect) and the postmodern thinking that sees everything and everyone as motivated by power. So John, can we talk about some of those points that I think are important for this discussion? I would really like to know how you see our culture unravelling in this so-called postmodern era? Also, can we expand a little bit on what I identify as the clash between individual freedom and the post-modern thought such as that of Michel Foucault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the post-modern notion that truth is a cultural construction is the source of the narcissism of the current secular culture. Foucault and Derrida show the problem with objective claims but then use this to discredit much of the history of thought. Imagine a physicist who said we cannot know much with certainty about subatomic particles, so physics is a waste of time. This is blatant arrogance, a form of intellectual hubris where only Foucault and Derrida understand what is really going on. Postmodernism also came into its own on the coat-tails of Freudian psychology whose reduction of meaning to little more than the frustration of erotic instincts is almost humorous for those of us who lived through the last half of the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional cultures never deify instincts or claim that meaning needs to be constructed out of individual sentimentality. Martin Buber notes in &lt;em&gt;Eclipse of God&lt;/em&gt; that the Enlightenment (and post-modern) motif of “deifying instincts instead of hallowing them in faith” is a replay of ancient Gnosticism, the notion that intellectual humility and self-questioning is a kind of naivety. Nietzsche and Marx are also contributors to the grand illusion that the transcendental is an illusion perpetrated to keep people in line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the cultural backdrop for the modern notion of individual freedom. Freedom cannot be expected to be ordered to a specific religious or ethical code because this means denying INSTINCT. But this does not mean we are all petty animals. We can use our instincts to create meaning for ourselves which is genuinely one’s own. And society must not interfere with this marvellous creative process with any appeals to any ‘higher’ principles than those which I create for myself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome is what appears to be a culture so boring that people discuss tattoos but not books or nature, because boredom is what you get when nothing matters but ME, ME, ME. Meaning, real meaning, is only possible when you acknowledge something other than the self. Medieval masons did not read theology, but they built cathedrals out of a sense of profound mystery. Many knew that the work would not be finished in their lifetimes. They sensed that life had a horizontal and a vertical dimension and that holding both in mind made life bearable even in the face of poverty or other challenges. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t agree anymore with your analysis of the intellectual facade of Foucault and Derrida. I am yet to discover why this intellectual discipline is so attractive amongst intellectuals and especially in our universities. Many might not have even read or heard anything about postmodern thinkers but are the partial embodiment of those ideas. For instance, the idea that everything in nature including human intention is motivated by power (in the negative sense) started with Nietzsche originally when he wrote the book &lt;em&gt;Beyond Good and Evil&lt;/em&gt;. His claim was that most philosophers did not have an ‘instinct for knowledge’ but that essentially their philosophy was a tool to further their instinctual interests in some way or the other. And that I think is partly true but the hunger for generalisation is greed. And this idea, as it occurs to me, was expanded by Foucault when he institutionalised it in the political arena while generalising it into every domain of human life. I see this doctrine or ideology as the ‘vampire’ who sucks the life out of things that are noble, beautiful and transcendent. And, as scary as it seems, I do think that this ideology is embodied in many people as I see it acting out in our culture in a way that it is hard not to identify and its role is to ‘deconstruct’ and destroy. Metaphorically, John 10:10 is perfect to demonstrate this: “The thief comes only to steal and kill and destroy; I have come that they may have life, and have it to the full.” And I think all postmodernism as a doctrine and as a cultural phenomenon (important to make the distinction) is concerned with is to steal, kill and destroy while sucking all life out of the beautiful and the transcendent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder as you correctly pointed out that people have deified their instinctual desires as we have metaphorically and literally killed the soul. And in Platonic terms, we have killed the white and noble horse and have enabled the black and ignoble one to fully take over the charioteer. I suppose that our culture has gone a step further and developed the third horse of mirrors. It is a horse of mirrors as all you see is ‘yourself’ and the direction of the charioteer of our culture seems to be under the full control of the horse of mirrors which is even stronger in our world of ‘social media’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, when I am thinking about the clash between the idea of individual freedom and the post-modern thought, what screams at me is that for the postmodernist, there is no individual that is transcendent of his desires and especially the ones associated with power and dominance. And therefore, there cannot be an individual who is free. And this has two important implications. First is that you are always a victim of others or of ideas attempting to take power over you, which I think fully destroys all human relationships as you are constantly under threat. And there is no possibility of a healthy relationship with anyone. And this is, I think, why Simone de Beauvoir and Sartre agreed that their relationship was all about their own self-interests. And, I think, the second implication is that there is no redemption for you as you too are a perpetrator or a potential one as you are not an individual, but a sort of an AI that is coded to achieve a certain self-interested function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have talked about the madness in which we have drained ourselves, John. What do you think is the solution to all this, since people seem to think that this culture has figured it all out? I mean, I am starting university in a few days and what struck me was how much the university used the nightlife culture as a tool to convince students why Oxford is a good place to study. I am not against partying but I see the problem much deeper that there are an enormous amount of other reasons why one should study there and the nightlife should not be something that the University encourages as there are other forms of enjoyment, but what are they? Have we forgotten those? Again, what is the practical and real solution to all these, John?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (I,II and III). The first chapter is as follows:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Test of the West II</title>
      <link href="/The-Test-of-the-West-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Test of the West II" />
      <published>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Test-of-the-West-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Test-of-the-West-II">&lt;p&gt;This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-I&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-II&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-III&quot;&gt;III&lt;/a&gt;). The second chapter is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 2—the solution to the excessive chaos of post-modern ideas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My theology and spirituality has a lot to do with the Jesuit notion that God is directly accessible to consciousness, but we have to learn discernment - a practice involving all of our conscious agencies: feelings, imaginings, reasoning and mystical encounter to experience God’s personal call in one’s life. We all have a call, a purpose that unfolds, no matter what life brings us, good things or bad. You might think that your study habits brought you to university, but the spirit played a role as well. A Higher Power, a grace deeper than the conceptual, but integrative with thought and reason. The secular night-life, on the other hand, will leave you bored and drained, what the mystics call ‘desolation’. But where the Spirit leads you will produce the opposite effect—joy, rather than pleasure—what they call consolation. So, as a practical matter, be a pilgrim rather than a tourist. Visit sacred places: the Taize and L’ Arche communities in England and on the continent. The great cathedrals and monastic centres. Wherever you feel the deeper promptings. Discern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your description of the postmoderns sucking the life out of people is deeply insightful. They are psychologists not philosophers and they don’t even understand psychology all that well. Sartre’s “hell is other people’’ is based on his own narcissism in my view.  Here is freedom without responsibility to anything other than self. When he wrote &lt;em&gt;Existentialism as a Humanism&lt;/em&gt;, there was something of the grandeur of the human. But without something other to engage with, one is thrown back on self-gazing. No wonder there are so many ‘flaneurs’ in France!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here is where spirituality comes in. My view is that absence of God produces self-hatred. Closed in on the self, post-moderns claim this is some kind of virtue. So, individuals try desperately to attain the unattainable, falling into intellectual despair. I saw your video with your philosophy teacher who kept saying “probably there is no God”. But if that is the case, why go on repeating the phrase? I am sure that many bright people who were taken over by fundamentalism, need this revolt to regain their sanity. But revolt is just the first step. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thinking about writing a paper to be called ‘Human beings: animals or icons?’ Sartre was unconsciously projecting his inner ‘hell’ onto others – hating others because he hated himself. God is what first produces self-love. It can be a struggle but I see myself as an icon reflecting transcendent beauty, and I come to see this in others, in nature, etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christian philosophers look at revelation and then see how philosophy helps deepen our understanding of the notions given in the revelation. If you want a good text, look at Joseph Owens, &lt;em&gt;An Elementary Christian Metaphysics.&lt;/em&gt; He is from the generation that read ALL the relevant sources and can summarise them with authority and depth. So, I would encourage you to turn from reading the “flavour of the month”  (Nietzsche and friends) and find the real scholars. If anybody at Oxford is offering a course or talk on Aristotle’s metaphysics, check it out. Also, see if there is a Lonergan Centre there. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In later scribs I can show you the philosophical problems that come from Descartes, Hume and Kant and why their false understanding of the self helped bring us to where we are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of discernment is very interesting, and I would like to think about it practically for the sake of it being an accessible argument for those who are not part of any community of faith. And your analysis very much reminds me of Jung’s idea of circumambulation. Indeed, this idea describes that during a person’s lifetime, there are individual meaningful phenomena that occur that points one to a fraction of his destination or ‘Being’ and the sum total of a set of significant experiences could lead one to pursue a certain path in life towards the completion of their ‘Telos’. I think your very insightful notion of discernment can be shown practically and without the requirement of any sort of faith. In short, one needs to become aware of his experiences, and also to become a master of his own self, if that person is to attain anything approximating his Telos. And the tool that allows you to become fully aware and deeply conscious of your experiences; that enables you to understand why they are happening to you, as well as that which frees you from the shackles of your own misapprehensions is discernment. And indeed, one needs a source of divine inspiration (literal or metaphorical) or divine sense of direction to discover one’s own deep Telos whilst becoming strong enough spiritually and mentally to move towards the completion of one’s essence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your comments on the postmodern thinkers; that they have created or at least strongly influenced the current narcissistic culture is something I strongly agree with. So far, the student committee at Oxford has tried their best to impose their ideologies onto us in the most aggressive and reprehensible manner, including a compulsory workshop on ‘Consent’ and a compulsory talk on Diversity and Inclusion which included doctrines such as micro-aggression and cultural appropriation. The very fact that they were compulsory signals to me a disease that far exceeds the narcissism of the typical kind because, to begin with, they presented their ideologies as facts and explained that anything contrary to these beliefs is morally abhorrent and will be met with consequences. So it is not only that they are narcissistic for using this sort of activism to feel virtuous or good about themselves, but that we also must do this too if we are not to be identified as the ‘other’, the unknown that lurks in the background and is nothing but a reprehensive and morally repugnant being. An important caveat is that this is not unique to this wonderful university with its rich history and amazing education but that this post-modern, resentful and tribal culture has infiltrated deeply the collective unconscious soul of the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And your comment that “Sartre was unconsciously projecting his inner “hell” onto others—hating others because he hated himself” is extremely insightful. This is similar to the sort of idea that you read into situations your own toxic ideas or experiences. Why? I believe the feeling of having the upper moral hand is overwhelmingly motivating and Nietzsche’s notion of resentment is also a strong possibility; that people hate those who are better than them along any dimensions (e.g. economic, social relations and status). Moreover, finding an enemy seems very much convenient as a tool to escape responsibility, but even stronger than all motivations is the one that seeks to demolish all that is noble and beautiful as an act of revenge that is morally justifiable (from their eyes) and perhaps even virtuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last section of this dialogue, can you put forward your analysis of the philosophical problems that come from Descartes, Hume and Kant and why their false understanding of the Self helped bring us to where we are today? I also think a good way to end this dialogue is to provide a practical solution to this desolated and resentful culture that is filled with narcissism, nihilism and nothing beautiful or transcendent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John A Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Alex for your reflections. I want to begin by agreeing with you about the philosophical aspects of discernment. Consciousness, and I am speaking about particular or existential consciousness, is caught up with history. All of us know our lives will end, and so we are constantly in touch with the “arc of one’s own life”. Beginning with Socrates, we have a well thought out record of what one must do with this knowledge. The Greeks, and I am thinking of Socrates, Plato and Aristotle, point to the ethical as a conscious response to this awareness of human finitude. But ethics is understood from the angle of metaphysics. These thinkers argued that our self-knowledge, and indeed our scientific knowledge is ‘going somewhere’. No need to put a lot of religious names to it. They left us with an insight. They knew that the study of the physical world is a study of mechanisms, but there was an intuitional sense that the explanation of all these mechanisms, can’t be more mechanisms. For Aristotle, the summit of meaning for humans is contemplation. This contemplation is a ‘habit of thought’ for those who practice it. This ‘habit’ is grounded in the desire of consciousness to go beyond itself. It is intuitional but not outside the intellectual activities of rational knowers. A modern Aristotelian, Andrew Beards, points to the multiple referentiality of thinking that forces us to consider some “whole” for which all this complexity tends. Metaphysics is the wisdom which develops in the pursuit of the whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the backdrop for understanding modern philosophy, and the turn to the Self that begins with Descartes and continues to challenge us today. Descartes claimed that the intuition to go beyond the self which founded Western philosophy should not be trusted. Ironically he substituted a subjectivist intuition for a realist/existential one. His intuition came from the clean lines and unambiguous concepts of geometry. However his notion of clear and distinct ideas is neither clear nor distinct. Even if I were to concede that some ideas are clearer, better, more rational than others, why should I insist that such things can prove anything about those ideas that are neither clear nor distinct? Werner Heisenberg won a Nobel Prize for proving that the foundations of the material universe are not at all clear and distinct notions; and he explains that the ‘Uncertainty Principle’ had much in common with Aristotle’s notion of ‘substantial principle’, which is both actually existing and potentially something more than it appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hume is equally captivated by intuitions leading to a similar dead-end as Descartes. Perhaps the self is being controlled by cleverly constructed fictions like causality, confused notions that are psychologically grounded but not rationally defensible. I simply have a ‘feeling’ that A causes B, but this is not ‘because’ of knowledge of the material world. But we can level the same criticism here as applies to Descartes, namely, why should the ‘feeling’ that I can’t know causality be more reliable than the scientific knowledge that comes from studying the reasons behind things and their behaviour? Why is this psychological intuition more reliable than the reasons offered for saying ‘smoking causes cancer’? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Hume and Kant claim that they have knowledge based on rational argument. But rational argument is based on the notion of something following from something else. And it is through judgement that we know when such connections are justified and when they are not. Hume is using the idea that something follows from something else to discredit causality (the idea that something follows from something else). Kant is claiming that we have no real knowledge beyond appearance, but this is a self-contradiction. It amounts to saying: a) All knowledge is appearance. b) Knowledge of ‘a’ is not appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, post-moderns have their own set of ‘intuitions’ that they see as somehow self-evident. Their focus on language as ultimately subjective is based on the mistake of taking a tool for studying reality, to constitute reality. I can use language to structure reality but only because I am not structured by it. Language is a tool, nothing more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joseph Owens in &lt;em&gt;An Elementary Christian Metaphysics&lt;/em&gt; points out that phenomenological studies of consciousness (forms of “know thyself”) are the source and substance of philosophy, but many phenomenologies choose to ignore one of the phenomenological givens that cannot be ignored for long—EXISTENCE. When I study the apple on my desk and attend to the course of thoughts and perceptions in this conscious activity, one very clear intuition is EXISTENCE. This apple is not just a mass of subjective impressions; actual existence is one of the biggest impressions of the exercise. It cannot be bracketed because ‘to be’ is irreducible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a practical programme for going forward, one needs to become involved in curriculum development. The ‘telos’ for all conscious activities should be ‘truth’. But truth is a historically motivated study. Curriculum must return to the historical component of self-knowledge. Humans need to re-assert the value of knowing how we have come to the place where we are today. This involves truth-telling, the vocation of ‘the witness’. The great error of the philosophers that I have criticised is their complete abandonment of history. They have taken the Self to be a non-historical psychological entity without any ontological significance. As Gabriel Marcel noted, &lt;em&gt;“Thought far from being a relation with itself, is on the contrary essentially a self-transcendence.”&lt;/em&gt; There is more to existence than self. This fundamental intuition is the foundation of human beings. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (I,II and III). The second chapter is as follows:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Test of the West III</title>
      <link href="/The-Test-of-the-West-III" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Test of the West III" />
      <published>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Test-of-the-West-III</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Test-of-the-West-III">&lt;p&gt;This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-I&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-II&quot;&gt;II&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/The-Test-of-the-West-III&quot;&gt;III&lt;/a&gt;). The third chapter is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 3—Final thoughts on cultural evolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Omidvar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John, you made very interesting points and I really like the way you recorded the history of postmodern ideas that are now poisoning the West. I recently became aware of an extremely interesting philosopher and theorist called Ken Wilber and I have to say that I really find his work fascinating. His ideas were influenced by people like the developmental psychologist Piaget, and his Integral Theory fits in what you said in the last paragraph about moving forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His Integral Theory was that ‘a system’ like culture requires two things if it hopes to move forward and to progress. First, is transcendence, and by that, he meant an update from the old culture, though the second principle is ‘to include’ the previous culture. So the model goes something like this: In order for culture to progress and to prevent it from fragmentation, it needs to transcend and include the previous culture. In practicality, this means that some ideas of the past will be rejected and some new ones will be inserted. However, a new system must include the previous ones, because otherwise, you get a culture war, where people’s first principles are widely different. This is where we are right now as postmodern culture is acting like the Freudian superego, repressing the previous cultures that came before it. This produces nothing but polarisation, cultural fragmentation and a serious suspension of progress, or perhaps even a move towards regression. However, as Integral Theory suggests, we are also to be grateful for some postmodern ideas such as ‘diversity and inclusion’, not in the sense of what it means now but merely in our change of attitude towards ‘those who are not like us’ to feel included. The fact that there is less hatred for these groups is also something that the postmodern movement has contributed to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I could not agree with you more on your comments on how to move forward. I also think that the spoken truth (the logos) is the antidote to this chaos, hence why I am in the process of creating a youtube channel for Oxford Students to come forward and speak their minds. Equally, your emphasis on the interconnectivity of the self with the past is very insightful. When we read the great works of the past, we are, in a sense, resurrecting the souls of those who came before us and shaped who we are today. And, this is, I think, extremely important as if we do not know ‘them’, we do not know ‘ourselves’, and if we ignore what they had to say, we end up in this empty and materialistic universe where the self is no more than consciousness due to chemicals reacting in our brains. And, what replaces our sense of self is the product of this technological environment where consciousness and Instagram are in an unholy union. We have, in essence, given up our true essence and the ground of our being for the sake of pleasure which only produces dopamine and leaves us in an empty state of inertia and meaninglessness. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as a note to finish this enjoyable dialogue, what is your view for the next ten to twenty years; will we be able to redeem ourselves or are we headed for disaster? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Artibello&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with the notions of Ken Wilber in that they remind me of how McLuhan spoke of culture. He would say that as we move forward in time we often retrieve ideas from different periods. There have been several cycles in which ‘classical’ ideas have been brought back to light the way forward. I am thinking for example of Werner Heisenberg, winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics, who stated “some statements of ancient philosophy are rather near to those of modern science.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important news for us who have seen the many problems with postmodernism, particularly its complete abandonment of transcendence, in favour of subjectivism—full stop.  The past is ‘still here’ and just as brilliant as before. Important ideas are not made obsolete by the mistaken notions that the present must be better than the past and that we must be wiser than those who have gone before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally I believe the way forward is by adopting some of the medieval courage to consider all ideas as worthy of examination, not just the ones we have been told are politically correct. We might also benefit from the medieval notion that we are pilgrims upon the earth not masters and power seekers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there is a bizarre hubris in those who think a new system of ideas is possible without including the leading insights of the past. Clearly, thinkers of the pedigree of Werner Heisenberg, are stating as much in their reflections on, for example, advanced science. There is no law that says that as we move forward in time the quality of our thinking gets better. McLuhan and others called this out long ago. He suggested we look at history as a collective consciousness, a mosaic made up of different independent notions which also combine into a kind of whole. And there is the warning that those who ignore history are condemned to repeat it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the next ten to twenty years, we need to go in the opposite direction to the ‘exclusive humanism’ and ‘immanentism’ of many in academia. We must humbly hold up the value of being pilgrims not masters—of listening to those who accept reality as it is rather than those who think reality can be magically constructed based on our desires and dreams. We need to challenge the obscurantism of those who claim questions about the ultimate meaning of it all cannot be answered, and should never be taken seriously. We need to champion the civilising structures that have been the great gifts to humanity, and acknowledge their spiritual roots, without lapsing into psychologism or sociological whimsy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been noted how philosopher-theologians like Bernard Lonergan “showed how the methods of modern empirical science - once stripped of their extra- scientific assumptions of exclusive humanism and naturalism - imply an open-ended, non reductive, emerging universe which integrates the natural and human domains and is dynamically oriented to a transcendent reality beyond it.”  (Michael McCarthy)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either we think of ourselves as icons reflecting a deeper light and truth than we can fathom, or we succumb to some idol or other, trying to convince ourselves of some half-truth that hollows rather than hallows our deepest yearnings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an authentic self-examination and self-appropriation, why not look at our talents and gifts, not as ‘subjective’ traits, but as ontologically necessary for making life to be what it is meant to be? In the depths of our hearts, is there not a still small voice, pointing to all the transcendent realities that we hope are true, and can we find the voice to make them real - here, now, and forever? &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is the transcript of an extremely stimulating and insightful conversation between Alex Omidvar and philosopher John Artibello. John Artibello had taught philosophy for 22 years at Centennial, George Brown and Humber Colleges in Toronto, Canada. He did graduate work in philosophy at the University of Toronto where he met, and was inspired by Marshall McLuhan, Bernard Lonergan and Jean Vanier. His special interests are in ethics, spirituality, the psychology of meaning and ecology. Many of the writings contained at this site are attempts to synthesize ideas from a variety of sources and reflect the contributions of countless thinkers and writers engaged in the humanities and global learning. The conversation between Artibello and Alex has been divided into three chapters (I,II and III). The third chapter is as follows:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Chaos and Order—How to Bring the Ego to Equilibrium Through an Act of Metamorphosis</title>
      <link href="/Chaos-and-Order" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chaos and Order—How to Bring the Ego to Equilibrium Through an Act of Metamorphosis" />
      <published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Chaos-and-Order</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Chaos-and-Order">&lt;p&gt;I would like to begin this article by an act of meditation, and would also like to humbly ask you to participate in this process by allowing your mind to freely explore the depth of your imagination and to make links, connections and associations between the following words. Please allow the following words to gently hover in your mind as you are reading this article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;chaos, order, uncertainty, self-discovery, death, rebirth, transcendence, the ego, your grounding, metamorphosis, culture, creation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As human beings, we are all struck by existential problems—we do not know where we come from, we do not know why we are here in this mysterious world, and we also do not know where we are going. All the advances in knowledge should not lead one to be deceived about how much we don’t know. Far too often we like to claim knowledge or understanding because certainty keeps us sane and helps us in our survival. If we all wake up in the morning and start questioning our lives and our choices really honestly as we go through our days, we will be held suspended in a state of inertia and existential angst. There is a point where we act on our beliefs even though we are not sure about them. And, herein lies the conundrum of our lives: we all know that we don’t know but we act as if we know. What is the solution? Or a question to be asked first, is that, why is it that most people from the learned to the unlearned, from the sane to the insane, from the poor to the rich, often act and behave in a manner as if they somehow know the ‘truth’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As animals, human beings are part of the fabric of the evolutionary processes, and as such, much of what we refer to as ‘me’ is simply the by-product of the evolutionary processes. Specifically, in the cortex of the human brain, even though we don’t understand it fully, there are a few observations we can make. Firstly, that in its process of evolution, the two hemispheres of the brain have been both specialised for certain specific functions, with the right hemisphere being the one that is involved in the acts of exploration that opens us up to possibilities, and the left hemisphere being the one that seeks to tie itself down to certainty (see &lt;em&gt;The Master and his Emissary&lt;/em&gt; by Iain McGilchrist). And, the constant interplay of these two hemispheres can be understood as the brain trying to balance between chaos and order. With chaos being that which is beyond our understanding, or that which we do not understand; and order being the polar opposite, that which is within our grasp, or that which we do understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already we can see from evolution’s point of view that it would be overwhelming for the human mind to perceive all the realities surrounding it, and just like the importance of forgetting, it is also important that we only receive certain sensory data from the world in the form of perceptions. And, as evolution is concerned with our survival, the brain also evolved such that it only perceives realities that concerns it for its survival, and as we have already observed, the left hemisphere, and indeed about 25% of the entire brain’s context acts as an inhibitory mechanism. In other words, the brain as observed by Huxley (see &lt;em&gt;The Doors of Perception&lt;/em&gt; by Aldous Huxley) blocks off much of the sensory data produced by the surrounding environment. Now we have addressed the first question, which was that, why do humans act as if they know the truth—simply because our brains give us a very convincing illusion of reality (an incomplete picture of reality, not inaccurate!). Here also lies the problem of the ego, as much of the ego is the result of complex evolutionary processes which formed for a multiplicity of reasons such as self-defense, survival, dominance, self-identify and many more factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, from the very moment we are born, we are inhabited by the spirit of our ancestors, so to speak - a metaphor of this long evolutionary process. The brain of a human child is then nourished and developed through one’s upbringing into his family, society and above all into his culture. This is where the biological foundations of the ego are then built on by the culture. A simple example is the universal thirst for economic prosperity; once a biological drive for survival, it is now transformed to a culturally ego-driven desire to consume with ever-more new products being created for such desire, and with much emphasis being placed upon the acquisition of objects, and sometimes people for that matter! In fact, most aspects of culture are about the creation and maintenance of boundaries and order—and what is the driving mechanism that fuels culture? — The ego of course! It is as deep as the dawn of humanity, it is ancient and present in every single human being. The ego is self-centered, it advocated for its own growth at the cost of everything including nature herself—no reference is needed in the current ecological disaster where man cannot stop himself from constant exploitation of the environment. In short, as Terence McKenna once said, “The ego will become like a cyst if left untreated”, and I actually think that the ego is more like a tumor, that if untreated, it will lead to collective seizures which gets manifested in forms of natural disasters, human bloodshed, exploitation of others, and ultimately, the destruction of our world. And, culture far from balancing this toxic order as fuelled by the ego with the feminine spirit, it further strengthens the ego and advocates for the continuation of its survival. Only after the times of major collective disasters (eg: global pandemics), will we see major change in our attitude towards each other and towards our environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But parts of the ego is necessary. In the book, &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;, Nietzsche explores the necessity of the first stage of human metamorphosis, which he represents as the camel. He writes: “the weight-bearing spirit takes upon itself all these heaviest things: like a camel hurrying laden into the desert, thus hurries into its desert”. Understanding the camel as human beings and the weight that is being carried as tradition and culture, it is a natural stage of man’s development where we acquire our self-identity and become a slave to our cultural values. However, the solution as advocated by Nietzsche’s character as represented in the second and third state of man’s metamorphosis is that of the lion, and then the child. Once we have nourished and developed our ego and learnt the wisdom of the past, it is time to doubt them with a spirit of courage (the lion stage), and then, finally, we must participate in a process of self-discovery, self-exploration, and above all to create one’s own values (the child stage). Thus, the act of creation, and constant death and rebirth of one’s values and beliefs is necessary for the final stage of man’s metamorphosis. But Nietzsche’s abstract ideas can also lead to the re-growth of the ego as one is in total freedom to create one’s values, so why not to create novel ego-driven values? This is where man’s true and complete act of metamorphosis must be in direct harmony with the spirit of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I have delineated the history and the origin of the ego and its processes of development within culture, and explained how the ego becomes not only toxic to ourselves but also to nature herself. But, I also indicated why the ego is necessary and inevitable, it need not be destroyed but it requires to be treated through acts of metamorphosis. Now a question which we asked in the beginning, what is the solution? All these abstract ideas of self-transformation seem all well and good but none are of any practical use. And, that is why the practice of ego-dissolving activity in shamanism is necessary if the ego is to be treated. The other solution as we already alluded to is to wait for major disasters so that the ego can observe the effects of himself, and in an act of pathetic self-preservation, mutate and change course, but don’t be fooled, this is only for the short term. Whereas, activities like community, love, caring and connecting to nature and each other, connection and the bringing together of people on the internet, the use of psychedelic plant medicines all act as a cure for the toxic elements of the ego. Particularly, the proper use of psychedelics in its shamanic context with right intentions can bring about a shift in consciousness and a dissolution of the ego such that our values become aligned with planetary values—that of care and love for nature and one another. The chaos that psychedelics introduce into the cultural machinery is one reliable way to bring the ego to equilibrium. But, as I have already indicated, the ego need not be completely dissolved but only treated, as we do need our personal identities and we should be grateful for some of the achievement of the ego like our advanced civilization, or my act of writing this very article until 5 am in the morning for a girl that I have a crush on.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I would like to begin this article by an act of meditation, and would also like to humbly ask you to participate in this process by allowing your mind to freely explore the depth of your imagination and to make links, connections and associations between the following words. Please allow the following words to gently hover in your mind as you are reading this article:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Explo-Consciousness: The Science, Phenomenology and the Implications of Psychedelic Experience</title>
      <link href="/Explo-Consciousness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explo-Consciousness: The Science, Phenomenology and the Implications of Psychedelic Experience" />
      <published>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Explo-Consciousness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Explo-Consciousness">&lt;p&gt;Since the 1930’s, with the discovery of LSD (Lysergic Acid Diethylamide) by Albert Hoffmann, and much later, with the introduction of Psilocybin mushrooms (magic mushrooms) to the west by Gordon Wasson, there has been much heated debate on the topic from all disciplines. The true history of psychedelics is as old as our evolution, and some like Terrence McKenna have even proposed that human beings developed their unique characteristics, especially that of our deep awareness and self-consciousness as a result of the consumption of varieties of psychedelic plants, especially the psilocybin mushrooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, the advent of many religions is also very likely associated with the experience of psychedelics due to the similar character of religious experiences. This view is further confirmed by the fact that, evolutionary speaking, almost all primates consume mushrooms found in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My purpose here is not to draw attention to the medical benefits of these substances; that is the job of the scientist, but I am mostly here to describe what we call ‘the psychedelic experience’, and to finally go into a theory that I have been deeply thinking about, which is called: ‘Explo-Consciousness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before anything, it is of great importance to explore the science of these substances. Both LSD and Psilocybin are psychedelics, meaning, mind-manifesting or mind-expanding substances. These substances, unlike most recreational drugs, do not increase ‘the pleasure chemicals’ like dopamine, and as such, they do not possess any addictive properties. Instead, they are called serotonergic substances; meaning that they bind with serotonin (the receptor responsible for mood and sleep regulation). When ingested, they alter the user’s perception, and interestingly they bring about hyper-connectivity within the brain as the following diagrams show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//brain-connectivity.png&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two diagrams are the representation of the brain state; (a) is the state of someone who has been given the placebo with few neuro-connectivity, whereas (b) is the brain on psilocybin. This research, carried out by the Imperial College Centre for Psychedelics, is the first time we have understood, using brain scans, that, on psilocybin, the brain becomes hyper-connected. This hyper-connectivity is also understood to suspend the brain’s ‘Default Mode Network’, which is somewhat equivalent to the ‘ego’ or the ‘self’. The DMN is what provides you with a theory of who you are, and it is particularly active when one thinks about the past or plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The over-activity of the DMN is closely correlated with mental illnesses like depression and anxiety, as, roughly stated, the former is in relation to being stuck in the past, and the latter is in relation to worrying about the future. This is, perhaps, what explains the experimental medical use of psychedelic substances to treat anxiety and depression, as for a short while a patient is, simply put, taken out of the prison of the judging and destructive self. As a result, they develop new perspectives about themselves. Such results could also be novel and life-changing for older people, as they too become imprisoned by deeply structured patterns of behaviour and belief. In short, ego dissolution or the suspension of the DMN is not only good for treating mental illnesses but could provide most people with new perspectives in extremely profound life-changing experiences. Such profound experiences were observed in many studies carried out by the John Hopkins Institute, for those of you interested to look further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when describing the psychedelic experience, one must necessarily possess a new language or form of expression, if one is to truly communicate these experiences. And, this is only possible if one enters through ‘the doors of perception’ and arrives in the place, beautifully described by Rudolph Otto, as “the wholly other” with a unique sense of “&lt;em&gt;Mysterium tremendum et fascinans&lt;/em&gt;”. This is a place where all previous beliefs become trivial and one is then struck by a sense of mystery that is infused by feeling of the holy; both imitating love and terror. One feels in union with God, if God means anything! There cannot be anything in the realm of visual and emotional experience that is more spiritual or religious than the psychedelic experience. The experience, for many, takes the turn of a true and meaningful conversation with this energy or cosmic-consciousness. As a result, if the experience is integrated, the profundity of the experience, whether positive or life-changing, can remain with the voyager. And, if negative, it can be managed with integration; hence why it is necessary to have an experienced guide when taking these sacred substances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own experiences with mushrooms have always been profound; especially the second time when I took a huge dose of 6 grams of dried Liberty Caps&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; I probably should have taken less, perhaps 4 grams. As with any psychedelics, ‘&lt;em&gt;set and setting&lt;/em&gt;’ is more important than the substance itself. My ‘set’ (state of mind) was that of a readiness to have a spiritual experience but it also expected to be terrified. And, my setting was a dark quiet room with a comfortable bed that I laid on after ingesting the mushrooms. Indeed, I was alone…and it was in this environment that I experienced the wholly other. This was my fourth time, so I saw no need for a sitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 20 minutes, I felt like my body was warming-up, in a strange spiritual sense. It was as if my body was preparing to travel to another dimension; I felt uneasy and excited at the same time. I was like a snake shedding its old skin, and subsequently after 1 hour, all my recent life-choices came in front of me from a different angle. I saw where I went wrong…. I saw and understood my recent errors or areas in life that I had not paid attention to. All of us know our weaknesses and faults but the DMN or the ego stops us from truly accepting, comprehending and feeling them. We may even admit to other people that we are in the wrong but deep in the foundation of our beliefs, we always manage to convince ourselves that the other is in the wrong. But, this time was different. This time, I gained the power to truly separate myself from my ego, and then from those eyes looked and analysed my mistakes and weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This internal feeling was neither judging nor merciful. It was, rather, like being able to look at all my infirmities with a naked eye that was free from all contaminant lenses, so pure and honest! Imagine looking through the window and seeing the disorderly garden of one’s house. Normally, we are moved by emotions such as disgust, sadness or even perhaps the urgency to clean and organise one’s garden. In my experience, there was only the observable garden and its disorganised state, I was like God just observing… After some time of seeing and understanding all my faults, I was then touched by this divine sensation of love that communicated to me that “it’s ok”. This was the most profound moment in the entire experience where I deeply felt that I didn’t have to be oppressed by my past faults and mistakes. The experience was not only meaningfully self-exploratory but deeply healing and transformative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, the purpose of human beings has transcended survival. It seems that all human cultures have understood the importance of knowledge, whether practical or theoretical. Similarly, all cultures have also understood the importance of experience not only as an activity that is fun and enjoyable but also as something that is deeply related to the human essence. In fact, these two things are not separated, but it is clearly observable that knowledge is also a derivation of either direct experience or reflections of experience. As such, the meaning and purpose of human beings is directly intertwined with experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, the more we have access to different repertoire of experiences and the more we live as humans, the closer we get to completeness of what humanness really means. It is also likely that the process of becoming more human is akin to transcending the current reality of the essence of man. In other words, such an evolution or transformation pushes one to become more than a human. One who has more, has more and is perhaps more prosperous, but one who ‘becomes’ more, he transcends himself, even surpassing God himself. For God supposedly created man…now man can constantly re-create himself and ascend at a place that God himself could never attain. For God’s essence is fixed and his nature unchangeable. All varieties of human experiences offered to us by the world (both positive and negative) is a necessary condition if one were to attain such transformation. It occurs to me after my own study and experience that the ‘psychedelic experience’ is the most profound of all possible human experiences; and yet most modern societies have demonised these sacred substances. The function of the ‘mushroom’ and other sacred plants is teaching and they are the wisest of all teachers as they teach you to think for yourself. Other than this, and many other profound functions that these plants play, they also freely gift you the most challenging and life-changing experiences, and these are not only healing but also what one needs for a true spiritual awakening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;Explo-consciousness&lt;/em&gt; simply means the explosion of consciousness, and this seems to be the essence of the psychedelic experience. In an explosion, there is death and rebirth and hence why we can participate in a constant process of becoming and hence the human being can attains such transformation that even God himself cannot. In every explosion, there is death and destruction but with the explosion of consciousness, death gives way for the resurrection of something new, of something spectacularly novel and beautiful. With the explosion of consciousness, one realises that one is in union with everything and is nothing at the same time; this is the place of the mystic…it is where they live and breathe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the question is, do you prefer a life full of indoctrination and culturally sanctioned values; a life whose contents have been determined by others? Such a life is comfortable as it requires no self-examination and self-exploration of one’s authentic self. When one enters in the psychedelic realm, one realises that the essence of man is so much more than just the ego, which is the construction of society and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, true enlightenment is a lifestyle and not a destination; true enlightenment is the process of constant death and rebirth of the self and what we refer to as the psychedelic experience does just that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Terrence-McKenna.png&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;I want to dedicate this piece to the great Terrence McKenna whose ideas have helped me integrate my psychedelic experiences!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since the 1930’s, with the discovery of LSD (Lysergic Acid Diethylamide) by Albert Hoffmann, and much later, with the introduction of Psilocybin mushrooms (magic mushrooms) to the west by Gordon Wasson, there has been much heated debate on the topic from all disciplines. The true history of psychedelics is as old as our evolution, and some like Terrence McKenna have even proposed that human beings developed their unique characteristics, especially that of our deep awareness and self-consciousness as a result of the consumption of varieties of psychedelic plants, especially the psilocybin mushrooms.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
