<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/tushar.singh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-01-03T09:31:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/tushar.singh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Diary of a Confused Indian Economics Student</title>
      <link href="/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diary of a Confused Indian Economics Student" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dear Diary,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I return to you, yet again. You have been a constant support in times like these. I wonder if this happens with everyone- for days, you are the king of your small world, a world which you understand; then, all of a sudden, everything crumbles down, every fact which you thought was true becomes fiction, every emotion you had turns out to be shallow, every moment you lived seems worthless. I feel shelterless, the roof of meaning taken away from above my head. Hence, here I am, meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be used to my spiraling down of emotions by now. However, this time, it’s different (trust me). Unlike all my previous breakdowns, there is no particular person to blame, and this leaves me even more clueless. How puny us humans are, always looking for a guilty party, to make ourselves feel lighter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the issue now. The reason behind my sudden disillusionment with the world is the new Indian GDP back series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it? Oh, of course, I have to explain it, you are just a silly diary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the GDP growth rate of our country over the past decade or so has been revised and updated. As per the updated GDP data, India grew at 6.7% between 2004 and 2014. This is in contrast to previous figures of 8.1% from 2004-09 and 7.46% from 2009-14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the issue with that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I AM NOT SURE. That’s the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if we are a high growth economy or not. The world thinks so (or thought so). Even I thought so, till yesterday. However, the new data doesn’t. We never crossed the 9% growth rate, EVER.  Some numbers here and there, and I am questioning my own country’s growth story, something which I was proud of (till yesterday, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean we never grew at the pace we thought we had? But, I have seen luxuries become necessities for the consumer every five years, middle class getting richer, sons earning in their first year more than what their fathers earned throughout their lives. Doesn’t this count as exceptional growth? Or worse, what we experienced in the past decade was nothing exceptional, and the Indian economy, even after 70 years, has nothing to show for achievements. No, no, this cannot be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if we didn’t achieve high growth (more than 9%), what explains the high inflation we faced towards the end of 2013? How can there be high inflation without high growth? Was the inflation JUST because of external factors like Oil? So much purchasing power wiped away by double digit inflation rates because a few countries (Read: OPEC) wanted to have fun with the world? The worst of my thoughts are yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world knows that we have a highly indebted banking sector. Rising NPAs (non-performing assets, basically loans given by banks which don’t get repaid completely) have been the single largest threat to the Indian economy for the past 5 years, at least. It is widely acknowledged that banks lent rapidly (and sometimes indiscriminately) between 2008 and 2014, which has led to this problem today. However, in the short-term, this excessive lending helped us achieve exceptional growth rates, even touching 10.3% in 2010-11. All this, obviously, as per the old data. Now, the ‘excessive lending’ (should we still call it that?), which has created an unprecedented crisis in our economy, didn’t even help us achieve ‘high growth’ phase. Much ado about nothing. Why doesn’t the government also downgrade the NPAs in the economy? I am sure there is a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh Diary, spare a thought for all the poor foreign investors who were fooled into investing into this apparently ‘high growth’ economy which wasn’t! A decade of optimism, all for nothing. It was a lie. A scam. In case I haven’t made it clear enough, an economy is in a ‘high growth’ phase when it crosses 9% growth, which India didn’t (I know I have made it pretty clear. I just needed another reason to repeat it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that the new GDP data has been released by NITI Aayog, a government think-tank, and not by the Central Statistics Office, as is the norm. I feel sad for poor Adarsh, my close friend. He is working so hard to join the Indian Statistical Institute in Kolkata, only to find his dream job has being taken over by a bureaucrat run organization!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two beneficiaries from the new data, though, and this (somewhat) gives me a reason to smile: Unemployed youth and distressed farmers. These poor fellows had been wondering how did a high-growth phase not create enough jobs/ increase the standard of living for them. They now have an answer: there was no high growth economy to produce jobs/ increase standard of living in the first place!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I am just overreacting. Yes, yes. I am overreacting. Arvind Virmani, our former Chief Economic Advisor, has said that usually GDP data updates like this one lead to a downgrade of a country’s growth. He must know better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just, one thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before this data was released, another revised GDP data was ‘leaked’. As per this particular leaked data, India actually grew at a faster pace than even previously estimated. Yes! We touched double digit growth more often than we had thought. However, the government (this happened a few months ago) had then said that the revision of GDP numbers is still under process and these are not the final numbers. What I understand is that there are several ways to revise GDP numbers, and the leaked and the newly released official version are only two of the many alternatives. SURELY, the government won’t intentionally recognize a methodology to discredit the growth rates under it’s political rival. Surely, it won’t. Not before an election year. Definitely not. After all, this government is known for respecting institutions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ndtv.com/india-news/rbi-vs-government-10-things-to-know-1941159&quot;&gt;Read: RBI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really sorry, I know I am going over-board. I just have a few silly questions to end with (Don’t laugh). If our percentage growth has been downgraded, our absolute GDP must have come down too, wouldn’t it? I was hearing that Indian GDP (nominal basis) will overtake United Kingdom’s in 2019. I suppose this won’t happen. OR will it? Why hasn’t our absolute GDP number been downgraded, yet? Data also shows that India did not recover from the global financial crisis as quickly as initially thought. Are we a resilient economy as we thought we were, or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several international institutions have been coming up with research (using old data) showing the huge number of people India lifted out of poverty, something which I take pride in. A low GDP growth means more people must still be under poverty than previously estimated. &lt;em&gt;‘A stroke of a pen and millions are poor again’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t end on such a melancholic note. Hear this story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
 Last week, I asked my philosophy teacher this, “What GDP number, what military capability, what standard of living, what cultural clout do we need to achieve in order to become a Superpower?”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teacher’s answer left me thinking, and it seems relevant today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

“0”

&lt;br /&gt;

“0?”, I asked confused.

&lt;br /&gt;

He said, “What use is any of what you said to a nation whose soul is great enough to capture hearts of billions? Develop the soul of your nation.”

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diary, you know what’s the best part about developing the soul of my nation? No methodology can downgrade it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Diary,</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Chasing Inflation</title>
      <link href="/Chasing-Inflation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chasing Inflation" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Chasing-Inflation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Chasing-Inflation">&lt;p&gt;To someone not from an economics background, the idea of ‘chasing inflation’ might seem counter-intuitive. Why pursue inflation―a general increase in the price level of commodities-which wipes off your purchasing power? We, however, are well aware of how increasing inflation (rather bringing back the ‘lost inflation’) which reached near zero levels during the financial crisis, has become an obsession of central banks. Few developed countries will mind additional doses of inflation today. Bank of Japan is still in the trajectory of negative interest rates in the hope of countering the deflation that has plagued the country since the 1990’s. The Fed, at least till last year, was wondering why inflation hadn’t picked up despite the economy nearing full employment. Germany’s inflation rate is not going much beyond the 2% line, which 30 years ago, with the same level of unemployment, would be 5%. This has contributed to Germany’s current account surplus because of increased savings; it is also making it harder for peripheral countries to improve their competitive position vis-à-vis Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ‘missing inflation’ could mean two things. One, there is a force which is holding inflation back inside many countries. Two, there lies some problem with the way inflation is tracked in these countries. Surprisingly, the answer to both these problems lies in the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not guessed already, the culprit is Amazon. Largely called the ‘Amazon Effect’, retail prices in the USA have been withheld primarily because of the e-commerce giant’s discounting policies. This is not the first time this has happened. Since the 1990’s, Walmart and cheap Chinese imports have held prices back. This pressure seemed to be easing after the financial crisis, until the advent of e-commerce on the big stage. Online sales account for more than 10% of retail sales in the US. From 2000 to 2009, the online price index rose from a little above 90 to 100, implying an inflation rate of about 1% per year. But since 2009, the price index for goods purchased via e-commerce has actually been declining by about 1% per year. This implies a deflationary pressure of 10% on all retail sales. If this is not enough, add to it the slashing of prices by brick and mortar competitors to keep Amazon and other e-tailers in check. Goldman Sachs’ chief US economist Jan Hatzius has said that this effect is reducing core goods’ inflation by 0.25% and reducing overall core personal consumption expenditure (PCE) inflation by 0.1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Amazon effect isn’t going to die down soon. Amazon is one of the most valuable companies in the world, and with its billionaire founder, Jeff Bezos, it is looking to expand its horizons. Its acquisition of Whole Foods Market, a supermarket chain, could do to the $800 billion grocery market what it did to the retail market. According to Bloomberg, prices were cut as high as 43% on a range of items at Whole Foods on the first day under Amazon. Food makes up about 14.6% of the consumer price index. Very significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon might not stop at the grocery. Amazon Web Services has disrupted the IT industry. Its impact has been called ‘deflationary’ by Citigroup. This triggers a chain reaction of other competitors cutting their prices, and their profits (if not their employees’ wages). As Amazon increases in efficiency, helped by automation, one has to be very optimistic to predict a rise in prices in this war with e-commerce on one side, and all the rest on the other. Nomura had declared ‘Amazonification of Inflation’ one of its 10 grey swans of 2018. As of now, the Amazon effect has had only half the influence of the Walmart effect on inflation. But I would not bet my money against the former outshining the latter very soon. ‘Amazon effect’, in fact, is more of a misnomer. It is not Amazon specific. It is true for all e-tailers in all countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With it established how online players can disrupt inflation targeting by central banks, it is imperative that policymakers take into account the effect of online transactions on inflation. The Billion Prices Project (BPP) aims to do just that. BPP gathers data from online retailers in over 70 countries, allowing for real-time inflation updates. It tracks the price level of 5 million goods sold online. Data is published daily, rather than monthly, and with a lag of three days, rather than several weeks. It offers an immediate measure of inflation. A brainchild of 2 MIT economists, BPP also prevents data twisting by governments. It was set up in 2008 in Buenos Aires and it found that the inflation rate in Argentina was three times the official government estimates; 4 years later, The Economist rejected official Argentine numbers. It has more benefits. It costs less and the frequency of measurement is high. It solves many problems of data collection which exist in the status quo. A basket of goods is updated on a real-time basis as new products enter the market and old ones are discontinued. Currently, data gatherers assume people shy away from expensive products. For example, if beef’s price increases, it is assumed people switch to chicken. It ignores how people also consider quality and personal preferences while purchasing. Online purchase data collection solves this as well. It, however, does not give a good enough indication of the price level of services, as they (usually) aren’t sold online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central Banks are already adapting to this shift in consumer-producer interaction. Bank of England uses data from Google searches to gauge economic sentiment (searching “estate agent” is a good indicator of housing transactions, for example). Google is itself working on a price index based on online shopping. Asia is already one step ahead of the West. Policymakers throughout all budding Asian economies, from India to South Korea are looking over the internet to gauge inflation. Japan has set up a team to improve its data collection which takes into account online spending. There are strong chances that online purchases will be an important part of Japan’s upcoming Consumption Trend Index, which would measure personal spending. ASEAN members Malaysia, Thailand, Singapore, and the Philippines are not behind as well. “This ‘Amazon effect’ is well documented in the US, but we think they also play a substantial role in keeping inflation low in Thailand as well,” a Bank of Thailand statement adds. China, already a potential leader of the world in the age of big data, is not only monitoring e-commerce activity but also engaging with executives to study the impact in detail. Brace yourselves; leftists predicting the collapse of all social order because of government supervision over our online activity are coming.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">To someone not from an economics background, the idea of ‘chasing inflation’ might seem counter-intuitive. Why pursue inflation―a general increase in the price level of commodities-which wipes off your purchasing power? We, however, are well aware of how increasing inflation (rather bringing back the ‘lost inflation’) which reached near zero levels during the financial crisis, has become an obsession of central banks. Few developed countries will mind additional doses of inflation today. Bank of Japan is still in the trajectory of negative interest rates in the hope of countering the deflation that has plagued the country since the 1990’s. The Fed, at least till last year, was wondering why inflation hadn’t picked up despite the economy nearing full employment. Germany’s inflation rate is not going much beyond the 2% line, which 30 years ago, with the same level of unemployment, would be 5%. This has contributed to Germany’s current account surplus because of increased savings; it is also making it harder for peripheral countries to improve their competitive position vis-à-vis Germany.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
