<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/tushar.singh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-06-01T12:09:31+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/tushar.singh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lost Votes - A Call to First-Time Voters</title>
      <link href="/Lost-Votes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost Votes - A Call to First-Time Voters" />
      <published>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lost-Votes</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lost-Votes">&lt;p&gt;The elections are, literally speaking, a celebration in India. The Indian Election Commission in its campaign to encourage citizens to turn up and vote calls them ‘&lt;em&gt;Desh ka Tyohar&lt;/em&gt;’ ( The National Festival). And why not? After all, this is the only time when politicians are knocking on the doors of 900 million eligible voters and not the other way round. For Indians, elections are about debating a host of complex and not-so-complex issues, and then choosing whosoever will deliver the highest standards of living to them. For the rest of the world, Indian elections are about their awe-inspiring size and the grandeur (much like any big Indian wedding). For the Indians living abroad, it is somewhere in between…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a young country when compared to its more developed Asian peers like China, Japan and Singapore. In the last general elections in 2014, 24 million first-time voters were added to the electoral list. If this number is astounding enough for you, what about the 45 million first-time voters in 2019? This number is larger than the populations of 200 countries (not even kidding). Most of these 45 million voters are aged between 18 to 24. No wonder a lot of campaign issues like unemployment, nationalism under the garb of national security, income guarantees try to capture the imagination of these voters. Politicians are bearing the hot Indian summer, campaigning incessantly, using social media, releasing music videos, and whatnot, to get the youth to their side. What a waste of effort will it be to see many of the youth not voting at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you talk to students in Delhi University (which has the youth coming to study from across India), many are not going to vote for two reasons: one is stupid, and the other is sensible, but not sufficient enough to not vote. Talking about the sensible reason first, the trouble is that of travelling back to their hometowns to vote. Most first-time voters are studying in places far away from their hometowns. For them, travelling back for &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; one day for &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; a single vote which ‘&lt;em&gt;won’t even matter&lt;/em&gt;’ is not worth it. Add on to this their stupid reason: they &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; don’t see a suitable candidate to vote for. They dislike the incumbent, they hate the alternatives. You combine these two reasons: of having to travel all way back to your hometown (India is a big country, geographically speaking) only to vote for someone you do not support, and you become sympathetic to their case of not voting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem here is that everything is problematic. Voting is NOT a privilege which can be compromised at the cost of personal comfort. There are voters participating in the festival of democracy by braving the gunshots and IED bombs of Maoists. These villagers are warned by local Naxalites to vote only at the expense of losing their lives, not to mention the election officials and security personnel who facilitate the voting in these remote areas, often at the cost of their lives. The State is making attempts to make sure every eligible citizen votes in the elections. Their work has stretched from setting up a polling booth specifically for one person in the middle of the Gir forest in western India amongst Asiatic Lions to election officials walking through knee-deep snow for 45 kilometers in the Himalayas with their election equipment for a meagre 37 voters. Oppressed women and Dalits fight their oppressors to exercise their franchise independently, every time they are asked to not vote or vote for a particular political party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these examples do not hit the young Indian’s “Lutyens’ Delhi” conscience, then the idea of voting should. A vote is an expression of freedom. It symbolises a free people living in a free land - a luxury not all human beings can enjoy. From being labelled “unfit to govern ourselves” by the British (White Man’s Burden, remember?), which became an excuse to oppress millions of people before independence to doomsayers predicting our Balkanisation after independence, an Indian’s vote is a slap to every coloniser or India-skeptic who ever questioned our right to nationhood. It is not, I repeat, a luxury. Lastly, young India’s vote determines India’s future. But, who cares? Saving a few Rupees on travel cost and having ‘exam prep’ is more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the young, educated Indian’s attitude brings with it ironies which should be pointed out. How can we complain of the lack of young politicians when the youth does not prioritise engaging in democratic practices? How can we complain of lack of alternatives (the stupid excuse to not vote) when the youth does not care about the nation’s future? Aren’t our politicians a reflection of the society, no matter how skewed the reflection is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, 281 million registered voters did not vote. To give you some perspective, ‘only’ 183 million voters are registered in the US- the world’s second largest democracy. It is as if a whole nation did not vote. 2014 was a wave election when the country was inspired by an ambitious leader. Voters also, for the first time, had the option to vote NOTA (None of the Above). Hence, the number of people opting not to exercise their franchise, in 2019, is expected to be larger. While high voter turnouts in percentage terms show how much faith Indians have in democracy, what is being argued here is the reason(s) to not vote of a very important section of the society is deplorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a young democracy. As we mature, we are bringing more reforms to our democratic setup. NOTA was one such reform. NOTA gives the ‘frustrated’ voter to register his anti-establishment sentiment in an established way. How many countries can take pride in this? While NOTA has been criticised for its ‘impotence’ (even if NOTA has most votes in a constituency, the candidate with highest votes still gets elected), it is a step in the right direction. Reform does not come in one go, but only gradually. If NOTA’s vote share keeps on rising, as it has since being introduced, policymakers might be tempted to give it its due potency a few general elections down the line. There are still more reforms which can be discussed but won’t be due to lack of space, like the Right to Recall or the introduction of a ‘Proportionate Representation System’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the above-mentioned reforms, ideas like proxy voting, postal ballots, online voting and setting up ‘voting centers’ to enable those who live away from their hometowns to vote in their city of stay are being floated around. In fact, the &lt;em&gt;Times of India&lt;/em&gt; has started a petition called ‘Lost Votes’ to bring to the government’s notice the need to enable voting from the place of residence. Change will come but who will bring the change? &lt;em&gt;The leaders of tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. What are &lt;em&gt;the leaders of tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; doing? Thinking of the &lt;em&gt;Right to Vote&lt;/em&gt; to be a &lt;em&gt;privilege&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an appeal to all those first-time voters who have been caught in the inertia of everyday life. Remember, if we don’t change anything, then nothing will change. It is time we change the system &lt;em&gt;by being a part of it&lt;/em&gt; rather than being a part of it &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the system reforms itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The elections are, literally speaking, a celebration in India. The Indian Election Commission in its campaign to encourage citizens to turn up and vote calls them ‘Desh ka Tyohar’ ( The National Festival). And why not? After all, this is the only time when politicians are knocking on the doors of 900 million eligible voters and not the other way round. For Indians, elections are about debating a host of complex and not-so-complex issues, and then choosing whosoever will deliver the highest standards of living to them. For the rest of the world, Indian elections are about their awe-inspiring size and the grandeur (much like any big Indian wedding). For the Indians living abroad, it is somewhere in between…</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why ‘Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word</title>
      <link href="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why 'Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word" />
      <published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindutva as a political ideology manifests the ‘Hinduness’ of the Indian people. On a primitive level, Hindutva means the ‘Inherent Hinduness’  of all Indian people. Savarkar, who coined the term Hindutva, was an atheist himself and defined Hindutva in a strictly geographical and cultural sense. The word ‘Hindu’ comes from ‘Indus’ (the river around which we started off as a civilization) and the common bond which all Indians inherently share is hence called ‘Hindutva’. Simply put, any person born within the boundaries of the subcontinent is a Hindu and his inherent ‘Bharatiyata’ is called Hindutva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definition of Hindutva is, historically, the only true answer for Indians to the question “Who are we?” All other answers divided Indians into different religions, castes, regions and even races. In fact, the Hindu Code Bill defined a Hindu as someone who is “NOT a Christian, Jew, Parsi or Muslim”! Clearly, we need this ‘Bharatiya’ definition of Hindutva to have a true, positive consciousness of our identity as an extremely diverse nation. Socially, the concept of Hindutva, or there being a certain kind of Hinduness which we inherit from the fact of us being born in this holy land looks beyond divisions of caste and religion to unify the Indian masses. It brilliantly distinguishes Indians from the rest of the world. An American does not start possessing Hindutva if he converts to Hinduism (Sorry David Frawley). But an Indian Muslim has an inherent Hindutva and is very distinct from an Arabic or South-east Asian Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not fashioning an artificial answer here on the question of Indian identity based only in geography. Instead, we are verily identifying the common culture and syncretic tradition that exists only within that geography. The Hindutva we speak of is not simply due to the happenstance of people living in a piece of land, it’s due to the overarching unity among diversity they have developed, the story they have told themselves. This Hindutva is manifested in the numerous public holidays of Eid, Christmas and Diwali we Indians enjoy together― whether we are Hindu, Christian, or Muslim. It is found in the consistent requests for Biryani by Hindus to their Muslim friends. From the Rig Veda’s declaration (RV 1.164.46) that “Indra, Mitra, Varuna, Agni…The wise speak of what is One in many ways” to Kabir’s elegant verses on religious unity, Hindutva is about the rich cultural inheritance of all Indians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first key aspect of Hindutva is the fact that we have overcome so many foibles and problems, skirmishes and conflicts to emerge as one nation. Yes, there was once a time we officially designated people as ‘untouchable’ but still, our Constitution was written by a ‘Dalit’ man. Yes, Mahmud Ghazni plundered the Somnath Temple 17 times, but Ghalib’s verses would be non-existent without Muslims. It is through the schisms between us that we have developed this complex and unique identity. We have been through multiple disagreements on grounds of caste, faith, state and language. And in overcoming them we have discovered our underlying unity. Therefore, the first theme of Hindutva involves a sense of Indian pride, a feeling of common triumph of having risen above so many conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second aspect of Hindutva is religion, or rather the peculiar part it plays in making us so distinct. Religion is very strongly present in India’s public life, from the raucous dispute surrounding the Babri Masjid to the controversy on beef and mob lynchings. However, even if religion is a cause of conflict in India, it is undeniably the bedrock of its cultural identity too. Without Hinduism and its multiple gods, esoteric texts and ancient hymns, India is unimaginable. Without the Buddha its culture is barren; and without an Indian version of Islam, there would be no Sufism, no qawwalis. Faith is a wonderful thing in India that makes us separate from the barren West. In the West, as Nietzsche states (in The Gay Science), “God is dead, he remains dead, and [they] have killed him”. In India, the ‘Samudra Manthan’ of religions yields the nectar of meaning, whether it be in the form of Khwajaji’s sermons, Adi Shankara’s works, or Lalan Fakir’s songs, all we need to do is share it equally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third historical aspect of Hindutva explains how our unity exists through our diversity, and not despite it. We Indians may have had our problems, but just like a big Indian joint family, we are one. Hindutva ideologues like Golwalkar (in his Bunch of Thoughts) and Deendayal Upadhyaya (in his Integral Humanism) have time and again emphasised how Hindutva is broader than Hinduism because Indians following ‘Avaidik’ Dharmas like Sikhism, Jainism, Buddhism and even religions like Islam and Christianity have Hindutva in them. The reason for that is cultural intermingling. Arjuna’s marriage to Naga princess Ulupi and Manipuri princess Chitrangada in The Mahabharata is a classical and literary example of how we Indians cherish a mixing of traditions in our rich mythology. Even the Indian Supreme Court noted in 1995 that Hindutva is a way of life (and a ‘state of mind’). This way of life has been accepting of all people (both the oppressed and the oppressors), and even ‘foreign-origin’ rulers like the towering Mughal Emperor Akbar have patronised this way of life that epitomises a unity that stems from diversity. While the Parsis immigrated to both China and India, it was the latter where they finally found refuge in. The Jews have thanked us enough for being the only country without an instance of anti-Semitism. In fact, the Jewish quarters of Kochi stand right next to the Palace of the King of Kochi. The Hindu philosophical idea of every creature being a part of the Supreme Brahman (irrespective of his faith) has made us an all-welcoming people. And the word Hindutva embodies that openness of mind ever so poignantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line of this article is to tell the reader to embrace Hindutva. Why? Because Hindutva is India’s gift to the world. It was Hindutva which ‘Indianized’ parts of Iran, Afghanistan, Tibet, South-East Asia and even Japan. Thailand’s erstwhile capital is named Ayutthaya, after Lord Ram’s capital Ayodhya. What makes India stand out is not its history, its philosophy or its many religions, but an optimum combination  of all three. Once upon a time, European merchants wanted to trade with us, hence the mad pursuits by Columbus and Vasco Da Gama to ‘discover’ the magical land called India. But what do we find today? Growing westernization and inferiority complex amongst Indians! The same India which was a shining example of an ideal country to the world is now restyling itself based on western ‘isms’ like Capitalism and Socialism. This cannot happen. Hindutva is India’s ‘Soft Power’. All Indians have to be proud of Hindutva, for we can’t expect the world to respect us if we don’t respect ‘who we are’. Unless India becomes ‘Indianized’ again, ‘Superpower 2020’ (realistically speaking, ‘Superpower 2050’), will remain a distant dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>harsh.tiwari tushar.singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Diary of a Confused Indian Economics Student</title>
      <link href="/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diary of a Confused Indian Economics Student" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dear Diary,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I return to you, yet again. You have been a constant support in times like these. I wonder if this happens with everyone- for days, you are the king of your small world, a world which you understand; then, all of a sudden, everything crumbles down, every fact which you thought was true becomes fiction, every emotion you had turns out to be shallow, every moment you lived seems worthless. I feel shelterless, the roof of meaning taken away from above my head. Hence, here I am, meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be used to my spiraling down of emotions by now. However, this time, it’s different (trust me). Unlike all my previous breakdowns, there is no particular person to blame, and this leaves me even more clueless. How puny us humans are, always looking for a guilty party, to make ourselves feel lighter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the issue now. The reason behind my sudden disillusionment with the world is the new Indian GDP back series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it? Oh, of course, I have to explain it, you are just a silly diary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the GDP growth rate of our country over the past decade or so has been revised and updated. As per the updated GDP data, India grew at 6.7% between 2004 and 2014. This is in contrast to previous figures of 8.1% from 2004-09 and 7.46% from 2009-14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the issue with that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I AM NOT SURE. That’s the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if we are a high growth economy or not. The world thinks so (or thought so). Even I thought so, till yesterday. However, the new data doesn’t. We never crossed the 9% growth rate, EVER.  Some numbers here and there, and I am questioning my own country’s growth story, something which I was proud of (till yesterday, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean we never grew at the pace we thought we had? But, I have seen luxuries become necessities for the consumer every five years, middle class getting richer, sons earning in their first year more than what their fathers earned throughout their lives. Doesn’t this count as exceptional growth? Or worse, what we experienced in the past decade was nothing exceptional, and the Indian economy, even after 70 years, has nothing to show for achievements. No, no, this cannot be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if we didn’t achieve high growth (more than 9%), what explains the high inflation we faced towards the end of 2013? How can there be high inflation without high growth? Was the inflation JUST because of external factors like Oil? So much purchasing power wiped away by double digit inflation rates because a few countries (Read: OPEC) wanted to have fun with the world? The worst of my thoughts are yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world knows that we have a highly indebted banking sector. Rising NPAs (non-performing assets, basically loans given by banks which don’t get repaid completely) have been the single largest threat to the Indian economy for the past 5 years, at least. It is widely acknowledged that banks lent rapidly (and sometimes indiscriminately) between 2008 and 2014, which has led to this problem today. However, in the short-term, this excessive lending helped us achieve exceptional growth rates, even touching 10.3% in 2010-11. All this, obviously, as per the old data. Now, the ‘excessive lending’ (should we still call it that?), which has created an unprecedented crisis in our economy, didn’t even help us achieve ‘high growth’ phase. Much ado about nothing. Why doesn’t the government also downgrade the NPAs in the economy? I am sure there is a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh Diary, spare a thought for all the poor foreign investors who were fooled into investing into this apparently ‘high growth’ economy which wasn’t! A decade of optimism, all for nothing. It was a lie. A scam. In case I haven’t made it clear enough, an economy is in a ‘high growth’ phase when it crosses 9% growth, which India didn’t (I know I have made it pretty clear. I just needed another reason to repeat it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that the new GDP data has been released by NITI Aayog, a government think-tank, and not by the Central Statistics Office, as is the norm. I feel sad for poor Adarsh, my close friend. He is working so hard to join the Indian Statistical Institute in Kolkata, only to find his dream job is being taken over by a bureaucrat run organization!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two beneficiaries from the new data, though, and this (somewhat) gives me a reason to smile: Unemployed youth and distressed farmers. These poor fellows had been wondering how did a high-growth phase not create enough jobs/ increase the standard of living for them. They now have an answer: there was no high growth economy to produce jobs/ increase standard of living in the first place!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I am just overreacting. Yes, yes. I am overreacting. Arvind Virmani, our former Chief Economic Advisor, has said that usually GDP data updates like this one lead to a downgrade of a country’s growth. He must know better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just, one thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before this data was released, another revised GDP data was ‘leaked’. As per this particular leaked data, India actually grew at a faster pace than even previously estimated. Yes! We touched double digit growth more often than we had thought. However, the government (this happened a few months ago) had then said that the revision of GDP numbers is still under process and these are not the final numbers. What I understand is that there are several ways to revise GDP numbers, and the leaked and the newly released official version are only two of the many alternatives. SURELY, the government won’t intentionally recognize a methodology to discredit the growth rates under it’s political rival. Surely, it won’t. Not before an election year. Definitely not. After all, this government is known for respecting institutions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ndtv.com/india-news/rbi-vs-government-10-things-to-know-1941159&quot;&gt;Read: RBI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really sorry, I know I am going over-board. I just have a few silly questions to end with (Don’t laugh). If our percentage growth has been downgraded, our absolute GDP must have come down too, wouldn’t it? I was hearing that Indian GDP (nominal basis) will overtake United Kingdom’s in 2019. I suppose this won’t happen. OR will it? Why hasn’t our absolute GDP number been downgraded, yet? Data also shows that India did not recover from the global financial crisis as quickly as initially thought. Are we a resilient economy as we thought we were, or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several international institutions have been coming up with research (using old data) showing the huge number of people India lifted out of poverty, something which I take pride in. A low GDP growth means more people must still be under poverty than previously estimated. &lt;em&gt;‘A stroke of a pen and millions are poor again’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t end on such a melancholic note. Hear this story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
 Last week, I asked my philosophy teacher this, “What GDP number, what military capability, what standard of living, what cultural clout do we need to achieve in order to become a Superpower?”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teacher’s answer left me thinking, and it seems relevant today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

“0”

&lt;br /&gt;

“0?”, I asked confused.

&lt;br /&gt;

He said, “What use is any of what you said to a nation whose soul is great enough to capture hearts of billions? Develop the soul of your nation.”

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diary, you know what’s the best part about developing the soul of my nation? No methodology can downgrade it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Diary,</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Chasing Inflation</title>
      <link href="/Chasing-Inflation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chasing Inflation" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Chasing-Inflation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Chasing-Inflation">&lt;p&gt;To someone not from an economics background, the idea of ‘chasing inflation’ might seem counter-intuitive. Why pursue inflation―a general increase in the price level of commodities-which wipes off your purchasing power? We, however, are well aware of how increasing inflation (rather bringing back the ‘lost inflation’) which reached near zero levels during the financial crisis, has become an obsession of central banks. Few developed countries will mind additional doses of inflation today. Bank of Japan is still in the trajectory of negative interest rates in the hope of countering the deflation that has plagued the country since the 1990’s. The Fed, at least till last year, was wondering why inflation hadn’t picked up despite the economy nearing full employment. Germany’s inflation rate is not going much beyond the 2% line, which 30 years ago, with the same level of unemployment, would be 5%. This has contributed to Germany’s current account surplus because of increased savings; it is also making it harder for peripheral countries to improve their competitive position vis-à-vis Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ‘missing inflation’ could mean two things. One, there is a force which is holding inflation back inside many countries. Two, there lies some problem with the way inflation is tracked in these countries. Surprisingly, the answer to both these problems lies in the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not guessed already, the culprit is Amazon. Largely called the ‘Amazon Effect’, retail prices in the USA have been withheld primarily because of the e-commerce giant’s discounting policies. This is not the first time this has happened. Since the 1990’s, Walmart and cheap Chinese imports have held prices back. This pressure seemed to be easing after the financial crisis, until the advent of e-commerce on the big stage. Online sales account for more than 10% of retail sales in the US. From 2000 to 2009, the online price index rose from a little above 90 to 100, implying an inflation rate of about 1% per year. But since 2009, the price index for goods purchased via e-commerce has actually been declining by about 1% per year. This implies a deflationary pressure of 10% on all retail sales. If this is not enough, add to it the slashing of prices by brick and mortar competitors to keep Amazon and other e-tailers in check. Goldman Sachs’ chief US economist Jan Hatzius has said that this effect is reducing core goods’ inflation by 0.25% and reducing overall core personal consumption expenditure (PCE) inflation by 0.1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Amazon effect isn’t going to die down soon. Amazon is one of the most valuable companies in the world, and with its billionaire founder, Jeff Bezos, it is looking to expand its horizons. Its acquisition of Whole Foods Market, a supermarket chain, could do to the $800 billion grocery market what it did to the retail market. According to Bloomberg, prices were cut as high as 43% on a range of items at Whole Foods on the first day under Amazon. Food makes up about 14.6% of the consumer price index. Very significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon might not stop at the grocery. Amazon Web Services has disrupted the IT industry. Its impact has been called ‘deflationary’ by Citigroup. This triggers a chain reaction of other competitors cutting their prices, and their profits (if not their employees’ wages). As Amazon increases in efficiency, helped by automation, one has to be very optimistic to predict a rise in prices in this war with e-commerce on one side, and all the rest on the other. Nomura had declared ‘Amazonification of Inflation’ one of its 10 grey swans of 2018. As of now, the Amazon effect has had only half the influence of the Walmart effect on inflation. But I would not bet my money against the former outshining the latter very soon. ‘Amazon effect’, in fact, is more of a misnomer. It is not Amazon specific. It is true for all e-tailers in all countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With it established how online players can disrupt inflation targeting by central banks, it is imperative that policymakers take into account the effect of online transactions on inflation. The Billion Prices Project (BPP) aims to do just that. BPP gathers data from online retailers in over 70 countries, allowing for real-time inflation updates. It tracks the price level of 5 million goods sold online. Data is published daily, rather than monthly, and with a lag of three days, rather than several weeks. It offers an immediate measure of inflation. A brainchild of 2 MIT economists, BPP also prevents data twisting by governments. It was set up in 2008 in Buenos Aires and it found that the inflation rate in Argentina was three times the official government estimates; 4 years later, The Economist rejected official Argentine numbers. It has more benefits. It costs less and the frequency of measurement is high. It solves many problems of data collection which exist in the status quo. A basket of goods is updated on a real-time basis as new products enter the market and old ones are discontinued. Currently, data gatherers assume people shy away from expensive products. For example, if beef’s price increases, it is assumed people switch to chicken. It ignores how people also consider quality and personal preferences while purchasing. Online purchase data collection solves this as well. It, however, does not give a good enough indication of the price level of services, as they (usually) aren’t sold online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central Banks are already adapting to this shift in consumer-producer interaction. Bank of England uses data from Google searches to gauge economic sentiment (searching “estate agent” is a good indicator of housing transactions, for example). Google is itself working on a price index based on online shopping. Asia is already one step ahead of the West. Policymakers throughout all budding Asian economies, from India to South Korea are looking over the internet to gauge inflation. Japan has set up a team to improve its data collection which takes into account online spending. There are strong chances that online purchases will be an important part of Japan’s upcoming Consumption Trend Index, which would measure personal spending. ASEAN members Malaysia, Thailand, Singapore, and the Philippines are not behind as well. “This ‘Amazon effect’ is well documented in the US, but we think they also play a substantial role in keeping inflation low in Thailand as well,” a Bank of Thailand statement adds. China, already a potential leader of the world in the age of big data, is not only monitoring e-commerce activity but also engaging with executives to study the impact in detail. Brace yourselves; leftists predicting the collapse of all social order because of government supervision over our online activity are coming.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">To someone not from an economics background, the idea of ‘chasing inflation’ might seem counter-intuitive. Why pursue inflation―a general increase in the price level of commodities-which wipes off your purchasing power? We, however, are well aware of how increasing inflation (rather bringing back the ‘lost inflation’) which reached near zero levels during the financial crisis, has become an obsession of central banks. Few developed countries will mind additional doses of inflation today. Bank of Japan is still in the trajectory of negative interest rates in the hope of countering the deflation that has plagued the country since the 1990’s. The Fed, at least till last year, was wondering why inflation hadn’t picked up despite the economy nearing full employment. Germany’s inflation rate is not going much beyond the 2% line, which 30 years ago, with the same level of unemployment, would be 5%. This has contributed to Germany’s current account surplus because of increased savings; it is also making it harder for peripheral countries to improve their competitive position vis-à-vis Germany.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
