<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/rachit.kumar/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-04-14T13:47:07+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/rachit.kumar/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?</title>
      <link href="/Stocks-Rallying-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?" />
      <published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stocks-Rallying-Again</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stocks-Rallying-Again">&lt;p&gt;Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus outbreak got worse day-by-day and even now cases are rising every day although if you see the popular stock market indices, they are again back to the point where they were before March lows. A rally is bringing the indices back to their pre-March levels. Are the economies getting better? No. Have we recovered from the virus? No. Is GDP growth recovering? NO, instead most of the nations have announced contraction in GDP and are further expecting it to contract till 2021. Why have stocks been moving up again then? Let’s find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries worldwide went under complete lockdown. People tried looking for sources of income during this time and as the stock market never sleeps people turned to stocks to earn something in their free time. Everyone became a trader. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z&quot;&gt;Robinhood&lt;/a&gt; trading app, the most popular stock trading app in the US that charges zero commission, saw a rise in new account openings during the lockdown. The revenues of Robinhood have doubled in a quarter which clearly shows that retail participation has risen and is continuing to rise as we speak. Retailers with no knowledge of stocks, futures and options are trading just for the sake of earning some extra income during their free time and are buying stocks like grocery items, which is one of the main reasons for the rally of stock indices. All market indicators show that the market is overbought and a second wave of crash is due. Big retailers on seeing a big fall in the market start selling stocks to average out their price, and when they enter the market after a fall, it helps the market to regain again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the big question arises: where do we invest our money right now? Seeing a crash due in the market again, and positive signs not being visible in the short term for the economy, it is best to have a diversified portfolio. Over the years, the investment that is the most promising is gold but becoming wealthy through gold is almost unheard of. Seeing the current scenario one must have around 15-20% of his/her investment in gold, paper gold is preferred as you don’t have to keep it safe and don’t have to worry about it. Around 30% of the portfolio should be in mutual funds (Systematic Investment Plan) and 25% should be allocated to equities that too in ‘blue-chip’ stocks because right now profitability of companies is not important, the most important thing is survival and these companies have a huge amount of capital backing. If you want higher returns then you can switch to mid-caps and small-caps too, but your risk increases as well. 10% should be invested in very safe investments like fixed deposits for safe and a minimum guaranteed return. The remaining portfolio can be kept as cash-in-hand, and then one can wait for dips and add stocks of their choice. This portfolio investment has been advised for people who want to take moderate risk with decent returns. If you wish, you can go for high risk by allocating more to equities and if you want less risk then decrease your dependence on equities. Therefore, investing in such turbulent times depends totally on a person’s risk appetite and the depth of his pockets. No one can predict the movement of markets in such unprecedented times. It would be better to have a well-diversified portfolio and not expose yourself too much to a particular type of investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rachit Kumar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?</title>
      <link href="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever there has been any economic crisis, people tend to stay away from the stock market because market crashes are highly unpredictable. We all know about the 2007-08 financial crisis, and how in every country there was reluctance in investing in the stock market. However, people who still had savings went right to the commodity exchange and bought gold. This was clearly visible from the fact that the rally in gold continued from 2007 to 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we are witnessing in this current scenario with the coronavirus spreading all over the world and lockdown of economies leading to bankruptcy for many companies, people are pulling out their money from stocks and other financial instruments and buying bullion to park their money in safe investments. Exchange-Traded Funds (ETFs) have been piling up on gold reserves as well, which has more than made up for the domestic lack of demand. Demand for gold comes from another significant set of investors who tend to invest in real estate. The sector itself being in limbo due to the pandemic has forced such investors to invest in the yellow metal. Additionally, the metal is benefitting from the ultra-loose monetary policies being pursued by bankers and expectation that such a stance will tend to continue in the long run. Rising fiscal deficits and increasing debts are also contributing to the rising shift to gold. The fiscal policies adopted and the printing of more currency have led to inflation and have been the contributing factors in the current rally in gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, central banks around the globe are regularly keeping a check on the economy and are providing liquidity. During the past few months, central banks too, have been buying gold and increasing their gold reserves in order to face any unforeseen circumstances. Central banks of China, Russia and India were the biggest buyers of gold in 2019, and many countries are still adding more to their coffers. This rally is expected to continue until we see any stability in the stock market and people feel safe to buy stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold prices have gone through the ceiling in the past few weeks and every banker has his/her own perception regarding the future price movement. All in all, it remains to be seen whether gold prices will continue to rise, or will gold lose its steam. However, the metal has yet again proven its mettle in trying times, when every other investment fails to provide returns, it keeps its investors happy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rachit Kumar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
