<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/udayon.sen/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-12-18T13:32:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/udayon.sen/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Walk Again: On Love In Shinkai’s Anime</title>
      <link href="/To-Walk-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Walk Again: On Love In Shinkai’s Anime" />
      <published>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/To-Walk-Again</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/To-Walk-Again">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narukami no sukoshi toyomite&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(A faint clap of thunder)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sashi kumori&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(Clouded skies)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ame mo furanu ka?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(Perhaps rain comes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kimi wo todomemu&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(If so, will you stay here with me?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fate, sometimes, begets in itself the funniest stories as well as the most
melancholic ones. It writes its own comedies and tragedies. The way we interpret
it, however, is what finalises the effect fate has on us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makoto Shinkai is a giant in the world of anime. Deservedly and frequently does
he get compared to Miyazaki; a genius in the field. I do not wish to compare two
of the most amazing anime directors. Their work and their storytelling have
always touched a chord in my heart; a reaction spanning all of the people who
have watched their movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shinkai is, however, criticised due to his lack of versatility in approaching
the themes of stories. &lt;em&gt;Most&lt;/em&gt; of his stories pertain to separation and love,
requited or otherwise. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt;, one of his works, is not any
different. However, the multitude of perspectives that went behind the making of
the story’s concept is what makes the story stand out, in the midst of a
plethora of influential anime films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; sets up an atmosphere which most of us can relate to on a
superficial level. Shinkai has never been afraid to work on stuff he personally
connects to, as a result of which three things come forth in his films as
defining motifs: train, rain, and pain, strangely enough they rhyme too. &lt;em&gt;Garden
of words&lt;/em&gt; interweaves a beautiful love story between the two protagonists and
despite their mutual feelings for each other, they remain visibly disconnected
from each other. They remain separated by the immense difference in age that
exists between the two of them. 27-year-old, Yukari Yukino is a teacher in the
same school as the 15-year-old Takao Akizuki, albeit unbeknownst to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fine rainy day, both of them chance upon each other in a Japanese-themed
garden where they both had sought refuge from the rain. The two share a moment
of connectedness. Yukino leaves him, after sharing with him a cryptic &lt;em&gt;tanka&lt;/em&gt; (a
short Japanese poem). Yukino and Takao end up forming a connection and start
meeting each time it rains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things turn topsy-turvy when Yukino is wrongfully accused of being involved in a
relationship with a student. She is in a soup herself, left with feelings of
remorse and shame even though she had done no wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Takao is an aspiring shoemaker. He comes from a broken family; having been
abandoned by their mother, he and his elder brother lived together. Takao is a
responsible human despite being a mere high school student, he assumes a
part-time job in order to ensure ends meet. Takao, helps Yukino ‘to walk again’
and get back up on her feet. His affection and bond with Yukino make him resolve
to make a shoe for her, a project he works passionately and dedicatedly for.
&lt;em&gt;Love&lt;/em&gt; is the central theme that runs throughout the story. Ultimately, the
rainy season is over and despite wanting each other’s company, they both
hesitate to meet. Takao still continues to work on the shoe. On one particular
day, he realises how Yukino is a teacher in his school and has been wrongfully
accused of something that she did not even commit. Takao decides to take it upon
himself to resolve the issue, and ends up getting involved in a fight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One certain day, Takao and Yukino get a chance to meet up again. In the midst of
a conversation, Takao confesses his love for her. Yukino, unable to process it,
makes him realise that she is still technically his teacher. Takao and Yukino
share their feelings with each other but realise the limitations of their own
understanding and that of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; provides a unique perspective, a tale of love, which is
unrequited and beautiful in its own way. It was Takao’s behaviour towards her,
and his compassion, respect and love that ultimately heals Yukino. This story
makes one introspect upon a form of love that was much popularised by the
philosopher Plato himself: platonic love. There are no boundaries, no
restrictions and no limitations in platonic love and every form of expressing
this love is pure, considerate and understandable. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; gives us a
look into a world of people to whom we can relate, beings we can understand and
sympathise with. It makes us realise the harshness with which society conditions
us and shapes our views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separation is the ultimate form of connection because it provides a &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; for
two people to connect, and know each others’ places in their lives better than
ever. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words,&lt;/em&gt; with its sensitively structured soundtracks and
breathtaking animation, helps us make a connection in separation. A separation
of ages does not restrict a human from pacifying and helping the other person
‘learn to walk again’. Japanese culture is founded on the principles of mutual
respect, understanding and love. The story provides us with that and more. One
must learn to enjoy the things one takes for granted, take the opportunity to
understand someone better and maybe heal them as well as ourselves in the
process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the world is a cold place and all we have is ourselves, and the crucial
key to understanding our own selves is to understand the ones who need our help.
Maybe we are all Takao, living in a broken, mundane, disjunctive world but we
can still always try to find someone like ourselves, broken and battered and
unable to walk, and learn to walk together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to search for the love that we seek all our lives, we can try
to help one another and seek acceptance within ourselves. After all, “We all are
humans, we all have our own quirks, don’t we?”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Narukami no sukoshi toyomite (A faint clap of thunder) sashi kumori (Clouded skies) Ame mo furanu ka? (Perhaps rain comes) Kimi wo todomemu (If so, will you stay here with me?) Fate, sometimes, begets in itself the funniest stories as well as the most melancholic ones. It writes its own comedies and tragedies. The way we interpret it, however, is what finalises the effect fate has on us. Makoto Shinkai is a giant in the world of anime. Deservedly and frequently does he get compared to Miyazaki; a genius in the field. I do not wish to compare two of the most amazing anime directors. Their work and their storytelling have always touched a chord in my heart; a reaction spanning all of the people who have watched their movies. Shinkai is, however, criticised due to his lack of versatility in approaching the themes of stories. Most of his stories pertain to separation and love, requited or otherwise. Garden of Words, one of his works, is not any different. However, the multitude of perspectives that went behind the making of the story’s concept is what makes the story stand out, in the midst of a plethora of influential anime films. Garden of Words sets up an atmosphere which most of us can relate to on a superficial level. Shinkai has never been afraid to work on stuff he personally connects to, as a result of which three things come forth in his films as defining motifs: train, rain, and pain, strangely enough they rhyme too. Garden of words interweaves a beautiful love story between the two protagonists and despite their mutual feelings for each other, they remain visibly disconnected from each other. They remain separated by the immense difference in age that exists between the two of them. 27-year-old, Yukari Yukino is a teacher in the same school as the 15-year-old Takao Akizuki, albeit unbeknownst to him. On a fine rainy day, both of them chance upon each other in a Japanese-themed garden where they both had sought refuge from the rain. The two share a moment of connectedness. Yukino leaves him, after sharing with him a cryptic tanka (a short Japanese poem). Yukino and Takao end up forming a connection and start meeting each time it rains. Things turn topsy-turvy when Yukino is wrongfully accused of being involved in a relationship with a student. She is in a soup herself, left with feelings of remorse and shame even though she had done no wrong. Takao is an aspiring shoemaker. He comes from a broken family; having been abandoned by their mother, he and his elder brother lived together. Takao is a responsible human despite being a mere high school student, he assumes a part-time job in order to ensure ends meet. Takao, helps Yukino ‘to walk again’ and get back up on her feet. His affection and bond with Yukino make him resolve to make a shoe for her, a project he works passionately and dedicatedly for. Love is the central theme that runs throughout the story. Ultimately, the rainy season is over and despite wanting each other’s company, they both hesitate to meet. Takao still continues to work on the shoe. On one particular day, he realises how Yukino is a teacher in his school and has been wrongfully accused of something that she did not even commit. Takao decides to take it upon himself to resolve the issue, and ends up getting involved in a fight.  One certain day, Takao and Yukino get a chance to meet up again. In the midst of a conversation, Takao confesses his love for her. Yukino, unable to process it, makes him realise that she is still technically his teacher. Takao and Yukino share their feelings with each other but realise the limitations of their own understanding and that of society. Garden of Words provides a unique perspective, a tale of love, which is unrequited and beautiful in its own way. It was Takao’s behaviour towards her, and his compassion, respect and love that ultimately heals Yukino. This story makes one introspect upon a form of love that was much popularised by the philosopher Plato himself: platonic love. There are no boundaries, no restrictions and no limitations in platonic love and every form of expressing this love is pure, considerate and understandable. Garden of Words gives us a look into a world of people to whom we can relate, beings we can understand and sympathise with. It makes us realise the harshness with which society conditions us and shapes our views. Separation is the ultimate form of connection because it provides a reason for two people to connect, and know each others’ places in their lives better than ever. Garden of Words, with its sensitively structured soundtracks and breathtaking animation, helps us make a connection in separation. A separation of ages does not restrict a human from pacifying and helping the other person ‘learn to walk again’. Japanese culture is founded on the principles of mutual respect, understanding and love. The story provides us with that and more. One must learn to enjoy the things one takes for granted, take the opportunity to understand someone better and maybe heal them as well as ourselves in the process. Perhaps the world is a cold place and all we have is ourselves, and the crucial key to understanding our own selves is to understand the ones who need our help. Maybe we are all Takao, living in a broken, mundane, disjunctive world but we can still always try to find someone like ourselves, broken and battered and unable to walk, and learn to walk together.  Instead of trying to search for the love that we seek all our lives, we can try to help one another and seek acceptance within ourselves. After all, “We all are humans, we all have our own quirks, don’t we?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Exploration of Ourselves</title>
      <link href="/Exploration-of-Ourselves" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploration of Ourselves" />
      <published>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Exploration-of-Ourselves</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Exploration-of-Ourselves">&lt;p&gt;“What makes you, well, you?”- Michael Stevens, Vsauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plato in his thesis and conceptualisation of perfect beings, explored and introduced to us the concept of Forms and how the ‘World of Forms’ is the state of perfection of every being in our world, the achievement of which may be well beyond our capabilities, owing to the limitations that bound us. The World of Forms is a utopian disposition, a state of perfection, which exists only in the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the question which arises from it is: what kind of a being would be a perfect form of us? To understand this, we must question ourselves on our true nature and the most fundamentally important, yet unanswered question we are faced with. The question is: who are we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re probably thinking that this is another clichéd take on who you are, or on how who someone &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; is can never be defined and yet there will be attempts to explore this subject, leading to countless innovative and daring philosophical initiatives in order to reach a comprehensive definition of our being? Oh blimey! That’s some misplaced and crooked jugular, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, you could be right, this probably is another one of those inquiries that we dive into, modelling ourselves into the Thinker’s pose, trying to figure out what defines us, what it means to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; us. Rene Descartes once remarked, “I think, therefore I am”, posing keen albeit ambiguous arguments on the definition of a man, on the basis of his consciousness first, after which we can define our being. Sartre took his chance and played with “Cogito, ergo sum” to make his own phrase, “I am, therefore I think” and even though it may seem to be just a play of words which it is (maybe). It does, however, attempt to make more sense from Jean Paul’s version of existentialist propagation, prioritising our being over the form of mind. Note that there can be some valid arguments over the interpretations of what each of them meant when using these words in order to elucidate their thoughts, it is on us to interpret them in the way we like for the adoption of our own code to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of who we are is an intriguing one and even more so when we are to discuss one of the very interesting philosophical analogies of all time, which has been used as a plot device in several anime and movies such as &lt;em&gt;Ghost in the Shell&lt;/em&gt;. The concept is generalised and popularly known as the Ship of Theseus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of the argument is based on the historical and mythical artefact of the Ship used by Theseus in his journey. If the Ship of Theseus is displayed in a museum, it’s safe to assume that after some time, some parts will start rotting and will have to be replaced with new parts. Say, the rotten parts of the ship are preserved, in order to restore them when the adequate technology is available. Gradually, all parts of the original ship are replaced and they are kept in a store house. The question which arises, at this point of time, is if this Ship, the one which has been entirely replaced with new parts, is still the same ship which Theseus used for his journey?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say that thanks to technology, we can restore the rotten parts of the ship in a proper manner. If we gradually replace the ship with its original parts, can I consider this ship to be the original one? The question being explored is how can we still call it the same ship if it has none of its original parts. If after dismantling and reorganising, what makes the ship, the same original ship used by Theseus? Are we right in the way we approach this problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to this philosophical question has been debated and deliberated upon since the time of Plato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several arguments which have been made in order to determine what would be the consequence of such an action. There have been propositions, made on the basis of ‘forms’, by Aristotle, in which he argues that anything is formed out of four essential causes: the formal cause (on the basis of its form), material cause (on the basis of its constituent materials), efficient cause (on the basis of its principle) and the final cause (which is indiscrete in its mannerisms but is a part of all the above causes). He argues that the causes are more or less consistent in all the cases with only one divergence in every case, and therefore it is in principle the same ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another argument is that of the transitive property via which it relates to all the forms of the ship to be the representative of the ship itself. There is also the argument that there is loss of identity over time, and therefore, it is not the same ship anymore and can be regarded as a different ship in the frame of time. This theory, however, has been heavily criticised owing to the assumptions it makes on several fronts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of the Ship of Theseus is an intriguing one, and questions the understanding of ourselves from within, that if we are in the same position, being replaced, what makes us the same person as before? What makes us, us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Davidson in his paper, &lt;em&gt;Knowing one’s own mind&lt;/em&gt;, gives an example of The Ship of Theseus. He talks about the possibility of a clone being born out of his dead body in a thunderstorm. How will his family or anyone else differentiate between the actual him, who is dead, and the clone borne out of the thunderstorm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argues that ‘there will be an inherent difference’ but he does not further enunciate his point. It places us under a precarious and delicate situation. Does it benefit us if we define ourselves within some definition and make sense out of ourselves? Do we need to know the difference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identity crisis may be a philosophically daunting question, but from a stoic’s perspective, this will not matter because the world we live in will not change with the change in me, and thus it will still be us in some way. Which goes on to say that there is no need to think about it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, is it wrong to explore and understand ourselves better in order to develop the characteristics of self resolution within us? Maybe we will never know or maybe knowing the answer defeats the human purpose which is not to define but keep a limited form in order to open up more interpretation. Thus, knowing who we are is a small fragment of understanding our consciousness, the universe beyond us and our purpose in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section, I will dig deeper into the realm of our nature to find clues as to what makes me so different from you on the other side of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes me, me and you, you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay Tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“What makes you, well, you?”- Michael Stevens, Vsauce.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk</title>
      <link href="/Beauty-and-Brazen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk" />
      <published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beauty-and-Brazen</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-and-Brazen">&lt;p&gt;“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his
humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in
&lt;em&gt;Berserk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of
other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the
least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an
adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his
life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close
to the &lt;strong&gt;Truth&lt;/strong&gt; and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more
interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he
know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to
script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche
refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered
to be, the future of humanity, &lt;em&gt;Ubermensch&lt;/em&gt;, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’.
Thus begins the journey of &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; and its protagonist, the most bad*rse
anime/manga character in history, &lt;em&gt;Guts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the
very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story
is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate
&lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; overtake him and he &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be entwined with his future, with what is
already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not
always free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in
&lt;em&gt;Twilight of the Idols&lt;/em&gt;, where he referred to causality as the cause of
humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning
to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause
behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to
support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; that free
will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians
exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche
thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a
protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it,
at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been
hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him.
When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him.
Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to
survive in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary
group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He
falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and
the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith
sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as &lt;em&gt;Eclipse&lt;/em&gt;, is a momentous image
of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get
killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get
violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He
does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining
several scars of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably
his most interesting piece of work, &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; introduced the
concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and
philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is
an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps:
The Camel, The Lion and The Child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the
knowledge of the &lt;em&gt;Dragon&lt;/em&gt; (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore
listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself.
As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told
to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’
demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a
Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system
in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The
Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of
the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the
system himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to
Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being
who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to
struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’
transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to
integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who
defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very
epitome of the Overman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the
Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company,
unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a
society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man.
Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the
other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of
this ambition. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in the same manner, brings about the reference of
Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not
understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand
the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the
light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all
their goals and dreams as one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of
Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to
resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true
goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs
and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been
highlighted in &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, where we are informed of the existence of a
monotheistic religion, termed as the &lt;em&gt;Holy See&lt;/em&gt;, whose ideals bear similarity to
Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who
could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro
Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all
odds, through Guts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is
all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit
of a fighter. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and
deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled
under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher
Man’, despite not being from the nobility. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in Berserk. Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close to the Truth and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered to be, the future of humanity, Ubermensch, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’. Thus begins the journey of Berserk and its protagonist, the most bad*rse anime/manga character in history, Guts. Berserk is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate will overtake him and he will be entwined with his future, with what is already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not always free. Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in Twilight of the Idols, where he referred to causality as the cause of humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in Twilight that free will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge. Berserk challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it, at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him. When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him. Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to survive in the wild. Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power. The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as Eclipse, is a momentous image of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining several scars of his own. Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably his most interesting piece of work, Thus Spoke Zarathustra introduced the concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps: The Camel, The Lion and The Child. The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the knowledge of the Dragon (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself. As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel. When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’ demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the system himself. That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’ transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very epitome of the Overman. A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company, unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man. Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of this ambition. Berserk, in the same manner, brings about the reference of Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all their goals and dreams as one.” Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been highlighted in Berserk, where we are informed of the existence of a monotheistic religion, termed as the Holy See, whose ideals bear similarity to Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all odds, through Guts. Berserk has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit of a fighter. Berserk, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher Man’, despite not being from the nobility. </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game</title>
      <link href="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game" />
      <published>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Codes-and-Ciphers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers">&lt;p&gt;“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will
miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and
you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are
and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen.
You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a1/Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer
scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War
II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The
Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the
Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the
Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s
original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German
movements during the War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/_dchris/19612913884&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//enigma-machine.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was
broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system
has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists
like Shamir and Bonhe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the
history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous
cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to
communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the
authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is
replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a
similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets
replaced by H and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://s4scoding.com/images/caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of
steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of
cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information,
using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the
very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of
people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone
to crack it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher.
A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages
or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication
even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time, 
being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the
throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code.
The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code,
is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you
guessed it, Samuel Morse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b5/International_Morse_Code.svg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//International_Morse_Code.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic
messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the
letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and
it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has
been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps;
tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed
it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if
masked properly that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements
in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most
talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have
talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that
age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the
Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher
replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous author David Kahn notes in his book &lt;em&gt;The Codebreakers&lt;/em&gt; that history
has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many
mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher
used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no
dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher
system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to
replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher)
to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without
the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human
comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no
matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused
to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an
inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to
Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule
the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest
concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex
and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract
concepts on the quantum nature of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting
up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we
are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build
and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only
for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is
truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be
brought down, thanks to humans themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of
the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into
effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen. You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - The Imitation Game, 2014. Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German movements during the War. The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists like Shamir and Bonhe. The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets replaced by H and so on. One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information, using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone to crack it. Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher. A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time,  being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code. The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code, is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you guessed it, Samuel Morse. For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps; tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if masked properly that is. Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text. The famous author David Kahn notes in his book The Codebreakers that history has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher) to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without the key. However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract concepts on the quantum nature of information. Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be brought down, thanks to humans themselves. Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into effect.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy?</title>
      <link href="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy?" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths">&lt;p&gt;From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least  400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the criminal context, this leads to some bold and difficult questions that have left even the Behavioral Science Unit of the FBI scratching their heads. How could we, by asking the right set of questions, successfully identify what kind of person is likely to commit a crime? How can we understand his possible motive behind his crime? And, most importantly, can we preempt the criminal’s future course of action? In examining these questions, the term this Behavioral Science Unit coined for the perpetrators of repeated crimes, i.e. ‘serial killer’ is now cult famous. These were the people who would go on a certain form of a spree, committing possibly similar or even dissimilar acts in order to prevent any trace leading up to them. The Unit was exploring how to connect these actions and how to develop a fool-proof method of doing so. Moreover, the Unit wanted to distinguish someone who just kills people and someone who does that because he believes the devil commands him to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were too many questions which could have been asked and none of them could have had any proper answers. But John E Douglas, a member of the Behavioral Science Unit, notes that there was a lot of fruit borne out of their investigations and rightly so. Douglas and his colleagues spent years interviewing criminals across penitentiaries all over the country in a span of more than a decade. Their subjects included Ted Bundy, the killer of several innocent girls, John Wayne Gacy, the infamous “Killer Clown”, who is also thought of to be the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;IT&lt;/em&gt;’s antagonist—a killer clown called Pennywise. The Unit interviewed the “Son of Sam”, David Berkowitz, who claimed that he shot people in cold blood because his cat – a manifestation of Satan himself – asked him to do so. They also interviewed Ed Kemper, a ‘giant’ in all literal senses with an extraordinary IQ of 145, who was convicted of killing his own mother, grandparents and 3 others whilst engaging in necrophilia with their bodies. The insight the Behavioral Science Unit gained from these studies influenced criminal profiling and psychopathic documentation over the years, giving rise to new fields within psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinctive features, John Douglas noted, that were possessed by most of these subjects was an incessant amount of ego. Douglas compared Ted Kaczynski, the Unabomber who was an extraordinarily intelligent criminal, and Dennis Rader, a comparatively less-educated one, and said that both their downfalls were due to their narcissism. Douglas contended that a heightened sense of ego, a lack of remorse and all such associated feelings, innate aggression, a traumatic childhood, and a poor, sexually malignant upbringing were all factors that could contribute to a person’s choices of insanity and crimes. He wrote his critically-acclaimed book, &lt;em&gt;The Mindhunter&lt;/em&gt;, on his studies which till date serves as a manual for some at the Quantico, which is the training ground for FBI agents in the US. This book explores all of his findings and delves deeper into the psyche of how a psychopath could possibly be thinking in accordance with Freudian psycho-sexual stimulation or violence-induced arousal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting fact, however, is that Douglas points out that it is wrong to believe that all psychopaths are just remorseless, guiltless, killing machines. He says that there is more complexity to them than that. Psychopaths have a lopsided view of emotions and morality, it’s not that they don’t ‘feel’, just that they feel very differently from the way most people do. Their ability to take cold, completely unemotional decisions is one that is cherished by most CEOs in today’s world. The only difference between psychopathic killers and corporate executives is the presence of external factors like a tough childhood, poverty, trauma etc., which makes the former a threat to society. As it is posed by another psychopath, albeit fictional in this case, Hannibal Lecter from the series of books by Thomas Harris, the human mind has an unfathomable level of variability and complexity. Who knows for sure what makes the Bundys and the Kempers the people they are? All we know is that they’re not born so, they are made to be so.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least 400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Questioning Humanity: The Stanford Prison Experiment</title>
      <link href="/Questioning-Humanity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questioning Humanity: The Stanford Prison Experiment" />
      <published>2019-02-14T21:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-14T21:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Questioning-Humanity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Questioning-Humanity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Whoever fights monsters should see to it that in the process he does not become a monster. And if you gaze long enough into an abyss, the abyss will gaze back into you.”&lt;/em&gt; - Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Humanity’ as a word essentially includes, but is not limited to, all the better things in the world: Peace, Happiness, Co-operational Existence for the betterment of the community, Altruism and so on. But what if this definition was farcical at the very least, or worse, misleading and based on chosen references rather the entire spectra of Truth? What if humans are the monsters they are themselves scared of? History does cite its own examples and notions on this issue. Tyrants, dictators and people in positions of power have always exploited those not in power since the beginning of time. But what if this was the true nature of Man? To seek answers to this question and more, Dr Philip Zimbardo along with his associates conducted the now infamous Stanford Prison Experiment in August 1971 in the basements of Stanford University’s Psychology Department. The aim of the experiment, as decided by Dr Zimbardo, was to conduct a social psychology experiment. Zimbardo’s primary motive for conducting the experiment was to focus on the power of roles, rules, symbols, group identity and situational validation of behaviour that generally would repulse ordinary individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Zimbardo, in his own words at the Toronto Symposium in 1996, “had been conducting research for some years on deindividuation, vandalism and dehumanization that illustrated the ease with which ordinary people could be led to engage in antisocial acts by putting them in situations where they felt anonymous, or they could perceive of others in ways that made them less than human, as enemies or objects”. In the Stanford Prison Experiment, he created a struggle of sorts between two groups and decided to evaluate the power dynamics behind it. He created a prison-like setup, where a certain set of individuals would be representing the ‘guards’ (the dominant strata) who would be controlling the ‘prisoners’ (the lower strata). The unsuspecting, and must we also add, willing volunteers in the experiment were divided into the groups only as a matter of chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Zimbardo set up the experiments to establish the breakdown of one’s own personality to take someone else’s. The guards were asked to react harshly in order to establish their power over the prisoners. Dave Eshelman, the most infamous guard during the experiment recalled that all actions were committed in order to fulfil the purpose behind the experiment, even though the experiment showed that some guards had very sadistic tendencies. The prisoners were taken from their own homes, and the Palo Alto Police cooperated with Zimbardo for a more genuine atmosphere. The prisoners were stripped and searched, their names were taken away from them and they were assigned numbers. The first day of the experiment went as it was expected to, without any issues. There were 9+3 guards and they were arranged to take charge in shifts. The conditions of the small container-like prison cells were largely in contrast with the living conditions of the guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the second day, however, things started turning more macabre. The prisoners locked their doors and refused to come out. The guards used fire extinguishers to subdue the revolt without any permission from Zimbardo, who acted as the “superintendent of the prison”. The guards decided that there would be privilege rooms, which had way better food and beds, where the prisoners who did not support the rebellion would be kept. The interesting thing was even the people who had not supported the rebellion did not choose to be in these rooms. The guards continued to establish their dominance by removing the mattresses and forcing the prisoners to sleep on the ground, not even allowing them to clean their chamber pots. After 36 hours, a certain prisoner #8612 claimed to have lost his mind and was forced to be released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the atrocities of the guards continued. They stripped the prisoners and asked them to repeat the numbers assigned to them in order to enforce their new identity on them. While Zimbardo was concerned that the released prisoner would come back and was busy relocating the experiment, the guards continued their naked displays of power. A certain prisoner #416 locked himself in his room and refused to eat his sausages. He was forced into solitary confinement. There were several times when the prisoners asked for parole, only to be refused under the condition of no payment for their services. Zimbardo claimed that the prisoners stayed back even if no money was involved because they had internalised the roles of the oppressed prisoners in themselves. It was only after Zimbardo’s fiancé, Maslach, arrived on the sixth day of the experiment and questioned the morality of the situation that finally the experiment concluded. Zimbardo noted that out of the 50 people who participated in the experimented, nobody questioned its morality apart from Maslach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several thought experiments and social and anthropogenic situations reenacted along the lines of the Stanford Prison Experiment. A notable one is the Milgram Experiment, where a person in one room was given the option of using an electronic switch which would send a current to another person in another room. The result of these experiments gives us a simple forlorn conclusion: Humans are, in most circumstances, sadistic creatures, and those with power will most likely prey on those without it. Even though the Stanford Experiment is challenged for having fraudulent methodology, the question remains that if humans are provided with an unrestricted and unbounded amount of power, will they behave like the guards did or will their ways be dependent on other factors such as the surrounding environment, i.e. the factors which were left unaccounted for in Zimbardo’s version? Or is there more to it than what meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several questions which arise on the origins of morality and cognitive behaviour if we analyse the results of the Stanford Prison Experiment. Maybe we will find more about it when we recreate the circumstances. Or maybe we could all just accept the tyrant within us, the mass murderer within us and also embrace the empathy within ourselves and let them battle it out for the soul of mankind. In &lt;i&gt;Dark Knight&lt;/i&gt; , the movie, The Joker presents a similar experiment where he provides people with the option of destroying one of two boats, where one is filled with civilians and the other is filled with criminals and the remote for the detonation of the bomb in one boat is placed in the other boat. Even though the film chooses not to explore the darker aspects of the human mind and depicts humanity as still residing within us, it is after all the matter of a film. The question is: what if this happens with all of us right now? What would you choose? The ball is in your court.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Whoever fights monsters should see to it that in the process he does not become a monster. And if you gaze long enough into an abyss, the abyss will gaze back into you.” - Friedrich Nietzsche</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“A Strange Game. The only Winning Move is to not Play.”</title>
      <link href="/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“A Strange Game. The only Winning Move is to not Play.”" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play">&lt;p&gt;The cold war science fiction movie War Games had a very cold yet direct message to its audiences and the dispatch remains important to us, even more so, at this point of time too. A nuclear war has no clear winners and thereby, referring to Sun Tzu’s key principle in the Art of War, “a battle where no one wins must be avoided.” A nuclear war and its implications have always been a source of inspiration for several authors and filmmakers. It stems from a deep fear of a “mutually assured destruction” of civilization as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doomsday Clock has been a representative of how far we are from a situation of nuclear war. The Doomsday Clock is updated by the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists based in Chicago and it has been maintained since 1947. The hypothetical global catastrophe is represented as “midnight” and the minute hand represents how far we are from that midnight. In 1991, post the Soviet collapse, it was the furthest away from the midnight, 17 minutes. The clock has been turned and has changed positions several times, 23 times to be precise, but never has it been more alarming than recently. In 2018, the clock was said to be only 2 minutes away from midnight due to the “looming possibility of climate change and nuclear war”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is funny how Metal fans can relate to it, as epitomised by a famous Iron Maiden song which was quite rightly called “2 minutes to midnight”. The chorus of the song carries a blatant warning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Hands that threaten Doom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two minutes to midnight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To kill the unborn in the womb”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I will not be referring to any political commentary by any world leader in reference to why this has been the most alarming period of human history. But this opportunity will be used to highlight why exactly we are not going to survive a nuclear holocaust if such a situation does arise in the future. We have come a long way since Dr. Oppenheimer’s infamous commentary after the success of the nuclear bomb testing, when he is supposed to have said (allegedly quoting the Bhagavad Gita) , &lt;em&gt;“I am become death, the destroyer of worlds”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we have become destroyers of worlds. The rate of development of nuclear technology peaked amidst the rising tensions during the Cold War, when certain ideologies involving the then Soviet Russia and United States put both of them in a collision course. It was an alarming period of time, but the tension peaked during the testing of the Soviet RDS-220 hydrogen Bomb, commonly known as the Tsar Bomba. The aspect which was truly alarming was that the bomb was named, in a rather unpopular manner, as Kuzma’s mother. This was believed to be a reference to Nikita Khrushchev’s statement in United Nations General Assembly in 1960, when he claimed that he would “show United States Kuzma’s mother”. He was intending to broach a Russian idiom which translates to, “we will show them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tsar Bomba was the most powerful explosive ever detonated, yielding a staggering 50 megatons of TNT. In fact, the initial plan envisioned of 100 megatons of TNT but that never happened, fortunately. The bomb was detonated at Sukhoy Nos cape of Severny Island, part of Novaya Zemlya. It was too big to be placed in a missile and too heavy for the planes to carry it with enough fuel. It was thereby carried in a release plane and the pilot Durnotsev and his crew were only given a dismal 50% chance of survival. The surprising fact was that the bomb which was expected to hit the ground was prevented from doing so by its own shockwave which reflected it back. The fireball was 8 km wide and was visible almost 1000 km away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mushroom cloud was about 64 km high—that is around 8 times the size of Mt. Everest. All buildings around a 55 km radius of ground zero were completely annihilated. It is said that a participant saw the bright flash from 270 km away with dark goggles and still felt the thermal pulse. In fact, the shockwave travelled the world around 3 times before it finally subsided. It was truly an alarming period of time in the midst of the show of power between nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is where the truly sinister shock is found. If an evaluation of the true capabilities of the Tsar Bomba is done, using the NUKEMAP software by Alex Wellerstein, if 10 of these bombs are used at key locations all around the world, around 2 billion of world’s population would get eliminated almost immediately. This does not even account for the long lasting effects of radiation and 3rd degree burns which several people will, inevitably, ultimately succumb to. Even a small scale nuclear war would have devastating effects on the planet. A research article by Dr. Mills proposes that even a local regional nuclear conflict, such as the India-Pakistan conflict would have devastating tolls on the planet’s ozone retention and protection capability. The ozone level would inevitably get decreased to alarming levels never before seen in human history, which would lead to a sudden fall in the Earth’s temperature, leading to possible frosts. Surface temperatures would go on decreasing for more than 25 years due to thermal inertia. This combination of cooling and less protection from the ozone layer would lead to enhanced UV rays from the sun, putting pressure on global food supplies that could lead to a global famine. This is only based on the assumption on equal use of artillery from both the sides though—which is clearly a very generous conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear war would have devastating effects on the planet’s resources and thereby would have a range of climatic effects which would surely spell doom for human civilisation. It is time we finally realized that there are no victors in this war. However, even the eradication of nuclear weapons places us in a catch-22 situation: There are no ways for the safe disposal of these weapons and a failure to handle them would only place them in the wrong hands. The technology which was expected to solve the energy crisis during the initial days of research has ended up being a nuisance of its own. War Games resonates with us as a cold reminder of a dystopia which lies beyond a nuclear catastrophe, that is if we survive it at all. Maybe with all the words and warnings, we could finally strive to push within us a sense of realization and maybe avoid the danger while there is still 2 minutes to the midnight.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The cold war science fiction movie War Games had a very cold yet direct message to its audiences and the dispatch remains important to us, even more so, at this point of time too. A nuclear war has no clear winners and thereby, referring to Sun Tzu’s key principle in the Art of War, “a battle where no one wins must be avoided.” A nuclear war and its implications have always been a source of inspiration for several authors and filmmakers. It stems from a deep fear of a “mutually assured destruction” of civilization as we know it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Space and Loneliness</title>
      <link href="/On-Space-and-Loneliness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Space and Loneliness" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Space-and-Loneliness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Space-and-Loneliness">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxi Driver’s principle character Travis Bickle outlines these very principles as espoused by the great American author (who I happen to be a big fan of) Thomas Wolfe. Loneliness is a derivative of several complex emotions which arise within the spheres of our consciousness. This article however will not stress on our individual perspective of loneliness but rather a collective sense of loneliness, i.e. the feeling that we could be the only civilization to breed conscious life in a whole goddamn universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1961, Frank Drake, in his very famous equation, discussed the possibility of the existence of the extraterrestrial beings and our chances of actually finding them and making contact with them. This was not to quantify the number of civilizations in the universe but rather a way to stimulate scientific dialogue on the search for extraterrestrial beings. It is just an estimation technique which is popularly known in the scientific community as the Fermi Problem. It provides a back-of-the-envelope solution to the entire problem at hand. The Drake equation features 7 unknown parameters which can be treated as variables in order to find an answer. This includes variables like the number of civilisations in our galaxy with which communication might be possible (i.e. which are on our current past light cone); the average rate of star formation in our galaxy; the fraction of those stars that have planets; the average number of planets that can potentially support life per star that has planets; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inspirations behind these variables was actually an article in the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; journal that was provocatively titled: “Searching for Interstellar Communications”. One of the first known attempts to connect with the extraterrestrial beings was made by the 1977 American Scientific program that employed the use of 2 robotic satellite probes, namely, Voyager 1 and Voyager 2, respectively. It was actually intended to study the outer solar system, i.e. the outer planets of Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune. It was launched under conditions of a favourable alignment of the four planets. The initial plan was to study the four planets, but currently, the Voyagers explore the outer boundary of the heliosphere in interstellar space and the mission has been extended way above it’s time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacecrafts contain very advanced technological instruments in order to collect and transmit proper, accurate data back home. The Voyagers have stabilized guidance systems, controlled by computers, to point their high gain antennas to Earth for efficient transfer of important results and data. The message transmission is also helped by the use of an electronic photography system which has been an instrumental part of the satellites. One thing of immense interest in the spacecraft, however, is the Voyager Golden Record. These records are phonograph records which contain sounds and images , “selected to portray the diversity and culture on Earth” to any intelligent extraterrestrial life that may come across it. Carl Sagan, the renowned astrophysicist who was allocated the duty to decide which records to include on the disk noted that “the spacecrafts will be encountered and the record played only if there are advanced space-faring civilisations in interstellar space”. But the launching of this “bottle” into the cosmic ocean says something very hopeful about life on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl Sagan chose and assembled 115 images and varieties of natural sounds. There are collections of songs and spoken greetings and printed messages from the likes of US President Jimmy Carter and UN Secretary General Kurt Waldheim. It includes an inspirational message which is “per aspera ad astra” or “ through hardships to the stars”, which is what this entire struggle of choices is supposed to signify. There are several photographs from the notable photographer Ansel Adams along with the recorded brain waves of Ann Druyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one song which resonates with this entire struggle is the simple choice of a gospel blues song written and performed by American musician Blind Willie Johnson that was recorded in 1927. The song was named: “Dark was the Night. Cold was the Ground”. It is basically an instrumental song with the self-taught slide style used by Willie and accompanied by his moaning and humming. Johnson was not blind when he was born, but it is speculated that he was blinded by his stepmother when was only 7 years old. Apparently, during an argument, she splashed Willie with a caustic solution of lye water which ended up permanently blinding him. However, that was not the end of his suffering. He used to perform on the streets and had a tin cup tied to his neck to collect money. During his career, he was praised for his style which became quite popular but he was never financially well off. Post the Great Depression, his audience was completely wiped off, and he never recorded again. And in strange series of circumstances in 1945, his home got destroyed in a fire and he continued to live within the ruins of his house, where he was exposed to humidity and dampness, following which he contracted Malaria. His health steadily worsened due to several other factors and hospitals were not willing to admit him owing to his visual impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He passed away on September 18, 1945. His life has been a true testimony of his song, which has immortalized humankind’s search to cure loneliness. His song truly represents the primal feeling which we all have, whether individually or collectively, for a greater purpose and a direction to every event. Floating in the endless space, it represents a sign of hope and a possibility on how loneliness could be a feature which could give us a new path to our existence. But maybe being alone is not bad after all. Maybe we could all be God’s lonely men. I guess we simply need a few aliens to tell us what the truth is.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
