<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/udayon.sen/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-03-11T21:53:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/udayon.sen/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy?</title>
      <link href="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy?" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths">&lt;p&gt;From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least  400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the criminal context, this leads to some bold and difficult questions that have left even the Behavioral Science Unit of the FBI scratching their heads. How could we, by asking the right set of questions, successfully identify what kind of person is likely to commit a crime? How can we understand his possible motive behind his crime? And, most importantly, can we preempt the criminal’s future course of action? In examining these questions, the term this Behavioral Science Unit coined for the perpetrators of repeated crimes, i.e. ‘serial killer’ is now cult famous. These were the people who would go on a certain form of a spree, committing possibly similar or even dissimilar acts in order to prevent any trace leading up to them. The Unit was exploring how to connect these actions and how to develop a fool-proof method of doing so. Moreover, the Unit wanted to distinguish someone who just kills people and someone who does that because he believes the devil commands him to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were too many questions which could have been asked and none of them could have had any proper answers. But John E Douglas, a member of the Behavioral Science Unit, notes that there was a lot of fruit borne out of their investigations and rightly so. Douglas and his colleagues spent years interviewing criminals across penitentiaries all over the country in a span of more than a decade. Their subjects included Ted Bundy, the killer of several innocent girls, John Wayne Gacy, the infamous “Killer Clown”, who is also thought of to be the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;IT&lt;/em&gt;’s antagonist—a killer clown called Pennywise. The Unit interviewed the “Son of Sam”, David Berkowitz, who claimed that he shot people in cold blood because his cat – a manifestation of Satan himself – asked him to do so. They also interviewed Ed Kemper, a ‘giant’ in all literal senses with an extraordinary IQ of 145, who was convicted of killing his own mother, grandparents and 3 others whilst engaging in necrophilia with their bodies. The insight the Behavioral Science Unit gained from these studies influenced criminal profiling and psychopathic documentation over the years, giving rise to new fields within psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinctive features, John Douglas noted, that were possessed by most of these subjects was an incessant amount of ego. Douglas compared Ted Kaczynski, the Unabomber who was an extraordinarily intelligent criminal, and Dennis Rader, a comparatively less-educated one, and said that both their downfalls were due to their narcissism. Douglas contended that a heightened sense of ego, a lack of remorse and all such associated feelings, innate aggression, a traumatic childhood, and a poor, sexually malignant upbringing were all factors that could contribute to a person’s choices of insanity and crimes. He wrote his critically-acclaimed book, &lt;em&gt;The Mindhunter&lt;/em&gt;, on his studies which till date serves as a manual for some at the Quantico, which is the training ground for FBI agents in the US. This book explores all of his findings and delves deeper into the psyche of how a psychopath could possibly be thinking in accordance with Freudian psycho-sexual stimulation or violence-induced arousal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting fact, however, is that Douglas points out that it is wrong to believe that all psychopaths are just remorseless, guiltless, killing machines. He says that there is more complexity to them than that. Psychopaths have a lopsided view of emotions and morality, it’s not that they don’t ‘feel’, just that they feel very differently from the way most people do. Their ability to take cold, completely unemotional decisions is one that is cherished by most CEOs in today’s world. The only difference between psychopathic killers and corporate executives is the presence of external factors like a tough childhood, poverty, trauma etc., which makes the former a threat to society. As it is posed by another psychopath, albeit fictional in this case, Hannibal Lecter from the series of books by Thomas Harris, the human mind has an unfathomable level of variability and complexity. Who knows for sure what makes the Bundys and the Kempers the people they are? All we know is that they’re not born so, they are made to be so.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least 400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Questioning Humanity: The Stanford Prison Experiment</title>
      <link href="/Questioning-Humanity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questioning Humanity: The Stanford Prison Experiment" />
      <published>2019-02-14T21:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-14T21:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Questioning-Humanity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Questioning-Humanity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Whoever fights monsters should see to it that in the process he does not become a monster. And if you gaze long enough into an abyss, the abyss will gaze back into you.”&lt;/em&gt; - Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Humanity’ as a word essentially includes, but is not limited to, all the better things in the world: Peace, Happiness, Co-operational Existence for the betterment of the community, Altruism and so on. But what if this definition was farcical at the very least, or worse, misleading and based on chosen references rather the entire spectra of Truth? What if humans are the monsters they are themselves scared of? History does cite its own examples and notions on this issue. Tyrants, dictators and people in positions of power have always exploited those not in power since the beginning of time. But what if this was the true nature of Man? To seek answers to this question and more, Dr Philip Zimbardo along with his associates conducted the now infamous Stanford Prison Experiment in August 1971 in the basements of Stanford University’s Psychology Department. The aim of the experiment, as decided by Dr Zimbardo, was to conduct a social psychology experiment. Zimbardo’s primary motive for conducting the experiment was to focus on the power of roles, rules, symbols, group identity and situational validation of behaviour that generally would repulse ordinary individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Zimbardo, in his own words at the Toronto Symposium in 1996, “had been conducting research for some years on deindividuation, vandalism and dehumanization that illustrated the ease with which ordinary people could be led to engage in antisocial acts by putting them in situations where they felt anonymous, or they could perceive of others in ways that made them less than human, as enemies or objects”. In the Stanford Prison Experiment, he created a struggle of sorts between two groups and decided to evaluate the power dynamics behind it. He created a prison-like setup, where a certain set of individuals would be representing the ‘guards’ (the dominant strata) who would be controlling the ‘prisoners’ (the lower strata). The unsuspecting, and must we also add, willing volunteers in the experiment were divided into the groups only as a matter of chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Zimbardo set up the experiments to establish the breakdown of one’s own personality to take someone else’s. The guards were asked to react harshly in order to establish their power over the prisoners. Dave Eshelman, the most infamous guard during the experiment recalled that all actions were committed in order to fulfil the purpose behind the experiment, even though the experiment showed that some guards had very sadistic tendencies. The prisoners were taken from their own homes, and the Palo Alto Police cooperated with Zimbardo for a more genuine atmosphere. The prisoners were stripped and searched, their names were taken away from them and they were assigned numbers. The first day of the experiment went as it was expected to, without any issues. There were 9+3 guards and they were arranged to take charge in shifts. The conditions of the small container-like prison cells were largely in contrast with the living conditions of the guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the second day, however, things started turning more macabre. The prisoners locked their doors and refused to come out. The guards used fire extinguishers to subdue the revolt without any permission from Zimbardo, who acted as the “superintendent of the prison”. The guards decided that there would be privilege rooms, which had way better food and beds, where the prisoners who did not support the rebellion would be kept. The interesting thing was even the people who had not supported the rebellion did not choose to be in these rooms. The guards continued to establish their dominance by removing the mattresses and forcing the prisoners to sleep on the ground, not even allowing them to clean their chamber pots. After 36 hours, a certain prisoner #8612 claimed to have lost his mind and was forced to be released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the atrocities of the guards continued. They stripped the prisoners and asked them to repeat the numbers assigned to them in order to enforce their new identity on them. While Zimbardo was concerned that the released prisoner would come back and was busy relocating the experiment, the guards continued their naked displays of power. A certain prisoner #416 locked himself in his room and refused to eat his sausages. He was forced into solitary confinement. There were several times when the prisoners asked for parole, only to be refused under the condition of no payment for their services. Zimbardo claimed that the prisoners stayed back even if no money was involved because they had internalised the roles of the oppressed prisoners in themselves. It was only after Zimbardo’s fiancé, Maslach, arrived on the sixth day of the experiment and questioned the morality of the situation that finally the experiment concluded. Zimbardo noted that out of the 50 people who participated in the experimented, nobody questioned its morality apart from Maslach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several thought experiments and social and anthropogenic situations reenacted along the lines of the Stanford Prison Experiment. A notable one is the Milgram Experiment, where a person in one room was given the option of using an electronic switch which would send a current to another person in another room. The result of these experiments gives us a simple forlorn conclusion: Humans are, in most circumstances, sadistic creatures, and those with power will most likely prey on those without it. Even though the Stanford Experiment is challenged for having fraudulent methodology, the question remains that if humans are provided with an unrestricted and unbounded amount of power, will they behave like the guards did or will their ways be dependent on other factors such as the surrounding environment, i.e. the factors which were left unaccounted for in Zimbardo’s version? Or is there more to it than what meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several questions which arise on the origins of morality and cognitive behaviour if we analyse the results of the Stanford Prison Experiment. Maybe we will find more about it when we recreate the circumstances. Or maybe we could all just accept the tyrant within us, the mass murderer within us and also embrace the empathy within ourselves and let them battle it out for the soul of mankind. In &lt;i&gt;Dark Knight&lt;/i&gt; , the movie, The Joker presents a similar experiment where he provides people with the option of destroying one of two boats, where one is filled with civilians and the other is filled with criminals and the remote for the detonation of the bomb in one boat is placed in the other boat. Even though the film chooses not to explore the darker aspects of the human mind and depicts humanity as still residing within us, it is after all the matter of a film. The question is: what if this happens with all of us right now? What would you choose? The ball is in your court.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Whoever fights monsters should see to it that in the process he does not become a monster. And if you gaze long enough into an abyss, the abyss will gaze back into you.” - Friedrich Nietzsche</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“A Strange Game. The only Winning Move is to not Play.”</title>
      <link href="/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“A Strange Game. The only Winning Move is to not Play.”" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play">&lt;p&gt;The cold war science fiction movie War Games had a very cold yet direct message to its audiences and the dispatch remains important to us, even more so, at this point of time too. A nuclear war has no clear winners and thereby, referring to Sun Tzu’s key principle in the Art of War, “a battle where no one wins must be avoided.” A nuclear war and its implications have always been a source of inspiration for several authors and filmmakers. It stems from a deep fear of a “mutually assured destruction” of civilization as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doomsday Clock has been a representative of how far we are from a situation of nuclear war. The Doomsday Clock is updated by the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists based in Chicago and it has been maintained since 1947. The hypothetical global catastrophe is represented as “midnight” and the minute hand represents how far we are from that midnight. In 1991, post the Soviet collapse, it was the furthest away from the midnight, 17 minutes. The clock has been turned and has changed positions several times, 23 times to be precise, but never has it been more alarming than recently. In 2018, the clock was said to be only 2 minutes away from midnight due to the “looming possibility of climate change and nuclear war”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is funny how Metal fans can relate to it, as epitomised by a famous Iron Maiden song which was quite rightly called “2 minutes to midnight”. The chorus of the song carries a blatant warning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Hands that threaten Doom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two minutes to midnight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To kill the unborn in the womb”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I will not be referring to any political commentary by any world leader in reference to why this has been the most alarming period of human history. But this opportunity will be used to highlight why exactly we are not going to survive a nuclear holocaust if such a situation does arise in the future. We have come a long way since Dr. Oppenheimer’s infamous commentary after the success of the nuclear bomb testing, when he is supposed to have said (allegedly quoting the Bhagavad Gita) , &lt;em&gt;“I am become death, the destroyer of worlds”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we have become destroyers of worlds. The rate of development of nuclear technology peaked amidst the rising tensions during the Cold War, when certain ideologies involving the then Soviet Russia and United States put both of them in a collision course. It was an alarming period of time, but the tension peaked during the testing of the Soviet RDS-220 hydrogen Bomb, commonly known as the Tsar Bomba. The aspect which was truly alarming was that the bomb was named, in a rather unpopular manner, as Kuzma’s mother. This was believed to be a reference to Nikita Khrushchev’s statement in United Nations General Assembly in 1960, when he claimed that he would “show United States Kuzma’s mother”. He was intending to broach a Russian idiom which translates to, “we will show them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tsar Bomba was the most powerful explosive ever detonated, yielding a staggering 50 megatons of TNT. In fact, the initial plan envisioned of 100 megatons of TNT but that never happened, fortunately. The bomb was detonated at Sukhoy Nos cape of Severny Island, part of Novaya Zemlya. It was too big to be placed in a missile and too heavy for the planes to carry it with enough fuel. It was thereby carried in a release plane and the pilot Durnotsev and his crew were only given a dismal 50% chance of survival. The surprising fact was that the bomb which was expected to hit the ground was prevented from doing so by its own shockwave which reflected it back. The fireball was 8 km wide and was visible almost 1000 km away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mushroom cloud was about 64 km high—that is around 8 times the size of Mt. Everest. All buildings around a 55 km radius of ground zero were completely annihilated. It is said that a participant saw the bright flash from 270 km away with dark goggles and still felt the thermal pulse. In fact, the shockwave travelled the world around 3 times before it finally subsided. It was truly an alarming period of time in the midst of the show of power between nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is where the truly sinister shock is found. If an evaluation of the true capabilities of the Tsar Bomba is done, using the NUKEMAP software by Alex Wellerstein, if 10 of these bombs are used at key locations all around the world, around 2 billion of world’s population would get eliminated almost immediately. This does not even account for the long lasting effects of radiation and 3rd degree burns which several people will, inevitably, ultimately succumb to. Even a small scale nuclear war would have devastating effects on the planet. A research article by Dr. Mills proposes that even a local regional nuclear conflict, such as the India-Pakistan conflict would have devastating tolls on the planet’s ozone retention and protection capability. The ozone level would inevitably get decreased to alarming levels never before seen in human history, which would lead to a sudden fall in the Earth’s temperature, leading to possible frosts. Surface temperatures would go on decreasing for more than 25 years due to thermal inertia. This combination of cooling and less protection from the ozone layer would lead to enhanced UV rays from the sun, putting pressure on global food supplies that could lead to a global famine. This is only based on the assumption on equal use of artillery from both the sides though—which is clearly a very generous conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear war would have devastating effects on the planet’s resources and thereby would have a range of climatic effects which would surely spell doom for human civilisation. It is time we finally realized that there are no victors in this war. However, even the eradication of nuclear weapons places us in a catch-22 situation: There are no ways for the safe disposal of these weapons and a failure to handle them would only place them in the wrong hands. The technology which was expected to solve the energy crisis during the initial days of research has ended up being a nuisance of its own. War Games resonates with us as a cold reminder of a dystopia which lies beyond a nuclear catastrophe, that is if we survive it at all. Maybe with all the words and warnings, we could finally strive to push within us a sense of realization and maybe avoid the danger while there is still 2 minutes to the midnight.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The cold war science fiction movie War Games had a very cold yet direct message to its audiences and the dispatch remains important to us, even more so, at this point of time too. A nuclear war has no clear winners and thereby, referring to Sun Tzu’s key principle in the Art of War, “a battle where no one wins must be avoided.” A nuclear war and its implications have always been a source of inspiration for several authors and filmmakers. It stems from a deep fear of a “mutually assured destruction” of civilization as we know it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Space and Loneliness</title>
      <link href="/On-Space-and-Loneliness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Space and Loneliness" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Space-and-Loneliness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Space-and-Loneliness">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxi Driver’s principle character Travis Bickle outlines these very principles as espoused by the great American author (who I happen to be a big fan of) Thomas Wolfe. Loneliness is a derivative of several complex emotions which arise within the spheres of our consciousness. This article however will not stress on our individual perspective of loneliness but rather a collective sense of loneliness, i.e. the feeling that we could be the only civilization to breed conscious life in a whole goddamn universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1961, Frank Drake, in his very famous equation, discussed the possibility of the existence of the extraterrestrial beings and our chances of actually finding them and making contact with them. This was not to quantify the number of civilizations in the universe but rather a way to stimulate scientific dialogue on the search for extraterrestrial beings. It is just an estimation technique which is popularly known in the scientific community as the Fermi Problem. It provides a back-of-the-envelope solution to the entire problem at hand. The Drake equation features 7 unknown parameters which can be treated as variables in order to find an answer. This includes variables like the number of civilisations in our galaxy with which communication might be possible (i.e. which are on our current past light cone); the average rate of star formation in our galaxy; the fraction of those stars that have planets; the average number of planets that can potentially support life per star that has planets; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inspirations behind these variables was actually an article in the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; journal that was provocatively titled: “Searching for Interstellar Communications”. One of the first known attempts to connect with the extraterrestrial beings was made by the 1977 American Scientific program that employed the use of 2 robotic satellite probes, namely, Voyager 1 and Voyager 2, respectively. It was actually intended to study the outer solar system, i.e. the outer planets of Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune. It was launched under conditions of a favourable alignment of the four planets. The initial plan was to study the four planets, but currently, the Voyagers explore the outer boundary of the heliosphere in interstellar space and the mission has been extended way above it’s time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacecrafts contain very advanced technological instruments in order to collect and transmit proper, accurate data back home. The Voyagers have stabilized guidance systems, controlled by computers, to point their high gain antennas to Earth for efficient transfer of important results and data. The message transmission is also helped by the use of an electronic photography system which has been an instrumental part of the satellites. One thing of immense interest in the spacecraft, however, is the Voyager Golden Record. These records are phonograph records which contain sounds and images , “selected to portray the diversity and culture on Earth” to any intelligent extraterrestrial life that may come across it. Carl Sagan, the renowned astrophysicist who was allocated the duty to decide which records to include on the disk noted that “the spacecrafts will be encountered and the record played only if there are advanced space-faring civilisations in interstellar space”. But the launching of this “bottle” into the cosmic ocean says something very hopeful about life on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl Sagan chose and assembled 115 images and varieties of natural sounds. There are collections of songs and spoken greetings and printed messages from the likes of US President Jimmy Carter and UN Secretary General Kurt Waldheim. It includes an inspirational message which is “per aspera ad astra” or “ through hardships to the stars”, which is what this entire struggle of choices is supposed to signify. There are several photographs from the notable photographer Ansel Adams along with the recorded brain waves of Ann Druyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one song which resonates with this entire struggle is the simple choice of a gospel blues song written and performed by American musician Blind Willie Johnson that was recorded in 1927. The song was named: “Dark was the Night. Cold was the Ground”. It is basically an instrumental song with the self-taught slide style used by Willie and accompanied by his moaning and humming. Johnson was not blind when he was born, but it is speculated that he was blinded by his stepmother when was only 7 years old. Apparently, during an argument, she splashed Willie with a caustic solution of lye water which ended up permanently blinding him. However, that was not the end of his suffering. He used to perform on the streets and had a tin cup tied to his neck to collect money. During his career, he was praised for his style which became quite popular but he was never financially well off. Post the Great Depression, his audience was completely wiped off, and he never recorded again. And in strange series of circumstances in 1945, his home got destroyed in a fire and he continued to live within the ruins of his house, where he was exposed to humidity and dampness, following which he contracted Malaria. His health steadily worsened due to several other factors and hospitals were not willing to admit him owing to his visual impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He passed away on September 18, 1945. His life has been a true testimony of his song, which has immortalized humankind’s search to cure loneliness. His song truly represents the primal feeling which we all have, whether individually or collectively, for a greater purpose and a direction to every event. Floating in the endless space, it represents a sign of hope and a possibility on how loneliness could be a feature which could give us a new path to our existence. But maybe being alone is not bad after all. Maybe we could all be God’s lonely men. I guess we simply need a few aliens to tell us what the truth is.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
