<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/alex.madajian/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-22T19:37:36+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/alex.madajian/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">My Family’s Genocide Will Never Be Forgotten</title>
      <link href="/My-Family-Genocide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Family's Genocide Will Never Be Forgotten" />
      <published>2020-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/My-Family-Genocide</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/My-Family-Genocide">&lt;p&gt;If we’ve ever had the pleasure of being personally acquainted, one of the first things I make sure people know about me is that I am an Armenian. Now, what is that you may ask? It’s a person from a tiny part of an obscure corner of the world. It’s neither in Europe, nor in Asia, nor in the Middle East, yet the inhabitants have ties to all the three. In the Caucasus mountains south of Russia and just north of Iran, is a country known as Armenia. It used to be far larger. Under &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ancient.eu/Tigranes_the_Great/&quot;&gt;King Tigran the Great&lt;/a&gt;, its furthest extent stretched from the Caspian sea, all the way to the Mediterranean while even holding part of Israel as its vassal state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps what Armenia is most known for, is that it was the first country to adopt Christianity as the state religion. Even before the Bible was canonised during the Council of Rome in 382 AD, Armenia officially became a Christian kingdom 81 years earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For centuries, Armenia was the battleground between the world’s two greatest powers: Rome and Persia. Never fully yielding to either side, using diplomacy and sometimes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8d4FHivSplU&quot;&gt;military defiance&lt;/a&gt;, Armenians maintained their cultural, religious, and, usually, their political independence for centuries. Then came the Turks. In the 11th century, the Turks swept through Anatolia, effectively rendering Armenia a vassal state with minimal independence. Nevertheless, the Armenians persisted under this new Turkish and, later, Ottoman rule. Even under the massacres of the last Sultan, Abdul Hamid II, which led to the deaths of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.armenian-genocide.org/hamidian.html&quot;&gt;hundreds of thousands of Armenians&lt;/a&gt;, they still eked out a living. But sadly, this was only the beginning of the birth pains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sultan was not a popular man. He was eventually deposed by a revolutionary group known as the Young Turks. This group of revolutionaries, led by the Committee for Union and Progress (CUP) had partnered with the Armenians promising them religious toleration, a prospect sorely longed for by the Armenian community for centuries. It is a shame these promises of equality were only worth as much as the sand in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through modern &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/383673.A_Shameful_Act&quot;&gt;historical research&lt;/a&gt;, we now know from the beginning that the CUP had a nationalist vision of a Turkey unified by one Turkish ethnicity and one Islamic religion. As over 2 million Christian Armenians were living in Anatolia, there was an ‘Armenian problem’ to this vision. However, Enver Pasha, the leader of the CUP, had his own final solution. It was so barbaric and sadistic, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meforum.org/3434/armenian-genocide-hitler&quot;&gt;Adolf Hitler drew inspiration from it&lt;/a&gt;. On April 24, 1915, the Armenian intellectuals, politicians, military members, and artists were rounded-up and never seen again. Notices went up all across Anatolia that all Armenians were going to be deported. They were to leave behind all their belongings and were assured they would return to retrieve them later. They were told this deportation was to put them out of harm’s way from the violence of World War I. All of the promises were lies. Town by town, the Christian Armenians, Greeks, Assyrians, Chaldeans, and other Christian minorities were gathered up and sent on death marches through the desert. In addition to being deprived of food, water, and rest, they were subject to torture, rape, and outright murder. Often, as a mockery to their faith, the Turks would nail victims some to make-shift crosses. As a small example of this genocide’s barbaric nature, the Turks responsible for the massacre of the village of Marsovan &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=KeR9AAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;dq=&quot;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; didn’t want to waste their bullets, so they used axes instead. Even my family’s story carries some of the brutalities of the Genocide. When my mother’s grandmother’s family was fleeing for its life, the family was stopped by a Turkish patrol and the father was beheaded in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many countless atrocities with details too unbearable and barbaric for civilised readers such as yourself. With such wanton destruction and human death, one would like to believe this tragedy was condemned by the world. Sadly, Turkey has worked very hard to sweep the blood under the rug. For over a century, they have spent millions of dollars lobbying foreign governments into perpetuating a silence on the massacre of over a million through state-sponsored genocide. They even propagate an army of phoney academics such as Justin McCarthy and fund social media campaigns like #lethistorydecide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technique of gaslighting and throwing distracting nuances into the conversation has not deterred the academic consensus nor does it discredit &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.clarku.edu/guerguerianarchive/&quot;&gt;the endless archives&lt;/a&gt; detailing the crimes of the Turkish government. Also, the fact some parts of the Turkish archives are &lt;a href=&quot;http://asbarez.com/167394/how-turkey-destroyed-or-disposed-its-historical-archives-and-documents/&quot;&gt;spotty at best and missing some of the time&lt;/a&gt; gives a strong indication of suspicious knavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why so many countries have not acknowledged the Armenian Genocide as a genocide is because the modern republic of Turkey has made itself a useful Middle-Eastern ally to many powerful states, including the US. During the Cold War, they allowed the US to host their closest military bases to Moscow. After the fall of the Soviet Union, they were a vital strategic partner in the US’ wars against Iraq. Even though President Obama promised in his 2008 election campaign to acknowledge the Armenian Genocide, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/promises/obameter/promise/511/recognize-armenian-genocide/&quot;&gt;he remained silent for his 8 years&lt;/a&gt;. Most likely due to the fact that Turkey was an ally against ISIS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the recent collapse of the terrorist group, the excuses were out. In October 2019, the US House of Representatives voted with an overwhelming 97% margin to acknowledge the Armenian Genocide. Later that year in December, the US Senate (albeit on their 4th try that session) voted unanimously to acknowledge the Armenian Genocide. Now all that remains is for the current President to release a statement recognising that the extermination of over 1.5 million Armenians, in addition to other Chrisitan minorities, was perpetrated by the Ottoman government. Granted, the current American President has an impressive talent for saying things people don’t like to hear, but like all of his Presidential actions, we shall wait and see what he does next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this all mean? Why should we care about recognising the Armenian Genocide? After all, it was over 105 years ago. The reason this is important today is that if a country cannot come to terms with its past mistakes, what assurance do we have they will not commit the same atrocities again? Genocide denial is genocide perpetration. In addition to the tragic loss of life and the decimation of entire communities, there is also a cultural genocide which continues to this day. Few people have heard of the Armenians, let alone their historic tragedy. My hope is after you are finished reading this, you leave with an impression of our uncompromising resilience and unflappable strength of will. On the commemoration of the 105th anniversary of the Genocide on April 24, remember our story. Remember us. We are here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I should like to see any power of the world destroy this race, this small tribe of unimportant people, whose wars have all been fought and lost, whose structures have crumbled, literature is unread, music is unheard, and prayers are no more answered. Go ahead, destroy Armenia. See if you can do it. Send them into the desert without bread or water. Burn their homes and churches. Then see if they will not laugh, sing and pray again. For when two of them meet anywhere in the world, see if they will not create a New Armenia.”&lt;/em&gt; - -   William Saroyan&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If we’ve ever had the pleasure of being personally acquainted, one of the first things I make sure people know about me is that I am an Armenian. Now, what is that you may ask? It’s a person from a tiny part of an obscure corner of the world. It’s neither in Europe, nor in Asia, nor in the Middle East, yet the inhabitants have ties to all the three. In the Caucasus mountains south of Russia and just north of Iran, is a country known as Armenia. It used to be far larger. Under King Tigran the Great, its furthest extent stretched from the Caspian sea, all the way to the Mediterranean while even holding part of Israel as its vassal state.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Calvin Coolidge: Libertarian Hero or Economic Assassin?</title>
      <link href="/Calvin-Coolidge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calvin Coolidge: Libertarian Hero or Economic Assassin?" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Calvin-Coolidge</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Calvin-Coolidge">&lt;p&gt;In the American right, there has been longing for a fiscal conservative. For years, the most touted example was Ronald Reagan, and although he presided over one of the nation’s largest tax cuts, he ran up major deficits. With the election of President Trump and the implementation of his multiple socially conservative policies, many conservatives have cast away Ronald Regan as their poster-child for a conservative icon. But as far as issues go, neither can hold a candle to the smallest-government libertarian in American history: Calvin Coolidge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coolidge was born in Vermont in 1872 (ironically, the same state as the current democratic-socialist Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders). His father was a farmer, small business-owner and politician. Tragically, his mother died when he was only twelve years old. For college, Coolidge moved to Amherst in Massachusetts, then went on to open up a law firm in 1898. Seven years later, he married Grace Goodhue, a talkative social butterfly. She was an incredible contrast to Coolidge’s notoriously quiet and serious demeanour. Eventually, he started running for public office while branding himself as a progressive Republican. He quickly moved up through local government, the Massachusetts state legislature, and eventually was elected Governor. By today’s standard, one would think a progressive Republican from Massachusetts would be radically leftist, after all, Massachusetts is one of the most far-left states. However, over a hundred years ago, a progressive was not someone who advocated for transgender rights or the Green New Deal, but someone who fought for woman’s suffrage and the civil rights of people of colour. Nevertheless, they also saw a bigger and more powerful government as a means of producing this society. So how did Coolidge become both a libertarian hero and a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/calvin-coolidges-surprise-contribution-to-progressivism/&quot;&gt;progressive Republican&lt;/a&gt;”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As stated earlier, he was notoriously restrained: both in personality and in government action. He believed it was progressive to restrain the government from restricting the liberty of others’ access to civil rights. This stood in stark contrast to a stream of previous progressive Presidents who sought to expand the reach and size of government as much as possible, such as Woodrow Wilson and Theodore Roosevelt. In spite of his silent personality, Coolidge was chosen to be the Vice President of the Republican Nominee, Warren Harding, for the 1920 Presidential race. In a twist of fate, his opponent — James Cox — had chosen the polar opposite to be his Vice President: the one and only Franklin Delano Roosevelt. In that election, Harding and Coolidge won. Although Harding did have a very conservative administration, his corrupt practices got ahead of him in what is known as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.history.com/topics/roaring-twenties/teapot-dome-scandal&quot;&gt;The Teapot Dome Scandal&lt;/a&gt;.” In the midst of members right and left of Harding being found riddled with corruption, Harding died. Yes, just like that. He died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for the country’s sake, Coolidge was not found to be corrupt and &lt;a href=&quot;http://press-pubs.uchicago.edu/founders/tocs/a2_1_6.html&quot;&gt;was supposed to succeed the President anyway&lt;/a&gt;. After Harding’s death in August, 1923, Coolidge finished Harding’s term and ran for a full term in 1924 and didn’t bother seeking re-election. But what was the Coolidge administration like? Again, it cannot be restated enough, Coolidge believed in as little government action as possible, in virtually all areas of life. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/budget-and-tax-lessons-from-president-calvin-coolidge/#_edn5&quot;&gt;In a speech&lt;/a&gt;, he once said, “Government extravagance is not only contrary to the whole teaching of our Constitution but violates the fundamental conceptions and the very genius of American institutions.” But how much did he enact this belief?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for policy, Coolidge still held too many old-time progressive ideals. On civil rights, he accomplished much for his time. During the height of the Jim Crow era, where government-sanctioned racial discrimination laws were prevalent, Coolidge didn’t appoint any member of the Ku Klux Klan to government or the judiciary, even though some Senators and Judges held strong ties to it. He also helped pass several anti-lynching laws. It should be no wonder that during the election of 1924, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/1924-election-conflicting-minority-endorsements/&quot;&gt;historian John Berry estimated&lt;/a&gt; that “well over 90% of northern blacks voted Republican.” In addition, he supported child labour laws and women’s rights, making the first female appointment to the federal judiciary whilst giving Native Americans &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/story/2017/06/02/coolidge-signs-indian-citizenship-act-june-2-1924-238983&quot;&gt;citizenship&lt;/a&gt;. He also fought in the most contested battle of freedom during the era: prohibition. Coolidge wasn’t known to be a major drinker, but as far as public policy goes, he was a bit of a mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On foreign policy, he refused to recognise the new Soviet Union. Also, much to the delight of modern-day libertarians, he refused to join the League of Nations. Overall, he attempted to have America do as little as possible in foreign affairs. His economic policies really did reflect the libertarian &lt;em&gt;Laissez-Faire&lt;/em&gt; philosophy. Even to this day, he has been the only Republican in the past 100 years to have a surplus budget in any year, and the only President to have had one every year he served. Compared to now, almost no federal regulations were in place. Coolidge cut taxes, and unashamedly fought against farm subsidies (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/well-farmers-never-have-made-much-money-coolidges-case-against-subsidies/&quot;&gt;a major issue at the time&lt;/a&gt;). In fact, perhaps Coolidge’s only fall from the libertarian’s grace is that he did favour tariffs to protect American manufacturing. But this was one of the major sources of revenue for the United States government &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/briandomitrovic/2018/03/09/when-tariffs-worked/#5a4dfd3770f9&quot;&gt;and had been the biggest&lt;/a&gt; until the income tax was instituted in 1913.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like his policy, Coolidge was a man of restraint. His nickname, ‘Silent Cal’, was given for a good reason. At a party, a woman once proclaimed that she had accepted a bet that she could get him to say three words. He curtly replied: “you lose.” During some periods of his Presidency, he would sleep for eleven hours and work only four hours a day. Some of that time was spent staring out of his window &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ozy.com/flashback/historys-laziest-leaders/6494/&quot;&gt;counting the cars&lt;/a&gt; that drove by. He would also hide in his office, then hit the emergency buzzer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historytoday.com/archive/silent-cal&quot;&gt;see how long it took&lt;/a&gt; for the guards to find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As light-hearted the President might have seemed, he did not have a joyous presidency. While his son, Calvin Jr., was playing tennis without socks, he got a blister that became infected and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@Anthony_Bergen/blister-the-day-calvin-coolidge-lost-his-favorite-son-and-his-passion-for-the-presidency-fe7b6b638f&quot;&gt;shortly resulted in his death&lt;/a&gt;. He was 16 years old. As this happened during the election year, Coolidge barely bothered to campaign. He still won overwhelmingly, but carrying out the duties of his Presidency was clearly painful. In his own autobiography, he wrote that once his son had died, “the power and the glory of the Presidency went with him.” Coolidge died of a broken man barely more than three years after leaving the Presidency at the age of sixty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Ronald Reagan hung a portrait of Coolidge in the Oval Office and claimed he was his favourite President. Perhaps Coolidge did inspire Reagan on many issues, but other than that, there are few traces of Coolidge’s administration today. Because he was so restrained on enacting legislation, we have few reminders of his presence, unlike Presidents who used the government to take action and left strong impressions generations after they left office. Lincoln’s victory over the South, Wilson creating the Federal Reserve, FDR’s New Deal, and LBJ’s Great Society all serve as living reminders of their legacies well after their deaths. But in Coolidge’s case, the conspicuous absence of grand schemes is what serves as a reminder of his brilliant legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till this day, there is still a great debate on what caused the Great Depression, and how much Coolidge was responsible for it. Those who oppose capitalism see him as the obvious culprit. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fee.org/articles/chaos-in-the-marketplace-don-t-believe-it/&quot;&gt;some economists&lt;/a&gt; credit tariffs to be the principal reason for the Great Depression, and since Coolidge did not remove them, he could be held partly responsible. Although most of the blame ought to fall on his Secretary of Commerce and successor: Herbert Hoover. Hoover was very much an interventionist in the economy and even expanded the tariffs by signing the Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this mean for us today? For one, it proves that there is no such thing as perfection or purity. As much as the American libertarian right would like to dream of a world without tariffs or silly government bans like prohibition, Coolidge was the best example of a libertarian President. But he also lived at a time when there was little government to restrain anyway. The United States was not entangled in virtually every region of the world, so there was little need to remove itself. There was no massive social safety net, nor sprawling government bureaucracy. Seven departments existed in the Executive Branch during Coolidge’s time and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_federal_executive_departments&quot;&gt;eight have been added since&lt;/a&gt;, not to mention so many government agencies within those departments: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/waynecrews/2017/07/05/how-many-federal-agencies-exist-we-cant-drain-the-swamp-until-we-know/#1205b8591aa2&quot;&gt;government itself isn’t sure how many are there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Coolidge was not perfect, he probably knew he couldn’t be. Perhaps that’s what made Coolidge so restraining. He knew he couldn’t do everything or be everyone. He simply did the best he could and allowed history to decide his fate. As all of us should.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the American right, there has been longing for a fiscal conservative. For years, the most touted example was Ronald Reagan, and although he presided over one of the nation’s largest tax cuts, he ran up major deficits. With the election of President Trump and the implementation of his multiple socially conservative policies, many conservatives have cast away Ronald Regan as their poster-child for a conservative icon. But as far as issues go, neither can hold a candle to the smallest-government libertarian in American history: Calvin Coolidge.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)</title>
      <link href="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)" />
      <published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West">&lt;p&gt;I have written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood, dirt, and money — or a combination of the three — are responsible for virtually all conflicts. Of course, the Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception, but on a fundamental level, the radicals on both sides see this as a religious struggle. In the current generation, we tend to secularise everything so that we can pretend to scientifically map out a solution. But with conflict as complicated as the Arab-Israeli conflict, it’s easy to wrap ourselves with the blanket of self-pity and proclaim “Oh! It’s just so complicated. So many different perspectives and feelings. I’ll just never understand it!” It is true that we will never solve the conflict with the systematic precisions given to us by science because not every societal problem can be solved in such a manner. If we want to progress, we have to move beyond the fact no one will completely understand everything about the conflict. However, we must still strive to understand it. Even if religion seems strange or difficult to understand for some, it is essential for one to recognise the control it has over people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going any further, I must highlight my shortcomings. One popular saying I encountered while travelling to Israel was “two Jews have five opinions.” By this, the saying means that there are a lot of internal disagreements within the Jewish community. So when I write “The Jews believe this…” or “Muslims have faith that…”, I implore you to take it with a grain of salt. Every religion is filled with people who dissent on virtually every aspect. There are very few dogmas or beliefs completely agreed upon by an entire religion. Even among radicals, the interpretations of those dogmas are bitterly disputed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask any religious person, even those who have spent decades training and study, if they understand their own religion. I anxiously await to hear back from you. Until you find that person, the world will keep on rotating while the Israeli and Palestinian children die. We will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; understand even just one perspective of this conflict, however, we can (and must) strive to at least understand where both sides are coming from. The Arab-Israel conflict is very much religious conflict. Not just between Jews and Muslims, but also between the different factions within those faiths, in addition to many other religions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Israel and Palestine have religious sites sacred to Christians and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldheritagesite.org/list/Bah%C3%A1%E2%80%99i+Holy+Places&quot;&gt;Baha’i&lt;/a&gt; (and probably more religions), the local population is mostly made up of Jews in Israel and Muslims in Palestine. Although the minorities play a role in the history and international relations, the chief actors — Israel and Palestine — have undeniable ties to the religion of their majorities. Therefore, if one does not understand religion, they will never understand this conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my dear secular readers, religion may superficially seem like a way of life or a set of traditions, but if that is the extent of your view of religion, then allow me to correct your course. This may be true for a casual religious observer, but we are not solely dealing with casual observers, we are dealing with hardliners and fundamentalists. Now I consider myself to be a Christian fundamentalist, so allow me to explain what ‘fundamentalism’ means. Essentially when one is seeking to get to the fundamentals of one’s religion, they are a fundamentalist. For some, it means pursuing a message of peace and love, for others, their perception of the fundamentals of their religion is to rid themselves (and others) of impurity by any means necessary. Again, even within fundamentalists, you can see a wide range of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a person may arrange their day-to-day schedule or diet around their religion. Perhaps take special holidays and be extra motivated to spend time with their family. But any serious or dedicated religious person will tell you, it is also a philosophy. It’s a framework for understanding how the world works and how you must act every day. Both Jews and Muslims may agree to pray often, not eat pork, celebrate certain holidays, or go to a special building for worship, but if you think that makes them essentially the same, you’re a fool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, they are both Abrahamic religions, they both admire similar people (such as Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Elijah to name a few), and they both love a good falafel. But these are all superficial things. Muslims believe the Jewish sacred law books (the Torah) have been corrupted, and their holy book (the Quran), which was completed over a thousand years later, is the true word of God. The fundamentalist Jewish zionists believe God has given them all of the land held by the Palestinians. These are two &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different religions. To expect them to put aside years of bloodshed is one thing, but to expect them to live without resentment for the other’s disrespect for their texts is not an expectation to be taken lightly. Nevertheless, if there is to be peace between Jews and Muslims, what should be the extent of our hopes? And how do we get there? Do we ask them both to just put aside their history? Their faith? Or we ask both of them to search for the fundamentals of their religion. What is the most fundamental aspect of religion? To look after the widows and orphans. Be you a Jew, Muslim, Chrisitan, Buddist, or Scientologist, if this act is not being done, how can you be so sure your religion — or your interpretation of your religion — is being fundamentally carried out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are voices of wisdom and charity on both sides. But because this conflict is so frustrating, people are giving ear to the voices of violence and hatred. In order to preserve peace, we must seek to give a stronger platform to the radicals. Not the radicals for their own religion, but the radicals for peace, justice and love. The radicals for those fundamental virtues all humans strive to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part II)</title>
      <link href="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part II)" />
      <published>2020-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-II">&lt;p&gt;In one of the most complicated conflicts on the international stage, you would think there would be a massive effort to understand the conflict on its own terms. Unfortunately, this is not the case for the West and it’s involvement in the Arab-Israeli conflict. On one hand, it’s wonderful to know so many people in the United States and Europe care about resolving the conflict. But on the other hand, there is a strong lack of understanding of the fundamental aspects concerning the conflict. At its core, this conflict is a Middle-Eastern conflict with Middle-Eastern people. Yes, Western powers have played a role in both its history and present situation. But a major reason why everything is messed-up is because they didn’t understand the situation then, nor do they now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is to be done? Abandon everything and pretend that the situation doesn’t exist? Or do we just turn the whole region to glass? I would make the case, we should first take a step back, and realise our own prejudices and perceptions have always given us a flawed view of the situation. We cannot talk about what we should do when we don’t even know what has already been done, and what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now first, let me apologise. For me to say ‘the West’ is extremely misleading. There are dozens of countries and hundreds of agendas and perspectives within those countries of ‘the West.’ Each has varying degrees of concern for the conflict. Obviously, I cannot go through them all, but I would like to highlight two major views, and explain how they miss the mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the view I am most familiar with from my upbringing: Evangelical Zionism. Now both Evangelicals and Zionists come in many different degrees of radicalness that emphasises different things. Essentially, these are people who are fundamentalist Christians (usually not Jewish, but they could be Messianic Jews or ethnic Jews who converted to Christianity) who believe God has given the Jewish people a divine right to the land from &lt;a href=&quot;https://temple-news.com/what-does-from-the-river-to-the-sea-mean/&quot;&gt;the Jordan River to the Mediterranean sea&lt;/a&gt;. Now it’s important to note, they usually are just unaware of the situation of the Palestinians. Although many who hold a “river to sea” mentality &lt;a href=&quot;https://mosaicmagazine.com/picks/israel-zionism/2018/12/why-the-slogan-from-the-river-to-the-sea-is-a-call-for-the-destruction-of-israel/&quot;&gt;do operate with malice&lt;/a&gt;, this group is usually just oblivious to the injustice they would create. Many don’t even realise Christians both live and worship in the Palestinian territories. Western media sometimes depicts the Palestinians as crazy terrorists who will stop at nothing to murder innocent Jews. Although that may be true for radicals within Hamas, the majority of the Palestinians prefer to avoid as much violence as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Evangelical Zionists take a fundamental interpretation of the Bible, some see any nation as obstructing Israel as rebellious against God. Thus, they are staunch supporters for the United States and Europe to support Israel. What they get wrong however, is the Bible does not give the government of Israel a green-light to do whatever they wish. Again, the Evangelical Zionists are not malicious people, they are simply ignorant of many aspects of the situation. Perhaps they may visit Israel once every other year with their local church, have notifications on their phone that Rockets were fired into Israel from the Gaza strip, or follow the Israeli Defense Force (IDF) on Facebook. What they must realise is Israel by no means is a perfect country or government. To believe it has an inherent right to the land which surpasses the rights of the people currently living there is both situational and even Biblical ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I consider myself an Evangelical Christian. I do believe Israel has a right to exist. However, I am not anti-Palestine and I would be very reluctant to call myself a Zionist. Where I stand is I believe the human and civil rights of both sides must be protected and should be without the expense of the other. From a Biblical perspective, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy+28%3A15-68&amp;amp;version=NIV&quot;&gt;God does give conditions&lt;/a&gt; to the nation of Israel, that if they are righteous he will bless them, and if they stray from God’s commandments, he will punish them. Evangelical Zionists tend to emphasise God’s blessing, but mysteriously ignore God’s warning. I can’t imagine God favouring a country that potentially &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy+28%3A15-68&amp;amp;version=NIV&quot;&gt;leads the Middle-East in abortions&lt;/a&gt;. That being said, Israel is comparatively one of the best Middle-East for freedom of worship. Nevertheless, they just have a long way to go before they can claim they have God’s blessing to do anything they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the more Left-wing side of the West, we have the BDS movement. For those who do not know, BDS stands for Boycott, Divestment, and Sanctions. It’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://bdsmovement.net/what-is-bds&quot;&gt;a movement which seeks&lt;/a&gt; to remove recognition and international economic activity for the state of Israel and believes it’s membership from international bodies such as the UN should be suspended. It’s very popular on many Western college campuses, and usually causes many young people to join their ranks because they are inspired by the message of freedom and ending oppression against the Palestinians. Many accuse &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/27/world/middleeast/bds-israel-boycott-antisemitic.html&quot;&gt;the BDS movement to be anti-Semitic, but the leadership denies it&lt;/a&gt;. But does it actually help the Palestinians?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, some Palestinians think the BDS movement &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtoninstitute.org/policy-analysis/view/the-palestinian-case-against-bds&quot;&gt;isn’t helping their plight&lt;/a&gt;. Even the leader of the Palestinian Authority (PA) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timesofisrael.com/abbas-we-do-not-support-the-boycott-of-israel/&quot;&gt;stated they do not want anyone to boycott the state of Israel&lt;/a&gt;. The reason why is because many Palestinians will cross the border and work in Israel. By boycotting Israeli businesses and forcing them to shut-down, they give the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pcbs.gov.ps/portals/_pcbs/PressRelease/Press_En_30-4-2019-labour-en.pdf&quot;&gt;already heavily unemployed&lt;/a&gt; Palestinians even fewer jobs. Not to mention, Israel and Palestine trade with each other. To economically hurt Israel, is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.albawaba.com/business/ordinary-palestinians-full-support-bds-impossible-712178&quot;&gt;hurt the Palestinians&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the point of all this? Hopefully, everyone reading this will realise that “taking a side” is not something that ought to be done recklessly.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I&quot;&gt;I’ve stated it before&lt;/a&gt;, and I’ll state it again. The problem with the conflict is that Israel is scared of violent radicals. So they increase their security measures which infringe on the civil rights (and sometimes human rights) of the Palestinians. This causes them and their Arab neighbours to grow frustrated and become radicalised. The radicalisation reinforces Israel’s fear, and the downward spiral continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So can the West help break the cycle? It has the potential to help — but it also can make things worse. One could argue the modern conflict started with the British mandate which reorganised the different countries in the Middle-East and drew borders in seemingly random and uncalculated methods. On top of that, forcibly removing some Palestinians from their homes and replacing those areas with Jewish refugees from Europe was bound to cause major chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignorance has caused and perpetuated many other problems around the world, and the Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception. So what can the West do to mitigate or resolve the conflict? First, and most importantly, be informed. Not just by reading the news and history, but also by having conversations with Palestinians and Israelis. Ask what is their personal stake in the conflict, what is their perspective, and what they think is the potential solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, know that violence is not the answer. Violence only causes more resentment and revenge, which in term causes more violence, thus perpetuating the cycle. Anyone — be they Arab or Jewish — who seeks violence or force as a solution should be avoided. Ignore people who believe the other side has no right to live. Don’t give a platform to ideologies who are more interested in “their tribe” than the overall situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, build bridges of peace. People in the West should serve as &lt;em&gt;mediators&lt;/em&gt;. It’s only natural to pick sides in any conflict (especially if you have a Western mindset), but if we are to help ‘our side’ the best way is by helping &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; sides. If one side is hurt, so is the other. If one side prospers, the other could also benefit. The West’s role in the conflict should be to rise above the tribal ‘our side versus their side’ mentality. Instead, they ought to work to bring the two people together. Deradicalisation will come through a strong mutual understanding. Unfortunately, both sides live in societies that teach their children to resent the other. Palestinians and Israelis rarely understand the issues or perspective of the other side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peaceful solution to the conflict &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be a conscious intergenerational effort. The best way the West could help is by facilitating such an effort. But that can only begin if the West realises it is not some white knight that will save all the poor, oppressed people. The West, at best, ought to serve as a &lt;em&gt;mediator&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;educator&lt;/em&gt; which strives to help both sides come to peace. Better a teacher, guide, and friend, than a warrior looking for a righteous cause.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In one of the most complicated conflicts on the international stage, you would think there would be a massive effort to understand the conflict on its own terms. Unfortunately, this is not the case for the West and it’s involvement in the Arab-Israeli conflict. On one hand, it’s wonderful to know so many people in the United States and Europe care about resolving the conflict. But on the other hand, there is a strong lack of understanding of the fundamental aspects concerning the conflict. At its core, this conflict is a Middle-Eastern conflict with Middle-Eastern people. Yes, Western powers have played a role in both its history and present situation. But a major reason why everything is messed-up is because they didn’t understand the situation then, nor do they now.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part I)</title>
      <link href="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part I)" />
      <published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I">&lt;p&gt;When we look at the Middle East, we see chaos, war and violence, and usually have no idea why it is so. The Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception — in fact, it may be the poster-child for a Middle Eastern conflict. Although the history of the conflict goes back thousands of years, the modern conflict effectively started 72 years ago. The question is: why is it still going on? Why hasn’t a peaceful solution been reached? After spending several days in Israel and the West Bank studying the conflict and listening to journalists, politicians and other people from both sides, there are a couple things the West needs to understand as to why peace hasn’t been achieved. But first, some context must be given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand any conflict in the Middle East, one must take note of the Middle Eastern mind. Although I was born and raised in America, I can speak on this, as my ancestry is Middle-Eastern from the country of Armenia. Obviously, people from the Middle East are not monolithic (the British and French cartographers never understood this), there are hundreds, if not thousands of cultures and co-cultures in the Middle East and greater area — such as North Africa and Western Asia. Among those cultures, there are a variety of ethnic groups, languages and customs. So, this is more of a general guideline to understand the mindset, not a hard rule, but it is often neglected from consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Middle East, the two most important things in life are the land you live on and your traditions. What makes the land important is the same thing that makes tradition important: It is where your ancestors lived and died for generations. Some people were more nomadic, but many ethnicities (especially the Jews and Palistinians) see the land as a part of their culture and identity. If you take away their land, you take away what makes them. So as you can imagine, they’ll fight tooth and nail to keep it. In America or Europe, it’s not uncommon to move from city to city, state to state, or even country to country. But this is not the case here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as for the conflict itself, why is it still going on? The truth of the matter is simple, but it’s the reality that is complex. The truth is that the majority on both sides want peace, but the reality is both also want control over all of the disputed land. In other words, it is a paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it gets even more complicated when you consider that this is not simply the Israeli-Palistinian conflict, this is the Arab-Israeli conflict. If the typical American has parents who do something the former doesn’t like, they usually won’t continue. But typically in the Middle East, you continue doing what your parents did and learn to love it. Other than the land, there may not be anything more important than traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, tradition and homeland are deeply rooted in the Middle-Eastern mind. Part of what that means is fighting for your people. Israel is surrounded by countries who hate it: Egypt, Lebanon, Syria, Jordan and Iran, to name a few.  Conversely, because there is a worldwide diaspora of Jewish people, they will often lobby and petition their governments to support &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; people. Yet, of all the actors mentioned (and the many that were unmentioned), their agenda is not so simple as either supporting the Jewish people or the Palistinian people. Each one has a complex relationship with both and with the other aforementioned neighbors, in addition with multiple internal groups who also have competing ideologies. Some of them see the Israelis or the Palestinians as pawns in their own game to protect their own land and traditions against another actor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aside from all this, if the principal parties — as well as the majority of the international community — really want peace, why hasn’t it been resolved yet? For one thing, there is corrupt leadership on both sides. The Israeli government is motivated by fear, so they continuously impose more expansive security measures on the Palistinians. However, these security measures are economically inhibiting and they usually infringe on the civil rights — and sometimes human rights — of the Palistinians. This oppression breeds extremism and sympathy towards violent action within the Palistinian community. This, in turn, makes Israel more afraid, and it responds by imposing more security measures, thus, perpetuating the downward spiral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the governing body over the Palistinians, known as the Palistianian Authority (or PA) handles it poorly as well. They make little effort to de-radicalise the Palestinians, and if anything, encourage hatred towards the people they claim they want to have peace with. On one hand, the PA does encourage peaceful resistance to the Israeli government and promises democratic reforms, but on the other hand, they have not had an election in over a decade. This is because the last election in 2006 was held in the Gaza strip and it led to the takeover of the terrorist group Hamas. Israel feels that Hamas will also takeover the West Bank if there is another election, causing even more violence and instability. Furthermore, if peace and prosperity comes to the West Bank, the PA officials currently in power won’t have an easy pitch to ask for foreign aid. Once foreign aid dries-up, their life gets affected badly. Thus, they are more motivated to not back down and hold their position. Even if it is at the cost of the innocent Palistinians who live under them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there an easy solution to the conflict? For people who are living far away and unaffected by it: yes.  But for the people involved, it is a resounding: no. Now that is not to say that people outside of the affected area cannot help with the peace process, there is a place for good-hearted help from the West. But the conflict will not be solved by the West.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When we look at the Middle East, we see chaos, war and violence, and usually have no idea why it is so. The Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception — in fact, it may be the poster-child for a Middle Eastern conflict. Although the history of the conflict goes back thousands of years, the modern conflict effectively started 72 years ago. The question is: why is it still going on? Why hasn’t a peaceful solution been reached? After spending several days in Israel and the West Bank studying the conflict and listening to journalists, politicians and other people from both sides, there are a couple things the West needs to understand as to why peace hasn’t been achieved. But first, some context must be given.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
