<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/alex.madajian/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-03-05T18:34:28+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/alex.madajian/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)</title>
      <link href="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)" />
      <published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West">&lt;p&gt;I’ve written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood, dirt, and money — or a combination of the three — are responsible for virtually all conflicts. Of course, the Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception, but on a fundamental level, the radicals on both sides see this as a religious struggle. In the current generation, we tend to secularise everything so that we can pretend to scientifically map out a solution. But with conflict as complicated as the Arab-Israeli conflict, it’s easy to wrap ourselves with the blanket of self-pity and proclaim “Oh! It’s just so complicated. So many different perspectives and feelings. I’ll just never understand it!” It is true that we will never solve the conflict with the systematic precisions given to us by science because not every societal problem can be solved in such a manner. If we want to progress, we have to move beyond the fact no one will completely understand everything about the conflict. However, we must still strive to understand it. Even if religion seems strange or difficult to understand for some, it is essential for one to recognise the control it has over people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going any further, I must highlight my shortcomings. One popular saying I encountered while travelling to Israel was “two Jews have five opinions.” By this, the saying means that there are a lot of internal disagreements within the Jewish community. So when I write “The Jews believe this…” or “Muslims have faith that…”, I implore you to take it with a grain of salt. Every religion is filled with people who dissent on virtually every aspect. There are very few dogmas or beliefs completely agreed upon by an entire religion. Even among radicals, the interpretations of those dogmas are bitterly disputed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask any religious person, even those who have spent decades training and study, if they understand their own religion. I anxiously await to hear back from you. Until you find that person, the world will keep on rotating while the Israeli and Palestinian children die. We will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; understand even just one perspective of this conflict, however, we can (and must) strive to at least understand where both sides are coming from. The Arab-Israel conflict is very much religious conflict. Not just between Jews and Muslims, but also between the different factions within those faiths, in addition to many other religions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Israel and Palestine have religious sites sacred to Christians and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldheritagesite.org/list/Bah%C3%A1%E2%80%99i+Holy+Places&quot;&gt;Baha’i&lt;/a&gt; (and probably more religions), the local population is mostly made up of Jews in Israel and Muslims in Palestine. Although the minorities play a role in the history and international relations, the chief actors — Israel and Palestine — have undeniable ties to the religion of their majorities. Therefore, if one does not understand religion, they will never understand this conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my dear secular readers, religion may superficially seem like a way of life or a set of traditions, but if that is the extent of your view of religion, then allow me to correct your course. This may be true for a casual religious observer, but we are not solely dealing with casual observers, we are dealing with hardliners and fundamentalists. Now I consider myself to be a Christian fundamentalist, so allow me to explain what ‘fundamentalism’ means. Essentially when one is seeking to get to the fundamentals of one’s religion, they are a fundamentalist. For some, it means pursuing a message of peace and love, for others, their perception of the fundamentals of their religion is to rid themselves (and others) of impurity by any means necessary. Again, even within fundamentalists, you can see a wide range of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a person may arrange their day-to-day schedule or diet around their religion. Perhaps take special holidays and be extra motivated to spend time with their family. But any serious or dedicated religious person will tell you, it is also a philosophy. It’s a framework for understanding how the world works and how you must act every day. Both Jews and Muslims may agree to pray often, not eat pork, celebrate certain holidays, or go to a special building for worship, but if you think that makes them essentially the same, you’re a fool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, they are both Abrahamic religions, they both admire similar people (such as Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Elijah to name a few), and they both love a good falafel. But these are all superficial things. Muslims believe the Jewish sacred law books (the Torah) have been corrupted, and their holy book (the Quran), which was completed over a thousand years later, is the true word of God. The fundamentalist Jewish zionists believe God has given them all of the land held by the Palestinians. These are two &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different religions. To expect them to put aside years of bloodshed is one thing, but to expect them to live without resentment for the other’s disrespect for their texts is not an expectation to be taken lightly. Nevertheless, if there is to be peace between Jews and Muslims, what should be the extent of our hopes? And how do we get there? Do we ask them both to just put aside their history? Their faith? Or we ask both of them to search for the fundamentals of their religion. What is the most fundamental aspect of religion? To look after the widows and orphans. Be you a Jew, Muslim, Chrisitan, Buddist, or Scientologist, if this act is not being done, how can you be so sure your religion — or your interpretation of your religion — is being fundamentally carried out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are voices of wisdom and charity on both sides. But because this conflict is so frustrating, people are giving ear to the voices of violence and hatred. In order to preserve peace, we must seek to give a stronger platform to the radicals. Not the radicals for their own religion, but the radicals for peace, justice and love. The radicals for those fundamental virtues all humans strive to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I’ve written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part I)</title>
      <link href="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part I)" />
      <published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I">&lt;p&gt;When we look at the Middle East, we see chaos, war and violence, and usually have no idea why it is so. The Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception — in fact, it may be the poster-child for a Middle Eastern conflict. Although the history of the conflict goes back thousands of years, the modern conflict effectively started 72 years ago. The question is: why is it still going on? Why hasn’t a peaceful solution been reached? After spending several days in Israel and the West Bank studying the conflict and listening to journalists, politicians and other people from both sides, there are a couple things the West needs to understand as to why peace hasn’t been achieved. But first, some context must be given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand any conflict in the Middle East, one must take note of the Middle Eastern mind. Although I was born and raised in America, I can speak on this, as my ancestry is Middle-Eastern from the country of Armenia. Obviously, people from the Middle East are not monolithic (the British and French cartographers never understood this), there are hundreds, if not thousands of cultures and co-cultures in the Middle East and greater area — such as North Africa and Western Asia. Among those cultures, there are a variety of ethnic groups, languages and customs. So, this is more of a general guideline to understand the mindset, not a hard rule, but it is often neglected from consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Middle East, the two most important things in life are the land you live on and your traditions. What makes the land important is the same thing that makes tradition important: It is where your ancestors lived and died for generations. Some people were more nomadic, but many ethnicities (especially the Jews and Palistinians) see the land as a part of their culture and identity. If you take away their land, you take away what makes them. So as you can imagine, they’ll fight tooth and nail to keep it. In America or Europe, it’s not uncommon to move from city to city, state to state, or even country to country. But this is not the case here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as for the conflict itself, why is it still going on? The truth of the matter is simple, but it’s the reality that is complex. The truth is that the majority on both sides want peace, but the reality is both also want control over all of the disputed land. In other words, it is a paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it gets even more complicated when you consider that this is not simply the Israeli-Palistinian conflict, this is the Arab-Israeli conflict. If the typical American has parents who do something the former doesn’t like, they usually won’t continue. But typically in the Middle East, you continue doing what your parents did and learn to love it. Other than the land, there may not be anything more important than traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, tradition and homeland are deeply rooted in the Middle-Eastern mind. Part of what that means is fighting for your people. Israel is surrounded by countries who hate it: Egypt, Lebanon, Syria, Jordan and Iran, to name a few.  Conversely, because there is a worldwide diaspora of Jewish people, they will often lobby and petition their governments to support &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; people. Yet, of all the actors mentioned (and the many that were unmentioned), their agenda is not so simple as either supporting the Jewish people or the Palistinian people. Each one has a complex relationship with both and with the other aforementioned neighbors, in addition with multiple internal groups who also have competing ideologies. Some of them see the Israelis or the Palestinians as pawns in their own game to protect their own land and traditions against another actor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aside from all this, if the principal parties — as well as the majority of the international community — really want peace, why hasn’t it been resolved yet? For one thing, there is corrupt leadership on both sides. The Israeli government is motivated by fear, so they continuously impose more expansive security measures on the Palistinians. However, these security measures are economically inhibiting and they usually infringe on the civil rights — and sometimes human rights — of the Palistinians. This oppression breeds extremism and sympathy towards violent action within the Palistinian community. This, in turn, makes Israel more afraid, and it responds by imposing more security measures, thus, perpetuating the downward spiral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the governing body over the Palistinians, known as the Palistianian Authority (or PA) handles it poorly as well. They make little effort to de-radicalise the Palestinians, and if anything, encourage hatred towards the people they claim they want to have peace with. On one hand, the PA does encourage peaceful resistance to the Israeli government and promises democratic reforms, but on the other hand, they have not had an election in over a decade. This is because the last election in 2006 was held in the Gaza strip and it led to the takeover of the terrorist group Hamas. Israel feels that Hamas will also takeover the West Bank if there is another election, causing even more violence and instability. Furthermore, if peace and prosperity comes to the West Bank, the PA officials currently in power won’t have an easy pitch to ask for foreign aid. Once foreign aid dries-up, their life gets affected badly. Thus, they are more motivated to not back down and hold their position. Even if it is at the cost of the innocent Palistinians who live under them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there an easy solution to the conflict? For people who are living far away and unaffected by it: yes.  But for the people involved, it is a resounding: no. Now that is not to say that people outside of the affected area cannot help with the peace process, there is a place for good-hearted help from the West. But the conflict will not be solved by the West.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When we look at the Middle East, we see chaos, war and violence, and usually have no idea why it is so. The Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception — in fact, it may be the poster-child for a Middle Eastern conflict. Although the history of the conflict goes back thousands of years, the modern conflict effectively started 72 years ago. The question is: why is it still going on? Why hasn’t a peaceful solution been reached? After spending several days in Israel and the West Bank studying the conflict and listening to journalists, politicians and other people from both sides, there are a couple things the West needs to understand as to why peace hasn’t been achieved. But first, some context must be given.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
